Okay, so let's get started. So uh last
time we discussed some kind of the some
more uh kind of the concrete ideas for
the uh diffusion models especially for
the DDPM, right? So let me briefly go
over uh these kind of the basics of the
uh these are basically all the most
important kind of the some basic ideas
for the vision models that we're going
to keep iterating over this class. So
basically compared to the other digit
models the basic idea for the diffusion
models in general not only for some
specific model for the uh many for the
family of the diffusion models the basic
idea is that we are basically defining
the fourth and delivers the processes as
kind of some sequential the processes.
So it is basically not having some kind
of a single latent the variable but we
are sequentially mapping the data point
into the sequence of the latent the
variables in terms of that the final the
latent variable becomes the sample from
the distribution that we know typically
that's the standard the gausian
distribution and also that the
generation the process becomes the
reverse the process starting from the uh
standard gausian the sample and all the
way basically we are mapping to the data
point from the some sequential process
uh and to basically make it easier in
terms like training uh we are basically
uh simplifying this kind of the process
in a way that the for process is
basically not some kind of the learned
process but we are predefining the for
the process uh so that is kind of the
basic idea and also to make it like
simpler we are basically matching all
the electron variables to have the same
dimensions so those are kind of the the
basic setups for the depiction models
And the specificity models that we have
seen last time uh were basically having
this kind of two characteristics right
the first the key characteristic was
basically having the marovian process
which means that the sampling of the xt
only depends on the xt minus one in the
old process. So this was kind of the one
key idea and also it's the same for the
reverse process as well. The sampling of
the XT + one was also only depended on
the basically XT right
uh that's the kind of one thing and the
other thing is that we specifically
defined the for the transitional
distribution into this form. So we going
to basically keep seeing some kind of
some of the Gaussian form of the for and
also the reverse the transition the
distribution and last time we
specifically define this for the
transition into this specific form with
those kind of the parameters right uh
with some kind of the parameters of the
beta t here
and based on that uh we could see some
kind of the bunch of the other some
distributions in the food processes. Uh
basically this was kind of something
that we defined right the fourth the
transition the distribution uh using
those kind of the parameters and based
on that actually we also could derive
these two uh the formulations more right
so this was something that I was calling
as kind of like the for jump like
basically what this showed is that we
don't need to really like running the
fold process in like iterative way we
can directly jump the the sample any of
the intermediate the data point directly
from the the data point right and from
our definition of those like both the
transition this was also defined as kind
of the another gausian distribution into
this form right so this was kind of the
good thing in terms like making
everything is kind of the gausian with
kind of like those kind of the the
definition and based on that we could
also derive the closed form of those
this distribution sampling the xt minus
one from the post xt and the x0 right
this kind of like the uh distribution
that we wanted to match with the uh
using the the livery uh the transition
distribution. So the elbow function was
basically derived into you know way that
you know we are basically matching the
liver transition distribution to be the
same with this distribution right and
the good thing was that this was also
derived into the another decian form
with some kind of slightly more complex
the mean function there right so the
basic idea with the DDPM was to
basically how we are going to match the
liver the the transition the
distribution the same with this one
right uh for that we also discussed the
three options like the first option is
to directly predict the mean of that the
uh the reverse the the transition the
distribution which was the case that we
having the mean predictor uh instead of
that we we could consider basically
predicting the expected value of the
final the output of the the x0 given the
xt right so that was the case that we
are having the clean sample the
predictor and based on that the clean
sample the predictor we could bally
compute the mean of the distribution and
was also doing the sampling right and
the other option is not to predict the
expected value of the xu but the
expected value of the epsilon t epsilon
t was basically the kind of the gaus and
the the standard gaus and the sample
that was being used to sample the xt
from the x0 right we could see some kind
of the the formulations for that so
given this kind of the noise predictor
we could also compute the uh mean of the
the reverse the transition the
distribution and do the sampling. Right?
So there are basically those kind of
three options.
So basically we need to see basically
how you know once we basically get the
some prediction of the either mean or
the the prediction of the clean sample
or the noise how we can basically
compute the other right. So do those or
something that we could also be derived
and the good thing is that whatever the
predictor that we have the loss function
was basically defined as kind of like
these are basically some of the outputs
after we decompose the elbow function
and they're doing some kind of the
derivation right so after the all the
way of the derivation what we could see
is that the elbow function becomes
basically very simple the L to loss the
expected value like this while having
some kind of the waiting time for it to
be time step right. So we just dropped
the waiting term here. After dropping
the waiting term, you could see that
these are all the same kind of the L2
the loss function that we can easily
implement.
So given this kind of the page idea uh
so this is really something that you
will need to implement in your the first
assignment right. Uh so these are
basically all about how we going to
basically uh run the uh gradient descent
uh with kind of the expected value and
for that we will basically need to
sample the time t and also the sampling
the x0 and based on that we are sampling
the xt and then now we can compute
either basically the noise or the clean
sample and also the mean right and then
we are minimizing the output loss and
this is exactly something that we need
to implement And in our training the
procedure, right, we just need to sample
the clean sample uh yeah the clean the
data point X0 the time t and based on
that we are also sampling the xt right
and then uh b from the process of like
comput sampling the xt we're going to
have the uh the the standard gausian
noise here that's something that we will
need to match in our loss function and
then we need to just like run the back
propagation through this like the l to
lose and that becomes basically learn
some kind of the some sort of the
expected value of the the noise there
right so this is like quite
straightforward
uh yeah and also in the generation the
process once we basically train the uh
the noise predictor then we can uh do
this kind of the iterative process uh
which is basically computing the mean of
the reverse the transition uh the
distribution and based on that we just
need to sample the xt minus one uh in
the iterative manner so that's the bas
of the generation differs.
Do you have any questions uh regarding
this?
And one kind of the question that also I
was asking last time was that know while
we are basically modeling this kind of
the reverse the transition the
distribution as the bian distribution.
uh after like training all the things
the sampling of the uh xju from the x
capital t uh this
is not necessarily the gausian
distribution this is typically
non-gausian distribution right so this
is quite opposite to the fold case in
the four case somehow the fold the
transition distribution was the gausian
distribution then the fed jump
distribution was another the gausian
distribution uh that was because of the
fact that the uh the mean of the
transition distribution was defined as
kind of linear function. But for the
cases that when the mean is defined as
kind of the linear function with respect
to the disc condition then we can see
that the kind of the accumulation like
some kind of iteration of like sampling
also becomes another distribution. But
for the cases like when the mean of this
like the transition the distribution is
basically non linear function uh then
this kind like the iterative sampling
may not be basically the gausian the
distribution. So that was basically the
basic idea right.
So in the for process that basically
allows us basically not to basically
running the iterative process. We can
directly jump the sample any of the XT
uh given the X0 because like this kind
of default jump could be also seen as
kind of another like the Gaussian
distribution. But in the reverse process
we cannot basically skip like all the
iterative process because of that the
all the uh the the posterior
distribution here would not be basically
may not be the gausian distribution. So
we don't know some kind of closed form
of this distribution. So that's why we
still need to basically run the all the
kind of sampling the process in the EP
way that make sense any questions on
this
so the key thing was that we have seen
lots of some kind of the math here but
all the way like doing all the things
the implementation you're going to see
that is quite simple and also this can
be quite effective way to basically
model some very complex distribution of
these kind of the H so this is likely
with distribution sampling XJO given the
unique G and the sample X capital T.
So before we move on to some kind of the
other ideas uh the one quiz that I
wanted to basically uh small like
changing gear a bit is that so we are
assuming that actually we are having
like lots of the the data points right
for the image generation the case uh I
told you that there's kind of the data
set is some kind of the more than like
five billions of images right then given
this kind of like the five billions of
images we basically discussed the idea
in terms like how we can make the model
that can sample the another one, right?
But if we already have the five billion
images, then do we really need a
generate model? Why don't we just like
sample one of those coins?
Do you have any uh answer for this? This
is the quiz that you will need to post
your answer in the CMS.
So actually I'm asking this question
because like we going to see kind of the
uh exactly what's the difference between
like this kind of the direct sampling
and also the sampling from the division
model uh today's the the class uh but
before we get into that uh so this is
really some the question that we can ask
right if you already have like five
billions of images then do we really
need to have some kind of the a model
why don't just like take one of those
kind of things right uh anyone who want
to speak
>> something say I want
>> uh So yeah the the point with the
conditional degeneration makes sense uh
also for the unconditional generation
wouldn't there be any kind of advantages
like having the models
so basically we can see first see this
is kind of the compression right so if
you going to really just like store the
five billions of images in some kind of
the storage I don't know how much kind
of the memory uh that we need right that
could be huge amount of the the memory,
right? Uh but if you really just like
download some kind of a pre-trained from
uh some legit models like uh you don't
need to take a photo of this. I'm I'm
going to some kind of update version of
this slice. Yeah. So uh basically um if
you going to basically uh if you
download some kind of some pre-trained
some image diffusion models for example
and the the the size of those kind of
the printed model would be basically
like hundreds of the the megabytes uh
which is in terms of the compression is
basically huge kind of the compression
the ratio right so we are basically
compressing the information uh in the
five the the billionth images uh into a
few megabytes a few hundreds of the
megabytes basically which is is kind of
like much more efficient in terms of the
we are basically encoding all the
information into the a single model into
the very compact size. So that can be
basically advantage in terms of the
scalability and also the efficiency and
also in terms of the nobility and the
diversity uh basically our diffusion
model is not trying to just like pick
one of some kind of a given images but
it would basically some kind of the new
image right so in terms of that no uh we
may be able to handle some kind of some
sort of the primus issue it's not really
basically revealing some kind of the
exact the data should be used in the
training data but based on we are making
some kind of the new data points. So in
terms of some making some kind of the
novel images uh there can be some kind
of the advantage in terms of that we can
handle some sort of the some privacy the
issues but does this mean that the
hourly division model will not generate
some any kind of the images in the given
the training data set?
uh no guarantee actually there are
actually some cases that the output of
the printed model is really generating
some kind of the images that even we can
google uh in the intern so it's not
perfectly automatically handling all
those kind of privacy issues but there
are some kind of be some potential that
we can basically uh make our deep models
not to basically directly just pick you
know generate some kind of images
exactly the same image in the deep data
set but making some kind of the new
image So that can be also kind of some
advantages and also as uh we also
discussed that know we in terms of like
making some kind of the conditional the
model uh there can be some much more
some kind of advantage of the benefits
in terms of that we can basically find
some kind of the uh some kind of data
points that are more aligned with some
kind of input condition. So we're going
to discuss this kind of the the
conditional regeneration the case
sometime the next week. So those are
some kind of some advantages. there can
be more. Uh so these are some kind of
the um the ideas in terms like why we
need to have some kind of the uh digit
models.
Okay. So today's the main topic is
actually about the core based models and
before we get into that actually what I
wanted to bring up is that so we
discussed those kind of the three
options right the mean predictor and the
clean sample the predictor and the noise
predictor. So these two have some
basically very have some very uh
explicit and the clear mean in terms
like what we are predicting right. So we
are directly predicting the mean of that
the reverse the transition the
distribution or we just directly predict
the expected value of the clean the data
the points but what's the meaning like
this right uh it's just like something
kind of like reasonable because like now
the the things that we need to predict
is the standard gian sample so in terms
of some like managing some kind of the
training the procedure of the diffusion
models this kind of like makes sense but
what's what's the meaning of like this
kind of the noise Right? This does not
have some kind of some explicit meaning
in terms of the our the context of the
different models. So today we are going
to get into the meaning of like
predicting what's the meaning of the
basically the predicting the noise
there.
Uh for that basically we're going to uh
start to see some kind of the uh some
the definition of the new terminologies.
So today we're going to discuss some
many kind of new concepts uh in the
statistics uh we going to talk about
this core uh uh basically this core here
is not this core that you know but here
this core has some kind of the very
specific demand. So basically this core
here basically means the gradient of the
log likelihood with respect to the data
point actually this is the gradient with
respect to the the data point x out. So
when you have any kind of the
probability the density function here we
just put the data point x here if you
take the gradient of the log the
probability that's basically the
definition of this core function uh make
sense. So we're going to use this term
this core lots of the times in this
class. You will need to get used to the
meaning like this right this core
function. Uh so let's do some kind of
the simple the exercise here. Uh
so we defined this kind of the um
sort of default the jumping the
distribution right uh directly sampling
the xt from the x0. So this was
basically derived as some kind of the
the closed form into the gausian
distribution here right. So if we
compute this core function of this
conditional z distribution uh what the
the the function look like?
So let's try the divide the closed form
of like those uh this square function
here.
Did everyone get this?
It's nothing but just like we know the
PDF of the Gaussian distribution. uh
from the Gausian distribution we just
need to take the log first and taking
the gradient with respect to the x then
we're going to get this one right
uh you can try yourself but now after
seeing this we can see that this is
something kind of like related like we
what we have seen before right uh so
when you define the epsilon t so those
uh that the epsilon t was basically the
gausian the sample the unique gausian
sample that was has been basically being
used to sample the XT given the X0 right
so the form was basically defined like
this so given the definition of the
epsilon t here actually we can see that
our the epsilon t that we has been used
for the noise prediction the network is
actually identical to the score function
of those like 4 jump distribution up to
scale so it's nothing but basically when
you multiply some kind of this the
scaling factor into this like the nodes
that actually becomes of this core this
core function of the for the jump
distribution.
So that's kind of thing uh what we are
uh doing is that this kind of the noise
prediction the network was kind of like
predicting uh the this core function of
this distribution uh the up to the
scale. So that's basically what we are
basically we are doing with the noise
depiction network but actually this is
not the precise kind of interpretation
we're going to get into like the preset
interpretation delay
and this was also basically the case
that we are having this uh core function
for this like conditional distribution
right
uh what if we want to derive the uh this
core function uh not for the conditional
distribution but for the xt vector paper
for any kind of the intermediate data
point XT here. Uh what if we uh derive
some kind of this core function of like
this distribution. So this is not that
straightforward right for the
conditional case we know the closed
form. So we could basically directly
basically derive some kind of the the
score function there. Uh in this case we
will need to have use some kind of the
some mathematical tools here. uh so as
kind of some kind of tool here uh let's
briefly see this the twist formula uh so
we are without basically proving all the
things the meaning of the the twist
formula is basically this
so let's think about that we are
basically sampling the x here
and for those kind of like the the data
point x uh we know some kind of the some
likelihood distribution uh with with
respect to some kind of the mean here so
uh so you can see that this is the same
thing. So uh given some kind of the uh
the mean function here given the mean
function we know that the x has some
kind of the conditional distribution
with this kind of the gausian
distribution
and we also have the prior distribution
with respect to the mean here right then
all the marginal distribution will be
defined into this form right
so you can see that like given basically
we having some prior and the likelihood
here and both we don't know what's the
the prior is but it's like we know the
likelihood. So this is the setup that we
may not know about the the priority
distribution but at least like given the
mu we can now say that the likelihood
distribution have this kind of simple
form actually the these 3D formula can
be generalized into the much more
complex forms but let's think about this
like simple form in a way that the
likelihood distribution is defined as
the gausian and also the mean becomes of
the the condition itself
right in this case basically what we are
basically seeing is that uh uh while we
going to we'll be able to sample the X
given the mean
uh we are basically doing the opposite
like given the sample the data point X
uh what would be expected value of the
mean here
right so if we think about the sampling
process of the PX here what we going to
do here is that we're going to first
like sample the mean here mu here from
the prior distribution and then based on
that we're going to sample the X using
the likelihood distribution.
But let's say we don't have the
information for the prior distribution
here. And what we want to do is that
given the uh the sample from this like
the marginal distribution uh we want to
get the some kind of the guess of like
what will be some expected value of the
mean especially for each of the the data
point
doing the opposite.
Then what actually the twist formula is
that actually the mean conditioned by
the each of the data point x the
expected value of this mean can be
simply computed uh into this form
when we have some kind of this core
function here.
So this is the case that when you have
the information of the marginal and the
likelihood how can you get some kind of
the sense of the prior distribution
doing the opposite. So typically we
assume that you know we have the prior
and the likelihood and based on that we
do the sampling the margin right but
let's say we already have all the
samples of the x uh and then we also
have some kind of information for the
marginal distribution and also the
likelihood. So not exactly having the
marginal distribution but we have this
core function of the marginal
distribution and based on this core
function of the the marginal
distribution how can it get the sense of
kind of the mean in terms of like
getting the expected value of the mean
for each of the the data point and for
that like the this the 3D formula
basically says that yeah it can have
this kind of like some simple form so
this is the kind of basics uh with this
it would be not easy to get like what's
happening there. So let's also simply
see what this basically means. Uh
uh before that uh let's first basically
see uh uh these kind of some basics for
the gausian distribution. So another
kind of good thing in terms of having a
gausian distribution is that so this is
actually something that we kind of
discussed before. But when we define our
the prior distribution and also the
likelihood distribution like this both
as also the gausian distribution and
also with the linear function in the
mean here then we can see that the
marginal distribution becomes another
the gausian distribution like this. So
keep this in mind uh just you know take
this slide then to basically try
something with the twist formula uh
let's think about some kind of a simple
case that we have the both the
likelihood and both the prior and the
likelihood defined like this.
So this is actually something that we
don't know but let's assume that we know
this information for now. So the mean
distribution is the standard Gaussian
distribution and given the sample of
each of the mean. Now we're going to
sample the X here. So that's the
likelihood distribution. And based on
that now we can derive the close form
for the margin here. Right? PX. Uh
what's the marginal and also this score
function here?
You you will need to use the this fact.
Uh so maybe you can download this slide
or
based on this what is this?
So you see this right? I mean so simply
when you set the plier and the
likelihood into the gausian like this
then we can see that uh this will be
basically the our margin distribution
while also having this kind of linear
function and this function. So then
let's think about the opposite. Now we
have some kind of the uh this as our
marginal distribution and we know that
the our uh the data point dx there is
the sample uh conditioned by some kind
of the mean value the mu value there
right and then uh given some kind of the
some likelihood that we don't know uh
sorry yeah but sorry given some kind of
the uh the marginal distribution and
also the likelihood the the distrib
distribution uh given the 3D twist
formula uh how can you get the kind of
the sense of like what will be some sort
of the expected the value of the mean
for the data points so let's say you
have some kind of the lack of the data
points here
and this the data point would be sampled
from some kind of the some some kind of
the mean value the mu here right uh so
given the kind of the uh the data point
can you get this some kind of the sense
of the uh the mean value the expected
value of the the mu here uh for example
let's say that uh given this setup that
I just like mentioned here should be the
x here from the marginal distribution uh
when we take a sample which value is
basically the positive uh what would be
kind of the expected the the mean uh the
the value with respect to the x would it
be smaller than the x or the larger than
the
Oh see so
uh given this the uh prior and the
likelihood we derive this marginal
distribution. So let's say now we sample
uh uh basically lots we have lots of the
samples of the x uh which was actually
sampled uh by sampling the mu and then
conditionally sampling the x conditioned
by the mu right so let's basically do
some kind of reverse the process I mean
given the x uh if you want to get what
was the uh the de mu that was basically
used to sample this x uh what we kind of
expected value of that de mu
uh especially in the case like when the
the data point has some kind of the
positivity values.
So let's say we have the data point
here. This data point X here was
basically sampled by some kind of
another kind of the mean value, right?
Uh then would the the mean value be
placed in the left hand side or the
right hand side when the the point X is
positive with the value?
Left or the right?
should be left. No, the from the TW
folder what we have seen is that uh this
is kind of like linear function right.
So when you see this square function
here uh if the x is positive
we can see that this core is the
negative right.
So then from the twist formula we we
know that this is also the positive and
this is like negative when the x is
positive right. So which means that the
expected value of the mean
uh becomes smaller than the x because
these parts becomes the negative right
and this is quite well aligned with our
intuition. So if we consider basically
sampling some the mean first and then
sampling the x uh conditioned by that
mean with the gaussian distribution as
we go right and the right and the right
the x there uh alo would be some kind of
on the right side of that the
conditional distribution which means
that the mean be probably on the left
hand side of that the point of the x
right so as we you go further further to
the right hand side this X would be some
kind of the some outlier the sample of
the the conditional the distribution
with respect to the mean which would
means that the mean would be on the the
left hand side
the expected value to be the left hand
side right
if you go left hand side then there will
be some kind of some solution the the
distribution for the conditional
distribution as you go left and left the
mean would be more likely on the likely
on the right hand side of that the data
point right
should be greater than the data point.
So this is basically aligned with some
kind of the uh the definition of the
twisted wonder
make sense.
So yeah so you need to get used to like
what we are doing here. I mean here the
meaning of it is that uh even without
basically knowing some kind of the
information about the prior distribution
uh from the data point of the x how can
you get the you know estimate of the
mean that would result in sampling of
like this x uh that's basically uh the
idea of like the two for and the giving
the sense how we can compute this kind
of the estimate of the mean
uh actually we can use this information
uh this fact uh to compute this core
function of the xt uh not xt conditioned
by the x0
because what we can see is that so
that's basically what we want to compute
uh here uh so this is basically what you
know right sampling the xt conditioned
by the x0 right uh then this means that
uh when you take this as kind of the mu
this whole part is the mu right then
looks this the same as like what we have
seen in the previous slide right uh so
when we take this as kind of mu the
conditional the distributed xt also
becomes like this uh with the same form
here then using the the twist formula
what we can see is that now we can
compute the expected value of like this
part the x0 multiply by this like
scaling factor uh conditioned by the XT.
Right? This is basically nothing but
directly applying the idea of the the
tweeted formula.
Then the meaning like this is that uh
from the clean data point uh we can
directly know sample some kind of the
intermediate data point XT right. So now
let's do the opposite given some kind of
the uh noisy the latent variable the XT.
uh what will be the expected value of
the x0?
uh so we are basically computing this
with some kind of a scaling from here
that can uh be popped out of the
expected value here and then using the
score function here.
So if we know this core function
uh of the xt uh the the the probability
of the xt then based on that what we can
do is that given any kind of the
intermediate the data point uh we can
compute the expected value of the final
some clean the data point in the reverse
the process
make sense
this can be derived from the the twer
not Okay.
So from from this information what you
can see is that basically this core
function uh has some kind of the some
very close relationship with the
expected value of the x0 from the xt. Uh
so you know this has some you can see
that this has lots of information. Uh
once we have that this function given
the xt uh now we can actually compute
the expected of the xx0. uh that's
basically our some kind of the sort of
the forecasting of the final outputs in
the uh reverse processor
that can be derived using the TW
and this is also aligned with basically
what we have seen in the conditional
case basically this core function for
the XT can be computed as the expected
value for the score function for the
conditional case all the all the X0 that
could be sampled from the XT right so
this is the uh yeah the the score
function kind of things. So we can
compute the score function of the xt by
taking the expected value of the
conditional case for the all the x
condition by the xt and we know how we
can derive this right. uh this can be
derived using the uh the definition of
the gausian distribution what we have
seen in the previous slide and then we
can see that now this formulation that
we derived using the gausian
distribution is aligned with the some
formulation that we derived from the
twist formula
so these are all basically aligned in
this way
uh any questions on this
uh so here No, we we are basically
taking some kind of the some expected
value of like this term conditioned by
the XT and XT conditioned by XT is
basically itself like all the other
things are basically some kind of
constant values. Then this becomes the
this becomes the only part that we need
to compute the expected value condition
by dxt
here to here. Oh, so I'm just like
replacing these parts
uh with this. This is like something
that we have seen in the previous slide
from from
here to here. So I mean yeah so this is
the score function for the xt then what
we can do is that actually we can take
the for all the possible the x0. So this
is like if we just I rewrite this for B.
This is the expected value for the all
the samples of the XT that could be
basically resulting from the X uh X0 uh
that could be basically coming from the
XT. So all the possible sample of the X0
uh that can basically result in sampling
the XT in the B process. Uh we are
basically computing this like the score
function for the continued
value. So that's the meaning of this
formulation.
Any other questions?
>> So let me go quickly. So basically
that's the thing. So now what we can see
is that
the score function has some kind of the
meaning in terms of like getting the
expected value of the x0 for the xt and
actually we're going to see some kind of
the more meanings for this.
Let me skip this. So why do we care
about the this core function?
So actually the main idea that actually
we uh need to discuss for today is that
uh what we have seen at the very
beginning is that for the cases that we
know some kind of the closed form for
the probability the density function
especially like if we if we are able to
compute the inverse of the cumulative
distribution then based on that we can
directly sample the data points uh from
the the distribution. Typically we don't
know right so that's kind of the the
point but here the thing is that uh
in the case that we have the information
of the score function uh not this
division so even when we don't know
exactly about the probability the
density function uh if we have the score
function then based on the information
of the score function then we can sample
from the distribution
uh so the process that allows like this
kind thing is the things the process is
called the lamb body dynx which is
coming from the physics how many you are
measuring physics here
for the physics pit this might be more
familiar right uh but what we can do is
that like what the long demand dynamics
basically uh shows is that the sampling
process from the qx here uh can be done
in this way without using the qx
information but using these core
function information. So this is
something quite similar with like what
you have seen in the other leg model
case. So what you can do is that uh
without any proof here uh the procedure
is that you know once you sample the
data point from any kind of the prior
distribution if you iterate this process
basically know moving this point a bit
based on this core function down here
with some kind of injecting some kind of
the the gausian noise. If you iterate
this kind the multiple the times lots of
times then you can see that this the uh
the output will uh the converge into the
distribution especially like when uh
this term uh is full and when you
basically iterate this like the quite
many times and this is basically the
case that you know we are doing some
kind of a sampling uh from this
distribution without directly having the
priority density function but only using
this called function
make sense.
So this means that no actually even when
you have some kind of the uh the the
probability the the density function if
we cannot compute the inverse the the
cumulative distribution then we don't
know how exactly we can sample from that
right but the thing is here now you
don't need to compute the inverse of the
cumulative the the uh the distribution
you just need to take the gradient of
the log of that the property the density
function then if you like this like
multiple times uh then you can basically
sample from the distribution. So you can
see that actually this core function uh
basically has like all the information
about the given the the uh the
distribution. So let me play this.
So this is kind of the example. Then we
are having some kind of a score the
function which is kind of the vector
field over the entire space. And once we
sample from a start from some kind of
some I guess the uniform the
distribution or the yeah it's kind of
prior the uh uh distribution over time
you can see that all the basically
sample is converging to the some
specific distribution. Right. This is
the long diffuses
which means that now we can see that you
know this core function uh encodes the
all the information about the
distribution. So if you basically want
to sample from that specific
distribution the only thing is that you
just need to encode uh this core
information.
So we can think about just like pre I
mean training some kind of neural net
that can basically learn this encode
this kind of score information for the
all the points in the overly space.
So given kind of the the information
that we have for this core function uh
we can basically compress all the
information into this core predictor in
terms of training uh the score
predictive with the out loss like this
right this is already quite something
quite similar with like what we have
seen with the noise prediction
but this is the case that like when we
have the this information for this core
function
uh what's the case that we have
in our case like training the models we
only have the samples of the X right uh
we don't have the information even for
this C
so here the question is that uh if we
only have some kind of the samples uh
from the qx then based on that how we
can basically compute this core function
uh obviously if we only have the samples
of the x then uh we cannot directly
compute this core function so what we
are going to do is that we are going to
somehow approximate
uh this qx function uh using some the uh
the samples of the x that we have. The
way that we are approximating this like
the qx here is taking some kind of the
sort of the gausian convolution for the
all the samples.
So let's think about some kind of the
another distribution which is the qxt.
uh so you can now the ignore the t here
but basically this t indicates kind of
this is kind of the another distribution
right so let's say this is kind of the
another uh the distribution uh that is
basically coming from uh this kind of
the uh the definition of the the
marginal distribution so now this is the
case that we are taking the uh the
distribution that we want to learn as
kind of the prior here and having some
kind of another the small gausian
distribution as the likelihood hood and
define another distribution which is the
QFT
make sense. Uh so
yeah like this.
So uh yeah if we have some kind of some
kind of the um the qx distribution for
some kind of the concentrate on the
these like some three regions some kind
of the gausian the blurred uh the uh the
distribution the qxt will look like this
right making slightly blurry like this
by just like having the margin form like
this
then what we can see here is that uh
once we define the qxt into this way
then we know how we can sample from the
qxt. So sampling from the qxt will be
bally sampling from uh this distribution
and then sampling from this gausian
distribution
and we have lots of the samples from
this the distribution right. So we can
somehow approximate like sampling from
this is taking one of the data points
that we have
and then we just like sample again based
on this this uh this gausian
distribution
make sense.
Yeah. So here basically sampling from
the qxt becomes equivalent like sampling
the x. This this is already the samples
that we have right we already have the
samples of the x and based on the
samples of the x then we can also sample
the xt here. Then why do we need to
define this kind of the new
distribution. Uh the thing is that uh
given like the q the qxt uh now we can
so uh what we want to do is that we want
to basically learn this core function of
the distribution.
But after some kind of the derivation
what we can say is that for those kind
of this some Gaussian sumoed version of
the distribution uh like learning this
core function here uh becomes the same
uh with like minimizing this like this
expected value. So the thing is that
while we don't know how we can compute
this right we don't have the information
for this right uh but after basically
deriving some those kind of things what
you can see is that we just need to
actually minimize like this expected
value here the thing is that for this
conditional value we define this as kind
of the gausian distribution.
So we know how we can compute this.
So you can see that actually after we
define some kind kind of the gambler the
uh distribution here we are de composing
this core function into the sampling the
xt uh from the x0 sorry sampling the x0
here. So this should be here sampling
the x0 one taking one of the the data
points and computing this core function
with the conditional distribution in a
way to minimize the out to the the
function. Right?
So we didn't know how we can basically
compute this right but we can after the
component this into this we just need to
take one of the samples of the x0 and
for the gausian distribution we know how
we can compute the the score function
right so now it becomes basically
feasible in terms of that we are
learning this uh this uh training this
quality predictor
make sense and this is actually exactly
the same form that we have seen in the
noise prediction case uh in the uh the
diffusion models. In the DDPM case we
have that we have seen the the the noise
predictor right for the noise predictor
we are basically having the noise
predict here which is matching the
epsilon t here basically instead of we
have the epsilon t we have some kind of
the score term which is nothing but just
like multiplying some scaling the factor
into the the noise term here right you
can see that actually this is the
identical with the ddpm we are basically
up to some kind of scale
So we are basically having some kind of
the interpretation like what's we are
doing uh in the diffusion model. So in
the diffusion model the noise predictor
is basically learning some kind of these
core function of this kind of the gaus
and convoluted comb some kind of the uh
the distribution
make sense
any questions on this?
So here the question is that how we are
going to uh determine the variance of
this kind of like some uh some gausian
dev convolution.
So this is some kind of the factor that
we can define. Uh the thing is that as
we basically make it very small uh as
the variance would be very small then
what we can see is that this like the
new distribution would be quite close to
the original distribution that we wanted
to learn right that's kind of the
advantage. Uh what would be disadvantage
as we have some kind of the
multimodality in the distribution uh
there will be some regions where the uh
the probability becomes almost zero for
those kind of the some sort of the low
density region where the the probability
becomes very close to zero. uh the the
score function the local likelihood also
would be very close to zero right so
this is nothing we going to learn using
our some kind of the the loss function
here which means that for those kind of
the low density region where the kind of
the probability becomes very close to
zero uh the score function would be very
inaccurate
uh so for the kind of the in terms of
running the random the the dynamics for
the row the density regions uh some kind
of the process that we are doing would
be very kind of the some kind of the
noisy the process because of the
inaccurate score function. you're going
to learn here because like as you have
seen in the previous the case uh in this
slide.
So we are starting from some kind of the
so in this specific example we are
starting from some kind of the uh
uniform the samples over these like 2D
space and then moving that uh along the
kind of score the function right uh but
if the prediction of this core is
basically inaccurate uh then kind of at
the beginning the process the points
will be moving some kind of the random
points not really reaching to the high
density region so that's basically not
good for us
So that's kind of the problem. So for
the low density regions, we're going to
get some kind of inaccurate kind of
scores in this case. So then what we can
do is that we can consider increasing
this variance in terms of that this
becomes like more blurred uh the
distribution not having some kind of
some pickiness in some regions but
having some more blurry like this.
For those kind of cases since we are not
having this kind of the low dense
regions uh the core the
uh this core value will be kind of the
higher in this kind of cases then we
might be able to have some more chance
to get some more accurate the score
prediction across the entire division.
The problem is that now this uh blur uh
the distribution is more different from
the original uh distribution right. So
even when you basically uh you know
sample the uh the points using this kind
of the blurry the distribution that will
not be exactly the samples that we
wanted to see right. So here the point
is that actually we wanted to basically
sample from the qxt in terms of that
this become some kind of the good
approximation of this the original the
the distribution.
So there are some kind of the pros and
the cons
as we basically increase the variance
here.
As we increase the variance here, the
bad thing is that uh the QXT become some
kind of the bad approximation of the
original distribution. uh which means
that at the end of the all the language
dynamic process the output that we are
getting may not be some kind of the some
the the points that we wanted to get
that's not exactly the sample of the uh
the QX0 right so that's kind of the
problem but the good thing of having the
blurry the distribution is that we are
not having the low density regions which
means that there are some kind of no
issues in terms of having some less
accurate score function on some kind of
some some regions right
uh for the cases when the variance is
basically this small then the uh the the
the qxt becomes quite close to qx0 right
so in the high density regions we will
be able to basically move all the points
accurately into the sample state we
wanted to get the problem is that when
the points starting from some kind of
the low dens regions those will be some
kind of regions that these corresponding
might be less accurate so at the very
beginning uh the lang dynamics will be
less accurate in this case uh in the
case like when the variance is the high
the long-term dynamics may be more
accurate at the beginning but less
accurate at the end make sense
so that's the idea in terms like so what
we need to do so uh so what typically we
do is that we are basically starting
from some kind of the more broad
distribution
uh in a way that we can have some kind
of a would start with some kind of the
random points. So the in the the
particles but over time we want to
basically move those points more
accurately into some high density
regions. of the original distribution.
Uh in terms of that we are gradually
decreasing the variance uh the variance
here. Uh in terms of that no at the
beginning the even for the low dense
regions the points are moving to some
kind of the some good regions here and
after the points are moving to that
closer to the higher the density regions
then now we are having some more
accurate some kind of the the moving of
the all the particles by matching the
qxt to be closer to the or the
distribution
and this is actually exactly what we are
doing in our the reverse process of
diffusion models.
Uh so in the fold process in the
diffusion models uh you may remember
that you know uh if you recall uh the
our default the the the transition the
distribution we are increasing the
variance right gradually basically
adding some kind of the increasing the
variance of those kind of the some
Gaussian and the convolution uh in the
default process and the reverse process
is kind of the opposite. we are
gradually decreasing the variance of the
the transition uh the the qx here in a
way that we can start from kind of the
uh good start in the low density regions
in the the langu dynamics and then
moving to the right points in the high
density regions. So this is kind of the
one way that we can interpret our the
diffusion process into the language
dynamics and seeing the noise it t as
kind of this core function. So we can
basically consider our kind of the noise
predictor into the individual models as
kind of this core predictor basically
learning the log of the pro uh the
gradient of the log the probability of
the xt uh in a way that we can learn the
language like this
make sense
so I like to recommend you to check out
some kind of the some details here I'm
going to update all the slides in the
link
you know you can check out. So you need
to basically see the meaning of this
core function there and how exactly this
concept is aligned with the diffusion
models that we discussed last time.
Right? So we're going to keep discussing
this idea of this core function all
around the all the the lectures in this
class. So you need to get used to the
meaning of that and what's the meaning
of that you know we are sampling based
on this core function and also the lang
dynamics. So let's continue discussing
this on the Wednesday and then we're
going to and also all the different
models we discuss is the based on the
marovian the process right and we're
going to start to discuss some kind of
non-marovian the process next