This next lecture is one of my favorite
lectures in terms of the topic and also
the relevancy of of generative modeling.
And I think you may be here because you
recognize that we're in this tremendous
age of generative AI. And today we're
going to really learn the foundations of
generative modeling where we'll talk
about building systems that can not only
look for patterns in data and use that
to make a decision but also go a step
past this to actually generate new
instances of data based on those learned
patterns. This is a really really
complex and powerful idea and it's
exploded in a couple year in the past
couple years across a range of
applications and we've already actually
got a sense of how powerful and how
tremendous these types of generative
models are. And so we started off the
lecture yesterday with advances in image
generation and audio generation. And
here we're going to continue a little
bit on that same theme. So, here are
three examples of faces. And I want you
all to take a moment and think about
which one of these three faces is
real. Raise your hand if you think it's
face
A, face
B, and face C. All
right, I'd say A was the majority. But
in fact, all of these faces are not
real. They're all
fake. This So, so this really highlights
kind of the realism of these methods and
the power of generative modeling. And
indeed, with generative modeling, we're
able to go into a new set of types of
learning problems that we're able to
handle. So far in the course, we've been
looking at problems of what we call
supervised learning, which means that we
are given a set of data. And that data
comes with labels. And our goal is to
learn a mapping from the input data to a
label like a class label or a numerical
value. And in this class, because it's a
class on deep learning, we've been
concerned about learning these mappings
that are defined by deep neural
networks. But fundamentally that
function that maps from data to label
could really be
anything. Now we're going to turn our
attention to a brand new set of problems
of what we call unsupervised learning.
And in this case, we have just data. We
don't necessarily have labels. And our
goal is to build up a deep learning
model that can learn the underlying
structure patterns to the data. And this
can give us some insights in sort of the
foundational level of the distribution
of this data and be used to actually
generate brand new data
instances. And really the fundamental
principle of generative modeling which
is a instance and type of unsupervised
learning is that given samples from some
training set we want to learn a model
that represents the distribution of the
data that we have sampled from. And we
can use such a generative model that
models this probability distribution in
a couple of ways. The first is by doing
what we call density estimation where
the principle is given some set of
samples right along some probability
distribution. We want to train and build
up a model that can learn the underlying
dist the underlying probability
distribution that describes and captures
the space from which this data came. Now
when we learn this distribution, what
that allows us is to sample from this
probability distribution to now actually
generate brand new data instances
because we've built up a model that
captures that underlying probability
distribution of the data. What this
means is that generated samples reflect
that distribution. And in both cases,
our underlying question here is how can
we effectively learn this estimate of
the probability distribution P of X
that's going to be as close and as
similar to the true data distribution as
we possibly can get. Right? So this is
the core principle of generative
modeling trying to learn a good
probability distribution that represents
your
data. Why why do we care? Why can we uh
care about generative modeling and how
can we leverage it in the real world?
Well, first of all, by doing this
density estimation and probability
distribution learning, generative models
are capable to uncover the underlying
features in a data set. So for example
if we've gi we're given a data set of
faces human faces there could be many
many different faces and a priori we may
not know what is the underlying
distribution of these faces in terms of
features like hair color skin tone pose
um clothing etc. And so our training
data may be over represented with
particular features or under represented
with particular features and we may not
know this. Using generative models as
you'll see in today's lab, we can
actually automatically uncover and
identify these features and learn which
repres uh features are more or less
represented and use this to actually
create fairer and more representative
data sets. Another great example and use
case is an outlier detection. So in the
example of self-driving cars in autonomy
that Alexander introduced, it's really
critical to be able to ensure that the
car can handle all possible scenarios
that it may encounter on the road, not
just those that are most common. Using a
generative model, we can identify those
rare events, those outliers that are at
the tails of our probability
distribution and use this to detect
those rare instances and adjust the
control of the car accordingly.
Finally, perhaps the most the use case
that many of us may be interested in or
familiar with is actually using the
generative model to create new data
samples and new data
instances. Because these generative
models are modeling and learning
probability distributions, that means
that sampling from that distribution
yields new data instances. And this is
really the fundamental backbone of
generative AI. And in this course,
you'll see how this concept is really,
really powerful in domains from natural
language to computer vision to even the
sciences and
healthcare. So hopefully this motivates
and sets this stage for why we really
care about generative models. And today
we'll focus on two foundational classes
of generative models. latent variable
models that are broken down to
autoenccoders and a really foundational
architecture that we call generative
adversarial
networks. Both of these foundational
classes are what we call latent variable
models. And to get into that, the very
first thing we need to do is understand
what exactly is a latent variable. I
think a really great example to
demonstrate this is this story from a
ancient work Plato's Republic. And this
is known as the myth of the cave or the
allegory of the cave. And in this story,
there's a group of prisoners. And as
part of their punishment, they're
constrained to face a wall. The only
things that they are able to see are
shadows of objects that pass in front of
a fire that's actually behind them. They
can only see the reflections or the
shadows of those objects on the wall.
And so to these prisoners, those
shadows, those observations are their
reality. But they can't actually
directly see or measure those true
structures that are casting the shadows
that they observe. Those objects behind
the prisoner's heads are like the
underlying features or the underlying
latent variables that govern the
distribution of a data set. And all we
can do is give some way to observe those
data instances. But maybe what we
ultimately care about is capturing those
driving underlying features or latent
variables that uh yield the observations
that we can make.
So really one way to think about our
goal in generative modeling is to find
an effective way to capture these
underlying features and extract them
these latent variables when we are only
given uh some observed
data. So the very first way that we're
going to approach this is using a simple
and intuitive generative model that we
call an autoenccoder. And what these
models try to do is to self-encode the
input data that they
see. To take a look at how the
autoenccoder works, let's consider this
simple example of handwritten digits
images. Here we are taking this example
where we feed the image as raw data and
pass it through a a deep neural network.
Let's say it's uh convolutional layers.
And ultimately what an autoenccoder does
is it takes these successive layers and
tries to output a lowdimensional latent
space a representation of that data
which is our goal in what we're trying
to model and try to
predict. We call this network an encoder
because we're mapping the data X into
this set of latent variables Z.
Now let's ask ourselves, okay, why would
we care about the dimensionality of this
set of latent variables Z? Any ideas on
on why we would care about how many
latent variables we're trying to learn?
We want to abstract the most
important features that might not be
necessarily needed for other
Exactly. We're trying to extract and
distill down to those most important
features. Keeping a lower dimensional
latent space means that we're
effectively compressing the data,
encoding it into a small latent vector
and learning this very compact very rich
feature representation.
Now the question is okay if we are able
to generate this lower dimensional
latent space how do we actually train
the model to learn this latent variable
vector. Do we have any explicit examples
or labels of this training data Z that
we we try to model? Can we do normal
supervised learning?
I think we have in principle we have we
have the
data but we don't have the
data so
we add some
yeah so if we if we had some prior on
features that we care about maybe yes we
could try to supervise against this but
remember our fundamental goal is to
uncover these features automatically we
want to learn that directly from data
without any supervision so that we don't
bias our perspective on what are the
actual important features from a
datadriven way. So the idea is instead
of using labels that are prespecified by
us as the humans, we can use the data
itself as a signal to learn these
features in an unsupervised way. And so
the way we can do that is we by not
assuming any labels for what these uh
features are. Instead what if we just
try to reconstruct the input and train a
neural network to go from that space of
pixels of the image go down to this
lower dimensional space and then build a
decoding model that can reconstruct the
original image from that latent space.
Now here we can compare this this
original input to the reconstructed
output and train the network by simply
minimizing the distance between the
inputs and that reconstructed
output. And a way we can do this easily
in images is we can take something
simple like the mean squared error
between the input and the reconstructed
output. subtracting the two images from
each other, squaring the difference, and
that gives us a pixel to pixel metric of
the difference between the input and the
reconstruction. And so what you can
probably appreciate is now if we look at
this loss function that we're actually
using to train the network, it doesn't
require any specification of labels or
what the identity of these important
features are. we can just use the signal
of reconstructing that input as a way to
learn these
features. Now let's simplify this plot
just a little bit. Abstract away the
individual layers in these two
components of our autoenccoder, the
encoder and the decoder. And again,
right, our loss function doesn't require
any labels at all. This is really really
a powerful idea because now we're
getting into the capability of
unsupervised learning. We can learn a
quantity like that those latent
variables in that lane space Z that
we're interested in without any
prespecification and without the need to
directly observe
those. Back to the question about why
the dimensionality of that latent space
matters. Well, it has a huge impact on
the richness and of features you're able
to extract out and the bottleneck you
place. If we think about this notion of
autoenccoding as a form of compression,
what that means is that the lower the
dimensionality of the latent space, the
more we're going to compress our data,
the worse we're able to do at the
reconstruction. And so really now the
key concept of this autoenccoding
approach is that we can use this
bottleneck hidden layer to extract these
latent features Z without any presp
specified or supervised labels using a
loss called the reconstruction loss that
forces the network to encode as much
information as possible through this
process of having to decode back and
reconstruct the input. In this way,
we're automatically encoding information
within the data into the latent space Z.
This principle of an
autoenccoder. In practice though, what
is commonly used is a buildup and a
variation on this idea that introduces a
little bit more diversity to be able to
actually generate new data samples. And
that's the concept of variational
autoenccoders or VAEEs which are really
really a workhorse generative model in
the capability of latent variable
modeling as we just saw right in a
traditional
autoenccoder. The operation is
deterministic. We have in our encoder
normal layers in a neural network just
like any other layer that we've seen
before. And we have normal layers on our
decoder that take the latent variables
and decode back out to generate an
output. What this means though is if we
feed in an input, we're going to get the
same output reconstructed out so long as
the weights are the same. If we don't
change the weights given an output,
we'll always get a same reconstructed
out uh output back out. The way to think
about this is as a deterministic
encoding that allows us to reconstruct
an
input with VAEEs. In order to learn a
good quality latent space, we actually
need to introduce some randomness, some
stochasticity into this autoenccoder.
And that's the principle behind
variational autoenccoders or VAEs.
What we do with VAES is now instead of
having a purely deterministic
layer Z, we're going to introduce some
sampling, some notion of uh
stochasticity.
Instead of learning the latent variables
directly, if we parameterize each of
these latent variables as a probability
distribution defined by a mean mu and a
standard deviation sigma, we can now
learn these vectors of means and
standard deviations separately such that
we get a distribution over each of the
latent variables in our latent space.
What this means is that it's simply a
probabilistic twist on this concept of
autoenccoding. In effect, what this
means is now we can sample from these
means and standard deviations to now
produce new data
instances. And all you can tell here is
that VAEs are the same concept of
encoding going down to a latent space
and decoding back out to the original
data space with just this probabilistic
twist to it where we can sample uh
through these latent variable
layers. If we now start to make this a
little bit for more formal, right?
Effectively what the encoder and decoder
are doing are trying to learn
probability distributions. The encoder
is computing a probability distribution
of the latent space given the input data
X and the decoder is doing the reverse
trying to compute the probability
distribution of the data given the
latent variables Z.
These two networks are defined by two
separate sets of weights phi and theta.
But we can train this network completely
uh end to end with one loss function
that's going to be a function of the
input data and these two sets of weights
fi and
theta. So if we now take a closer look
at what this loss looks like, we have uh
two terms. One is the reconstruction
loss which is very similar to what we
saw as in the standard autoenccoder and
secondly a new term called the
regularization term which we'll get uh
into in closer detail in a little
bit with the reconstruction loss. It's
the same as just before. You can think
about it as the error or the comparison
of your input to your reconstructed
output. And you want to try to match
that to be as low as close as possible,
right? Do a faithful
reconstruction. Now with the regular
regularization term, things get a little
bit more
interesting. Recall now that we're
trying to learn a probability
distribution over these latent variables
given the data X and that's what's
computed by the encoder.
As part of regularizing this probability
distribution, what that means is we want
to make some initial prior guess on what
these distributions of the latent
variables should look like. This helps
us infer in infer and enforce latent
variables that follow this
prior. And so when we introduce this
regularization term, we need a way to
compute a uh sense of distance between
the distribution of those latent
variables and our prior about what that
probability distribution should look
like. So to break this down a little
further, D is effectively just a
distance metric. And what we're
comparing is how similar that
probability distribution of an inferred
latent variable is to some prior some
initial guess we play place on what that
distribution should look
like. To understand this a little bit
further, let's first think about how we
even choose this prior and why it's
important.
One very common way to choose a prior
for a VAE is to say okay let's do
something simple. Let's say that we're
going to uh promote these latent
variables to roughly follow a normal
distribution centered around a mean of
zero and having a standard deviation of
one.
This encourages our encoder in our VAE
to now try to locate the latent
variables evenly and smoothly around the
center of the latent space and
distribute and the encoding such that um
we can cover this latent space
smoothly with just like with any other
loss function like the cross entropy
loss or the mean squared error. We need
a metric that computes how close we are
to that initial prior. And one very
common way to do this is a distance
metric that compares how close two
probability distributions are to each
other. And this metric is called the KL
divergence. The equation for uh KL
divergence with a normal prior is shown
here. But effectively what you can think
about this is as a way to compute and
quantify the distance between two
probability
distributions. So right now at this
point you're probably thinking okay well
I get the principle of we're trying to
learn a probability distribution over
these latent variables. We want some
prior on how they look. But why is this
actually important? Why do we even need
to place these priors? And why do we
need to regularize our latent
space? To do that and to gain intuition,
let's first consider what properties we
want our latent space to actually
achieve. The first thing we care about
in learning these features is this
notion of continuity. Meaning that if we
have two data instances and they end up
close to each other in the lane space,
there should be similar content in those
two data instances. meaning that
closeness in the latent space
corresponds to closeness in the data
space. The second criteria is this idea
of completeness. We don't want there to
be gaps. Meaning that if we sample from
somewhere in our latent space, we should
be able to still reconstruct or de
decode back out some meaningful data
instance. It should not be completely
random or completely completely
garbage. To intu to intuitit this a
little bit further, let's now consider
the consequences of if we were to place
no priors on these latent variables and
not regularize them. Without
regularization, we c we could have
instances where there were two points in
the latent space that had completely
different meanings in our original data
space. So in this example, we're
thinking about shapes, right? Squares,
triangles, and circles. Here, if a
square and a triangle end up close in
the latent space, but are not similarly
in decoded or in the original data
space, that's not desired. We want
triangles to map closer to triangles
than they do to squares.
Secondly, there if we don't have
completeness, if we just draw some
sample from the latent space, we could
end up with nonsensical
um squiggles back out, not meaningful
shapes.
In contrast, what regularization allows
us to do is to encourage the closeness
where points that end up close in the
latent space are semantically related
similar shapes and also completeness
meaning that we can sample from anywhere
in this grid of the latent space and
still get a good shape out when we
decode.
So this is a really really important
concept of using regularization of the
latent space to ensure continuity and
completeness. What is important to keep
in mind is that just choosing some
probability distribution doesn't
necessarily guarantee these
properties. Without a good term and a
good prior for regularization, we could
still have issues with the quality of
our latent space. It turns out that by
using a normal prior, we're able to
regularize the latent variables
accordingly by centering the means and
controlling the spread of the variances
so that we encourage continuity and
completeness in these latent spaces.
So hopefully that conveys some intuition
about this concept not only of
regularization but why a prior like a
normal prior can often work very well to
build up a latent space that is both
continuous and complete.
This at its core kind of gets at this
concept of latent variable modeling and
with VAEEs how we can go from encoding
to the latent space and decoding back
out. The last step is to define exactly
with these components of the loss
function the reconstruction term and the
regularization term how we can actually
train the network end to end.
The problem that we run into is because
we have this probabilistic latent space,
we can't pass gradients back through. We
can't back propagate normally like we
saw in lecture one. Back propagation
requires deterministic neural network
layers or neural network lo nodes.
The key idea that unlocked the ability
to train VAEs is to actually do a clever
modification of this sampling uh
operation to allow for training using
back propagation end to end. Instead of
just sampling our latent variables
directly from a normal distribution par
parameterized by a mean and standard
deviation, we can instead sample our
latent variables as a sum of a fixed
deterministic set of means mu, a fixed
set of standard deviation, sigma, and
scale those standard deviations by
another term that controls all the
randomness that we care about, all the
stochasticity and we call this constant
epsilon. In practice, what this means is
now z is the sum of mu plus sigma scaled
by this random constant that's drawn
from that normal prior. We can visualize
this very clearly by now looking at a
diagram like this and how that affects
back propagation and actually training
the network. Originally, if we're trying
to go directly through this sampling
node Z, we can't back prop and we can't
pass gradients through. Instead, if we
now break out Z to uh control and encode
all the sampling randomness into this um
stochastic constant epsilon, we can
allow for back propagating and passing
gradients directly through Z back all
the way to the input X. This is really
really important now because now we can
actually pass gradients through end to
end and learn these latent variables
based on the data in a datadriven
way. Finally, right once we've trained
our network, what is powerful about VAES
is we can go in and inspect those latent
variables to see actually what are the
features that were learned by the model
in this process of encoding and
decoding.
And what's really beautiful and
intuitive is often times those features
have interpretable um considerations
back in the original data space. So if
we look at how we can do this in the
context of images, let's say we take a
trained VAE over images of faces and now
we sample from just one uh from
variables in the latent space to now
generate new data instances by decoding.
If we can keep all but one variable
fixed and just slowly perturb the value
of a single latent variable, you can see
that there this actually corresponds to
a very interpretable feature with
respect to what in the image is actually
being picked up by this latent variable.
In this case, it's the pose, the shift
of the head in terms of how it's looking
at the camera. And so this gets at the
concept of with a method like a VAE,
we're able to capture different latent
variables that correspond to different
interpretable features in the space of
the data that we care
about. As you'll see in the software
lab, we can use these models that can
uncover these underlying latent
variables as a means to actually uncover
what are features that are relatively
well represented in a data set or what
features are under represented. And this
has really really important implications
for when we think about what biases or
under representations could exist in our
data sets that we use to train uh these
deep learning models. And you'll get
hands-on practice with this in the
software lab where you'll actually build
a VAE model to automatically uncover
latent features in uh data sets of human
faces. All right. So to summarize the
key concepts of these autoenccoder
approaches like VAEEs, they're able to
compress data into a set of latent
features that are of lower
dimensionality.
We can do this completely unsupervised
without any labels by reconstructing the
original input back through a
decoder. From this uh
representation uh we can generate the
reconstructions in an entirely
unsupervised way. We can we saw how we
can use reparameterization to learn
these networks end to end. And we also
saw how these latent variables actually
have key meaning corresponding to
important and interpretable features in
the data space we we care about. And
finally, by sampling from those latent
variables, you can use the decoder
portion of the network to now generate
brand new instances of your original
data space.
So really vaes give us a very powerful
way to combine this concept of density
estimation over a set of latent
variables with sample generation through
decoding. But what if our primary goal
is to generate new samples as the output
and we don't care so much about having a
set of latent variables that could
potentially be interpretable.
One very early and very uh foundational
approach to do this and focusing more on
sample generation is an approach called
GANs or generative adversarial
networks. And the principle of GANs is
motivated by the fact that what if we
care just about generating new data
instances that are very similar to the
data that we trained our model on. What
this means is that we're trying to
sample from this really complex
distribution and we want our model to
learn a good way to approximate that
distribution. It can be very very
difficult to learn this distribution
directly. So instead, what Gans propose
is an approach to transform something
really simple, even as simple as
completely random noise into the actual
data distribution that we care about.
And as we'll see, the GAN approach
trains a generator model that can learn
a mapping from a distribution of
completely random noise to the
distribution of our training samples.
The approach that GANs take is actually
kind of clever and fun. Our goal is to
try to produce this distribution of
generated data that's as close to the
real deal as
possible. GANs proposed an approach to
doing this by putting these two
competing neural networks side by side
with each other, a generator and a
discriminator.
And the concept is that these are in a
sort of a battle with each other. The
generator network is tasked with trying
to go from this distribution of
completely random input noise to produce
an imitation of the data.
Then the discriminator looks at
generated instances that are supposedly
an imitation of the data and its goal is
to try to discriminate what is real and
what is fake and learn a classifier to
distinguish real versus fake. And by
having these two networks compete
against each other, we can try to force
the discriminator to learn really well
how to delineate good uh real versus
fake. And the better it becomes at doing
that, it forces the generator to in turn
be better and better at producing fake
data that can try to fool the
discriminator.
to get a sense of the intuition behind
this and how this works. Let's start
with this really um one of my favorite
illustrations of this example that
conveys this intuition. So let's say we
have just data on a onedimensional line
and there are some instances of fake
data. They're going to lie somewhere on
this
line. Generator remember is starting
from completely random noise. So
initially without any training it's not
going to be very good at producing uh
fake
data. It produces some instances and now
the discriminator sees these points and
it also sees some real data. Its task is
to be trained to output a probability
that any given data example it sees is
real.
So, we're going to train the
discriminator. And at the beginning, its
predictions may not be that great, but
we train it. And it starts to increase
the probabilities of what's real,
decrease the probabilities of what's
fake until we get a perfect separation
where the discriminator can perfectly
distinguish what's real and what's fake.
Now the generator comes back and it sees
where the real data lie and it starts
moving its generated fake data closer
and closer and closer to those
instances. And now the discriminator
receives these new points, this new
round of generations. And again, its
task is to train and learn how to
delineate real versus fake. It's going
to estimate the probability that any
given point is real and learn to
decrease the probability on the fake
points and increase the probability on
the real
points. We repeat again one last time.
The generator starts moving its
creations closer and closer and closer
to the real data such that the fake data
are almost exactly overlapping the
locations of the real data. And now at
this point, it's going to be very very
hard for the discriminator that's going
to apply its classifier to these
instances and do a good job of
delineating real versus fake because
those generated instances are so close
to the real data. So really this is the
core intuition be behind how these two
components of a GAN are essentially
competing with each other.
Bringing back to our diagram, we can
summarize this. A generator is just
trying to create new data instances to
fool the discriminator. And the discri
discriminator is trying to identify
these instances through this uh
competing objective
between between the generator. And
ideally we reach a an optimum where the
generator is able to perfectly reproduce
the true data distribution and
completely fool the discriminator's
ability to
classify. So this is really really kind
of a fun and interesting idea that
initially led to a lot of excitement
about generative models. And
fundamentally what I want you all to
take away is that you can think about
these uh generative models like GANs as
learning a distribution
transformation going from the ability to
move from pure Gausian noise random
noise to eventually be able to produce
instances across a learned target
distribution when the train generator of
a GAN is synthesizing new instances.
What it has done is use its learned
mapping from that distribution of
Gausian noise to the target data
distribution to uh learn this mapping
from one point somewhere in that noise
distribution to a particular output in
the target data space.
If we consider some other point some in
another initial point in that initial
distribution of noise and fed it through
the generator now it would produce a new
instance somewhere else in the target
data
distribution somewhere else on the data
manifold. And what we can actually do is
smoothly interpolate and try to traverse
in the space of completely random noise.
And it turns out it yields actual smooth
interpol interpolations in this learned
data manifold. And as you can see right
the results are kind of striking where
we can see very concretely a
transformation in series that reflects
this sort of interpretable trans uh
traversal or transversal of the data
space. And so this is really a powerful
concept that gets at this notion of
distribution transformation. We can do
something as seemingly wild as going
from a distribution of complete random
noise to some
target. We can also do things like going
from one source that's not random to
another target source. And there have
been variations on GANs such as cycle
GANs that propose exactly this. Instead
of starting from gausian noise and
moving to a target data manifold, we can
consider one data manifold and try to
learn a mapping that takes us to another
data
manifold. This is really cool because it
leads to some clear capabilities in
things like style transformation.
So in images for example, we can do
completely unpaired translation of
images from one style to another using
this architecture called a cycle GAN. So
this visualization is showing you uh a
cycle GAN that's trained on natural
images. And here we're seeing a domain
transformation from a domain of horse to
a domain of zebra. And this is a concept
of effectively style transfer. And how
cycle GANs work is that they employ this
kind of cyclic loss where you actually
have two sets of generator and
discriminator one for each of the
domains and an additional code
dependency that links those two domains
together.
In fact, we ourselves just a few years
back built out a cycle GAN to uh do not
uh to do something that we introduced
yesterday in the beginning lecture which
is speech and audio
transformation. It turns out that you
can actually represent audio waveforms
as images called spectrograms. And very
similar to how we saw in the zebra horse
example, what we did uh five years back
is trained a cycle gan to transform
speech spectrograms from one style to
another. And if you recall, Alexander
showed the snippet of the video from
Obama introducing the the course that we
used a few years ago. And as as you saw,
right, that video was synthetic.
Unfortunately, Obama did not actually
come and grace us with his presence to
introduce the class. What we did instead
was used audio recordings, several hours
of audio recordings to now convert those
audio recordings into spectrogram images
for both source voice and target voice
and train the cycle GAN to do this
unpaired translation from one voice
domain to another. Yes. function that
you use.
Yeah. So, let me pull actually I have it
right here. That's a great question. The
core principle is we want to put the
discriminator and the generator and
optimize them jointly. Right? So, I can
actually pull up the exact loss
function.
So the loss term is based on the same
intuition of comparing the real data
with the generated data
instances. First, if we consider the
loss term from the perspective of the
discriminator, what it's seeking to do
is maximizing the probability that data
is correctly identified as real,
correctly identified as
fake. And as you can see right that
involves a discrimination over the
generator's output here G as well as a
discrimination over the real data
X fake versus real and again this is
focusing on the discriminator. The
generator on the other
hand is trying to now minimize
uh the minimize the probability that the
generator that its generated data is
identified as fake. So now it's that
same objective but all it's doing is the
converse. We're trying to minimize the
probability that fake data is um
classified as fake. We want to be as
close to moving it to the real data as
possible. And in concert we can then put
this together. We have uh one one term
here that is jointly maximized by the
discriminator and minimized by the
generator.
So it's this dual this kind of um
competing objective where again the core
intuition is we want to optimize the
discriminator to do as well as possible
in delineating real versus fake and
optimize the generator to produce as
synthetic and realistic instances as
possible.
Yes, that's a great question. It is
differentiable, but it turns out in
practice it's very it can be very
difficult to train GANs stably. And so
there have been works proposed that give
variations on this loss or introduce
other methods to try to uh improve the
stability. Awesome.
So one
second. So so to summarize and maybe
conclude right with GANs first right the
core principle is this competition
between these two networks that can be
optimized and trained jointly through
this objective that we just saw. And
this is in contrast with a more density
estimation focused approach like a VAE
where our goal is really to learn
underlying latent variables that capture
the core features present in the data um
that give us a lower dimensional
representation of our data examples.
Now, these are really foundational
approaches to generative modeling, and
they've paved the way for great advances
that have come in the past couple of
years that have yielded very, very high
fidelity and high quality generations
across a number of domains. And we're
going to see in tomorrow's lectures some
of these very cutting edge and new
frontier advances in generative modeling
including models like diffusion models,
language models that are the driving
tools behind the advances in generative
AI we see today. So I'll end by giving
you a snap uh preview that we're we have
much more to come in lectures six and 10
on diffusion models for different
domains. Hopefully, this gets you
excited about the promise and the power
of generative modeling and you'll have
hands-on experience in today's software
lab that bridges the themes of computer
vision with the themes of VAEEs and
generative models where you actually
train uh CNN based VAE to do facial
detection and debiasing of facial
detection systems.
So with that we will conclude and links
uh to download and get started with the
labs are available um
online. Before we we close and break to
the office hours, I want um I believe we
have our TAs who have joined us uh
today. So if you can raise your hands or
come down to the front um that would be
great so everyone in the class can
recognize you and identify you for help
on the software labs.
Yes question.
Yes. Piaza is the place for um posting
questions
asynchronously. Oh, Victory
is Yeah. So, we're going to break into
the office hours session. Victory is one
of our amazing TAs. Um she will be able
to help answer questions related to
TensorFlow, PyTorch, and the labs. And
of course, if you have questions on the
content itself for the lectures, uh
Alexander and I will be here as well.
Thank you.