okay cool hi uh my name is sh super glad
to be here and talk to you about LM
agents uh brief history and overview so
today's plan is very straightforward uh
I want to talk about three things so
first what is LM agents to start with
and then second I want to talk about a
brief history of LM agents both in the
context of LM and in the context of
agents and lastly I want to share some
ideas on some future directions of
Agents so
uh as you know this field is a moving
piece and it's very big and messy so
it's impossible to cover everything in
agents so uh I I just try to do whatever
is in the best of M and you can see
there's a QR code and you can scan scan
it and give me feedback and I can
improve the talk
accordingly okay so let's get
started uh first what is LM agents uh do
anyone know do anyone think they know
the answer if so raise a
hand like do you have a definition for
what is L on
agent okay uh there are like maybe three
people so uh that means this field is
really a moving piece so I think if we
want to Define what is LM agent we want
to First Define the two components what
is LM and what is
and uh does everyone know what is Ln
okay uh so so so really what left what's
left is we need to Define what's agent
and if you search Google image uh this
is this is Agent right uh but but in the
context of AI obviously uh we know it's
a notoriously broad term it can refer to
a lot of different things right from
autonomous car to go to play video game
to chat B so uh first what exactly is
the agent so um my definition is that it
is an intelligent system that can
interact with some
environment and depending on like
different you can have different agents
right you can have physical environments
such as robot autonomous so on and you
can have agents that interact with
digital environments such as video games
or iPhone and if you count human as an
environment then chatbot is also some
kind of agent and uh if you want to
Define agent you really need to Define
what is in intelligent and what the
environment and what's really
interesting is that throughout the
history of AI the definition of what
intelligent often changes across time
right so like like like 60 years ago if
you have a very basic chat bot using
like three lines of rule then it can it
can be seen intelligent but right now
even CH is not surprising anymore so uh
I think a good question for you all is
like how do you even Define
intelligence okay so let's say have some
definition of agent then what is LM
agent so I really think there are three
uh categories or three uh Concepts so I
think the uh first level of concept is
what is a Tex agent and I think test
agent is defined as uh so you have this
agent interacting with the environment
and if both the text and act observation
is in language then it's a text so
obviously uh you can have text agent
that's not using LMS and in fact we have
tax agent from the beginning of AI like
several decades
ago and I think the second level of
definition is LM agent which is agents
that are Tex agent that are also using
LM to act right so uh and I think the
last level is uh what I call reasoning
agent and the idea is you uh those
agents use LMS to reason to act and and
uh so right now you might be confused
what is the difference between the
second level and the third level uh
which I will explain
later so like I said uh people have been
developing tax agent from the beginning
of AI right so uh for example like back
in 1960s there has already been chat bot
so Elisa is one of the earliest chat
Bots and the idea is really simple you
just have a bunch of uh and what's
really interesting is that using like a
bunch of rules you can already make a
chat out that's uh that's quite human
right and what it does is it keep asking
you questions or repeating what you said
and and people find it very human and
uh uh but obviously like there are
limitations to those kind of rule based
agents as you can see like if you want
to design rules then it often is very
task
specific and for each new domain you
need to develop uh some new rules right
and and lastly like those rules not
really work Beyond a simple domain right
suppose you write many rules to to build
a chat bot but then you need to write
many rules for a video game agent and so
on and so
forth so
uh before alms there's another very
popular Paradigm which is to use RL to
build tax agent and the idea is uh I'm
sure everybody have seen video games
right so you can imagine text games
where instead of pixels and keyboard
you're using text as observation and
action and you similarly have rewards
you can similarly use reinforcement
learning to optimize the reward and idea
is you can just optimize the reward and
you you exibit some kind of uh language
intelligence but again uh this kind of
method are pretty domain specific right
for each new domain you need to train a
new agent and it really requires you to
have skill reward signal for the task at
hand which many of the task don't and
lastly it takes extensive training which
is a feature of
RL so really if you think about the
promise of LMS to revolutionize Tech
agent right uh this LMS are really just
train on next token prediction on
massive Tex Cora yet during time it
could be prompted to solve various new
tasks so uh this kind of generality and
FAL learning pH
will be really exciting to build
agents so uh next I want to give a a
brief overview ofm agents and it's also
like a historic View and uh it's
obviously very simplified so
um I think what what's happening is so
first we have something like LM in 2020
I think the beginning of M is GB3 and
then people start to explore that across
different tasks
and some tasks happen to be reasoning
task such as symbolic question answering
and so on and some tasks happen to be
what I call acting task you can think of
games or Robotics and so on so
forth and then uh we find that this
Paradigm of reasoning and Paradigm of
acting are start to converge and we
start to build what I call reasoning
agent that's actually quite different
from all the previous
agents and from reconing agent uh we
start to explore uh on one hand more
interesting applications and tasks and
domains such as web interaction or self
engineering or even scienic Discovery
and so on and on the other hand we start
to explore new methods such as memory or
learning or planning or multiv and so
on so uh first I want to uh introduce
you know what I mean by the Paradigm of
reasoning and what I mean by the
Paradigm of acting and how they converge
and what is this Paradigm of reasoning
agent and uh history is always massive
so for now let's just assume uh let's
focus on one task which is question
answering which can simplify our uh
history discussion a little bit and then
we'll come to more
tasks so question answering is a very
intuitive task right so uh if you ask a
language model what is 1 plus two it
will tell you three right that's
question answering it's very
intuitive uh so it's also happens to be
one of the most useful task in NLP right
so obviously people try to use language
models to do question
answering and then people find a lot of
questions a lot of problems when you try
to answer
questions okay so if you have some
question like this uh it will be very
hard for the Transformer language model
to just output the answer directly right
so it turns out you need some reasoning
and uh then covering the last talk like
Chain of Thought reasoning and so on and
so forth there has been a lot of people
investigating how to do better reasoning
with language
models uh you can also Imagine like
language model trying to answer
something like this and it will probably
give the answer wrong because uh for
example if a language model is trained
before
20124 and the prime minister of UK
change often as you know so it might get
a answer wrong right so in that case you
you need new knowledge and people are
working on
that uh and for another example like you
can ask something that's really
mathematical and really hard and in that
case like you cannot really expect
Transformer to give the answer right so
in some sense you need some way of doing
computation Beyond uh beyond the laive
auto regression of
Transformer so as you can see like there
are many types of question answering
tasks and people find many problems
when using language model to to answer
those questions and then people come up
with various
Solutions so for example if you're
trying to uh solve you know the the
problem of computation right what you
can do is you can first use the language
model to generate a program and then
this program will run and give you a
result that's the way you can answer you
know question about prime factorization
or was a a 50 fibach
number so for the for the problem of
knowledge uh there's this Paradigm of
retrieval argumented generation right
and and the idea is uh very simple right
you you have you assume you have some
extra Cora for example Wikipedia or uh
this uh COA of this company for
example and then you have a retriever
whether it's a bm25 or DPR or or so on
and so forth uh you can think of
retriever as kind of a search engine
right so what it does is given a
question this retriever will actually
just pull the relevant information from
the cpra and then append that to the
context of the language model so that
it's much easier for the language model
to to answer the
question uh so this is a very good
pattern however uh what if there's no ca
for the knowledge or information that
you care about right for example if I
care about to this's weather in San
Francisco it's very hard to expect any
existing C to have that right
so uh people also find this solution
called to use and the idea is uh you
have this natural form of generation
which is to generate a sentence but then
you can introduce some special tokens so
that it could invol tool calls right for
example you have a special token of a
calculator or a special token for a
Wikipedia search or a special token for
uh calling a weather
API
um so this is very powerful obviously
you can argument uh language models with
a lot of different uh knowledge
information and even
computation but if you look at this this
is not really a very natural format of
text right there's no like blog post or
a Wikipedia passage on the internet that
looks like this so if you want language
model generate something like this you
have to fine-tune that in this very
specific format and it turn are very
hard to call that uh uh more than once
across the uh across the
text so uh another natural question come
right what if you need both reasoning
and knowledge and people actually come
up with a bunch of solutions for a
different tasks right for example you
can imagine interleaving the Chain of
Thought and retrieval or or generate
followup questions and so on so forth um
but uh with need to get into the details
of all the mths I just want to point out
like uh the the situation at the time
was a little scattered right so you have
this single task called QA when it turns
out to be more than a single task you
actually have like tons of different
benchmarks right and they happen to
challenge language models in very
different ways and and people come up
with uh solutions for each of the
Benchmark so it's it feels very piz at
least for me right and at least for me
at the time uh the question is uh can we
really have a very simple and unifying
solution and I think if we want to do
that we really need abstraction Beyond
you know individual task or mthod we
need like a higher level abstraction
over what's
happening so the abstraction that I find
at least for myself is the obstruction
of reasoning and
acting so what is reasoning uh hope you
already know that from Denis talk last
time uh so Chain of Thought right uh
it's very intuitive and it's just a very
flexible and general way to to argument
test time compute and to syc for longer
uh during inference time to solve more
complex questions right however if you
only do Chain of Thought uh you don't
have any external knowledge or tools
right even the biggest smartest model in
the world does not know the weather in
San Francisco today so if you want to
know that you need external environment
knowledge and
tools and what I have described as like
ride or retrieval or code or tool use
and so on and so forth in some sense
it's just a paradigm of acting because
you're just assuming you are having an
agent and you have various environments
whether it's retrieval search engine
calculator API or python right um and
the benefit of interacting with the
external environment is that that it's
very it's like a flexible and general
way to argument knowledge and
computation and feedback and so on and
so
forth however uh it doesn't have
reasoning and we will see later why
that's uh
Troublesome so uh the word the idea of
this word called react is actually very
simple right uh so you have this two
Paradigm recently
acting uh and before react like language
models are either generating reasoning
or acting and for react the idea is to
just generate both and we will see that
it's actually a great way to synergize
Po in the sense that reasoning can help
acting and acting can help reasoning and
it's actually quite simple intuitive you
will see later it's actually you can
argue that's how like I solve the task
or you solve the task it's a very human
way to solve the task and it's very
general across the
domain so the idea of react is very
simple right suppose you want to a task
and what you do is you write a prompt
and the prompt consists of a trajectory
that looks like this so you give a
example task and as a human you just
write down how you think and how you do
what you do to solve the task along with
the observation along the way right so
if you're trying to answer a question
using Google engine you just think about
some stuff and do some search and then
you write down that and they also write
down the result Google and you keep
doing that until you solve the
task uh you can give this one
example uh and then you can give a new
task and given this prompt language
model will generate a thought and action
and this action is parsed and fit into
the external environment and then that
would figure some observation and then
the Sol action observation is appended
to the context of the langage model and
then language model generate the new Sol
and new action and so on so
forth so obviously you can do that using
a single example that's called One Shot
prompting you can do that with few
examples that's called f sh prompting if
you have many many examples you can also
find T Lang model to do that so it's
really about a way to use langage model
rather than a prompting or
fine-tuning so as a concrete example uh
let's say you want to answer a question
right if I have S trillion dollars uh
can I buy Apple Nvidia and Microsoft uh
I make this slide back in March and that
was a trendy Topic at the time uh
so you can write down a prompt like that
you just say Okay language model now
you're agent and you can do two type of
actions you can either Google or you can
finish with the answer and you just need
to write on the Sol an action okay so
that's very intuitive and let's say what
language model do right so this is what
gbd4 does back in March so it first
generat start right so first I need to
understand I need to find what is the
market cap of those companies and then
add them together so that I can
determine if7 trillion dollars can buy
all three
companies um and then this triggers this
action to search on Google and this
Google Search returns this snamp as a
result unfortunately like it just
contains all the market caps you need so
uh the react AED that and now I have the
other market cap all I just need to do
is to add them together so it uses
search engine as a calculator add them
together and get a result and it will
think okay uh so $72 is not enough so
you need additional money to buy that I
think if it's us today then it's even
more money because Nvidia is much higher
now uh yeah so that's how react solve
the Tas and you can see it's a very
intuitive way very similar to how humans
solve the Tas right you think about the
situation you do something to get some
more knowledge or information and then
based on information you think more
uh and then I try to be a little more
adversarial so uh instead of finding all
the market caps uh I inject this
adversar observation right nothing is
fine and here comes the power of
reasoning right so reasoning actually
finds a way to adjust the plan and guide
the action to adapt to the situation
right because the research is not result
is not fine maybe I can search for
individual market cap right so I can
just search for the market cap of Apple
and then I try to be out zero again I
give the stock price inside of the
market cap and here reasoning helps
again right based on common sense it
figures out right this is probably the
price not the market cap so if you
cannot find the market cap what you can
do is you can find the number of shares
and then you can multiply number of
shares and the market and the stock
price to get a market cap and then you
can do that for the uh all three
companies and then you can solve the
task so uh from the example I you can
see that it's not really acting helping
reasoning right obviously acting is
helping reasoning to get realtime
information or doing calculation in this
case but also reasoning is constantly
guiding the acting to plan the situation
and rep situation based on uh
exceptions so uh you can imagine uh
something like this to solve various
question answering task all you need to
do is to provide different examples and
provide different
tools so uh okay this is good uh we're
making progress uh but I think what's
really cool is
uh like this param goes beyond QA right
so if you think about it you can
literally use it to solve any
task and and to realize this all you
need to realize is a many task can be
turned into a text game so imagine if
you have a video game what you can do is
you can assume you have a
you know video captioning or image
capturing model and you can have some
controller that can turn language action
into a keyboard action and then you can
literally turn many of the task into a
text game and then you can literally use
react to solve them so uh it goes well
beyond uh press
answering so uh after you know the the
invention of n model obviously another
part of the history is uh the are people
from race for learning robotics video
game so on and so forth they're trying
to apply this technique and there are
many works and I'm only listing one for
example and the idea is uh very uh
intuitive like I said you can try to
turn all the observation into text
observation and then you can try to use
Lage model to generate text action and
then you turn the text action into some
original format of action and then you
solve the solve the
task but what what's the issue of this
right so uh this is an example from a
video game where you're trying to do
some household task in a kitchen right
and uh the the problem really is
sometimes it's really hard to directly
map observation into the action because
uh for for one you you may have never
seen the domain second like to to to
process you know like from the
observation to action you need to think
but if you don't have this thinking
paradigm like all you're are doing is
just uh trying to imitate the
observation to action mapping from the
from the prompt or from the future
example so in this case uh in the syn
Bas in one there is no paper shacker so
nothing happens but uh because it
doesn't have the capacity to sync it
will just keep doing that and keep
feeling because uh like it's it's like
language model it's just trying trying
to imit it so it's not really trained to
solve the task like agent
so what we us is actually something very
simple right you are literally just
adding another type of action called
thinking and thinking is a very
interesting action because you can think
about anything right so in this video
game you might only be able to go
somewhere or pick up something that's
the action space defined by the
environment but you can think about
anything and you can see that this sying
action is very useful because it help
you plan the situation it help you keep
track of the situation and help you plan
rep plan if something wrong
happens so as you can see like react is
a general pattern that helps uh across
various task and is systematically
better than if you only do reasoning or
only do
AC so
um this is interesting right and uh I
just want to point out why this is
interesting from a more theoretic
perspective so uh again abstraction
right so if you think about all the
agents that you have everything right
from video game to Alpha go to
autonomous car whatever like all the
agents
uh like one common feature is that you
have action space that's defined by the
environment right so assume you're
solving video game say Atara game then
your action space is left right up down
like you can be very good you can be
very bad but your action space is
fixed and what's really different for
language agent or LM agent or reasoning
agent is that uh you have this
argumented action called
reasoning and what's really interesting
about this argumented action is that it
could be any language right you can
think about anything it's a INF space
you can think about a par you can think
about a sentence you can think about a
word you can think about 10 million
tokens and it doesn't do anything to the
to the word right no matter what you
think it doesn't really change uh the
Earth or or the video game you're
playing all it does is it changes your
own context right it Chang changes your
memory and then based on that it changes
their followup
actions so uh so that's why I think this
new paradigm of rising agent it's
different it's different because
reasoning is an internal action for
agents and reasoning has a very special
property because it's an infinite space
of
language cool
um so we've covered the most important
part of the
talk uh I think the history goes on
right so from now on we have the
Paradigm of reasoning agent and then we
have more me more task and there's a lot
of progress obviously and I cannot cover
everything so on the methodological side
I just want to cover one thing today uh
which is longtime
memory so we just talk about what is
resing Agent and the idea is uh you have
an external environment be it video game
or uh Google search engine or or your
car or whatever and we just talk about
the difference reasoning agent is that
the agent can also think
right another way to to think about this
is uh you have an agent that has a shter
memory which is the context window of
the language
model
and it's interesting that uh you can
append interesting thoughts and actions
and observations to to this
context but
uh if you look look at this uh contest
window of the langage model first is
append only right so you can only app
new tokens to the
context and you have limited context
right so it could be a, token two years
ago it could be a million token now it
could be 10 million tokens uh next year
but you have a limited uh size of
context and even let's say we have a 10
million uh token window uh you might
have limited attention right so you can
have uh a lot of distracting things if
you're like doing a long Horizon SC
right and uh
lastly uh it is a shter memory because
this kind of memory does not persist
over time or over new task right so you
can imagine uh let's say this agent
solved REM hypothesis today which is
really good but then unfortunately if
you don't find tun language model right
it doesn't change right so next time we
have to solve from scratch again and
there's no guarantee whether it will
solve tomorrow right so U I think an
analog I want to make is it's kind of
like a golden fish right so uh folk
wisdom is a golden fish only has three
seconds of memory right so like you you
can you can solve something
remarkable but if you cannot remember it
then you have to solve it again and it's
really a shame
right so uh hope that's motivating
enough to introduce this concept of not
memory right so it's just like as a
human right you cannot remember every
detail in the in every day right but you
maybe you you may write a diary right
that's kind of like a long memory you
read and write important stuff for your
life for your future life like important
experience important knowledge are
important skills and hopefully that
should persist over new experience right
so you can also Imagine a mathematician
right writing a paper on how to prove
REM hypothesis that's kind of like a l
of memory right because then like you
can just read the paper and you can
prove it you you don't have to solve it
again
so uh let's look at a very very very
simple form of L memory in this word
called reflection which is a very simple
followup from
react so let's say you're are trying to
solve a coding task right this is a task
and you can imagine you can write some
program you can you can run a program
you can you can reason you can do
whatever uh but at the end of the day
right right you tested and let's say it
doesn't work right some some some some
tests
failed so if you don't have a lter
memory then you just have to try again
right um but what's different now is if
you have a long memory what you can do
is you can reflect on your experience
right so if you read a program and it
filled some test you can think about it
right it's like oh I I feel this task
because I forget about this col case so
if I write this program again I should
remember this and what you can do is you
can persist this piece of information
over time like when you write this
program again you can literally read
this lter memory and then you can try to
be better next
time uh and and hopefully it will
improve so this turns out to be working
really well for various tasks but
particular coding right because for
coding you have uh great feedback which
is the unit test result and you can just
keep reflect on your failure or success
and then you can keep track of the
experience as a sort of not memory and
then you can get
better another way to think about this
is uh it's really a new way of doing
learning right so if you think about the
traditional uh form of reinforcement
learning right so uh you do something
and then you get a skill
reward and and what you do is
essentially trying to back propagate the
reward to update the ways of your policy
and there like many many algorithms to
do
that if you think about uh reflex sound
right it's really a different way of
doing learning because first you're not
using skill reward you can use anything
right you can you can use a code
execution result you can use a compiler
Arrow you can use the feedback from your
teacher which is in text so on and so
forth and it's not doing learning by
ging descent right it's learning by
updating language right by language I
mean a lot of memory of task knowledge
and then uh you can think of this
language as affecting the future
behavior of the policy
right so this is only a very simple way
simple form of L memory and I think
fullop work did more complicated stuff
you will hear about Voyager from JY uh
later I guess where you have like a
memory of code based skills right and
the idea is for example you're trying to
play Minecraft and you learn how to uh
build a sword in in this kind of API
code then you can you can try to
remember it the next time if you want to
kill a zombie you can first pull the
skill of building a sword you don't have
to try to try it from scratch right and
uh for example in this work of
generative agents uh the idea is you
have like 20 human like agents in this
small town trying to be human you know
they have jobs they have life they have
social interaction so on and so
forth uh you have this episodic form of
longterm memory where you literally each
agent keeps a log of all the events
that's happened right every hour right
that's like a most detailed possible
diary you can possibly have and you can
imagine like like later if you want to
do something you can try to look at the
log to decide what to work on right
because if if you like drop off your kit
at this place you want to retrieve that
piece of information and then you pick
it
up uh you can also have this of sematic
memory where uh you can you can look at
your diary right and you can draw some
conclusions about other people and
yourself right you can realize you can
reflect on that and you can say okay
okay a Jim is actually very curious guy
and I actually like video game and this
kind of knowledge can actually affect
your behavior
later uh yeah so this is L memory and um
and I I think another the final step to
to finishing this part is to realize
that
uh you can actually also think of the
language model as a form of longterm
memory right so uh you can learn by
learn I mean improve you can improve
yourself or you can say you can change
Yourself by either changing your
parameters of the new network which is
to find to your language model or you
can some piece of code or language or
whatever in your L memory and then you
can retrieve from it later right so uh
that's just two ways of learning but if
you think of both the new network and
the and whatever uh text CA as Bose a
form of L memory then you have a unified
abstraction of
learning and uh then you have an agent
that has this power of reasoning over a
special form of short short term memory
called contest window of the L model and
then you can have various form of long
memory and in fact you can show that
this is almost just sufficient to
express any agent so uh I have this
paper called koala which I don't have
time to cover today but I encourage you
to check out where uh the student is
that you can literally just express any
agent by the memory which is where the
information is stored the action space
like what the agent can do and the
decision- making procedure basically
given the space of actions what what
which action you want to take right you
can literally express any agent with
these three parts so this is a very uh
clean and sufficient way of thinking
about uh any
agent and
uh uh I want to leave two questions for
you to think uh and I have answer in
this paper that you can try to
retrieve uh so the first question
is what what makes external environment
different from internal memory right so
imagine if the agent opens up Google doc
and write something there is that a form
of longterm memory or is that like some
kind of action to change the external
environment or like imagine if the agent
has a Archive of internet right and it
tries to retrieve some knowledge from
there is that a kind of action or is
that a kind of retrievable from a
longterm
memory I think this question is
interesting because if you think about
physical agents like humans are
autonomous cars right it's very easy to
Define what is external and what is
internal because for us like what's
outside our skin is external what's
inside our skin is internal right it's
very easy to Define but uh I want you to
think about for digital agents how can
you even Define
that and lastly like how do you even
Define longterm memory versus shortterm
memory like suppose you have a language
model context of 10 million tokens Can
can that still be called a l
memory uh know that those terms are
defined from kind of human Psychology
and Neuroscience and uh think about this
two questions
so okay so we have covered some brief
history of elm agents uh I also want to
uh talk about you
know uh the history of LM agents in the
broader context of Agents right we have
talked about how we start from LM to
derive various things and other
developments of language
agents uh but if you look at a more
Asian history how is reasoning agent
different from all the previous
paradigms of agent
so here I want to give a very very
minimum history of agents and it's
definitely wrong so it's just for uh
illustration right don't take that too
seriously but I think if you want to
write a very minimal history of agents
in one slide uh at the beginning of AI
right the Paradigm is called symbolic Ai
and you have symbolic AI agents and the
idea is kind of like programming right
you can program all the rules to
interact with all the different kind of
environments and uh you can have expert
system and stuff U and then you have
this period of AI winter right and and
then you have deep learning and you have
this very powerful Paradigm of RL agent
and it's usually deep R agent where you
have a lot of amazing miracles from
Atari to Ala go so on so
forth and only very recently we have L
Majors right so this is this is
obviously wrong but if I have to put
things in one slide this is kind of the
perspective um and and remember the
examples we look at at the beginning of
the talk right this is like a very
typical example of a symbolic a agents
and lstm DQ is very like typical example
of a deep RL agent in in the text
domain uh and I think one way to think
about the difference between the three
paradigms of Agents is uh the problem is
is the same right so you have some
observation from the
environment and you want to create
action right you want to take some
action and the difference is uh what
kind of representation what kind of
language do you use to process from the
observation to the action right so if
you think about symbolic AI agents
essentially you're first mapping all the
observation into some symbolic state
right and then you're trying to use the
symbolic state to derive some action you
can think of if else rule essentially
you're just trying to map all the
possible complex observations into a set
of logical Expressions
right and if you think about all the
Deep RL agents like a very abstract way
of thinking of this is you have many
different possible forms of observations
where it could be pixel it could be text
it could be anything but from a
different perspective it doesn't really
matter because uh it's mapped into some
kind of embedding right is processed by
new network to some vectors or matrixes
and then use that to derve some actions
right
uh and in some sense uh what's different
for language agent or reasoning agent is
that you are literally using language as
the intermediate representation to
process observation to action right like
instead of this neur neuro embedding or
this kind of symbolic State you're
literally thinking language which is
kind of the human way of doing things
right and um and the problem with
symbolic state or neur embedding is that
if you think about it it takes intensive
efforts to design those kind of symbolic
agents right if you think about how VMO
is built as a autonomous car right you
probably write minons of line of rules
and code right and if you think about uh
all those different agents most of them
it takes millions of steps to to pain
them right and and the problem is uh
both are kind of f specific right if you
write a minons of lines of code for
autonomous car right you cannot really
reuse that for playing video game
similarly if you train a agent using
using Min steps to to play video game
you cannot use that to drive cards
right
um language is very different because uh
first you don't have to do too much
right because you already have Rich
requires from LMS that's why you can
prompt to build LM agents it's really
convenient and uh it's very general
right you can think about how you drive
a car you can think about how to play a
video game you can think about uh which
house to buy right considering mortgage
rate and stuff uh and and sying is very
different from symbolic State and deep
RL because uh the symbolic State and the
Deep RL Vector right they usually have a
fixed size but you can think arbitrary
long right you can think about a
paragraph you can think about a sentence
and and that brings this whole new
dimension of infite time scaling and uh
and that's why fundamentally reasoning
agent is
different okay so
uh I just realized I just covered half
of uh the later half of the brief
history of AD agents right we talk about
long memory and why the methodology is
fundamentally different from the
previous agents I also want to briefly
talk about the new applications and
tasks that LM agency enabled so U as you
can see in the beginning of my talk the
examples are basically question
answering and playing games uh and
that's pretty much the the if you think
about it that's pretty much the
predominant Paradigm of MLP and RL right
but I think what's really cool about
language agents is that it really
enables much more applications and in
particular uh what I call digital
automation right so uh what I mean by
digital automation is imagine if you
have a assistant that can help you file
reimbursement reports or help you write
code uh
wrong experiments help you uh find
relevant papers help you review paper
help you find papers that's that are
relevant right if all of them can be
achieved then everybody can graduate
undergrad in two years or PhD in three
years
or uh or like get 10 year in three years
like everything can be speed up but if
you think about it like before charb
right there's literally no progress if
you think about Siri right which is the
state of art digital agent before chvt
right it literally can do nothing right
and uh and why is that uh I think the
reason is
that uh you really need to reason over
Real World Language right if you want to
write a code like this Paradigm of
sequence to sequence mapping is not
enough you have to think about what you
write it and why you write it and you
have to make decision over opened
actions over long Horizon right
uh but unfortunately if you think about
if you look at all the agent benchmarks
before before the existence of L or
agents they often look something like
this right so they usually they are
usually very like sythetic task very
small skill and not practical at all and
uh and that's that's been limiting for
the history of L agents because even you
have the best agents in the world if if
you don't have the good
task like how can you even show progress
right because like let's say we solve
this like great game with 100% accuracy
then then what does it mean right so uh
I think the history of LM agents on one
side is all the mthods getting better
and better but uh equally if not more
important side of the history is we're
getting um more practical and more
skillable
costs so so uh to have a flavor right
this task is called webshop and I
created with my co-authors in 2021
2022 and the idea is you can imagine LM
agents to help you do online shopping so
it give you give the agent instruction
to find a particular type type of
product it could just brow the web like
a human right it could click links it
could type search crus it could check
different products and go back and
search again and if it has to search
again has to explore different items let
think about how to reformulate the query
right you can you can immediately notice
right the environment is much more
practical and much more uh open-ended
than than grid
work and uh let's say you find a good
product you can just uh click all the
customization options and you can click
by now and uh you are you can also give
a reward from the1 indicating how good
yourself going pass so it's really like
a very standard Paradigm of
reinforcement learning environment
except that the observation and action
is in text and it turns out to be a very
very practical
environment and uh web shop is
interesting because it's the first time
people build large scale complex
environment based on large
scale uh real internet data right so at
the time we script more than a million
Amazon products and we build this uh
website and we build some automatic
reward system to uh to tell you know if
you find a product and here's the
instruction then how can you give a
reward to indicate how matching are the
two
things and you can clearly see it's
perhaps harder than the G word task
because uh you need to understand not
only the images and language in real
world domains but you also need to make
decisions over long Horizon right like
you have to maybe look like explore 10
different products or in different
search ques to find the perfect
match and um and for example on this
direction of lab interaction like full
work has made a progress great progress
you know beyond shopping you can you can
actually solve various tasks uh on the
web and and you can also uh try to solve
other practical tasks uh for example
software engineering right so uh in this
example suben is a is a task where uh
you are given a GitHub repo and a issue
right so you are given a bunch of files
in a repository right and and you're
given issue right this thing doesn't
work help me fix it and you're supposed
to Output you're supposed to Output a
faive that can resolve the issue right
so it's a very clean definition of the
task but it's very hard to solve right
because because if you want to solve it
you have to uh intera a s code base
right you have to create unit test you
have to run it and
uh and you have to
uh you have to try various things just
like a self-
engineer
um so
another example that I think is really
cool is uh like it's I think the current
progress is well Beyond digital
automation right so in this example from
uh camc a work that I really like uh the
idea is uh they're using reasoning oron
agents to try to find new
chromal and what's really cool is that
uh you give the agent a bunch of data
about some chemicals and you give them
access to use tools like python or
Internet or whatever and they could do
some analysis and try to propose some
kind of new chemical and also the the uh
action space of the agent is somehow
extended into the physical uh space
because the the action or the suggestion
from the agent is then synthesized in
the we lab and and and then you can
imagine you can get feedback from the
web and then you can use that to improve
yourself and stuff like that B so uh I
think it's really exciting that you can
think of language agent not only as
operating in the digital domain but also
in the physical domain not only in
solving like TDS tasks like bookia door
Dash but also more intelligent or
creative task like selft engineering or
scientific
discovery okay so great so we have
covered this slide finally so
uh in summary I have talked about you
know how we start from LM we have this
Paradigm of reasoning we have this
Paradigm of acting they converge and
that brings up uh more diverse tasks and
mthods and we have also covered in a
more broader you know time scale the
paradigms of agents and why this time is
different and uh also from a tast
perspective right
so uh the previous paradig of tast if
you think about in AI uh you can think
of games you can think of simulations
you can think of uh robotics but uh
really LM agents bring up this new
dimension of task which is to automate
various things in digal
word so we have covered a lot of history
and uh
uh I just want to summarize a little bit
in terms of lessons for doing research
right so uh I think personally uh as you
can see you know the it turns out some
of the most important work is some
sometimes most simple work right you can
argue like Chain of Thought is incred
incredibly simple and react is
incredibly simple and and simple is good
because simple means general right if
you have something extremely simple then
you have
probably something extremely General and
that probably is the best
research
um but but it's it's hard it's hard to
be simple right so uh if you want to be
simple in
general uh you need to
both like have the ability to thinking
abstraction right so you have to jump
out of individual tasks or data points
you have to syn in a higher level but
you also need to be very familiar with
the the individual task the data the
problem you're trying to solve right so
uh notice that you can actually it could
actually be distracting to be very
familiar with all the task specific
methods right so remember in the history
of QA I covered all those a lot of like
task specific methods like if you are
very fism then you might end up you know
trying to create an incremental solution
after that but if you're familiar with
not only QA but a lot of different tasks
and you can think in OB Direction then
then you can propose something simpler
and more
General and in this case I think really
learning the history helps and learning
other subjects helps uh because they
provide you some prior how for how to
build abstraction and they provide uh
Ways to Think in abstraction
okay so this is mostly the talk I think
uh I will just briefly talk about some
thoughts on the future of LM agents
right so uh everything before this slide
is history and everything after this
slide is kind of the state of art or the
future
um obviously future is very
multi-dimensional uh there are many
directions that are very exciting to
work on
uh I talk about I want to talk about
five keyword that I think
are uh truly ex truly exciting topics
that are first very new in the sense
that if you get to work on this now
there might be a lot of low highing
fruit or you might have a chance to
create some very
fundamental
uh results and second is somehow doable
in the Academia setup so you don't have
to be open ey to do this
uh but it's still good to be
open um so uh this five topics actually
um correspond to three recent work that
I did and I'll only cover them briefly
and if you have more interest you should
check out those papers uh yourself so
the topic is uh first training how can
we
train models for agents where can we
have the data right uh second interface
how can we build an environment for our
agents third robustness right how can we
make sure things actually work in real
life uh for human how can we make sure
things actually work in real life with
human right and lastly Benchmark how can
we build good
benchmarks so first uh training right so
I think it's interesting to note that
like up until this
year uh language model and agent are
kind of disentangled in sense that the
people that are training models and the
people building agents are kind of the
different people right and what is the
Paradigm is
that the model building people build
some model right and then the agent
building people build some agents on top
of it using some fine tuning or some
prompting mostly mostly
prompting however this model are not
trained for agents right so if you think
about the historical root of language
model it's just a model that's trained
to text like people can never imagine is
one they used to solve like chemical
Discovery or self engineering right so
that brings the issue of discrepancy of
the data array so it's not train to do
those things but then it's prompted to
do those things so the performance is
not
optimal and one solution to do that is
uh one solution to fix this is you
should train
models targeted for agents and one one
thing one thing you can do is you can
use those prompted agents to generate a
lot of data and then you can use those
data to find the model to be better as
agents and and this is really good
because first you can improve all the
agent capabilities not covered in
internet right so you can imagine uh on
the internet which is the predominant
source of language model training
there is not a lot of like self
evaluation kind of data right people
only give you like a well written blog
post but no one really releases all the
thought process and action process of
how to write the blog post but that's
actually the what matters for agent
training right so you can actually
prompt agents to to have those
trajectories and you can train models
all those
things
and and that's I think really one way to
fix the data problem because we all know
internet data is running out and how can
we have the next trillion dollars to
train models uh this is very exciting
and I think a
very like maybe not best analog is you
can think of the like the the Synergy
between GPU and deep learning right
because GPU first was not designed for
deep learning right it was first
designed to play games and then people
explore the usage find oh it's very good
for deep learning and then what happens
is that not only people use existing
gpus to build better deep learning
algorithms but also the GPU Builders fre
better gpus to fit the Deep learning
algorithms right you can build a GPU
that's speciic for Transformer or so on
so forth I think we should also
establish the Synergy between model and
agent and the second topic is interface
and in fact human computer interface has
been a subject for decades right it has
been a
a great topic in computer science and
really the idea is if you really cannot
optimize the agent you can optimize the
environment right because if you're
trying to write a code right even if
you're the same person it makes a
difference whether you're doing that in
the text edit interface or the vs code
interface right you're still the same U
like you're not being more smart but if
you have a better environment then you
can solve the Tas
better I think the same thing happens
for uh for agents right so it's a very
concrete
example you can imagine uh how can the
agent like say search files in OS right
so the the the human interface in
terminal as we all know is to use LS and
CD and so on and so forth uh it works
for humans but it's not the best
interface for agents
uh you can also do something like you
can you can you know you can define a
new command called search and then it
will it will give a result and then you
can use this action called next to get
the next result but it's probably still
not the best for language model So In
This research Called Agent what we find
is that what turns out to be the best
way to help agents uh search files is to
have this specific command called search
and instead of giving one result at a
time you just give 10 result at a time
and then use that the agent decide
what's the best file to look at right
and you can actually do experiments and
show like you can use the same language
model you can use the same agent prompt
but the interface matters for for for
Downstream
tasks so uh I think this is a very very
exciting topic and it's only getting
started and it's a great research topic
for Academia you don't need to have a
lot of gpus to do that uh and and it's
interesting because models and humans
are different so social interfaces right
you cannot expect language models to use
vs code to be the best code interface
right so there must be something
different and we need to explore
that uh and in this case you can think
of the difference as being that human we
just have a smaller shter memory right
if I give you 10 results at the same
time you cannot just read them that's
why for human interface you have to
design that in an interative way right
you have a next button right if you do
control F you can only read one thing at
a time but actually for models it's it's
worse because models have a longer
content window right so if you control F
you should just probably give everything
to to the model right so if you design
better interface it could help you solve
H better with
agents it could also help you understand
agents better right it could help you
understand some of the fundamental
differences of human and
mods uh lastly I I want to point out
this topic of human the loop and
robustness
so um I just want to point out there is
this very big discrepancy between
existing benchmarking and what people
really care in the real real world right
so you can think of a very typical agent
task or AI task say coding with unit
test and and this is a part from alpha
alpha code 2 and basically the idea is
if you sample more times then the chance
that you have a right submission
increases right that's very
intuitive and if you have a unit
test then then you can SLE many many
times obviously and what you really care
is what we call pass at K right what you
really care about is can I solve it one
time out of 10,000 times or thousand
times or million times right it's kind
of like solving REM hypothesis you just
need to do it once right what you care
about is if you sample 10 million times
can you solve it
once but if you think about all the most
of the jobs in the real world it's more
about robustness right so suppose you're
trying to do customer service right uh
like LM agents already deployed for
customer service but sometimes they
loses and there are consequences right
and if it may do something the company
might have composition and stuff that
right so
um arguably you know customer service is
much easier
than coding or or or proving REM
hypothesis at least for human right but
here it really presents a different
challenge because what you care about is
not can you solve it one time out of a
thousand time what you care about is can
you solve it a thousand time out of
thousand time right you care about what
I feel it one time out of s time because
if you feel one time then you might lose
a customer right so uh it's more about
getting simple things done
reliably so I think really that calls
for a different way of doing
benchmarking and uh we have this recent
work called tall bench and the idea is
uh first you have a very practical task
which is to do customer
service second uh you're the agent is
not only interacting with some kind of
environment like digital environment
it's also interacting with a human
but it's a simulated human right
so the idea is uh the customer service
agent just like a human customer service
agent need to interact with both the
backand NPI of the company and also some
kind of
user and the agent really needs to
interact with both to solve the task and
the trory might look something like this
right so the the the human might might
not give you all the information at the
beginning right which is a a predominant
Paradigm of all the task right now if
you think about self engineering and so
on so forth imagine say something like
change flight and then you you might
need to actually prompt the user oh can
you tell me like which fly are you
changing and you need to interact with
the user over multiple terms to to
figure out what they need and to and to
help them right and this is very
different and also it makes the metric
that you care about different right so
uh you can imagine for the same task
right uh you can sample the CH multiple
times with the same user
simulation so if you look at a dash line
it's called pass at K which is measuring
you know if you sample 10 times can you
solve it at least one time and obviously
as you sample more the chance that you
solve at least one time increases
right but
here you don't care about whether you
can solve it one time out of 10 times
you care about whether you can solve it
10 times out of 10 times
because otherwise you will lose client
you might lose customer right so so so
the solid line measures is you sample
more what's the chance you can always
solve the task across all the possible
tasks and what we see in today's
language model is that obviously they
have different starting points meaning
like obviously they have different
capabilities but uh what's really
concerning is they all have this
decreasing Trend right so if you sample
more the robustness always go down like
from the small model to big model they
all have the similar Trend the ideal
Trend should be something more flat
right so if you can solve something you
should be more reliable to solve the
same thing over time so I just want to
point out that uh I think we also need
some more effort in taking more real
world elements into benchmarking and
that requires new settings and
Matrix so uh we have this blog post uh
that talks about you know some thoughts
on the future of language agents and one
way to think about that is you want to
think about what kind of jobs uh they
can replace right and and if you think
about it right maybe the first type of
task is kind of not that intelligent
right but really require robustness
right if you think about simple
debugging or doing customer service or
doing Simple assistant over time and
time
and second you need to collaborate with
humans and third you might need to do
very hard task right you can you might
need to do like write a survey from
scratch or discover a new chrom aold and
that requires some new type of ways for
the agents to explore on its own but I
think it's in general very useful to
think about what jobs uh they can
replace and why they're not replacing
those human jobs yet and what are
missing and how can we improve it
um Lastly lastly uh this is a like
limited time and we're going to have a
uh em tutorial on language
agents uh in November and uh it will be
three hours so hopefully it will be more
comprehensive than this