Yeah, please take Lou.
>> All right, cool. Yeah, thank you. Thank
you so much for the kind introduction.
Um, all right. So, today we're going to
talk about uh diffusion language models
um which was you know the focus of my
thesis research during my PhD uh at
Cornell. Okay. So, uh traditionally auto
reggressive models uh have been the
dominant uh language generation
paradigm, right? uh but now they face
serious challenges from um from this new
class of algorithms called diffusion
language models. Unlike AR models which
generate text strictly in a left to
right fashion, diffusion models are
freed from this constraint. Uh which
means that they can generate text in any
sequence. uh and most notably they can
generate words in parallel right and
recently these models have attracted
significant attention with major
releases such as um Google's Gemini
diffusion by dancer's seed diffusion and
inception labs Mercury coder their
impact has even reached the mainstream
with Forbes and Fortune you know
publishing articles highlighting the
effectiveness of these of these
algorithms and all this excitement is
justified these models are not only
highly effective but also substanti
faster than the auto reggressive
counterparts. In this talk, we'll take a
closer look at these models, examining
the innovations that drive their success
and you know and and why they represent
such a compelling shift in the landscape
of text generation. Um, okay. So, here's
a quick overview of the timeline.
Diffusion alms were first introduced in
2022. Uh unlike AR models which predict
left to right, these models were uh
generate words uh in a randomized order
as you can see in this uh GIF. Um let me
turn on the laser pointer. Okay. Uh the
main drawback though was that you know
despite being much faster their text
quality lagged behind that of utter
regressive models and the community
didn't really take this model seriously
until early last year when lu at all
showed that diffusion LMS when paired
with modern transformer architectures
could match the sample quality of older
auto reagent models like GPD2 while
being significantly faster. Um a few
months later we released MDLM uh where
we formulated uh where we reformulated
and simplified the diffusion training
algorithm and showed that these models
can match the performance of auto
reggressive models at least on smaller
text data sets. Um the next breakthrough
came earlier this year um in this paper
called the diffusion duality where we
proposed distillation algorithms which
allow these models to generate let's say
thousandword sequences in just 10 steps
with little to no degradation in and uh
central quality and finally we developed
SOM uh which fuse auto reggressive
models with discrete diffusion unlike
previous methods SOM support KV caching
without compromising parallel generation
and hence our orders of magn magnitude
faster at inference than standard uh
diffusion models and together these
papers have uh made diffusion elements
practical and um you know like like most
notably by dancers's uh seed diffusion
framework was built uh on uh was built
using the MDLM framework that we're
going to cover in this talk. Okay. So uh
for today uh we're going to focus on
these two papers um uh MDLM and SLMs and
um yeah let's uh I would say yeah let's
get started with our first paper which
is simple and effective mass diffusion
language models. Um okay so uh our goal
is to design a language model from which
you can do parallel sampling that is um
you don't want to generate words in a
left to right fashion you uh you know
like AR models do it and these are slow
so we want to design a language model
which can generate multiple words at the
same time so the way this this is going
to work is you start with a sequence of
all blanks and then you feed this into a
bird-like model is essentially a
transformer with birectional attention,
right? Where every word dep like you
know depends on uh the entire context
unlike auto reggressive models where
each word depends uh on itself and uh
and and and the the and the uh prior
context. Okay. So you feed this sequence
of models into a birdlike model and the
bird is going to fill out words uh uh
fill out you know fill out some words uh
fill out some more some more and finally
when it's done you'll have a true sample
from the underlying distribution
um let's assume we have a sentence like
the one that I showed earlier in the
talk uh represented as a sequence of 1D
sequence with colored boxes at the
bottom uh when we talk about noise we're
going to talk about masking noise we'll
wipe out words specific specifically to
represent that they are masked and of
course while talking about mass
diffusion we will be comparing against a
standard auto reggressive model. Um to
get started you can think of auto
reggressive language model as generating
words by auto reggressive unmasking.
That is you start with the sequence of
blanks and then the model fills out one
word at a time right like given uh
having predicted these words the model
will predict the next word so on and so
forth. And you know finally when it's
done you have the the clean clean
sentence shown at the very top of the
slide. Um
in this work we're going to take a step
towards discrete masking diffusion. Uh
in the upcoming slides I'll first
introduce the MDLM framework that we
proposed in this paper and then later on
we'll discuss some of the results and we
will try to compare and contrast as to
how MDLM differs from the prior uh
discrete fusion approaches and what led
to the success of uh MDLM. Okay. So
here's what our process uh would look
like. We have the clean sentence X at
the very top of the slide and the fully
mass version at the bottom. So here we
have function Q that goes down and wipes
out words, right? Uh and then uh you
have a function P theta on the right and
the goal of you know generative model
generative modeling is that to undo a
known corruption process. So you have
this function Q that is going down and
is trying to con and converts this the
sentence X into a sequence of all mass
tokens. Um we don't yet know how Q
works. Uh which we which we'll discuss
in the next few slides. And then the our
ultimate goal is to learn this function
P theta that is going to take us from a
sequence of all blanks to the clean
sentence text uh at the top. Right?
Okay. So, um,
so what I'm highlighting in red is a is
a partially mass sequence. We're going
to call it ZT. Um,
and
and okay, so now now let's break this
down into individual components. Well,
the first step is we need to understand
what going down means, you know, like uh
how do we go from clean sentence to a
sequence of all mass tokens? Uh first
we're going to subdivide the space based
on based on the signal level alpha t. Uh
so alpha when alpha t is one it
represents a clean sentence x and when
alpha t is zero it represents a fully
masked version right and uh to go from
clean sentence x to um this uh
intermediate noisy state z what we do is
we simply flip a coin. So for every uh
clean word we flip a coin and we mask
the word with a probability 1 minus
alpha t right. So imagine this let's say
for this uh at this point let's say
alpha t is.3. So you flip a coin for
every word and you mass the word with
probability 7 and doing that will give
you uh this intermediate sequence uh ZT
here right okay now now this is probably
the most uh one of the most important
slides uh in this entire talk this
function q of zs given zt comma x
describes the is the unmasking function
right so let's try to understand like
what this is so this is this tells This
is essentially the u uh reverse
posterior.
So this function uh says that okay given
some noisy sequence zt how do we go to a
less noisy sequence zs right. So if you
notice this function q has two is like
is conditioned on two things zt and x.
So what this tells you is that you know
hey if I have this noisy sequence ZT uh
for every mask token I unmask it with a
probability uh given here. So again
alpha s is some noise level alpha s is
the sorry alpha is the signal level
corresponding to uh your time step s you
know s is just a time step that is less
than t and alpha t is the noise is the
signal level corresponding to zt and
then you have this uh this term here and
it says that okay given zt I unmask a
token with probability this and uh the
token is unmasked to the clean version
because in this case you know what x is
You know what the clean signal is, you
know what the noisy sequence ZT is. The
question is what is the the less noisy
sequence zs right? Naturally, this is a
very um you know, well, if you have like
this function itself uh isn't very
useful in the sense that if you have x,
there's no reason for you to simulate
the unmasking process starting from m,
right? If you have x, you're just like
the challenge arises uh uh the the
challenge is you do not have x and the
goal is to learn some representation of
x that you can plug in here during
generation because imagine this. So
during generation you have a sequence of
blank token like sequence of mass tokens
M. You do not know what X is. So the
question is how do you go from M to X
right and for that we're going to use
this function. So that's the P theta
function. So P so what we're going to do
so what we do is we train a neural
network which we will discuss you know
the exact loss function and you know
what is the principal way to train such
a network in the next slides. But to
give you some to give you some sense of
what the function p theta is is this
essentially uh you imagine you have a
trained uh birdlike model. Um and uh to
go from a noisy sequence zt to a less
noisy sequence z you would simply plug
in the represent the clean
representation that you network learned
into this into the q function and then
that gives you the p theta function. So
P theta will take you from ZT to ZS. And
uh the way unmasking works is you have a
clean clean token that stays that always
stays clean. We'll talk about it later
why. And for the unmasked token, you
know, you so so given a mask token, you
flip a coin and you unmask it with this
probability that we saw earlier, but it
is not yet clear like what token it
unmasks to, right? So so so you simply
sample you know X theta is essentially a
categorical distribution uh uh for for
the entire for all the mask positions.
So you flip a coin and you draw uh a
token specified by X theta and that
becomes your unmasked uh token. Um okay
anyway so now the question is how do you
tr train this D noising transformer X
theta right? Um all right so
uh we'll go over this uh uh uh one by
one. So at the very top what I'm showing
you is um uh it's called uh the elbow um
in auto reggressive model. The way you
train an auto reggressive model is uh
you have the true likelihood of the
sentence and you're trying to minimize
the negative log likelihood which
essentially means maximizing the
likelihood. But in diffusion models you
cannot compute the exact likelihood. So
what you do have is a bound on the
likelihood which is given uh by this
equation here and um yeah and this is
what I'm showing you is uh one of the
loss functions that uh one can use to
train these discrete diffusion models.
Um okay so there are a couple of things
here. First we have an expectation.
Let's try to understand like how to
compute this expectation. So you you
remember like uh we subdivide the space
you know like from top to bottom where
alpha t was very like t equals alpha t
equals 1 uh was clean signal x and that
also represented t equals z. So your
diffusion process essentially you know
starts with this x which is t equals 1
and goes all the way to t equal sorry
your diffusion process starts at x which
is t equals0 and goes all the way to t=
1 which is fully mass sequence. You
sample a you sample a time step t
randomly corresponding to that you flip
a coin and you get a noisy sequence zt
right. So this zt is essentially fed to
the dnoising model. Okay. So the next
thing is uh you have another term here
uh in the diffusion elbow which is alpha
which is a chance of unmasking. This is
something that we discussed earlier. So
the purpose of this slide is to show to
give you an intuitive explanation as to
what every individual term in the
diffusion loss means. Right? So you have
you wait uh you have a waiting term
which is essentially the chance of
unmasking and finally you have a cross
entropy loss. Now here what this means
is um your your x theta is a transformer
uh you feed the noisy sequence zt into
the transformer and you're computing the
loss across the entire sequence right
but due to some uh and this transformer
has a copy over operation which means
that if uh something is clean you can
just predict it as it is. So it's
effectively this uh cross entropy loss
is only computed for the missing masked
tokens and yeah you're you're feeding ZT
into a BL light model and you're
computing the cross entropy loss uh for
the missing tokens and you sum them over
you have a waiting term boom and that's
your that's your uh diffusion loss but
uh one interesting thing um you know we
have been talking about uh so if if I go
back to the previous slide there's a
capital T So this capital T tells you
that how many uh uh the number of time
discretizations between t=0 to t= 1. Uh
in the mdlm paper we essentially show
that you know if you set capital t to
infinity uh this effectively uh
represents a continuous time markoff
chain and uh the term uh and then you
have this diffusion elbow uh which looks
like something like this. you have this
alpha t prime over y minus alpha t and
um yeah and this uh in a nutshell uh is
the MDLM paper like this is the main
contribution of the uh MDLM paper
proposing this very simplified uh
diffusion elbow which is very useful to
train these models and also during the
evaluation of these models we will talk
more about we'll talk more about the
interesting properties of this loss
function later on this slide But um
yeah, I just want to like summarize how
to train you know how training works in
MDLM.
Okay. So now now let's try to like
compare uh the training algorithms of um
auto resive model and the MDLM model. So
in AR the way this works is you have a
data set you sample a sentence X you
would feed this sentence into again X
theta is a deal is a causal transformer
in the in this case here. uh you and
then you compute the cross entropy loss
at every token right so every token is
only conditioned on the prior context um
yeah and then you train the model uh
using gradient descent and on the right
hand side I'm showing u the training
procedure of the MDLM model and you can
see these are very similar you sample a
sentence x um in addition uh
additionally like you you also have to
sample a time step t um and this
equation here is a very fancy way of
saying you mask out words by flipping
coins. So uh it tells you that you know
you mask every uh every token in x with
probability 1 minus alpha t that gives
you a noisy sequence zt that zt is fed
into this dn noising model that uses
birectional attention instead of causal
attention and you have and instead of
using cross entropy loss you have this
waiting term alpha t prime over 1 minus
alpha t and yeah there you go and then
this uh and that's how you train a mass
diffusion model. So this slide basically
tells you how if you know how to train
an auto reggressive model, you pretty
much know how to train a mass diffusion
model as well.
Okay. Now let's say you know we have
trained this model. Um uh the question
is how do we actually sample from this
model? So in this slide I'm showing one
step of generation, right? So given a
noisy sequence ZT, how do we go to a
less noisy sequence ZS? If you notice ZT
ZS has fewer mass tokens than ZT. Well,
the way this works is you just simply
feed feed this into the birdlike model.
And this model is going to fill out uh
um fill out all the mass tokens, right?
And the way this works is this model has
essentially learns a distribution over
possible tokens for every mask token and
you sample from that distribution and uh
you just fill out the fill out the
entire sentence and you selectively
remask some of the predictions that the
model made. Um so the clean tokens in ZT
stay clean. the mass tokens uh only the
predictions that were made for the mass
tokens will be remasted and this is one
step of generation. Now I must say like
this is ancestral sampler. Uh this is
not something that I came up with. When
you solve the maths uh when you do the
maths you come up with a uh sampler that
that force that tells you to keep the
mask tokens so to keep the clean tokens
clean and only remask um the predicted
tokens. However, there are a lot of uh
heristic ways to go about sampling from
these models. I'll only talk about it if
there is a general interest. Otherwise,
we can we can safely skip those. Um
okay. So, this is one step of
generation, right? Uh now, if you want
to generate from the you know uh yeah,
so the the full generation scheme looks
something like this where you would
start from all mass tokens and you
recursively use the onestep generation
scheme. that we talked about earlier
until you end up with a clean sentence
size. So here what you see is uh in the
first den nosing step only this word is
predicted in the next den nosing step
you predict the these two words and you
know like that's how that's how uh you
recursively
use the previous uh unmasking strategy
and you and you uh end up with a cleat
sentence x and uh yeah so you know like
that's that was the that's how you train
and sample from the MDLM model. Now
let's try to take a look at some of the
experimental results. Okay. So um on
LM1B uh what we see is um on the Y-axis
we report perplexity. Perplex a lower
perplexity number means a better fit to
the data. In language modeling
perplexity is the go-to metric because
um at the end of the day what people
care about is downstream performance.
let's say on coding data sets or on on
coding reasoning and all those things,
right? What people found empirically was
that if you if a model gets good
perplexity scores on uh on your train or
the on on the validation set, it maps to
better performance in the downstream
test. Right? So that's why uh perplexity
is a is a very um useful metric in in
NLP. Okay. So y-axis perplexity on the
x-axis we have MDLM and other baselines
as well. SE is probably the the the
closest baseline to MDLM.
Um and what we see is that MDLM
significantly outperforms all the
baselines and approaches the AR
performance um approaches the AR
performance simil and this was on LM1B.
LM1B is a small data set um and the
context length was 128. So when we
increase the context length to,24 we do
see a similar thing where uh you know
like MDLM gets better perplexity than
said but however there's still still
some gap but it's um but it's not uh but
it's it's still pretty promising um
given you know like earlier uh mass
diffusion models were way worse than the
AR baseline. Um okay now now in this
slide I'm showing zero shot likelihood.
So what this means is you train your
data on open web text and you see how
well your model performs on other data
sets that it had not seen uh during
training like PTB archive or PubMet
right um what we and again world number
means better what we see is that like
MDLM consistently uh outperforms said
and uh very interestingly it uh gets a
better score than on three out of seven
uh data set uh which at that time was
very promising.
Uh okay and and NDLM you know like has
been scaled up at um uh at 8 billion and
uh I have some I'd like to share some
results from this paper Lada large
language diffusion models. Okay. So
effectively LA is is exactly an MDLM
model but at 8 billion scale. Uh they
name it Lada and uh in the blue here we
have the auto reggressive baseline. So
this plot here is about uh multi
multitask language understanding. Um a
higher number means better on the
y-axis. On the x-axis you have training
flops. Essentially you train you're
training this model this 8 billion
parameter model uh for a long period of
time and then you monitor the downstream
performance on this data on this
particular test. what you see is very
interesting like MDLM consistently
gives you better uh better score than
the AR baseline right even though like
in the previous slide we saw that there
was some gap between performance between
MDLM and AR in this slide we see that
when you look at actual downstream
performance on this particular test MDLM
does much better than the AR baseline
right similar on reasoning you see that
the the scaling for MDM them is way like
it's probably exponential as compared to
uh like linear in the AR case. Uh and
this again is very promising um um like
MDLM does like way better at reasoning
than it does than it does uh sorry than
the AR model. Okay. There were some
negative results in the paper as well
where uh they saw that on test like
common sense questions or coding uh MDLM
was at par with AR or slightly worse
like here I mean it's inconclusive if
MDM is better but you know we would say
that you know MDM is at par with the AR
baseline um and here um MDLM slightly
lagged AR
okay now MDLM was also um now okay so
here we talked talked about language
generation, right? So, language
generation implicitly has a left to
right bias. That's how humans talk. It
is also reflected in the way natural
text appears. Uh now, if you look at
modeling other discrete data structures,
let's say protein generation or drug
discovery or molecule generation, there
is no left right nature. Uh there is no
left right bias and that's where we see
uh MDLM perform the best. For instance,
uh in this paper, Gen Mo, um
uh these people trained an MDLM model
for uh predicting molecules. And what
they found was, you know, they modified
the sampling scheme that we discussed
earlier uh where they did some greedy
they had some um yeah, they came up with
a curriculum uh that uh that performed
some uh sampling with the temperature
basically. And when you okay effectively
this paper suggested a sampler and when
you vary the hyperparameters of that
sampler you get this paral frontier what
you see is this on the y-axis you have
the quality of a of a predicted molecule
a higher quality means high quality
molecule that the model predicts and on
the x axis you have diversity right what
these people found was um the AR
baseline in this shin star uh you know
there is no such trade-off but with the
MDLM you can you can um vary the the
sampling temperature and get this parad
frontier where you are strictly better
than the ARB baseline here. So you can
you can depending on your need you can
modify the uh the the the sampling
hyperparameter to get generate molecules
that are of very high quality and less
diversity.
But if you care about diversity, you can
also do that. It's going to degrade the
quality naturally, right? um while
increasing the diversity of the
molecules. So yeah, so MDLM has been
really successful uh has been
successfully applied
on um tasks like uh drug discovery and
also there are a lot of uh controllable
guidance tasks which unfortunately I
could not include the slides for. Um
MDLM does really well there. So imagine
okay imagine this you have uh this
generative model MDLM model that
predicts the molecules right let's say
you want to you want your generated
molecule to have certain properties uh
and it is very difficult to do that with
the AR model uh AR models uh are very
notori are notoriously difficult to to
uh perform controlled sampling from uh
So but with MDLM um if you remember uh
but MDLM is highly suitable for control
generation. The reason is very simple.
If you remember from the previous slide
u you have this uh noisy sequence ET and
then you get this and the BL like model
will fill out all the mass tokens right
which means that you have access to a
representation of what the final sample
can look like. And because you have
access to that information, that high
level information, you can tweak your
sampling process in a way that will
allow you to generate samples with
desirable properties. So yeah, um there
are certain some papers that came out
early this year that that highlight
that. Uh okay, now let's talk about the
limitations of uh of uh MDLM. Well, the
first thing is especially in the context
of language generation, there's
something called KB caching. Let's take
a look at like what is KV caching,
right? So the way KB caching works is
this. So you have a token you know like
you have a word and then your causal uh
transformer is going to map the word the
first word to the next word right and
then you you take that word feed that
into the model again the model the your
AR transformer will map it to the next
word. But if you notice one thing um the
the word a does not change right I mean
the activations corresponding to the
word a are never going to change as the
model predicts words because it's causal
the this tok the activations here do not
depend on the future tokens. So what
during inference uh what people do is
they would freeze the activations uh uh
once a word is predicted right so you
predict B you can safely freeze the
activations without any degradation in
quality uh whatsoever so yes so this is
uh and naturally you can see as you
predict the words you're doing a forward
pass of a single word instead of doing a
forward pass of the entire context right
imagine when you're predicting a con
like let's say you're predicting a
sequence of of text with 20,000 tokens
it becomes and at some point attention
is going to be the biggest bottleneck
because it's an n squed operation. So
because of KV caching um you don't need
to do a full forward pass of the entire
context and you just freeze the
activations you know and that's why even
though your AR model has thousand
thousands of steps of decoding every
every decoding step is very cheap but in
MDLM we have a problem. So imagine this
uh you when the generation starts you
start with a sequence of all mass tokens
you feed this into the model and let's
say your model predicts two words right
like this B and D so in the next doozing
step you would feed B and D into the
model uh these are the activations and
let's say you sample A and F right now
something interesting happens here when
you feed A and F into the model you
cannot just simply freeze the
activations corresponding to B and D
here, right? Um the reason is this uh
because of birectional attention uh
every time your input changes all the
activations change. Recall like in AR
model um there because of causal because
you know they had this uh causal
attention and that one token never was
not affected by the future tokens. they
could freeze the activations but in MDLM
because every token attends to
everything else you cannot freeze the
activations so that prevents uh that
prevents KV caching. Uh and the
implications are are are very simple. uh
even though MDLM can generate
let's say,000
words in just uh 500 or 400 steps uh
every step of generation is much
expensive than the auto reggressive
model and um yeah and that's why like
it's much slower than the AR model. So
how do we so uh in this we we we uh this
paper is is currently under review and
in this paper called esoteric language
models we propose a lot of things like
uh but the main the main selling point
of the paper was KV caching for MDLM. So
the question is how do you do how do you
design the transformer uh so that you
can support KV caching during inference
right so here's what we do again like
this is in this slide what I'm showing
you is the regular training um scheme
for the MDLM model uh you have a noisy
sequence DT with the transformer and you
train it with this cross entropy
weighted cross entropy loss uh we do
something funky here where we say that
uh we replace the birectional attention
of the transformer
uh what we do is this we apply some
shuffling like if let's say this is the
noisy sequence right you shuffle the
input and you uh have and you sort of
like um cluster all the clean tokens to
the left and all the mass tokens to the
right and then apply causal attention.
Now there are a lot of questions uh here
like it's not it's very unclear like why
do the shuffling uh and why do this
clustering to the left and right right
it is not at all clear here I will
describe it'll become obvious in the
next slide when I describe the sampling
how how to sample from this model but
the change that we make in this paper in
the MDLM training is very simple you uh
instead of applying birectional
attention across the entire context you
Shuffle the clean tokens, put them to
the left, shuffle the mass tokens, uh,
put them to the right, and apply causal
attention. That's it. So, naturally, you
can see that, you know, this particular
mass token only depends on the clean
context. This one only depends on the
previous mass token and the clean
context and not the future mass tokens,
right? Okay. By future mass tokens, I
meant the tokens appearing on the right
hand side uh in the shuffle sentence.
Okay. Now let's see how to do inference
in the SOLM model. Um this is uh uh yeah
this is how it works. So uh let's say
you're uh
um okay first of all like you you decide
which mass tokens you want to den
noiseise in ancestral sampling any
number of tok so so tokens appear at a
very randomized fashion and um yeah
tokens appear at a very randomized
fashion and n number of token like what
yeah also like the number of tokens that
are decoded depends on the number of
sampling steps that you fix a priority
right let's say uh your ancestral
sampler wants to decode tokens at
positions three and two. So what you do
is perform a forward pass of the mass
tokens uh and you and you add the
positional embeddings for three for the
positions three and two do a forward
pass and you decode both the mass tokens
right that C and B you can see how C and
B appears like let's say this is your
entire context instead of doing forward
pass of the entire context of length 8
you just you selectively do forward pass
of the tokens that you want to den
noiseise which is mass tokens at
position positions three and two, right?
You do a forward pass. Sample the
tokens. Okay? In the next denosising
step, let's say your ancestral sampler
wants to decode the tokens at positions
1 and 8. So, you would do a forward pass
of mass tokens uh alongside the
positional embeddings for 1 and 8. Do a
forward pass and and you uh denize them.
And again, here I'm showing you the
attention scheme of the transformer. It
it is causal. It is no longer
birectional. What this means is the
tokens B are not the activations for
tokens B and C are not affected by the
future tokens. Right? So naturally you
can see uh because of this uh because
the model you know during training was
trained with a causal attention and all
the clean tokens were to the left and
were randomly shuffled. The inference
supports this style of generation. So,
so this in this inference scheme
dictates dictated the attention uh
pattern that we saw before or the
training scheme that we saw before. So
we knew during inference that u I do not
want to perform a forward pass of the
entire context of the full you know like
imagine this like you're performing a
forward pass of only mass tokens like
mass tokens don't really carry any
information right it's very feudile and
um and um it's very comput inensive so
you save on a lot of flops by
selectively doing for pass of the tokens
that you want to den noiseise and also
you your inference is faster because of
KV caching. So yeah and this is how the
the inference proceeds. uh you keep on d
like you decide let's say you want to d
noiseise uh the mass token position five
uh you know you just perform for pass of
this mass token um and uh yeah all the
previous all the previously predicted
tokens like like like yeah like the
activations for the previously predicted
tokens are are uh frozen
and uh yeah then this is how you
incorporate KV caching in uh in uh in
this model Um okay now uh at the end of
the day uh what we care okay the reason
why we want to use um diffusion is
because you know we hope to have faster
sampling and also to have a choice where
we can trade off the sample quality for
sampling speed uh and in this curve uh
that's exactly that's exactly what I'm
showing so
is the method that we proposed uh uh uh
in esoteric language models paper and
BD3 lens is the block diffusion
algorithm. Um, so block diffusion is
this, right? So it says uh let's say our
goal is to generate text of length a
thousand. What we're going to do is
instead of doing diffusion over uh the
entire context, you divide the context
into small blocks um blocks of let's say
100 and you do diffusion only over those
blocks, right? for natural language it
just perfectly makes sense um uh where
you do diffusion over the first block of
100 tokens then uh and then you move on
to the next block and so on and so
forth. So at any so during doising you
do not you're not doing you're not doing
um
uh dnoising on the you're not doing a
forward pass of thousand tokens but you
do forward pass of 100 tokens which is
which is tractable thousand to like
thousand tokens is still fine but when
you start doing doising over 100,000
tokens uh context length it becomes uh
prohibitively expensive. So BD3M is the
block diffusion algorithm. Sooms is our
algorithm that we proposed in this paper
and this is MDLM right so so if you look
at the speed if you it's very it's very
clear that um it's very clear that MDLM
is very slow um so the curve in blue uh
now BD3 LM because it does this
blockwise generation it supports KV
caching because you den noiseise the
first 100 tokens you move on to the next
block of 100 tokens so there you're
allowed to the model is trained in a way
you know like uh where uh this block
does not depend on the future blocks. So
you can freeze the activation. So the
first block when you are den noising the
future blocks so on and so forth. So in
BD3LMs you see like it gets it's really
fast uh if you incre like for uh if you
increase the number of sampling steps
but as you decrease the number of
sampling steps that is as you start
predicting multiple words at the same
time there's a significant degradation
in quality which is here. So it almost
become becomes worse than MDLM here. Now
in green is our method and in uh as per
our method you can see uh uh like the
perto frontier here it is way faster
than MDLM produces better quality
samples than MDLM. It produces better
quality sample because of very simple
reason where uh one of the contributions
of our work is was also to interpolate
between AR and uh mass diffusion. Um so
so um I did not go into the details
because uh training that model uh was a
bit um is is is a bit non-trivial
effectively with SOM you can do left to
right generation as well when you do
that uh you get a you you get really
good quality samples but it's uh you
know uh almost as fast as AR but there's
slight gap in performance but uh when
you look at the tradeoff between speed
and quality it's much better than much
better than BD3LM or MDM Again, it's
only because this model supports KV
caching. So, it's highly efficient as
compared to any of the baselines in
BD3M. There's partial KV caching where
you can only do KV caching across
blocks. There is and while doing doising
within a block of 100 tokens, there's no
KV caching. But the moment you have
denoised one block, move move over to
the next block, you can freeze the
activations of the prior blocks. Um but
yeah so uh yeah and then if you look at
the sampling time as well like SLM is
way faster to to uh in terms of wall
time. Um so here we're we're on the
y-axis we have sampling time and uh we
report this number for a very small
model like at 110 million scale uh
with,024 tokens. Um okay so uh in
conclusion uh you know like diffusion uh
can be made
as performant as AR as we saw. Um,
bite densus diffusion is bu built on top
of the MDLM framework that we uh covered
in this talk. Nvidia is uh using MDLM uh
for um uh for generating molecules uh
which is pretty cool. And uh yeah, I
think uh that's uh uh that's all uh
that's all for today. If if you have any
questions, please please uh let me know.
>> Yeah, thank you for the great talk. Um,
so then