uh today we're happy to have Nathan
Lambert a research scientist at the
Allen Institute for AI uh who focuses on
rlh FF and the author of interconnects
doai he'll be presenting a really cool
talk on aligning open language models
today so thank you for joining us
Nathan yeah thanks for the intro okay
this is a long time coming this is a
brief intro on why I'm doing this I
think generally since chat GPT you'll
see a lot has obviously happened but I
don't think it it's been a blur for me
as much as anyone else so kind of taking
the time to retell like what has
happened in this kind of fine-tuning and
Alignment space since chaty PT happened
is something that I thought was a worthy
undertaking so this is not really a 101
lecture but it will probably give you a
lot of context on why people are
mentioning certain things and what still
matters and what does not so hopefully
this is fun um I can see the chat I
don't know exactly if questions are
going to come to me or if I will see it
the whole time I think clarifying
questions are good maybe not discussions
the whole time and I'll try to keep sure
that there's time for questions at the
end so um let's get into
it um generally we're going to talk
about language models so everyone wants
to talk about these days is I need to do
some of the older history so I can talk
about recent history the place I like to
start is actually with Claude Shannon
who kind of had this paper talking about
approximating um arranging characters to
create language models um that's
probably why anthropic called their
models Claud that's not that's pretty
well known and a lot has happened since
these very early um papers on predicting
sequences of text and this is largely
built on this loss function which is
called the autoaggressive loss function
so if you kind of have this training
example where you have something like is
saw a and you're trying to predict what
comes after this the whole idea is that
there's going to be one correct token
that is the correct label and their
training loss is going to increase the
probability of that token and decrease
the probability of everything else this
very simple loss function classifying
which token to to use and actually
predict has enabled wild things and this
kind of took another turn in 17 when
this Transformer paper was born
attention is all you need everyone here
has heard about this it's a great
exercise to actually dig into what the
attention mechanism is doing not the
focus of this talk we'll quickly kind of
keep going in 2018 there was three main
things these are slightly out of order
um Elmo was the earliest one which is
contextualized world word embeddings in
the same year we also had gpt1 and Bert
released which is kind of the beginning
of core ideas on which modern language
models and Transformers were trending
towards and just getting these better
models training on large pre large
internet scaled corpa Bert was a
classifier gpt1 was generating text and
we kind of continue along these Trends
through the years gpt2 was when we
started learning about scaling lws and
if you use orders of magnitude more
compute the actual test loss will
continue to decrease in a linear fashion
with respect to the log
compute these ideas now are common place
when we talk about language models um
gbt2 also pioneered a lot of discussions
on releasing language models so gbt2
when it was first announced they were
holding access back because of the risks
of language models and this started a
lot of the conversations around um what
you should or should not release with
language models they eventually actually
released gpt2 and you could download the
models on hugging face and use them but
this is where that kind of conversation
around release strategies emerged in
2020 is when language models really
started to be noticeably good so gpt3 C
is when a lot of people are like whoa
this can actually do really interesting
things if I kind of create a really
clever prompt figure out how to give it
my information correctly and gpt3 could
do a ton of things with kind of this few
shot or multi-shot learning which is
when you give it a few examples in the
prompt and then ask it to do another
rendition of it and with this power came
many harms and this is kind of a
discussion of what are the risks of
releasing language models what types of
groups will be hurt by this
very important problems that kind of
culminated in 2021 with the stochastics
parrots paper which is arguing about
whether or not language models can be
too big is in the title but there's it's
a really a critique on how we should be
thinking about language models what are
the limits of them are they actually
doing the things like are they actually
thinking or doing any of these human
things or are they just kind of
following patterns in the data and then
just the year after after that this is
kind of like the it's like the tragedy
of sastic parrots as no one talks about
it now is that chat 2bt came the year
later and totally reshaped the whole
narrative around language models one
more time and this is really where we
start today's talk is like how does this
idea of alignment emerge in chatu BT and
then what happens after this so the
question that I ask myself is like or I
tell a lot of people is can chbt exist
without rhf and what we saw in the
release day so if go back and read the
actual open AI blog about rhf they list
all these limitations but they say that
rhf was an important tool to launching
chat TBT and the limitations that they
list are really the things that we're
still researching and that we're talk
about in this talk it's a great blog
post to go back to but a good way to
frame it is that rhf seems to be
necessary but it's not sufficient you
can't do something like chat PT or
gemini or Claude with a technique that
without something like rhf but it's not
the thing like pre-training is still
most of the work
but the fact that RF is needed is really
important to kind of contextualize all
these improvements that we've seen in
the open in the last 14 months or
so some examples that I like to site on
rhf being relied upon you can list many
more models here than I have um this
kind of this figure from anthropics
constitutional AI paper is the single
one that I go back to all the time
showing how just kind of using rhf can
get these more desirable behaviors from
their model in really dramatic ways so
these kind of Elo measurements aren't um
kind of calibrated so we don't know how
to compare llama 3 on this chart
compared to anthropics models but the
level of investment that anthropic has
had in these kind of techniques and
showing this kind of wide ranging
improvements of their models with rhf is
a kind of flag that we can follow to try
to learn how to do alignment with this
much precision and with this much kind
of impact as places like anthropic or
opening eye will have one such example
is just a simple quote from the
llama 2 paper which is kind of like the
colloquial way of reading this quote
which I will read is that whoa rhf
worked really easily and what the quote
is is meanwhile reinforcement learning
known from it for its instability seemed
a somewhat shadowy field for those in
the NLP research Community however
reinforcement learning proved highly
effective particularly given its cost
and time Effectiveness so this is one of
the biggest endorsements of rhf and it's
always fun for me because I came from
the RL side and then I've been learning
NLP but for NLP researchers to say these
things like yes reinforcement learning
is known for instability and but given
that is cost effective and time
effective for an RL person that's
shocking it's like RL has never been
particularly cost and time effective but
for in these language model domain where
we're fine-tuning with it rather than
learning from scratch to have people in
NLP that are saying this is just really
striking for how much impact it can have
and the timeline alignment and open
alignment is really like when do we see
these benefits like these benefits
didn't show up in models that people
were playing with for quite a bit of
time so this is kind of a little Atlas
I've thrown together I also made a
hugging face collection where I tried to
add all the models that I talk about to
it so you can actually click on the
models or try to use them if you're so
inclined of actually running the models
yourself it's just kind of another way
of documenting um the artifacts I talked
about and the artifacts that for me this
is a good review on like what What
mattered What mattered in this really
noisy journey in the last year of course
some disclaimers I'm not covering every
model since chat GPT this this little
plot of model icons could probably look
more like an exponential than this kind
of capped bar um and there's so much
history of NLP that people are building
on in the alignment space that is
totally swept under the rug here a lot
of academic and infrastructure
contributions that I'm not talking about
but are really important to kind of this
proliferation of fine-tuning
models so just kind of describing what
this image that I have here is um is
kind of summarize um some of these are
base models I'm not going to focus on
base models as much as fine-tuned models
the base models are extremely important
like none of this happens without llama
none of this happens without llama 2 the
base models are the Bedrock of this
ecosystem and then the alignment models
are what people the aligned models are a
lot of times what people can play with
and what you could try out what you
could do yourself on much less computing
infrastructure and all these things so
I'm going to talk more about the aligned
models but everything matters it's one
big
ecosystem um another thing that's not
fun but I'm going to do for the sake of
kind of flag posting no one really likes
listening to definitions um here are
some things that you'll hear thrown
around this isn't even all when talking
about quote unquote alignment I have
like here like alignment I've defined as
a general notion of training a model to
mirror a user's desires really with any
loss function it's not restricted um
there's other ter so like there's a
difference between instruction fine
tuning and supervised fine tuning
instruction fine tuning is about trying
to get a model that will respond to
queries formatted instructions while
supervised fine tuning is more about
learning a specific tasks capabilities
these get interchanged all the time like
that's okay it's good to know that
they're different and then two kind of
more ones I need to touch on and we
could go on even longer is reinforcement
learning from Human feedback there's
this multi-stage process it's it's a
specific tool for aligning ml models to
human data um it's kind of a class of
tools so it has some sort of you learn a
preference model and then you extract
information from it so there are so many
different ways to do it it's really an
approach and then there's a term that
I'm kind of trying to grow which is
preference fine tuning which could
Encompass rhf methods like Po but
there's the question of how do we
differentiate something like direct
direct preference optimization which
doesn't use an RL Optimizer from all of
rhf and I'll kind of come back to this
but it's good to have some common rounds
to build on because I might be going
through some of these things pretty
quickly this is a chapter that I cover
in one slide because it's really tapping
into a lot of different personal stories
it's hard to retell how crazy things
were when chat GPT dropped people were
not really losing their mind but there
was a lot of uncertainty on what the
future held
especially that it was clear that
language models were important but it is
not clear there's a lot of articles on
like titled we're going to reproduce
open chat GPT which you can't really
have a mo open model that does what a
closed product does there's a difference
between model weights and this product
that chat GPT represents but there is so
much excitement that everyone is saying
they're going to do these things and
trying to figure out the right
coalitions for actually doing so and
it's it's interesting this this delay is
kind of this land grab where people are
learning the basic things like what is
red teaming how like what is the
difference between a dialogue agent and
a predictive language model like what
tools should we use and everything kind
of follows from here with what people
are building but like personally I just
remember multiple meetings where like
people are like yeah you should do it
you should go try to build open chat GPT
and when you look back that goal is just
so wild that so many people are just
going like we need to we need to build
this thing in the open source and it's
just like it doesn't even make sense
because you can't open source a whole
system that
way but there are some things that make
a bit this makes a lot more sense which
is when things start to get grounded in
actual models so the first llama Suite
was released and I think in February I
have the date in some notes somewhere um
and then these instruction tuned models
started to show up on this first llama
model the first one to really crack the
narrative was this alpaca model and it
did a bunch of things that still are
used today so this was trained on 52,000
self- instruct style data distilled from
text venci 3 there's a lot in the
sentence I'll say what self- instru
struct means but this wasn't even data
generated from chat gbt it was generated
from one of open ai's API models so if
we talk about in this is all on how to
apply instruction fine tuning and this
is thing I mentioned on the definition
slide but really it's about making a
model that will respond to specific
styles of inputs what often happens at a
technical level here is that the model
is learning to integrate something
called like a chat template the ability
to include system prompts so you want to
tell you want the model to know it is an
agent you want the model to know what
day it
is excuse me you can do this in the
system prompt which is something the
user doesn't see but it steers the
behavior of the model and instruction
tuning is really where we make the model
capable of having these behaviors but
the question is like what data are we
training this behavior on so the most
common example is kind of um you
continue training with this Auto
regressive loss function on question
answer pairs so it's like what is a
Transformer and then you'll the language
model will predict an answer it could be
from stack Overflow it could be
something else and this example is human
data but what made alpaca in a lot of
these um early models and even today
really popular and accessible is by
using data to answer questions that is
generated by an
AI so this is where the kind of idea of
self- instruct data comes in self-
instruct was a paper from Al Ali and
udub in 2022 before chat GPT where
essentially the idea is how do we expand
on the distribution and instruction data
that we have this training data for
fine-tuning a language model without
getting more humans in the loop so um
what you really have to do is you start
with some high quality often human
prompts and then what we now see as more
common practice today but was very new
then is asking a stronger language model
create a list of prompts that are
similar to this but still diverse and
then once you have a list of prompts you
can use trap GPT or another model to
actually generate completions because
then what you have is a really big list
of question answer pairs but you don't
need to go through the bottleneck of
getting humans to sit down and write all
of them so what alpaca was really why
alpaca worked is because of kind of
realizing this and taking in this better
model from open AI so you can see this
figure here on the right is from the
alpaca paper or blog post one of the two
they took this model from open Ai and
they asked it to generate more tasks so
they had 175 to start and then they
ended up with over 50,000 kind of tasks
and they also generated completions from
this open AI model and um then what they
did is they took these meta weights that
had just come out and they instruction
fine tune them and then you end up with
alpaca this is kind of a pattern this is
a pattern that we've seen many times
with alpaca which is essentially you
take you you generate some data with
from a stronger language model and you
find tune on it it sounds so obvious
today but this was the first Model to
actually release
this I can now see questions coming in
I'll I'll answer the ones that are
clarifying and stuff like this so thanks
for asking them and we can come back to
more at the
end once alpaca happened it felt like
there was a new model every week the
second model was vicuna
and really what they changed was they
added new sources of prompts to the
distribution so you can see that I say
share GPT they also introduced the idea
of llm as a judge which is now obvious
from a lot of their later evaluation
work but let's talk about why Shar GPT
was so
interesting so Shar GPT was one of the
only data sets that got open language
model Builders so people like me prompts
that were similar to what people um were
asking chat gbt so what was happening
was you would install this browser
plug-in and it would let you share your
prompts from chat gbt on Twitter or
whatever so it was making it easier to
share the prompts before in your
conversations before open AI made a tool
to do this and it now there's this legal
gray gray area
over the data set because most of these
data sets are unlicensed and they were
kind of created without consent or they
were released without consent so there's
a legal question on whether or not
people should be training on this data
but the fact of the matter is that Shar
gbt was really important to this kind of
acceleration and progress on fine-tuning
models because the diversity of data is
just so much stronger than what people
were going to get from like this alpaca
self- instruct idea and it set the bar
much higher it's only today and in the
last like few months or six months for
some of them that were getting data sets
that could replace these so you see I
mentioned um lmis chat one 1M which is
just a million conversations from
chatbot Arena which took a lot of work
to clean out personal information and
then a project from the Allen Institute
of AI which is wild chat which is really
similar to share gbt but the users were
given consent at the start that their
data was going to be collected and
released in exchange for using a
language model for free so there's a lot
of happen stance in the story where
something like this which is legally
gray and the data is still on hugging
face but it's looks kind of odd um where
these little things helped enable the
ecosystem even though looking back it's
like oh we don't know if that should
have
happened following vuna is one called
koala from also from Berkeley and like
it's with you look at the time frames
it's pretty obvious that a lot of these
were developed concurrently and then the
release dates just happened to be
slightly different koala is mostly known
for having kind of a different diverse
set of data sets they used some from
alaka they used some from shared jpt
again they also used anthropic data that
has been released and they had some
human evaluation from grad students so
this just added more data diversity and
the evaluations weren't necessarily
better but it was an important model
that a lot of people noticed just from
these kind of bringing back up these new
data sets that had been in the
literature from years prior something
they might ask looking at these slides
is that it's like why weight differences
I have all these slides like weight diff
to llama 7B weight diff um essentially
when llama was released it was released
as research only and just you had to and
it was distributed to researchers upon
request and the license prohibited
people from updating llama one to
hugging phas so it's kind of this
annoying phase where in order to use a
model on hugging face you had to clone
it and then you had to run a script to
convert it with this kind of Delta into
the new model in order to in order to
actually use it so this is kind of a
really frustrating phase from a user
perspective because it just made
experimentation have one one more
barrier to entry and thankfully it was
changed with llama 2 but it was really
something that many people dealt with at
the time and we now today see different
license restrictions on how llama is
used I mean the Llama 3 released today
essentially if you if if I find tuna
model for my research and I release it
at ai2 llama 3 needs to be in the name
so if I wanted to release a new like
Tulu model it would have to be llama 3
Tulu 4 DPO it's like the namings are
going to be crazy but there's always
been restrictions on using llama weights
or how you how you share
them and the final model that I kind of
group into this batch of this real first
swing was Dolly so dolly was fine-tuned
from a different base model it was
fine-tuned from the pit models from
alther which were a suite of early
scaling experiments from alther AI which
is still used extensively but they added
some human written data to the loop
which is just really important because
almost all of the projects that I'll
mention today talk about synthetic data
or data derived from open AI there's
only a few of them that actually added
new human data to The Loop and this is
what everyone remembered dolly for and a
lot of its performance limitations are
probably from the base model Pia which
is trained in a Time where this type of
inference that people expect wasn't as
popular and it was kind of before this
the scaling laws were thought of it
differently you can kind of see through
these where we're going to start with
different model sizes and different Mt
bench scores I'll talk about what Mt
bench is in a few slides it's an
evaluation tool and this is really just
to ground you on what the kind how the
scores would change over time so I have
these throughout the talk as we kind of
go through different models just just to
show um kind of how this how the scores
continue to progress over time from one
small change to another as the community
gets better at these
things while I was talking about human
data so remember dolly is all about
human
data the probably the still the single
busiest um human coordination project
for data generation was open Assistant I
think it's easy now if you get into fine
tuning to see the open system data set
and not realize
how important it was to the process of
alignment in this whole summer and it is
still used today so essentially there's
this quote on the top but they the
leaders ran a community project to
generate human written prompts and these
kind of like human written responses in
many different languages with rating
them so you could use it as preferences
with the slide has a bug where it's like
like has over 10,000 anod trees and over
thousand U volunteers this is still used
extensively today will come up again in
the talk they also released models so
the first mod one of the the first model
used on hugging chat which I don't
remember the launch date of was an open
Assistant model so open Assistant was
probably the first majorly successful
project of the era and the data set is
still used
today where I will end this talk is
saying that we need more things like
this it's like really one of the most
important things is we need more human
data in the
open this is a quick aside it's kind of
out of the flow of the talk but on April
28th of 2023 typo on the slide of April
28th of 2023 stable vuno was released
from Carper AI which looks now like the
style of training models except for the
data set which was um is now popular
they they got po to work they had some
human evaluations that were solid it was
a good chat model it wasn't um out of
distribution but Carper AI was really
ahead at the time and then it seems like
priorities kind of shifted from
stability but it's important to know the
extent by which there were still some
players who knew how to do rhf really on
early on even though they were pretty
rare this is the last this is the last
slide of this kind of first chapter on
instruction tuning was the idea of qor
which was kind of unlocked a whole new
um bunch of players into actually being
able to find two models so for the quick
60c
overview um Laura stands for low rank
adaptation which is the idea of you can
freeze some model weight you freeze most
of the model weights and you add new
weights to specific layers that you can
then fine-tune as if you were
fine-tuning the whole model you use the
same approach of instruction data with
question answering but it takes much
less r memory Q Laura was a technique
that built upon this by adding very
specific quantization and GPU tricks to
make it so that memory requirements to
fine-tune models was even lower um tin
demmer's and team also released this
guano model with it which was another
big step up in performance of these
models I have a few more slides on it on
the method so you can kind of see on the
right this difference full fine tuning
and Laura they look similar where Laura
you have fewer parameters is kind of
what the smaller shapes mean in Cura um
they quantize the base model that you're
propagating gradients through to save
most of the
memory so this is an approximation of if
you're fine-tuning different model sizes
on the top so 7 billion 13 billion 30
billion with full fine tuning different
amount of bits but full fine tuning
versus Laura versus Cura and you can
kind of see um for reference one a100
GPU has about 80 gigabytes of memory and
these are really hard gpus to get plenty
of consumer gpus will only have like 24
to 32 gigabytes of memory so you need to
use these Cur techniques to actually get
the ability to fine-tune models at the
seven or 13 billion parameter
size um and like guano did this and they
released 33 billion and 65 billion
parameter llama fine tunes which were
clear steps up in the kind of state of
the art at the time
and they also figured out ways to filter
this open Assistant data set that I
mentioned and this kind of filtered
version of open assistant is what is
still most popular
today I'm going to kind of pause and
skim through the questions and see if
there's anything on that section and if
not I'll save the relevant ones for
later okay I'm going to keep going
they're they're great questions and I
appreciate them um but they're mostly
not specific enough where it's worth the
digression this chapter 2 phase is
really like where it seemed like things
were a little bit slower on the ground
but when we look back at a lot of things
that came out of this time like DPO Pap
the DPO paper was in this era everyone
read it but we didn't know what to do
with it yet and the new evaluations are
still really
used transitioning in setting the seam
for being not sure of things work um a
lot of people are continuing to try to
build on these Laura methods and Cura
method me I remember a lot of excitement
at hugging face where we were setting up
our rhf pipeline where we could do rhf
on 7 billion parameter models and we
could maybe do it on a consumer GPU it
was really cool to see the loss going
down it's great to bring more people
into the space but weeks and weeks would
go by and they like why has no one
picked up what we released in the blog
post and trained a really good model
with it and the kind of consensus now is
that
um these Lura methods just have some
sort of weird limitation in how you use
them or how the gradients flow that make
it much much harder to get a really good
model out if you only have a certain
number of gpus such that Laura is your
only option definitely use it but for
people that have more gpus figuring out
how to scale is normally a better
solution than just using something like
Laura that fits and is easier for in the
short
term another defining moment of this
arrow is the Llama 2 back Clash um I'm
guessing some people remember this which
is like the the famous line was people
asked llama if how to kill a python
process and it would say no and this
really started a whole bunch of new
discussions around what kind of
alignment means or what model should or
should not do here's an example from a
paper for a safety evaluation test set
called XS test and it's just like should
chat models be saved or should they
follow the instructions that I want and
this is a fundamental question it'll
differ by organization it'll differ by
individual and this is the point where
this became very serious and something
that people actually had to reckon with
because there were models that were
actively disagree people were really
disagreeing with this specific take I
don't have any clear solution to it but
one of the things that led to is this
idea of uncensored models um it's a
really popular category on
uh kind of hugging face right now where
the idea is you remove filtering so if
we're using synthetic data and I ask a
language model a question like if I
asked chat gbt how to make a bomb it's
going to say I'm sorry I'm as a language
model I shouldn't make this and the idea
of uncensored models is to remove those
points from our kind of remove those
points from our fine-tuning data set I
think there's a lot of confusion over
the name because language models were
never at this stage really aren't
censored to with but it's really that
the data set and the method for creating
these data sets needed more filtering or
they needed some way of becoming
unbiased so like there's a lot of people
now that only build models to try to
make them unbiased against any sort of
refusal a refusal is when you ask a
language bottle something and it says no
and this goes on today and this came out
of this llama 2
thing but otherwise this is a transition
period where there's a lot of good
solid models being trained but either
they didn't have a lot of documentation
they didn't have the right release team
to Splash as big as they should have the
methods were complicated to implement or
something like this so like I could run
through these and I remember all these
models coming out but none of them were
really things that are household names
like alpaca is today like wizard the
team from behind wizard L LM where they
created this method called inval
instruct which is a synthetic data
method like all these things were
clearly working for them based on the
models they were generating but for
whatever reason the narrative wasn't
actually changed um there's some new
data sets from Ultra like ultr LM is
from open BMB in China that is releasing
new data sets more people training on
share GPT the model called xwin LM was
the first one to be like a similar
Ballpark and it's like also trained with
rhf so not just that Carper model but
for whatever reason it's like
these didn't really Splash and that's
kind of was this kind of Summer after
llama 2 where fine tuning was chugging
chugging along but the narrative wasn't
changing all of that much at least from
my perspective but hope that's why I'm
here but what was happening in the
background while the models weren't
seeming that different is that new
evaluation tools were coming out that
ended up kind of being the standard of
today so you can see the dates here so
May May 3rd bot Arena June 8th alpaca
ofal June 22nd Mt bench sometime in
early July the open llm leaderboard all
of these things were created about the
same time where there's a desperate need
to get some sort of signal on what our
fine-tuned models are doing in the open
like we don't have the capability of
paying humans to compare our responses
like they do at anthropic where they're
always trying new models on humans
that's way too expensive we need
something that you could sit down as an
engineer and get feedback in 10 to 15
minutes
so kind of run through these in order
and some a lot of these are obvious but
it's important to take this from the
perspective of what can I use when I'm
trying to align models and like what is
an immediate feedback versus what is
kind of this long-term signal so chapot
arena is obviously fantastic like
everyone looks at this today as
something that is defining um it's like
defining corporate strategy is defining
the biggest language model players like
if Cloud 3 is better than GPT 4 but if
I'm an engineer a many small providers
aren't going to get their models in and
B it takes especially previously it used
to take weeks to get your models rating
but now it takes days like I need to
know what my models of are before I
decide to actually release it so that's
the biggest thing where like I know I
need something Beyond chatbot Arena just
for my engineering
development and this is where like
alpaca of Val and Mt bench really Thrive
so alpaca of Val got the slide forting
got changed but um I'll just kind of
keep rolling through this um alpaca ofal
is the idea of you have a list of
prompts that you compare to some a
strong other base model like um open
ai's D vinci3 or gp4 and then you ask a
language model which is better and the
data set here is compiled from all these
popular data sets that um I have been
talking about so far so data sets from
open Assistant vuna koala anthropic like
all these data sets that people have
been using they took the test sets from
those and that's what Al pack Val
mirrors it's kind of a known thing it
has some limitations because there's
only so many prompts and it's like
asking a language model to provide a
rating is going to have some ceiling
where we don't know how to compare two
really good models so has more samples
than Mt bench so there's more
um so there's just kind of Le smaller
error bars and it's easier to use
because it's a single turn generation
but we've heard about the length bias
for a really long time and it's not
clear how to interpret these top results
so if you this is the older screenshot
of leaderboard but what is beating a
model 95% of the time mean to another
language model that's the questions that
we can't really answer in the short
term a paco of al2 came out which takes
steps to this where it rate compares the
GPT 4 rather than D Vinci 3 D vinci3 was
an instruct gbt variant but at the end
of the day if the like um gbt 4 is
answering these questions in the alpaca
style really well so what does beating
gp4 exactly mean I we need to get more
specific in our valuations because I
don't really know if I care too much
about a 20 or 30% score and alpaca about
2 because I don't know what it means and
this is one this is the opaqueness of
all of our evaluations we'll see this
time and time again where we don't know
what an increase in score means so it's
like the next step after being able to
do it
easily this update was pretty
recent um Mt bench is is pretty similar
where instead of comparing to one model
you ask a language model to provide a
score to a list of prompts so if I have
a model I'm training a gener the
completion to 80 diverse prompts and
then I asked gp4 hey from 0 to 10 how
good were each of those uh completions
and this is good but it runs into the
same problem of like what if our model
is getting really good if our model is
getting really good it's it's just like
it becomes saturated like gp4 only gets
to about nine and there's only about 80
prompts in the evaluation set and all
these things it's just and one of the
nuance points is that there's actually a
variance so even if you set the
temperature to zero gp4 versions change
your own Generations from your model
you're trying to change train can change
and this makes it better where it's like
okay I can tell if a model was really
bad if Mt bench and Alaco Val have
really low scores but it's hard to like
it's it's still we have these this goal
for a precise evaluation so like in
pre-training we have Mt bench and Alpac
and H swag and all the or sorry in
pre-training we have like mlu and hellis
swag and all these things that people
can look at and average over 10 tasks
and if you get like a 2% Improvement on
average you're doing great but we don't
have this clear indicator in alignment
evaluation the open llm leaderboard was
the same where
it's this came out of the team I was
working on at hugging base where we were
just trying to evaluate more models to
get more signal which was that we needed
to know what our competitors are doing
and get some ballpark estimate and what
this grew into is this whole kind of
like ecosystem supporting Discovery tool
just because like getting any signal is
so useful so this is where we were
starting with evaluation which was just
like no signal and why this leaderboard
was so successful is because it gave
everyone access to a little bit more
signal on the models that their
evaluation but it didn't really solve
any of the fundamental problems and it
didn't show us that like doing RL jeon
models would actually make the scores go
up it's starting to get better today but
that's like a year on from the launch of
this
leaderboard so like these problems are
still this is talking about a section
from July of 2023 and it seems like the
things that if I were to go into like go
into work and talk to people what we're
going to do with our new models like
these are the same questions that we're
still asking which is why it's there's
it the these evaluation schools are
still so useful and it's why people
still talk about opaco Val but it shows
how much of an opportunity there still
is so this kind of a summary of what I
was talking about it's like how easy is
it to use these evaluations like chapot
arena is everything like Andre Cory
tweets about it and it's great and you
can go there and you can use models but
like I I don't know how to make sense of
that as if I'm trying to sit down every
day and write code and the alpaca andal
and Mt bench mostly solve this by being
cheap and pretty accessible but I really
really think there's a huge opportunity
here to come out with more so the
colleague at ai2 launched wild bench
which is a good tool that kind of fits
in it's like a chatbot Arena alpaca of
Al hybrid and you can use it a little
bit faster it's like how are we going to
continue to push this along is a great
question and I would love to hear what
people
think we'll take another pause I think
we're getting good questions in the chat
around um rhf and other things um to
what extent are do aligned models
actually reason about whether user
attent is malicious rather than perform
talk detection to detect to avoid unsafe
topics this is a question that I wanted
to read because it kind of gets at this
model versus system topic so when trbt
was released on day one it has an output
filter that does moderation the language
model that is instruction tuned or rhf
tuned generates a bunch of text and then
a separate model says yes or no and
that's like the where it actually does
detection and with the release of llama
3 there's another model that's called
like llama guard and this is a
classifier which will take this text do
the moderation and say which type of
unsaved topic it is the actual model
that is generating does no reasoning
over um kind of what is actually an
unsaved
topic so I'll come back to other ones
I'm going to do some discussions about
um rhf right now so this will kind of
give grounds for where we can continue
some of these discussions on um there's
orpo or reinforce I don't cover all of
them in the lecture but I kind of lead
on to why we would talk about
them so this this chapter is when I
started to get validation as an RL
researcher that being otic and going to
work in language models was actually a
good idea for a lot of this there was a
lot of uncertainty over if the people if
people in this kind of open ecosystem
were even going to be able to use rlf at
all or if being a quote unquote rhf
researcher for me meant I was going to
do instruction fine-tuning and talk
about aows and never think about RL
again it turned out to be wrong
um I'm going to review some RL
fundamentals just to kind of make sure
we're talking the same language as we
talk about this and this will lead into
direct preference optimization so
there's a reason why I'm doing math I no
we don't this is not a normal lecture
but here is the equation where you'll
see this in rhf papers this is what
we're optimizing when we're optimizing
rhf it it looks kind of nebulous here
I'll break it down so on the left side
we're really maximizing with respect to
some policy Pi um this reward that is
parameterized by a network fi and we're
have a penalty that is this kind of KL
term which is the distance from our
policy to some reference we want to
increase reward and but we want to
constrain the model so that it doesn't
the this kind of optimization doesn't go
too
far and the primary questions when doing
this is how do we Implement a good
reward function and how do we optimize
the reward these are a really RL Centric
way of doing it which is like if you
give me a reward function I can optimize
and the classic RL idea was I'm in an
environment the environment has the
reward function built in in rhf we're
designing our own reward function so
this adds a lot of weirdness to the
actual optimization that we're
doing and what we do is to get this
reward function is we learn what is
called a preference or reward model and
the most popular way to do this is to
take a take a language model that's kind
of predicting this separation of two
preferences this is called a Bradley
Terry model which goes back to some
economics but the key idea is that the
reward will be proportional to the
probability that the text they have
would be chosen over any other arbitrary
text quickly sounds really Theory like
but it outputs a scaler which is now a
reward function and is based on this par
wise
data so the idea is with this equation
what if we just use gradient Ascent on
this equation and instead of trying to
learn a preference model and learn this
R what if we just use gradient Ascent
directly this is really what direct
preference optimization is doing there's
a bunch of math in here to get what this
R is but this was released back in May
so we've already moved on months ahead
this chapter starts in kind of late
September October back in May when we're
still talking about open Assistant this
DPO paper came out it's a fantastic
paper if you hadn't read it it's a great
way to learn about language model map it
it's worth reading but the core idea is
like why are we spending all this time
um learning a reward model when we can
just use gradient
and solve for the loss
function some key ideas to think about
with DPO is that DPO is extremely simple
to implement on the right here side is
the example code from the DPO paper
where it's like as long as you have
access to the log probs from a model
which is a very core thing for training
language models um you can compute the
DPO loss um because of this because the
loss function is at a nice abstraction
it scales nicely with existing libraries
and
it what it's actually doing is training
an implicit reward function so the
reward is a function of the log probs I
don't have the equation here because it
quickly becomes a rabbit hole um but
whatever the whole DPO versus poo debate
means or um o RPO I don't remember what
the paper me title is um we're going to
see a lot of these things because it's
simple and it's scales well that doesn't
necessarily mean the fundamental limits
are higher but it sometimes it doesn't
matter if the Li are higher if it's
easier to make progress on something
because it's EAS it feels better when
progress is being made so that's really
a core thing is we'll keep seeing these
models and we are and there's this whole
debate that has gone on kind of crushing
a whole bunch of these questions by um
redirecting them in a very political
manner but it's like should we use
reinforce what about po what about like
other things um there're very different
styles of optimization so in one half
we're used RL update rules which is
ultimately about learning a value
function and then learning to update
taking gradient steps with respect to
that value function in DPO we're taking
gradient steps directly from the
probabilities of the language model
they're very different optimization
regimes and there's this great meme
where like all the like there was a
month where the whole NLP Twitter was
just arguing about this but both of them
are continuing to progress and that is
good like it will not just be one or the
other um so what really made this debate
kick into gear was this release of the
Zephyr beta model from hugging face it's
after I left hugging face but the team I
was on and it was the first Model to
make a splash with DPO and it was a big
step up in how models were perceived
this model was added to like the U
search engine people were using all
sorts of crazy things so it just felt
really good to use it was building on
this better base model mistol had come
out a new data set this Ultra feedback
data set that I mentioned is still one
of the core data sets used today when
we're kind of practicing alignment this
was back in September October that this
model came back one of the core things
to getting DPO to work was using really
low learning rates like 5e minus 7
there's memes about 3E minus 4 being the
only learning rate you need to do deep
learning and changing it being kind of a
joke DPO is the case where that is not
even remotely true and then you can see
the Mt bench scores again continuing to
rise so this is like a validation proof
that DPO works that came four months
after the paper was released that delay
is something that nobody expected we
were kind of losing Hope on DPO at many
times and now look at where it is and
then when I joined ai2 they were already
working on this project and I had just
helped kind of get it across the line
it's like the classic advisor thing
where sometimes it's just easier is the
first model to scale DPO to 70 billion
parameters the last question was oh yeah
DPO works on small models when I ever
use it on a big model answer is yes and
it's like built on the same recipe as
Zephyr with a little bit different
instruction tuning data sets but scores
continued to climb this was this model
was so close to beating GPT 3.5 on
chatbot Arena it was like a couple ELO
points below so we didn't get the title
of being the first on to do that but
open models were starting to get that
kind of Chatty behavior that for so long
had eluded them because we had figured
out scale because we hadn't figured out
these data sets so it was great progress
very important and kind of major
transition in my career where now it's
like okay rhf
methods really can work and these
weren't just I was not the only one
touching things that did this a couple
other projects that are really important
so Nvidia had steer steerm where steerm
was collecting um feedback data where
there was attributes on it like how
helpful the message was how concise the
message was and they did of fine tuning
and released Good Very solid models and
they also showed that PO is better than
DPO which is interesting and then
Berkeley came out with this um Starling
LM Alpha where they had a new preference
data set nectar which is still looked at
today and then they also used this kind
of Po method after training a reward
model and both of these came out about
the same time and they're like huh DPO
isn't doing as well for us the models
are really good recently the second
starling model came out its reward model
is very strong in my testing it's a 7B
model that's almost reaching chat GPT
levels in chatbot Arena it's crazy how
fast these models are going but we still
get a lot of models that are both with
po or with DP it's really not one of the
other at this
point okay I think this is a reasonable
time for me to take a couple of these
questions might come back to them in
more slides
but someone asked is there a particular
alignment method that I use um there
this is teasing a paper but there was a
recent paper that was came out where I
don't remember the group I can I can
find it later but they did what they
called a systematic study of Po and DPO
and they showed that PO is better I will
say that in the experiments that I'm
seeing at allna AI I'm also seeing po to
be stronger and we hope to release this
stuff soon um it's not a um one crushes
the other it's that we're seeing that
there's for some reason PO is just
getting a bit more performance um and
then The Logical question is um why not
reinforce which is another one of these
questions I would love to try it it's
just like we have the code that we have
and we don't want to touch things that
are working well and there's just so few
people that are kind of working in the
space which I'm like let's get more
people working on these things because
there's so few people that can answer
all these questions so there's another
question that says like some say
reinforce can work as well as if not
better than po it probably can it comes
down to your infrastructure carefully
fine-tuning it what people are excited
about and a lot of luck so we'll see
these continue to play out um throughout
the year but it's it's
complicated I'll come back to the Lama 3
question I have I have one slide for
that in a little bit but really this
modern ecosystem
is how investment in releasing open
models that people can use is continuing
to grow into 2024 I think there's always
been this tenuous period of like there's
only a few people releasing these
aligned models there's these important
people in the ecosystem that are just
doing this because they want to and it's
for fun they might have a day job and
it's like how long can this go on like
what are the limitations on this but in
in 202 before we've really seen more
companies kind of come into the space
and someone drew meta llama 3 on the
screen was like talking to co-workers
and like you're yeah you're going to
need to keep adding models you're never
going to be able to give this lecture
yeah it's a losing battle I know um but
the modern the there's just way more
types of models so I get away with not
having llama 3 on this specific slide
because I'm talking about diversity of
players and models not just the fact
that there are more great models so
there's interesting models like this one
gen struck from new research in the last
few months where it's like a
specifically fine-tuned model for
rephrasing any text into instructions so
if you have a book and you want a model
to be able to answer questions about
this why don't we just throw it at this
rephrasing question this rephrasing
model and the teams that I work on at
ai2 we're trying to release instruction
models where every single thing that
we've done to train it is documented and
reproducible from data to what compute
it was there're just these models are
getting new features in these little
ways other than just being the quote
unquote best open model um such as like
these corporate entities that are going
for really standing out in the open so
there's data bricks dbrx model um coh's
command R plus model I think people were
mostly blindsided by coher releasing
model weights but it was the first open
model to pass gbd4 on chatbot Arena and
that has been a long time coming I think
beating gp4 on human evaluation is not
easy and yes the open is still like a
year behind but that's fine as long as
we have a functioning ecosystem it'll
continue to grow then there's other
things like interesting research models
like row came out does data waiting um
we're finally starting to get
multilingual models with a which is also
from cohere um people are getting more
mixture of expert models to train on
which are just a bit more of an
efficient pre-training equation State
space models are really taking off they
had this moment in December with Mamba
and now it's kind of continuing in 20124
so there's just a lot going on and this
makes me feel good because it's like
okay I just have to keep doing what I'm
doing and encouraging people to
participate and we're going to keep
being able to do this kind of fun thing
of figuring out how to make models and
share them with
people this is my slide for llama 3 um
the reason why I didn't make a lot of
slides about this all day is that llama
3's release is more about scaling and
the kind of ecosystem as a whole than it
is about alignment the Llama 2 paper was
extremely detailed about alignment and
we're going to get a llama 3 paper soon
if you can believe multiple sources of
meta which I choose to and when the
Llama 3 paper comes out is when we will
learn all the interesting alignment
things that they have done that being
said they are very unlikely to release
the human preference data that they did
um yet to succeed in getting them to
release a reward model for llama 2 or
llama 3 from alignment so we have more
work to do on getting meta to support
this kind of open alignment ecosystem to
the same extent that they are supporting
the pre-training ecosystem and this kind
of scaling story that I'm saying very
much connects to the previous slide
where scaling and solving this is very
much determined by the market markets
and like Capital incentives but so long
as scaling is continuing to happen in
the open ecosystem it just means that
more players are going to stick around
and in some ways it kind of feeds back
into itself where if this llama 3 is
rumored to have or they're training a
400 billion parameter model which we're
not 100% sure that the weights will be
released but it seems like that's Mark
Zuckerberg's intent and having that
which is about gbt for Quality really
changes what you can do to get language
models running in your products so llama
3 and how many people are playing in the
open space right now goes to show that
we have more of the same coming which is
interesting models coming on a weekly
basis and most people are just kind of
accommodated it to it now like people
don't freak out when there's a new well
they like mistral's model because
there's a magnet link and it's funny but
like we're used to it and I still expect
that to be the case for the next year or
two with this pace just kind of being
how it is and it's really fun to follow
and I I just think that it's like not a
time to be worried about scooping being
scooped but to just kind of keep
figuring out where you can contribute
whether it's on evaluation or some of
these other alignment methods that
people have talked
about so I have a quick thing on kind of
current directions which we I'll come
back to some of these data things that I
mentioned multiple times and then we can
get to
questions um and mo the thing that
people want to know a lot is are open
models going to catch up to closed
models my answer is probably not ever
completely there will be some friction
in the system by a time delay by which
open models are closed and open model
weights are not inherently unsafe the
open versus Clos debate has mostly
converged around this but given the
territory that we're going with in AI
where we're uncovering new capabilities
we've never seen I think it's okay that
if there's a few months wait before you
have open weight so you can run on your
laptop as we're discovering what AI can
do if you look at someone if you look at
Maxim's plot with trend lines showing
them it shows that open models are
getting closer but we're not really sure
if open models will stay closer on
chatbot arena in the long term there
will always be an open and close
category because there is demand to have
models that are tuned to what you want
them to do so this kind of Lins into my
current directions data is the biggest
limitation to alignment which is we have
like two or three data sets that are
driving all the research in open
alignment and thropic HH data set for my
friend deep got that uploaded back in
2022 I think um Ultra feedback from open
bmbb and nectar from Berkeley neus flow
with the Starling models are what most
people are focusing on we need more
particularly if humans wrote it to add
more diversity to our models and more
robustness um DP o is continuing in an
academic sense there is a comedy of
papers extending DPO so there's um this
is odds ratio preference optimization
which doesn't need a reference model
constrained DPO identity preference
optimization I don't remember what bco
is and then I can't pronounce the kto
authors but like ktky something
optimization from contextual in Stanford
dno sdpo which is like sequential DPO
and self-reward there are so many and
that's good and that Trend will continue
and at the same time we're seeing more
model sizes most alignment happened at
the seven or 13B scale I think there's a
large drive to make smaller models
aligned Google is releasing 1 billion
parameter paramet models but it's also
an opportunity where there aren't that
many people playing in the space but
it's something that a lot of people want
just because to run these models locally
making them smaller makes it way
easier and then kind of running back to
two themes throughout this lecture is um
what are specific
evaluations that we should be building
and how do we personalize these models
they kind of go hand inand these are the
things that I'm thinking about I welcome
feedback from them I kind of identified
some people that I'm following to see
where new models come out so I try to
release models at ai2 um hugging face
quickly turns around new aligned models
Under The Zephyr brand these kind of
Berkeley necks and necks of slow people
building data sets and Starling models
new research is a kind of they started
as just the guy technium was fine-tuning
models and now it's a company for
fine-tuning models um open BMB in China
has been doing a lot of preference data
sets they recently released some data
sets called Ultra interact which is some
math preference data for doing rhf and
fine tuning um Argilla is a startup
around building tools to annotate data
is focused on refence data and there's
even just individuals that are driving
this narrative so Maxim and John there's
just a lot of people model merging is
something I didn't talk about but it's
kind of like DPO but taking it even
farther where it's model merging is so
accessible it doesn't you don't need a
GPU to merge models it's a for Loop so
people are going to try it and there's
going to be iteration on it so in this
alignment space never bet against people
where they can just try things and see
what's better excuse me and eventually
learn that's what model merging is and
it's going to be here to
stay so thanks for listening um happy to
take questions and thanks to my many
teammates at hugging phas and ai2 that
make it look like I did so many of these
things but there's a lot of great
contributors that underly this so I'll
kind of slow down and drink some water
and answer some questions but thanks for
coming
again yeah so the top question on scores
if please rate them because it's easy
for me to see them was about odds ratio
preference alignment I think it being
agnostic to the method is the best thing
but you probably need to be good at
engineering to get really good at one
method to get um a specific model
out and kind of getting these
deliverables important to getting
recognition I don't know if people can
talk via microphone which is a much more
natural experience but I'm just going to
keep talking to myself
uh there's a question around the future
of alignment given simple methods can
circumvent fine-tuning um I think that
the future of alignment is like safety
is not the only thing that matters
there's a lot of Promise showing that
alignment helps with how much people
like the model so how much rhf improves
the user experience and how much it
improves code and math abilities so like
while everyone hates qar like qar has
some things to guide towards which are
using synthetic data RL search and stuff
to improve the raw capabilities rather
than just talking about
safety okay
onwards yeah someone people are asking
about the fact that llama 3 uses llama 3
said that they use instruction fine
tuning rejection sampling DPO and PP PO
for their aligned models which I was
like I don't know how they're using all
of these things but I think they're
Shifting the abilities incrementally to
provide nice initialization for the next
method and to keep being able to use new
human data and make the metrics go up I
think over time that will become simpler
in the future meta will not have this
convoluted five-stage multimethod
process and we'll figure out a way to
distill that to one
algorithm um pitfalls of synthetic data
is repetitiveness and not robust
distributions so most of the synthetic
data sets out there are about like they
have very similar things in there and
that is like the models are going to
generalize less well and probably get
less well less boosts from alignment
training if there's not this kind of
General Improvement to capabilities so
um we want to take some imperson
questions um oh yeah that's much better
does anyone have some inperson question
questions to ask
Nathan
okay hi thank you so much um for the
talk what do you think are the greatest
hotspots of like research or work in
terms of personalized language models
and where do you see them having the
most
impact this is one of the things that
I'm excited about the local llm
community like I'm not
particularly ideologically aligned with
like the effective accelerationist stuff
but I do think that they have a lot of
drive to create a language model that
they like to use so that therefore
there's going to be things we learn from
them and that's kind of a classic like
how to integrate multiple communities so
it's like academics aren't used to
looking there but I'm sure there's a lot
to learn there yeah I guess there were
multiple questions about advice for the
field whether it's like grad school or
I'll give my advice with the Caged
advice that is that you should be very
wary of listening to people's advice
because it based on their situation but
I think that the most important thing
you can do when the field is crazy is
just keep trying to develop skills and
keep trying to build something that you
think matters because it's like at the
end of the day that's what you're making
progress on and you'll never be able to
keep track of everything and that's okay
and I can't keep track of everything and
I'm still trying to train models and
build data sets so it's just like like
school is about learning to do research
and that still has value but industry is
also fun if you want to do a startup so
it's there's not like here's think about
what you want to do all I think someone
sent me you can hear me right someone
sent me a question through Zoom um a
quick question you indicated that making
lower methods work with reinforcement
learning is tricky do you think lore
methods work well with DP or its
variance I haven't seen it be
particularly successful so that's that's
my general role of thumb is I really
wait to go deep into a method until
there's been a model release that's in
like the relevant ballpark with that
type of with that method so the fact
that it's been around for so long and
hasn't happened could be a blind spot
but I think that there's some weirdness
that's preventing it from
happen great okay another one
um thank you for the talk you mention
GT4 being used as an evaluation metric
but it causes data contamination what
are some ways to mitigate
this oh man yeah I mean this is why it's
like nice to have human evaluation but I
I don't know if I have an answer at this
point I'm kind of fried from Reading
llama 3 stuff and giving this lecture
but that like that's the fundamental
problem is how to disambiguate various
evaluation like various biases and
evaluation and still get the signal out
of
them right okay one more
um give me a
second for stuff like llama 3 training
on so many tokens like 15 trillion would
that actually make it harder to align
this model without losing some
capabilities uh learn from this
overtraining um it's not technically
overtrained but
every every model will have kind of a
different point by which they're
released East so it's like that's why
you'll need a different learning rate in
back sles and data sets for models so
you will need a different um kind of way
of continuing it but that that is a
common confusion on like how like I I
mean I don't even have an intuition for
it just to know that I have bought this
thing in the past and been proven wrong
about it but it's like it's not that
it's overtrained or harder to fine-tune
it's just that there's more information
into the model and as you continue to do
this the model can keep learning it just
takes more and more data to get marginal
improvements so meow is willing to
invest more money into the model to make
it just a bit better but that shouldn't
that should only help that shouldn't
hurt right great uh here's another one
um do you think synthetic data
generation like cosmop is the way to go
for making controlled or trusted domain
specific
models I think it'll be very good I also
think it's a good way to get around the
fact that
um like Google is paying Reddit $60
million a year to use their data so that
we can no longer train on the newest
Reddit data I think that um cosmop media
and synthetic data sets at a large scale
can be a way around this and there are
rumors that industry is doing something
similar give me a second I think there's
one that I missed
um um could you please share some
insights on why you are finding po
better than
DPO it's mostly like it it ends up
extracting more the data so it's like
the benchmarks end up being a little bit
better if we get it set up correctly
with the same like starting point so
it's like we you choose a set of
evaluations that you care about and you
look at them and through fine tuning the
it's primarily a group of great grad
students doing this is just running a
ton of models and trainings and they're
seeing that PP over liely can be doing a
little bit better and it's like this is
this is the fine margins that a lot of
AI works on
nowadays great um do you foresee a
better evaluation method to be
determined by a stronger or more
specialized model which means world
based are Dead
Forever
um maybe I try not to say no to things
this is becoming philosophical which is
like I'm trying not to say no to things
in the language model space with how
fast things are progressing it's like I
should try not to bet against progress
continuing this goes for pre-training
and alignment and it's like at multiple
stages in the last few months come to
benefit me so it's like if you just
assume that things will get better and
they will work
it it's like just makes it a little bit
easier to wrap your head around
things one last one here
from um give me a
sec at its cor and llm is trying to
approximate a complex distribution would
you say that alignment is the process of
squashing specific parts of this
distribution according to what humans
prefer
yeah I think that's phrased generally
enough that I could get behind it it it
is it's like alignment is about changing
the distribution and it's it can be
multiple tokens of it's like a multi-
turn prediction like RL is not just
autor regressive like it can be these
kind of multi-ring different things that
are getting shifted around and it's a
really different loss
function here's one from um how do you
envision the usage of watermark for both
open and closed uh language
modk I think it's a lot of times feels
like a losing battle um I think that a
practical solution in the future is that
a lot of if you want to prove something
that is human made you can prove that it
was generated by a human by having a
certain tool rather than trying to
understand if a specific content was
made by an AI so the Assumption will be
that all content was made by an AI less
proven to be human is not what I would
consider a sociologically like good
answer it just seems like a practical
one makes sense I think we have a few
more minutes so if anybody has any last
minute questions feel free to send them
um over to me on the zoom
chat yeah this is much that was much
better than me half reading the
question all right here's one um what
are your thoughts different optimization
functions to train large language models
rather than using
mle what could be good research um
directions
through I think this is the whole idea
of what rhf represents unless why like
if you ask people have been in NLP
longer one of the most compelling
Arguments for rhf for me is like you now
have extreme flexibility on the loss
function while we were kind of limited
on what our regressive losses could do
so there's kind of arguments that it's
like why is there any limit if we could
just keep doing more and more tokens of
RL training it's a really like General
framing but like rl's loss function it
it you make it so that the training of a
language model can incorporate many
different things and that's very
exciting that could be like the 10-year
goal of
rhf to what
extent is trading on adversarial data
effective for defending against
Crescendo and other simple multi-turn
attacks
I haven't spent as much time on safety
as I would want to but I think that it's
like it'll be this Everlasting dance
where if you have example data you can
defend against it but it will not be
impossible to generate new data so it
mostly comes down to the use case that
you're looking at protecting so if you
want to protect something really
important you need to have layers on
that that are not just sensitive to a
new prompting technique but like limit
what the model can do that's kind it's
like a use focused theme well the kind
of whole like security is a very
complicated thing
otherwise here's one on
quantization
um do you see potential in quantization
methods such as
bitet um like 1.58 bit if so do you
think bitnet will become
popular I have no idea I wouldn't Ru
this is what I mean it's like okay
sounds cool wouldn't rule it out
you think there is a need or a way to
control large scale data extraction from
large language models like cosmop
pedia I do think there's a lot of wills
and a lot of ways to explore making the
synthetic data better I think it's very
early I have a project that's going on
it and it it is one of the few ways that
can generate more tokens which is like
like like people are actually running
out of tokens especially if you try not
to train on things that you're not
supposed to train on it's like like then
you can just generate more data and as
we've seen with llama if you have the
compute more data will help
you let's see selfplay like things any
chance um you can kind of expand upon or
share your opinions on self-play likee
things like open AI super alignment
work I think people will keep using
language models in the loop training
other language models but it's it's a
kind of broad field that doesn't have
full agreement on how to do
it okay cig I think we're pretty much
out of time so um if folks want to get
in touch or have more questions can they
email you or yeah read great but yeah
thanks so much again um for taking the
time and for giving us such a great talk
um so yeah give it
forthan and I think the slides as well
as the hugging face collection are all
posted on our website as well as um
Discord so in case anybody wants to
follow
along sounds good thanks a lot for
having me no worries see everyone soon
bye bye