great so I think let's get started
because we have a lot to cover today uh
so my name is Yan uh for those who don't
know me I'm a third-year PhD student
advised by Tatsu and Percy and today
I'll be talking about benchmarking and
evaluations uh so benchmarking and
evaluations are honestly something that
I think not enough people look at in
Academia uh but if you really want to
put something in production and you
really care about let's say real world
machine learning uh evaluation is really
key so let's talk about
that so overview of what we'll talk
about first is uh different reasons for
measuring performance uh then I'll talk
about text classification and and how
you measure performance there then text
generations and how you measure
performance there and finally like how
do you evaluate Uh current large
language models um and some issues and
challenges with the ways that we
actually to perform
evaluations okay so my mental model of
how you actually develop a machine
learning model is that first you will be
uh training your model uh so here
measuring performance is really key uh
because you need to have a loss um that
you need to know when basically how to
optimize um then once you are optimizing
your loss the second step is basically
development uh so usually this is highi
tuning or for example if you have um
early stopping during your models like
if you see that your model is not
performing that well you might or that
there's like some overfitting happening
you might decide to to stop or you might
decide to like change the learning rate
during the training of your model so
development is kind of the Second Step
um and here you need to measure
performance because you need to know how
to do actually uh models uh sorry High
Prim tuning um and and like changing
High parameters uh then the third step
is essentially model selection so if I
have a task that I really care about uh
which model performs best for my task
that might be a model that I have
trained it might be a model that another
group has
trained uh and finally at least in the
real world you would decide to deploy
your model and here per uh measuring
performance is really key because you
need to know whether your model is good
enough to put in production um in the
parallel universe that we live in
there's also the publishing uh so you
basically need to um test like evaluate
a model on standing bench marks and the
reason why we do that is essentially for
communicating to different groups the
quality of our bottle so at every step
of this pipeline you really need to
measure performance and that's what
we'll talk about today but what is key
to understand is that at different steps
you need to measure performance in
different ways so there's really not a
single way of of uh not a single ideal
way of measuring
performance so for example on the left
when you train your model uh for
evaluating performance you really need
to uh have a way of measuring
performance that is super fast super
cheap uh and differentiable because
usually I mean with new networks you
basically back propagate through the
loss so it needs to be differentiable
and finally you really cannot have a way
for your model to optimize some
shortcuts um to optimize the loss even
though it's not really what you wanted
to optimize uh and as you move more to
the right basically you you allowed or
like you will you will um measure
performance uh less often so it's fine
if it's more expensive uh but you really
like the the risk that that um or you
really need your perform your measuring
like your your evaluation metrics to be
higher quality uh because um the issues
if you put a model in production are
higher um so during the development
stage you need a way of measuring
performance that is fast cheap and also
kind of avoiding shortcuts because when
you do high PR tuning you're essentially
also optimizing over certain
objective uh model selection it can be a
little bit less fast and less cheap but
still you will have to do it that many
many times and most importantly when you
deploy a model you really want the way
to evaluate performance to be
trustworthy uh because once you put
something in production there's kind of
no way to go back for what happened
during that time where it was in
production uh you also want things to be
very task specific so if I care about a
certain task when I put when I put my
model in production H it really you
really need to evaluate on that specific
task I don't care about other tasks and
finally you need your metrics to be
absolute uh so the reason why I'm
highlighting that is that in the in the
three other steps you really just care
about comparing between things um so
that is very different than if you if
you want to kind of have a a threshold
which says if I have less than 95%
accuracy I'm not putting my model in
production okay and now let's talk about
publishing this is a little bit
different than honesty evaluation in the
real world uh but when you publ when you
basically do academic benchmarking and
when you evaluate uh your models and
academic benchmarks you want the
Benchmark to be reproducible and
standardized and the reason why is
basically because for the next five or
six or 10 years everyone will be
evaluated on that one Benchmark and you
want papers in three years to be
comparable to yours uh so it's really
important that your evaluations are
reproducible honestly you don't really
care about that in the real world um you
also want things to be easy to work with
because researchers are uh usually a
little bit they don't want to do
additional work that they need to uh and
also they usually don't have that much
resource so it needs to be fast and and
and cheap um
and finally one one thing which I really
want to highlight is that for the
academic benchmarks that we usually have
it's fine if the metrics that we use are
not perfect because really what matters
is that over 10 years uh the direction
that your metrix is showing you to to go
into like basically the how the field is
moving um really if if the metric is
saying that it's slightly better uh
sorry that it's better over 10 years
that in reality the the the field has
made some progress um so at a meta level
it's fine if you use crude metrics in in
um in
Academia and also you kind of need to
um to balance between difficulty and
simplicity and what I mean by that is
that if your benchmark is way too
complicated uh then basically all
methods will have essentially random
performance so no one will use your
benchmark and if uh your benchmark is
too simple then the basine will be so
good that no one will use your benchmark
because no one can beat the the the
Baseline this is really something that
is specific to Academia in the real
world you're not going to be able to
change the Tas that you're performing uh
based on like how good your model is so
that's why I I kind of just want to
highlight that because usually people
talk about evaluations but there's
really different like different ways of
evaluating and different reasons why we
evaluate is that all makes sense also
feel free to ask
questions great Okay so benchmarks in
Academia this is really the way we drive
the field so this is The mlu Benchmark I
think archit briefly mentioned it but
I'll talk about it later again um so
this is the most standard Benchmark
right now and you basically see that in
the last 4ish years uh it has gone from
25% accuracy which is essentially random
because uh it's multiple choice um and
there are four choices to around 90 is%
accuracy um so yeah benchmarking is
really what Drive the the the progress
in the field and again you see what I
mean here what I meant here is that it's
not really the differences between small
points that matter at least in Academia
you have to take a step back and you
have to think what matters is is like
how your models will perform over 10
years and making sure that the model on
the top right here is better than the
model on the top on the bottom left um
even if the if even if the Benchmark is
not perfect and I I think mlu is a
pretty good one in that
sense okay so there are two main types
at least classically of um tasks in in
NLP um close ended tasks uh so I'll talk
about it later but essentially you can
think about classification where you
know exactly uh the label the correct
label for uh the task that you're
performing so here this is the IMDB data
set where you're asked to say whether a
sentence is has positive sentiment or
negative sentiment so the text is read
the book forget the movie so this is
about uh sentiment classification of the
movie so here it's basically negative um
and then there's open-ended evaluation
so think about Chad GPT like how do you
evaluate something like that where
really there's no correct answer uh and
there are many or there are many
possible correct answers and they all
have like different qualities um so
we're going to distinguish between those
two so close ended
evaluation so as I just said close ended
tasks uh there's a limited it's Define
one uh as the task where is's a limited
number of potential answers um think
like less than 10 um and often there's
just one or maybe a few correct POS
possible answers um so this really is
standard machine learning if you think
about standard classification you can
just do accuracy you can look at your
Precision your recalls um there's
nothing special here about NLP uh that
is not to me to say that it's simple
it's just that there's nothing special
about NP here
uh so some tasks some uh close-ended
tasks I already told you about uh
sentiment analysis so usually this is a
binary binary classification task where
you just have to say whether the
sentiment is positive or whether it's
negative uh another task is entailment
um also for sentiment analysis the
typical benchmarks I always put it next
to the task uh is IMDb and SST from
Stanford entailment is snli also from
Stanford where basically you have some
text so here a soccer game with multiple
males playing and then you have a
hypothesis some men are playing Sport
and you have to say whether the
hypothesis is implied or entailed by the
text uh so here it is uh other tasks
part of speech uh typical Benchmark um
pentry bank and name entity recognition
uh which is a caral uh
Benchmark a few other tasks you don't
need to know all of them but just to
give you a brief overview uh cor
reference resolution um so this is
actually a pretty challenging uh NLP
task where you have to say what pronoun
which pronoun refers to what noun so you
have here the sentence Mark told Pete
many lies about himself uh himself which
Pete included in his book uh he should
have been more truthful and now you have
to say uh what does he refer to um
whether he refers to Pete and then there
question answering uh where you
basically have a long text and you ask a
question and uh well the test ask a
question and you're supposed to provide
an answer based on the on the text that
you have before so those are some
examples of of uh close ended tasks and
again uh the key here is that the way we
evaluate those is just standard machine
learning you can look at accuracy
precision recall F1 score uh hopefully
you all know about these type of metrics
but if you don't you should look at um
Chris Peach's uh class uh I think it's
cs224u uh but his lecture is online and
it's actually really good um on
different
metrics um so the ways that people
evaluate some of these benchmarks uh is
usually by looking at many of them uh
concurrently uh so the most common I
would say like super or multitask
Benchmark is called superglue um so here
you see on the on the columns here you
have all the different tasks uh in super
glue so I think there are eight or nine
um and then you you really just look at
the average uh performance in each of
these benchmarks and you get a ranking
on that and that is kind of a attempt to
measure General language capabilities um
this is what people used to do I would
say until maybe two years ago um I will
tell you about what people do now uh
around the end of the lecture uh but
yeah super glue is is definitely
something you should at least be aware
of uh and the example of tasks uh that
are in superglue uh one is a bull Q
which is simply you have some text you
have some question and you have to say
whether the answer is yes or whether
it's no so that's very easy to evaluate
you just look at accuracies or Precision
recall uh entailment we already talked
about um and then the other ones like
co- reference resolution which we also
talked about and meaning of words which
is something where you have two
sentences with uh the same words and you
have to say whether they actually mean
the same thing in this sentence for
example if if you have Bank could mean
Bank like water and Bank like money and
you have to say whether in these two
sentences um they refer to the same
concept uh and there are some question
answering tasks too um so this is about
super clue are there any
questions no cool um so again although I
said many times that this is essentially
just classical machine learning uh I
want to emphasize that it doesn't mean
that it's simple and and you really have
to think carefully about what you do
when you use those type of close-ended
tasks in particular you're going to have
to choose whether you look at accuracies
Precision recall F1 score Rock curves Au
curves if you don't know these names you
should really check out the es learn uh
documentation or the lecture from Chris
Peach that I that I I linked above um
both of which are really good but
depending on which metric you will
choose uh you will have very you will
decide on very different type of
algorithms and the usual example is is
that if um let's say you look at uh spam
you want to do classification of whether
um a email is spammed or not most emails
are not spammed uh thankfully at least I
hope um so let's say that 90% of emails
were actually not spam and only 10% of
them are spam uh if you look at the
accuracy then just a random classifier
uh that predicts the most likely label
will get 90% accuracy um and that seems
if you don't know really about your data
set like 90% accur seems good but in
reality here it means that you're not
classifying anything um so that's why
you want to look at Precision recall and
Fon call um anyways I will not talk too
much about that because again this is
not specific to NLP but it doesn't mean
it's easy um another issue is that once
you have multiple different tasks
there's a question of how do you
aggregate these metrics so right before
I told you oh you just take the average
between all of these things this
honestly is a really terrible thing of
do um to do but that's actually what
people do um but these columns actually
mean very different things some of them
are accuracies others are F1 score
others are correlations uh and you just
average everything I can't remember
which uh Benchmark but I remember a few
years ago there was one Benchmark where
actually one of the columns was uh you
were better basically you had better
performance if the if the value was
lower and you still took an average of
these things until someone realized like
maybe we should take a put a minus there
so uh um so yeah be careful and like
don't always think that what people do
in in in Academia or like in yeah that
what people do is correct um you should
think a little bit uh about that then
there are some other questions I want
you to think about uh where do those
labels come from I said that is usually
a a real answer but how you actually get
those La labels is is unclear so I will
tell you about like some issues uh in
the next slide and uh and also related
to that the might be some superious
correlations and that's what we're going
to talk about right now so we already
talked about um snli so uh entailment so
here you have again your premise the E
economy could still be better uh and the
hypothesis the economy has never been
better and you have to say whether the
hypothesis is implied by the premise uh
and what this paper from 2019 found that
actually all the different models were
performing really well but if you looked
if you just classified based on the
hypothesis you could also perform really
well so even if you did not look at the
at the premise which seems like
something that you need to take into
account because it's part of the task
you could perform well and the reason
why is because uh they realized that
when the humans actually wrote the the
hypothesis they will ask oh write a
hypothesis which is not entailed by the
premise and how humans usually do that
is by adding a negation um so if you
only look at the hypothesis and you see
this a negation it's very likely that
it's not entailed by uh by the premise
um so again even though this is standard
machine learning be really careful about
what metric you use and what where do
the labels come from uh and don't do
everything like don't just use what
people do thinking that like if there
was an issue people would have realized
um so yeah so that is Pur correlations
uh any questions on close ended task
cool okay open-ended evaluations I'm
going to mostly talk about that because
this is what is specific to uh
NLP um so open-ended evaluation or
open-ended task is essentially the
opposite of the close ended task which
is to say that there are many possible
correct answers and you cannot enumerate
all of them um so you really can't use
standard machine learning metrics uh and
more oops um even more than the the fact
that you cannot enumerate all the
possible answers usually uh there are
different levels of correctness so if I
ask you to write a book or if I ask chpt
to write a book like it might be a
decent book but it might be a better
book uh that it could have written or
that another model could write so it's
not just right and wrong there's like
diff it's a Continuum or or yeah it's a
Continuum uh so stand examples for
open-ended tasks the two most common
ones are summarization um so
summarization you have a long uh piece
of text and you just ask to summarize it
in less than X characters um standard
Benchmark is the C uh CNN and daily mail
um Benchmark so the way they actually uh
um collected that data set is that they
took a lot of CNN articles and you know
at the top of CNN articles you have
bullet points uh that kind of say like
what are the most important things in
the article so they use this as the as
essentially the gold summary um so this
is the classic one for summarization for
translation you basically have sentences
in two different languages and you have
to translate from one to the other uh so
those are the classical ones uh the way
that people currently do it is I would
say the the most standard task right now
is instruction following instruction
following is kind of the uh the mother
of all tasks in the sense that um you
can view any previous task as just a
chat bot or like some question that you
ask to basically chat GP you can think
classification I could just ask CH GPT
to do that you can think summarization I
could ask CH GPT to do that so
essentially you could just view a
chatbot as the most General type of task
and you can per you can ask it to
perform any possible task and it should
just provide the answer for that task uh
so this is what we call instruction
following uh so as you might think um
evaluation is very hard in that domain
uh and that's what we'll talk about
later is how do you evaluate something
like CH GPT
okay so types of evaluation methods for
text generation or open-ended tasks um
the classical ones are content overlap
metrix which I'll talk about then so
that's really comparing just the the the
words between a reference answer a gold
answer that humans wrote and the actual
Generation generation that you got from
your model uh then there's a there are
model based metrics where you basically
uh turn evaluation into machine learning
so you ask a you train a model to
basically become an evaluator um and
then there human evaluation which is uh
usually seen as the gold standard for
open-ended
tasks so content overlap metrics so as I
just said this is really just comparing
word by word um or group of words
between the generated sequence and some
reference um so here I have the
generated sequence being the woman went
to the hardware store and the gold
reference which is uh the reference
written by humans I actually don't even
know what the task is but the reference
here is they walk to the grocery store
and then what you do is that you just
compare uh the two different sentences
by looking at the lexical similarity
between those two
texts um and this is super fast and
efficient and the way you usually do
that is by using engram overlap metrix
so what I mean by this is that uh the
simplest possible thing is just to say
whether for every word in the generated
sequence whether it appears in the
reference sequence and if if it does
then you kind of increment um your
performance uh so engrams is essentially
the same thing but instead of looking at
a single word you basically look at Iams
trigrams and and and kind of um uh
multiple words uh next to one another so
the usual overlap metrix the most common
ones are blue and Rouge uh blue means
blue and Rouge means red um that's not
what they stand for though and I I
always forget what they stand for
uh but basically blur what it is is that
it's a engram overlap metric that um
tries to look at Precision while Rouge
is what looks at it looks at the recall
uh so as I as I said before as alluded
before what is important even if you
turn everything into a kind of sentence
classification you have to think about
whether you care about Precision or
recall um so those metrics are not ideal
but until I would say two years ago they
would have gold standard for translation
and summarization uh for translation
people use blue uh because you really
want to yeah you really want you
basically look at the let's say I'm
translating from French to English uh I
want to look at the uh generated
sequence in English and the actual
reference sequence in English and I want
to know whether every uh Bagram that I
generated appears or like how many of
the bams that I I generated appears in
the uh in the reference sequence um the
there's one additional thing which is
that they don't only look at Precision
because you could get a very high
Precision by actually predicting
something very small uh for example if
you always predicted the word the only
generated the word the you would most
likely get very high Precision uh
because the usually appears in every
sentence or like let's say a full stop
um so there's also like some length
penalty uh and Rouge is kind of the
opposite it just look said we call um so
those are the the common the common
content overlap metrics and I'll just to
illustrate why those are not ideal um
well they have many issues but one of
them is that they don't really take into
account the the semantic relatedness
between words um so imagine that Chris
asks you are you enjoying the cs224 N
lectures uh of course the the gold
answer is heck yes um so that's the
reference answer so now let's say that
the model just generates yes so here
what you're going to have is if I look
at the blue the blue score uh I will
have
67% uh um essentially blue score because
two of the words that I generated or two
of the unigrams I generated are in the
reference um in the gold reference if I
generate you know it then I will only
have a single um token in the generated
sequence that appears in the reference
sequence which is the exclamation point
uh I get a much lower um blue score and
if I just say yep then that doesn't
appear at all in the generated uh sorry
in the reference sequence so I get zero
uh blue score which is a false negative
because really it literally means the
same thing as uh heck yes um so
hopefully you see that like these
metrics really have issues um also you
can have false positives for example if
you say heck no uh then most of the
words are the same so you get 7% uh blue
score um but it really means something
completely
different uh does that make sense any
questions cool so very naturally now
that you know everything about what it
Bings what you might ask is oh why do we
look at words if what we could do is
looking at like learn representations
which really kind of uh maintain the the
semantic similarity uh between words uh
so this is exactly what people have done
um around 2019 I think is that they took
uh some some or even before actually
2016 they took some word embeddings um
they Associated every word in the uh in
the reference sequence to a word
embedding every word um in the generated
sequence to the corresponding word
embedding and they basically started
comparing the word embeddings so a very
simple way of comparing word embeddings
is just you take the average uh between
the word embeddings in the reference
sequence and the average between the
word embeddings in the generated
sequence and you maybe look at cosine
similarity I mean there are mod ways of
doing it but honestly at this point it's
not that important uh so you can think
about
averaging um another one uh as you
know at this point um what embeddings
don't really take into account the
contextual um or like the context of the
of where the word basically appears uh
so better way of getting good
representations for for word is by
looking essentially at at BIR so what
you could do is you could take a bird
model you could pass the generated
sequence through it you get some
embeddings um and then you can take bird
again the same bird you pass the
reference sequence to it you get some
other embeddings and then you do again
some comparison I mean this bird score
uh pretty famous paper they do like some
smart comparison but it it's not that
important to understand what EX exactly
they do um what is important is that
they take like some smart averaging um
between those
words cool any
questions
okay um so that was the simplest uh the
simplest type of of meth of learning
methods which is uh word uh word
matching another slightly more
complicated one is called blurt also
pretty famous which is a mix between
blur and bird uh so the the way that
they did that is that basically they
they took a pre-trained bir um and then
they do some continual pre-training by
trying to predict the the blur score and
some other metrics and then they
fine-tune that's the important part is
that they F tune the pre-train model uh
to actually do the evaluation that they
care about so let's say that I have a
lot of different uh sequences and I I I
have some human annotations of how I
should be evaluating it I could just
treat that as a normal machine learning
task and I just fine-tune my bir uh to
do the
evaluation so this is
blurt any
questions yes curious if you pre-train
on uh blue wouldn't it cause the same
problems as the if you if your
pre-training fast is blue then your
would learn the ability to model
languages semantically in the first
place yeah uh that's a very good point
so actually I I also find it kind of
surprising so they did two things first
they do the real pre-training of of uh
of bird and then they do continual
pre-training for predicting uh blue and
the reason why is because usually they
say we have a lot of uh sequences in our
data set that are unlabeled so we have
like some reference um sequences and
some uh generated sequences but we don't
have like the human annotation of
whether this is good or bad so we will
treat that as unsupervised learning
objective uh so what you use for the
supervised learning objective well you
have to use something and they basically
use blur and they also use actually um
uh Bird score so they use like many
different tasks and they basically do
multitask
learning
cool okay so one important uh issue with
all these methods is that really they
are they can only be as good as the
references are and in reality the
references are usually not that good uh
so this is in part this is a paper that
looks at summarization um of news so
basically as I said before most of the
news summarization benchmarks um they
they usually take the the reference uh
summary as being the bullet points that
you find at the top of an article um and
this is usually not that good so here
what you see on the um sorry on on the
left this is what if you look at the
correlation between the x-axis being the
the human uh rate of or like the human
evaluated performance of every model and
on the y- axis you see the uh Rouge L
which is just a variant of rouge um and
you look at whether uh basically these
two are correlated and what you see is
that it essentially not correlated which
means that rou L on standard um
references is really not correlated to
what humans would say is a good summary
um that is not to say that rou is a bad
score that is to say that actually the
references are bad because if you look
at the exact same thing uh but now you
ask experts to write very good summaries
uh then you see that the correlation
actually increases by a decent amount
still not perfect uh Rouge is definitely
not perfect but at least it's much
better um so this is to say that the
metric itself is is not always perfect
but not only this the the references are
usually actually uh not
great cool so that begs a very natural
question which is can we just dump uh
and Le yeah basically move away from
reference based evaluation so as we just
said uh reference based evaluations are
the ones that compare human written
references to some model outputs uh
using some different type of metrics um
and those used to be the standard
metrics for evaluating or the standard
Benchmark for evaluating NLP tasks uh I
would say up to like 2 or 3 years ago
right now now I think uh papers still
have to always show the blue scores like
for example in Translation um because
review is W those but I'm I don't think
like anyone in in uh in the real world
actually uses them but I might be wrong
on that um so yeah so blue Rouge Bird
score oh and I was mostly talking about
blue and Rouge Bird score is actually
still uh decently used and and actually
pretty good okay so reference free
evaluation so reference free evaluation
is uh basically you have a model and you
ask it to give a score uh but there are
no human references um so the way that
this is that this used to be done is
essentially by taking a model like like
B again but instead of comparing between
a reference a reference answer and the
generated answer you could just ask it
to to take the input and just predict
the score uh that's like one simple way
of doing it that used to really not work
well uh and I say used to because until
basically Chad GPT and GPT 4 uh now what
people do and honestly that works super
well is that you just ask gp4 to do the
uh the same task as you would ask a
human so you give like a very long uh
text and then you uh you give the
generated summary and you ask like how
good is it essentially and that works uh
surprisingly well um so common
benchmarks here alpaca eval and empty
bench uh there are many others now
honestly most people uh start using
these type of of techniques um but we'll
be talking at least about app Eva
um good okay so let's talk a little bit
about human evaluation before looping
back to um to basically
gp4 um so as we saw the metrics until
now they are they all have some
shortcomings um and they definitely not
as good as if you ask directly human
evaluation because they are based on on
um on
references uh so human evaluation is
really the goal standard for open-ended
uh open ended tasks um and not only is
it really the the standard way of doing
evaluation or like the goal standard for
evaluation it's also the gold standard
for developing new automatic evaluations
so every time you you develop a new
automatic evaluations you will want to
compare to uh what humans would have
basically uh predicted
um
yeah okay so doing human evaluation i'
first it might seem very simple you
basically ask humans to evaluate the
quality of some generated text seems
simple right uh but actually it's super
complicated and it's a it's a real like
Challenge and it has many issues so
first um oh sorry I I'll talk about that
before maybe one additional thing is
that you should not only ask the human
you usually ask it also to um ask them
to evaluate across different axes for
example the fluency of the text or the
coherence of the text or like common
sense or like the the style
grammaticality redundancy and like
different axes that you might care about
um another thing to note is that you
should absolutely never compare uh
different human evaluations so if
there's one paper that says oh uh humans
have evaluated the fluency of our text
to be I don't know four out of five uh
and then another paper that says like
three out of five like they use
different humans different ways of like
prom prompting the humans um so it's
it's absolutely not comparable
okay so let's go back to some of the
issues so as I said human judgments are
regarded as the gold standard uh but
definitely has issues uh first it's
super slow um as you might expect humans
are definitely not as fast as automatic
uh metrics uh second at least in
Academia it's it's still pretty
expensive to do um because I mean when
you pay well your workers um it's pretty
expensive to do well uh human evaluation
um another part is interannotator
disagreement so if I take two random
people in this room and I ask them to
evaluate the quality of a generated text
I can assure you that you will really
not agree uh so this is even if it
especially if it's subjective it's
really bad but even if you talk for like
one hour before about uh like how you
should be evaluating um uh Generations I
can most likely guarantee you that you
will you will still disagree on many of
the evaluations and to give you an
example uh when we were doing uh alpaca
form last year which is uh something
where we basically had to take um some
inputs and then take two models um think
chat GPT alpaca and these type of models
and you just uh have the two models
predict an answer and then you ask the
humans to say which answer they prefer
this is a very simple task um and this
is but I will talk about it later this
is what like a lot of people basically
use right now for evaluating um models
like J GPT um so natural question is
whether humans are good at doing that
and what we saw is that so we were five
researchers doing that and the five of
us we talked for like two or three hours
we write wrote extremely detailed uh
rubrics about how to do their
evaluations and still we only agreed 67%
of the time so 50% is like uh random uh
and if we just label things
independently we only uh agree 67% of
the time and we really try to do our
best like we were working on this thing
so it's not as if we were trying to do
it like quickly so really people
disagree of course if you if you then
allow like discussions between the
annotators then agreement actually
improves uh but then it becomes even
more like slower and more expensive
intra annotator disagreement this is
something that is extremely annoying
which is that if I ask a human if I ask
myself right now to evaluate something
or like in three hours like after I have
dinner or after I went to to run I will
actually give different different
annotations um
yes
to um you mean for
validating yeah so this is a very good
question honestly there's no good answer
the usual way that people do it is that
you look at some statistical um like
some stati iCal metrics basically where
you're like okay I want to compare
between these two models uh I'm going to
look at I'm going to basically perform a
t test and I'm I want to know that like
my P value is less than a certain amount
um what people usually do also when they
have humans annotations um I
unfortunately didn't put a slide on that
but they have a metric for computing the
intra annotator basically agreement and
they try to achieve a certain intra
annotator agreement and if not they will
essentially ask for more humans or for
Rel
labelings um
yeah it's not reproducible and this is
like partly because of the two things
that we said before uh but also partly
because um yeah I mean mostly because of
the two things before so this is a an
interesting paper um I think it's I I
forgot which year I think it's from 2021
but I'm not sure uh where basically they
say and I read from the abstract here
just 5% of human evaluations are
repeatable in the sense that there are
no prohibitive barriers to repetition
and sufficient information about EXP
experimental design uh is publicly
available for rerunning them so this is
a paper that analyzed I think
128 um different papers that were
published across like five years I think
between 2015 and 2020 um and they found
that essentially only 5% of those papers
were reproducible um uh so honestly
working with humans is hard that's
definitely something to
remember uh another part is that humans
only uh basically evaluate precision and
not recall so what I mean by that is
that if I if I if you show me uh what
the model generated I can only evaluate
that generation I cannot gen evaluate
all the other possible Generations I
could have generated um because then you
really have to sample a lot of things
and that that will become way too slow
and way too expensive and finally uh
usually the incentives are not aligned
so what you want is for the humans to
basically do the best possible
evaluations uh but what crowd workers
usually want is basically to maximize
the the amount of money that they get
paid uh per hour so to give you again a
concrete example when we were doing
alpaka Farm um I I think we were paying
relatively well in the sense that we
were paying a u 1.5 times the the
minimum wage in California um and then
we divided basically we we looked at how
much time we would spend to do the thing
like in the basically to evaluate a
single example the best we could uh um
and then we divided by that time to
basically know how much how much we
would pay for every example um and what
we realized is that they ended up being
paid I think two or 2.5 times the
minimum wage because they were just
doing things like two three times faster
than us uh and I don't I mean we could
be slow but I think what was happening
is that they were just trying to
maximize the dollars that they were
getting per hour and as a result they
were uh finding like shortcuts for doing
their evaluations um and this is
something that you really see in the of
papers uh for example in our case uh you
saw that humans really preferred longer
answers and of course if you give me two
uh two very long gener like two sorry
generations and you ask me with minimal
amount of work to say which one is
better like if I see a longer one I'm
like H probably there are more details
proba it's better uh anyways it's not to
say that everyone is like is like that
but definitely it's it's the incentives
are on line so you have to be careful of
this uh other challenges uh first you
have to decide how to descri the task uh
you really have to give very detailed
rubrics for how the humans have to
evaluate the task um then there's a
question of how do you show the task to
the humans uh for example the order in
which you give examples actually really
important uh the in our case because we
had two examples side by side they're
actually which one is on the left and
which one is on the right is actually
also very important so all these things
really matter um of course you can
randomize these things away but but it
is like it adds challenges um what
metrics to use I mean this is not
specific to humans uh selecting the
annotators this is also very complicated
uh you might think okay I have some
money now I I can go on on Amazon M
turkers and I can just ask them to uh
evaluate uh or to do some annotations
but in reality you want to have the good
annotators so how it usually works in
Amazon uh in in m is that basically you
you uh say oh here's a task I want like
30 different people to do these
annotations uh and then they start
annotating and then you if they don't
achieve the level that you want you
basically pay for what they they
annotated until then and you you work
with someone else afterwards uh so then
there's a question of how do you decide
whether they achieved the performance
that you want uh so you probably have to
do like some gold labeling before and
then look at like some accuracies of how
well and like some intra anator
agreement with you and with like the
other researchers on your team uh so it
is very
complicated and not only this you have
to monitor that over time um so there
are many different ways you can monitor
that over time looking again at the
accuracy so maybe every let's say a
typical thing is that every batch of
example that you label you give a few
you give a few examples that are
actually uh ones that you already know
what the Gold Label is and you see how
well they're performing on that another
way to look at is like the time that
they take to annotate um
yeah okay so that was about humans uh so
human evaluation is hard but it is a
gold
standard okay now let's talk about uh
reference free evaluation and chat bots
so so I already told you about uh about
it before very briefly how do you
evaluate something like chat GPT um this
is extremely complicated because
basically you could ask it any task you
want um and it can answer text that is
arbitrarily long and that just makes
evaluation extremely hard um so as I
suggested before the usual way that it's
done is that you take two models you put
them side by side you as the same
question and you just ask either some
humans or some model as we will see
afterwards uh which which one is better
um so this is the most common Benchmark
right now I would say for human
evaluation it's called chatbot Arena uh
where basically anyone can go online and
just play with for free with some of
like the best models out there and all
they ask you is to say whether you
prefer the one on the right or whether
you prefer the one on the left
essentially uh and then once they reach
I think a crazy amount of data 200,000
human votes for example they basically
add it to a leaderboard uh and the way
they add it to leaderboard is that they
um essenti I don't know if you know how
chess works but they basically look at
the ELO ratings um so it's they
basically put everything as if it was a
t tournament uh such that not every
model has to uh play against every other
model uh and then they get Elo Elo
scores okay so what's missing with this
side by side human evil as I said this
is really the gold standard for
evaluation of CH chat LMS but there are
still some challenges uh first like it's
basically random people online uh that
ask random questions and they provide
like their preferences um so that might
may not be representative although
arguably when you have that many
examples like it becomes actually pretty
representative of what people would want
Al um
so it's probably better than whatever we
have um but it is still not ideal and
then really the big the big issue is
cost uh this takes a huge Community
effort and a lot of people to work on
that um also it takes a lot of time to
get uh new models on The Benchmark and
only the notable models so think like
the openi models and the cloud and like
the Google ones uh and the Facebook ones
are going to be benchmarked uh you will
never have for your random model 200,000
uh um people who are willing to annotate
it for free um so this is an issue and
again like as as we talked about in the
first slide even for those big companies
they can definitely not do that for like
development of their model uh this is
something that comes at the end for
maybe model
selection okay so how do we make it
faster um so one uh very natural uh
solution is basically to ask uh a large
language model to do the evaluation for
you so imagine that I want to compare
chat GPT with Moll I basically add G as
GPT 4 to evaluate uh which one is better
um this is surprisingly good and I will
show you some results afterwards and
some common versions are Paka eval and
empty bench probably the two most common
ones um so when we started doing that
that's a problem I told you about uh we
started that around last year um and we
found that using gp4 essentially for
evaluation is at least if you look at
the prices now would be 100 times faster
and 100 times cheaper than if use human
evaluations uh but and this is very
surprising the agreement with humans
actually higher than humans agree with
themselves so what I mean by that is
that if I ask so this is what we found
if I ask four humans uh let's say I have
a pool of four humans and I take out one
human and I look at the agreement
between that that human preferences and
the mode of the preferences of the three
others and I I do that in a leave one
out fashion and I look at this agreement
uh this will be lower than if I ask um
for the model to predict essentially the
preference of the mode of the humans um
so in some ways models are more highly
correlated with humans than humans
themselves which is very surprising and
I will tell you about it in two seconds
a little bit more um when we did that we
actually use that for uh collecting uh
human preferences for rhf so that's what
we call R AI as I think Arch told you
about these things uh last
week um so going back to this ISS or
this like surprising result that
actually models are more highly
correlated with humans and humans
themselves the reason why this is is
because humans are actually uh have high
inter annotate disagreement and have
high variance essentially um models they
will always be very consistent or maybe
not perfectly like there's still some
some circity but essentially they will
they will always predict the same uh
label so they have very little variance
so here what you see on this plot is on
the Y sorry x-axis we estimated the the
variance and you see that the human has
a variance of like around 31 or 33 um
well if you look at the red point this
is basically if you just add gp4 to do
evaluations so even though the bias is
still pretty high um so bias by
definition for humans is zero uh for
gbd4 it is like around 32% the viance is
much lower um than than humans so this
is why you can see that actually
sometimes agreement is higher but that's
really because there are there's no
varant or very little Varan in uh in
LMS um yeah does that make sense
yeah lens is higher than a human sorry
it means the internal cerence is higher
than exactly so which which is actually
a good sign because that means it's
that's makes it much easier for for
research the bad sign is that the bias
is still
high yeah okay so things to be careful
with when you work I mean this is both
with humans and with uh llms uh there
will be some spus correlations so we
already talked about SP correlations but
you will see a lot of those um one very
common example is length so if you just
as I told you before if you ask crowd
workers which examples they prefer they
are highly biased towards longer longer
output so here the blue is humans it's
around I think 70% preferences for
longer outputs and and models are around
the same uh same bias um and another
example is preference for lists so
usually if you if you see lists in an
output uh models prefer these these
examples and models uh model and humans
prefer these examples uh another another
bias or SP correlation is a position I
told you like how which one you put on
the left which one do you put on the
right when you compare to when you ask
humans to to label there's the same
thing with models but this is usually
pretty easy to control for you just
randomize both uh another issue is GPD
for Self Bias so very naturally you
might like you might wonder if if I ask
GPD for to to evaluate itself like it
will probably bias it will prefer itself
than other models uh and this is true
but less than what you might think I
will tell you about later okay so Al EV
TR wait until what time do I
have you have 30 minutes oh thanks great
um okay alpaka eval so alpaka eval is
The Benchmark that we developed when
when we were working on alpaca um so as
I told you before we need um one thing
which is very important is what you use
for development um so basically for high
propri tuning so what what we did is
that we basically did not trust many of
the benchmarks out there at this point
uh for instruction following so we just
developed a very small Benchmark for
ourselves and this is what we were doing
for I tuning uh and then it kind of
became its own thing um so alpaka eval
in a few numbers it has very high
correlation with chatboard Arena so the
ranking if you look at the the
correlation between the ranking in
chadbad Arena and and in alpaka eval
it's 98% so very high and it takes
around 3 minutes and $10 to to evaluate
um and the way it works I think I
already mentioned it but basically you
take an instruction you generate an
output from one one model and then from
another model that you're you're
comparing it to um and you as gp4 to
basically give the probability that it
prefers uh the model that you're
evaluating versus the Baseline that
you're comparing to um and then you do
some reweighting and the reason why you
do some reweighting is because uh these
models as I said are very uh biased
towards longer outputs so you want to
rewe such that uh if it's a longer
output you give it a slightly less High
preferences uh High preference and then
you average across your entire data set
and you get a red rate um so that's how
it
works any
questions cool um so system level
correlation so here what you see on the
x-axis is basically alaka I mean a
slight transform of it but essentially a
back a EV valid scores and on the y-axis
is this chatbot Arena which is the gold
standard and you see that things are
relatively highly correlated and on the
on the lower plot you see basically the
correlation between different Benchmark
and chatbot Arena and you see like mty
bench and alpaka Eva which are the two
ones that use llms for evaluations are
relatively highly correlated with
chadbad Arena and mlu which is the
automated one that doesn't use anlm is
also very highly correlated
um so I told you very briefly about the
fact that we had to do some reweighting
um so I'm not going to tell you how we
do it but I want to tell you why we do
it um one of the issues that we
realized uh a little bit too late is
that if if you take something like GPT 4
um and you just ask it you prompt it to
be much more detailed to basically
provide much more detailed answers uh
its win rate so its performance on your
on your benchmark goes from 50% to 64.3
uh so that's this one
64.3 uh if you're ask it to be more
concise like it decreases to 22.9 and it
really doesn't fit like our mental model
of what benchmarks should be doing um if
I just change tweak a little bit The
Prompt I don't want my model to change
completely its ranking um so that's why
we have to do some reting and you see
that after the reting uh you basically
have that the uh uh performance after
you as the model to be more of a boss is
is very close to the performance uh
without any any prompt uh
tuning
cool so I told you slight or very
briefly before about self bias I do want
to say that I'm pretty surprised about
this result but actually Self Bias
exists but is not as high as you might
uh think so here you see on the xaxis
the ranking um or like the the different
models that you're evaluating and on the
sorry that's on the rows and on the
columns you see who is evaluating which
model are you using for evaluation and
you actually see that regardless of the
model that you that you evaluate with uh
the ranking will be the same so even
though it's true that um if I look
at um
mol uh evaluated by mol it gives itself
a much higher accuracy uh it is it still
prefers Claud and gp4 uh so it's not as
bad as what you may think it's still bad
though
cool okay so that leads me to talking
about current evaluation of llms so i'
would say there are three main ways that
people currently evaluate llms um the
first one is perplexity um which is
essentially just looking at training
losses or validation losses um the
second one is basically averaging
everything uh which is actually
surprisingly more common than what you
may think and the third one is uh is
this Arena like or where you basically
have comparisons between models and
either use humans or use uh um models to
do the evaluation and usually how it
works is that pre-trained model let's
say the new like when L 4 comes out or
like when GPT 5 comes out they B
basically mostly show perplexity and
like average over everything and the
fine-tune models they usually tend to
show average over everything and um uh
Arena like performance under Arena like
models uh and the reason why is because
uh models that are pre that are
fine-tuned usually the the log
likelihood that they predict is is not
um yeah it's not calibrated for your for
your data
set so what do I mean by everything um I
would say the two most common uh
benchmarks that basically look at
everything are Helm and hugging face
openm uh leaderboard it's really just a
collection of a lot of different autom
automatically evaluated benchmarks um
and you evaluate across all of them um
so what are some of the common Benchmark
that we use uh one is um yeah measuring
like math performance so GSM 8K that's a
pretty common one that's basically grade
school math mlu uh is multiple choice
question answering on like Math Science
History uh legal bench is is uh is on
the legal aspect then you have Med QA so
this I I believe this is for Helm Med QA
is uh um yeah medical licensing exams so
you basically ask many many different
questions that you can uh automatically
evaluate um and you hope that by taking
averages um it will say like how well
your model performs so that's kind of
like the newer version of super glue I
would say um one data set that I want to
highlight which is probably or one
Benchmark which is probably the most
widely used and the one that people
believe the most is mlu so massively
multitask language understanding um so
this is I I think maybe Archard
mentioned it last week but this is
basically um uh multiple choice uh
questions on 57 different tasks you so
you have tasks like formal logic
conceptual physics econometrics and and
uh these type of tasks so here's an
example um what is true for type 1 a
supernova uh this type occurs in binary
system this type occurs in young
galaxies and you basically have to say
which answer so that seems very simp I
mean the task is not simple but the way
you evaluate seems simple uh and then
like high school biology in a population
of Gira an environmental and then you
this is an example of directional
selection um so that seems simple but
actually it's it's also more complicated
than what you might think
um and I think I will tell
you okay I will tell you about it later
um but that's that's mo one of the most
common probably the most common
Benchmark and what people actually look
at uh for example when Mark Zuckerberg
like said that LMA 3 was out uh he
yeah he talked about MML U scores which
I I find kind of crazy but yeah um other
capabilities that people look at coding
uh coding is a very common one that
people evaluate on um for two different
reasons one because coding uh is usually
if you perform well on code you usually
actually these models perform well on
reasoning um which is actually pretty
cool um so that's like highly correlated
with things that people care about uh
two I mean a lot of us are Cod is so uh
we like to have uh uh better models for
helping us coding and three the other
point is that it's actually pretty easy
to evaluate uh because you can write
test cases so you basically as the model
to generate very long uh uh code or like
functions to to to do something and then
you just run the test and you see
whether it it succeeds or not yes sorry
going back to the prev evaluations some
of them was short answ currently um how
would you validate like short QA type of
thing where it's like multiple choice
makes sense but if it's like short
answer QA how would you say something is
correct as an automatic
met uh think specifically to the
top yeah I actually don't
know huh I actually don't know yeah I
should check sorry um so I don't know
specifically for this one but Hot Pot QA
and beer QA are other QA uh data sets
and then they look at F1 for the true
and false and then they also have an
exact match which is pretty punitive
because like if you say President Reagan
and the answer is like President Ronald
Reagan like will de you but anyway so
they use like an exact M on
that yeah um cool thanks okay Sam you
coding another one that people start
looking at are agents I think shakar is
going to give election on it uh so I'm
not going to talk too much about it but
like one cool thing that LMS can do
right now is basically call apis uh and
then take actions in the real world
essentially or like take control of your
computer um you should not give it
control to your computer uh so a natural
question is like how do you evaluate
these type of things this is a real
challenge um because I mean the biggest
challenge is that if you for example if
I really wanted to to evaluate like how
good it is at coding or like how good it
is at doing things in my terminal I need
to give it access to my terminal and I
really don't want to give my LM access
my terminal um so you really need to
sandbox environments for the specific
cases of terminal I mean it's pretty
easy to sandbox but once you want to do
evaluation of like a model that that I
don't know P people on slack or like
writes things in your emails then you
have to write an entire uh uh sandbox
environment for all the applications
that you want your llms to have access
to uh so this is actually really
complicated and something that people
really have to deal with in in kind of
the real
world uh at least we have to because
right now it's still not in
production okay the last part is uh or
the penultimate one perplexities uh so
one thing which is very uh surprising um
at least the first time you see it is
that really the performance that you
have on um pre-training is extremely
highly correlated uh with basically
performance on any Downstream task um at
least for the current types of LMS so
what I mean by this is that if you just
look at your training performance uh
just predicting the next word it's
extremely highly correlated so this is
the x- axxis which is essentially
perplexities um and the y- AIS which is
just the average over like many
different tasks what you will see is
that tasks that perform well on
your uh on perplexities will actually
have high uh High average scores um and
as a result a lot of people actually end
up when they develop just looking at
perplexities and they just trust it
enough that they don't need to uh do the
downstream evaluations I would not
recommend doing it but if you have to
have something like quick and dirty it
usually works pretty well um one thing
to be careful with though is that the
perplexities are not going to be
comparable across different data sets um
so you really have to be careful with
like what perplexities you're looking at
and two it will depend on the tokenizer
um so if you have like Lama 3 or and and
you compare it to Gemini even um uh yeah
even on the same data set it's going to
give different different scores and it's
not comparable uh yes
uh the the easy answer I mean it's not
the only answer but the easy answer is
that if the vocabulary changes the the
size of the vocabulary changes uh then
clearly the type of um I mean everything
is not on the like the upper bound is
different
sequence uh a sequence like normal yeah
but I'm talking but I'm not talking
about that I'm talking about the fact
that I mean just think about it if you
have a vocabulary size of one oh then I
have to always predict the same thing so
like you you're like the basically your
entropy depends your entropy is uper
bounded by log of like the cardinality
of your vocabulary size so you're going
to depend on
that
cool and the last one is Arena like as I
already told you basically you compare
different models uh you make them fight
essentially against each other and you
have U um ELO ratings at the end so
that's really a more General way of
saying it is I really just let the users
decide uh and that works also pretty
well okay issues and challenging with
issues and challenges with current
evaluations uh first consistency issues
uh if you look at question answering uh
sorry um multiple choice questions um if
you just change so you see on the top
left and top right if you just change
ABCD to like random symbols uh the the
generations that you will give are
actually going to be different and then
the rankings between different models
will be different um so even things that
are very simple like multiple choice
like like selecting out of four choices
uh will be very dependent on exactly
like how you format uh these choices uh
and one real example that's that's what
I was alluding to before is mlu so mlu
seems really simple to evaluate you just
ask it to say like what which one of the
four uh the model prefers um but
actually for a very long time I think
for nearly one year uh there were three
main implementation of mlu and people
were comparing between those three
having no idea that like those three
gave like different scores um and the
reason like the two main differences
were one people use different prompts so
that clearly will give different answers
but two they were using different ways
of sampling to get the the actual to get
the actual like most likely prediction
so one of them for example was saying um
I have the four choices now to get my
most likely uh let's say that the
correct answer is D um I will just look
look at the most likely answers out of
ABCD even though like Z zigot was
another answer that has a higher
likelihood uh I will not look at it
because I will I will basically do
constraint decoding um and if I do
constraint decoding here I will say that
the correct answer is d uh but if I
actually just look at the most likely
token I will not get the correct answer
so like those were two different
implementation and a third different
implementation which uh seems really
different is that instead of generating
the correct uh token which is basically
the letter ABCD you can look
at after this question what is the
likelihood that the answer sorry that
the model would generate this so you
would look at the log likelihood um or
like the perplexity essentially of
predicting this thing log likelihood of
predicting that and that gives very
different answers uh so if you look at
the top right uh you see that Lama 65b
MML on Helm was 63 3.7 and the original
mmu 63.6 but on harness uh which is the
thing that actually hugging face uses is
48.8 so that's like a huge difference
yeah what is Helm harness and original
it matches to these three things there
uh yeah one I can't remember which one
does what but each of them does
something different actually now it's
not true anymore so the middle column
change what they're doing so they start
matching the other two ones uh but at
that time they weren't
uh I'm not sure which one my guess was
would be that they did the the last one
uh but I'm not in
show okay
questions cool another issue
contamination um so here you have harass
he if you don't follow him on Twitter
you should um I and he basically said
that he was looking at um like code
benchmarks and he was saying that pre
pre 2021 uh I can't remember which Mar
or gbt 4 was getting 10 out of 10 on
questions on code Force but after 2021
or like more recent problems it was
getting zero out of 10 which seems very
very uh strange uh so that really
strongly points to the fact that it was
contaminated and was probably the model
was probably pre-trained or like that
data set or the code Force data set was
probably in the pre-training data set
and of course if you I mean essentially
you do you do training on your test set
then you're going to perform really well
um and Suzanne said also to follow also
said something similar for uh F 1.5 um
which is a model from
Microsoft so what is challenging here is
that with' closed models um I mean there
are two things actually that are
challenging one is that those are
pre-trained on so much data that even if
we had access to the data it would be
hard to actually know what they like if
they were pre-trained on your test set
but two those are all close Source
models so you really don't even have
access to a data set so you have no idea
if they were pre-train on that
data um overfitting issues that's also
relatively related uh but could be
slightly different uh so here you see
how much time it took for standard data
sets to achieve uh quot like squary
quotes uh human level performance um and
what you see is that on the recent ones
where you really have this pre-training
in less than like six months uh you
perform at human level performance um we
don't really know if it's because of the
contamination or if it's simply that
like a lot of people are basically
developing and trying to do Hy prar
tuning on these test sets uh we don't
know why but it's clearly an issue with
over
overfitting um so how do you alleviate
that one you can have private test sets
uh so there's a paper from I think two
weeks ago uh that presented GSM 1K which
is the same thing as the GSM 8K that we
saw before which is the the math uh data
set but um tries to reamp basically
regenerate or resample this data set uh
or recollect this data set and then they
look at how well different models um
perform on both the GSM 1K and the GSM
8K and what you see is that at least the
open source models they they perform
much worse on the on a new data set than
on the one that people are able to tune
on um this is not true though for like
cloud and
gp4 another one is Dynam Ben or just
Dynamic test sets uh so ideally every X
number of days you would basically have
new instructions or new inputs to the
models and and your data set would
basically be dynamic that's essentially
also what chatbot Arena does so uh that
definitely
helps um another way of alleviating
contaminators is that you may try to
estimate or like to look at whether the
the models were actually trained on your
on your test set so one very simple way
of doing it which actually works I think
relatively well um is just looking at
the probability of different answers and
you will see that if uh your model is
really sure about a certain answer then
probably was strein on that answer um
another one which which is also really
cool is um looking at the order of your
test set so if your model was uh if a
model was trained or pre-trained on the
test set then most likely it thinks that
example two comes after example one so
if you switch example one and example
two and you see drops in log likelihoods
then most likely the model was actually
pre-trained on that data set
um
cool any questions
here okay so another issue is that I
mean really there's a monoculture of NLP
Benchmark benchmarking what I mean by
this is mostly the fact that we all just
look at English um and this is a paper
from
2021 2022 I think but they look at ACL
2021 which is the probably the the most
common uh um conference in or like yeah
conference in in in NLP and they look at
the best papers so the oral papers and
they saw that out of the 461 papers uh
70% of them only look at English and 40%
of them only look at accuracy so
essentially just performance um so there
are very few papers that look at
multilinguality and like uh even like
efficiency and interpretability or
fairness um and
there's a similar paper from that
analyzes another conference in 2008 and
it was essentially the same finding so
unfortunately it doesn't seem to improve
over
time um the thing is there are actually
a lot of benchmarks for multilinguality
uh I just highlight a few here uh Mega
Global bench extreme uh those have at
least uh 30 40 languages and many many
different tasks um so it's not that we
don't have the benchmarks is that
there's no incentives um unfortunately
in Academia to actually train or like
sorry to um to evaluate on those
benchmarks um so if you have the chance
use those
benchmarks um another issue is that
really we reduce everything to a single
metric so I already told you before the
way we aggregate metrics this is usually
kind of broken in in some of these super
benchmarks but also we only look at
performance and in in in the real world
like we really care about computational
efficiency too we also care about biases
and we care about many other aspects and
like most of these benchmarks don't
consider those um another part is that
we usually average across every example
uh we just say that every example has
the same value essentially the same
weight um so this is definitely unfair
for like minoritized groups but more
than this I think if for example if you
think about like um agents where maybe
one example will be like how well it
performs on um
I don't know writing codee that will
actually be put in production versus
just like
uh like answering your daily question
about like where I don't know where to
buy the best burger um like the value
that you will get out of these examples
are very different and we right now when
we evaluate stuff we don't actually
consider that so that's I think a real a
real issue um and also we basically we
don't take into account that different
people have different
preferences um so a few outs one
considering computational efficiency so
ml puff has a great Benchmark uh where
basically instead of trying to maximize
the performance on a certain Benchmark
they say I want to achieve that
performance in the least amount of time
um so now you basically consider both
like accuracies and like speed either
for training or for for inference uh for
biases uh dis remal is a good data set
from um uh entropic where basically they
they have some templates um and they so
they try to ask questions like uh uh
knowing whether someone should should
keep their insurance or not and they
have templates where they change um like
the race or like the gender of of the in
the template of the person and they see
how the decisions made by the model
would change um and I mean unfortunately
but unsurprisingly uh you will see that
some groups are much more discriminated
than others
uh other biases in our evaluation so I
already told you slightly about the
multilingual issues but honestly this
this issue about English is like much
more prevalent than you would think for
example blur and RK they really assume
that you basically have access to words
like you know how to tokenize and how to
get words so I used to work with uh Tai
and Vietnamese with Vietnamese you have
spaces in between words and T you have
no spaces between words like you have no
idea how to run like blue Rouge like
really these it's much more than just
the data like all all our algorithms are
are really like focused on English or at
least Western languages uh bias uh
biased llm uh based evaluations so one
thing is that I told you about is that
it's really cool because now you can use
essentially gp4 for doing uh uh uh
labeling um but that also means that
given that gp4 is very consistent if it
has some biases then most of essentially
the NLP community will have these um
biases scaled up essentially um so one
Benchmark which tries to look at uh
whose opinions llms reflect uh by
default uh this is actually pretty cool
work that looks at
the uh output distribution of llms on
public opinion surveys so just trying to
understand um whether llms um uh reflect
opinions from from which groups and they
find that at least after
when you only do pre-training uh the
models actually relatively well
uh they are not too optimized to a
single group uh but after so this is in
red but after fine-tuning uh you
basically see that the models really
start being optimized for certain
preferences uh which is unsurprising
because that's how we actually train the
model um and typically these models are
actually uh um mostly show uh uh ref es
from um actually the answer as if they
were from uh I mean white and uh
Southeast Asian so I think the selfie
station is actually pretty interesting I
think it's probably because a lot of
these models were uh the human data that
was used for supervised fine tuning and
for HF was actually labeled by people in
Southeast Asia uh which would explain
why these models have um these type of
views and usually also highly educated
okay so this is the main challenge uh
the challenges of all challenges uh we
saw that there are many challenges in
evaluation in in at least in academic
benchmarking but the biggest one is that
really there's no incentives for us to
move to anything else um and this is uh
actually pretty interesting paper that
looks at uh machine translation between
all the papers of or many papers um from
2019 to 2020 in machine translation and
they found that 82% of papers they only
evaluated blue scores and as we said
like blue scores have many many issues
and if you see like we know that there
are many better uh metrics um but still
people are not incentivized to look at
anything else and actually reviewers
will usually ask you to show uh
performance on Blue scores so it's not
even that your incentivized not to look
at something else or also incentivized
to continue and it kind of makes sense
because you want to be able to compare
to methods from two three years ago go
but it also means that we we it's it's
hard for the academic field um to change
to other benchmarks um but this is
really specific to Academia like in
reality if you know that your metric is
bad just
switch um okay evaluation takeaways uh
so first we I I mentioned that there
were different uh types of evaluation
and different uh desired properties for
different types of evaluation uh then I
talked about close ended tasks um and
how you evaluate those the fact that
it's basically standard machine learning
um but that you have to think carefully
even though it's standard machine
learning of how you evaluate them uh
then there are open-ended tasks uh where
you look at content overlap metrics
typically uh so things like blue uh uh
and Rouge um and Bird score and then you
have chatbot evaluations uh which is
extremely difficult um but uh people
have start has have started doing with
uh using essentially LM based
evaluations um and then we talked about
challenges one of them being consistency
the other one contamination uh and the
third one biases um in reality honestly
the best evaluation is just check your
outputs um so I think too many people
they just believe numbers in reality
like never just believe numbers like I I
remember when we did initially alpaca
like we we kind of believed our alpaka
eval but uh but once we saw playing with
it that's when we were like okay this
thing is actually I mean at that time
good now it's it would be a pretty bad
model but at that time we're like okay
this thing is actually pretty good um we
should do something about it even though
on maybe standard academic benchmarks it
was pretty bad um so yeah don't rely on
numbers and I'm happy to what time is it
to take any other questions uh that you
may
have yes question about so there's this
whole issue of bias which we're trying
which we really trying to deal with but
we're sweeping under the rug here so if
we have a problem in which we're dealing
with a very specialized
domain and yes we try and go and run and
run um reference re vales using like
let's say gbg4 yeah uh sh like is it
considered bad practice to be checking a
subset of these gp4 evals ranking them
as ourselves and then like and
then using and then using
ourself uh like inserting ourself and
and our bias into this process by
actually looking at many many many data
points uh so just to make sure I
understand your question you're saying
that if we try to look ourselves at the
answers we might be incorporating some
biases there yes but we should look at
the answers to make sure that gp4 isn't
being biased when it looks at the
answers there's this tension here and I
don't know what the cuz in a in a
controlled scientific experiment you
would blind yourself to looking at these
answers how do you deal with this yeah
that's a good question I actually don't
quite know but one thing um I actually
feel less concerned about biases of a
single person uh my issue with the gp4
biases is that it's the same across
every model so things really scale up
and kind of uh um it's really it becomes
a monoculture and I think that that I
think that's less that's much worse than
if everyone incorporates a little bit of
the biases that they have in their
Direction I'm not saying that that's the
the best answer but I think it's
slightly better than than just going
with whatever they have yeah how does
one following up on that how does avoid
a situation if we're like one is trying
to solve a problem with a model yeah uh
and uh one evaluates it with GPT chat
gp4 yeah uh and then one starts to to
like look at it and say okay is this is
this good and stuff and then one goes
okay this is great and everyone else in
the world and GT4 thinks it's a terrible
terrible model and it's just someone
being and it's just some academic being
like uh like pressuring themsel into
publishing something that doesn't
actually work how do you how does the
field structurally avoid situations like
that um well I I think that's one reason
why they want standardized benchmarks
and why all every reviewer actually
wants standardized benchmarks because
because at least even though everyone
knows that they're wrong they understand
how they are wrong um so I think that's
like one perspective another thing which
is not doesn't completely answer your
question but but um I think could be a
potential solution um is that how I view
gp4 is just something that is really
good at performing what I want it to
perform uh right now the thing is I I
not very specific about what I wanted to
perform um and as a result it will it
will basically come in with its own biy
that that come from its pre-training
data or or fine tring data um a
potentially better way of doing it is
that I could write exactly what I want
so right now when we say when we do the
the prompting to gp4 I basically ask a
question simple question like how good
is the summary uh out of five uh but a
much better way would probably be
writing a very detailed rubric of
everything that has to be uh in this
answer for it to be a good answer and if
you think about it this is exactly what
like professors do uh when they evaluate
for class like they
basically say Okay Yan is a TA but I
cannot trust him per like blindly so
what I will do is that I will write a
very detailed rubric and I trust that he
can apply that rubric and I think that's
also how we should be thinking about gp4
and this is not how we currently do
it any other questions