Welcome to the fifth iteration of our
CS25 transformers class. Um so Dave and
I kind of started this class a long time
ago. Um after seeing you know how
transformers and machine learning in
general um and AI became such a
prevalent thing and how we predicted how
it would become an even bigger part of
our lives going forward which does seem
to be the case. Um so as large language
models and AI in general takes over the
world um whether it's through things
like chatbt or image generation models
like Sora um video generation models
like Sora um and so forth um we felt
that you know having a class where
people are able to sort of come and
learn about transformers how they work
and especially hear from leading experts
in industry and academia working on
state-of-the-art research in this area
um how that would be very beneficial to
um everybody's learning and um help us
progress um further um within AI and
technology in general. Um so yeah, so
welcome to our class. Um so how our
class works is typically each week we
invite um a leading researcher from
either industry or academia to come
speak about some state-of-the-art topic
they're working on um in transformers.
Um so we have an exciting lineup of
speakers um prepared for you guys this
quarter. And so this first lecture will
be delivered by us where we'll sort of
go through the basics of transformers.
And then we sort of divided this lecture
um a bit differently from the previous
lectures in that we kind of have um a
section on pre-training and data um
strategies and then a section focused
more on post-training which has become a
very popular um topic these days. We'll
also touch briefly on some applications
um of transformers and some remaining
sort of um weaknesses or challenges that
we should hopefully address to be able
to further improve um the state of AI
and our machine learning models. Um so
yeah, I forgot I have control. Yeah. So
we'll start with some um instructor um
introductions. So we have a very um a
good team of um
co-instructors. Um so my name is
Stephen. Um I'm a current thirdyear CS
PhD here. Um previously did my undergrad
at Waterlue in Canada. Um I've done some
research in industry as well at um
Amazon and Nvidia. And in general my
research sort of focuses hovers around
natural language processing. So machine
learning for language and text. Um
looking at things like can we improve
the controllability and reasoning models
of large language models. Um and more
recently cognitive science and
psychology inspired work especially
bridging the gap the data gap and the
learning efficiencies between um machine
learning models and how the humans learn
how human children learn and how our
brains are able to learn so efficiently.
Um also done some work with multimodal
um as well as computer vision. So things
like dusion models and image generation.
And just for fun I also run the piano
club here with Kuran. Um and we have an
upcoming concert on April 11th in case
you guys are interested.
Uh hi everyone. Uh I'm Curran, a second
year electrical engineering PhD student.
Uh I did my undergrad at Calpaly San
Louis a Bispo after which I was a
research scientist here. Um now doing my
PhD. I'm a little bit more on the
medical imaging and computer vision
side. So a lot of my current work uh is
at the intersection of computer vision
and neuroscience. Uh working with things
like fMRI and ultrasound. uh and I
currently work at the uh SCAI lab uh a
new lab under Dr. Assant Adelli.
Hi everyone, I'm Chelsea. Um I'm a first
year master student in symbolic systems.
Um and my general research interests are
in multi-agentic frameworks um
self-improving AI agents and overall
just kind of improving like the
interpretability and explanability of
models. Um, so previously I studied
applied math and neuroscience and I did
a bunch of like interdisciplinary
research in computer vision, robotics,
uh, cognitive science, things of that
sort. Um, and currently I'm working
part-time at a VC firm and over the
summer I'll be interning at a
conversational AI startup as a machine
learning engineer. Um, so I'm very
interested in exploring the startup
scene here at Stanford. So feel free to
reach out.
Hi everyone, I'm Jenny. I'm a current
student u majoring in Simsus as well as
a sociology co-term here at Stanford. My
background is primarily in technology
ethics and policy. So if you have any
questions or want to talk about that,
I'd love to have a conversation. Um in
the past I've worked um doing product at
DE Shaw and also research in the tech
ethics and policy space. And this summer
I'll be working at Daydream which is an
AI um fashion tech startup in New York.
And
so yeah, so Div was unable to join us
today. Um but he's working on his new um
agent startup called AGI Inc. Um
currently on leave um from a CSP PhD
here. Um he's passionate about you know
robotics, AI agents and so forth. And
later this quarter um he'll likely be
giving a lecture actually on everything
to do with AI agents. So if you're
interested in that um definitely look
forwards to it. Um and previously you
know he's worked at Nvidia, Google and
so forth. um and he's the one who sort
of, you know, started um um this class
in the first place. So, all right. So,
um I'll go over some of the course
logistics. So, first announcement is we
have a new website up. Um that's just
cs25.stanford.edu. And so, all of our
updates and as well as the speaker
lineup will be posted there in the
coming weeks. Um that will also be the
link to share our Zoom with people who
are not Stanford affiliated or are on
the wait list or have not been able to
gain admission into the class. So we
encourage everyone to share this class
with their network and um ensure that
anyone can access it from Zoom. Yeah. So
some takeaways from the course include a
better understanding of transformers and
the underlying architecture of many of
our large language models. Um guest
speakers which will be talking about
applications in language, vision,
biology, robotics and more. Exposure to
new research especially from leading
researchers all across the country. um
innovative methods that are driving the
next generation of models as well as key
limitations, open problems and the
future of
AI. Believe this
is okay. Uh next I'll give a really
brief intro about transformers and how
attention
works. So the first step um for language
is word embeddings. So words aren't
numbers. So we obviously can't just pass
them into a model as is. So the first
step is converting them into dense
vectors in a highdimensional space. Uh
this is done through various methods but
the goal is to capture semantic
similarity. Uh essentially that cat and
dog are more similar than cat and car
even though the latter uh is more
similar from a character standpoint.
Doing so enables uh visualization
learning with transformer models or uh
arithmetic like I've shown like king
minus man plus queen would approximately
be queen in some embedding space and
classical methods for this are like word
ofve fast text um and many more these
days but uh static embeddings for
instance um giving the word bank the
same meaning in just bank as in
riverbank uh have limitations.
Therefore, uh the current standard is
using contextual embeddings which take
into account um the context and the
sentence that a word is
in. Self attention um can be applied to
this to learn what to focus on for a
given token.
So to do this, you learn three matrices,
a query, key and value uh which together
comprise the attention process. A quick
analogy for this is imagine you're in a
library looking for a book on a certain
topic. This would be your
query. Now, uh let's say each book has
some summary associated with with it. Um
a key. You can match your query and key
um and get access to the book that
you're looking for. The information
inside the book would be your value. So
in attention, we do a soft match over
the values to get info from say multiple
books. And this comprises the attention
operation.
And uh as you can see in this
visualization when you apply this to
language you can see that across
different layers of the model uh
different words um have connections to
the rest of the words in the
sentence. The next component is
positional uh encodings or embeddings
which add order to the sequence. Uh
without these the model uh since you
have just uh linear multiplications here
would not know what the first or the
last word in the sentence is. Therefore,
you add some notion um of order through
say sinosoids or in the simplest form
you could think that the first word
would be a zero, the second one a one
and
on. Beyond this uh is basically just
scaling uh through multiple layers and
multi head attention. Uh more heads to
attend to different parts of the
sentence and more parameters means that
you can capture more diverse
relationships uh from your sequences and
this gives you the final transformer.
Transformers today uh have overtaken
pretty much every field from LLMs like
GPT4, 03, DeepS uh to vision with models
that are getting increasingly better at
segmentation and whatnot. Uh speech,
biology, video. Um you'll see a lot of
these applications
uh throughout the quarter. Uh with large
language models, uh these are
essentially just scaled up versions of
attention and the transformer
architecture. um you essentially just
throw a large amount of data uh general
text data derived from the web uh at
these models and they can learn very
well to model uh through a next token
prediction objective uh
language and as you scale up uh we've
seen that emergent abilities pop up. So
while at a smaller scale you might not
be able to do a certain task um once you
get to a certain scale you just have a
peak uh in the ability to do that task.
Some disadvantages though are that these
models have very high computational
costs and therefore also concerns like
uh with climate and the carbon emissions
they may
produce and um like I was mentioning
with larger models um they're very good
at generalizing to many uh abilities or
tasks and they're essentially
plug-andplay with fewer zeroot learning.
All right. So now I'll talk a bit more
about pre-training. So as Karan
explained how the transformer works, but
typically with a language model,
especially a large language model, um
you typically divide it into two stages.
Pre-training stage where you sort of
train the neural network from scratch
from randomized or initialized weights
um randomly initialized weights um to
give a more general capabilities. Um and
a big portion of this is the data
itself. So the data is sort of the
fundamental fuel that sort of allows
your model to learn because that's what
the model is learning from, right? Um so
your goal typically again like I said
with pre-training is to train on a large
amount of data to obtain some sort of
general level of capabilities and
overall knowledge or intelligence. Um
and this is arguably again the most
important aspect of training especially
pre-training. um especially because LLMs
learn again based on statistical
distributions predicting the next token
um given previous tokens. Um so to
effectively learn this you typically
need a large amount of data. Um so
because of its importance you know how
do we maximally leverage it? So again um
smart dating um smart data strategies
for um pre-training is definitely one of
the most important topics um these days.
Um so I'll briefly touch upon two of the
top uh projects I recently worked on um
on two different scales. The first is
looking at you know what makes small
childlike data sets potentially
effective for language learning
especially on the smaller scale and the
second is looking at um smart data
strategies for training um large models
on trillion on billions or trillions of
tokens which is on the much larger
scale. Um so sort of um why are humans
able to learn so efficiently? Right?
This kind of looks at you know like how
human children learn and interact with
the environment and learn language
compared to a model like KGBT which is a
bit analogous to you know how the human
brain learns language and learns in
general compared to something like a
neuronet network. Um so some potential
key differences are that humans learn
continuously. We're continually
learning. We don't just you know
pre-train. we don't just sit in a chair,
have someone read a whole internet to us
and then we kind of just stop learning
from there. Um so that's unlike a lot of
current models which are more single
pass um pre-training models. Um further
we have more go- based um approaches to
learning and interaction with the
environment. That's a major reason we
learn um whereas again these models are
typically just pre-training on large
amounts of data using next token
prediction or auto regression. Um
further we learn through continuous
multimodal or multiensory data. So it's
not just text only. We're subconsciously
exposed to you know probably hundreds of
senses that sort of guide our the way we
learn and sort of approach our daily
lives. Um further I believe our brains
are fundamentally different in that we
learn probably in more structured or
hierarchical manners for example through
compositionality rather than against
simply next token prediction. Um and the
focus of this project in particular is
more on the data differences. So again
humans are exposed to you know um
dialogue from people we talk to um story
books um especially children up um
compared to you know large amounts of
data um on the
internet. Um so this is a work that was
published um so why why do we care about
small models and training on small
amounts of data? Well this will greatly
improve the efficiency of training and
using large language models and this
will open the door to potential new use
cases. for example, um models that can
run on your phone that you can run
locally and so forth for many different
use cases. Um smaller models and train
on less data are also more interpretable
and easier to sort of control or align
um whether it's for safety purposes to
reduce bias and so forth um to ensure
you know people are using them um um for
safe reasons and you have appropriate
guardrails in place. Um this will also
enhance the open source availability um
allowing research and the usage of these
models for more people around the world
rather than simply companies with large
amounts of compute. Um and in general
this might even allow us to more greatly
understand the other direction which is
how humans are able to learn so
effectively and
efficiently. Yep. So this work is titled
is child directed speech effective
training data for language models? um
which I presented at um EMNLP in Miami
um last November. Um so again the sort
of hypothesis here is that children you
know we sort of probably learn
fundamentally different from LLMs. This
is why we're able to learn on several
magnitudes less language data in
particular um than many of these large
language models these days which require
trillions of tokens. Now there's several
hypotheses. One is the data we receive
as humans is different um fundamentally
from LLMs, right? rather than just
training on internet data, you know, we
actually interact with people. We talk
to people um we hear stories um that our
parents or teachers tell us and so
forth. The other is maybe um the human
brain just fundamentally learns
different. So our learning algorithm is
just different from um large language
models. And another is maybe it's the
way or the structure in in which we
receive this data. So any any data we
receive is somewhat curricularized. Um
we start off with simple data, simple
language as a child and then you know
learn more complex grammarss, we hear
more complex um speech from our parents,
um co-workers and so forth. Um anything
we do whether it's learning math you
know we start simple and then you know
move on to more difficult problems.
Whereas language models you typically
don't care too much about ordering or
curriculum. Um so there's multiple
different hypotheses here. Um so in
order to test some of these what we did
is we trained some small GPD2 and Robera
models on five different data sets. Um
one is child which is a natural um
conversation data with children. So this
is transcribed. Um and then we collected
a synthetic version called tiny
dialogues which I'll discuss some more
later. Um baby LM which is a diverse
mixture of different types of data. This
includes Reddit data, Wikipedia data and
so forth. So this is closer to your
typical um large language model
pre-training data. And then we also did
a bit of testing with um Wikipedia as
well as open subtitles. So movie and TV
transcriptions. So we collected um tiny
dialogues and this was inspired by the
fact that you know a lot of again I said
our learning as children is through um
conversations with other people and
conversations naturally lead to learning
right we talk to someone they give us
feedback we reflect on how the
conversation went. So it's both pure and
self-reflection. Um furthermore,
conversations lead to not only learning
of knowledge but other things like
ethics and morals. For example, parents
or teachers, you know, telling us as
children, you know, um what's right or
wrong to do. And there's many different
types of conversations you can have with
many different types of people um
leading to a lot of diversity and
learning. So, what we did is we
collected a fully grammatical and
curricularized um conversation data set
with a limited childlike restricted
vocabulary using GPD4. Um and we
collected different examples that differ
from differ by child age um the
different participants in the
conversation um and so forth. And here's
just some examples of um um some um data
points in our collected data set. So you
see as the age goes up, you know, the um
utterances or conversations become more
complex, they become longer, the
participants also um differ um by age
appropriately. So we also ran an
experiment a curriculum experiment where
we ordered either by um ascending age
order, you know, so um the model will
first see two-year-old conversations and
then 5-year-old conversations and then
10-year-old and so forth versus um
descending order. Maybe it's possible a
language model might actually learn
somehow better from more complex
examples first and then of course the
typical baseline of randomly shuffling
all your data examples. So we have some
basic evaluation metrics um targeted at
fundamental capabilities. One is um
basic grammatical and syntactic
knowledge and there's another is um a
free word association metric um called
word similarity for um assessing more
semantic knowledge. So you see here from
the different data sets that actually it
seems like training on childlike data is
worse than a heterogeneous mixture of
just internet data like baby LM. Um so
both metrics degrade um quite
substantially especially on child um the
more natural um um conversation data set
um between children and their
caregivers. And you'll see in terms of
curriculum um you we don't see many
substantial differences um no matter
what order you sort of um provide the
examples in to the model which is again
surprising because as humans you know we
sort of go from simple to more
difficult. Um so looking more closely at
sort of convergence behavior or loss
curves um you'll see here that the
training loss um the training loss sorts
sort of um has these sorts of um a
cyclical pattern um depending on the
sort of buckets you use for curriculum
but the validation loss which is what
you really care about. So the
generalization and learning um it has
the exact same trend no matter what
order um you feed the examples in which
is again a very interesting sort of um
finding. So overall we see that diverse
data sources like baby LM seem to
provide a better learning signal um for
our language models than purely child
directed speech. Um we do see however
that our tiny dialogues data set
noticeably outperforms the natural
conversation data set likely because
that data set is um very noisy whereas
ours is again synthetically collected by
GP4 and um again global developmental
ordering using curriculum learning seems
to have negligible impact on
performance. So overall we can kind of
sort of conclude that it's possible that
other aspects of children's learning not
simply the data they're exposed to are
responsible for their efficient language
learning. For example, learning from
other types of information like
multimodal information or it's the fact
that our learning algorithm in our brain
is just fundamentally different and more
data efficient um than language modeling
techniques. Um so if you wish to learn
more um we have our data sets um
released um on hugging face as well as
um GitHub um and the paper is up on
archive as
well. So now let's go bigger scale. So
we were investigating you know small
models trained on small amounts of data
similar to a human child. Now what about
current large models billions of
parameters trained on trillions of
tokens. Um so I recently um during my
last summer internship I worked on a
project with Nvidia titled maximize your
data's potential um enhancing LLM
accuracy with two-phase pre-training. So
this is to sort of optimize data
selection as well as um training
strategies and large scale pre-training.
Um so a lot of works like llama
highlight the effectiveness of you know
different sorts of data mixtures um but
they don't really um shed light into the
exact mixtures and how these decisions
were made um whereas we know you know
data blending and ordering is crucial to
um effective LLM pre-training. So can we
shed more light on this which is what
our work does. So firstly, we sort of
formalize and systematically evaluate
this concept of two-phase pre-training
um and we show that empirically it
improves over continuous training um
which is typically what's done with LLM
training and you just feed in all the
data rather than separating it into you
know particular um buckets or um a
different schedule. We also do a fine
grid analysis of data blending for these
two um pre-training phases. Um, and we
sort of have this notion of prototyping
blends on smaller token counts before
scaling up. So this two-phase
pre-training approach, it's sort of
inspired kind of, you know, by how
pre-training and post- training works,
which is the first phase is on more
general data. Um, so this is to learn
more broadly. Um, so it's on more
diverse data and the second is to shift
to more high quality domain specific
data such as math and so forth. However,
it's important to sort of balance
between quality and diversity in both
phases as if you upweight any data set
too much um it can lead to
overfitting. Um so firstly does phase
two-phase training actually help. So we
found that you know all our our phase 2
blends or our phase two um our two-phase
pre-training experiments outperform the
baseline of simply just um continuing
training on a single phase. And this is
um noticeably better than just a
randomized mixture of both phases as
well as um the natural data distribution
compared to our sort of upsample data
distribution for phase 2. Um and we also
showed that this is able to scale um
both on model scale and data scale. So
if you blow up the token counts as well
as the model size um we show that
performance um further improves with our
two-phase pre-training compared to a
single phase. Um so this kind of
highlights also the effectiveness of
prototyping um on um smaller data blends
before um scaling up. Um and
furthermore, we investigated sort of the
phase the duration of phase two, right?
Um so, you know, should we um train on
diverse data for a little bit and
immediately switch to you know, highly
specialized data like math or should we
wait longer? And what we found is
performance improves up to a point
around 40%. Until there's diminishing
returns likely from overfitting because
specialized data, you know, it's more
specialized, it's more um there's
typically a lower number of it and it's
less diverse um compared to things like,
you know, web crawl data. So um too much
of it can lead to um detrimental um or
diminishing returns. So overall we see a
well ststructured uh two-phase
pre-training approach with careful data
selection and management is essential
for optimizing LLM performance while
maintaining scalability and robustness
um across different downstream tasks.
And in case you're interested um this
paper um is also preprint is up um on
archive.
So overall I guess the overall takeaway
from these two projects and what I
wanted to get at is like um the fact
that data um effectiveness especially
for pre-training it's not just the
amount of data but it's about you know
the quality of a data the ordering and
structure of data and how exactly you
use it. Um so for our first project we
saw there's negligible impact of global
order in smallcale training. Um but we
saw that phase-based training for larger
scales is highly effective and in
general smart data decisions are
essential for models to generalize
across tasks. So sort of um takeaway is
our research underscores that effective
language modeling isn't just about
amassing data but about smarter data
organization that harnesses its
structure, quality and characteristics.
And by continuing to sort of refine
datacentric approaches, the future of LM
training promises smarter, more
efficient um and highly adaptable
models. Um so now we'll be moving to
sort of the second stage after post
pre-training which is post- training um
which Chelsea will talk about. All
right. So, we have a pre-trained model.
Um, now what like how do we adapt to
specific tasks and different domains?
Um, so some major strategies include
fine-tuning for instance like
reinforcement learning with human
feedback. Um, or some prompt based
methods or some sort of like rag
architecture and retrievalbased methods.
Um so one major approach is called chain
of thought reasoning. Um I'm sure you
all have heard of it by now. Um so it's
essentially a prompting technique to
think step by step. Um so it shows the
intermediate steps uh provide guidance
and this is sort of similar to the way
how humans think. Um we can imagine that
we typically break down uh a problem
into subsequent steps to help us better
understand the problem itself. Um and
another benefit of chain of thought is
that it allows some sort of
interpretable um window into the
behavior of the model. Um and this can
kind of suggest that there is more
knowledge embedded in the model's
weights um than just prompting a
response.
Um so this here is an example of chain
of thought. Um on the left we have it
solve um a problem in like a oneshot
manner which turns out to get to the
wrong answer. Um and on the right over
there uh it produces a sequence of
reasoning chains and ultimately it
arrives at the correct answer.
So naturally this brings up an extension
of chain of thought which is called a
tree of thought. And this is another
prompting technique but instead of
producing a singular reasoning path as a
chain of thought does it um considers
multiple reasoning trajectories um and
then uses some sort of self-evaluation
process to kind of um decide on the
final outputs such as like majority
voting. Um so in the picture you can see
that tree of thought kind of generates
like different reasoning paths and
selects the best one at the
end. Um so another way is through
program of thought and this basically
generates code as the intermediate
reasoning steps. Um and overall what
this does is that it offloads some sort
of um problem solving technique to some
code interpreter um to some code
interpreter. So it formalizes language
into programs to arrive at more precise
answers. Um so we have seen that this
sort of problem
decomposition seems helpful for
different tasks. Um so one way is
through Socratic questioning which is
basically using a self-questing module
to propose sub problems related to the
original and solves those in like a
recursive sort of manner. Um so for
instance um if the question is like what
fills the balloons um this kind of leads
to the next sub question which is like
what can make a balloon float and then
by decomposing the original problem into
like subsequent problems um it can
better solve um at the
end. Um so finally another problem
decomposition method is through
computational graphs. Um so this
basically formulates compositional tasks
as a computation graphs um by breaking
down the reasoning into different um
subprocedures um and nodes. So the key
takeaway here is that transformers can
solve compositional tasks by reducing
reasoning into subgraphs. Um and this is
like without developing some sort of
systematic problem solving skill. Right?
So Chelsea sort of touched on chain of
thought and everything that sort of
expands upon it or improves it and
that's sort of mainly a prompting based
method um for inference time. Um next
I'll be talking more at reinforcement
learning and feedback mechanisms which
are typically used for things like um
further fine-tuning um a pre-trained
model. Um so the most popular is this
thing called reinforcement learning with
human feedback or RLHF. So this trains a
reward model directly from human
feedback. So what you sort of do is you
take your pre-trained model, get it to
generate several responses and then you
typically take a pair pair of responses
and have humans sort of rate which one
they prefer and you can sort of train a
reward model um based on this basically
being using a reinforcement learning um
optimization algorithm such as PO.
Um now there's an improvement to PBO
called DPO or direct preference
optimization. So this sort of more
directly trains the model to prefer
outputs that humans rank higher compared
to having a separate reward model which
is much more efficient. Um so basically
it um actually get um sort of you can
think of it as it sort of more closely
ties the reward directly into the loss
function itself um by um helping the LLM
to maximize the likelihood of generating
preferred responses um and minimize the
likelihood of the responses that the
humans um did not
prefer. Um, and there's a sort of
extension to RLHF, which is called RL
Aif. So, this is simply replacing the
human with an AI. Um, so you typically
have a pretty good um, LLM that's able
to provide accurate preference judgments
of which response it prefers. Um, and
this is less costly basically um,
compared to human annotators. And then
you basically you do the same thing. You
train a reward model based on um, the
LLM's um, preferences instead. And they
found that actually human evaluators um
found that RL Aif tuned outputs were
around um similar to RLHF showing that
you know this is a more scalable and
costefficient um approach compared to
human feedback. But there's one sort of
disadvantage here which is it really
depends on the capabilities or the sort
of accuracy of judgments of the LLM
you're using to provide your um
preferences. Um so if you're using one
that is um sort of incapable um or very
noisy then that's going to hurt um your
post training. Um the next is this thing
sort of um very hot now which was um
used in deepseek um both their R1 as
well as some other models like their
math ones. Um so this is called group
relative policy optimization or GRPO. So
this is a variant of the PO optimization
algorithm but rather than ranking um
simply pairs of responses it actually um
ranks response um a group of responses
in a different order. So this provides
richer feedback which is more fine grain
and is much more sort of efficient
compared to simply um ranking pairs of
outputs. Um so this helps stabilize
training um which is one reason deepseek
is um very much more data and compute um
efficient. Um it also um um they saw
that it improves um even things like LLM
reasoning especially on things like
math. Um there's also been other
variations of you know RLHF and so
forth. One is this thing called conmani
optimization. Not sure if I'm
pronouncing that correctly um but KTO.
So this modifies the standard loss
function typically used um in post-
training things um to account for human
biases such as loss aversion. So as
humans, you know, we typically we care
more about minimizing disastrous or
negative outcomes than achieving
positive ones. We're more risk averse in
the most case, although it's very um
dependent on the person, right? So they
encourage the AI to sort of behave in a
similar manner by avoiding negative
outcomes. Um and this this basically
adjust the training process to reflect
this and they showed that this is able
to sort of improve performance um on
different tasks. um although it kind of
depends on the task but overall it shows
more sort of humanlike behavior um on
particular tasks. Um and these are just
um a subset of this sort of RLHF and
sort of reinforcement learning and
feedback based
um algorithms. Uh one one I want to
touch upon um before I finish off is
this thing called personalizing RLHF
with the variational preference
learning. Um so the authors sort of saw
that different demographics you know
have different preferences. So typical
RLHF um sort of averages everything
together. Um so what the authors do is
they introduce a latent variable for
every user preference profile for
example different demographic like
children, adults um and so forth. Um and
trains reward models conditioned on
these sort of latent um vectors or
factors. Um so this leads to something
they call pluralistic alignment which is
improving the reward accuracy for these
particular demographics or subgroups.
So, it enables a single model to sort of
adapt its behavior to different
preferences, preference profiles, and
different demographics um or groups of
people. Um and now I'll hand it back to
Chelsea to talk about, you know,
self-improving.
All right. Um so, yeah, let's talk a
little bit about uh self-improving AI
agents. Um so, what exactly is an AI
agent? Um so it's essentially a system
that perceives the environment uh makes
decisions and takes actions um towards
achieving some sort of specific goal. Um
and usually the this goal is given by
the human um so for instance like game
playing task solving or like research
assistance. Um and there's several
components of an AI agent. So one it's
goal directed um two it can make its own
sort of decisions. Um, three, it can act
iteratively. Um, four, there's usually
some sort of memory component to it and
like state tracking component to it. Um,
and finally, there's um some agents that
can use some tools such as like API
calls or like function calling. Um, and
finally, it can learn and adapt on its
own.
Um, okay. Yeah. So self-improvement um
basically models can reflect on their
own outputs um leading leading to
iterative improvements um over time. So
this typically consists of several
steps. Um there's you know some sort of
reflection of its own internal states.
Um there's an explanation of its own
reasoning process. Um it can evaluate
the quality of its own outputs. And
finally, it can also simulate u
multi-step reasoning
chains. Um so one technique is um
refinement. So this is where um you have
some sort of iterative prompting
technique where an LLM critiques um and
improves its own outputs. Um so it
generates some sort of initial response
and then refineses it over time. Um and
this kind of uses uh feedback loops to
sort of enhance the overall performance.
Um so an example would be like um it
generates some answer and then it
evaluates itself for weaknesses and
inconsistencies and finally it refineses
the response um based on the own
self-critique
method. Another technique is called uh
self-reflection. So this is where a
model learns from past mistakes and
adjusts future responses based on past
failures. Um so there usually is some
sort of like long-term memory component
to this. Um and an example would be like
the model first detects some sort of
like weak response from its own outputs.
Um and then it kind of reflects on its
own mistakes and generates um some sort
of improved answer to it. and over
multiple iterations um accuracy and
reasoning should improve over
time. Another technique is called react
which is essentially just combining
reasoning with um external actions such
as you know API calls or like
retrievalss from a database. Um and this
is basically some model that can
interact dynamically with its
environment. Um so it gets feedback from
taking multiple action sequences um and
kind of incorporating that into its
outputs. Um so for instance the model
will generate a reasoning plan um and
then it will call some sort of external
tool um such as like web search or some
API call and then this model
incorporates the retrieved data into its
final
response. And finally, this leads us to
um a framework called language agent
tree research. Um so basically what lats
is is that it extends the react
framework to incorporate multiple
planning pathways. So you can kind of
think this like analogous to chain of
thought versus tree of thought. Um it
kind of gathers feedback from every path
to improve the future search process
which is kind of like some sort of
verbal reinforcement learning inspired
technique. Um and it uses Monte Carlo
tree search to optimize uh planning
trajectories where um in the tree
structure every node represents a state
and every edge represents um an action
that the agent can take. Um so an
example would be like it generates n
best new action sequences and then it
will just execute them all in parallel.
Um then it will use some sort of like
self-reflection technique um to score
each one and then overall just continue
exploring um from the best state and
update the probabilities of the past
node and yeah
all right um next I'll be talking about
a few other applications of transformers
outside of language uh I'll start with
vision transformers uh which have taken
vision by storm.
Theology here um is that so as I talked
about transformers take in sequences
right but images aren't sequences
however um what the authors of the VIT
paper came up with was to split an image
up into patches um which can then be
embedded to form a sequence. um passing
this through a simple transformer
yielded very good results um for
instance on classification uh just by
adding an MLP head to the
end. You might ask uh why apply
transformers to this problem uh when
CNN's are such a mainstay in the field.
Um the main reason is that when you have
a very large data set uh say in the tens
of millions of examples transformers
bring in less inductive biases. uh CNN's
assume locality and that pixels are
grouped together. Whereas with
transformers and treating your images as
sequences, you can see better results
when you have enough data to train
them. One um common architecture that
was impacted by this was clip uh which
uses vits for its image encoders. Um
this is the basis of models like GPT40
or other vision language models. uh and
essentially works through contrastive
learning. So you take a data set of
paired images and text pairs um and you
train your model to align the encoded
representations of both. So if you have
a image of a cat and a uh and the word
cat, then you can learn to align those
embeddings. And like I mentioned, uh
these have been applied to vision
language models like GPT4 or 40. Um the
way these are trained is you concatenate
your encoded image and text and you can
train in different stages um such that
your model learns to take both uh and to
account for its responses and these have
done very uh well on benchmarks and
tasks uh for instance like test
questions like I've shown here.
Next uh I'll talk about a bit of my work
in neuroscience which applies VITS to um
other kinds of
data. So a main stay in my field is
functional magnetic res resonance
imaging or fMRI. Uh essentially this
captures the amount of oxygen that each
voxal part of your brain is using at a
given point. Um and this provides a very
detailed proxy for the activity going on
in your brain. Uh it can be used to
diagnose diseases. um and capture
various amounts of data um for better
cognitive
understanding. However, this is very
highdimensional. Uh you might have like
a million or so voxels or 100 thousand
in the brain. So, the first step to
using this data uh with transformer
models is usually averaging uh across
like well-known regions or just grouping
together voxels. And this gives you a
more tractable um computationally
tractable number of parcels that you can
train on.
A traditional tool uh in this field was
just to use linear pair-wise correlation
maps and just these were enough to get
pretty good diagnoses of things like
Parkinson's. However, uh with the advent
of tons of computer vision techniques,
uh we can apply larger and more
sophisticated models to these tasks.
One cool uh large body of work uh in
this area is divvying up the brain into
different functional networks. So let's
say like your vision system um or your
daydreaming network or control
etc. And uh I'll get into how we use
this uh to sort of guide our
work. So like I mentioned early ML
models just took like linear correlation
maps so making lots of assumptions about
the data uh and just applied typical
like neural networks to the task for
regression or classification tasks or in
some cases graph-based analyses to try
to get a deeper understanding of how the
brain uh different parts of the brain
interact with each
other. With computer vision, we can take
our raw data and just throw that at a
transformer model and that does very
well uh as a pre-training objective. So
what we do is uh let's say we have some
number of ROIs across time. We can just
mask out uh some portion of that data,
pass the rest of the data through a
transformer model and have it predict
this portion. You repeat this across a
large data set and uh all of your ROIs.
And this provides a very good
self-supervised training objective uh
for this task. So self-supervised
essentially means that there is no
paired labeled uh data here. We're
essentially just using our raw data and
posing our objective such that we can
learn directly off of it.
Once you've trained uh this sort of
model um you have these dense
representations inside the model that
can be applied downstream to various
tasks like predicting patient attributes
uh or the risk of disease and you can
also look at the weights that your model
has learned um
to do analyses of brain
networks. So um in brief our approach
essentially consists of taking the
activity in the entire brain
partitioning out some small region let's
say it's your vision
system you pass the unmasked portion
into a transformer model which learns to
predict the mass portion and you can
compare this to your ground truth to
provide uh your training
objective. One key thing we use here is
cross attention. So what we talked about
before with language was self attention
wherein you're attending um to the
current sequence you're looking at in
cross attention you have two different
sequences let's say in machine
translation you have one in English and
in French uh and essentially you apply
attention between the two sequences uh
instead of just on a single
sequence. So our our most basic
architecture takes advantage of this
through just a singular cross attention
decoder. Uh having a very small model uh
makes for better interpretability and
like I mentioned this model just learns
to predict masked brain regions from
unmasked ones. Uh once we've done this
we can analyze again the attention
weights um to gain a deeper
understanding of networks and also apply
this to downstream tasks.
So some modeling results here I've
plotted like the brain activity from
different patients and you can see that
the model uh does pretty well in
matching the ground truth for uh two
networks that I've shown here uh the
salience network which is involved in
like uh your senses and decision- making
and the default mode network or DMN
which uh is responsible for like
daydreaming or just recapitulating uh
your brain information when you're not
doing a certain task.
On the bottom we have the attention
weights um for this model which I've
split up by all of the other networks.
So for instance on the left when
predicting the salience network uh we
can see from our model that it is
heavily dependent on the default mode
and control networks. So this gives us a
better understanding of how different
brain networks are connected uh to each
other or how they might share
information inside the brain.
For other networks though uh like vision
these are more singular we can't predict
them very well or subcortical regions
say those involved in like memory we
also cannot predict very
well so this is all well well and cool
we can predict brain activity uh but
what can we do with this model um if we
simply replace uh one component of the
model with a learnable token uh which
corresponds to predicting Parkinson's
disease then we can use this model um to
again predict that um ailment. So if you
look on the right after some finetuning
on a labeled data set we can see uh some
clustering in the model's
embedding which corresponds to um
getting close to 70% accuracy in
predicting this disease uh which is much
higher than um using like the
correlation based methods or linear
assumptions I talked about earlier.
All right. So now that we have some
background on these transformer models
and a couple of their applications,
let's talk about the future and what's
next. So overall, these transformer
models can enable a lot more
applications across every industry and
sector. This includes generalist agents
as well as longer video understanding
and generation across the finance and
business sector. domain specific
foundation models like for example one
could imagine a doctor GPT or a lawyer
GPT or an insert field GPT as well as
potential real world impacts like
personalized education and tutoring
systems advanced healthcare diagnostics
environmental monitoring and protection
real-time multilingual communication as
well as an interactive environment and
gaming for example non-playable
characters. Um, what is missing though?
What information might we need and what
can we develop in the future? Currently
we're missing um reducing comp reducing
computation complexity enhancing human
um controllability alignment with the
language models of the human brain
adapted learning and gener
generalization across different domains
and finally multiensory multimodal
embodiment like intuitive physics and
common sense. So these might uh one
might consider these barriers to
developing artificial general
intelligence and these are some of the
limitations of current transformer
models. Um some other things that are
missing include infinite and external
memory like neural touring machines,
infinite self-improvement capabilities
like continual or lifelong learning.
This is another central um tenant of
human learning that we're not able to
replicate at the moment. Complete
autonomy including curiosity, desires,
and goals. and long horizon decision-m
as well as emotional intelligence,
social understanding, and of course
ethical reasoning and value
alignment. Right? So there's still a
sort of plethora of remaining sort of
weaknesses or challenges um around
transformers, large language models and
AI um in general these days. So I'll
touch upon a couple of them briefly. The
first is like I mentioned earlier,
efficiency. Um, being able to minify or
sort of have tiny LLMs or models that
you can run on your phone, on your
smartwatch, and etc. Um, so that's a big
trend uh these days is using LLMs for
everyday applications and purposes. Um,
and again, you want to be able to run
them quickly and easily on smaller
devices. Um, right now there is more and
more work on smaller and more efficient
open source models, things like Deep
Seek, Llama, and Mistral. Um, but
they're still somewhat large and a bit
expensive, especially if you're looking
to fine-tune. Um, they're still not
accessible to everybody, especially on
um smaller devices. So, in the future,
again, we want to aim to have the
ability to sort of fine-tune or run
these models locally on um whatever
device you want.
The second is as our models as our LLM
scale up um trillions of parameters
trained on trillions of tokens across
the internet what happens is this makes
it a huge black box that is difficult to
understand or interpret um it's hard to
know what exactly is going on behind the
scenes when you ask it to solve XYZ and
it comes up with answers ABC how exactly
did it get there why did it choose those
answers instead and so forth um so more
work on interpretability for LLMs will
give us a better idea idea of what or
how to improve them, easier um ways of
controlling them um and better
alignment. For example, being able to
prevent them from producing certain
outputs that might be unsafe um or
unethical. Um so there's this area which
has gotten even more popular recently
called mechanistic interpretability
which is trying to understand how
individual components or operations even
sometimes down to the individual um node
level um so very granular um in an ML
model contribute to its overall
decision-m process with the goal again
of sort of unpacking this black box um
for clear insight on how exactly they
work behind the
scenes. Um, next, um, I feel like we're
approaching, um, or we're already seeing
diminishing returns with simply scaling
up. So, larger models on more data, um,
does not seem to be the beall end all
solution. So, one sizefits-all and
frozen pre-trained models have already
started leading to diminishing returns.
Um, so again, pre-training performance,
so the first the first sort of um, half,
right, of training LLMs, it's likely um,
saturating. Hence, there's been more
focus on post-training methods.
everything we've talked about feedback
and RL mechanisms um prompting methods
like chain of thought um
self-improvement and refinement and so
forth. However, all of these
post-training mechanisms are going to be
fundamentally limited by the overall
performance or capabilities of the base
model. So you can argue that the
pre-training is fundamentally what gives
the basis or the foundational knowledge
and capabilities to the model. Um so we
should not just stop investigating
pre-training just because we're hitting
scaling limits. Furthermore, too much
post-training can actually lead to an
issue. Um, this is called catastro
catastrophic forgetting where the model
forgets stuff it's learned beforehand.
For example, during pre-training because
you're overloading it with tons of new
information in a new domain or a new
task um during post-training. So, how do
we break through this sort of scaling
law um limit?
Um some potential um things to
investigate would be new architectures.
There is there are different things like
Mamba um state space machines um those
sort of architectures. Um and it would
be good to see more investigation on
even non-transformer architectures which
is a bit ironic considering this class
is transformers united. Um but we also
always encourage more diversity um and
thinking outside the box. Also again um
everything I talked about about high
quality data and smart um data ordering
and structuring strategies um and
overall improved training procedures um
improved algorithms um loss functions
optimization um algorithms and so forth.
Another goal as we've mentioned several
times is to be able to have bring these
advanced capabilities to smaller models.
Um furthermore, um we would still
encourage more theoretical and
interpretability research including
things like cognitive science and neuro
um science inspired work um which Karan
and I have some um talked about some of
that um that we've done recently. And so
the next step will be models that are
not just larger but ones that are more
smarter and more adaptable.
Um so again this there's this one um
major thing or or major weakness that I
think um um still bridges the gap
between AI and um humans which is sort
of continual or lifelong learning. So AI
systems that can continuously improve by
learning after deployment after being
pre-trained um using implicit feedback
real world experience and so forth. So
um essentially this is infinite and
permanent sort of fundamental
self-improvement. We're not just talking
about rag or retrieval, like putting
knowledge in a retrieval database that
you can um retrieve at test time, but
updating the brain or the weights of the
model continuously. So, this is similar
to us, right? So, we're learning every
day. I'm learning right now by talking
to you. Um I learn every time I talk to
somebody else as I'm going through my
daily life. But these models after
they're frozen or pre-trained, that
doesn't really happen. Um the only way
they truly learn or their brain or
weights are updated is through
fine-tuning. Um and again, we don't do
that, right? we don't sit in a chair
every 3 months and have someone reread
the internet to us or something like
that.
Um so again this is almost wasted work
right so currently during inference the
models are not actually learning and
updating their weights when they're
talking when chat GBT is talking to you
it's not truly updating its brain or
weights um so this is a very challenging
problem but um in our opinion is likely
one of the keys potentially to um AGI or
truly humanlike AI systems um so there's
different current work um that tries to
tackle this there's things like
fine-tuning a smaller male model based
on traces is from a from a larger model.
Things like model distillation um
related to a lot of things like
improvement and so forth. Um but this is
again not truly continual learning. Um
so some questions are what mechanisms
could potentially truly enable um real
um lifelong learning. Um will this be
gradient updates? So you know actually
updating the brain? Will it be things
like targeting particular nodes in the
architecture? Will it be having um
things like particular memory
architectures or different parts of the
neuronet network? um solely focused on
sort of continuous updates and learning
or even things like metalarning and
looking more at the broad scale of
things um or the broader scope. So one
line of work um which has seen a bit of
traction is model editing. So this is
related to work on mechanistic
interpretability. So this is instead of
updating you know the whole model. If
we're given a new fact or new data point
can we target specific nodes or neurons
in the model that we should update. Um
so one work called um rank one model
editing or Rome um tries to do this
through causal intervention me um
mechanisms um to determine you know um
which neuron activations most correspond
to particular factual predictions and
then updating them appropriately. But as
you can possibly suspect this has a lot
of weaknesses. So firstly this works
mainly for knowledge based things or
simple facts. What if we want to update
the actual skills or capabilities of a
model? We wanted to be better at math in
general. We wanted to be better at
advanced analogical reasoning unlike
humans. Um then something like model
editing um based on factual predictions
doesn't seem like it'll work. The second
is these are targeting one fact at a
time. So it's not easy to propagate
these changes to other nodes um based on
related facts. For example,
um let's say the mother like someone's
mother um we want to update a fact about
them, then we should also update a fact
about um that person's brother because
you know they have the same mother. Um
but you know this sort of approach will
only update it for the original person
in question um but not the any of the
relatives. So this is just one example.
Um so there's a lot of other works which
have spun out recently in continual
learning which is good that this um sort
of area has seen more work. Um so I will
very briefly describe some of these.
Um one is this thing called memit which
is directly related to what I just said
uh about Rome but it's mass editing of
factual knowledge. So instead of a
simple sort of fact or memory at a time
it's able to you know simultaneously
modify thousands even ones which might
be related to each other like I said um
which is um useful. Um there's things
like chem or continue evolving from
mistakes. So it actually identifies the
ele l element mistakes somewhat similar
to what um self-improvement Chelsea was
talking about um but incrementally
updates the model to self-improve
um um just things like lifelong mixture
of experts um so what it does in instead
of having a simple fixed mixture of
experts architecture it continually adds
new experts for different domains um
over time um while freezing potentially
past experts which are no longer useful
or don't need to be updated to avoid
things like catastrophic forgetting. So
this is a very smart u sort of approach.
Another is called clob. So this enables
continual task learning using only
prompting without updating model weights
by summarizing past knowledge into a
compared prompt memory. However, not a
criticism of this work but um again this
is not take technically updating the
brain or the fundamental capabilities of
the model. So this is a more of a te a
prompt um only approach. Um and another
one of these is called progressive
prompts which again alerts a soft prompt
vector for each tasks and again
progressively um compresses them and
composes them together. Um so allowing
LLMs to continually learn without weight
updates um or catastrophic forgetting.
Um but again um my opinion is true
continual learning would update the
brain um or the weights of the model in
some way I
guess. So um thanks that's mainly our
lecture. So you know we gave a brief
overview of transformers how they work
talked about pre-training and especially
how data is important for that various
post-training techniques feedback
mechanisms um prompting mechanisms like
chain of thought self-improvement some
applications to neuroscience vision and
so forth and some remaining weaknesses
um like things like the lack of
continual learning and um data
efficiency being able to scale down and
run these models on our phone. Um, so
before we send you guys off, uh, I know
we ended a bit early. Um, so this class
going forwards every week, in case you
haven't attended, we'll have a speaker
um, typically from industry or academia
come in to talk about the
state-of-the-art work they're doing. And
we have, um, a cool lineup of speakers
prepared for you guys for the remainder
of the quarter. And some more logistical
things. We'll be um, posting updates
about lectures and so forth on our
website through the mailing list,
Discord, and so forth. So, please join
those if you haven't already. Thank you
guys. Hope you enjoyed the first
lecture. And if anybody has any
questions, feel free to come up and uh
stay around. But thanks