so again I'm very happy to have Jason
here um so he's an AI researcher based
in San Francisco currently working at
openi he was previously a research
scientist at Google brain where he
popularized key ideas in llms such as
Chain of Thought prompting instruction
tuning as well as emergent phenomena um
he's also a good friend of mine and he's
been here before to give some talk so
we're very happy to have you back Jason
and take it away great uh
uh
wow yeah thanks for the intro um so a
bit about the structure uh so I'll talk
for around 30 minutes and then I'll take
a few questions and then K Juan will
talk for 30 minutes and then we'll both
take questions at the
end um great so I want to talk uh about
a few very basic things and I think the
fundamental question that I hope to get
at is
is why do language
models work so
well um and uh one thing that I'd
encourage everyone to do that I found to
be extremely helpful in trying to answer
this question uh is to use a tool which
is
manually
inspect
data um and I'll give a short anecdote
I've been doing this for a long time so
in uh in 2019 I was like trying to build
one of the first lung cancer classifier
so like there' be an image and you have
to say like okay what type of lung
cancer is this um and uh my first my
first thing was like okay if I want to
train a neural network to do this I
should be able to at least do the task
so I went to my adviser and I said like
oh I want to learn to do this task first
and he said Jason uh you need like a
medical degree in like three years of
pathology experience to like even do
this task and I found that a bit
discouraging but uh I wouldn't did it
anyways so I basically looked at like
the specific type of lung cancer that I
was working on and I'd like read all the
papers on like how to classify different
types and I went to pathologist and I
said okay I like try to classify these
what did I do wrong and then what do you
think of that and in the end I learned
how to do this task of classifying lung
cancer um and uh the result of this was
like I gain intuitions about the task
that led to many
papers um okay so first uh I will do a
quick review of language models so the
way language models are trained are with
uh the next word prediction task so
let's say you have
uh let's say you have a sentence
Dartmouth students like
to um and the goal of next word
prediction is you have some words that
come before and then you want to predict
the next
word and what the language model does is
it outputs a probability for every
single word in the vocabulary so
vocabulary would be like a
arvar uh you know
drink
study and then all the way to like
zucchini um and then the language model
is going to put a probability over every
single word here so like you know the
probability of a being the next word is
like something really small arvar is
something really small and then maybe
drink is like say 0.6 study is like
0.3 uh zucchini is again really
small um and then the way that you train
the language model is you say I want
let's say drink is the correct word
here I want this number here 0.6 to be
as close as possible to one so your loss
is like basically how close is the
actual word the probability of the
actual next word and you want this loss
to be as low as
possible um okay
so the first
intuition that I would encourage
everyone to to use um
is
next
word
prediction uh
is
massively
multi-
task
learning um and uh what I mean by this
is the following I'll give a few
examples uh
so uh it when you train a language model
on a large enough database large enough
data set um on this task of next word
prediction you have a lot of sentences
that you can learn from so for example
uh there might be some sentence in my
free time I like to and the language
model has to learn that code should be
higher probability than the word banana
so it learn some
grammar um it will learn lexical
semantics so uh somewhere uh in your
data set there might be a sentence I
went to the store to buy papaya dragon
fruit and durian um and the language
model should know that the probability
of durian should be higher than
squirrel um the language model will
learn World Knowledge so there will be
some sentence on the internet that says
you know the capital of azer is and then
the language model should learn that it
should be Baku instead of
London um you can learn traditional NLP
tasks like sentimen analysis so there'll
be some sentence you know I was engaged
on the of my seat the whole time the
movie was and the language model looks
like okay if these are the prior next
words the next word uh should probably
be good and not
bad um and then finally or another
example is translation uh so here you
might see some sentence the word for
pretty in Spanish is um and then the
language model should weigh Bonita more
than
Ola um spatial reasoning so you might
even have some sentence like Ira went to
the kitchen to make T standing next to
iro zuk Zuko pondered is Destiny Zuko
left the and then kitchen should be
higher probability than
store um and then finally even some math
questions so uh you might have like some
arithmetic exam answer key somewhere on
the internet and then the language model
looks at this and says okay the next
word should probably be 15 and not
11 um and you can have like basically
millions of tasks like this when you
have a huge uh data set um and you can
think of this as basically extreme
multitask
learning um and these are sort of like
uh very clean examples of tasks um but
I'll give uh an example of
uh how arbitrary some of these tasks can
be um so uh here's a sentence from uh uh
Wikipedia Biden
married
uhia okay and then now uh pretend you're
the language model and you could say
like okay what's the next word here um
and the next word here is a hunter so is
Biden's first wife um and so like okay
what's the language model learning to
predict from predicting this word I
guess like uh World
Knowledge um and then what's the next
word after this uh turns out the next is
a comma so here the model is learning
like basically comma
prediction um and then what's the next
word after that uh I think it's that
kind of hard to know but the answer is a
um and I guess this is like maybe
grammar but like somewhat
arbitrary um and then what's the next
word after that um turns out it's
student uh and uh this I would say I
don't know what task this is this is
like uh you know you know it could have
been woman it could have been something
else um so this is like a pretty
arbitrary task and the point that I'm
trying to make here is that the next
word prediction task is really
challenging so like if you do this over
the entire database you're going to
learn a lot of
tasks um
okay the next uh intuition I want to
talk about
is
scaling which is by the way uh let's say
scaling
compute and by the way compute is equal
to how much data you have times the size
of language
model um reliably improves loss
um and uh this idea uh was basically
pioneered by Kaplan at
all in 2020 I would encourage you guys
to read the paper um and uh what this
basically says is uh you can have a plot
here and we'll see many plots like this
um where the x- axis is compute
um and the y- AIS is
loss and what this intuition says is you
can train one language model you'll have
that loss and obviously want loss to be
lower so you can train the next one
it'll have that loss if you train the
one after that it'll have that loss then
if you train the one after that it'll
have that
loss and you can basically predict the
loss of a language model based on how
much compute you're going to use to
train it
um and the reason why this is called a
law is that in this paper they showed
that the xais here is actually seven
orders of magnitude so like basically it
would be surprising if the trend broke
if you
continued and the important thing about
this is that the line does not go like
that
because if it went like that then it
would saturate and then putting more
compute or training a larger language
model wouldn't actually lead to lower
loss um okay so I think a question that
we don't have a good answer to as a
field uh but I'll give you like a hand
wavy answer is uh why does scaling up
the size of your language model um
improve the loss um and I'll give like
two basically handwave answers so here's
small
LM and here's large
LM um so one thing that's important is
like how good is your language model at
memorizing
facts um and imagine you're a small
language model and you you see a bunch
of facts on the internet you have to be
pretty choosy in like which facts you
memorize right cuz like if you don't
have that many parameters you like oh I
can only memorize like a million facts
is this one of the facts I want to
memorize to like get the lowest loss and
so you have to be very
selective whereas if you're a large
language
model you can memorize a lot of tail
knowledge and so basically every fact
you see you don't have to say oh is this
something I want to memorize you can
just memorize
it and then the other hand wavy answer
I'll
give is small language models uh tend to
learn first
tics
so if you're like a small language model
you're like already struggling to get
the grammar correct you're not going to
do your best to like try to get the math
problem exactly correct um whereas if
you're a large language
model um you have a lot of parameters in
your in your forward pass and you can
try to do really complicated things to
get the next token correct uh and and to
get the loss as low as possible
um okay so the third intuition I'll talk
about
is while
overall
loss
[Music]
improves
smoothly individual
tasks can
improve
suddenly um and uh here's what I mean by
this so uh you can write your overall
loss by this I mean you know if you take
uh uh some Corpus of data and you and
you compute the overall loss on every
word in that data set the overall loss
because we know that next word
prediction is massively multitask
learning you can decompose this overall
loss into the loss of every single
individual task so you have like I don't
know some small number times the uh loss
of say
grammar uh plus some small number times
the loss of like sentent
analysis plus uh some small number
times uh the loss of like World
Knowledge plus and then all the way to
like let's say you have uh something
times the loss of uh
math and so so you can basically write
your overall loss as the weighted sum of
the individual tasks in the data
set and now the question is let's say I
improve my loss from uh from four to
three um do each of these individual
tasks improve at the same
rate well I would say probably not so
you know if you have a good enough
language model it's already doing
basically perfectly on grammar and tens
analysis so this might not
improve so this might be
saturated um and maybe the law the loss
on math is not it's not that good at
math yet so this could improve
suddenly um and uh I'll redraw the
diagram to show
this um so
again compute
here uh and loss here and your overall
loss is like this
um what I'm saying is there might be
some part of that overall loss that
scales like this uh so this is say
grammar so for example you could say
like uh if GPT 3.5 is there and GPT 4 is
there you haven't actually improved the
grammar that much on the other hand you
might have something like this for say
doing math or harder tasks uh where the
difference between GPT 3.5 and GPT 4
will be much
larger um and it turns
out it turns out you can look at a big
set of tasks which I did um and you can
look at like what's the shape of of
these scaling curves um so I looked at
tasks uh there's this Corpus called Big
bench which has like 200 tasks I looked
at all of them um and here's the
distribution
so uh you have this was 29% of tasks
that were
smooth uh so if I if I draw the scaling
plot compute is on the x
axis and then here we have accuracy
instead of loss so higher is better then
you have something like this
um I believe this was
22% uh will be
flat so if you have your scaling curve
it'll just all be zero the task was too
hard uh
2% will be something called inverse
scaling I'll talk about this in a sec uh
but what that means um is the accuracy
actually gets worse as you increase the
size of the language
model um and then I think this was
133% will be not
correlated so uh you have like something
like that I don't know um and then
finally a pretty big
portion
33% uh will be
emergent abilities and what I mean by
that is if you plot your
compute and accuracy
for a certain point up to a certain
point your loss or your accuracy will be
zero and then the accuracy suddenly
starts to
improve um and uh so you can Define like
an emergent ability basically as for
small
models uh uh it the performance is zero
so it's not present in this model and
then for large models
um you have uh much better than random
performance um and the interesting thing
about this is let's say you had only
trained the small language models up to
that point you would have predicted that
it would have been impossible for the
language model to ever perform the task
but actually when you train the larger
model the language model does learn to
perform the task so in sense in a sense
it's uh pretty unpredictable
um I'll talk about time you have I'll
talk about one uh final thing uh which
is something called inverse scaling SL
shaped
scaling um okay so I'll give a tricky
prompt to illustrate this uh so the
tricky prompt is
this repeat
after
me
all that
glisters is not
glib
all
that
listers is
not um and uh this is the prompt I give
to the language model and the goal is to
predict this next word uh and obviously
the correct answer is glib because you
asked to repeat after after me um and
what you see is let's say you have a
extra small language Model A small
language model and a large language
model the performance for the extra
small language model will be
say here's 100% the small language model
is actually worse at this task
so something like something here and
then the large language model again uh
learns to do this
task so uh how do we basically explain a
behavior like this for a prompt like
this and the answer is you can decompose
this prompt into like three subtasks
that are basic being done um so the
first subtask is like can you repeat
some text
right um and if you draw the plot here
again uh extra small small large uh and
then here is
100 this is like a super easy task and
so all the language models
have perfect performance on that that's
one hidden task the other task is can
you uh fix a
quote so the quote is supposed to be all
that gly is not gold um and so you can
then plot again extra small small large
what's the ability to fix that quote
well the small language model doesn't
know the quote so it's going to get zero
and then or the extra small doesn't know
the quote so it's going to get zero the
small will be able to do it um and the
large can obviously do it so that's what
what the scaling curve looks
like um and then
finally you have the quote follow you
have the task follow an
instruction um and uh obviously this is
the instruction here um and you could
say okay what's the performance of these
models uh on this
task um and the small model can't do it
or the extra small model can't do it
small model also can't do it but the
large model can do it so you get a curve
like
this and then why does this explain this
Behavior here well the small the extra
small model it can repeat the it can
repeat it can't fix the quote and it
can't follow the instruction so it
actually gets it correct it says
glip says
glib the small model
can repeat it can fix the quote but it
doesn't follow the instruction so it
decides to fix the
quote and then the large model it can do
all three it can follow the instruction
so it just
repeats um and so uh that's how if you
look at the individual subtasks you can
explain the behavior of some of these
weird scaling properties
so I will
[Music]
conclude with one General
takeaway
um which is applicable if you if you do
research um and the takeaway is to just
plot scaling
curves um and I'll just give a really
simple example so uh you know let's say
I do something for my research project I
like f tuna model on some number of
examples um and I get uh you know this
is my
thing I get some performance there and
then uh here's the
Baseline of uh not doing whatever my
research project is uh and there's the
performance the reason you want to plot
a scaling curve for this is like let's
say you uh take half the data uh and you
find out that the performance is
actually here so your curve looks like
this um what this would tell you is you
didn't have to collect all the data to
do your thing and if you collect more
you probably won't see an improvement in
performance another scenario would be if
you plotted that point and it was
there then your Curve will look like
this and and potentially if you kept
doing more of whatever your research
project is you'd see an improvement in
performance and then finally maybe your
point is
there so your curve looks like this and
in this case you would expect to see an
even larger jump in performance after
you continue doing your
thing um so uh yeah I'll end my talk
here and happy to take a few questions
before him wants talk
uh yeah go
ahead
dat The Source repeat the question oh oh
yeah yeah thanks good question um so the
question is uh uh it during pre-training
how do you differentiate between good
data and bad data um the question is uh
or the answer is you don't really um but
you should buy only training on good
data so like maybe you should look at
like your data source and filter out
some data if it's like not from a
reliable data
source yeah do you want to give us maybe
the intuition behind the intuition for
one or two of the examples like
emergent or you know why taale knowledge
starts to develop sort of what's behind
that what do you mean intuition behind
intuition intuitively these Concepts
that you're seeing in the graphs and
from your experience and expertise what
in the model itself is really causing
that emergent behavior
let's um what do you mean in in the
model
itself uh is it you know more depths
more nodes more I see attention in an
intuitive sense not
in oh yeah okay yeah so the question is
like what in the model makes uh you know
the Lang which model better at
memorizing tail knowledge or at uh um at
doing math problems um yeah I think it's
definitely related to the size of the
language model so uh yeah if you have
like more layers you could encode
probably more complex like function
within that um and then I guess if you
have like more breath you could probably
encode like more facts about the world
um and then like if you want to repeat a
fact or like retrieve something it
probably be easier
get one more in person and then we'll
move
this hi so when you were studying the
200ish problems in the big bench you
noticed that 22% were flat but there's a
possibility that if you had increased
the computer even further it might have
those might have turned out to be
emergent so my question to you is that
when you were looking at the 33% that
turned out to be emergent did you notice
anything about the loss in the flat
portion that suggested that they would
eventually become
emergent um oh yeah
um I didn't notice anything uh oh sorry
let me repeat the question uh the
question is like uh when I looked at all
the emergent tasks was there anything
that I noticed uh before the emergence
point in the loss that would have like
hinted that it it would become emergent
later um to me it's kind of tough like
we have a few plots of this like you can
look at the loss and it like kind of
gets better and then suddenly it spikes
and there's like no way to predict it
but also you don't have like perfect
data cuz like you might not have like
all the in media points for a given
model
size yeah great
question
um yeah we can move to
one we have a few online question online
oh okay yeah yeah um we just have a few
questions from people who are joining on
Zoom um the first one is what do you
think are the biggest bottlenecks for
current large language models is it the
quality of data the amount of compute or
something
else um yeah great question I guess like
if you go back to the uh like uh scaling
laws Paradigm um what it says is that uh
if you increase the the size of the data
in the size of the model um then you'd
expect to get a lot better performance
and I think yeah we'll probably try to
keep increasing those things gotcha and
then the last one um what are your
thoughts on the paper if you've read it
um are emergent abilities of language
large language models a mirage oh yeah I
always get this question um I guess uh I
would encourage you to read the paper
and and decide for yourself but like um
yeah like I guess what the paper says is
like if you change the metric a bit it
looks different um but I would say uh at
the end of the day like um I think the
language model abilities are real and if
you think like yeah I guess I don't
think that's a mirage so
yeah
yeah all right so thanks Jason for the
very insightful talk
and now we have uh kyang Wan um give a
talk so he's currently a research
scientist at um on the open AI Chad gbt
team um he has worked on various aspects
of large language models um things like
pre-training instruction fine-tuning
reinforcement learning with human
feedback uh reasoning um and so forth
and some of his notable Works include um
the scaling flan paper such as flan T5
as well as flan pal and t5x the training
framework used to train the Palm
language model and before open AI um he
was at Google brain and um he received
his PhD from MIT um so give a hand for
um H
[Applause]
one all right my name isan and really
happy to be here today and this week I
was thinking about by the way it's mic
working
fine yeah yeah um so this week I thought
about okay I'm giving a lecture on
Transformers at Stanford what should I
talk about and I thought okay some of
you in this room and in in Zoom will
actually go shape the future of AI so
maybe I should talk about that it's a
really important goal and ambitious and
we really have to get it right so that
could be a good topic to think about and
when we talk about something into the
future the best place to get an advice
is to look into the history in
particular we'll look at the early
history of Transformer and try to learn
many lessons from there and the goal
will be to develop a unified perspective
in uh with which we can look into many
seemingly disjoint events and and from
that we can probably uh hope to project
into the future what might be coming and
so um that will be the goal of this
lecture and we'll look at some of the
architectures of the Transformers so
let's get
started everyone I see uh it's saying AI
is so advancing so fast that it's so
hard to keep up and doesn't matter if
you have like years of experience
there's so many things are coming out
every week that it's just hard to keep
up and I do see many people spend a lot
of time and energy catching up with this
latest development the The Cutting Edge
and the the the newest thing and then
not enough attention goes into old
things because they become um deprecated
and no longer relevant but I think it's
important actually to look into that
because we really need to when things
are moving so fast beyond our ability to
catch up what we need to do is study the
change itself and that means we can look
back at the previous things and then
look at the current thing and try to map
how we got here and from which we can
look into what where we are heading
towards so what does it mean to study
the change itself
first um we need to identify the
dominant driving forces behind the
change so here dominant is an important
word because typically a change has many
many driving forces and we only care
about the dominant one because we're not
trying to get really accurate you just
want to have the sense of directionality
second we need to understand the driving
force really well and then after that we
can predict the future trajectory by I
know rolling out the driving force and
so on and you heard that right I
mentioned about predicting the future
this is a computer science class not
like an astrology or something but we do
I think it's actually not that
impossible to predict some future
trajectory of a very narrow scientific
domain and that um endeaver is really
useful uh to do because uh you let's say
you you do all these and then make your
prediction accuracy to from 1% to 10%
and then you'll make say 100 predictions
10 of them will be correct say one of
them will be really really correct
meaning it will have an outside impact
that outweighs everything and I think
that um is kind of how uh many I've seen
M General thing in life that you really
have to be right a few times so why um
so so if we think about why um
predicting the future is difficult or
maybe even think about the extreme case
where we can all do the prediction with
perfect accuracy almost perfect accuracy
so here I'm going to do a very simple
experiment of dropping this pen and
follow this uh same three-step process
so we're going to identify the driving
dominant driving force first of all what
what are the driving forces acting on
this pen gravity downwards and is that
all we we also have like a say um air
friction right going if I drop it and
that will cause What's called the drag
force acting upwards and actually
depending on how I drop this the
orientation the the aerodynamic
interaction will be so complicated that
we don't currently have any analytical
way of modeling that we can do it with
the CFT the computational fluid dynamics
but it will be non-trivial so so we can
neglect that this is Happy enough that
gravity is probably the only dominant
Force we simpli simplify the problem
second we do we understand this dominant
driving force which is gravity and we do
because we have this Newtonian mechanics
which provides reasonably good model and
then with that we can predict the future
trajectory of this pen and if you
remember from the this um Dynamics class
if we have this initial velocity is zero
I'm not going to put any velocity and
then let's say position is zero here and
then uh 1 12 GT Square will give a
precise um trajectory of this pen as I
Dro this so if there is a driving force
single driving force that we really
understand it's actually possible to
predict what's going to happen so then
why do we really um fear about
predicting the future in the most
General sense and I argue that among
many reasons the number of driving force
the sheer number of dominant driving
forces acting on the general um
prediction is so complicated and their
interaction creates a complexity that we
cannot predict the most General sense so
here's my cartoon way of thinking about
the prediction of future x- axis we have
a number of dominant driving forces Y
axis we have a prediction difficulty so
on the left hand side we have a dropping
of pen it's a very simple case we it's a
difficulty is very small you just need
to learn um physics and then as you add
more stuff it just becomes impossible so
how does this fit into the AI research
and you might think okay I see all the
time things are coming in we are
bombarded by new things and some people
will come up with the new agent new
modality new MML score whatever that we
just see so many things it just um I'm
not even able to catch up with the
latest thing how can I even hope to
predict the future future of the AI
research but I I argue that it's
actually simpler because there is a
dominant driving force that is governing
a lot if any if not all of the AI
research and because of that I would
like to point out that it should it's
actually closer to the left than to the
right uh than we actually may perceive
um
so what is that driving force oh maybe
before that I would like to caveat that
uh when I do this kind of talk I would
like to not focus too much on the
technical stuff which you can probably
do better in your own time but rather I
want to uh share how I think and for
that I want to share how my opinion as
is and so it will be very strongly
opinion and I'm by no means I'm saying
this is uh correct or not just wanted to
share my perspective so coming back to
this driving force for AI what is that
dominant driving force and here's a plot
from Rich suton and on the y- axis we
have the uh calculations flopped if you
pay $100 and how much computing power do
you get and it's in log scale and then
xxs we have a a time of of more more
than 100 years so this is actually more
than like exponential and I don't know
any Trend that is as strong and as long
lasting as this one so this whenever I
see this kind of thing I should say okay
I should not compete with this and
better I should try to leverage as much
as possible and um so what this means is
you get 10x more compute every five
years if you spend the same amount of
dollar and so in other words you get the
cost of compute is going down
exponentially and this and Associated
scaling is really dominating the AI
research and that is somewhat hard to
take but that is I think really
important to uh think about so coming
back to this AI research how is how is
this U exponentially cheaper compute
Drive the AI research let's think about
the job of the AI researchers it is to
teach machines how to think in a very
general sense and one somewhat uh you
know unfortunately common approach is we
think about how we teach machine how we
think we think so meaning we model how
we think and then try to incorporate
that into some kind of mathematical
model teach that and now the question is
do we understand how we think at the
very low level I don't think we do I
don't I have no idea what's going on so
it's fundamentally flawed in the sense
that we try to model something that we
have no idea about and what happens if
we go with this kind of approaches that
it poses a structure that serves as a
shortcut in the short term and so you
can maybe get a paper or something but
then it becomes a bottleneck when when
because you it we don't know how this
will um limit further they're scaling up
um more fundamentally what this is doing
is we are limiting the degree of Freedom
we are giving to the machines and that
will backfire at some point and this has
been uh going on for decades and bitter
lesson is I think the single most
important piece of writing in Ai and it
says uh this is my Waring by the way SE
past 70 years of entire AI research can
be summarized into developing Pro
progressively more General method with
weaker modeling assumptions or inductive
biases and add more data and compute in
other words scale up and that has been
the recipe of entire AI research not
fancy things and if you think about this
the models of 202,000 is a lot more
difficult than what we use now and so
it's much easier to get into AI nowadays
um from technical perspective so this uh
is I think the really the key
information
we have this compute cost is going down
exponentially and it's getting cheaper
faster than we're becoming a better
researcher so don't compete with that
and just try to leverage that as much as
possible and that is the driving force
that I wanted to uh identify and I'm not
saying this is the only driving force
but this is the dominant driving force
so we can probably neglect the other
ones so here's a graphical version of
that xaxis we have a compute Y axis we
have a performance of some kind let's
think about some general intelligence
and let's look at two different methods
one with more structure more modeling
assumption fancier math whatever and
then the other one is a less structure
what you see is typically you start with
a better performance uh when you have a
low compute regime and then but it
plateaus because of some kind of
structure backfiring and then with the
less structure because we give a lot
more freedom to the model it doesn't
work at the beginning but then as we add
more comput it starts working and then
it gets better we call this more
scalable method so does that mean we
should just go with the least structure
most freedom to the model uh possible
way from the get-go and the answer is
obviously no let's think about even less
structure case this red one here is um
it will pick up a lot later um and
requires a lot more compute so it really
depends on where we are we cannot
indefinitely wait for the most General
case and so let's think about the case
where our compute situation is at the
starting line if we're here we should um
choose this less structure one as
opposed to this even less structure one
because the other one doesn't really
work and the the other one works but
crucially we need to remember that we
are adding some structure because we
don't have compute so we need to remove
that later and so the difference between
these two method is the additional
inductive biases or structure we impose
someone impose uh that typically don't
get removed so adding this uh what what
that means is that that at the given
level of compute data algorithmic
development and architecture that we
have there's like an optimal inductive
bias or structure that we can add to the
problem to make the progress and that
has been really uh how we have made so
much progress but these are like
shortcuts that hinder further scaling
later on so we have to remove them later
on when we have more compute better
algorithm or whatever and as a community
we do adding structure very well and
because there's an incentive structure
of with like papers you add a nice one
then you get a paper but removing that
doesn't really get you much so that we
don't really uh do that and I think we
should do a lot more of those so maybe
another implication of This Bitter
lesson is that because of this what is
better in the long term almost
necessarily looks worse now and this is
quite unique to AI research because the
AI research of current um Paradigm is
learning based method meaning that we
are giving models Freedom the machines
choose how they learn so because we need
to give more freedom it gives uh it's a
more chaotic at the beginning so it
doesn't work but then when it start
working we can put in more compute and
then it can be better so it's really
important to have this in mind so to
summarize we have identified this
dominant driving force behind the AI
research and that is this exponentially
cheaper compute and Associated scaling
up now that we have identified if you
remember back from my uh initial slides
we the next step is to understand this
driving force better and so that's we're
going to spend uh most of the time doing
that and for that we need to go back to
some history of Transformer because this
is a Transformers class and analyze key
structures and decisions that were made
by the uh researchers at the time and
why they did that whether that was an
optimal structure that could have been
added at the time and why they might be
irrelevant now and should we remove that
and we'll go through some of the
practices of this and hopefully this
will give you some flavor of what um
like scaling research looks like so now
we'll go into a little bit of the
technical stuff Tech uh Transformer
architecture there are some variants um
I'll talk about three of them first is
the encoder decoder which is the
original Transformer which has a little
bit more structure second one is the
encoder only which is popularized by
Bert and then third one is um decoder
only which you can think of as a current
um like gpt3 or other language models
this has a lot less structure than the
encoder decoder so these are the three
types we will go into detail second the
encoder only is actually not that useful
in the most General sense it still has
some um place but we will so U just
briefly go over that and then spend most
of the time comparing one and three so
one has more structure what's the
implication of that and so on so first
of all let's think about what a
Transformer is just um uh at a very high
level or first principles what is a
Transformer is a sequence model and
sequence model is a has an input of a
sequence so sequence can be um sequence
of elements can be words or images or
whatever it's a very general Concept in
this particular example I'll show you
with the words sentence is a sequence of
words and then we the first step is to
tokenize it because we have to rep
present this um word in computers which
requires just some kind of a uh encoding
scheme so we just do do it with the
fixed number of integers then we have
now sequence of integers and then the
dominant Paradigm uh nowadays is to
represent each sequence element as a
vector dense Vector because we know how
to multiply them well and then so we
have a sequence of vectors um and
finally this um sequence model will do
the following we just want to model the
interaction between sequence elements
and we do that by let them take the dot
product of each other and if the dot
product is high we can say semantically
they are more related than the do
products that is low and that's kind of
the sequence model and the Transformer
is a particular type of sequence model
that uses and what's called attention um
to model this interaction so let's get
into the details of this encoder decoder
which was the original Transformer it's
quite many many pieces so let's go into
a little bit a piece at a time so
starting with the encoder so here I'm
going to show you an example of machine
translation which used to be very uh
cool thing and so you are you have an
English sentence that is good and then
we're going to translate into German so
first thing is to uh encode this into a
dense Vector so here I'm representing it
with a um this like a vector of size
three or something and then we have to
let them take the dot product so this um
you know lines represent which element
can talk to which element other elements
and here because it's an input we take
what is called a bir directional
attention so any token can talk to any
other token and then we have this U um
MLP or feed forward layer which is per
token it doesn't have any interaction we
just do some you know some some some
multiplication just because we can do it
and then that's one layer and we repeat
that end times and that is the
Transformer encoder and at the end what
you get is the sequence of vectors each
representing the sequence element in
this case a word so that's the the
output of this encoder now let's look at
the decoder which is similarly shaped um
St of layers so here we put in as an
input um the uh what what the answer
should be so here B is a beginning of
sequence and then do is good I don't
know how to pronounce it but that's the
German translation of that is good and
so we kind of go through the similar
process here we have a caal self
attention meaning that the tokens of
time step T can only attend to T and
before because when we start generating
it we don't have the future tokens so we
cannot when we train it we should limit
that and and that way we this is done by
like masking but uh just just different
from the
encoder so after this you can get um
after again end layers you get this um
sequence output and you have this the
output is sequence so sequence to
sequence mapping this is a general um
encoder decoder architecture and when
you get this end of sequence you stop
generating it so this is the the overall
picture now I'll point out some
important uh attention patterns so we
are translating um the into German what
is in input to the encoder so there has
to be some connection between the
decoder and the encoder that is done by
this cross attention mechanism shown in
this red which is just that each Vector
representation of each sequence in the
output decoder should attend to some of
them in the encoder and that is done in
particular the design feature which is
interesting is that all the layers in
the decoder attend to the final layer
output of the encoder I we'll come back
to the implication of those design so um
yep that's that and now move on to the
second type of architecture which is
encoder only we'll spend a little bit of
time here so again we have to uh in we
have the same input uh and and we go
through similar uh structure and then
the in this case the final output is a
single Vector regardless of the length
of the uh sequence we just get a single
vector and and that is uh that represent
the input sequence that's the dense uh
Vector representation and then let's say
we do some kind of a sentiment analysis
we run through a Tas specific linear
layer to map it to classification labels
positive or negative probabilities here
and that's required for for all these um
test specific um cases and this is kind
of popularized by Bert and what this
means is that here at the time 2018 when
bird came out uh we had a benchmark
called glue which was a language
understanding test you have a sequence
in classification labels out for most
cases this was how the field really
Advanced at the time so when we care
about such tasks then there's an
incentive to think about simplifying the
problem adding the structure to the
problem so that we can make a progress
so this the additional structure that
was put into this particular
architecture is that we're going to give
up on the uh generation if we do that it
becomes a lot simpler problem instead of
sequence to sequence we're talking about
sequence to classification labels and
that's just so much easier and so um at
some point 2018 2019 a lot of the papers
or just research was like we sometimes
call it birth Engineers little bit
change of something get like 05% better
on glue you get a paper and things like
that it was like very chaotic era and
and but but if we look at from this
perspective we are putting the sequence
structure of not generating the sequence
that puts a lot of U performance win but
in the long term it's not really useful
so we're not going to look at this
encoder only architecture going forward
third architecture decoded only this one
is um my favorite personally and it
looks kind of uh daunting but uh because
of this attention pattern but it
actually is very simple so so here we
only have a single stack and it can
actually generate stuff and so there's
misconception that some people think
this decoder only architecture is used
for language modeling next to comp
prediction so it cannot be used for
supervised learning but here we can
actually do it the trick is to have this
input that is good concatenated with the
Target and if you do that then it just
becomes um simple the sequence in
sequence out so what what we do is um
the self attention mechanism here is
actually handling both the cross
attention between Target and the input
and self attention sequence uh learning
within each so that's the causal
attention and then the the yeah as I
mentioned the output is a sequence and
then the key design features are self
attention is so serving both rules and
we are in some sense sharing the
parameters between input and Target so
same set of parameters are applied to
both input and the target sequences so
this is the decoder only now we will go
into the comparison so
I think there many um like they look
very different at least on the
schematics so how different are they
actually and to I I argue that they're
actually quite similar and so to
illustrate that we're going to transform
starting from this encoder decoder which
has more structures built in and then
into um the decoder only architecture
and see what what are some of the
differences and then interpret those
differences those additional structures
are they relevant nowadays now that we
have more compute better algorithms and
so on so let's have this table four
differences we'll see each of them and
then as we go through we'll um populate
the this table so let's first look at
this additional cross tension um what
that means is that this on the left is
an incoder decoder which has this
additional red block the cross the
tension compared to the simpler one that
doesn't have that so we want to make it
make the left closer to the right so
that means we need to either get rid of
it or something and a tension me
mechanism has kind of the four
projection matrices and so self
attention and cross attention actually
have the same number of parameters same
shape so we can just share them so
that's the first step share both of
these and then it becomes mostly the
same uh mechanism and then so that's the
first difference separate curs attention
or self attention serving both roles
second difference is the parameter
sharing so what that means is that
between the input and the target encoder
decoder architecture uses a separate
parameters and decoder only only has a
single stack so it uses the share
parameter so if we want to make the left
close to right we want to share the
encoder parameters so let's do that I
just colored this so now they share the
parameters third difference is the
target to input attention pattern so we
need to connect the target to the input
and how does that how is it done in the
encoder decoder case we had this cross
attention and then in the decoder only
it's a per uh the self tension doing
everything what the difference is that
um we have this
um every layer of the decoder attending
to the final layer output of the encoder
whereas if you think about this decoder
is actually per layer within layer when
we are decoding the say word dos we are
looking at the same layer representation
of the encoder and and that's within
layer and I think this is the design
feature so if you want to make this
close to that we have to bring back this
attention to each layer so now layer one
will be attending to to layer one of
this and that's the then finally the
last uh difference is the input
attention I mentioned about this by
directional tension and because we have
this decoder only typically with the um
uni directional tension we need to make
them matching so that's the we can just
get rid of it I just got rid of the the
some of the arrows so then at this point
these two architectures are almost
identical um a little bit of difference
in the cross tension but same number of
parameters and if you have in deep
learning if you just train this these
two architecture in the same task same
data I think you will get pretty much
within the noise probably closer than if
you train the same thing twice so um I
would say they're identical and so these
are the main differences now look at how
what are the additional structures what
they mean what they mean it means so
yeah that's the populated table now and
then so we can say that encoder decoder
compared to the decoder only
architecture has has these additional um
structures inductive biases built in so
let's go into each of them the first one
is the what what encoder decoder tries
add it as a structure is that input and
the target sequences are sufficiently
different that we it'll be useful to use
a separate parameters that's the
Assumption and so why is that useful
when that when can that assumption be
useful and one example is machine
translation uh back when the transform
was introduced in 2017
translation was really popular task and
it was difficult considered difficult
and because it's a sequence to sequence
and you can actually have a blue score
which is puristic based method that can
give you a single number and then people
can optimize that so what what that in
that task we have this input and Target
in completely different languages so if
you if the goal is to learn translation
only then it kind of makes sense to have
okay this parameter in the encoder will
take care of the English and this
parameter in the decoder will take care
of the the German that seems natural and
and what about now modern language
models is about learning knowledge and
it's not just about translation or not
even about language language just comes
up as a byproduct of doing this next
token prediction and translation as well
so does it make sense to have a separate
parameter for um this kind of situation
now like we have some knowledge in
German s some knowledge in English and
we if anything you want to combine them
and have if we represent them in a
separate parameters I don't think that's
natural so I would say with this U much
more General larger models that can do a
lot of things this assumption seems very
unnatural to me second example is a
little bit more modern uh two years ago
when I was at Google uh and with Jason
we uh did this instruction fine tuning
work and what this is uh is you take the
pre-rain model and then just fine tune
on academic data set and and so that it
can understand the language instruction
so the detail doesn't matter but here
let's think about the the performance
gain by doing this fine tuning on two
different architectures we tried so
first five is the flant T5 which is T5
base which is inod decod architecture
last one uh the letter five decoder only
architecture based on Palm so we spent
99% of the time on pal optimizing a lot
of these and then at the end we just
spend like 3 days on T5 but the the the
performance gain was a lot higher on
this and I was really confused about
this and in a very good way and after
the paper was published I wanted to like
think a little bit deeper into why this
might be the case
so uh the my hypothesis is that it's
about the length so academic data sets
we use we use like 1832 tasks and here
they have this very distinctive
characteristic where we have a long
input long in order to make the task
more difficult but then we cannot make
the target long because if we do there's
no way to grade it so there's
fundamental challenge of that so what
happens is you have a long text of input
and then short text of the Target and
and so this is kind of the length
distribution of what it went into the FL
uh fine tuning so then you see this um
you have a very different sequence going
into the encoder as an input and a very
different type of sequence going into
the target so now this encoder decoder
architecture has an assumption that they
will be very different that structure
really shines because of this it was a
kind of an accident but that was I think
why this really architecture was um just
suitable for fine-tuning with the
academic data sets what about now do we
care about this kind of a assumption and
if you think about the general use cases
of language models nowadays if anything
the more interesting cases involve
longer generation longer Target uh just
because we cannot great them doesn't
mean that we are not interested in them
actually if anything we are more
interested in that so now we have this
like longer Target situation so this
separate sequence length um parameter
doesn't seem to make much sense and
moreover we think about this chat
application like chat GPT we do multi-
turn conversation and then so what is a
target of this turn becomes the input of
the next turn and then my question is
does that make sense to even think about
a um different parameter if next turn
it's going to be the same
thing so um that was the first inductive
bi we just uh mentioned and then the
second structure is that Target element
can only attend to the full fully
encoded ones the final output of the
encoder n look at this additional
structure what that means so as I
mentioned we have this U very top layer
attending to it and so in deep neuronet
typically we see that the bottom layers
and the top layers incode information
at a very different level uh meaning
that for example in computer vision
lower layer bottom layers encode
something like edges top layers higher
levels combining the features something
like cat face and so we call this deep
learning a hierarchical representation
learning method and so now the question
is if decoder layer one attends to
encoder final layer which probably has a
very different level of information is
that some kind of an information
bottleneck which actually
um motivated the original attention
mechanism and in practice I would say in
my experience doesn't really make any
difference and that's because my
experience was limited to say 25 24
layers of encoder of T5 so layer one
attended to 24 probably fine but what if
we have 10x or THX more layers would
that be problematic I'm not really
comfortable with that so I think this is
also unnecessary um uh design that maybe
we need to revisit final structure we're
going to talk about is the when we do
this there's like a bidirectional thing
in the encoder decoder Let's uh think
about that so yeah by directional input
attention is that really necessary so
when we um in had this spt B invert
stand for bidirectional 2018 when we
were solving that question answering
Squad actually was very difficult task
so if you have any additional trick it
can make a huge difference P
directionality was really uh useful like
I think maybe boosting up the squat
score by like 20 so it was really huge
thing but at scale I don't think this
matters at much this is my highly
anecdotal experience so we did in flon 2
we tried both bidirectional and
unidirectional funing didn't really make
much difference so but but I want to
point out this bidirectionality actually
bring in an engineering challenge for
modern multi-turn chat application so at
every turn the new input has to to be
encoded again and for Union directional
tension is uh much much better so here
is what I mean by that so let's think
about this um more modern conversation
between user and uh assistant how are
you bad and why and so here if we think
about the bir directional case we will
and when we generate bad we need to
encode this input with the B directional
thing which is fine and then um after
the bad is generated when we're trying
to generate why we'll need to encode how
again because how can tend to bad so we
need to do everything from scratch again
in contrast if we do uni directional one
we can do uh much much better because
now when we are trying to generate why
we don't have to redo how because we
cannot uh attend to the ne future tokens
so we don't have to do anything so if
you see the difference this part can be
cached and then this part is the only
thing that can has to be encoded again
so this kind of makes a big difference
when we think about multi multi turns
going in so I would say by directional
tension did well in 2018 which is mostly
sold by scale and now because of this
engineering challenge we don't really
need that so to conclude we have looked
into this driving force Domino driving
force covering this AI research and that
was this exponentially cheaper compute
and Associated scaling effort and so to
understand this driving force we analyze
some of the additional structures added
to the encoder decoder compared to the
decoder only and then thought about how
what that means as a from the
perspective of scaling and I wanted to
just conclude with this remark so we
have looked at these kind of analysis
which are all one can say this is just
historical um artifacts and doesn't
matter but if you do many of these now
you look at the current events you can
hopefully think about those in a more
unified Manner and then um see okay what
assumptions in my problem that I need to
revisit and are they relevant and if not
why and you have an answer to it is can
we do it with a more General thing and
scale up and so I hope you can go back
and really uh think about these problems
and together we can really shape the
future of AI in a really nice way so
that's it thanks
hi thank you for the talk um so about
the uh mix of expert uh structure if um
you know you're say what you're saying
is correct that uh how long do you think
the mix of uh experts going to stay for
the for the new large language models uh
so so one thing I have to apologize is
the architecture is kind of a um um
thing that I'm not really um comfortable
sharing a lot that's why I'm like you
know limiting a little bit to the the
future so yeah if you yeah I'll probably
just
uh skip that but I would say that seems
quite
General um so some of the changes that
you described between incoder decoder
versus decoder only like the parameter
sharing and the bir directional
attention can they not be interpreted as
less structure or sorry more structure
or less freedom for the model to
learn yeah I think one one can do that
but I think uh somewhat subjective but I
think it's a simpler structure that the
model kind of um
if
H uh but we're just saying like input
and Target are just sequences and we
just um if you have enough capacity we
can just handle both and and there are
other um cases where
like yeah so yeah I can totally see or
actually maybe I should have repeated
the question the question is uh can we
think about this parameter sharing other
structures in the incoder decoder has
actually less structure but I think it's
a little bit more complicated model and
and and that's such complications of
like it has more assumption right the
the like input and Target are different
I think that's a stronger assumption
than okay it's a sequence we deal with
the SE sequence in a unified way so that
would be just my my my my
take uh do you have any thoughts on
recent State space models like Mamba and
how that fits into the Paradigm of less
structure more structure without
reli yeah yeah
um um
okay it's hard to like uh think about it
on the the spot but I I think there like
to me I talked about this architectures
but I don't like architecture is like
kind of
a it doesn't change things too much and
maybe it's a I think multimodalities
might might bring in another challenges
like when this Transformer uh structure
might become a bottleneck when we think
about that but um yeah I I so I think
it's we Transformers have done a good
job so maybe we should think about
especially with the multimodalities
so like for cross tension and Casual
tension is like imposing perational
variance in a way for uh for multi
tension uh instead of causal and then
for for computer version there's like a
lot of learning structure for uences for
self learning what do you think about
those in terms of uh complexities that
you talk about so so the question is um
this causal attention versus the like
the B directional tension they were
probably fine in the text domain but in
the computer vision case that um being
able to attend to the the Future Part of
it is really important yeah is is that
the
question CA tension remove the like
invariance for permutation so what do
you think about like in like for compion
like you learn lot Inari right for
augmentation so what do you think about
like those as a way to structure so so
so I think the the like I don't really
like this invariances and all these
these are like how humans think uh we uh
perceive the vision like CNN for example
is like translation in variance which
was very important we thought but it's I
don't think it's that important actually
if anything now is hurting the the model
learning more General thing and so the
the machines might be learning the
vision in a completely different way
from how
do and I don't think that's problematic
so those invariances um I think is like
could be a good cutting principle but I
don't I don't like I'm not too worried
about just um not having such structures
um I yeah I'll just just try out like
just um based on some Metric um if not
having that invariant structure is
actually better and more scalable and um
I think that's probably fine and
actually even better if we do it without
the structure it's actually better
um so I actually have two questions um
one so clearly you've been thinking
about how inductive biases and structure
limit our potential potentially so I'm
just curious um what are some um big
inductive biases currently that you
think are like Big Blocks that we can
put release as or let go of um as would
be one question go the C current
structure that we should uh get rid of
just current inductive say you think cuz
clearly you've been thinking about this
right so when you look at the state of
research you must be thinking oh man
this is like a big pretty big induct
bias it' be really cool if you could let
this go so I'm just trying to see what
your uh yeah so so so when I think about
this um as an architecture um I I think
the architectures are not the current
bottleneck in my view and so partly
because I did a lot of the architecture
research and at the end we we published
this paper called do like it's saying
okay we try like 60 different
Transformer modifications pretty much
same thing and none of that really Mak
sense make a huge difference U caveat
with like now maybe the conclusion can
be different so I have a very huge bias
against like not doing the architecture
research and and one message could be
that actually the architecture is not
the bottleneck in further scaling and I
think what's the bottleneck now is this
learning objective especially on the um
supervised learning Paradigm or even
like self-supervised pre-training what
we're doing with this maximum likelihood
estimation is okay given this um this is
the only correct Target and everything
else is incorrect because probability
measure is finite so is that really a
comfortable thing to do uh teaching
signal to give the model and I think if
we think about the old days we were we
have a we could um formalize the correct
behavior for a given input very well and
maybe one answer being the single
correct answer is fine but now if you're
thinking about very general especially
the chat applications okay for like
write a poem and then you say this is
the only correct answer I think that the
implication that could be really uh
severe so I think that's really um
something that I'm not comfortable with
and partly why I'm like interested in
rhf as one instantiation of not using
this maximum likelihood instead using an
reward model as a learned objective
function which is a lot less structure
now we can scale further our lhf itself
is not really that scalable I would say
but it just showed that um we can use
this supervised deep learning to train a
model that serves as a objective
function and that really works um in a
you know cool way I think that's a great
Paradigm uh thank you great answer not
that you're being judged or anything but
uh second question I would say is um so
then in the beginning of the talk um you
talk about the big driving force to be
the exponentially cheap computer right
but some of the stuff I've been reading
says more laws ending um and we're going
towards like performance or engine of
architecture so can we rely then on cuz
right the past 50 years we had
transistors doubling or whatever M law
um but yeah that's ending so when you
talk about the compute these demands
that we've been looking at and that
structure our history we're also
uncertain necessarily about how that's
going to project the future so what are
some of your thoughts on uh yeah I think
the moris law is really uring in this
case because it's like number of
transistors but that doesn't really
matter I think what matters is a compute
availability and like GPU for example is
a very different kind of architecture
and that enabled the continuation of
this trend and I think uh right now
20203 2024 we're kind of taking the
shortcuts with like low Precision thing
uh which still I think is cool but but I
think there are many other um like GPU
level uh things but also we if we are
kind of sure about the architecture this
is my my thoughts we can like hardcode
into the tips and that can provide a lot
of benefits and I think uh like training
for training I don't think that's really
done but GPU if you think about it is
like too General maybe that is like
something that we can revisit and so I I
I'm like not losing hope and I don't see
any like trend of doing that but maybe
other things will come come as a
bottleneck like maybe energy or
something yeah so physics probably
something that we need to study again if
you don't mind me like continuing then
the problem is like we're talking about
exponential like driving forces right
you can tell me that you want a hard
coach hips but that's not the same as
telling me that there's going to be
exponential growth that we can ride
right into like paradise or whatever the
hell we're going yeah um here's here's
my very U boring answer I think we just
need to do a little bit better and at
some point the machines will be better
than us in thinking about chip design
so so I I I I think it's half joking but
uh if we look back at say this video two
years from now I think it'll be less uh
more a serious thing yeah let's let's
let's get there first all right so
thanks toan for an amazing talk