uh Dorne is a nonprofit really focused
on how to protect kids online whether
that be from cesam uh to other areas and
that's what we're going to be talking
about in this session and it with and I
first got introduced to Julie in this
General space when I was working at
Apple so um at Apple we were late to the
party in terms of detecting this bad
content uh in mail and so we started
doing that and there was a lot of
discussions around iCloud photos which
will spare for another time when I'm
probably disposed at some point um but
anyway it's great to have you and can't
wait to share with the students this
really challenging issue that's only
growing in problems so I um started my
career in Wireless technology I worked
at Motorola and then I worked at an MBO
that was trying to bring before the
iPhone was trying to bring live
streaming television to America for the
first time from South Korea Telecom um I
love technology I um thought it could
change the world which it can um and
then I was introduced to um a nonprofit
this was 13 years ago that was starting
to look at the role of technology in
child sexual abuse and I should pause
here to say um we are going to talk
about child sexual exploitation um it is
a difficult topic uh if anyone needs to
you know take a break take a deep breath
walk out of the room totally fine um
because we are GNA talk about the
realities of harm that technology can
create but we're also going to talk
about the possibilities that um of good
technology can bring um in this world so
when we started working um at Thorne 13
years ago uh the iPhone had just come
out social media was just starting and
yet we were already starting to see this
pretty dramatic increase in the rise of
child sexual abuse material online and
so what child sexual abuse material is
is the documentation in images or videos
of the sexual assaults of a child it is
illegal content to possess produce
transmit store view anything period it
is one kind of at the time the only
content in the world that is illegal
period the law in the United States for
tech companies is you don't have to
detect it but if you detect it you have
to get it off your platform and you have
to report it to the National Center for
missing and exploited children in order
to help law enforcement find those kids
who are in those images and so if you
look back to
2004 before Facebook before Instagram
before the iPhone we were dealing with
hundreds of thousands of images that
were being reported to the National
Center and already law enforcement was
drowning they're like I'm getting
hundreds of thousands of images of kids
from somewhere in the world that I'm
supposed to go find and I have no idea
where to start and then all of a sudden
social media took off the iPhone took
off and every bad actor in the world who
was doing the most horrific crime in the
world had a a camera in their hand had
an upload button to cloud storage and we
started seeing the number of child
sexual abuse um files on the internet
Skyrocket and the problem was multifold
but we focused on two specific areas of
it one was there was no way that tech
companies and all the data that they
were processing would be able to find
these images and videos and take them
down and then second there was no way
that law enforcement who's now getting
over a hundred million files and
remember this this is just the files
coming from tech companies it's not even
the files that they get from terabyte
hard drives that they seize with search
warrants so now they have this massive
amount of data a la enfor officer
specialty is working in investigation
not doing data science and trying to
figure out which file is actually
relevant and they're drowning and they
can't run their investigations tech
companies can't get this content down
and so as a nonprofit um about six years
ago in our first six years back in 12
years ago we were doing normal nonprofit
stuff we were doing research and
bringing um Engineers from tech
companies together at the time there
were no trust and safety teams and we
were saying hey there's this emerging
problem you got to do something about it
and we just kept hearing well who's
going to build the software who's going
to build the software and so we actually
started building the software and the
tools for these companies to use um and
for those of you who are familiar with
hash matching our um original solution
was simply allowing companies to half
match images and videos against a known
list of child sexual abuse files so all
the files that had been seen in the
world we would give a hash list to the
companies and say don't let these files
appear on your platform um take them
down but then um about two and a half
years ago uh generative AI came
along and as I've now seen in my career
um some of the first users of emerging
technology are criminals and especially
in this field so uh we also work on the
dark web on uh websites on the dark web
that are 100% dedicated to child abuse
and the amount of generative child abuse
that started being published as soon as
the open- source generative AI models
hit um the internet uh I I won't say the
amount they did Skyrocket from zero the
large vast amount of content that's out
there still real children but we're
seeing the amount of generative abuse
Skyrocket so now we had a new problem
not only are we dealing with a 100
million files of images of children who
are being abused in the real world but
now we have these generative AI images
that are so lifelike that a law
enforcement officer could spend a year
trying to investigate who that child is
and it's not even a real child or we've
had cases where someone has Tak taken
images of a real child off the internet
and transferred them into child abuse
files and so now we have to figure out
how again to get all this content off
the internet and help law
enforcement um find these images and I'm
sure all of you have played around with
um gen models but this is just one
example we actually U partner with
Stanford um on a research report you can
look up Stanford Thorne and gen and
child sexual abuse and this was just
demonstrating you can take these Mo
models and take an image of an adult and
slowly start to reduce the age of that
adult and do other things especially
with open- Source models to ultimately
produce illegal
material um of kids and so again I I I
recognize some of this is hard to to
hear but just to be specific about
the types of crimes we're seeing
um the issue with overburdening of law
enforcement where um they don't know if
the images and videos they're looking at
of a real child and should they spend
time on that
investigation we're seeing children who
have already been abused have um new
abuse images be produced of them and new
victimization so there was a recent case
actually you can see in the news where
someone went to Disney World with a
GoPro and took pictures of kids and then
just produced a bunch of illegal
material of those children and published
it on the dark web and so if I'm asking
like when you're thinking about the
technologies that you're building and
the harms that they could potentially
produce um I want all the innovation in
the world it's what's going to help us
make this world better but I also want
every innovator to think about the worst
possible way that your technology could
be used um we're also seeing um voice
and personas being developed with
generative AI so um one of the fastest
growing crimes against children right
now and I bet some people in this room
have experienced this um is grooming and
sextortion so um someone friending you
online flirting with you possibly
getting you to send a naked image and
then within half a second turn around
and say if you don't send me $100 I'm
going to publish that image to everyone
that you know and they're doing this to
kids who have a lot to lose but um we're
tracing it back mainly now I mean
there's perpetrators everywhere but to
organize crime in Nigeria and the Ivory
Coast and there are people who are
running hundreds of sextortion scams at
one time using generative Ai and models
and personas that they' developed to
learn how to chat with kids as if they
were a kid themselves um so how do we
intercept um something like
that so at Thorn um we started asking
ourselves okay we already had this base
of a system we call it safer um it's a
product that we built for tech companies
that allowed so picture um X so X is a
customer every image and video on X runs
through our system and when we first
launched four years ago like I said we
would match every image and video
against a known set of hashes of child
sexual abuse material to make sure an
image that the world already knew was
illegal and abusive would not see the
light of day um now we've integrated uh
AI classifiers so predictive technology
to predict if an image or video and now
text based harms um are entering these
platforms and allowing those content
moderation teams to take action based on
their um terms of service so um our
product Suite started with uh safer
match which is Hash matching we
introduced safer predict which I'll just
show you a little bit more in a minute
and I forgot to look over here at
questions are there any questions
a couple things we have we invest a good
amount in research in two types of
research one um we talk directly with
kids to understand like what are they
what's happening to them online so that
we can um get ahead of it and on
technical research so the bulk we look
even though we're nonprofit we look a
lot like a small software company now
and we've had a data science team for
about six years that specializes in
computer vision and machine learning and
um we do a ton of
R&D to try to stay ahead of that and
then um one of the other things that was
really critical is that because we're
embedded in the tech companies um when
open AI launched two and a half years
ago we worked with them and about 12
other of the generative AI companies
anthropic inflection Microsoft Google
and we got all of those companies to
come together with us and agree on a
common set of by Design principles to
reduce the likelihood that their models
would be used for um this type of abuse
so a couple
different ways we stay ahead of it that
is tricky so as I said before uh cam is
illegal to produce possess transmit look
at and that holds true for us too the
only people who can do that in the
United States are law enforcement and
even within law enfor for ment those who
are on this crime type um and then the
national Center for missing and
exploited children which is um written
into law as the repository for all of
this content so we did a couple things
we built a partnership with the national
Center for missing and exploited
children and embedded um a lot of our
data science team there to train on the
largest repository of child sexual abuse
material in the world um and with with
law enforcement um and we have to we
can't our data scientists can't look at
it so we've had to get feedback from
them on um false positives and then for
our text models um we have actually been
able to use actual um data from grooming
conversations to train uh models but
it's interesting because without access
to there's other people trying to solve
this problem and they've been training
models on pornography and children and
they're just not as good because this
isn't pornography this is abuse and it
is different and so having access to
that data set has been really important
in the quality of the predictive models
that we've been able to build so how
we've built our our original um system
that we built was an enterprise system
that sits within each company I's S3
bucket or their own infrastructure and
they run um the matching or the
classification and the results go to
their content moderation team their
content moderation team gets to choose
what they take action on but if it is
illegal they have to report it and we
have a direct API into the national
Center for missing exploited children um
lately we've launched an API model which
makes it easier for companies to to get
started if they're not ready for an
Enterprise model and this is just kind
of a visualization of how our predictive
models work we can predict on image
video text obviously um these require
more manpower on their end so you have
to have human moderators if you're going
to use predictive models in content
moderation because you're going to have
some degree of false positives whereas
if you're doing hash matching they've
mostly been triple verified it's a match
is a match
you can report it without looking but
and so a lot of startup companies they
will start with just hash matching like
just plug in the hash matching let me
try to get the worst of the worst off my
system and report it but as you become
more mature like an open AI who we work
with um you know you don't want any of
this um or an X you don't want any of
this and you have humans who will look
at this um the one caveat I will add
that's not on the software side is
The Human Side of content moderation is
very difficult you are asking humans not
just in our space but depending on what
companies choose to moderate hate speech
terrorism all of that you are putting
humans to view the worst of humanity
over and over and over again so one of
the other parts of our product Suite is
uh the review tool that was designed
with mental health and mind so when the
moderators get all of the stuff coming
out of this pipeline everything on their
screen is blurred like the upper or like
that image so everything is blurred
there's a text description of what is in
the image so they can choose to look at
it or not the sound for video is turned
off automatically so you don't have to
hear the sound of any of these videos um
and you can do take a a cursor pen to to
view only the parts of the image that
you need to view to make a judgment call
on to as to what action you want to take
with that in your moderation flow so
that's just something to think about is
like how do you combine addressing a
harm like this at scale with um kind of
a ux UI mental health perspective of
when we're talking about all the harms
um on the internet this is my my last
slide um and everyone's going to say oh
it's going the wrong direction uh that's
uh that's okay so this is um I guess
it's very small text but just to show
the sheer volume of what we're
processing I think this past year we
processed about 200 billion files for
our partners we're in about 60 different
tech companies um today but the um
orange is the amount of child sexual
abuse material that's been detected and
the blue you can see how small the blue
was as a percentage of orange just a few
years ago but we're starting to get to a
place where the blue is the classified
the predictive models detecting and
we're now almost more than half of what
we are detecting on these platforms is
from our predictive models and the
reason why that's important is because
if you go back to the mission right our
mission is to End online child sexual
abuse to get as much content down if you
are um just finding hash matches you're
finding the content of children who most
likely have already been recovered and
it's just recirculated content which you
still want to take down because it's
horrific illegal content but the
predicted models are finding content
that the world has never seen which most
likely is a child who's been abused
right now and will most likely lead to
an investigation and so just one of
those stories actually one of our first
um uh customers who um used our
classifier they were our first beta
partner
um are you guys familiar with SmugMug
the the they they're one of our
customers and um they implemented the
classifier and they were beta customer
and their head of content moderation
came in and talked to Thor after this
happened and he said you know in my
moderation queue I implemented the class
classifier I saw that there had been a
hit and he's like as soon as I saw the
little you know notification I thought
I'm going to tell Thorn you know there's
a false positive I'm going to give some
feedback make the model better and he
opened up the file and it was a file of
abuse and of a child who's about eight
or nine years old and he looked at the
file he looked at the Tim stamp he
looked at the account he went into the
account he found cuz he they were only
um screening on upload so they hadn't
screened their backlog the spike is
customers who choose to go back and
Screen backlog of content um not just
upload so he goes back and looks in the
account there's about 200 images of
abuse of the same little girl he
automatically reports it within 24 hours
this was in the United States within 24
hours law enforcement in Austria went
knocked on the door recovered the child
arrested the dad he'd been abusing her
for years and Publishing it on the open
web so these this is real life work and
like I said I um our team is mainly
engineers and data scientists that do
this work mainly that we've recruited
from uh the private sector who've come
to do these jobs and I often have people
say to me like how do you like how do
you retain Talent like that in a mission
driven organization and the something I
say is like when that's the call you get
from law enforcement who says thank you
for what you just built I just rescued a
child instead of thanks for what you
just built I added a dollar to my stock
price usually those Engineers um like to
stay and do this work at least for I
sometimes I say it's a tour Duty like
try a gra Spears see how you like it um
so I'll pause there and we can answer
questions
but for our first six years years more
traditional asking for donations many
folks in Silicon Valley were some of our
initial donors because they understood
the harms and the approach um we got
very very lucky in 2019 we won a big
Phil philanthropy contest to inject um
about $60 million for us to scale our
software but that was built on the
premise that we could build an earned
Revenue model so we actually sell our
software to tech companies and then on
the law enforcement side I actually I
didn't mention this the predictive uh
Solutions we've now integrated into
forensic tools for law enforcement so
when they seize hard drives they run it
through our prediction tools which can
take you know gigabyte hard drives down
to like 2,000 images that they actually
need to pay attention to in a minute um
but we where possible we sell software
to law enforcement and we give it away
um so it's a hybrid philanthropy earned
Revenue
model actually the um if I anwers if I'm
going to answer this correctly I think
the company can control what they want
to do like how tight they want to focus
it depending on how much Manpower they
have to review false positives
we uh this was the Apple conversation um
but you're also seeing some of this
backlash with meta changing their
content moderation um and then you see
it with the arrest of was it the signal
founder um Telegraph sorry Telegraph
founder was arrested recently and then
he just shifted his policies to do child
sexual abuse uh detection so
um I don't think that they I don't think
privacy um and safety can't live
together so there is a need for
encrypted environments there's a need
for
um uh private communication and there's
a need for safety so we always say you
know in the places where it is public
information or um not encrypted you
should be detecting there's no reason
why you shouldn't every company in their
terms of service says do not use our
platform for illegal activity and most
of them call out child sexual abuse
material because it is the one illegal
piece of content um most of them don't
actually have a system to proactively
enforce their terms of service so um our
position is in your areas where you're
not encrypted do detection and then
similar actually the Australian e safety
commission just issued some guidelines
around this saying sure have encrypted
environments but then create other
mechanisms other ways of creating safety
in those situations so you can screen
Believe It or Not people use child
sexual abuse material in their um
profile images um we've seen it on
Spotify we've seen it on WhatsApp we've
seen it on uh other messaging apps
so you can't be perfect we can't detect
it encrypted environments but we can
detect um everywhere else and be
transparent about it I guess that's
another important thing is like if
you're a company that hosts content and
you don't want to host this stuff be
clear to your users we will not stand
for you using our platform for abusing
children and we're going to put in place
these systems and by most research um
customers are good with that
so yeah interesting I was just in slack
with my team today because we um we were
at the white house uh when they few
months ago when they wrote the AI safety
executive order that was just withdrawn
yesterday um and what someone on our
team sits on the nist Standards Board
and just helped write some of the
standards for red teaming AI models to
ensure they don't produce child sexual
abuse material
um we we're very apolitical organization
this issue
transcends politics and we've found that
that to be true um honestly I I don't
think it will have much effect because
again this this this content is it's not
fuzzy it's you're not being asked to
make a judgment call on whether you know
you should allow this or not this
content is illegal in I think 170
countries around the world and
even in um Zuckerberg's five minute
videos the I woke up to his face the
morning he published that and I was like
good morning Mark tell me what you think
about content moderation and
um and if you listen to it carefully
because it got everyone up in arms with
for you know variety of reasons um but
he did call out this area and say not
only are we not going to disinvest in
this but this will be an area we
continue to invest in so I don't don't
think it'll be affected our area in
particular will be affected much by the
new um and the AI companies even though
like the executive order and some of
this stuff will be called back I still
think they're going to do it they don't
want to be known as the company that
produces child sexual abuse material
like stability AI got drugged through
the mud because their first model they
hadn't cleaned their data set that they
built the model off of and most of the
perpetrators were using their first
model to build child sexual abuse
material and they got trashed which is
not good for any investor and so it just
doesn't build value to do this the wrong
way oh that's a good question that might
be outside of
my um expertise the one thing I will say
and I'm jaded so take it with a grain of
salt
um I wouldn't I
mean everyone ask this but
you I was talking to some the other day
I said tell everyone you love that when
they get the phone call with your voice
saying you're kidnapped to hang up the
phone and call you and make sure it's
not you so all of our like I have three
kids right they're on Tik Tok they're
everywhere I'm like you know that your
likeness has been scraped and your voice
is going to be used in a scam your like
your image is going to be used in scam
your video is going to be used in a scam
and it's going to be used to scam your
family and it's going to be used to scam
others so I would love to say do not put
your children's likeness out there but
our kids go do it themselves um beyond
that I don't have a lot of expertise on
other data um and how to keep them
private I I really think I was just
talking to Pam on my team who's here um
I just think we're in a different era
where we're going to be able to put all
the software you know Sol Solutions in
place but it's really going to require
actually a different kind of parenting
where parents have to understand how
fast is technology is moving how it's
going to be used for harm and it's going
to require a do dialogue as much as a
software um solution so and that doesn't
totally answer your question but bit of
a jaded perspective from
me when a company uh gets a hit right
they have to legally actually confirm
that it is illegal content so in that
you know the the machine has said it's
illegal but no one really knows it's
illegal until um they put eyes on it so
in that instance they can do it as long
as when they view it they then report it
to the National if you view it as a
Content moderator you have to then
report it and then that alleviates any
legal responsibility
I don't know yet but my CFO just texted
me that on my way here was like whatat
are we going to do with Stargate and I
was like I don't know can you let me
know so H good
question that's something we think about
a lot because 10 years ago the only well
the vast majority abuse that was online
was um the documentation of the physical
sexual assault of a child and my head of
research says that she said you know 10
years ago geography used to be a
protective barrier if you didn't live
near or with an abuser you would not be
abused and the internet has completely
eliminated that so our recent research
shows one in 10 kids has either produced
or seen a generative AI sexual abuse
image so 10% of kids in America um 30%
of kids have been approached by someone
online they think is an adult for a
sexual interaction 30% of kids um and so
we now have this world where
um you know when it was SE physical
sexual assault it was harder to prevent
it was the in school like tell someone
you know but now we are trying to figure
out if if there's interactions online
that are going to lead to this type of
abuse can we intercept those earlier and
that's where the um text based harms uh
detector is starting to go so there are
patterns in grooming that you can detect
that will tell you if that conversation
is most likely to go to an abusive place
and we're trying to flag those for
Content moderators early um I wouldn't
say that that is 100% yet but that's one
way we can get ahead of it another way
that some platforms are doing that I
don't think Thorne will have a role in
but um you uh meta an Instagram just did
this if you uh look at they took down an
entire network I can't remember the name
of the network but it was an organized
crime syndicate on their platform that
was creating all of these accounts and
then they would they would have a
similar pattern of how they would friend
kids and then of the communication with
those children and they were grooming
those children for harm that pattern
recognition they can find all day long
and that's what they did they looked at
this pattern of abuse and then they took
all those accounts down at once and
that's getting to prevention but um it
is happening at such a scale right now
on these networks it's really difficult
to get ahead
of yeah that's um we partnered with them
a lot on This research I
um you know the research continues I
think some of the researchers went to
other things and we still collaborate in
some areas there's other institutions
around the world that focus on this um I
think it was like loss in general in in
our space in particular because they
were doing some good research work and
they were a
collaborator um but it continues in
other
areas the initial idea for Thorne was um
our our tagline was to drive Technology
Innovation to combat child sexual
exploitation and we really thought we
would just be a researcher and a
convenor um because again it was 13
years ago and actually one of our other
board members who I asked to join the
board at the time she didn't tell me
this till a few years later um but she
said Julie I have to tell you I I joined
the board and I thought oh this is a
nice small nonprofit I don't really
think we're gonna have enough work to do
um well it just like took off and so I
we couldn't imagine at the time how big
of an issue this would become or um how
it would have changed because we
couldn't predict the technology shifts
um and
so I think one of the key things for us
has been back to I think the original
question of like how do we stay ahead of
the curve we've reinvented the
organization probably four or five times
over 13 years to try to I feel like when
we started we were like behind behind
this flood of harm that was happening
and now to see this wave of generative
Ai and for us to be at the table with
those companies um is encouraging I
wouldn't say we're ahead of the game but
we're maybe at the starting line now
where innovators are starting to think
of harms they want to do good they want
to build safe platforms um and we're
able to be there I think the next phase
is how do we get ahead of some of the
and anticipate some of the Harms
it's interesting I wouldn't say anyone's
against partnership like I find that um
most of the barriers to doing this work
are uh knowledge that this is even a
harm so this isn't something that a lot
of people talk about and yet it affects
anywhere that there is user generated
content there is child abuse I've said
that and no one has been able to prove
me wrong anywhere you have user
generated images videos or texts there
will be child abuse um so that's a very
broad swath of the internet and a lot of
those folks just don't even think their
platform could be used for harm so they
don't think about it which is why we
have a sales team and goes and knocks on
doors let me introduce you and then once
there's knowledge that this is an issue
and they might want to address it
barrier to doing something is usually
money or prioritization so this is a
cost center it's not going to drive any
value for the company and then the
company has to decide do we build it
ourselves or do we buy it or do we put
our head in the sand and not do anything
and you have different companies who do
different things usually what we find is
that it is much harder for startup
companies to do something because
they're putting all the money into
product development they just need to
scale they need to get users that's
their priority which I totally
understand but if what we have seen with
companies is if you implement safety
early in the development cycle your
platform doesn't get known as a place
where people can get away with things so
usually these you know the the hubs of
abuse where we find the most content is
when we go into a platform that never
had any safeguards and you just start to
clear out the bad content which is also
some of the spikes right it's not like
everyone's a bad guy there's a few bad
actors and you need to find them on your
platform get them off get all the
content off so um I don't think anyone
is averse to working
it's just knowledge money
ability um so we we really need the
company to take action so we want the
company to implement the software and do
it themselves and then law enforcement
mainly focuses on finding kids they
don't usually focus on like looking at a
platform that's a bad actor because
again the law in the United States is a
company does not have to look for this
content but if they know they have it
they then have to take action um and so
our what we're trying to do is get the
company to know they have it um
implement the software and then have an
easy way to take action
yes thank you
[Applause]