This is week two of the systems lecture
where we try to leverage the most out of
the hardware we have to make uh models
train
faster. And last week we talked about
parallelism within a single GPU and this
week we're talking about parallelism
across multiple GPUs. So this is a
picture you should have in your head. So
we have a bunch of nodes. These are
basically you know computers that have
each have a number of GPUs usually eight
and within each GPU there's a bunch of
uh streaming multipprocessors or SMS and
which actually do the work and you see
that in green here are essentially the
memory and the communication. So within
each SM you have an very small L1 cache
um with on a GPU you have u high
bandwidth memory HPM which is bigger and
then you have these u links that connect
the different
GPUs. So the way to think about it is
that compute has to happen within the SM
on these ALUS right and compute needs
inputs and uh needs to write outputs and
generally the the inputs and outputs are
can be relatively far if you're lucky
they're on the L1 cache if you're say
less unlucky they're in HPM and now this
week we're talking about multi- uh GPU
and multi- node training where the data
that you might need might be across on
another GPU you right? So the name of
the game is how do you structure all
your computation to avoid data transfer
bottlenecks because we want to remember
keep the arithmetic intensity high. We
want to saturate our GPUs make them go
um humalong and generally data transfer
is going to be a lot slower. So we have
to that's going to be the bottleneck.
So last week we saw a bunch of different
techniques to try to do that within a
GPU including fusion and tiling. So the
idea basically is that instead of
reading and writing from HPM you can
load into L1 cache or or I guess uh you
know shared memory which is using the
same type of um you know uh you know has
the same speed um and just work there on
your local scratchpad and then write out
to HPM um only judiciously. Um and this
week we started looking at communication
across GPUs and nodes where we have to
replicate and shard our models and
parameters and optimize our states. And
there it's uh the the way we do that
will determine the the
cost. So here's a kind of a I'm taking a
little bit of liberty to put everything
in kind of one hierarchy you can think
from small fast to big slow. So the
smallest and fastest is on a single node
single GPU you have L1 cache that's
extremely fast but very small and then
you have uh HPM on a single GPU and then
between
um uh GPUs on the same same node we have
MVL link and then finally we have you
know MV switch and of course this is all
in the Nvidia
ecosystem. Um so so the idea is that
many of the core concepts of minimizing
data transfer are really the same but
now uh the mechanics are a bit different
because um L1 is behaves differently
than these kind of envy um
switches. Um so this lecture is going to
be mostly about concretizing the
concepts from the last lecture in in
code. There's going to be a few new
things, but um Tatsu did an excellent
job of giving you an overview of all the
different types of parallelism. I'm
going to try to anchor it in the code so
we can more deeply understand what's
going on. Um and then u we're going to
have uh I'm going to refer to this
standard out file here which is the
output of running this this lecture. Um
there were some minor issues I'll spare
you of where if you have multi- um
processing then this uh this framework
doesn't quite work. Um okay so this
lecture has uh two parts. one. In part
one, we're going to look at the building
blocks um collective operations which we
discussed last time, how this is
implemented in nickel and pietorrch and
then we're going to do some benchmarking
and then in part two we're going to look
at actually distributed training data
tensor and par pipeline
parallelism. Okay, so let's start with
collective operations. So collective
operations are these primitives that are
used generally for distributed
programming and collective means that
you have um you know many nodes. These
are actually quite old from the at least
the the 80s in the parallel programming
uh literature. Um and generally they
provide a better abstraction than trying
to manage the pointto-point
communication um yourself. So these are
really tried and true um um you know
primitives that have stood the test of
time. So a bit of uh terminology. So
world size refers essentially the number
of devices for example four and the rank
um sort of confusingly if you're used to
kind of linear algebra is is actually
just refers to device. So we have rank
zero rank one rank two and rank three if
you have four devices. Okay. So um the
collective operations are as as follows.
Um so um starting from you know
broadcast the idea is you have t0 on one
of the ranks and you just want to put it
on all the other ranks or all ranks.
Okay so that's very straightforward.
Scatter is similar but you have four
values and you want to put each of the
values on different ranks. So each of
the ranks get different values, not the
same um value. Um gather is the sort of
the inverse of scatter where you have
each rank having a different value and
then you bring them all together onto
one rank. Um you know reduce is the same
as gather except for instead of
concatenating you add them. Um all
gather is the same as gather except for
you just do it for all the destinations.
um gather was just uh rank zero or you
know rank one or rank two or any
individual rank all gather as you do it
for all of
them and then finally reduce scatter I
couldn't um you know find a a good
picture of this so I'm reusing the one
from um from last time is um like reduce
um where you take a bunch of different
values and you um you know add them or
perform other commutive operation on
them and uh put it on one rank. But like
scatter um you're going to be um putting
different pieces of uh the vector or
tensor on different
ranks. Okay. And remember that all
reduce is equivalent to reduce uh plus
all gather. Um so the way to remember
this terminology is as follows. um
because it can get kind of confusing
like which one's all gather, which one's
reduce scatter is that reduce just means
you're performing some um you know
associative and commutive operation like
sum or min and max or average. Um
broadcast scatter is the inverse of
gather and all just means all
destination is all you know
devices. Okay, so hopefully this is a
review from from last time.
Um,
so actually any questions before I move
on since we're going to build on these
primitives? So it's it's useful if
everyone
understands. Okay. So now let's see how
this is actually implemented in um
starting with the hardware. Okay. So um
here's a classically what uh you know
hardware for GPUs looks like. So um this
is kind of in the home you have a
computer I guess um and you have your
CPUs and generally you have your GPUs um
on one node that communicate via a PCIe
bus. Um and if you have to go connect uh
communicate between different um nodes
then this is all connected to Ethernet.
So this is kind of typically how you
know machines were built. If you buy a
GPU and you're uh for you know gaming or
something um this is kind of probably
what your your setup looks like. Um as
we'll see this is uh kind of suboptimal
because um there's a lot of overhead
when the data gets needs to get shipped
from GPU to GPU. it has to go through
you know the kernel get copied into
buffers and then go through this kind of
a you know transport over Ethernet and
that introduces a lot of
overhead. So what has happened in modern
times uh with scientific computing and
you know deep learning is that u if you
know that you're going to just string a
bunch of GPUs together and do something
uh together then we're just going to
hook the GPUs up you know directly
basically um so in the Nvidia ecosystem
um we have MVLink that directly connects
the the GPUs um therefore bypassing the
CPU you don't need to go through kind of
the you know um the kernel of the of the
of the host machine. Um, and across even
across nodes, uh, we can connect the
GPUs directly via MV switch. So
therefore, we're bypassing Ethernet and
because Ethernet was developed a long
time ago, uh, clearly not for for for
uh, these type of applications. So MV
switch just and MVLink kind of skip all
that and just optimize directly for um,
the type of workloads that we're
interested in.
So if you look at H100's um each um node
has or sorry each GPU has 18 MV you know
links um generation 4 coming out so
that's uh gives you a total bandwidth of
900 gigabytes um if you compare to um
these um it's certainly a lot faster
than PCIe and it's certainly way faster
than you know Ethernet um and um in
comparison. Um, if you think about the
cost of just going from the SM to, you
know, reading from high bandwidth
memory, um, that's still quite a bit
faster, uh, by a factor of, you know,
four or so. Um, and of course, these
numbers are constantly changing with a
new black wells. Uh, this number is
like, you know, a like two or three
times um, more, I believe. Um, okay.
Yeah. for the PC like does it go to the
uh CPU and then like with another GPU or
it's directly used with the GPU. So the
question is for the PCIe where how does
the data get uh you know transferred? I
think it has to still go through the
CPU. Was there another
question? And the PI was I mean it's
developed for you know things like other
things are connected to it as well like
your sound card or your SSD hard drive.
So it's not really it's sort of like a
general purpose uh you know uh bus for
communication of devices. Yeah. MV link
also has connection with CPU.
Yeah. So the question is MVL link also
connects to the uh CPU. We're going to
see a bit later how um I think maybe
just in the slide how things are
connected. Yeah. So you still need to
talk to your CPU of course.
Yeah. Okay. So there's this command uh
that you can run um and this produces
some you know output which allows you to
see um how the GPUs are actually
connected. So, I ran this on, you know,
our our cluster. There's um eight GPUs.
I guess you won't be able to get eight
GPUs, but um but uh I guess if you
could, this is what it would look like.
And you see that between every pair of
GPUs, there's MV18
um you know, connecting. Um there's also
um these kind of network u you know,
cards and and other
things. Okay.
Um, oh yeah. So then network cards are
basically what gives you the PCIe
connection and and the the
CPUs. So um, okay. So that's the
hardware. So how do you use the
hardware? So Nvidia has spent a lot of,
you know, time developing really good
software on top of uh, their I guess
really good hardware. Um, and there's a
collective communication library by
Nvidia called Nickel. Um and this
essentially translates the collective
operations which we looked at before
like all reduce um into low-level
packets that need to be sent between
GPUs. So this library actually does a
lot of work because it allows the
programmer just to operate the level of
I need this tensor to appear on all the
machines and it just happens. Okay. Um
so you know just a little bit of what uh
what happens is when you configure um
setup nickel you bring up a bunch of um
you know devices and there's some
communication that happens to figure out
the topology of the hardware it
optimizes the path between the GPUs and
then uh when you actually call these
collective communication operations and
then launch CUDA kernels to send and
receive
data. Okay, so that's nickel. It's
provided as a as a library. But nickel
is still a bit too um low level to us
because most of what we're doing is um
you know in Python. So there's a
pietorch has this torch distributed
library which essentially provides a
clean interface for these collective
operations. Now from the comfort of your
PyTorch pro pytorch program you can just
write all gather into tensor on a tensor
and it will appear on all the uh on
different
ranks. Um it also has this uh nice uh
useful feature that it supports multiple
backends for different hardware. So in
particular nickel remember was for GPU
but you can also run collective
operations. Remember this is not GPU
specific. it's just for any set of um
you know devices. So you can also do it
for CPU using this back end called uh
glue. Um so if you're debugging stuff on
your laptop for your assignment for
example, you can use glue and still be
able to run things without even a a GPU.
Um so anyway that that's another
advantage of having these highle
primitives is that they're much more
portable than having to uh you know only
having something that's very GPU uh
specific. Um of course the performance
is going to really depend on the
hardware but at least logically you can
make sure your code um
runs. Um, Pyro distributed also supports
other highle things like uh, FSTP which
Tatsu talked about last lecture, but
we're not going to use this in this
class because in the spirit of
developing things from scratch, um,
that's just what we're going to
do. Okay, so uh let's look at some
examples of how to distributed
collective operations work. Okay, so
there's this uh utility function I wrote
um which you can take a look at it in
the code if you want which takes a
function and just um runs this uh
basically it's a wrapper around um
Python multipprocessing where it it just
runs four processes that execute this
function. So when you're in this
function, you should think about it as
there's actually worldsiz number of uh
processes running this identical
function where the rank indexes from
zero one all the way to world size minus
one. Okay, so right now I'm stepping
through uh just one of the ranks um uh
because lectures are not parallel. Um
and so generally what you do is you the
first thing the process uh needs to
initialize itself and you essentially
the they need to kind of find each other
right because you're
multi-processor running a lot of
processes they need to connect to a uh a
single host so that they can you know
figure know that each other exist. Um so
note that this is not where all of the
data goes. The data goes through nickel
but this is just for kind of
coordination. Um and since we have
a a GPU we can use nickel. Otherwise you
would use uh glue. Um okay so after you
set up um so now we're going to do some
stuff. There's this useful um function
called barrier which um basically waits
for all the processes in your process
group to get to this uh point right
remember everything's running
asynchronously
um and in some cases you just want to
have a synchronization point so barrier
does that um the reason I put it here is
actually sort of for trivial reasons
because I want all these print
statements to kind of be grouped
together um but there's other reasons
why you might unused barrier as we'll
get to later. So I'm going to for each
of these um groups construct a tensor.
So the tensor is 01 23 U plus you know
the rank. Um so I'm going to print out
um for each rank before the all reduce.
What does it look like? Okay, so here's
what it looks like. Um can people read
that in the back? Yes. Okay, good. All
right. So on rank zero it's 0 1 2 3.
Rank one 1 2 3 4 and so on. And notice
that because it's async the orders uh
it's just out of order in whatever order
it happens to print. Okay. So each
um um rank has a different tensor and
then then you all reduce. So all reduce
you pass in that tensor. You say I want
to sum it. Um in this case I'm not going
to do async but you can do async. um to
uh which is useful for overlapping
communication and um in computation. Um
and then you know afterwards what
happens after all reduce as advertised
basically for the first component you
you add them up you get six this you get
10 14 and 18. Okay. So after all reduce
the um basically this tensor gets
overwritten with um the the
corresponding um
sum. So it's very very kind of you know
nice and simple to
use. Okay. Um so so let's do reduce
scatter.
So reduce scatter
um I'm going to create an an input um
which is uh has dimension you know world
size in which case this is four um and
um I'm going to allocate an output
because reduce scatter is not going to
operate in in place this is just going
to be a scalar um so before the reduce
scatter um this is you know what it
looks like um I have my you know input
as before output um you know happens to
be zeros but it could be any value um
since I didn't initialize it and then
after the reduce scatter I pass in the
input and the output and I'm going to
sum um then I get um essentially what
happens is that for the first component
I sum and that goes on rank zero for the
se uh second component I sum and it goes
on rank one and so on. Okay, so as you
notice it is producing the same
operation as all reduce except for the
the output is sort of scattered across
all the different um
ranks. Okay, so now let's do all gather.
So um I'm going to just directly use the
output of reduce scatter which is um
this um as the input and then I'm going
to allocate an empty array for the the
output
um and then so so before um the all
gather um the input is this and the
output um I guess are just arbitrary
values um and uh after I do the all
gather
um you know what
happens is I get the all these uh
tensors to to show up in on all the
devices. Okay, so this is just a kind of
also an example. Uh hopefully now you're
very convinced that reduce scatter plus
all gather is just all reduce because I
computed exactly the same quantity as I
did for all
reduce. Okay,
questions this clear?
Yeah. In reduce scatter are we keeping
track of which GPU? So the question is
uh in reduced scatter do you keep track
of which index goes to which GPU? So by
convention
um the the dimensionality has to be the
basically the world's I mean it could be
a general tensor but one of the
dimensions is the world size and it just
you know infers that um basically what
you want to do is um the output is the
let's say the
um sorry um the input has to be
basically world size and then it knows
that uh basically the corresponding
you know computations go to each uh of
the
outputs. Yeah, you have to be a bit
careful with the making sure the
dimensionality uh align. So you know
going through this uh you know smaller
examples can be
helpful. Is there another
question? Okay. So finally we're now in
this um process that's uh running and
when you're done you just you know clean
up. Okay. So um so so far we've talked
about these collective operations um bit
about how they're implemented in you
know pietorch and it's uh nickel and
then pietorch um let's do a bit of um
you know benchmarking
um in the spirit of what we did in um
assignment uh or the first lecture or
rather the second lecture um we're going
to focus on one node uh you know for
now. So let's do all reduce. So I'm
going to have this uh tensor of 100
million elements
um and a world size of four. Okay. So
um I'm going to just allocate a tensor.
Um and generally as I I think um as you
hopefully are uh can appreciate now that
when you benchmark you have to really be
careful to kind of clean your pallet in
some sense like you um in this case I'm
going to warm up basically com run the
operation um once um and then
synchronize and do barrier. Some of this
is I think probably a bit defensive but
but just to be but just to be safe so
that all the kernels get you know loaded
and whatever needs to be kind of
computed gets computed and then I'm
going to start the clock all reduce and
then synchronize again and and and stop
the clock.
Okay. So um now I can look at the how
long that took. Okay. So if I scroll
down to here, um I guess this is not
that informal. I should have printed in
microsconds probably. Um it was I guess
very quick um some number of uh seconds.
Um and now let's measure the the
bandwidth which is the number of
gigabytes that were actually transferred
in aggregate per second. Okay. So the
way we do that is we have to think about
what actually gets transferred here. So
there's a tensor with that element size
and the size of each element is um I
guess this I think this is float um 32.
So that would be
uh you know uh
two or sorry four four bytes um
and and
um and so that's the size in bytes.
Okay. So now this is a little bit uh you
know subtle. So
um how many bytes are actually sent or
or transferred sent received um so each
tensor sitting on a rank has size bytes
okay and it needs to send it to world
size minus one you know other you know
machines or or not or ranks rather so
there but there's a factor of
two so why is there a factor of
too because you're doing an all reduce
remember. So you need to send all the
distinct um you know elements into
basically one place. It needs to get uh
summed up and then that needs to go back
to
everyone. Okay. So a rank needs to kind
of send the input out and then receive
the output. So that's why there's a
there's a factor of two there. And so
the total duration is um the world size
times the the actual duration that
passed. So I guess we're just kind of
assuming that every we're we're you know
if there's four processors that's sort
of like four times as much wall clock
time that happened. And the bandwidth is
just the bytes over the
duration. Okay. So what do we get here?
um is about 277 gigabytes you know per
second. Okay. So you know I think um for
H100
um be above I think I claimed that there
was something like 900 gigabytes uh per
second. Now of course as we know your
mileage varies depending on the size of
the tensors and the exact number of uh
devices and the weather and what no not
the weather but uh but you know various
factors. So your um your mileage might
vary. So it's always good to benchmark
to see what is actually the number of uh
gigabytes per second you're you're
getting. Okay. So so reduce scatter is
going to be very very similar. So let's
just go through this very quickly. So we
create a input um which is world size
times number of elements. So each rank
is going to have this um this the matrix
um
and and so we're going to warm up and
then um start the clock reduce uh
scatter
um stop the clock and then see how long
it took. Well, okay, that's not helpful.
Um and then let's look at the uh the
bandwidth. So the number of scent bytes
is no factor of two here because in
reduce scatter remember all you're doing
is you're you're sending um you know
your inputs into you know one place. If
you just think about uh reduce right all
the elements just go into one place and
that's it. And scatter just means that
different components of your tensor are
going to different places but it's
effectively it's it's like a you know
reduce. Okay. So if you do the same
calculation
um you'll see that it's I guess I get 70
in this case. Um so I don't exactly know
why it's exactly 70 as opposed to some
other number. Um I guess one could
speculate that all reduce generally
there's more traffic that you know
happens and um all reduces are you know
potentially more optimized. I think that
Nvidia hardware has this kind of sharp
acceleration that actually does sort of
um some of these um computations in you
know in the actual network um which
shaves off a factor of two but I don't
know if that completely accounts for a
difference here. Um there's a lot of
stuff that happens in nickel that it's a
little bit hard to kind of reason about
the performance exactly. Hence um
benchmarking.
Yeah. Another question about the set
bytes and or the data bytes and how that
was calculated specifically. It looks
like it calculates just like the uh data
that's being sent to the output. But
what about like the input? So the
reduction step. I was wondering how it
gets the inputs to do the reduction. So
the the question is it seems like this
is just the uh the bytes for the output
and what about the input. So to be clear
I am assuming that the inputs just are
already on the device. So I'm not
counting that time and just uh I'm just
counting what needs to happen to do the
reduce scatter.
Is this just a scatter operation?
This is a reduce scatter operation. So,
so you need reduction step. Um, so this
function does reduce scatter. So, it's
one operation.
Okay. I mean like we count it twice in
the previous uh because we were doing
reduction for half two by half.
So you're saying that for all reduce um
there were there was a 2x because you
needed to reduce and then you needed to
you know uh spread out again. Um for
reduce scatter I mean it's just a name.
It's called reduce scatter but it's
really just um a
reduction. Okay. And you can also see uh
based on this that um if you do reduce
scatter and you do all gather each of
those is doesn't have the factor of two.
So when you add them up you get a factor
of two which is another way to see that
all reduces um
twice. Okay.
Um and there's some references you can
go read about how to benchmark and um
these collective
operations. Okay. So let's now talk
about the distributed um training uh
piece. So our general approach here is
going to be I'm going to walk through a
barebones implementation of each
strategy on deep um MLPS essentially. So
recall that you generally are in the
regime where MLPS are the compute
bottleneck and transformers um not the
attention. So in some ways even though
this is a very simple architecture it's
fairly representative of the type of um
you know workloads that you'll see. Um
okay so let's start with data
parallelism.
Um actually just one note is that data
tensor and pipeline parism are you can
just think about them as different ways
of cutting up uh your um your either
your model or your your data which
hopefully I'll uh depict visually
here. Okay. So in data parallelism um
here's your model assume it has four
layers. Each layer of the MLP is just a
matrix multiply where this is the dimen
hidden dimension. Um and so the data is
also a matrix which is um there's the
batch dimension and then the hidden
dimension and data parallel just cuts
along the batch dimension into um you
know essentially smaller um you know
pieces. Okay. So now each rank is going
to get a different slice of the data. So
let's uh do an example here. Um so I'm
going to generate some sample data. So
let's say I have batch size of 128,
hidden dimension of
1,024. Um and then just generate some
random
data. Okay. So I have batch size by
number of dimension and I'm going to run
this data parallel algorithm um or DDP.
So
um so here um I'm going to so I got past
this this data. There's a batch size and
the dimension as as uh claimed from
before. Now I uh divide the batch size
by the world size. So I get the local
batch size. That's how many um uh you
know how big the batch size is on a a
given rank. Um and then I'm going to
based on the rank just um figure out
which um starting and ending indices um
of size local batch size I need to um
access and then get the corresponding
data from that. So basically I'm just
like reaching in and grabbing some
subset of the rows based on the on the
rank. Okay. So now I'm setting up the
the MLP here. Um and this is done very
um sort of bare bones you could say. So
here I am creating the MLP parameters.
So each layer has essentially a matrix
which is num demand mentioned by num
dimension and remember num dimension is
um and I'm going to create the
optimizer. So remember this
um uh function is running asynchronously
on all the different on each rank. So
each of the four ranks is going to be
running this with rank equals
0123. Um and now I'm going to start
training. So for a number of steps I'm
going to do a forward pass um through
the layers um matrix multiply
nonlinearity matrix multiply
nonlinearity. There's four layers here.
Going to compute some loss. I don't
really care what the loss is. It's just
made up. Something made up. And I'm
going to do the backward pass. So, so
far this just looks like I'm
implementing uh you SGD, right? Um and
that's the kind of the point. The only
difference is now to implement DDP is
that you just like inject this line here
which syncs synchronizes the gradients
across workers. So what you do is for
each of the layers you call it all
reduce
um where you're
averaging and the thing you're averaging
is
pram.grad. Okay. So it's just like
you've kind of hijacked this um
someone's sd code and you're saying wait
um I'm actually going to just mix all
the gradients after um the backward
pass. And then after you do that, you
just um update the parameters as uh
usual. So from the SGD perspective, it
seems like nothing is happening. I'm
just running SGD, but you know, someone
has just uh um you know, mixed my um
gradients.
Okay. So um so I guess just print out
some some things.
Um so data parallel um I'm printing out
the loss. So one thing to note is that
the the losses are different between all
the different ranks because they have
different datas. Um but after the all
reduce all the parameters are you know
the
same. Okay. So this is a kind of your
textbook uh application of all reduce in
ML setup. Um yeah.
when each rank runs this all how do they
ensure that they're all sort of at the
same
so the question is how do you
ensure if all of these uh processes are
just running asynchronously how do you
make sure that each of them is actually
for example on the same step um this is
because um all reduce is a is a
synchronization point it'll pop everyone
and um and do the all reduce. So you
have to be careful because if one of
your um you know ranks has a missing all
reduce then it'll just you know hang.
Yeah. Yeah.
Yeah. Oh why does getting the initial
parameters depend on the rank? The
question is why does getting initial
parameters depend on the rank? The same
they should be. They're the same. The
reason is just because I guess I don't
um the code for this basically puts it
on the uh the appropriate GPU.
Okay. Any other questions?
So DDP is something you implement in
assignment 2 which maybe some of you
have uh um you know look at or maybe
not. Um it will be done in the context
of a transformer but this is sort of the
sort of the most bare bones version so
you can see um very clearly what's
happening. Okay. So that's DDP. Um
um losses are different across ranks. Um
but the gradients are reduced to be all
the same. So therefore the parameters um
are of all the ranks are the same.
Right? So actually you're doing worldsiz
number of SGD runs but because they're
synchronized they're doing the same
thing. So you can think about this as
sort of an instantiation of you know
analog of activation you know
checkpointing where sometimes you just
do extra compute because you don't want
to store things. In this case you know
we could have for example ship the
optimizer state around but that would be
a bad idea because you know it's much
faster just to run the to update the
optimizer um state than to actually move
the the optimizer parameters
around. Okay. So last year I did try to
do FSDP that but that was a sort of a
hairball so I'm gonna skip skip that um
and do a tensor parallel. So here the
the picture is we leave the data the
same and now what we're going to do is
we're going to cut um the model along
the hidden
dimension. Okay. So um so each rank is
going to get every layer but it's going
to get only part of each layer and um
what we're going to end up doing is
transfer all the data and the
activations around. Um okay so so we're
generating the same sample data um and
let's look at tensor parallel
um okay
so so I have um the batch size and
number of dimension as before and now
I'm going to not before I was cutting um
batch size but now I'm cutting num dim
so I have local num dim equals 124 uh 1
024 4 um divided by world size and
that's
256. So each model essentially
uh sorry each uh rank gets a part of the
model which is one over the world size
fraction of the
parameters. Okay. And remember the whole
why we're doing parallelism at all is
because the model won't be able to fit
into a single GPU. So we're going to
shard it across multiple um GPUs. Um so
so the parameter matrices are now um num
dim by local num
dim. And now each rank is going to I'm
only going to implement the for forward
pass uh here um not the whole training
loop. Um so I'm going to start going
through all the
layers. So um I'm going to compute the
activations first. So this looks pretty
normal except for remember the
activations are actually batch sized by
local num dim rather than num dim
because I only each rank only has a
fraction of the activations now.
But now once I get the the activations
um I need to you know communicate
um and here
I what I have to do is um I'm going to
allocate memory for all the activations.
So at this point every one has a um as a
X but that X um represents a different
um part of the activations. Okay. So now
I'm going to just allocate um batch size
I'm local num dim but world size number.
So basically each rank is going to
basically have enough uh I'm going to
just get the
um basically have worldsized number of
batch size by local num um you know
matrices and
then I'm going to do an all gather.
Okay. So, um I'm going to send all the
activations. Um and this I mean it's you
know fairly uh simple. So X remember is
um batch size times local num dim but x
is different for every rank. So when I
do that all together, I'm going to put
it in activations which has essentially
a world-sized number of uh you know the
same shape as X. Okay. So now every um
rank has the same activations now has
activations of all the models of the of
the whole model. Okay. And then just
like just to concatenate them together
to get you know X
Okay. So now X is um now again batch
size by um num
dim. Okay. And I you know
repeat. So as you can see this is um you
know there's a quite a bit of
communication that happens which is why
you know remember Tatsu said that for
tensor parallel you need pretty high um
interconnects otherwise you'll be
passing a lot of these activations you
know
around. Okay and then you do it for the
next layer and the next layer and you
get the idea.
Um and just to print out some um output.
Uh so tensor parallel
um let's see here um forward pass
produces activations of basically the
you know the full size and everyone has
the same um activations at the
end. Okay. So backward pass I'm going to
skip because that's kind of a annoying
uh to do.
Um all
right. Any questions about that?
Yeah. I was just wondering why it's hard
to do.
Um so why is it hard to do the backward
pass? I I don't think it's necessarily
hard, but in I guess in in the
constrained, you know, time and space,
it's it's um it's not hard. It's just uh
you know, requires a bit more
work.
Okay. So now let's go to pipeline
parallelism. So in this case, we're
cutting um the model by layers. So all
the ranks get all the data. Um and
um all the
ranks each rank gets all of one layer
but they get different
layers. Okay. So sample the data and run
this program of this function for all
the the ranks.
Um okay. So here I'm going to
uh figure out how many layers go in each
um you know rank
um which is two here. So I have a four
layer network. I have two um you know
two ranks. So each rank gets two of the
layers
um just like this picture actually.
Um and here I'm going to um just
allocate the the parameters just for the
layers um that I
need.
Okay. So I'm going to do the forward
pass. Um remember there's a further
optimization that you can you do which
is um you know if you just you know do
it naively you get these pipeline
bubbles that Tatsu talked about um
before um one way to sort of mitigate
that is to break up the batch into
microbatches. So here I'm going to
divide um this this batch into um you
know uh batches of size 32. So four
batches of size 32. Um and then now the
idea is that every rank is going to
essentially wait for the previous rank
to pass it the activations. It's going
to apply those layers and then it's
going to forward it to the next rank. So
starting at the base case, we have rank
equals zero. That's uh just the data. Um
so I'm just chunking the the data into a
bunch of microbatches.
Um and going through each of micro
batches. Um I
um first I receive the tensor. So I'm
using these um pointto-point primitives
now um instead of the collective
primitives.
um and I uh
essentially you know ba basically
receive the tensor X um and then I'm
going to compute the layers that are
assigned to this rank. So in this case
there's only two of them and then um I'm
going to send it to the the next rank.
Um and then again send is a
pointto-point um you know
operation and then the next
uh batch I'm going to do the same thing.
So okay so I'm going to skip
that. Okay. So that's basically it. So
pipeline parallel at least the very
naive version of it is relatively
conceptually simple. As Satu mentioned
last time, um there's many things that
are missing from this basic
implementation. Um overlapping the
communication and computation is
something we're not um you know doing at
all here. Um for example, receive and
send are synchronous, but you should
really make them async. And also the the
order in which you do the forward. Um
actually this is just the forward even
the not the backward but once you have
the backward then um you have to figure
out how to interle the forward and the
backward uh steps.
Yeah wonder I guess like maybe what you
just mentioned about like the async not
being shown here it's I guess in
actuality like the GP will be sort of
listening like whether another one
passes something to it and it's kind of
this kind of kind of in like a event
driven sort of like it only starts
processing once the like layer before it
passes through it and then it starts
processing. So the question is is this
kind of like event driven programming
where you're just waiting for things to
happen.
Um, in I think in event- driven
programming, you basically write these
handlers and then whenever stuff
happens, maybe you get a mouse click,
maybe you get, you know, a file ready
event, then a piece of code runs. That's
quite different, I think, from this
style of coding where um everything has
to work in lock step. Um it is true that
you're sort of waiting for the previous
um
um your rank to send you the information
but at least in this implementation
there's no flexibility of where it's
getting from. It's not like it's waiting
for arbitrary data come from anywhere.
Um I think there are ways to do
asynchronous training which was you know
uh I think quite popular you know 10
more than 10 years ago where um there is
more event driven where um you have a
you know server that sends data and
whenever the gradients are ready it just
like uploads and then the gradients get
accumulated and if workers die then you
know that's um then you know that's sort
of handled more robustly.
But in modern training um despite
scaling up quite a bit um you know
everything seems to be kind of in a
synchronous
paradigm. Yeah. So it is true
that when I say the the workers are and
the ranks are operating asynchronous
that that's just because it's different
processes but you're still putting quite
rigid synchronization on how everything
is uh working in lock step.
Yeah.
How would you change this program to
handle to overap the configuration?
Um so the question is how would you
change this to overlap communication and
computation? So um for example when you
send this there's no reason to just wait
for the data to be sent. You just
basically fire off the send. Um remember
the the send actually gets hap happens
on the GPU via some kernel launch. So
that's sort of independent. Um and it
can just go and process another
microbatch you know right away. So um
the way I think you would do this is
there's another uh function called send
which is um uh asynchronous um actually
this should be as synchronous um
asynchronous which returns a handle and
so you basically do all the the send and
then at the end you basically wait for
all the um the sends to
complete. And then for overlapping the
um when you actually have the backwards
step then you basically have to you know
schedule that um in here.
Yeah.
Send and receive the same if you have
multiple sends multiple receives how
does it know which one is which? So the
question is if you have multiple sends
and multiple receives how do you know
which is which? So here you're spec the
the tensor name doesn't matter it's just
uh whatever variable is there and what
you're specifying is the the source. So
if I'm at a node and I'm receiving then
whatever the next message coming from
that rank I'm just going to you know put
in this uh x and move continue
executing.
What if I want to do two sends from the
same rank?
If you want to do two cents from the
same rank
uh to the same destination.
So, so I'm not quite sure about this,
but I think if you have two sends, it's
sort of put in a stream. So, the order
of the sends still is preserved. It's
just that other stuff can happen at the
same time like you know you can send to
um like I think if you have a a pair you
do two sends then that order is
preserved but um the order in which um
you know you send some other rank is
sending to another rank it can happen at
any time.
Yeah. What would happen if you just did
like this send but then no one's
receiving it would just get stopped
there or like so what happens if you
send and no one's uh receives it I think
it would just stop it just wait because
there's
no yeah I mean
because I mean the the process could
just be running and you don't know
whether it will it's just I mean it's
just code executing so you don't know if
it's never going to get there or if it's
just gonna be a matter of time. Yeah.
So the question is what happens to the
last rank? So at the end the last rank
has all the activation. So that has
basically the results of a full uh
forward pass. And then you know if you
implement the backward pass then you
would be actually now computing the
gradient with respect to loss and then
you would uh go back down and send um to
from rank to rank minus one and so
on. Okay. I guess maybe um I was afraid
I was going to run out of time, but it
looks like I had actually have time.
Maybe next year I should do the backward
pass.
Um okay, so actually I'm going to finish
quite early today, but um so if you have
any other questions, you should ask. Um
so so far we've gone through three
simple examples of data tensor pipeline
parallel. Um of course this is for
simple MLPS. um you would actually want
to do this with your own um you know
fancier model um like a transformer. Um
I did argue that at least at the the
core ideas you can sort of understand
through the MLP. Um I think
the but of course when you want to train
you want to train transformer not a deep
MLP. Um so you still have to implement
the the full complexity. Um what's also
missing is the communication and uh
computation overlap which is not really
handled very uh carefully here. Um and
there is generally a more complex code
with bookkeeping. I you know encourage
you to check out like Megatron LM or um
PyTorch's FSTP. It gets uh you know
fairly um hairy. And one of the things
that I think makes some of the
bookkeeping at least for let's say FSTP
and you'll be exposed to this in uh a A2
a bit is that um if you want something
that handles arbitrary architectures
then you have to you know figure out the
parameters and do a book a bunch of
bookkeeping to and you know figure out
what their layers are and and so on.
Whereas in the MLP case, it's just I've
sort of made the decision that I'm going
to split the model in this, you know,
particularly simple way. Um, one other
thing I'll just mention as an aside is
that all of what we're doing in this
course is is PyTorch, but it is useful
um to be aware of this whole other
ecosystem around jacks and TPUs. Um,
which is actually kind of uh nice in
some way. Um and the idea here is um Jax
has allows you to just define the model.
It define the sharding strategy and then
the Jax uh compiler handles the rest. So
there's this um toolkit that we uh
developed called Lavanter based on Jax.
Um and I'll just show you a snippet of
um what it happened. So this is FSTP and
10 lines of code and uh basically you
have a
um you know uh model and then you just
say shard with this partic I mean I
don't expect you to kind of read this
exactly but um basically you define
which dimension you're going to shard by
um and then you know that's it and
similarly for tensor parallel um you're
just saying I'm going to um shard um the
model along the you know you can shard
by the on the head dimension
um for uh for attention and also you can
shard based on um the the model
dimension. So in some sense you know
this gives you a sort of com you know
comp a conceptual simplicity of what
you're trying to do is you have
this basically um um computation graph
but it has these kind of dimensions you
know the the model dimensions the
embedding dimension the attention
sequence dimension and Jax allows you to
basically uh just specify which
dimensions you want to cut by and also
define a mapping from that onto the
actual uh TPUs and then the JAX compiler
magically just you know figures out how
to compile that down into the the
primitives that you know shuffle things
around. So this is much more higher
level than um you know doing the the
operating with the collective
communication. Um, but you know, we're
sticking with PyTorch um because it's it
allows you to see kind of underneath the
hood what's actually um happening. But
if you're actually doing this in the in
the real world, um obviously you don't
need a you and you probably shouldn't
implement all of this from
scratch. Okay, so that's the end of the
Jack's digression. Um so just just
summarize we've um seen many ways to
parallelize so far. Um and each of these
ways of parallelizing is you can think
about just like splitting either the
model or the um data along some
dimension either the data the batch
dimension the width dimension or depth
dimension or the um the context length
dimension. Um we also see these this
kind of recurring theme of you know
recomputation. you can
um you can kind of recomputee something
um from scratch or you can store in
memory and suffer the the data transfer
cost or in now in the multi-GPU
multi-node setting you can actually
store on another GPU's memory and then
you know communicate which is you know
even slower um so there's kind of these
these tradeoffs um you know here
And you know often recomputation is
actually um you know can be you know
better but obviously you can't you know
you can't repro compute the whole thing
and often you're either communication or
memory
limited. Um a final word is that um it
is the case that hardware is getting
better. So you might think that well
maybe none of this is really necessary
because in five years everything will
fit in you know L1 HPM. So this is not
going to be the case because um those
might uh grow quite a bit um although
there are still physical limits um we'll
always be ending up with bigger models
that sort of are at the limit of what
the hardware can do. So this
hierarchical structure um ever since
system computer systems was a a thing
has always been um with us and it will
always uh be
there. Okay, that's all I have for you
uh today. So I'm can take any questions.
Yeah,
increase with the same set of parameters
the cost might be different because like
your normalization might be a function
of the whole data set. uh for example in
so the question is in data parallel um
you're saying that even though the
parameters are all kind of synchronized
there could be other things that depend
on the the data like in batchorm um so I
don't actually know how you batch norm
is always kind of annoying Um, so I
don't know exactly how you would do that
off the top of my head. Um, and I guess
at least in the LM world that doesn't
really show up. Uh, because layer norm
is is is used. Um, and as long as you
initialize all the parameters and
they're using the same random seed,
you'll be fine. I mean there could be
like non-determinism issues um on on the
GPU but hopefully those are you know
minor
uh yeah
so the question is uh is does PyTorch
have um some nicities as well kind of
like what Jax offers is
Yeah. So I mean PyTorch does have the
FSTP library which you should absolutely
use if you're not taking this class. Um
which basically is a wrapper. You define
any model and it just does FFTDP on it.
Um, I think that now if you're asking
how well it can more custom allow you to
more do custom charting, I I think there
are some things that are coming but it's
not as I think as
developed. I mean I think there's sort
of this I think spectrum between the Jax
world where you sort of declarity define
things and I think the Google
infrastructure if you stay within the
Jack's TPU system is pretty well
developed and but then if you look at
kind of deepseek which is a kind of
opposite end where you have um these uh
GPUs with actually really bad inter you
know connect which means that they have
to go in and hack, you know, they
actually go to the kind of nickel level
and actually do a bunch of things which
I don't quite understand to ek out the
performance. Whereas if you're writing a
jack, you just kind of from on high
declare your model and then you know
stuff stuff happens. So it it's kind of
uh the ways that you leverage hardware I
think really depends on what what
ecosystem you're operating in.
Yeah. the the amount of recreation of
the applications they can rec some of
the
activations is there API which may
yeah so the question is activation uh
checkpointing what's there is an API
that's basically allows you to uh in I
mean I guess in PyTorch Njax to uh
specify which parts you want to uh
recomputee because clearly you don't
want to recomputee you know everything
and or nothing. um probably every few
layers probably right after like big
Matt malls where um for example if you
have let's say um mammal and then
pointwise um linearity I don't think you
need to store like two copies of um
basically if you have two things where
it's sort of trivial to uh comp um get
to then you might as well just store you
know one version
um yeah over Okay. GPUs are replaced by
specific hardware or like more
specialized.
So the question is are GPUs going to
ever be replaced by transformer specific
hardware? Um so you're seeing this in
the inference space uh uh quite a bit
already with um um like Grock and
Cerebras have specialized hardware that
can do um inference and also I guess
training. severe resist training. Um so
basically those hardwares um essentially
give you just a lot more kind of onchip
memory. I mean that's basically the the
name of the game. I think cerebrus has
like a huge um you know essentially
effectively a L1 cache so you don't have
to move things off and I think a lot of
simplifications can happen because GPUs
were there's a lot of baggage actually
if you think about because um they were
designed in an era where you had to do a
lot of branching and like you know
various types of ad hoc computations
which are not really needed in the deep
learning regime. So I think there are
quite a few opportunities to um improve
the hardware as well. Um I think there
was a hand back there and I'll
um I don't know if I this is like the
right question that I'm thinking about
but um in the context of the lecture
it's basically a model um that's being
trained in one go that's been optimizing
but I'm wondering if any of the
techniques that we're talking about can
be used to incrementally train a model
for example as you get new training data
um not just to like fine tune but
actually to kind of recapulate
everything without having to recalculate
them. Yeah. So the question is um can
these techniques be used to essentially
do continued um training? Um yeah
absolutely. So if you think about the
the unit of what we're working with is
just doing gradient uh steps, right? So
if you take a halftra, you know,
checkpoint, you can just like continue
doing what this is. There's nothing
specific about starting from scratch. Um
here
um I think there was a question there.
Yeah. So on the like the model specific
hardware end you know the previous
question um like presumably there's like
a physical technical reason you can't
make nodes much larger than they are
currently. Like what's
the change that you're talking about?
Like so if you could just make GPU nodes
like infinitely like as big as you
wanted people would do that. So
presumably there's a tech like a
hardware reason that's not possible. So
what's the actual advancement being done
for like the rock specific hardware you
mentioned? Yeah. So the question is
there are physical limits for sure uh
for a um you know for a GPU. Let me just
go. So the um so you can't make GPUs
obviously infinitely large um or
infinitely dense. I mean there's also
like you know power um issues uh you
know you need to get rid of all the the
the heat and um you know there's only so
much kind of bandwidth that can um you
know fit um so I don't know the the
exact um you know details but at least
in some of the cerebrous case I mean
they um they sort of have this way of
you know manufacturing you know
basically the the chips so that the um
the memory is kind of on on on the chip.
So So I guess it's just a way of putting
it on there. And I think that there are
obviously um you know trade-offs because
it comes at a um cost of not having as
much you know
flexibility. Um but in but in general I
think the way to maybe think about this
more broadly is that you know GPUs were
still developed in kind of the CPU era
where it's much more control focused
like I have code that I'm executing
that's the sort of first class citizen
and then data needs to be moved to you
know um execute the to to handle the
code but um the big difference with deep
learning workloads is that it's all sort
of data flow like the the computation
graph if you look at these sum is like
static. You know from the beginning
exactly all the computations that are
going to be done until essentially the
end of training, right? So using that
knowledge, you should be able to kind of
lay out your computation in a much
smarter way than having to deal with the
the flexibility uncertainty over ad hoc
uh computation.
Okay, maybe a few more questions and
I'll end there. Yeah. Is the
computational graph usually stored in
the CPU or in the GPU?
So the question is where is the
computation graph uh stored? Well, the
the code is um all I mean all this code
is running on on on this you know CPU.
Um but but when you call something like
um the PyTorch function it it that's
needs to run on GPU then it launches
kernels under the hood and the kernels
are code that runs on the GPU.
Um yeah, I'm not sure if that so so I
guess maybe another answer is that the
computation of graph is more of a I
guess a conceptual um you know it's not
like there's a graph literally that's
being you know uh I mean I guess there
sort of is but it's uh it's uh it's not
like the graph gets put on the GPU if
that makes sense.
Okay. So, so these communication
primitives that we have
like they are actually CPU instructions
or like are these programs using the
GPU? So the question is the
communication primitives are they CPU or
GPU? So these collective operations are
in some sense um abstract specification
of what types of operations need to
happen um which can happen if you
remember um this PyTorch distributed um
has different backends. So it could
happen on GPU or happen on um CPU.
But but when they're happening on CPU,
is it like is the CPU sort of scheduling
them or or is it like kernels which are
independently? Yeah. So well the CPU
sort of drives basically is the sort of
the master still and then when you do a
collective operation it calls the nickel
library which uh launches which is you
know it's still CPU and then it launches
some kernels that move data around.
Yeah. Okay. Maybe this is a good place
to end. All right. I will see you uh
next Monday or Tuesday.
[Applause]