So until the last week uh we discussed
some kind of the basics actually the
these were basics the DDPM and DDIM kind
of the models. So if you understood uh
the basic ideas about DDPM the DDIM then
now you are able to implement a
diffusion model for any kind of the
data. So the purpose of the first
assignment is to actually implement like
the DDPM the DDIM in a way that you are
making your own diffusion model yourself
with some kind of very basic data. So
this is really kind of some kind of
basic things in terms like implementing
the diffusion model. But if you want to
like apply those kind of the vision
models for the many the applications,
you might need to also know some kind of
the basic concepts for so many that can
that are basically necessary for the
many practical the applications for the
conditional generation or some kind of
the personalization for the many things.
So for this week uh we are going to
switch the gear a bit and in terms of
that we are going to discuss more some
kind of the some practical the ideas for
many kind of the applications. So the
plan for now is that we are going to
discuss some kind of more the practical
the applications and the practical the
ideas in this week and then we also
going back to the discussion about like
some theory and seeing like how the
diffusion models can be also uh defined
and also interpreted in the continuous
time domain uh in terms of that we can
do the further the acceleration of the
generation and these topic will be
discussed until the week of the midterm
and after that we're going to start to
discuss the flow models and we're going
to step back to some kind of more
applications based on the diffusion flow
models. So that's the plan for now.
So the the topics that we are going to
discuss today is that uh when we have
some kind of the additional the
information for the data. So for for
example like let's say we are making
some kind of the uh image diffusion
models that we can gen some kind of
images like this. But for many kind of
the cases the images might come with
some kind of some additional information
like some kind of the class labels or
some kind of the text descriptions.
So for those kind of cases like when you
have some additional information for the
data how can you utilize those kind of
the information to improve the quality
of the outputs. So this is the first
question that we are going to uh discuss
and second thing is also about some kind
of the fine tuning. So actually you will
see that there are quite many some
pre-trained model that are basically
pre-trained with the billions of images
for example uh for those kind of the
pre-trained models how can you
effectively fine-tune these models in
terms of that we can do some kind of the
conditional generation and also some
kind of the personalization. So those
are some kind of the basic things that
we are going to discuss today.
So probably today's lecture will be uh
shorter uh but I'm going to quickly go
over some kind of like those kind of
basic ideas.
So in terms like utilize some kind of
the additional information uh for the
given DMD data set uh let's think about
this kind of the simpler case that
especially for the image generation
let's assume that we have some kind of
the class labels for the old images and
given this kind of the class the labels
for the images how can you use this
information to improve the quality so
that's the idea which is called the
classifier the guidance
so for the classifier the guidance what
we are going to do is that now we are
going to consider not learning the
distribution for the image itself but
some kind of the joint the distribution
for both the image and the class labels
here then here the question is that what
we have seen in the DDPM and DDIM and
also for the scope DB based model the
case is that the noise predictor
actually can be interpreted as some kind
of this uh this core prediction right we
have seen this kind of the relation
relationship in terms of the quantity
that we are predicting using the noise
predictor which can be actually this is
kind of the same with this here up
to the skill def factor here right so
here the thing is that uh when you
consider not learning the distribution
of the image itself but the joint
distribution of the x and the y here uh
can also compute the score uh for this
like joint distribution in a way that we
can use that the score information uh
score information uh in the generation
So here like one quick question is that
uh what if we consider why do we need to
consider the like the joint
distribution. So typically we might want
to actually consider doing some kind of
the like the conditional degeneration
right that means that we might actually
be more interesting in basically
learning this core of the uh conditional
distribution like xt conditioned by dy
right
but here basically I say like you know
that we are going to learn this core
function for the joint distribution
uh what's the difference between these
two Uh this
why why do we care about the joint
distribution instead of the conditional
distribution? It sounds like we need to
know some kind of a conditional
distribution, right? Like given the
class label the Y, we want to change
some kind of image X, right?
Any
no ideas for that? Actually these two
are kind of the same because like the
joint distribution like pxy
is the same with the uh the condition
the the probability x conditioned by y
multiplied by the py right
and py would be some kind of the
constant value uh that would be some
kind of given information. So whether we
consider this score uh the function for
the joint distribution or the score
function for the conditional
distribution these are kind of the same
up to the scale the scale of the term
becomes of the py right uh which is some
kind of given information. So basically
like learning this core uh for the the
joint distribution can be interpreted as
kind of like some we are seeing this
core function for that the conditional
distribution make sense.
So uh the things that you need to know
in the context of the DP model is that
so basically what we all talk about
after we say this kind like the noise
predictor. So we also have seen some
kind of the other options like the mean
predictor and the clean sample the
predictor right but whatever the
predictors that we have all those
information can be interpreted as kind
of like predicting the noise here and we
also have seen that this like noise can
be interpreted as basically this like
score term right uh for any of the uh
for the intermediate data point if we
can compute this core the terms here
then based on that we can also interpret
compute the noise based on this like
score function and the rest of the steps
of the the generation would be exactly
the same. So the key things in the
diffusion model is that basically how we
are going to compute this like the score
function for any of the intermediate
data point of the xt. Uh that's kind of
the key idea. uh we're going to keep
seeing this kind of the ideas about like
how we are going to modify this square
function uh in terms like doing some
kind of the some uh conditional
degeneration or some kind of guided
generation for the many things. So many
of the applications of division models
come from basically doing some kind of
the manipulation of these core terms
here. Okay.
So in this case uh if we just quickly
see uh what we are going to do is that
we are basically calculating the score
function for this joint distribution
right this can be rewritten into this
way and you can see that finally it
becomes like having this formulation uh
which is basically having the same score
here uh but you know taking subtracting
like this amount of the kind of the
another the
uh which means that in terms of
basically computing the noise we just
need to update the audio noise uh by
subtracting uh this part right
so basically actually learning this core
function for the joint uh distribution
becomes basically modifying the noise
with basically uh the this amount of
some kind of the some bias and here the
question is that basically how we are
going to compute this part Right? So
somehow if we can compute this core
function for this conditional
distribution like the y conditioned by
the xt by subtracting this part now we
can update the noise and this updated
noise uh can be used in the our
generation process. That's the kind of
the basic idea.
How can you compute this?
Any ideas?
You can see that first we need to be
able to compute the probability of the
class label given the XT. Right?
Somehow if we have any kind of the
function that can compute the
probability of the class label given the
XT based on that the that function
actually the uh what we need to do is
taking the gradient of the logo of that
the function right.
uh what if we make a neuron net that can
compute the function of the probability
uh that becomes the function of the like
the computing the probability for the
class label given dxt. So if we have
like know computing these parts uh the
neural net computing these parts then we
can know naturally compute the log and
also the gradient of the log back
probability right
make sense uh what is the neuron net
that can compute the probability of the
class table given the xt
yeah so that's the classific efficient
network right uh
the only thing is that that's the
basically the classific ification
network which is not taking not only
taking the clean image but also that is
taking any intermediate the data point
right so that's kind of the only thing
uh so this means that we just need to
train a classification network that is
taking any intermediate XT and it's
corresponding line here right so can you
guess like how can you basically train
such kind of neuronet
which means that when you have some kind
of the pairs of the clean image and also
the class table. What you just need to
do is that you need to do the fold
process to corrupt the clean image into
the noise image. Right? starting from
the X0 and running the F process to make
some kind of the corrupted image
basically the noise the data point XT uh
that becomes the input to the
classification the network and then
basically predicting the probability for
each of the class label.
So basically having this kind of the
classification the network becomes that
we are being able to basically compute
this probability given the XT we compute
the probability for this of the class
label and what we are going to do is
that we are going to use this
information uh to be able to basically
update the noise term here. Basically it
becomes like updating this core function
right uh score function for for this
core function this will be the
corresponding the noise right and this
like basically updated the noise can be
injected uh into the our reverse process
and the rest of the steps will be
exactly the same.
So that becomes some uh the kind of the
things in terms that we are doing some
kind of the sort of the uh some
modification of these this the functions
here uh in a way that now we want to
generate some images that are basically
aligned with some kind of given the
condition of the class label
make sense.
So that's why basically so it's
important to understand the
relationships uh between the output that
we are predicting using the noise
friction network here and also this core
function here. But we are having this
kind of the the relationship between
these kind of the quantities. Uh which
means that for some kind of the
conditional degeneration for many kind
of the cases uh we can do some kind of
the some manipulation of the score
function here updating the noise here
that will basically guide the trajectory
of the uh the generation the process in
the reverse process the the the
trajectory of the XT in a way that the
output becomes something that we want to
see.
So this is actually quite uh uh
important the aspect of the diffusion
models. Uh you cannot simply do those
kind of things for the BAE or some kind
of again for the other kind of the
generative models. Basically for the
other legend models for the G and the
BAE if you want to make some kind of the
conditional the model that becomes like
that know you are you know training the
model from scratch again but making
another model that can take the
condition. uh but in this case what we
do is that we are basically having
pre-trained the mood predictor here
while basically training another the
network which is the classification
network here uh in terms of that this
information uh can give some kind of the
guidance uh in this quality prediction
uh while all the other steps becomes
exactly the same
make sense so it becomes like you know
if you see some kind of how the like xt
T basically evolves from the X capital T
all the way to the XU with this kind of
the the the banana noise for the
original noise. If we see this kind of
specific trajectory by adding this kind
of the additional term in this quality
function you're going to see some kind
of the some deviation of the trajectory
into the other path making another image
there right by updating this C function.
So this is the basic idea you're going
to see multiple times uh in the in the
class.
So yeah that's the thing. So once we
basically have the classifier here uh
based on that now you can update the
noise by just taking the gradient of the
log of that probability and by just like
multiplying those terms you can update
the noise the terms here.
uh one kind of interesting some some
practical the idea uh is that even you
can consider basically controlling the
strength of the condition. So by having
the weight time the w here uh by
increasing this the weight you can
somehow uh enforcing further in terms of
that the output is like more aligned
into the given the condition which is
the class in this case. So I'm going to
quickly go with the kind of formulations
here. But the meaning of like having the
weight here uh can be interpreted uh in
some kind of ways. But basically if you
uh see like all the derivations here uh
what it becomes is that uh it becomes
like we are having the
the the score term. Now for the the the
joint uh the distribution that we have
seen in the previous slide but for this
stuff.
So we are slightly modifying the hourly
distribution in a way that now we are
not seeing this uh the original joint
distribution but somehow like some sort
of the condition enhanced uh the
distribution in this case uh which does
not have some kind of any theoretical de
meaning in this form but practically
this basically means that we are
basically amplifying some the
probability for this like uh the
conditional the probability here in
terms of that we are basically enforcing
the outputs to be more aligned with the
given the condition the ide. So this is
some kind of the practical the ideas in
terms of bically how we are going to uh
you know
they have some kind of the strong
condition in the generation. So
typically also what we can see is that
when you have some kind of the higher
the weights here uh we can see that the
output is not only just like aligned
into the given the condition but also
become some slightly more the realistic
uh while basically also sacrificing the
diversity of it. So that's kind of the
some very practical the ideas in terms
of that we can also uh have some kind of
the some strengths of the condition in
the generation.
So you can also try this yourself. Uh so
the good thing of like this like the uh
the classifier the the guidance uh is
that know it's not just like liberating
the additional information not only to
improve the quality but that also
enables some kind of the conditional
degeneration. So that's kind of the
interesting the point. What will be the
downside of the classifier the guidance
if you are the developer making such
kind of system what are you going to
complain in terms of like making this
system.
Yeah that's the thing. So basically you
need to train another linear network
right. So still uh it might be easier
than just like training the diffusion
model from scratch again but still it's
like making another network right uh in
terms of that so it might be basically
some cursor in terms of having the two
neuron networks
so that's why we are basically
discussing this idea so if you see many
kind of some I don't know some blogs
where many some kind of the articles
many things about the some some the code
of many things for the diffusion models
you're going to see this term CFG
for many many the places. So this is
really very uh you know the the standard
techniques for now in terms of making
some condition the model and the uh
reason for like why they are having this
naming of the classifier the free
guidance is that actually this idea has
been like the motivate motivated by the
classifier the guidance and here the the
biggest motivation is to not to have the
classifier but while basically having
the same effect uh in the conditional
degeneration.
So the basic idea here is that how we
can do the same thing without really
having some uh declassification the
network. So what they are going to do is
that they are going to basically make
the train the diffusion model in a way
that they can directly compute the
conditional uh the score function. Uh so
it's not basically assuming that we are
having some kind of pre-trained
unconditional model. we are training the
diffusion model in a way that that can
trackly predict the conditional discore
functions.
So in which means that when you have
some kind of the noise prediction the
network that is not only taking the xt
but t here but also taking some kind of
the additional the condition the pi
here.
The kind of good thing like having this
kind of the some conditioner this uh the
the moves the predictor is that now this
condition does not need to be only the
class labels this can be anything can be
like I'm going to show some kind of the
many examples for that it can be text
description uh it can be even the audio
it can be even many other things right
uh so that's kind of thing but what we
are going to do is that actually the
advantage of like having the classifier
the guidance is that we could basically
control the strength uh of the the
conditioning right
basically by increasing the W here we
could basically make the output be more
aligned into the given the condition. So
here the question is that when you also
train the diffusion model to directly
predict the conditional the score terms
here how can you also control the
strength of the condition.
So to control the strength of the
condition uh what we are going to do is
that we are going to basically jointly
learn both the conditional discord the
function and also the unconditional
discore functions.
So you can think of like we are making
train the two neuron network. One is
basically taking some kind of the
additional condition information here as
the input and having the another network
which is not taking any kind of some
conditioning the information right so
that can be the case is that we are
running the conditional discord function
with one network and the unconditional
discord function with the other network.
Right?
But we also don't want to have some two
neuron nets right uh that's also
basically very uh you know just you know
you know taking some time right uh so
what we are going to do is that we are
going to make a single neuronet that can
learn both the conditional the square
function and also the uncontent score
function in a way to basically that know
we are introducing some kind of the null
label uh for example for the class label
cases if you going to have some kind of
indexes of the class labels from like
one to And uh we are having some kind of
the zero label which means that that's
the unconditional the case. So like
simple idea in terms of we are just
making a single neuron net that can have
the both the if I can predict both the
conditioning score and the unconditional
score and the null label here basically
indicating the case that we are
predicting the unconditional score. Make
sense?
And based on that the idea in terms of
the uh the enhancement of the
conditioning is that we are doing some
kind of the extrapolation
of this core function for the
conditional the case and the
unconditional case.
So in this formulation what you can see
is that if we set uh this the round to
be one uh sorry the round to be zero
here then this mean is that we are not
using any kind of the some unconditional
discore information only using the the
conditional discore information right
but we are we can also do some kind of
the extrapolation in terms of basically
increasing this like lambda here not
having the zero but having some kind of
the higher number in a way that we are
basically going further into this part,
right?
Make sense?
Okay. So, that can be kind of like the
way that we are somehow mixing the
conditioning the score information and
also the unconditional disc information
in a way to basically controlling the
strength of the the conditional
information.
So, it sounds like kind of the intuitive
that we are doing some kind of
extrapolation like between like these
two. uh but if we see how exactly this
is aligned with the classifier the
guidance uh actually we can see some
kind of the connection between the
classifier the pre guidance and the
classifier the guidance so I'm going to
go quickly some kind of formulations
here but check out this yourself uh but
basically what you can see is that
instead of like seeing the lambda here
let's see that actually this like the
lambda is basically the uh the w minus
one so this w will be basically aligned
with the weights the W here in the
classifier the guidance. So once you
basically have this basically introduce
the the W here become the same with the
one plus lambda then we can rewrite all
the formulations like this and after
also rewriting all the formulations uh
in a way like this you can basically
derive all those like yourself.
uh what we can see is that basically by
multiplying some kind of a constant term
here uh we can see that it turns out to
be exactly the same uh with the
conditioning the the strength the the
the control in the classifier the
guidance the case right
so it turns out to be that like you know
doing some kind of the extrapolation of
these quums in the classifier the free
guidance becomes uh the same like
aligned with some kind of the the
condition the the strength the the the
control in the classifier the the
guidance in terms of basically we having
the the weight the W here.
Okay, make sense. So by setting some
kind of the higher number for the W uh
you can uh basically do some kind of the
control uh the conditions. This is like
one specific example
when you set the actually this W should
be the same as the lambda here. Uh some
the W tob Z here. Uh you can see that uh
this was like the case like making some
specific
some species of the dog. I don't know
what's the exactly name of the dog here.
The do do you guys can you identify the
the some species of the dog here? the
what what is it husky probably husky I
don't know so you can see that uh we we
we are basically basically injecting the
class table as the addition of the input
right so you you start to see some more
the husky like the dogs at the beginning
but as you also increase the weight then
you can see that all the images are more
precisely aligned with the the quest
label which is the husky while also
making the ops to be more drealistic. Uh
so this is kind of the the case like
controlling the conditions
and compared to the classifier the
guidance uh with the classifier the free
guidance when you basically control the
weights here uh you can even see some
kind of slightly the better the
performance uh in terms of the quality
and the diversity.
So the basically the advantages of the
classifier the free guidance is that
it's very easy to implement. So the all
you need to do uh in terms of the
implementation is that you need to have
some kind of the module in the neuron
net that can take some kind of the
additional the input uh and then doing
some kind of this quality prediction
based on that and also the important
thing is that this idea now can be
applied to the not only for some kind of
the class labels but many other things
as I'm also going to show some kind of
examples there. The only downside is
that uh with some kind of the
pre-trainted neuron network if you want
to control the strength of the control
basically you need to uh run the the bit
for the process of noise prediction
twice both for the conditioning case and
the unconditioning case which means that
it takes some like twice of the time uh
in the generation the process. So that's
the only the downside but this is really
some very practical the idea that is
already widely being adapted to the many
some kind of the pre model. So if you
see many pre-trained uh image and the
video uh degenerate models they now can
basically take some kind of text
description as the input right for those
kind of the questions.
stress other than
>> oh actually sorry I uh I was like know
you know mixing some kind of there
actually this w is the same with the
lambda that I used in the previous slide
why we only have to just
What what is the meaning of like
interpolating the this course then?
>> Right. But actually I don't know why we
have to distract.
So the the thing is that uh so yeah I
was like using some wrong notations of
the the lambda there. So actually the
the w in the the the the in the table is
the same with the lambda right. So when
the uh the lambda is basically zero
basically this means that the w is one
right.
So if this like w becomes like less than
one uh what's the meaning of that?
So when the w is one that's the case
that we are learning the score the terms
for the joint distribution right and we
want to basically enh enhance uh the
conditioning the factor by having the
the number greater than one if we set
the w to be smaller than one that means
that we are basically reducing the
impact of the condition so that becomes
closer to the unconditional decay
make sense
Okay, that's what
ah I see. Uh I I see your point. Um
yeah so the question is that uh when
this quantity is smaller than the one
then if you compute the this power of
the w then this might be actually
decreasing this factor right uh this is
about like just like this is like just
decreasing the probability uh but it's
not decreasing the probability just like
changing so we care about these core
terms right uh in terms of these core
terms uh here
let me go to the classifier the case.
So actually the w times here right. So
as we basically have the similar value
of dw then actually when the w to be
zero then we are completely ignoring
this part right.
So in terms of like the the modifying
the score terms error right as we
basically decrease the uh the weight
double here then we are basically
reducing the impact of the the
conditioning as you can see in this the
the you know the extra terms here.
So actually we need to see not the the
probability but the how the score is
being changed uh with the waste that we
are using.
So the these are all connected in that
way. Uh so the lambda in the classifier
free guidance is basically somehow
aligned with the w uh as we have seen in
the previous slide.
Yeah.
The extrapolation the weight lambda in
the cfg
is actually the w minus one right. Uh so
the decreasing the lambda here basically
the same as like decreasing the w that
becomes like decreasing the factor of
the conditioning in this core top uh
becomes like all the same right
so I I was basically somehow mixing the
w and the lambda in the other kind of
things I I just wanted to use the lambda
in the exploration device here in a way
that you can see how this lambda is
basically uh connected to the W that we
are using the classifier the the case
but actually I just like copied those
the tables uh from the paper and they
are using the W instead of the L. So
mixing some kind of notations here.
Next sense any questions on this?
So yeah, so if you really um so I guess
have you seen the this library the
uh let me just quickly jump to this one.
Uh have you seen this?
So in the demo session probably in the
next Wednesday not this Wednesday uh our
TA will basically briefly introduce how
we can also basically play with some
kind of the pre-trained uh deep models
and the image the generation the not the
the visual content the the the the
contest uh will be basically about
making some kind of new visual the
content using some kind of the
pre-trained uh image diffusion model. uh
we we could make it not for the visual
content for the like molecule generation
for whatever kind of things but uh since
we can see many kind of the good
pre-trained model for the image
generation uh we just like decided to
make it basically playing with this kind
of pre model. So if you basically Google
the diffusers then you can see many some
kind of the pre-trained uh image the uh
diffusion models and based on that uh
you can do many things uh and for many
kind of pre models if you go like some
kind of the hugging face page or
something then actually you'll be able
to see some kind of the option to be
able to control the strength of the
condition. There are some kind cases for
that. Actually controlling the strength
of the condition is typically really
just like literally controlling the
weight in the classifier the free the
guidance. Uh and based on like putting
those kind of condition uh you can
basically make some the outputs that are
aligned with the given the text.
Uh so we're going to also see some
examples of like image to image
generation. Uh so you can do some like
replacing the fruits with the cake like
this. Uh yeah for those kind of cases uh
you can also consider using the same the
classifier the free guidance. Uh but we
going to also see some other examples
for that. Uh this is also uh the other
example that you are changing the
viewpoint of the images. So this is the
case that we are taking uh some both the
input image and also the some the angle
information as the extra condition and
based on the condition you are making
some kind of a new image. Uh so those
all can be done with the classified play
guidance also for the 3D generation. Uh
this is the example that PV made uh that
based on the given the text description
you can also even make some kind of 3D
uh like some hand generation making like
one hand conditioned by the other hand
here uh and also some for the audio uh
to image generation.
Can you hear the sound? Sound might be
too small. Uh based on the audio input
you can also make some kind of images.
Yeah. And also yeah there are many other
examples I mean this is even the case
that we are uh having some kind of the
negative prompt. So here the basic idea
is that uh instead of like setting some
kind of the uh the null prompt here uh
if we set the negative prompt here that
becomes like we are removing the concept
of like given by the this condition. Uh
for example uh in this case
what they do is that we are removing the
factor of the male
uh from this image. Uh for some people
this might be not comfortable to see. So
for bring this kind of some gender bias
kind of the examples but uh some why did
I put this? So for the this example like
if you remove the defect of the male
then you're going to see some kind of
more the female like images. uh for if
you also kind of like remove the effect
of the female then you're going to make
some kind of more the male like images
but obviously this is not the kind of
the binary things but I mean some
examples for like showing some uh making
have some kind of negative prompt right
so many examples based on the CFG
uh some more interesting examples using
the CFG might be that when it is like
combined with the DDIM the inversion so
last time we discussed the DDIM right so
the interesting the aspect of the DDIM
now is that uh we can make the
generation the process to be
deterministic right uh so we are
switching our some kind of the uh
reverse transition the distribution to
be aligned with like this distribution
uh in a way that we just need to have
the noise prediction based on that have
some kind of expected value x0ero
compute like this mean and basically
sampling from this distribution so the
whole process is kind of like exactly
the same with the DDPM case the only
difference was basically that we are
switching this transition distribution
and here we are going to have the quiz
uh by setting uh the variance to be zero
there setting the variance to be zero
basically means that if we go back to
the the algorithm here we don't need to
have this part right
having the variance zero here uh
basically means that we just directly
take this mean as the next step the the
the the latent variable, right? This
directly becomes XT minus one, right?
Because like this factor will be zero,
right?
So when you have the zero variance here,
we only have the two lines of the code
given the XT. Now we can just directly
compute the XT minus one without
injecting any kind of noise, right?
Can you quickly derive the formulation
of the XT minus one with respect to the
XT uh and also the noise prediction?
I can see that. Uh did you get this? Uh
I'm going to basically update this slide
so you don't need to take both of this.
Uh but basically what this show is is
that uh we can now this becomes like
usually like single line of the code
right given the XT uh once you basically
have the the noise prediction based on
that the XT minus one can be computed
with the single line of the code right
so that's kind of thing uh no noise
being injected in the DDM process so
that becomes uh uh that basically means
that from the mapping all the way from
the x capital t to the axio from the
unique gausian noise to the clean data
point the mapping from here to here
becomes deterministic.
So as I also mentioned last time this
means that once you be basically pick
any of the x capital t then you always
will going to see the same x0 right in
the ddim degeneration process that means
that can you also basically find the
inverse mapping
given the x0
can you also find the x capital t right
basically here like one small thing that
I'm also going to emphasize is that this
This is also for all the cases of the
unconditional degeneration right
uh when the there's no condition the x
capital t will go to the same x0 but if
we start to have some kind of the
condition uh injecting some kind of the
additional information here depending on
which condition that you set you're
going to get the different x0 right
that's that's a things but for the same
condition for the same x capital t
you're going to get the same dx0
then can you also get the inverse
mapping from the x0 to the x capital t.
Is it possible to get some kind of the
precise uh the computation of the
inverse mapping from the x0 to the x
capital t? Do you think it's feasible?
Yes, we have seen this formulation,
right?
So now we are computing the xt minus one
given dxt.
Then can you also compute the xt + one
given the xt?
Yes.
Can we compute? No. Yes. Yes.
No. No. Why? Why we can?
>> Yeah. So, that that's the thing, right?
So we are having this term. So it
becomes like we want to compute the uh
the xt from the xt minus one right. Uh
but if we want to compute the sorry xt
from the xt minus one right then what do
we what does that mean is that we should
be able to compute the noise here from
the given the uh the xt minus right xtus
one right. So that's some kind of
information that we don't know. So here
basically we are computing xt minus one
from the xt. But if you wanted to
compute xt + one from the uh xt that
actually the noise terms here should be
computed based on the xt + one that's
the information that we don't know it's
like the chicken and the egg problem
right if we want to comput the noise
from the ft plus one then we first need
to comput xt plus one but for that we
actually need to comput the noise for
that right so is the chicken egg kind of
thing right so then what we can do is
that uh we can do some kind of the
approximation by assuming that uh this
the noise function would be kind of the
smooth function over the xt which means
that when this the noise term is for the
xt or for the xt + one these will be
very similar to each other. So we can
use those kind of assumption right for
some approximation. So there are some
kind of bunch of the ways to basically
approximate this like inverse process.
uh like the simplistic idea that people
particularly using is that given this
formulation what we do is that we simply
replace like all the t minus one into
the t + one uh in terms of that we are
having some approximation of the xt +
one here uh in a way that now we can
compute uh the process uh based on this
formulation but starting from the x0 now
we can compute x capital t
what's the difference with the typical
default process.
Yeah, deterministic uh for the typical
default process was the sampling the
process, right? Uh but now we want to
run the for process in a way that the x
capital t that we are getting uh can
come back to the x0 by the deterministic
ddim reverse process
make sense.
So this would be clear right. Uh so what
we do here is that we basically map the
input image XG here to the X capital T
by the immersion and running the
regeneration basically generating again
using the DDM the deterministic sampling
the generation process. Then when you
have some basically very tiny the time
interval basically having lots of the
time step uh that we can see that we can
almost perfectly come back to the
original image x here.
But as I said we are basically
approximating the xt + one by assuming
that the noise would be kind of similar
for the xt and x t + one. This
assumption will hold when you when the
time step is like very small right when
the number of time steps is like very
big. many lots of the steps. When you
basically chop the time domain within
many interval the the lots of the
intervals then we can use this
assumption and this we're going to be
able to regenerate images
which means that if we reduce the uh the
number of time step if we have some too
large the time intervals uh there will
be some kind of failure cases like this.
Okay.
But the interesting based on like this
EDI inversion is that we can do actually
many interesting things. uh one uh kind
of the application based on DDM
inversion is that combined with the CFG.
What we can do is that we run the
inversion uh with the original prompt
like a photograph of a puppy here and
then now running the reverse process
with a new prompt a photograph of a gray
cat. then we're going to be able to see
some results in practice in terms of
that the output is kind of similar uh
with the input image while now the
output is like aligned with the new text
prompt
interest so this is kind of like one
example that we can use the pre-trained
uh diffusion model uh CFG based
diffusion model for some kind of the
image editing uh examples so the
diffusion model not uh can not only
basically generating images but can be
used for some kind of like editing the
input image right
uh another example like taking a
photograph of a face and making the
person to wear the sunglasses and also
making the face to be colorful so those
kind of the editing can be done by
combining the DDI inversion and also the
classified free guidance any questions
on this
so we're going to for some more like
some practical ideas a few more the
ideas the latent diffusion uh basically
all the uh pre-trained uh the immediate
diffusion models are basically trained
based on some kind of latent space the
problem here is that uh we are basically
uh people are basically typically using
this kind of the very huge size of the
the data set for the training of the
image diffusion models taking 5.8 eight
billions of images and also with some
kind of the very high resolutions of the
images like this. So the problem of the
diffusion model is that uh once you
basically have some kind of the some
high dimension the the data as some kind
of the training the set the thing is
that all the latent the the variables
should have the same dimensional some
kind of vectors right so everything will
be going to run in the high dimensional
space that will basically involve some
kind of huge computation
so if you are going to train the
did you expect this amount of the
training the cost uh for the training
the image diffusion models. If you
directly train the diffusion model for
the five something kind of billions of
images with the large resolution, the
thing is that uh if you use a single GPU
for training all the diffusion models,
it will take about like more or less
like two or three years, three years uh
when you use the single GPU to just like
train the the models. uh not only for
the training but also for the generation
if you want to make some like the 10,000
images uh with the pretend model with a
single GPU it will take a day one day uh
so it's huge amount of the computations
so the question is that how can you make
it basically more effective in terms of
the uh computation the cost the thing is
that with the diffusion models uh we
cannot basically reduce the the
dimensions of the data the all the
latent variables should have the same
dimensions with the input data Right. So
that's kind of the one of the uh
disadvantages. Uh so what we going to do
is that we can simply consider uh doing
some kind of the image compression the
first in a way that reducing the
dimensions.
So in terms of reducing the uh
dimensionality uh we can consider
actually using the BAE but here the
thing is that this is basically BAE but
not basically having some kind of the
high weight for the key divergization.
So it's actually close to the
autoenccoder in a way that we do focus
more on some kind of a compression uh
into the latence piece. The thing is
that we are reducing the dimension from
like to the uh much lower the dimensions
compared to the originality resolutions
of the images. And once we basically map
all the the input data into the
relatively low dimension of the space uh
based on the latent vectors here we can
consider running the uh diffusion models
over that the latent space. So this is
like very typical kind of the framework
uh the architecture of the neuronet
network uh to train the diffusion models
in the latent space. The thing is that
you're going to first pre-train the
image encoder and the decoder in terms
of basically mapping all the input data
uh into low image this space and you're
going to also have some kind of the
module that is basically taking some
kind of the extra condition and the
mapping this into some kind of the
latent vectors here and the latent the
so you can see that now the uh whatever
the architectures that we have for the
noise prediction here the what will be
the input to the noise prediction the
network.
The input to the noise prediction
network was the XT uh which is the noisy
the data point the corrupted the data
point and also the time t right and
additionally we might also take some
kind of the conditions here and as the
output we are basically getting some
kind of the noise right and the noise
and the input data point these two
should have the same the dimensionality
right so it's matter of like what sort
of the architecture that we use for that
uh so previously people using the unit
for that. Obviously many recently the
models are using the transformer for
that. Uh so the input to this like the
unit should be the XT uh here and also
the time time information and then we
are basically combining this kind of
input information with the conditions uh
using the attention the model inside the
architectures.
So that's basically some typical ideas.
So we going to have some kind of cross
attention between the some conditioning
the module here and some kind of the the
uh the noise the the data point
information coming as the input and also
there are some kind of the uh some
practicality ideas in terms of some kind
of the noise manipulation by also
basically controlling the some kind of
the attention the kind of the waste
there but I'm going to skip those kind
of ideas here but this is some kind of
very typical architectures in terms of
the making some image diffusion models
and also many other diffusion models. So
as I said if you go to this web page
also if you just look into many
pre-trained diffusion models you're
going to see that actually many
diffusion models basically have the same
architecture like this.
Okay. Uh before we end up uh the the
today's lecture let me briefly go with
the kind of some few shot the ideas.
Uh so so there are actually the bunch of
the applications for the especially for
the uh image diffused models. So let me
go into some the basic ideas. So here
the the thing is that uh we have seen
the idea of the classify pre guidance
right that can take any kind of the
additional information as the condition.
But let's think about this special case
that we are taking uh image as the
condition uh when and also the output is
also the condition. So we want to make
some kind of the realistic images like
this by taking some other images like
the some the map or some kind of the
human pose as kind of the input
condition. So how can we effectively
train this kind of model? Like one idea
is obviously using the classified fake
guidance, right? Uh what would be the
issue uh if we just use the crystal fake
guidance to train this kind of thing?
Can you guess?
So for all the conditional models uh if
you want to train those models from
scratch that means that you need to have
all the pairs right. So for the image
generation uh we have seen that there is
the data set with the five billions of
images.
If you want to basically achieve the
same quality of the outputs while making
some kind of the conditional the model
that means that now you need to have not
only just like five billions of the
images but the five billions of the
pairs of those images
will you be able to have some kind of
the five billions of the pairs of the
edge map and the clean images I mean
this is kind of like doable right
because like you can compute this from
this way but this I'm not sure but
obviously it just takes like lots of
computation right uh for collecting the
five billions of the pairs and that also
will become like training another model
uh to make the condition of the models.
So that's the thing uh what we want to
do is that uh we want to fully utilize
the information that is basically
already learned uh from the pre-trained
uh image diffusion models that is
trained with the five billions of the
images uh while basically making some
kind of a conditional model without
really taking some five billions of the
pairs.
So let's think about the case that we
already have some kind of pre-trained
model trained with the five billion of
the images uh while only taking way
smaller set of the pairs like less than
like 100k uh or 50k or something uh by
doing some kind of the fine tuning with
some kind of the pre-trained model. uh
can you basically do some kind of fine
tuning of the pre model in a way to
making uh some condition the models with
the much smoother the number of the
pairs. So that's the basic idea and
actually if you want to make some kind
of your own model or making your own
service whatever based on the diffusion
models you going to face this kind of
the issues uh most for for many many of
the applications uh what the typically
the Japanese people are interested in is
basically making some kind of the some
Japanese anime images like conditioned
by the real images making some kind of
the anime images or some kind of doing
the opposite right for those kind cases
uh it's basically impossible to make
some kind of the five billions of pairs
for that right then how can you make
this kind of some the condition models
for example uh actually there are many
other cases not only for the images but
for the other domains in terms of making
some conditional degeneration
so we going to see some kind of special
case in terms of that the output and the
input the conditioning the data those
are basically having the same the
modality so we want to make some kind of
the images and also the input is also
the image in the same resolution for
this specific case. Uh what we want to
do uh so this is the special case that
we want to basically take this small
data set of the pairs while basically
having some very few the additional the
learnable parameters and making the the
network to be frozen.
So this is like really the practical the
idea.
So what we want to do is that we already
have some kind of here let's say this is
unit but it does not need to be unit it
can be transformer right so this is the
noise prediction the network uh which is
taking the uh the noise the data point
xt as the input and taking the time also
as the another the input and the
predicting the noise right so which
means that we already have some kind of
the encoder and the decoder encoding the
uh noisy the data point and the decoding
this back to the into the the the noise
here, right? Uh we want to fully utilize
this information while making another
encoder that can now can the encode the
additional the conditioned information.
So but here are some kind of the two big
conditions. The first thing is that uh
from the over the the finetuning uh we
want to basically uh initialize initiate
the fining the process in a way that
from the beginning we can still make
some kind of a realistic the outputs
while this output may not be fully
aligned with some kind of given the
condition. So that's the kind of some
trick in terms like you know um doing
some kind of the better defined tuning.
Uh since we already have some kind of
the working the neuronet network uh we
want to keep this neuronet to be working
uh in a way that still making some kind
of realistic outputs while this output
may not be aligned with the given the
condition but over the finetuning we
want to gradually basically fine-tune
all the things in a way that that the
output still remains as the realistic
while still like you know uh to be more
aligned with the given the condition. So
that's the first thing we want to
basically start this like the
fine-tuning the process in a way that uh
starting to make some kind of the
realistic the outputs basically
preserving all the information that is
learned in the pretend network
while this may not be fully aligned with
the given the condition but over
training we want that the output to be
still realistic but know taking some
more information from the condition
that's basically what we want to do the
first condition okay the second thing is
that this encoder was trained to take
the noise data point XT as the input
right
and this is like very different the
types of the images with the condition
that we are defeating here so this is
some kind of the conditioned images so
they can be some kind of the sketches or
some kind of human pose whatever kind of
things basically different types of
images and this is also not the clean
data point so these can be also some
kind of corrupted data point right so
these are basically two different types
of images,
but we want to basically still take the
information from this encoder, right? Uh
basically copying the whole encoder here
like this uh and making this like all
the parameters to be still the
trainable. Uh but if you directly feed
some kind of condition the image into
this encoder then basically this encoder
was not trained with this type of
images. So the output will be kind of
the garbage right. uh so we don't want
to start from like taking the garbage
from like taking this condition as the
jack input to the the this encoder. So
that's kind of second thing. So how can
you also gradually uh make this the new
the copy of the encoder to be gradually
adapted to the new types of the image uh
is kind of the first part and also the
second thing is that how can you also
gradually basically inject the
information learned by the this encoder
into this network uh in a way that you
know at the very beginning this does not
make any impact to this neural network
but over time we are you know slowly
basically injecting some information
that we learned from this encoder to
this encoder in a way that we can do
some kind of demorality alignment.
So that's the basic idea. Uh we are not
going to uh change all the parameters in
the pre-trained network. We only just
like copy the encoder uh in the part uh
while making all the parameters to be
trainable.
And this is the encoder for the new
condition here. This is the the
conditioned images right and all this
information will be basically fed into
the decoding part uh in a way that know
that that is basically injecting some
the uh the conditioned information.
But the key things in terms of that we
are gradually basically feeding the
conditioning information into this
encoder and also gradually feeding this
like learned information to the this
decoder uh is based on the zero
convolution.
So the idea of the convolution is
basically nothing but having some kind
of the two parameters like uh so let's
say this x is some kind of the can be
input or the output and we want we are
basically having the two pars here a and
the b here it's kind of like some find
the the the function right so having the
scale factor and the bias factor here
and we want to basically initialize both
a and the b uh to be zero which means
that at the very beginning uh this the
output of the zero convolution becomes
zero giving zero impact but over the
training uh we're going to start to
basically tune the A and the B here in
terms of that this becomes like some
non-zero value
so based on this information what we are
going to do is that this might be kind
of look complicated
the uh at the very beginning what you do
is that so this f was the encoder for
the noise data point here x Right, f was
the encoder in the pre-trained neural
network which is taking the noise data
point. So when the noise data point uh
is like fed to as the input to this
encoder, we're going to start to see
some kind of be some meaningful the
outputs right because this f was trained
to basically take this as the input but
we want to slowly inject the information
the condition here. So at the very
beginning we want to make the impact of
this to be zero. So what that's why we
use the zero convolution here making the
a1 and b1 to be zero which means that at
the very beginning this will be zero.
This becomes as like we are feeding the
x to the f right the same as basically
like we are running the the pretend in
the network but over training uh we're
going to basically start to have some
kind of non-zero var for the a1 the b1
and having some kind of the making some
impact with the condition here in a way
that while also basically slowly
basically uh know finetuning the all the
parameters of the app there so that's
basically the procedure that we are
slowly basically feeding some
information of the this condition uh
into this like copied encoder while also
basically adapting all the parameters of
like this copied encoder
and at the end what we also do is that
uh
for the output of this kind of the
copied encoder when you also feed this
information into the pre-tend neural
network uh at the very beginning we are
not going to basically uh you know have
this impact basically the output become
the same as just running the pre-trained
the the network But by having the zero
convolutional again making these two
term to be zero but over time when you
basically have some kind of non-zero
values here we're going to slowly
basically inject the information like
learned from the copy encoder into the
decoder here uh in a way that we can
also basically uh basically reflect the
information coming from the condition.
So that's the the basic idea.
So yeah check out some more details
about the architectures here. uh but the
based on this kind of the some uh
architecture some kind of the the
changes uh what you can do is that even
with some kind of the much similar the
number of the pairs compared to the the
training the data set uh we can see some
this kind of the very realistic the
outputs but also quite well aligned with
the given the condition. So this is kind
of the very interesting the idea
and actually there are some kind of the
more the architectures for that
collision is also another the kind of
the architectures in terms of not using
using the gated attention or this
something something but you can
basically check out that there are some
kind of the many interesting the ideas
in terms of making some conditionally
different models that can effectively
take some kind of the additional
condition. So the control net was
basically the case that we are taking
the init condition. Uh but for the other
cases we can consider using the CFG for
the many other things. So we're going to
know also discuss some kind of the more
the applications and more the techniques
in terms of like making some having some
uh the conditional diffusion models and
doing some kind of the guided
generation. Okay. Any questions on this?
So we're going to probably continue the
discussion for the like the conditional
degeneration and also the guided
generation probably after the week of
the midterm. Uh and this Wednesday as I
said we're going to have the the
assignment one session and then next
week uh we're going to actually come
back to the discussion about the
acceleration of the generation and we're
going to start to discuss the diffusion
models in the continuous time domain.