okay hi everyone I'll be started okay so
it's Tuesday of week two so hopefully
that means everyone has done the
assignment one everyone done assignment
one um you know uh I'm if I'm saying
this I'm probably saying it to the wrong
people but it it seems like every year
some people blow some of their um late
days on assignment one and it's really
just the wrong place to use them um so
yeah hopefully you've all done
assignment one um and did not that this
is meant to be the easy onramp um and
then we go straight on from that so that
out today we have assignment two so
assignment two um has two purposes um
purpose one is to make you do some math
um to um some understanding of what
newal networks really compute and how
they compute it and that's what I'm
going to talk about today is also going
through that math um but then
simultaneously maybe it does three
things in assignment two um so we're
going to be learning something about
dependency paing which will be actually
something about um language structure
and Linguistics but then thirdly um for
assignment two we're going to start
using pytorch so pytorch is is one of
the leading software Frameworks for deep
learning and the one that we're going to
um use for this class um so for p i mean
the assignment 3 pytorch is
exceedingly um scaffolded so it's sort
of you know here's this thing and you
have to write these two lines use these
two functions um but nevertheless um for
help people get up to speed and get
started using pytorch on Friday at 3:30
in Gates bo1 or it will again be
recorded um we have a tutorial on
pytorch and so that's a great way to get
more of a sense of py torch and how it
works before doing assignment
two um yeah uh the other things yeah so
for nearly all the lectures we've got um
further reading of places that you can
look um of all the classes in the attire
um this um for many people might be a
really good one to look at the suggested
readings we have several readings which
are sort of shorter tutorials and
reviews of the kind of um Matrix
calculus um and linear algebra that we
need for this class um so really
encourage you um to look at those um if
you decide that one is your favorite you
can tell us on Ed which one you think is
the best one to choose between between
them I kind of like the one that's first
on the list but maybe you'll feel
differently um yeah um conversely um
yeah so today will be sort of all math
and then Thursday will be kind of all
language and Linguistics some people
find the language and Linguistics hard
as well um so I guess different kinds of
people um okay so getting straight into
it um so where we started last time um
I'd sort of shown these baby neural
networks and sort of said well we can
think of each of those orange things as
basically like a little logistic
regression unit and the crucial
difference from then the kind of um
statistics machine learning you see in a
stats class 109 or wherever is that in
those you have one logistic regression
and you're defining the input features
to it and you've got some decision
variable that you want to un have at the
output here you're sort of building
these Cascades of little logistic
regressions and so the idea is right at
the end we're going to Define what we
want we're going to capture that by our
objective function or loss function but
for the stuff in the middle that that
stuff in the middle is going to be a
chance for the neural network to learn
by itself what would be useful inputs to
further Downstream neurons what kind of
functions should I come up with in terms
of my inputs that will help me provide
um useful outputs to help the final
computation down the track um and you
know if you haven't sort of seen and um
thought about this much before I mean I
think you know it's worth uh sitting
with that idea for a moment CU this is
really a super powerful idea which is
what's made neural networks more
powerful in most circumstances than
other forms of machine learning the fact
that you have this
self-organization of intermediate levels
of representation that you use to
compute things that will be useful
Downstream for what you eventually want
to
do um the other reason I was bring back
up this picture is I've sort of wanted
to go straight from here um to matric
um so while you could sort of wire
together neurons however you wanted to
and arguably if you look at human brains
they look more like neurons wired
together however you wanted to but for
what's done with neural networks
basically there's always this kind of
regular structure of layers so once we
have this regular structure of layers we
are taking um the output of one of our
neurons at one layer and we're feeding
them together with weights um to produce
um the inputs to the next layer so we're
taking the X1 X2 X3 outputs we're
multiplying them all by weights we're
adding a bias
term um and then we're going to put it
through a nonlinearity and that will
give us the value at the next layer so
if we then kind of collapse that to a
vector and this to a vector
that then collapses into a computation
that first of all we're doing a matrix
multiplication we're calculating WX of
the inputs and then we're adding on the
biases as a a vector of biases which
gives us this intermediate value Z and
then we have this nonlinearity or
activation function which is applied um
to that which gives us the values in the
next layer of the new Network and the
activation function is applied to a
vector and produces a vector but it's
operating on each of the individual
components of that Vector one at a time
so we've got some Scala function that
we're just applying to each element of
the
vector um and so that's the kind of
picture um we saw when I did this
example and I'm going to continue to use
this example in today's class remember
we were going to decide whether the word
in the middle of the input window was a
location or not and so we were doing the
matrix multiplication putting it through
the nonlinearity we're then just doing a
DOT product here and then we're going
that got stuck into um uh sigmoid um to
predict yes or no um and the final thing
I wanted to say a little bit about is
these FS the
nonlinearity or the activation function
and where did they come in well the
starting point of where they came in in
the history of newal networks is when
people came up with this idea that well
you could represent um the operation of
a basic neuron by doing a matrix
multiplication of the inputs and then
having a bias term or here represents a
threshold term to see whether the
neurons should fire or not that was
actually in the very first
implementation which B dates back to the
1940s as done as a threshold right so
that if um the activation was greater
than Theta you output one otherwise you
output zero and well if you have a
threshold um the the two lines are flat
right so there is no slope there is no
gradient um so that's actually makes
learning much harder so the whole secret
of what we build with newal networks and
in an alternative name that's um popular
in some circles these days is
gradient-based learning and the entire
idea of gradient based learning is if we
actually have some slopes um then it's
like going skiing during spring break
you can work out where it's steeper and
you can head down where it's steeper um
and that will allow us to op imiz our
function to learn much more quickly and
so that's one reason that we don't just
want to have threshold units we want to
have things with slopes so we um have
gradient so in subsequent work people
started using activation functions with
slopes um and so the first popular one
um was this sigmoidal logistic that
we've seen for mapping to probabilities
but you know it's sort of imperfect it
seemed because you know the output was
always non- negative so that sort of
tends to push things towards bigger
numbers so um there was quite a bit of
use then of this tan H function um and
you'll actually see tan H when we do
assignment three we'll be using tan H's
in our current new networks um and so um
I've written there um the formula
usually give for Tan H in terms of
exponentials um yeah if your math is
Rusty it's not obvious that tan H and
logistic have much to do with each other
um but if you want to treat this as a
math problem um that a 10 H is literally
just a rescaled logistic you're
stretching it by two and moving it down
by one it's the same function
um okay um but you know so that's nice
but if you're calculating 10 hes you
have to do all of these exponentials and
you know exponentials are kind of slow
on your computer and things like that
you might wonder whether you couldn't
get away with something much cheaper and
so people thought about that and thought
oh maybe we could just use a so-called
hard tan H um where it has a slope of
one in the middle and is then just flat
outside that area and you know that
seemed to work in many cases and so that
then led to the popularity of the
rectified linear unit um so the
rectified linear unit is simply zero on
the negative region and then is yal x in
the positive region now this seems kind
of wonky and goes against what I was
saying about gradient based learning
because once you're in the negative
region there's no gradient um you're
just dead um but in the positive region
there is gradient and the gradient is
particularly simple right the slope is
always one um and so you know this still
feels slightly perverse to me but you
know this really became the norm of what
people use for a number of years because
people found that although for an
individual neuron it was dead half the
time anytime it went negative that
overall for your newal network some
things would be alive so it kind of gave
sort of a form of specializ ation and
the fact that the slope was always one
meant that you got um really easy
productive backward flow of gradients in
a way we'll talk about later and so um
learning with realu turned to be out to
be very effective and people started
using the realu nonlinearity everywhere
and it sort of became the default in the
norm and you'll see us using it in the
assignments in particular we use it in
assignment to and so get to see that it
works but nevertheless at some point
people sort of had second thoughts and
decided you know having a dead over half
of its range maybe isn't such a good
idea after all even though it seemed to
work great for a few years and so a lot
of what's happened since then is then to
come up with other functions which are
in some sense Ru like but not actually
dead um so
um um
okay I don't really yeah uh here we go
enough so one one version of that is the
socalled Leaky value so for the Leaky
value you make the negative half a
straight line as well with a very minor
slope but still it's got a little bit of
slope um there is then a variant of that
called the parametric value where you
have one extra parameter which is
actually what the slope of the ne the
negative part is and people showed some
positive result with that um more
recently again and this is what you
often see in recent Transformer models
um is you see um nonlinearities like
Swiss swis and Jello so both of these
are sort of fancy functions but kind of
what they both look like is basically
this is yal X to all intense and
purposes not quite but approximately and
then you got sort of some funky bit of
curve down here which again gives you a
bit of slope um it's sort of the curve
is going the opposite way that's sort of
a bit funny but they seem to work well
commonly used um in recent Transformer
models um so you know that's a bit of a
dump of all the nonlinearities people
use I mean the details of that aren't
super important right now but the
important thing to um have in your head
is why do we need nonlinearities and the
way to think about about that is that
what we're doing with neural networks is
function approximation there's some very
complex function that we want to learn
you know like maybe we want to go from a
piece of text to its meaning or we want
to be interpreting visual scenes or
something like that um and so we want to
build really good function
approximators and well if you're just
doing Matrix multiplies a matrix
multiply of a vector is a linear
transform so that doesn't let you
multiply complex functions I guess
strictly if you put a bias on the end
it's then an aine transform but let's
keep it simple linear transforms right
so if you're doing multiple if you're
doing multiple Matrix multiplies you're
doing multiple linear transforms but
they compose so you could have just
multiplied these two matrices together
and you'd have a single linear transform
so you get no power in terms of
representation by having multi-layer
networks that are just Matrix multiplies
you know as in a little aside in terms
of representational power having
multi-layer Matrix multiplies gives you
no power but if you think about in terms
of learning actually it does give you
some power so in the theoretical
Community looking at newal networks
there actually quite a few papers that
look at linear newal networks meaning
that they're just sequences of the
multiplies with no nonlinearities
because they have interesting learning
properties even though they give you no
representational power um okay but we'd
like to be able to learn functions like
this not only functions like this and to
be able to learn functions like this we
need more than linear transforms and we
achieve those by having something that
makes us be calculating a nonlinear
function and it's these activation
functions that give us nonlinear
functions okay cool
um okay so then getting on to today so
the whole thing we want to do now is
gradient based learning right this is
our stochastic gradient thecenter
equation where here you know that upside
down triangle symbol right that's our
gradient we're wanting to work out the
slope of our objective function and so
this is how we're going to learn by
calculating gradients so what we want to
know is how do we calculate the
gradients for an arbitrary function and
so what I want to do today is first of
all do this by hand um for math um and
then discuss you know how do we do it
computationally um which is effectively
um the famous thing that's taken as
powering um underpowering all of neuron
Nets which is the back propagation
algorithm but the back propagation
algorithm is just automating the math
okay and so for the math it's Matrix
calculus and at this point then there's
a huge Spectrum um between people who
know much more math than me and people
who barely ever learned this um but you
know uh I hope to explain the
essentials um or remind people of them
um enough that you're at least at a
starting point um for reading some other
stuff and doing homework too so um let's
get into that and so I'm going to spend
about half the time on those two halves
um and you know the hope is that after
this you'll feel like oh I actually
understand how new networks work under
the hood fingers crossed
okay so here we go so if you're a
Stanford student um you maybe did math
51 um or else you could have done math
51 which teaches linear algebra
multivariate calculus and modern
applications um math 51 covers every
everything I'm going to talk about and
way more stuff so if you actually know
that and remember it you can um look at
Instagram for the next 35 minutes um but
I think the problem is um that you know
quite apart from the fact a lot of
people do it as Frost um you know this
is a lot to get through in 10 weeks and
I think that a lot of the people who do
this class sort of by two years later
don't really have much ability to use
any of it um but you know if you
actually looked at this book really
Harden for a very really long time you
would have discovered that actually
right towards the end of the book in
appendix G um there's actually an
appendix on newal networks and the
multivariable chain roll which is
precisely what we're going to be using
um for um doing our neural networks um
but there are only two problems one
problem is that this is Page 697 of the
book and I'm not sure anyone ever gets
that far and the problem is even if you
do get that far you know I don't know I
find these pages that they're really
dense texty Pages it's not even easy to
understand them if you have gone there
so here's my attempt on that um so the
Mantra to have in your head is G if I
can remember basic single variable
calculus you know that I've got 3x squ
and the derivative of that is 6X that's
all you sort of need to know right the
ENT is multivariable calculus is just
like single variable calculus except
you're using
matrices okay so that's our article of
faith and we're going to do that and so
what we're wanting to do is to do Matrix
calculus or the generalization of that
tensor calculus sort of using um vectors
matrices and higher order tensors
because if we can do things and what's
referred to as vectorized gradients in
the neural network world that that will
be sort of the fast efficient way to do
our operations you know so if you want
to think it all through you can do it
single variable at a time and check that
you're doing the right thing and I sort
of tried to indicate that in the first
lecture but if we want to have our
networks go room we want to be doing
Matrix
calculus okay so let's work up to doing
that okay so this is the part that I I
trust everyone can remember right so we
have f ofx = x cubed and we can do
single variable um derivative and the
derivative is
3x² everyone remember that one okay
that's something we can all start from
and remember this derivative is saying
the slope of things right so the slope
of things lets us work out where is
something steep so we'll be able to go
skiing right that's our goal right and
so you can think of the slope of things
as how much the output will change if we
change the input a bit right that's our
measure of um steepness right so um that
so since the derivative is 3x^2 if we're
at x = 1 that means the slope is about 3
* 1 S 3 so if I work out the value of
the function for 1.01 it's gone up by
about three times point I move the X by
0.01 and the output moved by 0.03 where
if I go to x = 4 the derivative is 3 *
4^2 is 48 and so if I work out the value
of the function at 4.01 I get
approximately
64.4 versus 64 right that small
difference from 4 to 4.01 has been
magnified 48 times in the output okay
okay so now we just uh remember the
Mantra it's going to be exactly the same
single value calculus um but with more
stuff so if we have a function with n
inputs we're then going to work out its
gradient um which is its partial
derivative with respect to each input so
its gradient will now be a vector of the
same size as the number of inputs um and
there's this funky symb
um which people pronounce various ways I
mean you know this kind of originated
some kind of someone's weird way of
drawing a calligraphic d right so it is
really a D um so I think I'll mainly
just call it D but sometimes people call
it partial or funy D or some some other
name right so you have DF dx1 DF dx2 for
each of the variables okay so if we go
beyond that um and then have a function
with um n inputs and M outputs what we
then get for um the gradient is what's
referred to as the Jacobian now actually
um the dude this is named after was a
German Jew so it should really be yakobi
um but no one says that in this country
um Jacobian um okay so the Jacobian is
then a matrix of partial
derivatives um where you're working out
for each output and each input the
partial derivative between the component
of the input and the output so this
looks like the kind of thing that we're
going to have when we have a neural
network layer because we're going to
have um n inputs and M outputs for the
two layers of our neural networks so
we'll be using these kind of
jacobians okay um so then you know the
whole idea of newal networks is we've
got these
multi-level
computations and they're going to
correspond to composition of functions
so we need to know how to compose things
both for calculating functions and for
calculating their gradients so if we
have a one variable function and we want
to um work out um its derivative in
terms of a composition of two functions
what we're doing is multiplying um our
computations okay so um if you compose
together um Z of Y um that's the
function that we did at the beginning
that gives you oh was it no it's not
sorry it's different okay Z of Y gives
you
3x2 right and so we know that the
derivative of that is um
6X okay if we do it in terms of the
pieces we can work out DZ
Dy um which is just going to be three
and um Dy DX is 2X and we can work out
the total derivative by multiplying
these two pieces and we get 6X the same
answer right um so um Matrix calculus is
exactly like single variable calculus
except we're using um tensors of
different um so the word tensor is used
to mean as you go up that Spectrum in in
its size so from sort of Scala to Vector
to Matrix to then you know what in
computer science is normally still uh is
multidimensional arrays um that spectrum
is then tensors of different um
Dimensions okay so um when we have
multiple variable functions we're going
to multiply jacobians so here we have a
function WX + B and then we um compose
um the nonlinearity F to get H and so
we're going to be able to compute that
in the same way as a product of these
partial derivatives which are
jacobians okay so let's start looking at
a few examples of what we get so let's
count with start with an element wise
activation function so when we have a a
vector that's being calculated as the
activation function of a previously
computed quantity well we're Computing
that component wise as I explained
before so hi equals F of Z and where the
sort of f is our activation function
that actually applies to a scalar but
you know overall this layer is a
function with n outputs and N inputs and
so it's going to have an N by n Jacobian
and well what that's going to so this is
our definition of the Jacobian um but in
this case this is sort of a special case
because if I equals J um then we're
going to have um the output um
J the HJ depending on Z and otherwise
it's going to be zero CU for the off
diagonal entries it doesn't matter how
you change the value it's not changing
the output because the output only
depends on the corresponding index and
so what we're going to get for this
Jacobian of activation functions is a
matrix where everything is zero apart
from the diagonal terms um that
correspond to where we're calculating
the activation function and for those
ones we're going to have to work out how
to compute the derivative of our
activation function that was on
assignment one one of the questions on
assignment one I do believe or or was it
on assignment two no no it's assignment
two one of the questions on assignment
two I got that wrong one of the ones on
the new assignment is say hey um can you
work out um the derivative of a logistic
function well then we'd be a to plug
that straight into um fpre so I'm not
going to give that answer away today um
okay so um other things that we want to
do um with uh Jacobian is well we have
this um layer of our neural network
where we're um calculating WX + B and we
can want to work out the partial
derivative of that with respect to X um
you know this is the kind of place where
it actually works to remember the Mantra
and say Matrix calculus is just like
single value variable calculus but with
matrices so if you just don't use your
bra too hard and think oh it's just like
single variable calculus so what should
the answer be it's obviously going to be
W right and indeed it is um similarly if
we want to do the same thing for wxb and
work out the partial derivative with
respect to B um well that would be one
in terms of single variable calculus and
so in Matrix calculus that becomes an
identity Matrix okay slightly different
the same idea um but that's reflecting
the fact that b is actually Vector so we
need we need it to be coming out um as
an identity Matrix um okay so um higher
up in my example picture I did this sort
of vector um do product of
UT um and well what happens if we work
out the um the
um to C in of that what we end up with
strict ly is we come out with
HT um and you know this is sort of like
when you're working out um well we did
this in the first class right when we
did a a DOT product calculation that you
kind of get for each individual element
you get the opposite term and so you get
um the other Vector coming out um these
are sort of good ones to comput it at
home for practice to make sure um you
really do know the answers and why they
work out the way they
do okay um so let's go back to our
little neural net um this was most of
our neural net up above our neural net
um there was the
nonlinearity now I'm going to uh leave
that out of this time oh see I got it
wrong it's on assignment two um but you
know normally you'd be C calculating the
partials of the output the loss function
with respect to the inputs but since the
loss function is On Assignment two I'm
going to leave that out and I'm just
going to calculate derivatives with
respect to this score that feeds into
the loss function so we first we got um
the newal network layer the nonlinearity
and then we're doing this dot product to
work out a score for each position which
feeds into the logistic function so if
you want to work out
ddb um so that's with respect to the
bias for first so the way we do it is
you know we break up our equations into
our individual pieces that are composed
together and so that means we break this
up so we first calculate the zal WX + B
then we apply the activation function to
the different
components okay then after that
um what we remember to do is okay to
work out um our um partial derivatives
of B of s with respect to B that what
we're going to be doing is doing the
product of um the partial derivatives of
the component pieces so we're applying
um The Matrix calculus version of the
chain rule so dsdb equals D sdh * DHD Z
*
dzb um and which corresponds to these
three layers that are composed together
and so at that point um we remember our
useful jacobians from the previous slide
and we can just apply them so the top
one um DSD is um the you
transpose or else or maybe it's you
let's come back to that there's a fine
point on that that I will explain more
about later um
um okay um then for the DH DZ that was
the activation function where we got the
diagonal of um the derivative of f of Z
and then for dzdb that's where we got
the identity function okay um so we can
simplify that down and so what that's
going to end up as is the UT transpose
that funny symbol there times the um the
vector
element y's um derivative of f um this
symbol which doesn't normally turn up um
in your regular math course but turns up
all the time in New networks is referred
to as the Hadad product and the Hadad
product is meaning element wise
multiplication so it's not like a cross
product where you put two vectors
together and you get out one number of
Scala you put two vectors together you
element wise multiply them all and
you're left with another Vector of the
same
type okay so that so now this gave us
are working out of the partials of dstb
and for a neural network um we want to
work out all the other partials as well
so overall here in the picture right we
had the X the W the B um and the U and
we'd like to work out partials with
respect to all of those variables so we
can change their values and learn so
that our model predicts better um so um
so suppose we now want to um calculate
ddw so again we can split it up with the
same chain Rule and say
ddw equals the product of these three
things and the important thing to notice
is that two of those three things were
exactly the same ones that we calculated
before the only bit that's different is
that at the end we're now doing DZ DW
rather than
dzdb and so the first central idea that
we'll come back to when we do
computation graphs is oh we really want
to avoid doing repeated work so we want
to realize that those two parts of
things are the same and since we're just
sort of multiplying these um partial
derivatives together right we can just
compute what that part is and reuse it
and so if we want to um wait yeah okay
so if we're wanting to calculate
ddw the part that's the same this part
here we can refer to as Delta so Delta
is sort of the Upstream gradient or the
error signal the part that you've got
from sort of starting at the beginning
DS DH DH DZ this sort of shared Upstream
part we can calculate that once and then
we can use it um to calculate both of
these two things and for dsdb because
the dzdb just comes out as the identity
Matrix um the answer is just Delta but
for D
sdw we need to work out the DZ DW before
we're
finished okay so what um does what do we
get for that last piece so one question
you might start off with and is normally
a good thing to think about when you're
doing assignment problems on this and
other things is the first thing to think
about is you know what do things look
like like am I should the answer be a
vector a matrix uh what size should it
be and things like that so for
ddw um W is an N bym Matrix
um and S is a scalar so therefore since
we have one output and M * m inputs the
answer according to math should be that
we've got a one by n * m Jacobian I a
big long row Vector um but here's where
um things get a teeny bit tricky um and
there's sort of we end up with this
weird mess of um math and Engineering
convenience because you know immediately
what we're wanting to do is we're
wanting to take our old parameters which
will be in stored in the form of
matrices vectors and so on that we're
using as coefficients and we're going to
want to subtract from them um our you
know a fraction of our calculated
gradient so what we'd like to do is have
our um calculated gradients in the same
shapes as our parameters because then we
can just do subtraction whereas if
they've turned into a God Almighty row
Vector um that's not quite so convenient
um so it turns out that what we end up
doing um is using something that gets
referred to as the shape convention that
um we
uh uh
reshape our um jacobians so they fit
into things that are of the same shape
as the parameters that we are using so
we're going to represent um DSD W as an
N bym Matrix laid out as follows and
that's a place that one people can get
confused okay so that's what we want to
calculate that kind of Matrix but um and
so that Matrix is going to be Delta * DZ
DW so Delta is going to be part of the
answer and then we want to know um what
DZ DW is um and the answer is going to
be it's going to come out like this so D
sdw is going to be um delta T * XT so
it's going to be the product of the
Upstream gradient which was the same
thing we calculated before for the other
two quantities and then a local inputs
symbol which um is input signal which is
here coming out to
XT okay um and you know so we're taking
the transposes of those two vectors
which it means that we end up
calculating an outer product of those
two vectors um which gives us our
gradient um and so why is that the right
answer well you know it kind of looks
convenient CU that's giving us something
of the right shape um for what I was
arguing we want to find out and we have
the right number of terms um now I'm
going to rush through this so I
encourage you to read um the uh lecture
notes and do this more carefully but um
let me at least a little bit explain why
it makes sense right so um if you think
of one weight um in so all of these
connections are our Matrix right The
Matrix is being represented by all these
lines and in your network so if you
think of one number in The Matrix so
here is
w23 so it's connecting from input 3 or
it's multiplying input three to give
part of the answer of
H2 right so it's this line here um so
for this line here um this weight is
being used only in the calculation of
H2 and the only thing it's dependent on
is X3 um so that if you're then wanting
to work out the partial
of um h
two um or Z2 sorry yeah um sorry yeah
sorry Z2 the partial of Z2 with respect
to X3 it's sort of depending on these
two pieces only and that's what you're
achieving um by working out um the sort
of outer product like
that okay um yeah so let me just come
back um one more time to um this the
sort of question of the shape of
derivatives
um you know so I already sort of fudged
it um when I was sort of um talking
about oh should I put the the transpose
there or should I nod and get a row
vector is a column Vector um so there's
sort of this disagreement between
whether you kind of have the Jacobian
form which is what actually makes the
chain roll work right in terms of doing
multiplication um versus the shape
convention which is how we store
everything for our computations and Mak
doing stochastic gradient descent where
you're um subtracting um whatever kind
of tensor you have easy um so
um you know this can be a source of
confusion um since we're doing a
computer science course for the answers
in the assignment we expect you to
follow the shape convention so you know
if you're working out the derivatives
with respect to some Matrix it should be
shaped like a matrix with the same
parameters um but you know you may well
want to think about Jacobian forms and
Computing your answers I mean there are
sort of two ways to go about do doing
this one way of doing it is to sort of
work out all the math using Jacobian Al
math 51 and at the end just to reshape
it so it fits into the same shape as the
parameters according to our shape
convention I mean the other way is to
sort of do each stage following the
shape convention but then you sort of
have to be game to sort of reshape
things as needed by sort of doing um
transposing to have things work out at
the different
stages okay that was my attempt to
quickly review the
math most people are still here um I
will now go on to the second half and go
on to the um How We Do the computation
right so you know so most of um yeah so
the famous thing that powers new
networks is the back propagation
algorithm so the back propagation
algorithm is really only two things you
know its invention made people famous
because it gave an effective learning
algorithm but you know at a fundamental
level the back propagation algorithm is
only two things thing one is you use the
chain rule you do calculus of complex
functions and Thing Two is
um you store intermediate results so you
never recompute the same stuff again
that's all there is to the um back
propagation
algorithm and so let's just go through
that so if we're
computationally wanting to deal um with
you know functions and doing back
propagation we can think of them as
being represented as a graph and in some
way or another um this kind of graph is
being used inside your newal network
framework so here is here is a re-
representation of my little neural
network for finding whether the word at
the center is a location so I'm taking
the X Vector input I'm multiplying it by
W I'm adding B to it I'm putting it
through the
nonlinearity and then I'm um doing the
dot product with my Vector U right so
that was my computation and so the The
Source nodes are the inputs in this
graph the interior nodes then the
operations I do um and so then the edges
that connect those together then pass
along the result of each operation so I
passed along WX to the addition function
with B then I that gives me Z that I
pass through the nonlinearity which
gives me H which I then um dot product
with the U to get S okay so I do
precisely this computation and this is
referred to as Ford propagation or the
forward pass of a neural network so um
the forward pass just calculates
functions okay but then once we've done
that what we want to
do is then work out gradients so we can
do gradient based learning and so that
part is then referred to as back
propagation or the backward pass and
then we run things backward so for
running things backward we're going to
use the same graph and we're going to
backwards pass along at gradients and so
we start at the right hand side and we
have dsds so dsds is just one because
you know um if you change S you've
changed s and then what we want to do is
sort of then work further back so we can
work out DSD ddz dsdb ddw dsdx as we
work back um and so this is um the what
we want to work out with gradients um
and so how are we going to do that well
if we look at a single node so for
example our um our nonlinearity node but
any node where H equal F ofx what we can
have is an upstream gradient um DS DH
and what we want to do is calculate the
downstream gradient of the next variable
down the D
sdz and the way that we're going to do
that is we're going to say well let's
look at F what is F's gradient and
that's going to be our local gradient
and then this is immediately what gives
us the chain rule
that D sdz is going to be the product of
our Upstream gradient D sdh times the
DHD Z the local um gradient that we
calculate at that node so Downstream
gradient equals um Upstream gradient
times local
gradient
um oh yeah that's what that's what it
says when I press um that again okay so
this is the sort of the um single the
single input single output case though
those inputs might be vectors or
matrices or something like that um we
then have sort of more complex graph
cases um
so I think I should have retitled this
SL oh yeah so still so sorry so the next
case is for our node it might have
multiple inputs so this is where we're
calculating
WX so in that case we still have an up
we have a single Upstream gradient and
then what we're going to do is we want
to calculate the downstream gradient
with respect to each input and the way
we're going to do that is we're going to
work out the local gradient with respect
to each input and then we're going to do
the same kind of multiplication of
Upstream gradient times local gradient
with respect to each input again um
chain
rule okay um so here's a little example
of this so I'm this isn't really uh the
kind of thing you normally see in a
neural network but it's an easy example
so F of XYZ is going to be x + y * the
max of y z and we've got current values
of X Y and Z of 1 2 and z respectively
so here's our little computation graph
um and so for forward propagation you
know we're going to do this addition
we're going to do this Max function and
then we're going to multiply the two and
that gives us the value of f um so we
can run that with the current values of
X Y and Z and this is what we get so the
max of two and 0 is two addition is
three the answer is six okay so then
after having done that we run the
backward propagation and yeah so this
procedure you know is not actually
special to new networks right you can
use it for any piece of math if you want
to just run your math um on pytorch
rather than um working it out in your
head or with Mathematica um okay so now
we work out um backwards so we want to
know the local gradient so d a DZ is
going to be one
sorry I said that wrong d a DX is going
to be 1 so a = x + y d a d y = 1 um for
the max function that's going to depend
on which of the two is larger because
it's going to have a slope of one for
the one that's the biggest and zero for
the one that's the smallest um and then
for the product that's like what we saw
with vectors that dfda is going to be B
and D FDB is going to be a um so those
are all our local gradients and so then
we can use those to calculate out the
derivatives so dfdf is one um we then
multiply that by the two um local
gradients um that are
calculated
um for A and B so that gives us um two
and three where you're swapping over the
numbers then for the max um that we're
having the one that is biggest um we're
taking the Upstream times one so it gets
three the other one gets zero and then
for the plus we're just sending the
gradient down in both directions and so
both of them come out as two um and so
that gives us DF DX so the final
function value is two D
fdy we're taking the three and adding
the two I'll mention that again in a
minute which gives us five and then
DFD Z is zero um and we should be able
to again be able to quickly check that
we've got this right right so um if we
consider you know the slope around um Z
as you change z a little so Z is Z if we
make Z
0.1 that makes absolutely no difference
to what the computed function value is
um so the gradient there is zero that's
correct um so if I change up the Top If
I change x a little bit right if I
change X to
1.1 then I'll be calculating um 1.1 + 2
is
3.1 um and then I'll be taking the max
which is two and I'll be calculating
5.1 um and so wait no I did that
wrong oh times two
wait I didn't do the multiplication
right um sorry yeah so we get the 3.1
that's multiplied by two that gives us
6.2 so a change of 0.1 in the X has
moved things up by 2 so that corresponds
to the gradient being two and so then
the final case is well what if we change
y to um so y started off as two and made
it 2.1 then we're going to get 2.1
multiplied by 1 is
2.1 61 6.5 and right and then we've got
the 2.1
here the oh sorry I keep doing this
wrong 2.1 + 1 = 3.1 and then we've got
2.1 as the max so we've got 2.1 *
3.1 and that comes out to be
6.51 so it's approximately gone up by so
our 0.1 difference has gone up to
approximately 0.5 this is just an
estimate um and so that correspond to
the gradient being five right we get
this five times multiplication of our
changes okay um and so that that fact
that illustrates the fact that the right
thing to do is when you have outward
branches in your um computation graph
and you're running the um back
propagation that what you do is you sum
the gradients right um so that for this
case we had y being um the Y is sort of
going into these two different things in
our previous chart so once we've worked
out the Upstream gradients we sum them
to get the total gradient and so that's
what we did back here we had two outward
things and we sort of took these
calculated Upstream gradients of two and
three and we just summ them to get five
and that gave the right answer
okay um and so you can think about that
um for the sort of just generally how
the sort of things to think about as
sort of gradients move around in these
pictures so that when we have a plus
operation that um plush just sort of
distributes gradient so the same
gradient that's the Upstream gradient
goes to each input
um when you have a Max it's kind of like
a router of gradient so the max is going
to send the gradient to one of the
inputs and send nothing at all to the
other inputs um and when you have a
multiplication it's a little bit funky
because you're sort of um doing this
sort of switching of the forward
coefficient so you're taking the
Upstream gradient multiplied by the
opposite um for coefficient gives you
your um Downstream
gradient okay um so we kind of have this
systematic way of being able to sort of
forward pass calculate the values of
functions then run this backward to work
out um the um gradients heading down the
network and so the main other thing of
the back propagation algorithm is just
that we want to do this
efficiently so the wrong way to do it
would be to say well gee I want to
calculate dstb
ddw dsdx ddu so let me start doing those
one at a time and when I've done them
all I will stop because that means if
you first calculated dstb you do all of
the part that's in blue um but then if
you went on to DS
DW um you'd be calculating all the part
in red and well just as we saw in the
math part when we were doing it as math
um these parts are exactly the same
you're doing exactly the same
computations so you only want to do
those that part once and work out this
Upstream gradient or error signal that
is being then sort of calculated and is
then being shared so the picture that we
want to have is you're doing together
the Shar part and then you're only sort
of doing separately the little bits um
that you need to
do okay um boy I seem to have been
rushing through today and I'm going to
actually end early unless anyone is
going to slow me down but I did have uh
just a few more slides um to go through
um yeah so the sort of
generalization of this as an algorithm
is you know in the general case you know
so we normally have these sort of neural
network layers and matrices which you
can represent as vectors and
matrices um and you know it's sort of
nice and clean and it looks like um
doing that in Calculus class I mean
strictly speaking that isn't necessary
so the algorithm for forward propagation
and backward propagation that I've
outlined that you can have it work in a
completely arbitrary comput ation graph
providing it's a dag that doesn't have
Cycles in it um so the general algorithm
is well you've got a whole bunch of
variables that depend on other variables
there's some way in which we can sort
them so that each variable only depends
on variables to the left of it so that's
referred to as a topological sort of the
outputs and so that means there's a way
we can do a forward pass where we're
calculating um variables in terms of
ones that have already been calculated
but you know if we want to have some
extra wonky AR so it's not like nice
Matrix multiplies or anything we're
totally allowed to um do that or we can
have things not fully connected right so
there's no connections across here right
we can have an arbitrary computation
graph um and so that gives us our
forward propagation and then once we've
done the forward propagation we can
initialize the output gradient as as one
and then we're going to visit the nodes
in reverse order and at for each node
we're going to compute a gradient by
using the Upstream gradient and the
local gradient to compute the downstream
gradient and so then we can head back
down the computation graph and work out
all of the downstream gradients and so
the crucial thing to notice is that if
you do it correctly um that working out
um the the gradients has the same bigo
complexity as working out the forward
calculation right so that if you're
doing more you know in if if in terms of
Big O terms right you might have
different functions depending on what
the derivatives are but in bigo terms if
you're doing more work in the backward
path than you're doing in the forward
paths that means that you're somehow
failing to do this um efficient
computation and that you're recomputing
some of your
work okay um so because we have such a
good algorithm here you should be able
to just work out the backward path
automatically and that that gets
referred to as automatic differentiation
so if you had the symbolic form of what
you're calculating with your forward
pass um you should just be able to say
yo computer um can you work out the
backward pass for me and you know kind
of mathematical like it could look at
the symbolic form of all of your
functions um work out their derivatives
and do the entire thing for you um so
early on there was a
pioneering um deep learning framework
theano principally from the um
university of Montreal which attempted
to do precisely that that you had the
entire forward path computation started
in symbolic form and it just did the
entire thing for you and worked out the
backward pass
automatically um but you know somehow
that sort of proved to be um too
heavyweight or um hard to deal with
different things or people just like to
write their own python or whatever it is
um so that idea did not fully succeed
and so what in practice all of the
current main Frameworks have fallen back
on is something that's actually less
automated than that so it's sort of like
we've gone backwards in time but the
software's g a lot better really it's a
lot staer and faster um so all of the
modern deep learning Frameworks sort of
say look I will manage the computation
graph for you and I can run the forward
propagation path and the backward
propagation path but you're going to
have to work out the local um
derivatives yourself um so if you're if
you're putting in a layer or putting in
um you know a function like an
activation function in the in a neural
network your class your python class
that represents that you're going to
have to tell me what the forward um
computation is and what the local
gradient is and I'm just going to call
your local gradient and assume it's
correct um so there's a bit more that
has to be done manually so so the part
that's automated then um is that you
know when you know precisely this code
obviously but roughly you know inside
the Deep learning software um it's
Computing with a computation graph and
it's got a forward and a backward and
it's doing what I presented on the
pictures before so for the forward um
pass it's topologically sorting all the
nodes of the graph and then it's going
through them and for each node in the
graph it's calling its forward function
which will be able to compute its local
value in terms of its inputs which have
already been calculated because it's
topologically sorted and then it's um
running the backward pass and in the
backward pass you're reversing your
topological sort and then you're working
out um the gradient which is going to be
the multiplication of the Upstream error
signal times your local gradient and so
what a human being has to implement um
is that for anything whether it's a
single gate here's a multiply gate or a
newal network layer you have to
implement a forward pass and a backward
pass so here for my baby example since
we're just doing multiplication my
forward pass is that I just multiply the
two numbers and um return it so I'm
specifying that for the local node and
then the other part is that I have to
work out those gradients and well we
sort of know how to do that because
that's the examples that we've been
doing here um but notice that there's
sort of a trick right for what I've got
Now you kind of can't write down what
the gradients are cuz you know what
these cuz you know backward is just
taking as an input the Upstream gradient
and you can't work out what the
downstream gradient are going to be
unless you know what function values
you're calculating it at um so the
standard trick that all which is how
everyone writes this code is you're
relying on the fact that the forward is
being calculated before the backward and
so your forward method um shoves into
some local variables of the class what
the values of the inputs are and then
you have them available um so when you
get to the back backward pass you can do
what we did before um that um the DX is
going to be the Upstream error signal
times the opposite input and um and
similarly for Dy and that's going to
give us the
answer okay um just two last things then
to mention yeah so doing this um
your you need to write um you need to
get the math right for what's the
derivative of your function so you get
the right backward calculation so the
standard way to check that you've got
the right backward calculation is to do
manual gradient checking um with numeric
gradients so the way you do that um is
you sort of like for the couple of
examples I did when I said oh let's
check it by for
going from 1 to 1.1 what should the
slope be approximately we're going to do
that in an automated way and so we're
going to say at the value X let's
estimate what the gradient should be and
the way to do that is to pick a small H
there isn't a magical number because it
depends on the function but typically
you know for neural networks around 10us
4 is good um a small H and work out the
function value I forward part
at x + H and x - H divided by the run
which is 2 H and that should give you an
estimate of the slope what the backward
pass is calculating and you want those
two numbers to be approximately equal
you know within some 10us 2 of each
other and then probably you're
calculating the gradient right and if
they aren't equal um that um you
probably have made a mistake um yeah so
um note that this formul for the version
I did for my examples I just compared to
x with x + H right I did a one-sided
estimate which is normally what you get
taught in a math class if you're doing
this to check your gradients numerically
you're far far better off doing this
two-sided estimate because it's much
more accurate and stable when you're
doing it equally around both sides of
your H um yeah so this looks easy to do
um if if this was just so good why
doesn't everyone do this all the time
and forget about calculus um you know
the reason you don't want to do this is
that doing this is incredibly slow right
because you have to repeat this
computation for every parameter of your
model that you're not getting the kind
of speed UPS your getting from the um
back propagation algorithm but you know
it's useful for checking your
implementation is correct you know in
the old days before Frameworks like py
torch um you know we used to write
everything by hand and people often got
things wrong um but nowadays you know
it's less needed but it's good to check
that if you've implemented your own new
layer that it's doing the right
thing okay um yeah so that's everything
that we need to know about new Nets
propagation is the chain rule applied
efficiently forward pass is just
function application backward pass is
chain rule applied inefficiently um so
you know uh we're going to inflict pain
on our students by making them do some
math and calculate some of these things
and um do the homework and I know
that'll be harder for some of you than
others um you know that in some sense
you don't actually need to know how to
do this the beauty of these modern deep
learning Frameworks is they'll do it all
for you they predefine common layer
types and you can just plug them
together like pieces of Lego and they'll
be computed right and this is precisely
the reason that high school students
across the country and the world can now
do deep learning projects for their
science fairs because you don't actually
have to understand any of this math um
you can just use what's given to you um
but you know um we kind of uh want to
hope that you actually do understand
something about what's going on under
the hood and how new networks work so
therefore we make you suffer a little
bit and of course you know if you sort
of wanting to look at and understand
more complex things you need to have
some sense of what's going on so later
on when we get on to a current new
networks we'll talk a bit about things
like exploding and Vanishing great
and if you want to have some
understanding about well why things
aren't working and things are going
wrong um then you sort of want to know
what it's actually calculating rather
than just thinking it's all a black box
magic and so that's why we hope to have
uh taught something about that okay I
think I'm done if the audience is
sufficiently stunned um and we can stop
for today okay thank you