so welcome everyone to cs25 uh we
excited to kick off uh this class this
is the fourth iteration uh of the class
we're doing uh in the in the previous
iterations we had like Andre carpati
come last year we also had Jeffrey hint
and a bunch of other people um and so we
very excited to kick this off uh the
purpose of this class is to sort of like
have a uh discuss the latest in the
field of AI and Transformers and last
language models and have all the top
research ERS and experts in the field
come and be able to directly uh give a
talk and discuss their findings and
their new ideas uh to students here so
that this can be used to uh in their own
research or like uh spark new
collaborations um so very excited about
the class and uh yeah let's kick it
off so hi everyone I'm
div uh okay so will I'm currently to
leave from the PHD program from Stanford
um working on a personal AI agent
startup called mton uh you can see the
Shir um I'm very passionate about
robotics agents uh did a lot of like
work on on reinforcement learning on a
bunch of like State ofart methods on
online and offline a uh previously was
working with Ian good fellow uh at Apple
so that was really fun and just really
passionate about Ai and how can you
apply that in the real
world so guys hey guys I'm Stephen
currently a second year of PhD student
here at Stanford
um so I'll be interning at Nvidia over
the summer and previously I was a master
student at carig melon and an undergrad
at the University of waterl in Canada uh
so my research interests broadly hover
around NLP and working with language and
text um you know can we work on
improving the controlability and
reasoning capabilities of um language
models and recently I've gotten more
into multimodal work as well as
interdiciplinary work with psychology
and cognitive science I'm trying to
bridge the gap between how humans as
well as language model learn and reason
um and just some for fun you know I'm
also the co-founder and co-president of
the Stanford Piano Club so if anybody
here is interested check us
out hi everyone I'm Emily um I am
currently an undergrad about to finish
up in math and kogai here at Stanford
and also doing my masters in computer
science I am super interested similarly
in the intersection of artificial
intelligence and natural intelligence I
think questions around Neuroscience
philosophy and psychology are really
interesting and I've been very lucky to
do some really cool research here at
Stanford Med uh at NYU and also at CoCo
lab where Stephen is working as well uh
under Noah Goodman on some computational
neuroscience and computational cogn
cognitive science work um and currently
I am beginning a new line of research
with Chris Manning and Chris Potts doing
some NLP interpretability research
so hello um I'm a first year CS Master
student my name is singi um I do
research around natural language
processing um I did a lot of research in
HCI during undergrad at Cornell and I'm
currently working on visual language
models uh image editors for
accessibility and I'm also working with
Professor Hari suum monam in the HCI
department and I'm also working on
establishing consistency and long-term
conversations with Professor D Yang at
the NLP group um yeah nice to meet you
all um so what we hope you guys will
learn from this course is a broad idea
of you know how exactly Transformers
work how they're being applied um around
the world Beyond just NLP but other
domains as well as applications um some
exciting New Directions of research um
Innovative techniques and applications
especially these days of large language
models which have taken the World by
storm and any remaining challenges or
weaknesses um involving Transformers um
and machine learning in
general uh cool uh so we can start with
uh presenting first like the attention
uh
timeline um so I'll say initially we
used to have this uh pre historic era
where we had like very simple like
methods for like say language for
example so like you had like a lot of
like rule based methods you like paring
you have like RNN lstms and that all
changed I will say in the beginning of
around 2014 when people started studying
like attention mechanisms and this was
around like say initially around images
like how like can you adapt like the
mechanism of like how attention works in
the human brain to like images can you
focus on different parts which might be
more like Salient or more relevant uh to
like a user query or what you care about
and um I will say attention exploded in
the beginning of 2017 with the paper
attention is all you need by Ashish
vaswani and L and so that was like when
like uh Transformers became mainstream
and then people realize okay like this
could be like its own really big thing
it's a new architecture that you can
like use everywhere and after that we
saw like explosion of Transformers into
NLP uh with like BD gpt3 and then into
also other fields so now you're seeing
that in like Vision like protein folding
with Alpha fold you have all the video
models like Sora you have like uh like
like basically everything right now is
basically some combination of like
attention and some other like
architectures like diffusion for example
and uh this has now led to the start of
this generative AI era where now you
have like all this like powerful models
which are like billion parameters
trillion parameters and then you can use
this for a lot of different applications
and so if you think about it even like
one year before uh a was very limited to
the lab and now you can say like AI has
escaped from the lab it's now finding
real life real world applications and
it's uh has started to become
predominant so if you think what can if
you look at the trajectory right now
it's like sort of like we on this upward
Trend where we started like this and now
it's just growing faster and faster and
faster and every month there's just like
so many new models coming out it's like
every day there's just like so many new
things happening and so it's going to be
very exciting to see like even like a
year or two years from now how
everything changes and uh the society
will sort of be led by like this
revolutions that are happening in the
field of AI so a lot of things are going
to change on maybe like how we interact
with technology how we do things in
daily life how we have assistants and I
think a lot of that will just come from
like uh the things we might be studying
in this class
awesome thanks St for going through the
timeline um so generally the field of
natural language processing which is
kind of what Transformers were
originally um invented for um the
fundamental discrete nature of text
makes many things difficult for example
data augmentation is more difficult you
can't just for example Flip Flip it like
you flip an image change the pixel
values of it it's not that simple um
text is very precise one wrong word
changes the entire meaning of a sentence
or makes a complet
nonsensical um and there's also
potential for long context length as
well as memories um like if you're CH
chatting with chat gbt over U many
different conversations being able to
learn and store all of that information
is a big challenge um and some of the
weaknesses of earlier models which we'll
get to later um short context length
linear reasoning um as well as the fact
that many of the earli approaches did
not adapt based on context um so
actually I'll be running through briefly
um how NLP has progressed uh throughout
the
years um actually sun will be doing
that yeah so um I just while preparing
this I found this like really
interesting thing this is 1966 um this
was like the earliest chat bot called
Alisa and it wasn't like a real AI but
it was more of like simulating patterns
of text and words and sort of um
creating an illusion that this chatot
was sort of understanding what you were
saying so these were like the earliest
forms of NLP and they were most rule
based approaches where you're trying to
understand the patterns in like
sentences um patterns in way words are
said um and these were like the earliest
like linguistic foundations um Le about
semantic parsing um yeah then we needed
to go on to understand more deeper
meanings within words um so we come up
with things called word embeddings which
are vector representations of words and
they gave us different um semantic
meanings in words that we weren't able
to understand before so we create Vector
representations words that are similar
appear closer together in this Vector
space and we're able to learn different
types of meanings and then these like
examples I have here are like word to
VEC love bird Elmo um these are
different types of word embeddings and
they sort of evolve so word two vectors
like a local context um word embedding
where glove we get like Global context
within documents um so now that we have
ways to represent words into Vector
representations now we can turn them
into put them into our models and do
different types of tasks such as like
question answering or text summarization
or sentence completion machine
translation and we develop different
types of models that are able to do that
so here we have like RNN lstms um that
are used for different translation tasks
and so since we have our models the Now
new challenge becomes sort of to
understand how we can do these tasks
better right so thanks s ke so um she
talked about sequence to sequence models
those are um naturally just inefficient
as well as ineffective for many ways um
you cannot parallelize because it
depends on recurrence um it relies on um
maintaining a hidden context Vector of
all the previous words um and their
information um so you couldn't
parallelize and it was inefficient and
not very effective so this led to what
is now known as attention as well as
Transformers um so as the word kind of
infers attention means um being able to
focus attention to different parts of
something in this case a piece of text
so this is done by using a set of
parameters called weights um that
basically determine how much attention
to should be paid to each input at each
time step um and they're computed using
a combination of the input as well as
the current hidden state of the model so
this will become clearer as I go through
the slides um but you here you have an
example um where this an example of self
attention um if we're currently at the
word it um we want to know how much
attention do we want to play to all of
the other words within our input
sequence um and again this will become
clear as I explain more um so the
attention mechanism relies mainly on
these three things called queries keys
and values um so I tried to come up with
a good analogy for this um and it's
basically like a library system so let's
say your query is something you're
looking for um for example a specific
topic like I want books about uh how to
cook a pizza um and each book in the
library let's say has a key that helps
identify it um for example um this book
is about cooking this book is about um
Transformers this book is about um movie
stars and so forth um and what you do is
you can kind of look you can match
between your query as well as each of
these keys or summaries um to figure out
which books um give you the most
information you need and that
information is the value which you're
trying to ret retrieve but here in
attention we do a soft match match we're
not trying to retrieve one book we want
to see um what is the distri ution of
relevance or importance across all books
for example this book might be the most
relevant I should spend most of my time
on this one might be the second most
relevant I I'll spend a mediocre amount
of time on and then book three is less
relevant and so forth so attention is
basically a soft match between um
finding what's most relevant which is
contained in those values and hence the
equation where you multiply queries by
Keys um and then you multiply that by
the values to get your final um
attention
and here's also just a visualization
from The illustr Illustrated Transformer
about how self attention Works um so
you're basically able to embed your
input words um into vectors and then for
each of these you initialize a query key
as well as value Matrix and these are
learned as the um Transformers trained
and you're able to multiply your inputs
by these queries keys and values to get
these final query key and value matrices
um which is then used um again as shown
in the formula to calculate the final
attention score and the way the
Transformer works is it basically um
uses attention but in a way that's
called multi-head attention as in we do
attention several times because um since
each one is randomly initialized um our
goal is that each head of attention will
learn
something useful but different from the
other heads so this allows you to get um
a more sort of overarching
representation of potentially relevant
information from your text um and you'll
see these blocks are repeated end times
the point there is once the multi-ad
attention is calculated so the attention
scores are calculated from each head
they're then concatenated and then this
process is repeated several times to
potentially learn things like
hierarchical um features and more
in-depth sort of information and here
you'll see um this Transformer diagram
has both an encoder and decoder um this
is for something for example uh T5 or
bar which is an encoder decoder model um
used for things like machine translation
on the other hand things like GPT or
chat GPT that's um simply a decoder only
because there's no sour there's no
second source of input text um compared
to something like machine translation
where you have a sentence in English
which you want to translate to French uh
when you're decoding for an auto
regressive left to right language model
like Chad GPT um it basically only has
what has been generated so far um so
that's kind of the difference between
decoder only and encoder decoder um
Transformers and the way multi-ad
attention works is you initialize a
different set of querious keys and
values um these different matrices per
head which are all learned separately um
as you train and back propagate across
tons of data so again you embed each
word split these into um heads so
separate um matrices and then you kind
of multiply those together to get the
final resulting attentions which are
then um concatenated and multiplied by
final weight Matrix
um and then there's some linear layer
and then some soft Maxs to help you
predict uh the next token for example um
so that's the general gist of how um
sort of multi-head attention Works um if
you want a more in-depth sort of
description of this there's lots of
resources online as well as other
courses um and I'll briefly touch upon
like I said cross attention so here you
have actually an input sequence and of
different output sequence for example
translating from French to English so
here when you're decoding your output
your English translated text there's two
sources of attention one is from the
encoder so the entire sort of encoded um
hidden state of the input um and that's
called cross attention because it's
between two separate pieces of text your
queries here are your current
decoded um outputs and your keys and
values actually come from the encoder
but there's a second source of attention
which is self attention um between the
decoded words themselves so there the
queries keys and values are entirely
from the decoded side and these types of
architectures combine both types of
attention compared to like I said a
decoder only model which would only have
self attention among um its own um
tokens and so um how exactly are
Transformers compared compared with rnns
um so rnns recur neural networks um they
had issues representing longrange
dependencies um there were issues with
gritty and vanish as well as explosion
since you're concatenating all of this
information into one single hidden
Vector um this leads to a lot of issues
potentially um there were a large number
of training steps involved and like I
said you can't parallelize because it's
sequential and relies on recurrence
whereas Transformers can model long
range dependencies there's no gradient
Vanishing or exploding problem and it
can be parallelized um for example um to
take more advantage of things like GPU
compute um so overall it's much more
efficient and also much more more
effective um at representing language
and hence why it's um one of the most
popular deep learning architectures uh
today so large language models are
basically a scaled up version of this
Transformer architecture up to millions
or billions of parameters and parameters
here are basically nodes in the neural
network they're typically trained on
massive amounts of General Text data for
example mining a bunch of text from
Wikipedia Reddit and so forth um
typically there are processes to filter
um
this text for example get getting rid of
not safe for work things and general
quality filters and the training
objective is typically next token
prediction so again it's to predict the
next token or the most probable next
token given all of the previous tokens
so again this is how the autor
regressive left to right um architecture
like Chad GPT works and it's also been
shown that they have emerging abilities
at they scale up which Emily will talk
about um however they have heavy
computational cost training these huge
networks on tons of data takes a lot of
time money and gpus and it's also led to
the fact that this can only be done
effectively at big companies which have
um these resources as well as money and
what's happened now is we have very
general models which you can use and
plug in play um and use them on very um
on different tasks um without needing to
sort of retrain them using things like
in context learning transfer learning as
well as prompting um I know Emily will
talk about emergent
abilities yeah so so um I guess a
natural question for why our language
models work so well is what happens when
you scale up and as we've seen in the
past there's been this big trend of
investing more money into our compute
making our models larger and larger and
larger and actually we have seen some
really cool things come out of it right
which we have now termed emergent
abilities um we can call emergent
abilities an ability an ability that is
present in a smaller in a larger model
but not in a smaller one um and I think
the thing that is most interesting about
this is emergent abilities are very
unpredictable it's not necessarily like
we have a scaling law that we just keep
training and training and training this
model and we can sort of say oh at this
at this training step we'll have this
ability to do this really cool thing
it's actually something more like it's
kind of random and then at this
threshold that is pretty difficult or
impossible to predict it just improves
and we call that a phase
transition and this is a figure Tak by a
paper authored by uh a speaker we'll
have next week uh Jason we who I'm very
excited to hear from and he did this
really cool research project with a
bunch of other people uh sort of uh
characterizing and exhibiting a lot of
the emergent abilities that you can
notice in different models so here we
have five different models and a lot of
different uh common tasks that we test
language models on to see uh what their
abilities are and so for example
complicated arithmetic or um
transliteration being able to uh tell if
someone is telling the truth other
things like this and as you can notice
on this figure we have these eight
graphs and there's sort of this like
very obvious Spike it's not necessarily
like this gradual increase um in
accuracy and so that is sort of what we
can term that phase
transition and currently there's very
few explanations for why these abilities
emerge um evaluation metrics used to
measure these abilities don't fully
explain why they emerge um and an
interesting research paper that came out
recently by some researchers at Stanford
actually claimed that maybe emergent
abilities of llms are non-existent maybe
it's more so the uh researcher's choice
of metric being nonlinear rather than
fundamental changes in the model
responding to the
scale and so a natural question um is is
scaling sort of the best thing to do is
it the only thing to do is it the most
significant way that we can improve our
models um and so while scaling is a
factor in these emergent abilities it is
not the only Factor um especially in
smaller models we have new architectures
uh higher quality data and improved
training procedures that could
potentially uh bring about these
emergent abilities on smaller models and
so these present a lot of interesting
research directions um including
improving few shot prompting abilities
as we've seen before um through other
methods and theoretical and interpret
interpretability research computational
Linguistics work um and yeah other
directions and so as some interesting
questions do you believe that emergent
abilities will continue to arise with
more scale um is there like maybe once
we get to some crazy number of
parameters then our language models will
suddenly be able to think on their own
and do all sorts of cool things or is
there some sort of limit um what are
your thoughts on this current trend of
larger models and more data um it should
we uh is this a good direction larger
models obviously mean more money more
compute and less democra less
democratization of uh AI research and
thoughts on retrieval based or retrieval
augmented systems compared to Simply
learning everything within the
parameters of the model so lots of cool
directions
um yeah so we have some quick
introductions on reinforcement learning
from Human feedback I think a lot of you
might already know um so um
reinforcement learning from Human
feedback is a technique to train large
language models um usually you give
human like humans to outputs of the
language model ask them what they prefer
we select the one they prefer and feed
it back into the model to train a more
human aligned model recently there has
been more more um since like
reinforcement learning from Human
feedback has its limitations you need
quality human feedback you need good
rewards you need a good policy it's a
very complicated training process um a
recent paper DPO uh uses just uh
preference data and non- preference data
and feeds that into the language model
uh to uh and it's a much more faster
algorithm to train these language models
um so quick introduction to gbt um we
have GPT which is fine-tuned on GPT 3.5
we have like a diagram of the different
types of GPT models that have been
released and GPT 4 is um the next
version and it's supervised on a large
training data set with rhf like the apis
of text ofy also have been trained on
rhf um then we have Gemini which is
Gemini uh uh a model which was like
basically Google's AI from Bart now is
Gemini and um when it was release there
was like a big hype because it performed
much better on than chat PT on like uh
30 out of the 32 academic Benchmark so
there was a lot of excitement around
this and now as people have used it
there have been different like we
realize that different models are good
for different types of tasks one
interesting thing is that Gemini is
trained on thee model which is the
mixture of experts model where we have a
bunch of smaller neural networks that
are known as experts and are trained and
capable of handling different things so
we could have one neural network that's
really good at pulling images from the
web one good at pulling like text and
then we have our final gated Network
which predicts which response is the
best suited to address the
request right so now that takes us to
where we are right now um so AI um
especially NLP large language models
have taken off um like shanki said
things like gbd4 Gemini and so forth um
a lot of things involving human
alignment and interaction such as RL HF
um there's more work now on trying to
control the toxicity bias as well as
ethical concerns um involving these
models especially as more and more
people um gain access to them um things
like chb there's also more use in unique
applications things like audio uh music
neuro um Neuroscience biology and so
forth um we'll have some slides briefly
uh touching on those but these things
are mainly touched upon um by our
speakers and there's also um diffusion
models um a separate class of models
although now there's a diffusion
Transformer where they replace the unet
backbone in the diffusion model with the
Transformer architecture uh which works
better for things like text to video
generation for example Sora um uses the
diffusion
Transformer um so what's next um so as
we see um the use of Transformers and
machine learning um get more and more um
prominent throughout the world um it's
very exciting but also scary um so it
can enable a lot more applications
things like very generalist agents
longer video understanding as well as
generation maybe in 10 five 10 years we
can generate a whole Netflix series um
by just putting in a prompt or an um a
um description of the um show we want to
watch um things like incredibly long
sequence modeling which Gemini um um I
think now it is able to handle they
claim um a million tokens for more um so
we'll see if that can further scale up
um which is very exciting things like
very domain specific Foundation models
things like having a doctor GPT lawyer
GPT any sort of GPT for any use case or
application you might want and also
other potential real world impacts
personalized education as well as
tutoring systems Advanced Healthcare um
Diagnostics environmental monitoring and
so forth um real time multilingual
communication um you go to China Japan
or something um real time you're able to
interact with everyone um as well as
interactive entertainment and gaming
potentially we can have more realistic
NPCs um um which are run by Transformers
as well as
Ai and so what's missing um you know
this is Buzz word you know AGI ASI
artificial general intelligence or super
intelligence um so what's really missing
to get there um these are some of the
things that we we thought might be the
case firstly is reducing computation
complexity um as these models and data
sets scale up it'll become even more
costly and difficult to train um so we
need a way to reduce that enhance human
controllability of these models the
alignment of language models potentially
with the human brain adaptive learning
and generalization across um even more
domains multi- sensory multimodal
embodiment um this will allow it to
learn things like intuitive physics and
common sense that humans are able to but
since these models especially language
models are trained purely on text they
don't actually have sort of intuitive or
um human-like understanding of the real
world since all they've seen is
text um infinite or external memory um
as well as self-improvement and
self-reflection capabilities like humans
we're able to continuously learn and
improve ourselves um complete autonomy
and long Horizon decision making
emotional intelligence and social
understanding as well as of course
ethical reasoning and value alignment
uh
cool
um okay cool uh so let's get to some of
the interesting uh Parts about LMS so
there's like a lot of applications
you're already starting to see in the
real world like the chat GPT is one of
the biggest examples it's like the
fastest growing consumer app in history
uh which just like went like really
viral everyone started using it just
caused like this like like wow like
people know like AI exists in the real
world because before that was just like
like say like people like us who are
like at Sanford who are using Ai and and
then like a lot of the people in the
world were like okay like what is even
AI but like when they got their first
experience with like chat gbd they were
like okay like okay like this thing
actually works we believe in that and
now we are starting to see a lot of this
in like different applications like
speeches something where you have a lot
of this new models like whisper you also
have this like 11 Labs bunch of things
that are happening music is a big
industry image like images and videos
are also like starting to transform so
we can imagine maybe 5 years from now
all Hollywood movies might be produced
by like video models you might not even
need actors for example you might just
have like fake actors and like you spend
like billions of dollars just like going
to different like Parts in the world and
like shooting scenes but that can all be
just in video model right so like
something like Sora and like what what's
happening right now I think that's going
to be game changing because like that's
how uh movie production advertisement uh
all of like like social media will be
driven by
that and it's already fascinating to
just see how realistic all this images
and the videos look um it's almost like
better than like human artist quality so
so it's it's getting like a very
interesting uh and very hard to also
distinguish like what's real and what's
fake um and one uh very interesting
application will be like when you can
take these models and embody them in the
real world so for an example if you have
some games like Minecraft for example
where you can have a AI that can play
the game and then we already starting to
see that where like uh there's a lot of
work where like uh you have a AI That's
like uh masquerading as a human and
actually able to go and win the game
game so there's like a lot of like those
stuff that's happening real time and
people are doing that and it's actually
we are reaching like some level of
superh human performance there in
virtual games similarly in the robotics
um it's very exciting to see like once
you can apply AI in the physical world
you can just enable like so many like
applications you can have physical
helpers in your homes industry so on and
there's almost a race for building the
humanoid robots that's going on right
now so if you look at what uh Tesla is
doing what like this company called
figur is doing so everyone's like really
excited about okay like can we go and
build this like physical helpers that uh
can go and help you with a lot of
different things um in PH in real
life and so definitely like lot of uh
fun research and like uh um applications
have already been applied by open AI
deep mind uh meta and so on and uh we
have also seen a lot of interesting
applications in biology and Healthcare
so Google introduced this mpom model
last year we actually had the first
author of the work give or talk
in the last iteration of the course and
this is very interesting because this is
a transformal model that can be applied
for actual medical applications Google
is right now deploying this in actual
hospitals for analyzing like uh the
patient Health Data a lot of history
medical diagnosis uh cancer detection so
on so now we'll touch briefly upon some
of the remaining um some of the recent
Trends in terms terms of Transformers
research as well as potentially
remaining weaknesses and challenges so
as I explained earlier you know a large
amount of data compute and cost to train
over weeks or months thousands of gpus
and now there's this thing called the
baby LM challenge can we train llms
using similar amounts of text Data baby
exposed to um while Growing Up So
essentially um comparing sort of llms
and humans is one aspect of my own
research and um I believe that children
are different um we learn very
differently as humans compared to llms
they do statistical learning this
requires a large amount of data to
actually learn statistical relations um
between words in order to get things
like abstraction generalization and
reasoning capabilities whereas human
learns humans learn in more structured
probably smarter ways um we may um for
example learn in more compositional or
hierarchical sort of maners uh which
will allow us to learn these things more
easily and so one of my professors
Michael Frank he made this tweet um
showing how you know there's this like
four four four to five orders of input
magnitude difference between human and
llm emergence of many behaviors and this
is magnitude not time so like 10,000 up
to millions of times as much data
required for llms compared to humans
this may be to the fact that humans have
innate knowledge um this relates to
priors basically you know when we're
born maybe due to Evolution we already
have some fundamental capabilities built
into our brains second is multimodal
grounding we don't just learn from text
we learn from interacting with the world
with other people through vision smell
things we can hear see feel and touch
the third is active social learning um
we learn while Growing Up by talking to
our parents teachers other children this
is not just basic things but even things
like values human values to treat others
with kindness and so forth um and this
is not something that uh llm is really
exposed to um when it's trained on just
large amounts of text
data um kind of related is um this trend
towards smaller open source models
potentially things we can even run on
our everyday devices um for example
there's more and more work on auto GPT
as well as chat GPT plugins um smaller
open source models like llama as well as
mistro models and in the future
hopefully we'll be able to up fine tune
and run even more models locally
potentially even on our smartphone
um another area of sort of research and
work is in memory augmentation as well
as
personalization so current big weakness
of llms is they're sort of Frozen in
knowledge at a particular point in time
they don't sort of augment knowledge on
the fly as they're talking to you they
don't actually it's not stored into
their brain the parameters the next time
you start a new conversation there's a
very high chance it won't remember
anything um you said before although I
think there's I I'll get to rag in a bit
so one of our goals hopefully in the
future is to have this sort of widescale
um memory augmentation as well as
personalization somehow update the model
on the Fly while being able while
talking to hundreds or thousands or
millions of users around the world um
and to adapt not only their knowledge
but their talking style as well as
Persona to the particular user and this
is called personalization this could
have many different applications such as
mental health therapy and so
forth so some potential approach for
this could be having a memory rank um
this is not that feasible with larger
amounts of data prefix tuning approaches
which fine tunes only a very small
portion of the model however when you
have such huge llms even fine- tuning a
very small portion of the model is
incredibly expensive maybe some
prompt-based approaches in context
learning however again um this would not
change the model itself it will likely
not carry forward among different
conversations um and there's this thing
now called rag retrieval augmented
generation which is related to a memory
bank where you have a data store of
information and each time when the user
puts in an input query you first look at
if there's relevant information from
this data store that you can then
augment um as context into the llm to
help guide its output this relies on
having a high quality external data
store and it's also typically not end to
end and the main thing here is it's not
within the brain of the model but
outside
um it's suitable for knowledge or
fact-based information but it's not
really suitable for enhancing the
fundamental capabilities or skills of
the
model there's also lots of work now on
pre-training data
synthesis um especially after Chad GPT
and gbd4 came out instead of having to
collect data from humans which can be
very expensive and timec consuming many
researchers now are using GPD 4 for
example to collect data to train um
other models for example uh model
distillation uh training smaller and
less less capable models with data from
larger models like Chad uh gp4 an
example is the Microsoft five models um
introduced from their paper textbooks
are all you
need and speaking a bit more about the
five model it's a 2.7 billion parameter
model um five version 2 and it excels in
reasoning and language I'm challenging
or having comparative performance to um
compared to models up to 25 times larger
which is incredibly um impressive and
their main sort of takeaway here is the
quality or source of data is incredibly
important so they emphasized textbook
quality training data and synthetic data
um they generated synthetic data to
teach the model Common Sense reasoning
and general knowledge this includes
things like science daily activities
theory of mind and so forth they then
augmented this with additional data
collected from the web that was filtered
based on educational value as well as
content
quality um and what this allowed to them
to do is train a much smaller model much
more efficiently while comp um
challenging models up to 25 times larger
which is again very
impressive another area of debate is are
llms truly learning are they learning
new knowledge when you ask it to do
something is it generating it from
scratch or is it simply recurita
something it's memorized
before um this this line has been
blurred um and it's not clear because
the way LM is learn is from again
learning patterns from lots of text um
which you can say is somewhat memorizing
um there's also the potential for test
time contamination models might
regurgitate um information um it's seen
during training while being evaluated
and this can lead to misleading
Benchmark results um there's also
cognitive simulation so a lot of people
are arguing that um llms mimic human
thought processes While others um say no
it's just a sophisticated form of
pattern matching
and it's not nearly as complex um or
biological or sophisticated as a human
um and this also leads to a lot of
ethical as well as practical limitations
so for example I'm sure you've all heard
that a recent lawsuit copyright lawsuit
by New York Times on open AI uh where
they claim that open A's chat was
basically regurgitating um existing New
York Times articles and this is again um
sort of this issue with lm's potentially
memorizing text it's saw during training
rather than um synthesizing new
information entirely from
scratch another big source of um
challenge which might be able to close
the gap between current models and
eventually maybe AGI is this um concept
of continual learning AKA infinite and
permanent fundamental sort of
self-improvement so humans we're able to
learn constantly every day from every
interaction I'm learning right now from
just talking to you and um giving this
lecture right we don't need to sort of
fine-tune ourselves we don't need to sit
in a chair and then have someone read
the whole internet to us um every two
months or something like that um
currently does work on fine-tuning a
small model based on traces from a
better model or the same model after
filtering those traces however this is
closer to retraining and distillation
than it is to True sort of humanlike
continual learning um so that's
definitely um I think at least a very
exciting
direction another sort of area of
challenge is interpreting these huge
llms with billions of parameters they're
essentially huge black box models where
it's really hard to understand exactly
what is going
on um if we were able to understand them
better this would allow us to know what
exactly we should try to improve um it
also allow us to control um these models
better and potentially lead to better
alignment as well as safety and there's
this sort of of area of work called
mechan mechanistic interpretability
which tries to understand exactly how
the individual components as well as
operations in a machine learning model
contribute to its overall decision
making process and to try to unpack that
sort of Black Box I
guess so speaking a bit more about this
a concept related to mechanistic
interpretability as well as continual
learning is model editing so this is a
newer line of work which hasn't seen too
much investigation also because it's
very
challenging um but basically this looks
like can we edit very specific nodes in
the model without having to retrain it
um so one of the papers I linked there
um they developed a causal intervention
method to trace sort of the neural
activations for model factual
predictions and they came up with this
method called rank one model editing or
Rome that was able to modify very
specific model weights um for updating
factual associations for example um um
was the capital of Canada and then
modifying that to something else they
found they didn't need to refine tune
the model they were able to sort of
inject that information um into the
model um pretty much in a permanent Way
by simply modifying very specific nodes
they also found that mid layer fee
forward modules played a very
significant role in storing these sorts
of factual information or associations
and the manipulation of these can be a
feasible approach um for model editing
so I think this is a very cool um line
of work with potential um long-term
impacts and as Shi stated before another
line of work is basically mixture of
experts um so this is very prevalent in
current day llms things like gbd4 and
Gemini it's to have several models or
experts work together sort of to solve a
problem and arrive at a final generation
and there's a lot of research on how to
better Define and initialize these
experts and sort of connect them um to
come up with a final um result
and I'm thinking is there a way of
potentially having a single model
variation of this similar to the human
brain uh for example the human brain we
have different parts of our brain for
different things right uh one part of
our brain might uh work more for spatial
reasoning uh one for physical reasoning
uh one for mathematical logical
reasoning and so forth maybe there's a
way of segmenting a single Neuron
networker model in such a way for
example by m adding more layers on top
of a foundation model and then only
fine-tuning those um specific layers for
different uh purposes
related to continual learning is
self-improvement as well as
self-reflection so there's been a lot of
work recently that's also shown that
models um especially llms they can
reflect on their own output to
iteratively refine as well as improve
them it's been shown that this
Improvement can happen across several
layers of U uh self-reflection having a
sort of mini version of continual sort
of learning up to a certain degree and
some folks believe that that AGI is
basically a constant state state of
self-reflection um which is again
similar to what a human um
does lastly a big uh sort of issue is
the hallucination problem where a model
does not know what it does not know and
due to the sampling procedure um there's
a very high chance for example I'm sure
you've also used chap GPT before that it
sometimes generates text it's very
confident about but is simply incorrect
like factually Incorrect and does not
make any sense um we can potentially
enhance this through different ways
maybe some sort of internal based fact
verification approach um based on
confidence scores um this's this line of
work called Model calibration which kind
of works on that um potentially verif
verifying and regenerating output um if
it finds that its output is incorrect uh
maybe it can as be asked to
regenerate um and of course there's
things like rag based approaches where
you're able to retrieve from a knowledge
store which is also um a potential
solution people have investigated for
reducing this problem of
hallucination lastly Emily will touch
upon um some Chain of Thought
reasoning yeah so um Chain of Thought is
something I think is really cool because
I I think it combines the sort of uh
like cognitive imitation and also uh
interpretability uh lines of research
and so Chain of Thought is the idea that
all of us unless you have some
extraordinary photographic memory sort
of think through things step by step
right like if I asked you to multiply a
10 digit number by a 10-digit number you
probably have to break that down into
intermediate reasoning steps and so some
researchers thought well what if we do
the same things with large language
models and see if having them forcing
them to sort of reason through their
ideas and their thoughts helps them have
better accuracy and better results um
and so Chain of Thought exploits the
idea that ultimately these models have
these weights that uh know more about a
problem rather than just having it
prompt and sort of regurgitate what it
um what just to get a response yeah and
so an example of Chain of Thought
reasoning is uh on the right so as you
can see on the left there's standard
prompting so I give you this complicated
question let's say we're doing this
entirely new problem I give you the
question and I just give you the answer
I don't tell you how to do it that's
kind of ult right versus Chain of
Thought the first example that you get I
actually walk you through the answer um
and then the idea is that hopefully
since you kind of have this framework of
how to think about a question you're
able to produce a more accurate
output and so Chain of Thought resulted
in uh pretty significant performance
gains for larger language models um but
similar to similarly to what I touched
upon before this is an emergent ability
and so we don't really see the same um
performance for smaller models but
something that I think is important as I
mentioned before is this idea of
interpretability because we can see this
model's output as their reasoning and
their final answer then you can kind of
see oh hey this is where they messed up
this is where they got something
incorrect and so we're able to break
down the errors of chain of thought into
these different categories that helps us
better pinpoint why is it doing this
incorrectly how can we directly Target
these issues
and So currently Chain of Thought works
really effectively for models of
approximately 100 billion parameters or
more obviously very big um but uh and so
why is that um an initial paper found
that one step missing and semantic
understanding Chain of Thought errors
are the most common among smaller models
you can sort of think of oh I forgot to
do this step in the multiplication or I
actually don't really understand what
multiplication is to begin with and so
some potential reasons is that maybe
smaller models fail at even relatively
easy symbol mapping tasks they seem to
have inherently weaker arithmetic
abilities and maybe they have logical
loopholes and don't uh end up coming at
a final answer so all your reasoning is
correct but for some reason you just
couldn't get quite there um and so an
interesting line of research would be to
improve Chain of Thought for smaller
models and similarly um allow uh more
people to work on interesting
problems um and so
uh how could we potentially do that well
one idea is to generalize this Chain of
Thought reasoning so it's not
necessarily that we reason in all the
same ways right like there are multiple
ways to think through a problem rather
than breaking it down step by step and
so um we can perhaps generalize Chain of
Thought to be more flexible in different
ways one example is this sort of tree of
thoughts idea um and so tree of thought
is considering multiple different
reasoning paths and evaluating their
choices to decide the next course of
action and so this is sort of similar to
the idea that we can look ahead and go
backwards similar to a lot of the model
architectures that we've seen um and so
uh just having multiple options and
being able to come out with some uh more
accurate output at the
end um another idea is Socratic
questioning um so the idea that we are
dividing and conquering in order to have
this sort of self-questioning
self-reflection um idea that stepen
touched upon um and using so the idea is
a self-questioning module using a large
scale language model to propose these
sub problems um related to the original
problem that recursively backtracks and
answers the sub problem to the original
problem so this is sort of similar to
that initial idea of Chain of Thought
except rather than spelling out all the
steps for you um the language model sort
of reflects on how can it break down
these problems s how can it answer these
problems and get to The Final
Answer cool uh okay let's see so let's
go to uh some of the ne the more
interesting topics that are starting to
become relevant especially in 2024 so
last year we saw a big explosion in
language models especially with like
gbd4 that came out almost an year ago
now and now what's happening is like uh
we are starting to transition towards
more like AI agents and it's very
interesting to see like what
differentiates a agent uh from something
like a model right um so I can I'll
probably talk about like a bunch of
different things uh such as like actions
uh long-term memory communication bunch
of stuff uh but let's start by why
should we go and build
agents and uh uh think about that so one
key hypothesis uh I would say here is uh
what's going to happen is humans will
communicate with AI using like like
language and AI will be operating our
machines uh that's allowing for more
intuitive and efficient operations and
so if you think about like a laptop it's
like if you show like a laptop to like
someone who has never like uh who's like
like a kid who has never used like a
like a computer before they'll be like
okay like why do I have to use this box
why can't I just talk to it right like
why can't it be more humanlike I can
just ask you to do things and you can
just go do my work for me and that seems
to be like the more human like uh like
uh interface to how things should happen
and I think that's the way the world
will transition towards when instead of
us clicking or typing it will be like uh
we talk to an AI uh using like natural
language how you talk to a human and the
AI will go and do your
work uh actually have a Blog on this
which is called like software 3.0 if you
want to check that out um but yeah cool
so for
agents um like why like uh do you want
agents so as it turns out like a single
call to a large Foundation a model is us
not enough uh you can do a lot more by
Building Systems and by systems you mean
like uh doing like more things like
model chaining model reflection other
mechanisms and this requires a lot of
different stuff so you require like
memory you require like large context
lens you also want to do like
personalization you want to be able to
do actions you want to be able to do
like internet
Excel and uh and then you can like
accomplish a lot of these things with
this kind of Agents um here's like a
diagram breaking down the different
parts of the agents uh this is from
lilan Wang uh she's a senior researcher
at open air and so if you want to build
really powerful agents you need to
really just think of that as like you're
building this sort of like a new kind of
computer which has all the like
different ingredients that you have to
build like you have to build memory and
if think about memory from scratch like
how do you do long-term memory how do
you do short-term memory how do you do
planning like how how do you think about
reflection like if something goes wrong
how do you correct that uh how do you
have like chain of thoughts how do you
like decompose a goal so if I say
something like book me a trip to Italy
for example how do you break that down
to like sub goals for example for the
agent and also being able to take all
this planning and all this like steps
into actual action so that becomes
really important and uh enable all of
that using tool use so like if you like
say like calculators or calendars or uh
code interpreters and so on so you want
to be able to like utilize existing
tools that are out there it's like
similar to like how you as a we as a
human use like a calculator for example
so we also want like to be able to like
use like existing tools and become more
efficient and
Powerful um this was actually one of the
demos uh this is actually from my
company but uh this was like one of the
first demonstrations of agents in the
real world uh where we actually had it
past the online driving test in
California uh so this was actually like
a live exam we took uh as a
demonstration uh so this was like a
friend uh like a like a driving test
which you can actually take from your
home and so the person had their hands
up the above the keyboard and they were
being recorded on the webcam uh there
was also like screen recorded and the
DMV actually had the person install like
a special software in the computer to
detect like it's not a bot uh but still
the agent could actually like go on the
compete exam so that was uh interesting
to
see so we set the record in this case to
be the first AI uh to actually get a
driving permit in California uh and this
is sort of like the agent actually going
and doing things so here the person has
their hands just the keyboard for the
for the webcam and the agent is running
on the laptop and it's uh answering all
the questions so all of this is
happening autonomously in this case and
so this was roughly around 40 questions
uh the agent maybe made like two or
three mistakes but was able to
successfully pass the whole test in this
case so this was like really fun uh let
me go and
[Music]
[Laughter]
yeah so yeah so so you can imagine like
there's like a lot of fun things that
can happen with agents that this was
actually like a V attempt so we informed
the DMV after we took the exam uh so
this was like really funny uh but you
can imagine like there's like so many
different things you can enable once you
have the sort of like capabilities that
are available uh for everyone to
use and this becomes a question of uh
like why should we build more like
humanik
agents and I'll see this is very
interesting because it's almost like
saying like why should we build humanoid
robots like why can't we just build like
a like a different kind of robot why do
you want human robots and it's similarly
like question here like why do you want
like humanik
agents and I will say this is very
interesting because one is like a lot of
the technology websites is built for
humans and then we can go and reuse that
infrastructure instead of building new
things and so that becomes very
interesting because you can just deploy
this agents uh using the existing
technology uh second is like you can
imagine this agents could become almost
like a digital extension of you so they
can learn about you they can know your
preferences they can know what you like
what you don't like and and be able to
act on your
behalf they also have very less
restricted boundaries so they're able to
handle like say like logins payments so
on which might be harder with like
things like API for example but this is
easier to do if you are doing like more
computer based control like a human and
it's also very uh you can imagine the
problem is also fundamentally simpler
because you just have a action space
which like clicking and typing in uh
which itself is like a fundamentally
limited action space uh so that's a a
simpler problem to solve rather than
like building something that is is uh um
maybe like more general
purpose and another interesting thing
about this kind of human like agents is
you can also teach them so you can like
teach them how you will do things they
can maybe record you passively and they
can learn from you and then improve and
this is also becomes like an interesting
way to improve this agents over
time so when we talk about agents uh
there's this map that people like to use
which is called like the five different
levels of autonomy uh this actually came
from C driving cards so how this works
is you have like l0 to L5 so l0 to L2 is
uh the parts of autonomy where the human
is in control so here's the human is
driving the car and there might be some
sort of part partial automation that's
happening which could be like some sort
of like auto assist kind of
features what this starts becoming
interesting when you have something like
L3 so in L3 you still have a human in
the car but uh like most of the time the
car is is able to drive drive it itself
so like on highways or like on most of
the roads uh L4 is uh you still have a
human but like the car is like doing all
the driving um and this is maybe like
what you have like if you have driv a
Tesla on autopilot before that's like a
L4 autonomous vehicle and L5 is
basically you don't have a driver in the
car so the car is able to go and handle
all parts of uh the system there's no
fall back and this is what like voo is
doing right now so if you take a cell
driving uh if you set in a voo
uh in SF then you can experience like a
L5 autonomic car where like there's no
human and the a is driving the whole car
itself and so same thing also applies
for a a agents so you can almost imagine
um if you are building something like a
L4 level capability that's where like a
human is still in the loop ensuring that
nothing is going wrong and uh so this is
like you still have some bottlenecks but
if you are able to reach like L5 level
of autonomy on agents and that's
basically like saying like you ask an
agent to book a flight and that happens
you ask it for like maybe like go maybe
like order this for me or maybe like uh
go like whatever like things you care
about uh and that can all happen autonom
autonomously so that's where things
start becoming very interesting when we
can start reaching from L4 to L5 and
don't even need a human in the loop
anymore cool um okay so when you think
about building agents uh there's
predominantly two routes uh so the first
one is like API where like you can go
and control anything uh based on like
API that are available out there so
openi has been trying this with chat gbt
plugins for example there's also like a
bunch of work from Berkeley uh so
Berkeley had this book called gorilla
where you could train a a foundation
model to control 10,000
apis um and and there's like a lot of
interesting stuff Happening Here a
second direction of work is like more
like direct interaction with a computer
and there's like different like uh
companies trying this out so we have one
of that there's also this setup called
adapt which is trying this like human
like interaction
um yeah maybe I can show this thing so
this is like a an idea of like what you
can enable by having agents so what we
are doing here is uh uh like here we
have our agent and we've told it to like
go to Twitter and uh make a post and so
it's going and like controlling the
computer uh doing this whole interaction
and once it's done it can send me a
response back
uh which you can see here and so this
becomes interesting because like you
don't really need apis if you have this
kind of Agents so if I have an agent
that can go control my computer can go
control websites can do whatever it
wants almost in a humanik manner like
what you can do then you don't really
need apis because this becomes like the
abstraction layer uh to allow any sort
of like uh control um so so it's going
to be like really fascinating once we
have this kind of agent start to work in
the real world and a lot of like uh
transitions we'll see in technology
see cool okay so let's move on to the
next topic when it comes to agents so
one very interesting thing here is uh
memory so yeah so we say a good way to
think about a model is almost think of
it like a like a compute chip so what
happens is you have some sort of input
tokens which are defined in natural
language which are going as the input to
a model and then you get some output
tokens out and the output tokens are
again natural language um and if you
have something like uh gbd 3.5 that used
to be something like a 8,000 uh length
token with
gbd4 this became like a 16,000 now it's
like 128,000 so you can almost imagine
this as like the token size or the
instruction size of this comput unit
which is powered by uh n like a neural
network in this
case and so this is basically what a
gbd4 you can imagine is it's almost like
a CPU and that say it's taking some
input tokens defined over natural
language doing some competition over
them transforming those tokens and
giving out some output tokens uh this is
actually similar to how you think about
like memory chips for example so here uh
I'm showing like a myips 32 processor
that's one of the earliest processor out
there and so what it's doing is you have
input tokens and output Toons in binary
like zeros and ones but instead of that
you can imagine we doing very similar
things but just over naal language now
and now if you uh think more about this
analogy so you can start thinking like
okay like what we want to do is like
take whatever we have been doing in
building computers and like CPUs and
logic and so on but can we generalize
all of that to natural language and so
you can start thinking about like how
current like processors work how current
like uh computers work you have like uh
like instructions you have memory you
have like variables and then you like
run this over and over to like uh each
line of binary sequence of instructions
to like uh output code U and you can
start thinking about Transformers in a
similar way where you can have a like
the transformer acting as a computer
unit you are passing it some sort of
instructions line by line and each
instruction can contain some like uh
Primitives which are defining like what
to do which could be the user command it
could have some memory Parts which are
dried from like external like a dis uh
which in this case could be like
something like a personalization system
and so on as well as some sort of
variables and then you're taking this
and running this line by line and that's
like a pretty good way to think about
like what uh uh like something like this
could be doing and you can almost
imagine there could be like new sort of
programming languages you can build
which are like specific to programming
like uh
Transformers and so when it comes to
memory um traditionally how we think
about memory is like a disk right so
it's like long lived it's persistent
when the computer like shuts down you
save all your data from the ram to the
disk and then you can like persist it
and then you can like load it back when
you want um you want to enable something
very similar when you have like Ai and
you have agents and so you want to have
mechanisms where I can like store this
data and then retrieve this data and
right now how we doing this is like thr
embeddings um so you can like take any
sort of like um PDF or like any sort of
like modality you care about uh convert
that to embeddings using like an
embedding model and store that embedding
in like a vector database and later when
you actually care about like uh doing
some any sort of access uh to the memory
you can load the relevant part of the
embedding put that as part of your
instruction and fit that to the model
and uh so this is like how we are think
about memory with AI these days um and
then you essentially have the retrieval
models which are acting as a function to
store and retrieve memory and the
embeddings becomes like the layer of
like the it's like basically the uh the
format you're using to like encode the
memory in this case uh there's still a
lot of open questions because uh how
this works right now is just like you
just do simple K&N so it's like very
simp like nearest neighbor search which
is not efficient it doesn't really
generalize doesn't scale and so there's
a lot of things you can think about like
especially hierarchy uh temporal
coherence because like a lot of memory
data is like a Time series so there's
like a lot of like temporal Parts
there's also like a lot of structure uh
usually in a lot of data so you could
use a structure it could be like a graph
for example and there's also like a lot
of things you can do on online
adaptation because like most your data
is not static you're always learning
you're always adapting there things
changing all the time and uh a good
model over here is maybe like how the
human brain works so if you think about
like something like the hyppocampus it's
it's like uh people still don't know how
it fully works but it's like something
you're like learning new things on the
Fly you're creating new memories you're
adapting new memories and so on and so I
think it be very fascinating to see how
this area of research evolves over
time uh similarly like a very relevant
problem with memory is
personalization um like suppose now you
have this agents that are doing things
for you then you want to make sure that
the agent actually knows what you like
what you don't like like suppose you
tell an agent to go book you a ,000
flight but maybe it books you the wrong
flight uh and just Wast you a lot of
your money or maybe just it just uh does
a lot of wrong actions which is not good
so you want the agent to like sort of
learn about uh what you like and like
understand that and this becomes about
like forming a long Liv user memory for
example where like the more you interact
with it the more it should form a memory
about you and be able to use that and
this could be like uh this could have
like different flavors someone could be
like explicit where you can tell it like
okay here's my allergies here's my
flight preferences I like window versus
a seats here my favorite dishes and so
on but this could also be implicit where
it could be like say like I like maybe
like idas over Nike or if I have if I'm
on Amazon and if I have like this 10
different like shirts I can buy maybe I
will buy this particular type of shirt
and brand and so on and so there's also
like a lot of implicit learning you can
do which is more like based on feedback
or
comparisons and this's there's a lot of
challenges involved here so you can
imagine like it's like how do you
collect this data how do you form this
memory how do you
learn uh and do you use like supervis
learning versus feedback how do you like
learn on the Fly and how do you and
while you're doing all of this how do
you preserve user privacy because like
uh for some a system to be personalized
it just needs to know a lot about you
but then how do you ensure that if
you're building system like that that
this is actually safe and nothing is
actually getting like uh uh like it's
not violating any of your privacy
a very interesting uh area when it comes
to agents is also communication so now
you can imagine like suppose you have
this one agent that can go and do things
for you but uh why not have like
multiple
agents and what happens if you have like
a if I have an agent and you have an
agent and this agent starts
communicating with each other and so I
think we'll start seeing this phenomena
where you will have like multi agent
autonomous systems where like each agent
can go and do things and then each that
agent can go and talk to other agents
and so on
and uh so that's going to be
fascinating and uh like why do you want
to do this so one is like if you have a
single agent it will always be slow like
it have to do everything sequentially
but if you have a multi-agent system
then you can like paralyze the system so
instead of one agent if I had thousands
of Agents each agent can go do something
for me in par instead of just having one
second is you can also have specialized
agents so I could have a agent that's
specific for spread sheets or I have a
agent that can operate my Slack I have
an agent that can operate my web browser
and then I can route to different agents
to for like different things I want to
do and that can help like this is almost
like what you do in a factory like you
have like specialized workers like each
worker is doing like something like
they're specialized to and this actually
is something that we found over like U
uh the period of human history that this
is the right way to like divide tasks
and like uh uh get maximum
performance uh there's a lot of
challenges here to so one one the
biggest one is just like how do you
exchange information
because now what's happening is like
everything is happening over natural
language and natural language itself is
lossy so it's very easy to have
miscommunication gaps like even in when
humans talk to each other there's a lot
of like miscommunication uh you lose
information a lot because like natural
language itself is ambiguous so you just
need to have like better protocols or
like a better ways to like ensure that
if agents start communicating with other
agents it doesn't cause mistakes it
doesn't Le to like a lot of like Havoc
for
example and uh this this can also lead
to like building like different sort of
like interesting Primitives um so here's
like one example primitive you can think
about is where like suppose I what if I
have a manager agent and the the manager
agent can go and coordinate a bunch of
worker agents and this is very similar
to like a human organization for example
um so you can have this hierarchy where
like okay like if I'm a user I'm talking
to this one main agent but behind the
scene this agent is going and like
talking to its own worker agents
ensuring that each worker goes and does
the task and once everything is done
then the manag agent come back comes
back to me and says okay like this thing
is done and so you can imagine IM like
there's a lot of this Primitives that
can be built a good way to also think
about this is almost like a single core
machine versus a multicore machine so
like when you have a single agent almost
like saying I have a single processor
that's powering my uh computer but now
if I have multiple agents I have this
maybe like a 16 core or 64 core machine
where like a lot of this things can be
DED to different agents paralyzed and uh
I think that that's a very interesting
analogy when it comes to like a lot of
the like multi- agent
systems this still a lot of work uh that
needs to be done uh the biggest one is
like communication is really hard uh so
you need robust communication protocols
uh to minimize miscommunication you
might also just need like really good
like schemas and uh maybe like almost
like how you have HTP uh that's used to
transporting information over the
internet you might need something
similar uh to transport information
between different
agents um you can also think about some
Primitives here I'll just walk through a
small example if you have time like
suppose this is a manager agent that
wants to get a task done so it gives a
plan and a context to a worker agent the
work can say like okay I did this task
and then we get a response back then
usually you want to actually verify if
this got done or not because like it's
possible maybe the worker was lying to
you for example maybe it failed to do
the task or like something went wrong
and so you want to actually go and
verify that this actually was done
properly and if everything was done then
you know like okay this is good you can
tell the user this task was actually
finished but what could happen is maybe
like the the worker actually didn't do
the task properly something went wrong
and in that case like you want to
actually actually go and redo the task
and you just have to build this sort of
like a failover mechanisms because
otherwise there's there a lot of things
that can go wrong and so like thinking
about like this sort of like syncing
Primitives and how can you ensure
reliability how can you ensure fallback
I think that becomes like very
interesting with this kind of uh agentic
systems and there's like a lot of future
directions to be explored um there's a
lot of issues with autonomous agents
still the biggest one are around
reliability um so this happens because
like models are stochastic in nature
like if I have a AI model it's like a
it's stochastic it's like it's a
probalistic function uh it's not fully
deterministic and what happens is like
uh if I wanted to like do something it's
possible that with some error at Epsilon
it will do something that I didn't
expect it to do and and so like it
becomes really hard to trust it because
if I if I have traditional code I write
a script and I run the script through a
bunch of test cases and unit test I know
okay like if this works it's got over
100% of the time I can deploy this to
millions or billions of people but if
have an agent it's a stochastic function
uh maybe if it works maybe it works like
95% of the time but like 5% of time it
still fails uh and there's no way to fix
this right now uh so that becomes like
very interesting like how do you
actually like solve these
problems uh similarly you see a lot of
problems around like looping and plan
Divergence so what happens here is like
this like a you need a lot of multi
interactions when it comes to agents so
you want to like have the agent do
something then like use that to do
another thing so on so take like maybe
like hundreds or thousands of steps but
if it fails in like maybe like the 20th
step then then it might just go haire
don't know what to do for the remaining
like 20 like the remaining thousand
steps of the trajectory uh and so how do
you correct it bring it back on course I
think that becomes an interesting
problem uh similarly how do you test and
Benchmark this agents especially if
they're going to be running in the real
world and how do you build a lot of
observability on the systems right like
uh if I have this agent that's maybe
like has access to my bank account is
doing things for me uh how do I actually
know like it's uh doing safe things it's
not someone is not hicking into it
um how do I build trust and how also how
do we build like human fallbacks like
you probably want something like a 2fa
if it's going to go and like do
purchases for you or you want like some
ways to guarantee like okay like uh you
just didn't wake up and like uh have
like didn't have like a Zer bank account
or
something and so this are some of the
problems that we need to solve for
agents for them to become like real
world Deployable um and this is a
example of like a plan diverence problem
you see with agents like if you ask the
agent to go do something you will
usually expect expect it to follow like
a path where like it will like follow
some ideal path to reach the goal but
what might happen is like it might
actually deviate from the path and once
it deviates it doesn't know what to do
so it just keeps like making mistakes
after mistakes and this is something
actually you uh observe with like like
early agents like Auto gbd for example
um so I'm not sure if anyone in this
room has played with autog gbd uh has
anyone do that okay and so like Auto the
issue is like it's like like you it's a
very good like prototype but it doesn't
actually do anything because it just
keeps making a lot of mistakes it keeps
looping around keeps like going hawi and
and that's sort of like shows like okay
like what why you need really need to
have like really good ways to correcting
agents making sure like if it makes a
mistake it can actually come back and
not just like go do random
things uh so building on this there's
also like a very good uh uh analogy from
andreti so he likes to call this like
the LM operating system where uh like uh
how uh I was studying about like thing
about like llms and the Agents as
building computer chips and computers so
you can actually start thinking of it
like that like here the computer chip is
the LM and the ram is like the context
length of uh of the tokens that you're
feeding into the model then you have
this like file system which is a dis
where you are storing your embeddings
you're able to retrieve the embeddings
you might have traditional software 1.0
tools which are like uh your calculator
your python interpretor terminals Etc
you actually have this like if you have
like ever taken operating system course
there's this thing called ALU which is a
arithmetic logical unit which Powers a
lot of like how you do multiplications
division so on so it's very similar to
that like you just need like uh tools to
be able to like do like complex
operations and then you might also have
like peripheral devices so you might
have different modalities so you might
have audio you might have video you
probably want to be able to like connect
to the Internet so you want to have like
some sort of like browsing capabilities
and you might also want to be able to to
talk to like other llms um and so this
kind of becomes like how you will think
about a new generation of computers
being designed uh with all the
Innovations in
AI cool uh and so I would like to end
here by saying like uh how I imagine
this to look like in the future is like
you can think of this as a neural
computer where like uh there's a user
that's talking to a chat interface
behind the scene like the chat interface
has a action engine that can like take
the task rout it to different agents and
like do the for you and send you the
results
back uh cool so and then
um so let's uh yeah so to end this uh
this's like uh a lot of stuff just needs
to be done for agents and the biggest
prevalent uh issues right now we say is
like error correction so like what
happens if something goes wrong how do
you prevent the errors from extrating in
the real world how do you build security
how do you build user permissions like
what if someone tries to hijack your
computer or your agent how do you build
like like robust like uh uh security
Primitives and also how do you like
sandbox this agents how do you deploy
them in Risky scenarios so if you want
to deploy this in like Finance scenarios
or like legal scenarios uh there's a lot
of things where you just want this to be
very uh Str stable and safe and that's
like still something that has not been
figured out and there's a lot of
exciting um room uh to like sort of like
think on the problems both on the
research side as well as application
side cool all right so thanks guys for
coming to our first lecture this quarter
um stay back if you have any questions
and we might try to get a group photo so
if you want to be in that um also stay
back um so next week we're going to have
my friend Jason way as well as his
colleag kyang Wan from open AI um come
give a talk and they're doing very
Cutting Edge research involving um
things like large language models at
openai um and he was actually the first
author of several of the works we talked
about today like Chain of Thought
reasoning and emerging behaviors so if
you're enrolled please come in person
they'll be in person um so you'll be
able to interact with them um in person
and um if you're still not enrolled in
the course and wish to do so please do
so on access and for the folks on Zoom
um feel free to audit um uh lectures
will be the same time uh each week on
Thursday and we'll announce any
notifications by email canvas as well as
Discord um so keep your eye out um for
those and yeah so thank thank you guys