well thanks for coming Ben thanks for
having me give us a sense of the scale
that anthropics at right now yeah so in
terms of actual numbers I don't want to
get specifics but uh you can Google it
and see what you find what I can say is
that in the last year we've 10x our
revenue and we've in the last three
months following uh leading up to
December we 10x our Revenue just in the
coding segment so we're see absolutely
explosive growth in all areas and uh
having a pretty fun time trying to serve
all that traffic and how did you get to
where you are
now uh in life yeah yeah I guess I
started uh thinking about computer
science in undergrad and wasn't one of
these people who starts coding when they
were five and I just fell in love with
it I originally thought I wanted to be a
mechanical engineer and do robotics but
I hated mechanical engineering and I
hated robotics when I took the intro
classes and uh computer science just
kind of stole my imagination ended up
doing the AI track at Columbia and back
then AI was pretty different we were
talking about things like artificial
intelligence leading to systems that
could think like people do but it was
still pretty far away and it wasn't
practical in it by any means we were
talking about things like expert systems
and the AI winter of the 80s multi-layer
perceptrons which are the protozone
ancestors of the models that we have
today and that definitely caught my
imagination and so I worked at Google
for a while intending to just um sort of
learn the ropes and immediately start a
company which I imagine is pretty
familiar to an audience like
Stanford um but I kept on learning more
things but when imet came out in 2015
for me that was a tectonic moment where
suddenly these techniques that people
had been talking about for a long time
were suddenly practical in ways that
they hadn't been before uh on tasks that
typically would have required a human
judge to decide you know what kind of
dog asist and it was definitely way
better at classification than I was and
could be trained on a single GPU which
was amazing so from there I started
jumping into Ai and and learning about
it just on my own didn't do a masters
didn't do a PhD started reading a lot of
papers and figuring it out um worked
with a bunch of people who were starting
companies to get my feet wet and shortly
after that I decided to join open AI um
I had read this book called Super
intelligence by Nick fostr that talked
about how AI is going to be this really
important thing for Humanity as a whole
to figure out not just America or your
your school your your state or whatever
it's it'll be this thing that we need to
existentially Grapple with and it seemed
right to me so I joined open AI in
2017 and at that time we had no idea how
we were going to get to AGI we just
thought stuff is happening in Ai and we
should get on the frontier um and I
really bought the safety Mission at the
time
and I think there's some questions about
how how adherent they are still to that
mission today um but definitely making
some huge progress
and then all Fast Forward of it when
gpd2 came out I was like aha this is how
we get to AGI it won't be that we have
some simulated agents on a desert island
who are kind of battling it out and
trying to have intelligence emerge
instead we'll train it on all the
world's knowledge in the form of data
from the internet right and from there
uh it will exhibit properties of human
intelligence and a lot of people poo
pooed that and they were like oh it's
just pattern matching it's not real not
reasoning um humans are somehow special
but even at at that time I believe that
it was just a continuous ramp to getting
to the capabilities that we have today
and tomorrow uh and so I joined open AI
again after an interlude and at that
time I ended up with Dario and Tom Brown
Starting the uh gbd3 project so I was
one of the first authors on that paper
even though I didn't have a formal
research background I did all the data
engineering and a lot of analysis for um
how data affected the quality of the
model that came out of that process did
a bunch of uh architecture experiments
with Tom and to me that was sort of the
confirmation that scaling laws could
hold up across 13 ORD of magnitude back
then much more now um and it's actually
just very rare even in the physical
world that we see any phenomena that uh
with persist across that kind of scale
so was quite inspiring to me and then at
some point we felt like we could make
safety more uh core part of our mission
if we left to start our own company so
four years ago uh eight of us left the
company to start anthropic and uh since
then we've kind of leapt to the frontier
uh as the people who were building gbd3
at open AI we had a much easier time
doing it the second time around and on
top of that we were able to make a bunch
of safety breakthroughs that uh ended up
being really commercially valuable as
well which wasn't something that was uh
for granted wasn't necessarily going to
happen uh but ended up being really
important for us to create a race to the
top which is what we calm sort of
pushing all the other companies that are
in in the field to at least match us in
their commitments to making
Sai let's
uh let's focus on the gpt3 era for
herbit um you know one of the things
that uh is has been has been a very
consistent theme of computer Computing
systems uh across you know
infrastructure Primitives like storage
networking compute is that other than
Moors law which has been fairly
predictable and has not really um
diminished uh for for the greater part
of the 30 years or so that you know
we've had the the chance to to
empirically verify it and somewhat
predict
most other Computing um performance
metrics start off accelerating pretty
exponentially and then hit sigmoids they
start plateauing right if you look at
latency between interconnects chips um
bandwidth latency over the Internet um
if you look at the CPU performance too
right like we did have this
extraordinary moment of exponential
Improvement on most of these Computing
system improve uh performance metrics in
the '90s right and early 2000s and then
they kind of all start to plateau and so
for a lot of infra veterans from the
cloud era um when SK when gbd3 was first
published it was a yeah yeah yeah we've
seen this before but this isn't going to
hold and there was a lot of skepticism
right what was it in internally that
made you go even though you didn't have
a traditional you didn't have a physics
background you didn't have the a PhD and
you actually more likely from your prior
biases to have the engineering bias are
saying well these systems will Plateau
out what prevented you from falling into
that TR prop yeah I I might actually
dispute the premise that uh things like
memory bandwidth and uh and other
systems besides
CPUs uh more sigmoid I think there are
other factors that pushed that to happen
and now that for example fast
interconnects are something that people
really care about now they're like
continuing more of an exponential ramp
that it was just that those systems were
not the bottleneck for uh the systems to
continue to improve overall
um and that you you you'd say it was the
lack of investment in those fundamental
research breakthroughs not a fundamental
limitation of the system so like the
compute service
providers they said you know we have 30
gigabit interconnects between in our
between the machines in our data centers
and nobody is asking us for more so
we're not going to do anything and then
Nvidia acquires melanox which has like
400 gigabit interconnects and now
everybody's like oh now we have to
more interconnects and and now the the
pace of innovation for interconnects is
increasing a lot again um and if you
look at uh Apple's M series of of chips
uh their memory bandwidth is really
remarkable like that's one of the main
things that differentiates their M
series from the traditional like AMD or
or Intel silicon so is is your sense
that the the skepticism around scaling
laws then came mostly from uh observing
plateau was in performance evals for
previous AI models is that where this
kept isting why why do you think there
was so much in resist resistance to the
IDE scaling laws I think there was
resistance because people felt that it
wouldn't just keep happening and as an
example of this right before the gd3
paper came out a paper called T5 from
Google was published and it was about an
11 billion parameter model and in the
concluding paragraph of that paper they
said we don't see any returns to scale
we think that even T5 is undeployable as
it is like nobody will spend the amount
of money that it costs to do inference
on this thing people were locked in the
sort of Bert Paradigm where they were
doing like 300 million parameter models
and that was considered large right uh
and so to scale out to 11 it would take
like an entire GPU box with many
accelerators doing data parallel
operations
and people didn't think it was going to
work economically let alone from a
performance standpoint so I think this
is happened in a a bunch of different
areas so if you look at even like the
fastest mile that a person can run
there's this thing called the banister
effect where before somebody broke the
4minute mile people thought that it was
impossible and then as soon as somebody
did then everybody started doing it and
so I think it's it's pretty common for
for people to have a more conservative
worldview of like I've never seen this
happen and it seems unlikely because I
don't have any priors of it happening so
I'm just going to assume it can't happen
that's one piece and the second piece is
assigning something special to human
cognitive ability and if you look at
people like Fran chal who talk about
reasoning and the arc prize I think
there's a big question of like are the
reasoning models something special or is
that just a cap ability that you could
have elicited that is just weaker if you
don't train it
specifically um and so elicitation is
also a big part of this this question of
how good are the models and how much
performance can we extract on a certain
Benchmark once it started to become
clear that if you did scale you know you
would start to see um if as long as you
you threw enough compute and invested in
a sufficient flops budget that you could
solve you could improve elicitation
especially on adversarial metrics like
safety
um what was the what were the systems
that then once we had crossed that
barrier of saying okay we're it's it's
it's holding we've got enough compute to
throw at this what were the systems that
then started keeping you up at night
that you were concerned would
break I mean I think it was kind of
everything at every level of the stack
and I also feel like a big part of why
things didn't go fast is that it
required a really tight collaboration
between researchers and Engineers where
typically if you look at Deep Mind in
the early days it was mostly researchers
who were driving the ship and the
engineers were like the Lackey who they
would throw tasks over to no offense to
any of them uh but at open AI it was
very integrated and anthropic I would
say even more so right where it's
they're like cohesive teams that are
steering the ship together and
these things start becoming start
looking more like engineering Mega
projects you know like three gorgees Dam
style like we have to get a ton of
resources into this one thing and I
think that's another reason that Deep
Mind wasn't set up for success or uh
Google brain where typically they
organized as a bunch of researchers each
doing their own thing and if they wanted
to pull their resources to do one big
thing then they couldn't really convince
anybody right
make a big bet um whereas at open Ai and
and later at anthropic uh I think from
the beginning we've been doing these big
bets and uh they are quite risky but the
magic of scaling laws is it it allows
you to turn what was previously an art
where you kind of just throw stuff at
the wall and see what sticks into more
of a science to say look we know what
the scaling looks like in terms of hyper
parameters collection data set quality
and we can do these small cheap
experiments that will then give us
confidence that by the time we scale up
it will be a useful artifact instead of
a very expensive piece of
trash that's not an analogy I've heard
before but that's an interesting way to
describe um it if you had to contrast
that moment you know when you were uh
training
gbd3 with a system like Claude 3.5 Sonet
which is rough State ofthe art now what
what's the biggest difference in the
hardest engineering problems you have to
tackle then versus
now
um I mean one of the problems is
compartmentalization where now we have
hundreds of people working on these
models and we need all of them to be
able to coordinate with each other but
we don't want our compute multipliers
which is our secret sauce of uh you know
given techniques that raise the
capabilities for a certain compute
budget we don't want those to leak so
we've uh borrowed these techniques that
you know the American intelligence
organization uses for example where only
some people know about some of the
techniques uh or I guess
silicon um like CPU developers also have
have used these for a long time so no
one person can hold the whole system in
their heads and yet you still need to
create an artifact which is a cohesive
hole at the end so we have methods that
we use to to to try to make that
successful that's definitely one
Challenge from a systems engineering
perspective we also don't control our
own compute we rely on Amazon Google our
other compute providers to uh
orchestrate our clusters on our behalf
but our workloads look completely
different from many other workloads you
we're using kubernetes clusters with
very high numbers of nodes out of spec
for what the standard is supposed to
support and we're pushing these systems
to their limits on pretty much every
axis uh whether it be the reliability of
being able to if a job Fails Like if one
if one machine in a vastly distributed
job fails being able to restart quickly
and not lose a lot of progress uh the
cloud storage of storing all the
snapshots and transmitting the data to
the to the machines for the training um
and now the big thing is reinforcement
learning right which is even more
complicated where you'll have some kind
of stateful environments that the agents
are interacting with those agents need
to have the most recent model weights
and efficiently updating them so yeah
it's it's hard at every level and new
stuff breaks every day and uh you know
even at open aai we had we had a bug
where we flipped a negative sign on the
reward and the model was seeming to get
more and more evil as we trained it it
was a preference model reward I think
and uh at some point we realized
that actually there is a double negative
and so the bug had been there for a long
time uh and when we fixed it we actually
broke it so then we had to fix it twice
yeah let so let's talk about that
incident for a sec um was that for for
three or 3.5 uh I wasn't there for 3.5
so okay so this the three okay so at
this point three had already been done
training it was in prod this was a bug
that was live no no I think this was uh
in some like underlying test model like
we never release a model without red
teaming it and we have all these methods
of uh rapidly eving it over time right
while it's in training to make sure that
things look healthy and uh I guess to
give a sense of these runs you never
just like YOLO put it out there and then
hope that it works while it's running
you're constantly watching like hundreds
of different Diagnostics to make sure
that it's healthy and thriving uh and if
you've trained an ml model you know that
there are these loss curves that you
watch on the training distribution or
other distributions and for big models
in particular you often get lost spikes
so sometimes you just like roll it back
and hope that when you roll it Forward
again it doesn't Spike even though you
haven't changed anything and if the
spikes get too hard then then you have
to do a more deep surgical intervention
so it's very much an art and it also
feels kind of like you have a patient on
life support or like it feels very
critical to like always be watching it
right
um and uh yeah so I guess coming back to
the the question of like was it in pra
no this is just during training we we
noticed stuff was going wrong yeah uh
and maybe this is in the post training
um but yeah yeah this this is taking me
back to TW 20 uh 21 I think it was maybe
June or July when I was um out with s
with Tom who one of your co-founders uh
we were at a birthday or something and
you know Tom kept nervously refreshing I
think it was a some observability
dashboard um and and he was basically
babysitting the run right which is quite
a common thing was a common thing back
in the day you know dashboarding
alerting observability monitoring was
quite brittle and so you literally had
somebody babysitting the run for these
these uh situations how's that changed
now is are things any better at all or
is it still the INF for teams in a war
room for every training run every
ablation observability is you know just
as as Britt as it was then I mean we
definitely have borrowed a lot of tricks
from standard engineering practice in
terms of having on call rotations and
trying to make things sustainable and
even having like follow the sun
rotations where we have people all
around the world for whom it's daytime
so you don't have to get called in the
middle of the night and go uh clean up
the models pooping the bed or whatever
uh but yeah I mean Ben has two kids so
he's got I have two babies Rich body of
analogies to draw on here yeah six-month
old and a two-year-old um but yeah I
think it's still pretty hard I'm not
going to trigger code it um so so take
us into the training of one of these
systems today that are you know from a
complexity Point have have ballooned
dramatically because the sheer scale
rels gp3 now yeah um roughly 10 orders
of magnitude higher at least on size
CLA is you know it's not public how
large CLA is and so on but at least by
that much right um so you've scaled the
size of these system of the models you
scale the team by 10x that's working on
it and then roughly scal the number of
customers relying on the model in
production is on inference by well nor
north of 10 10x yeah is that right um so
that's one order of magnitude but uh but
actually I think I think your
users um relative to and know you
weren't there for 3.5 but roughly orders
and magnitude wise how many users do you
think anthropic is how many orders of
magnitude more users are is anthropic
supporting inference today than year
one so many more I mean year one we
started from zero fair enough uh so
let's the first Claud actually let's
talk let's use Claude the version that
had been done training in uh March 2022
yeah pre g chat gbt yeah because that
had a few thousand users right and
friends and family yeah so before tacha
BD came out we had a friends and family
version of CLA that people could use in
slack um and people really liked it uh
there is a big question of what would it
mean for us to expose that to the world
and we had a lot of debates about it
internally of what that would do to the
Zeitgeist and our general feeling was
that it would cause too much
acceleration um ironically there's a a
rumor that Chachi PT launched because
they thought we were about to launch
something which wasn't true uh but I
still feel pretty good that we gave the
world six more months to work on
safety uh in terms of that model it was
pretty basic uh and we hadn't done a ton
of optimizations to um like make it fast
to run or um make it like comfortable to
use but just using it in slack I think
woke up a lot of people who were in that
and family program I guess what was your
impression as one of those
testers I thought we should let her rip
yeah I mean it's extraordinary I you
know I had the privilege of being one of
anthropics First Investors you and you
Dario and Tom gave me a call in at the
end of 2020 and said we want to leave
and leave open and start anthropic and
uh I said sure what you know what do you
think we're going to need to raise to to
get to our first Milestone and you know
without blinking Dario said 500 million
and I was like well that's going to take
a while and how long do you think it's
going to to take us to get to our first
training run that would be comparable
and you know there was some debate about
whether we could initialize the training
run with open source weights um I think
Megatron 530b was like a candate at the
time but I mean I it the closest
estimate at the time of getting to
something of that level was going to be
like seven to nine months at least yeah
but it you guys trained it way faster
and it was extraordinarily coherent I
think that was the first observation I
had of using the bot in in slack was
that it GPT 2.5 was like your kind of
chaotic friend on drugs you know a
little bit like it was fun but like you
can have really a sustained coherent
conversation yeah with with
Claude um it was clear that it had
crossed the barrier of M of maintaining
character of being a helpful harmless
assistant was that actually a system
prompt was that explicitly designed how
did how did how did you guys get it to
to do that yeah I think there are a
couple of things one is that as models
improve in quality they just become more
coherent naturally right so if you've
ever used gpd2 which maybe none of you
have but I guess small models also
exhibit this Behavior even from like
sentence to sentence it can kind of lose
the thread or if you TR it to low
temperature it will just start repeating
itself over and over again um like if
you ever try to write Pros in uh GitHub
co-pilot it will it will do this right
very frequently um and so part of it is
is that we just had a better model and
then I think the other part is the
state-of-the-art of the time was
instruction tuning right and that's
typically like a single turn interaction
so once you get Beyond a single turn you
start having these more dialogue like
inter yes right the model is what we
call out of distribution where it hasn't
seen this in training and it kind of
gets confused and um performance falls
off a cliff so for our training runs we
very early on started collecting human
feedback right um and that human
feedback was always multi-turn from the
start and the prompt that we gave it
which I guess was sort of the early kind
of system prompt um was another dialogue
right so it was already trying to model
this behavior and as our models improved
and we would rapidly roll in the
feedback that the humans gave us back
into the training process and then put
those back in the interface and sort of
uh Oro Bor way up the up the chain right
it would get better and better at
maintaining coherence over long
conversations yeah so so that it was
that rhf you know which you guys
pioneered at open the ey uh um just
quick detour here how many folks know
what rhf
is okay never mind we're not going to
explain it then most people know my last
question for you is that was the first
iteration of rhf what was the why from a
systems perspective did you guys go from
betting on that to R aif and could you
explain
for the folks here what what the
meaningful difference is yeah so rhf
you're asking humans to submit
preferences and then those preferences
train a preference model that then
stands in for the human during
reinforcement learning and says whether
a given output is good or bad so you can
think of it as we're training a teacher
and then the teacher is training the
student right which is the model that
you end up seeing at the end
so and then you kind of throw the
teacher away when you're done um in a
nice way uh for rla aif it's very
different uh that's what we call
constitutional AI right that's one way
of doing RF where we write a set of
natural language principles that defines
how we want the agent to behave which
may be something like be kind or be
empathetic or don't write cyber secur
attacks or or like don't uh create
recipes for poon or something and then
in a completely
enclosed process with no humans in the
loop we asked the model to critique
itself and then based on its own
critiques up dat itself so this process
is much more steerable because humans
they come from very different
backgrounds maybe they will interpret
the instructions that we give them
differently maybe they uh won't remember
all the instructions that we gave them
with rif it's a very repeatable uh
amenable to science process that we can
iterate on uh in a laboratory setting
and really tune it to get exactly the
outputs that we want y but it's only
possible beyond a certain capability
threshold and if you try to do it with
too small a model it just won't work
because when you asked the model did you
comply with principle X when you said
this sample output it won't give you a
good answer and it won't be able to
revise in response to that right but
with strong enough models then you can
bootstrap to higher capability levels
and then keep on recursively
self-improving the the reason um I think
this is important is because for many of
you who are software Engineers um
wondering how do you contribute to the
frontier you know hearing Ben talk about
the ri pipeline should be it should
become clear that it's an engineering
challenge it's not just a research
Challenge and uh you know I know a big
part of anthropic has been making sure
that uh it's a great place for engineers
to to be able to contribute because the
the the fundamental Computing and infra
challenges are not just research for to
get the more capabilities
yeah all feel free to repeat it line
yeah so uh he's referring to an
interview that I did with Kevin Roose uh
maybe a year or two ago on anthropics
take on AI safety I think the title is
something like the AI doomers in San
Francisco something something um and the
question was uh in the interview I said
something like we're aware of the things
that can and do go wrong with AI system
training how do you do that evaluation
uh and how do you anticipate the new
things that might come
up um that's a good question evals are
extremely hard we actually have a blog
post on why evals are hard for the Gory
details but the short answer is uh we're
constantly trying to make our evaluation
better and we've made our policy of
evaluation public and how we do those
evaluations in our responsible scaling
policy so you can go look at the
document but basically it says uh we
care most about things like cbrn risks
which are chemical nuclear radiological
and biological risks uh these are things
that could really destabilize Society if
models were capable of doing these
things um but we also look at things
like cyber security uh capabilities and
things like that um and we work with
expert red teamers who uh you know you
can go hire pent testers from a cyber
security company we also work with
people who you can't really hire who
work for the US government and know
National nuclear secrets and work with
them to elicit these capabilities from
the models that said there is an
elicitation overhang which means uh even
if a model might have a capability
latent in it there may be like a special
way of asking the model for that cap
ability that we don't know yet so as an
example of this historically Chain of
Thought came about pretty recently where
if you ask the
model uh show me your thought process
step by step then it dramatically
improves the model's outputs even saying
something as simple as try very very
very very hard and all those varies are
actually important that also improves
model output or it did back when this uh
research was done so it's definitely uh
an ever advancing science um we
collaborate with the United States and
and UK AI safety institutes basically
it's a super hard problem we need more
people thinking about it and I actually
think uh academic settings is one of the
best ways to contribute to things like
evals where you don't actually need a
ton of resources to get a sense of what
the models capabilities are if you look
at benchmarks like OS world that came
out recently these give us a sense of uh
reproducibly across many model providers
how good is the model at manipulating a
desktop computer with a keyboard and
mouse um and while that in itself is not
risky it can point to risks like usage
for uh cyber attacks so uh we definitely
care a lot about this and we spend a ton
of time thinking about it we collaborate
with a bunch of people who spend a ton
of time thinking about it um but we need
more brains so please help us but more
and and maybe more
uh you
know sort of directly asking your
question as far as I'm aware um anthropy
is the only lab that is committed to
pausing development based on capability
thresholds using the RSP there's still
no other Frontier lab that is committed
doing that is that right yeah so
specifically what we've committed to is
uh each of our AI safety levels or asls
require a certain set of mitigations
that we've written down right and pre
commed to right so for example asl3 is
the next one and it's basically like if
the model has some ability to create
biological threats by itself can
marginally accelerate uh a human
researcher who's who's trying to do this
stuff um but isn't necessarily superum
at doing these things right uh if a
model meets those criteria then we need
to have certain controls in place like
two-party control for committing code so
you can't just single-handedly modify
the production environment for anthropic
you need to have at least one other
person review your actions right and
that helps us with things like Insider
threat risk um and uh given that that
makes us more
comfortable feeling like we won't be
manipulated by our own Financial or
other Market incentives uh to doing
things that we thought don't think are
safe um I I think you're right that
other companies have committed to this
or or at least maybe not the frontier
ones but uh I I'm not an expert on it
and then another thing worth that an
Tropic is unique at is having a the ltbt
which is a governance mechanism that can
shut down the company if they if if the
overseeing board decides that they're
not um developing AI in a way that's net
positive for Humanity anyway that's
that's something we could send out for
reading but as far as I'm aware
anthropic Remains the only lab that's
had a public ltbt governance set up
right yeah the question was now that you
can run uh Frontier models locally how
does that affect how anthropic does
things in the
future um I think the frontier will
always only be able to run on like data
center level compute and the things that
you can run locally will lag behind them
by a couple of years probably and I
think we were already seeing this with
llama models that you could already run
llama 300b on your machine uh people
like EXA had demos of like networking
Two Mex together so you could run the
biggest model uh but of course like
people are always improving quantization
and shrinking that down so from the
standpoint of what capability you'll be
able to get
locally yeah that's always going to be
increasing um but I think the frontier
is the thing that we care about the most
especially from a safety standpoint the
reason it's important for us to stay on
the frontier is that we want our safety
techniques to be applicable to the the
frontier of AI models and the ones that
are coming 5 to 10 years from now so as
long as we're able to stay ahead from
that perspective uh we'll be able to do
our best safety work and sort of show
everybody hopefully how to make big
models safe which a lot of people didn't
even think was possible before one one
Cory of that question I guess is um you
know a big part of large the large
pre-training era has been having access
to bigger and bigger single spine data
centers right where you have collocated
chips on a single spine so you you can
interconnect larger and larger numbers
of gpus for a single training run do you
think that continues to be the case for
inference
scaling um I mean inference definitely
doesn't mean as much interconnects right
so you can distribute your compute more
broadly um like for an inference scaling
for an RL training run over a long
Horizon Chain of Thought right is it
more advantageous to have workloads
running on a single spine
I don't think we know yet I think
pre-training is very efficient and can
get you very far and I I don't think
pre-training will disappear right um
like I think there is some experiments
with having a RL only run but I think
they still use distillation right uh
which is a form of supervised learning
so it's not that different from a
workload standpoint right from a
technical perspective um but what will
happen with RL I think it's yet to be
seen there are lots of companies and and
uh open source organizations who have
been trying to scale pre-training to
massive massively distributed networks
of of machines by doing like single bit
updates uh instead of like full
gradients
so that trend is already happening um
whether those are competitive with like
spending the money to get a a giant data
center nobody knows yet yeah certainly
there's economic intendent for that
right uh the question is how do we
Define safe Ai and what are the
mechanisms to make that happen uh safe
AI is first and foremost AI that doesn't
cause catastrophic harm to humanity and
maybe on a more micro level does what
you want and not what you say per se uh
like you wouldn't want sort of a monkey
paw Style Genie gry 3 wishes thing as
these agents become more powerful so in
terms of models today we we Define it as
asl2 where even if you had unfettered
access to the model uh and it wasn't
that aligned it wouldn't cause a lot of
harm in society so for example today
even before our computer use stuff came
out models were pretty good at beating
captas there's not a huge amount of harm
there were already other techniques and
more narrow models that could defeat cap
so the marginal risk of having an llm
that could do that wasn't very high
however as we get towards things that
can do automated cyber attacks and
things like that the risk increases and
that's why we've defined these AI safety
levels in terms of mechanisms to prevent
that we have uh a defense in-depth
mindset which comes from security um
where we don't just have one system that
tries to make the model safe it's at
every layer so we incorporate safety
training in in pre-training and
posttraining we have online classifiers
that try to detect whether people are
trying to do bad stuff that we call
Prompt
Shield um and we're developing more
techniques every day to to deel to do
scalable oversight one of the things I'm
most excited about is interpretability
mechanistic interpretability is is the
flavor that uh we are most uh pushing
forward and the idea there is that if
you could sort of peer into the mind of
the model as it's operating not just in
the tokens that it's outputting but how
those concepts are even formed
internally to the model then it should
be possible to audit what a model is
doing and make sure that it's not trying
to do things like uh resource
stockpiling or shutdown resistance that
uh you would want to
preserve uh in in the case of an
extremely powerful model so we're we're
seeing pretty pretty good advancements
in mechan mechanistic interpretability
its early days still um but I think
we're kind of like Chris Ola and his
team are creating this field from Whole
cloth which is pretty hard um and we're
starting to get a sense of of what's
going on so I think that's probably my
greatest
hope I think we've got time for one more
question the question was uh how do you
think about authoring a foundation model
at scale and what's the difference
between the API and the chat
offerings uh in terms of authoring I
mean there's just so many different
aspects to it it's very much an art we
had this podcast with Amanda asol and
Stuart can't remember his last name who
uh talked about our Claude character
efforts which are down in the details of
how we think about refusals and if you
are refusing can you like still give a
little bit of information
to express empathy and to give the
person uh something to chew on even if
you didn't give them the answer that
they wanted um so yeah that's that's a
very broad question that's hard to
answer but maybe I'll focus on the
second one which is the difference
between uh the chat experience and the
API
offering uh the chat experience is
actually much easier to move fast on and
develop with because we control every
aspect of it and if we need to like
change something or pull it back we can
do that unilaterally with an API uh one
of my co-workers who used to be at
stripe said apis are forever that once
you release an API now there are
companies Partners who are depending on
this API and if you change it they will
be upset and you may break them and so
even deprecating clae one clae 2 models
took us a very long time we only just
did it and I think Cloud 2 is actually
still in production somewhere which is
astounding given how much worse it is
than all other models but you know
businesses have other considerations
than just using the coolest stuff and
the best stuff um for them it might be
more about business continuity or uh
maybe they don't have engineering
resources so that's a huge difference
between those two and uh we also think
of a of the chat experience as a way we
can grant developers more power once we
realize how good or not good a certain
experience is so for example uh you can
now upload PDFs in the API we had that
in the chat experience for a long time
and we just wanted to make it easier for
developers to be able to do that with
Cloud because putting in context is one
of the most important things and I think
you'll see that continuing over time
that we use the chat experience as sort
of a Proving Ground for the things that
we then expose to other
developers awesome thank you so much BR
glad to be here nice