All right, welcome back everyone to
lecture 8. Uh, today we're going to talk
about attention and transformers. And I
think this is a this is a really fun
one. So, as a quick recap, last time we
were talking about recurrent neural
networks and recurrent neural networks
were this new kind of neural network
architecture meant for processing
sequences. And in particular, we saw how
neural networks by by processing
sequences let us attack a whole new
different kinds of problems than we than
we could with convolutional networks uh
before. So in particular usually we had
been thinking about these onetoone
problems where you input one thing like
an image and then output one thing like
a classification for what's in that
image. But once you have the ability to
move beyond images and move towards
sequences of data it let us tackle a lot
of new kinds of problems like one to
many problems image captioning maybe we
want to input an image output a textual
description of that image which is going
to be a sequence of words. Um maybe many
to one where we do input a sequence of
frames and output a classification for
those frames. um and a bunch of other
problems along this vein. Um so now
we're seeing that moving be moving into
these more um sophisticated neural
network architectures um both is sort of
more interesting architecturally but
also lets us tackle new problems than we
could with um with kind of more
traditional feed forward neural
networks. So today we're going to build
on that and talk about two new things in
today's lecture. Um the first thing is
going to be attention which is going to
be a brand new neural network primitive
that fundamentally operates on sets of
vectors. And then the second thing we're
going to talk about is the transformer.
And the transformer is a different
neural network architecture that has
self attention at its core. Um, and this
and the spoiler alert is that
transformers are basically the
architecture that we use for almost all
problems in deep learning today. So any
of the largest applications that you're
seeing out there in the wild today,
whether it's classifying images,
generating images, generating text,
classifying text, working with audio,
basically any kind of large neural
network today, um that is large,
state-of-the-art, trained in a lot of
data, um deployed by a big company,
almost all of them are going to be
transformers today. Um so that's really
exciting that we get to get you up to
speed on the latest and greatest
architectures that people are using now.
Um, but even though transformers are
this sort of state-of-the-art
architecture that everyone is using for
everything today, they have kind of they
have a relatively long history. Um, and
they initially like it's kind of
interesting watching these fields
develop because looking back on it when
the moment that Transformers came out,
it feels like it ought to have been this
big moment, this big thing when there
was a big sea change, this new
architecture, this new thing. But it
actually didn't feel that way because
even though there was one moment where
the transformer architecture was born,
um these ideas around self attention,
around using attention in various ways,
those had actually been around in the
field for several years at that time.
And in particular, these ideas around
attention, self attention, they actually
developed out of recurrent neural
networks. So we're going to start there
to talk about and motivate these
problems. So this is going to be a
little bit mirroring the historical
development of these ideas.
So for that reason um we're actually
going to in order to introduce
transformers we're actually going to
roll back and recap a little bit about
this idea of recurrent neural networks
that we saw in the last lecture. So as a
motivating problem um let's think about
this sequence to sequence problem of
translation. So we want to input one
sequence which is going to be a sequence
of words in English. Then we want to
output another sequence which is going
to be a sequence of words in a different
language Italian. Right? And because you
and we can't make assumptions that
there's any correspondence between those
words. Right? The the number of words in
the English sentence might be different
from the number of words in the Italian
sentence and the order of those words
might be totally different. So this is a
perfect application of the kind of
sequence processing algorithms that we
uh sequence processing architectures
that we saw in recurrent neural
networks. Um and indeed this idea of
processing these uh sequencetosequence
problems with recurrent neural networks.
This goes all the way back to 2014 um
even even a bit earlier than that. But
people had been processing sequences
with recurrent neural networks for more
than a decade more than a decade at this
point. So the basic architecture for
processing sequence sequence to sequence
problems with recurrent neural networks
is that typically you'll start with one
encoder. Your encoder is a recurrent
neural network. Um the recurrent neural
network recall is this function that
gets applied recursively um on two
inputs. One is your xt your input at the
current time step and the other is your
ht minus one which is your hidden state
at the previous time step. and your
recurrent neural network unit will then
spit out a next hidden unit, a next
hidden state at the next time step. And
then we can apply that same recurrent
neural network unit over in time um to
process a sequence of a of potentially
variable length. So in this case, we're
using a recurrent neural network encoder
that inputs the input sequence in
English. Um input sequence, you know,
you you got to use relatively short
sentences um to fit on slides and still
have all the boxes show up. So we're
using a kind of short, silly sentence,
uh we see the sky. Um, and this, you
know, each word in that sentence gets
processed but via one tick of the
recurrent neural network. And now, and
then we're going to the idea of this
encoder neural recurrent neural network
is it wants to process all of the words
in in the input sequence and somehow
summarize the content of that input
sentence so that we can translate it
into a different into our output target
language. So the the the more the more
concrete way that this happens is that
after processing all the words in the
input in the input sequence, we're going
to summarize the the entire content of
that input sequence into a single vector
called the context vector. Um and
there's a there's a couple different
ways that people would typically do
these in recurren recurrent neural
networks. I don't think the details are
too interesting. So as a you can just
think that that context vector is
basically the last hidden state of the
of the encoder recurrent neural network.
Um and now the idea is that because you
know this this these because of the
recurrent structure of our recurrent
neural networks the last hidden state
sort of incorporates information of the
entire input sequence. So we can think
of that last hidden state as summarizing
or encoding all of the information in
the entire input sequence. Um so then
that that is one vector that is going to
kind of summarize that entire input
sequence to do whatever we want with it.
Um and in this case what we want to do
with it is translate that input sequence
into an output sequence in a different
language. So to do that we're going to
use a second recurrent neural network
called the decoder. Um which usually has
the same architecture but potentially
different a different weight matrix
different set of learned parameters. Um
and this decoder GU is going to be a
different recurrent neural network with
different different learnable weights u
but has the same basic idea. Um now this
a recurrent neural network unit is going
to take three inputs at every time step.
It's going to take um yt minus one which
is the token and the output sequence at
the previous time step. It's going to
take ST minus one, which is the previous
hidden state in the output sequence, and
C, which is that context vector summariz
summarizing the entire input sequence.
Um, and then we kind of unroll that
output sequence just as we saw in the
last lecture and and produce words one
at a time in the output sequence. And I
don't speak Italian, so I'm not going to
try to I'm not going to try to pronounce
these, but um there's some Italian words
on the screen that you can see. And I'm
assuming that that indeed translates to
we see the sky. Um hopefully that's
correct, right? But the idea is we're
going to like tick this recurrent neural
network one tick at a time. It's going
to output words one at a time. And this
is basically a summary of what we saw
last lecture. So this should this should
basically not be too surprising in light
of the previous lecture.
But there's a potential problem here,
right? And that's the there's a
communication bottleneck here between
the input sequence and the output
sequence, right? The only way in which
the input sequence is communicating with
the output sequence is via that context
vector C. Um, and that C is going to be
a fixed length vector, right? Because
the size of that vector is fixed when we
set the size of our recurrent neural
network. Um, and maybe that's fine,
right? So C might be a fixed length
vector of like 128 floats, 1024 floats,
but the size of that input vector is not
going to change as our input and output
sequence sizes grow or shrink. And
that's a potential problem, right? So if
we're doing short sequences like we see
the sky, maybe it seems pretty plausible
that we can summarize everything we need
to know about that sequence in that
fixed vector of 12 the 1024 floats. But
what if we're not trying to translate
four words? What if we're trying to
translate a whole paragraph or a whole
book or like an entire corpus of data?
um then in that case we're going to run
into a bottleneck where at some point as
we scale that input sequence it's just
not going to be sensible for to ask the
network to summarize the entire input
sequence into a into a single fixed
length vector. So that's going to be a
problem.
So the solution here is actually let's
not bottleneck the network through a
fixed through one fixed length vector.
Instead let's change the architecture of
our recurrent neural network.
Intuitively, what we want to do is not
force a bottleneck between a in a fixed
length vector between the input and the
output. Instead, as we process the
output sequence, we're going to give the
model the ability to look back at the
input sequence. And now, every time it
produces an output vector, we want to
give the network the opportunity to look
back at the entire input sequence. And
if we do this, there's going to be no
bottleneck. It will scale to much longer
sequences. And hopefully, the the model
architecture will work much better. So
that's the motivating idea that led to
attention and transformers and all this
great stuff that we see today. It all
came like you know one way of telling
the story is that it all came from
trying to solve this bottleneck problem
in recurrent neural networks. So let's
see um how we can actually implement
this intuition and endow our recurrent
neural network with the ability to look
back at the input sequence on every time
step. So here we're going to you know
start with the same thing. Um our
encoder neural network is going to
remain the same. No changes there. we
still need to set some initial hidden
state for the output sequence. Um and so
we need to set some initial um decoder
state s0 in some way. But now once we
have that decoder hidden state, what
we're going to do is look back at the
input sequence. So the way that we're
going to do that is by computing some
alignment scores by comparing that that
basically compute um a scalar value a
scalar value for each step in the input
sequence that says how much does that
initial decoder state s0 how much does
that decoder state match each token of
the input sequence. So in this case
there were four tokens in the input
sequence. So we want to compute four
alignment scores each of which is just a
single number um that says how how what
is the similarity between the input to
the the input sequence the token of the
input sequence and this initial um this
initial uh this initial decoder state as
zero. Now there's a there's a lot of
ways that we could implement alignment
scores but um a simple way is just use a
simple linear layer that we're calling f
subat. And so that linear layer is going
to input is going to concatenate the
decoder hidden state s um with one of
the encoder hidden states H concatenate
those two into a vector and then um
apply a linear transform that squashes
that down into a scaler. Um and that's
just a linear operator that can be put
into a computational graph and learned
jointly via gradient descent just in the
way that we learn all other parameters
of a network. Um so now at this point
we've got sort of this scalar alignment
score um for each se for each step in
the input sequence. And now we want to
apply a softmax function. Right? These
scaler alignment scores are totally
unbounded. They're arbitrary val they're
arbitrary real values from minus
infinity to infinity. We want to put
some um some structure on this to
prevent things from blowing up. So one
way that we do this is apply a softmax
function. So we've got four scalar
values um telling us the alignment of
that decoder hidden state which each
with each of the encoder hidden states.
Um now we apply a softmax over those
four values to give us a distribution
over those four over those four values.
So remember the softmax function that we
saw a few lectures ago is going to take
a vector of arbitrary scores and convert
it into a probability distribution which
means it'll have the property that each
entry in the output softmax
probabilities will be between 0 and one
and they will sum to one. So we can
think of so whenever we have whenever we
run a vector through a softmax we can
think of the thing we get out as a
probability distribution rather a
discrete probability distribution over
those input scores. So in this case, so
in this so at this point after we take
those alignment scores and run them
through a softmax, what we what we've
essentially done is predicted a
distribution over the input tokens um
given that decoder hidden state. So now
what we want to do is take that
distribution over over the input tokens
and use them to compute a vector um
summarizing the information in the
encoder. So the way that we do that is
we take our attention scores which
recall are these uh these numbers a a11
a12 a13 a14 they're all between 0 and 1.
They sum to one. We're going to take a
linear combination now of the encoder
hidden states h1 h2 h3 h4. Um and take a
linear combination of those encoder
hidden states weighted by our attention
scores. Um and this will give us a new a
context vector that we're calling c1
here in purple. um which is going to
summarize the information in the encoder
sequence um in in some way that's
modulated by that by those by those
attention weights. Um and now at this
point right so then this this C1 is
basically some linear combination of the
input encoder states H1 to H4 things
look basically the same as they did in
the non-attention case. So we we have
our context vector um we concatenate it
with our in with our first token of the
output sequence y0 pass that to our
recurrent unit um to get both to get um
to get our uh next hidden state of the
decoder recurrent neural network as well
as the first output token from the
decoder recurrent neural network. Um so
basically the structure of that decoder
RNN did not really change. Um all we did
is rather than set we've computed the
context vector in a different way using
this attention linear combination
mechanism.
But now crucially um right so the
intuition here is that this context
vector basically attends or looks at
different parts of the input sequence
that is modulated by whatever the output
RNN wants to look at at this moment in
time. Um so for example you know part of
the input you know as uh part of the
input sequence has this token these
these two words we see. So then in
trying to produce that one word in
Italian that corresponds to we see the
network probably wants to go back and
look at those two words in the input
sequence in order to know what output
word to produce. So we might expect we
we might want to have some we might
expect that intuitively when trying to
produce the word um vendo um then the
network will want to look back at the
words we see and put higher attention
weights on those and it doesn't really
care about the sky because those words
are not necessary for producing that
vendamo output. Um and that's the kind
of intuition we're giving the network
the ability to look back at the relevant
parts of the input sequence for the word
that it's trying to predict at this
moment in time.
Um and the other thing to keep in mind
is that this is all differentiable. Um
we don't need to supervise the network.
We don't need to tell it which words in
the input sequence were required for
each word in the output. Instead, this
is just a big computational graph
composed of differentiable operations.
Um this all of this will can be learned
end to end via gradient descent. So at
the end of the day, we're still going to
have this, you know, cross entropy
softmax loss where the network is trying
to predict the tokens of the output
sequence. And in the process of trying
to predict the right tokens in the
output sequence, it's going to learn for
itself how to attend to different parts
of the input sequence. So that's that's
really critical, right? If we have to go
in and supervise and tell the network
the alignment between the two, it would
be very difficult to get training data
for this kind of thing. The question is
how do we initialize the decoder? Uh
we're actually using the word you got to
be careful we're using the word
initialize a little bit overloaded here.
So one question is the decoder is itself
a neural network that has weights. When
we start training that network we need
to initialize those weights in some way.
So then we will typically initialize the
weights of the decoder randomly and then
optimize them via gradient descent just
as we do with any other neural network
weights. Um but there's a second notion
of initialize which is that when the
network is processing a sequence um
whether whatever its current value of
the weights are we need some way to set
that initial hidden state at the time we
start processing an output sequence. Um
and in that case we need some rule or
some some some way to set that initial
hidden state of the decoder output
sequence. Um there's a couple different
mechanisms for this. Um sometimes you
might initialize it as the hidden the
last hidden state of the encoder is one
thing you'll sometimes do. You might
have a linear transform that um projects
has some learned projection from the
last decoder state to the first from the
last encoder state to the first decoder
state. Um or sometimes will people even
initialize the first hidden state of the
decoder to be all zeros. Um any of those
will work as long as you train the
network to expect that kind of input. So
the question is negations and exors
would this cause a problem? Maybe this
is this is a this is a hard problem but
then you need a lot of data a lot of
flops to try to hope the network can
disentangle this. Um but basically
recurrent unit takes three things as
input. It take in the decoder right it
takes the previous hidden state the
previous decoder hidden state it takes
the current context vector and it takes
the current um token in the output
sequence and then from that we produce
the next hidden state and then from the
next hidden state then we go and predict
the output token. So that's actually the
same setup as in the non-attention case.
I guess there there's an implicit
connection from there's a there's a
connection from S0 to S1 that we're not
drawing. So there there should have been
another arrow from S0 to S1. I think I
just dropped the S0 arrow. So sorry
about that. Well, we're basically
letting the network decide for itself to
look back at any part of the in input
sequence that it thinks might be
relevant for the task at hand. Um so but
the reason why we think that this
mechanism is plausible and might be
helpful for the network is because we
know that you know in a language task
there often is some kind of
correspondence between words in the
output and words in the input and we
want to let the network kind of look
back and pick out which are the relevant
bits of the input for producing this bit
of the output. But again we're not
directly supervising it. We're not
telling it how to use these attention
scores. But the intuition is that we
think that's a plausible thing that it
might choose to do given this mechanism.
Okay. So that's that's sort of like one
tick of the output. Um, and now
basically we do it again. We do this
whole process again for every time we
tick the decoder RNN, right? Remember
the problem we were trying to solve is
that previously the decoder was
bottlenecking through a single vector.
Um, now we're going to compute instead
of bottlenecking through a single
vector, we're going to repeat this whole
process again and compute a new context
vector for the second time step of the
decoder and go let it go back and look
at the whole input sequence yet again.
So now um basically given our S1 which
is our computed first hit like hidden
state in the decoder we're going to go
back you take S1 go back and compute
comparison and and use our attention uh
mechanism to compute similarity scores
between S1 and all of the hidden states
in the encoder. Um that will compute our
similarity scores using that exact same
fat that same linear projection that we
used at the first time step. um compute
these alignment scores again, cram them
through softmax to get a a new
distribution over the input sequence for
the second decoder time step and now
compute a new linear combination of the
encoder hidden states now weighted by
this new distribution that we computed
at the second time step. Um and this sec
this this will basically give us a new
context vector um C2
that now is a different summarization of
the input sequence that's now computed
as a new linear combination of the input
encoder hidden states and then we then
the whole thing kind of iterates right
we have a new context vector we use that
to run another tick of our decoder RNN
unit that will now now does include that
that mysterious missing arrow that
wasn't there on the previous time step.
So then given our new context vector,
given the next token of the output
sequence and given the S1 hidden state
of the decoder, we compute a new decoder
state S2 and then from that compute
another token of the output sequence. Um
and again remember you know in this case
it's producing ill which maybe is the
according to the slide. I hope that's
true. Um, and then you know in this case
there's maybe a one to one
correspondence between the word the the
network is trying to produce for this
sequence and one of the words in the
output and one of the words in the
input. So we might expect that the
network should put relatively high
attention weight on just one of the
words in the input sequence and
relatively low attention weight on all
the other words in the input sequence.
But again, we don't supervise this. The
network is deciding for itself how to
make use of this mechanism all driven by
gradient descent on our training task.
Um, and this whole thing is going to
we're just going to repeat that whole
process for every tick of the decoder
RNN.
Um, so now this basically solves our
problem right there. We are no longer
bottlenecking the input sequence through
a single fixed length vector. Instead,
we have this new mechanism where at
every time step of the decoder, the
network looks back at the entire input
sequence, reummarizes the input sequence
um for the to generate a new context
vector on the fly for this one time step
of the decoder and then uses that to
produce the outputs. So this is a this
is a pretty cool mechanism and this is
called attention because the network is
attending or looking at different parts
of the input sequence um at every at
every moment in its output. So we talked
about these attention weights and we
said that they were driven that the
network was learning for itself how to
set these attention weights based on its
training data based on its training
task. Um and another really cool thing
about attention is it also gives us a
way to introspect and see what the
network is looking at as it's trying to
solve this problem. So we never told it
how the what what what what what the
what the alignment was between the input
sequence and the output sequence. But by
looking at the attention weights that
that the network predicts when trying to
solve this task, we get a sense of what
the network was looking at um while
trying to solve the problem. So that
gives us a way to interpret the
processing of the neural network in some
way. Um and so here's so one thing that
we can do is then go and look at in the
process of producing a particular of
processing a particular sequence what
were the attention weights that the
network predicted when trying to do this
task and we can visualize these in a
two-dimensional grid. So here we're
looking at an example of English to
French translation. Um and across the
and across the the top we have our input
sequence. The agreement on the European
economic area was signed in August 1992.
And then running down the rows is the
output sequence which is in French which
I will not attempt to pronounce. Um but
you can see that like basically through
this attention mechanism for every
remember the way this attention
mechanism worked is that each time the
network produced one of these words in
the output sequence it predicted a
probability distribution over the entire
input sequence. So we visualized that in
that first row. So if you look at the
first row of this matrix, we're
visualizing that predicted probability
distribution over the entire input
English sentence. And we see that when
trying to predict that first um word the
of the French sentence, then it puts a
lot of probability mass on the English
word 'the' and basically no probability
mass on any of the other words. Then
when predicting the second word of the
output sequence, remember it goes back
and predicts a new distribution over the
entire input sequence and that's going
to be the second row in this matrix. So
you can see that accord um I it puts a
lot of probability mass on agreement and
then no probability mass anywhere else.
So then that gives us some sense that
the network actually kind of did figure
out the alignment between the input
words and the output words when doing
this translation task. And there's some
interesting patterns here that here that
kind of pop up when we look when we see
diagonal structures in this attention
matrix. That means that there was a
onetoone correspondence between words in
order between the input sequence and the
output sequence. So in particular we see
that the agreement on the the first four
words of the input sequence correspond
to this diagonal structure um in the
attention matrix. So that means that the
network has decided for itself that
these first four words of the input
sequence sort of align or match up or
correspond to the first four words of
the input sequence. And the same thing
for the last um several words. So again,
we see this diagonal structure at the
end of the sequence, which means that
August 1992 or in August 1992 um
corresponds to these uh these last
couple words in the French sequence. And
again, there's this one:1 correspondence
between words in the output and words in
the input. But we see some other
interesting stuff in the middle here. So
in the middle, um we see European
economic area, but in the French, we see
words that look kind of like those in a
slightly different order. Good question.
How does it figure out the grammar?
That's the mystery of deep learning. But
like basically we told the we didn't
tell the network anything about grammar.
We told the network we supervised it
with a lot of input output pairs. We
told it here's an input sequence in
English. Here's an output sequence in
French. Here's a mechanism for
processing this and learn via gradient
descent to to like set the weights of
this architecture in order to in order
to produce this output from this input.
Um we'd never told it anything about
grammar. Um but it kind of because we as
human designers have this intuition that
maybe it makes sense that there ought to
be some correspondence between some of
the words. So we bake in a mechanism
that we think as human designers might
be helpful for solving this problem and
the network figures out for itself in
the process of doing the endto-end task
how to make use of that mechanism um to
solve the problem we set for it. And
it's pretty pretty amazing that it
works.
Um right but in this case you know it
kind of figured out some of the grammar
for itself. So it sees that you know we
see this nondagonal sort of backward
diagonal in the attention matrix here
and that means that the network figured
out for itself this um other this like
different word order between words in
English and words in French um or in the
middle you see there's a little there's
a little like 2x2 grid um kind of here
and that kind of corresponds to a
situation where there might not have
been a one to one correspondence between
the English words and the French words.
There might have been two French words
that corresponded to two English words
and they didn't perfectly disentangle
perfectly. I mean the network just all
figures out this for itself over the
process of training um on a lot of data
and putting a lot of compute through
this and that's pretty cool.
Okay, so there's actually uh so that
that's basic so and this actually was
the initial usage of attention in
machine learning. Um it actually came
from this from these machine translation
problems. Um so this was from a paper
back in uh back in 2015 uh neural
machine translation by joint by jointly
alerting to align and translate. Um, and
this paper actually just won the
runner-up test of time award at iclair
2025. Uh, so that's pretty cool. A nice
nice uh, you know, this has been a
really impactful paper over time. Um,
but it turns out that there's actually a
more general idea here and a more
general operator hiding here. You know,
we approach this problem from the
perspective of trying to fix our
recurrent neural networks. But it turns
out the mechanism that we used to fix
the recurrent neural networks actually
is something general and interesting and
really powerful in its own right. So now
we want to try to pull that out, pull
out this idea of attention and divorce
the idea of attention from the recurrent
neural networks. And it turns out that
attention will be a very useful and
powerful computational primitive for
neural networks in its own right. even
even if then we can cut away the
recurrent neural network part and just
be left with attention as the core
primitive in our architecture and that's
kind of where we're what we're going
towards. So now what we want to do is
take this this idea of attention as we
saw it in recurrent neural networks and
try to generalize it and try to carve
out this independent operator that can
be used on its own. So let's think about
what this attention mechanism was doing.
Basically what this attention mechanism
did is there were a bunch of query
vectors. These are Well, maybe maybe it
makes sense to talk about these in the
other order. So, there's data vectors
which are like data that we want to
summarize. These are the the the the
encoder states of the encoder RNN. So,
we have this input sequence and we've
summarized that into a sequence of
vectors. Um, and the sequence of vectors
is sort of data that we think is
relevant for the problem that we're
trying to solve. Um, and now in the
process of trying to make use of that
data, we want to produce a bunch of
outputs. And for each output, we have a
query vector. A query vector is a vector
that we're trying to use to solve an out
to to produce some piece of output. Um,
and in this case, the query vectors are
the hidden states of the decoder RNN.
Um, and we have this this property that
for each query vector, we want to go
back look at the data vectors and
summarize the information in the data
vectors into a context vector. Um, for
each well, okay, from the purpose of
from the purpose of attention, this gets
a little bit weird. So the output of the
attention operator are the context
vectors that we just talked about for
the RNN. So if we're talk if we're
thinking about just what does that
attention operator do? The output of the
attention operator were the context
vectors that we feed into the RNN. So
then what is the attention operator
doing? The attention operator is taking
a query vector going back to the input
data vectors summarizing the data
vectors in some new way to produce an
output vector. Um and that's what the
attention operator is doing. Is that
does that is that does that kind of make
sense as a generalization of this
attention mechanism that we just saw?
>> Yeah. Yeah. I I'll repeat it again
because it's it's tricky. There's a lot
of stuff flying around here. A lot of
boxes and we're changing the words that
we're using to define the the define the
boxes. So I get it. There's a lot
happening. Um so what the attention
operator is doing is there's a bunch of
data vectors which are the encoder
hidden states. Um then for then we have
a bunch of query vectors which are the p
the things we're trying to produce
output for. Now, in the process of
processing a query vector, we're going
to go back to the data vectors,
summarize the data vectors in a new
custom way for each query vector, and
that will produce um an output vector,
which is the context to be fed into the
next tick of the RNN. Right? So, our
query vectors are these guys in green.
For each query vector, we go back to the
data vectors, summarize the data
vectors, and then produce a new output
vector, which is one of the contexts
that we then feed into the the rest of
the network. So um you know this is kind
of tricky because we're trying to like
go into this architecture and like cut
carefully cut out the attention part and
cut it out from the RNN. Um so then
we're going to try to like walk through
this again from the perspective of just
the attention operator. So from the
perspective of just the attention
operator we're going to start with just
one query vector at first um which is
you know one of the one of the states in
our RNN. We also have a bunch of data
vectors which are the encoder hidden
states in the RNN. Now the computation
that we want to perform is first compute
similarities between that query vector
and all of the data vectors. This is the
exact same thing that we just saw just
sort of written in a different way. So
we use this fat function to compute
these similarity scores um from our to
to to compute similarities between each
data vector and our one query vector.
Then once we have those similarities,
we're going to squash them through
through a softmax to get attention
weights. And this will be a distribution
over the data vectors that has been
computed on the fly for this one query
vector.
Then we want to do is produce an output
vector. And out this output vector is a
linear combination of our data vectors
where those linear combination weights
are the attention scores that we just
computed. So this is the output of the
attention layer. And then in the context
of the larger RNN that we saw, the
output of the attention layer or the
attention operator will become an input
to the next tick of the decoder RNN. But
we're trying to deprecate the RNN. So we
don't want to talk about that. We just
want to talk about the attention and
focus on the computation happening
inside the attention layer. So like so
this is basically the operator that we
saw in the RNN, right? We had this one
like we we did this process over and
over again of taking a query vector
using it to compute similarity scores
getting attention weights getting an
output vector. Then we got a new query
vector. Where did that query vector come
from? Attention operator doesn't care.
Get a new query vector. Go back
summarize the data vectors get a new
output vector. Um and that's that's the
core of the attention operator. So now
let's try to generalize this and make it
a even more powerful computational
primitive. Yeah. So in principle this um
this fat doesn't have to be it could be
any function. It could be any function
of two vectors that outputs a scaler um
in principle but in practice we're
actually going to make it simpler in in
a couple slides. But in principle yeah
you could just slot in any any function
that you wanted there.
Okay. So the first generalization that
we're going to do is actually um the
opposite of what you just suggested and
make that similarity function simpler.
So we said in principle it can be any
function that takes two vectors and
gives a similarity score. What's the
simplest possible function that inputs
two vectors and gives us a scalar
similarity score? It's a dot product. So
we want to try to make things uh simpler
and also generalize at the same time.
And it turns out that a dot productduct
is is good enough of a similarity score
to be used for this purpose. So the
first thing we're going to do is um
actually just only use dot products to
compute similarity.
Um but it turns out there's a slight
problem with dotproducts. So and this
one's kind of subtle because there's a
weird interaction between the dot
product and the softmax. Um and that has
to do with what happens when the when
the dimension of those vectors scales up
or down. Right? So if you have a like
the motivating example is that if you
scale the dimension of that vector, say
we had a constant vector of all ones of
like dimension 10 versus a constant
vector of all ones of dimension 100,
then as we go to the to the higher
dimensional vector, then when we compute
the sum inside that softmax, then we're
going to be dividing by a larger number.
So we'll end up with more squashed
probability scores as we go to higher
dimensional vectors. Um that can lead to
vanishing gradients as we just saw in
the previous lecture. and prevent
learning of this whole thing. So as kind
of a slight hack to prevent that um and
make this architecture more generally
more generalizably scalable up and down
to different dimension vectors um what
we're going to do is actually not use
the pure dot productduct but scale the
dotproduct down by the square root of
the dimension of those vectors that
we're looking at. Um and this is just a
way to prevent vanishing gradients and
give nicer gradient flow through the
softmax for a wider range of dimensions
of vectors. Um, and this turns out to be
very important because as we make these
networks bigger and bigger and bigger
over time, we want to get higher
dimensional vectors because that gives
us more compute, more capacity. So we
always want to think about how our
architectures will scale as we make the
parts of those architectures get bigger
and bigger and bigger. So this um this
this scale dotproduct is actually really
important for preventing vanishing
gradients here. Yeah. Question was we're
limited to data and query vectors of the
same size, but we'll actually fix that.
So uh our first generalization was to
use actually scaled dotproduct
similarity as our as our similarity
measure. Um so now you know if we go
back and look at the shapes of these
things we have one query vector of
dimension dq. We have data vectors of
dimension nx by dq as well because it's
a dot productduct they need to match. Um
but there's actually a next generaliz
generalization that we're going to do is
have multiple query vectors right like
maybe we don't want to process just one
query vector at a time. We want to have
the ability to process a whole set of
query vectors all at once. Um, and this
kind of happens in the RNN. You know, we
did end up with a bunch of query
vectors. Um, and it's useful for the
attention operator to be able to process
not one query vector at a time, but
basically process a set of query vectors
all in parallel and perform the exact
same computation in parallel for a whole
set of query vectors. So in this case,
we've now generalized it to have n. So q
is now a matrix of shape nq by dq. So we
have n q query vectors. Each of those
query vectors has dimension dq. We have
our data vectors is a matrix of size nx
by dq. And now uh this now the the
computation changes a little bit because
now want when we compute these alignment
scores when we when we compute these
similarities basically we want to
compute all pairs of similarities
between all of the input data vectors
and all of the input query vectors. And
that sim and each one of those
similarities is a dotproduct. So well
scaled dotproduct. So what's a very
efficient and easy and natural way for
us to compute dotproducts between two
sets of input vectors? That turns out
exactly to be a matrix multiply, right?
Cuz remember when you do a matrix
multiply, each entry in the output
matrix is the inner product of one of
the columns of one of your matrices and
the rows of your other matrix. And
that's what uh so then each entry in the
output of a matrix multiply is exactly
the dotproduct between the rows and the
columns in the output. So this by
computing a matrix multiply between our
um query vectors Q and our data vectors
X and you need to get a transpose in
there to make the rows and columns match
up in the right way. Um this basically
gives us you know lets us compute all
the scale all the similarities between
all the data vectors and all the query
vectors um all in one simple matrix
multiply.
Um now we still need to compute these
attention weights. Remember the
attention weights we want to compute for
each query vector we want to compute a
distribution over the data vectors.
Well, we already have these. Now, our
similarity scores are not just a single
vector of scores. They're now a matrix
of scores giving all the similarities.
But we still want to compute a
distribution over the data vectors for
each query vector independently. So, now
we need to comput the softmax over just
one of the axes of that um of that
matrix of similarity scores. So, this is
basically the exact same computation
that we just saw. We're just doing it in
parallel for a set of query vectors all
at once. Um now, we need to compute the
output vectors. And remember the output
vectors were going to be a um weighted
combination of the in of the data
vectors where those weights are the
values in the softmax. And it turns out
that this is also something that matrix
multiply does. Um another way to think
about matrix multiply is that when you
take a matrix multiply of two matrices,
a different way to view a matrix
multiply is that it takes a linear
combination of oh man, am I going to get
the rows and the columns in the right
way? But I think you get the the linear
combination of the columns of one of
your input matrices um weighted by the
values in the other input matrix. So
this is another interpretation of matrix
multiplication. So then if you kind of
work through the indices and draw some
little pictures for yourself to to prove
to yourself what's going on. It also
turns out that you know in order to
compute me now what we want to do is
compute many linear combinations of the
data vectors where each linear
combination will be given by the
probabilities in one of the rows of the
attention matrix. Um so we can compute
all of these all at once with another
matrix multiply between um the attention
matrix A and the data vectors X. And
again you need to get the transposes in
the right order to make this work out.
But basically, this is the exact same
operation that we just saw, but we're
now doing it for a set of query vectors
all at once. And it turns out that we
can do it all at once with just a couple
matrix multiplies. There's a next way
that we'll generalize this is notice
that in this equation, the the data
vectors X are actually entering in two
different places in this computation. Um
the first place that we're using the
data vectors X is to compute
similarities with the query vectors in
this uh similarities computation. So in
that in that notion what we're trying to
do is say oh for hey data vector how
much do you line up with each query
vector as measured by an inner product
but then we're also using the data
vectors again to compute the output
vectors. So we're we're re we're the
output vectors are now a linear
combination of the data vectors weighted
by our attention weights. Um and it
maybe seems a little bit weird to reuse
the data vectors in those two different
contexts. So now what we want to do is
um separate those two usages of the data
vectors um and let the network sort of
figure out for itself two different ways
to use the data vectors in those two
contexts.
So to do that we'll introduce this idea
of keys and queries. So now what we're
going to do is you know we had a set of
data vectors but what we're going to do
is for each data vector we're going to
project each data vector into two
vectors. One is a key vector one is a
value vector. Um, and the idea of the
key vectors are the key vectors are
going to be compared with the query
vectors to compute the alignment scores
and the value vectors are what we're
going to compute linear combinations of
in order to compute the output from the
layer. Um, and this also by so then the
way that we implement this is we add two
learnable weight matrices, the key
matrix and the value matrix which are
going to be um linear projections that
project the input that project the data
vectors into key vectors and value
vectors. So now the data vectors are we
have remember we have n data vectors
each of dimension dx. So now the key
matrix projects is a is a linear
transformation that projects from dx
into dq right because we know that we're
going to compare the key vectors with
the query vectors. So they need to have
the same dimension as the query vectors.
Um so that will project each so then
applying matrix multiply of k= x wk will
project each data vector into a key
vector of dimension dq. Then we'll
separately have another weight matrix
that projects from dx to dv which is the
dimension of the value vectors which in
principle could be different than the
query vector dimension. Um and then
we'll separately project each each data
vector into a value vector again with a
matrix multiply operator here. Um and
the intuition here is that it's kind of
like in a search engine like you want to
separate what you're looking for from
the answer you want in response to that
query, right? So like you go to Google
or these days chatgpt and you type in
like what is the best school in the
world that's your query and then the
value you get that's the that's the
query that needs to be combined with the
keys in the back end but then the value
the data you want to get back from that
query is actually different from the
query you typed in right so we want to
separate this idea of like you put your
query in what is the best school in the
world that query needs to go match on
all the different strings in the on the
internet and then the value you want to
get back from that query is Stanford
which is a different value come which is
a different value which is different
from the query that you put in. So
that's kind of the intuition another
intuition between separating the keys
and the queries and the values in this
way. The query is what I'm looking for.
The key is you know in the back end we
have some record of all the data back
there in the data vectors but um when we
query we want to match up against part
of the potentially just part of the data
vector and then the thing we want to get
back from the data vector is the value.
So we're separating the usage of the
data vectors into those two different
notions of keys and values. Then we can
visualize this in a different way. So
now we're we're we're finally throwing
away the RNN and we're looking at
attention just as an operator on its
own. So we can step through this
operation again. We've got our query
vectors coming in. We've got our data
vectors coming in. Now what we're going
to do is from the data vectors, we're
going to project each data vector into a
key and a value. Um then we're going to
compare each key with each query to get
our um similarity scores. Right? So this
is a similarity. This is a matrix of
scalers giving the similarities between
each key and each query. Then once we
have this matrix of similarity scores,
we want to compute um a distribution
over each qu a distribution over the
data vectors for each query. So that
means we need to run softmax over this
uh matrix of alignment scores um or we
compute the softmax over each row. Then
what we do is we want to take rewe the
value vectors by the attention scores in
the softmax. Oh actually no sorry we
want each we want a each column to be we
want each column to be a distribution.
uh right because each we want for each
query a distribution over the keys which
means we want softmax over the columns
right because we want it to be aligned
to the columns. So then what we do is
you know we've got this query one we've
prod we've predicted this distribution
over all of the keys um from this
computation. Then we're going to take a
linear combination of the values
weighted by these attention weights and
comput a linear combination of the value
vectors to produce our first output
vector y1. And then the same thing
happens over here. Our second query got
compared with all the keys. We computed
a distribution over those alignment
scores to get a distribution over the
keys for the second query which then get
linearly combine. Then we use those to
linear linearly combine the values to
produce our output vector. So now this
is now the attention operator sort of
standing on its own um divorced from the
recurrent neural network. The question
is how do you divide the data vector
into keys and values? The beautiful part
is we don't have to say we don't have to
say how just as we just give the neural
network the capacity to split it by by
to split it by itself by giving it this
mechanism to project separately into
keys and values but just but we're not
going to tell it how to do it. Um these
are just going to be the the key matrix
and the value matrix are just going to
be learnable parameters of the model
that will be learned via gradient
descent along with everything else. So
just as we did not tell it how to align
the English and the French sentences all
of that was sort of learned via gradient
descent. the model will learn for itself
how to separately project into keys and
values in a way that's sensible for the
problem for that's helpful for the
problem it's trying to solve. So that
the keys and values you might think of
it as some kind of filter right so the
data vector might have a lot of stuff in
there but for the task at hand we might
want to filter the data vector in
various ways and only try to match our
queries against part of it and we only
care about retrieving information of a
different part of it. So you could think
of those as yeah filtering you know the
information in the data vector in two
different ways.
Okay, so this is this is basically our
attention operator. And now like there's
no RNN here. This is just a neural
network layer that you could have
standing on its own, right? It receives
two inputs, the query vectors and the
data vectors. It has two weights of
learnable parameters which are the key
matrix and the value matrix. Um it
inputs two two sets two sequences of
vectors, outputs a sequence of vectors.
So this is a neural network layer in its
own right that you could start to plug
into your neural network architectures
in various places. This is sometimes
called a cross attention layer because
it has two sets of inputs coming in,
right? The idea is we have both data
vectors and query vectors. They're
potentially coming from two different
sources. Um, and this is sometimes
useful, right? So that I have a set of
queries. For each query, I want to go
and summarize information from my data
which is potentially different or a
different number or totally different
from my query vectors. Um, so this is
this is sometimes called a cross
attention layer because we're
crossending between two different sets
of things.
Um, but there's another version of this
that happens maybe even more commonly is
a self attention layer. So here what
we're going to do is we only have one
set of things. We only have one sequence
of inputs. We we have one set of
vectors, one sequence of vectors that
we're processing. Um, and then so now we
we no longer have this separation
between data vectors and query vectors.
We just have one set of input vectors
that we would like to process. So in a
self attention layer um we're going to
have one we're going to have a set of
input vectors and we're going to produce
a set of output vectors. So we want to
input a set of vectors X output a set of
vectors Y that are the same number as
the input vectors. But now the mechanism
of this is basically the same attention
mechanism that we just saw. Um but now
rather than projecting but we then we're
still going to use this notion of
filtering but now rather than projecting
our data vectors into keys and queries
as we previously did. Now, what we're
going to do is take each one of our
input vectors and project it to three
different things. Um, from each of our
input vectors, we're going to project it
to a query, to a key, and to a value.
Um, and so the the the equations change
just a little bit. Um, and but the
picture over here doesn't actually
change very much for each of our input
vectors. We separately project it to a
query, to a key, and to a value. Um, and
now we have, you know, the exact same
computation. Now we've got queries,
we've got keys, we've got values. From
the perspective of everything happening
up here, it's all the same. It just h it
just so happened that we computed the
keys and the queries and the values all
from different linear projections of
those same input vectors, but all the
computation otherwise shared. Yeah.
Question is how do you where what are D
in and D out? How are they sized? Um so
these are going to be architectural
hyperparameters of the layer, right?
Like just when we have a learnable
linear layer in a model, a linear layer
basically projects from a Din to a D
out. Those are going to be architectural
hyperparameters of the layer. Um same
thing with a self attention layer. The D
in and the D out are going to be
architectural hyperparameters of the
layer. Um and in principle they could be
different, right? There's enough there's
enough flexibility in this architecture
so that in principle D in D in and D out
could be different. Although I don't
think I've almost ever seen that. In
practice they're like almost always the
same. So I've been like a little bit
extra general in the notation here.
Okay. So I I don't know that we
necessarily need to walk through this.
Oh actually there is one important
thing. Right. So I said that um we are
separately projecting the inputs into
queries, keys and values. Um so that
happens via three matrix multiplies with
our three learnable weight matrices. Now
we have three learnable weight matrices.
One for keys, one for values, one for
queries. Um and we separately project
the the input vectors X into keys,
queries and values. Um but in practice
um we can actually typically compute
just one matrix multiply all at once for
those because it's typically more
efficient on hardware to do fewer large
matrix multiplies than it is to do more
smaller matrix multiplies. So a pretty
common trick in practice is to fuse is
to sort of concatenate these three matri
matrices along the dimensions and
compute all of these keys queries and
values for all the input vectors all at
once with one big matrix multiply. If
you've read transformers before, they
sometimes separate between encoder and
decoder transformers or encoder decoder
attention. So in that case like this
does this is this would be the decoder
only attention. Um if you've read
transformer papers before um and which
corresponds to the decoder
of the RNN initial example at beginning
of class um but like this mechanism is
actually just the most gen is like the
most commonly used flavor of attention
nowadays is this sort of so-called
decoder only attention. So we are we are
quite divorcing ourselves away from the
RNN now. Right? So this flavor of it
doesn't really make sense to be used in
the RNN that we saw at the beginning of
class. Right? So we basically been like
doing a little bit of a slight of hand
here where we introduced this
architecture for the purpose of RNN in
this very concrete case of machine
translation sequence to sequence. But
we've now generalized it to become a
totally different operator that can be
used all on its own. And in this
particular generalization into self
attention, it actually no longer can be
used in that decoder in the RNN. Um but
it's a very useful primitive that gets
used in a lot of other places. It turns
out the question is what's the benefit
or difference between the self attention
versus the cross attention. Um they
would get used in different contexts. So
in a in some situations you naturally
have two dis different kinds of data
that you want to compare which we saw
for example in the machine translation
setting we have an input sentence we
have an output sentence. We believe that
there there's some natural structure in
the problem that there's two different
sets of things that we want to compare.
Um that also might happen in say image
captioning right say we have an input
image we want to produce an output
sentence there's two different kinds of
things we want to compare pieces of the
image and tokens in the words that we're
generating so for some problems there's
just this natural structure where you
have two different kinds of things
floating around but for other problems
there aren't two kinds of things there's
just one thing um so say you're doing
image classification then there's only
an image we just want to process the
image so in that case we just want to
compare parts of the image with itself
and that's where you use a self
attention layer So they just get used in
different for different kinds of
problems.
Um but we want to but crucially we want
to reuse basically the same machinery
and the same uh computational primitives
to you to be used in those different
kinds of problems and that's very that's
really beneficial. There's a couple
interesting things about attention that
I want to get through. So one is like
let's consider what happens if you
permit permute the inputs right we had a
set of input vectors. What happens if
you shuffle them and process them in a
different order? Now actually a lot of
interesting stuff happens. So the keys,
the queries, and the values will all end
up the same, right? Because they are
computed as linear projections of the
input. So we'll end up getting the same
keys, queries, and values. They'll just
be in a different order, shuffled in the
same way that the inputs were. Um, and
now because our similarity scores were
just dotproducts, we'll also end up with
the same similarity scores, just again
kind of shuffled in accordance with the
way we shuffled input. Um, same thing
with the softmax. Softmax doesn't
actually care about the order of its
inputs. So it's the softmax is now
operating on the same vector, but
shuffled. So um each column of our
attention weights will end up the same
as they did before just shuffled. And
then same thing with linear
combinations. So our output val our
outputs y will actually still be the
same outputs as we said before. They'll
just all be shuffled. So that that means
that there's a really interesting
structure here um called permutation
equariance. Remember we saw we we saw
this a couple lectures ago with with um
with with convolution. Now we see a
different equariance property of these
uh self attention layers which is that
if we shuffle the inputs then the
outputs we get the same outputs just
shuffled in the same way that the inputs
were shuffled. And this kind of means in
this case that self attention doesn't
actually care about the order of the
inputs. If we change the order of the
inputs we'll get the same outputs just
shuffled in the same way. That the
computation of the layer does not depend
on the order in which we present the
inputs. So that means that we can think
of self attention actually not as
operating on sequences of vectors. They
happen to be packed into into an ordered
sequence of a matrix. But we really
think of it instead as operating on an
unordered set of vectors because the the
the the the outputs that we get don't
actually depend on what order we've
packed those vectors into our input
matrix. So we really think about this as
a kind of different neural network
primitive that fundamentally operates on
sets of vectors rather than sequences of
vectors. But this is sometimes a
problem. Sometimes it is useful to tell
the neural network what the order of the
se what the order of the entries is. So
as a quick fix to that, we'll sometimes
concatenate an additional piece of data
onto each of the input vectors called a
positional embedding. That is basically
some some piece of data that tells the
neural network this one's at index one,
this one's at index two, this one's at
index 3, blah blah blah blah blah. And
there's a bunch of different mechanisms
for that. The question is, is it going
to train to the same result? Um the
training, I'm not really talking about
the training here. I'm talking about if
you fix the weight matrices and just
consider the computation of the layer
then if I were to shuffle the inputs
then I receive the same outputs but
they'll be shuffled in the same way that
the inputs were shuffled. So like the
the the the question of what vectors do
I compute at the output does not depend
on the on the on the vectors on the
order of the vectors in the input but
the order of the vectors I get from the
output does depend on the order that
they were presented in the input. So
there's another couple tricks we can do
with self attention, but I'll go through
these a little bit faster. Um, so
sometimes, you know, in in a full self
attention layer, we allowed every piece
of the input to look at every other
piece of the input. But for some
problems, we might want to impose some
structure on this computation and say
that certain pieces of the input are
only allowed to look at certain other
pieces of the input rather than looking
at rather than everything being allowed
to look at everything. And we can
implement this via a notion called
masked self attention. So what we're
going to do is after we compute these um
these alignment scores E, we're going to
go in and override the alignment scores
with negative infinities in places where
we want to block the attention. Um and
now if you have a negative infinity in
your alignment scores, then after you do
a softmax, it's going to end up as a
zero if you walk through the softmax
computation. Um so that means that if
there's a zero if there's whenever
there's a negative infinity in the
alignment scores we end up with a zero
in the softmax in in the scores after
the softmax which means that that output
y will not depend on the value vector
computed at that index. So this is a
mechanism to let us control which inputs
are allowed to interact with each other
in the process of the computation. Um
and we might want to do this now for
language modeling right because now
we've generalized this operator to the
point where we don't need an RNN at all.
We can just use this in the for the same
problem that we used to use an RNN for.
So now we can use it to process sequence
of words like attention is very and then
output is very cool. So then in this
case we're doing the same language
modeling task that we saw last lecture
with RNN's but we can now do just do it
natively with this self attention block.
But in this case we want to make the
first output is only depend on the first
word. The second output vary only
allowed to look depend on the first two
words. We don't want to let that let the
network look ahead in the sequence and
cheat. So here is where we would use
masking.
Um another thing that we'll sometimes do
with self attention is called
multi-headed self attention where you
run n copies like h separate independent
copies of self attention in parallel.
Why do you want to do this? Because it's
more computation, it's more flops, it's
more parameters. Deep learning we always
want more and bigger. Um and this is
another way that you can make this
network that make this this layer more
and bigger and more powerful. So what
we're going to do is take our inputs X,
route them to H independent copies of
separate self attention layers. Those
will each produce their own outputs Y
which will then stack up um along the
output and then fuse the and then have
another linear projection at the output
to kind of fuse the output data from
each of the independent self attention
layers. Um and now in this case uh this
is called multi-headed self attention.
Um and this is basically the format that
we always see in practice. So this is
like whenever you see self- attention
used these days, it's almost always this
multi-headed self- attention version.
Um, and in practice, um, it turns out
that you can compute this all with
matrix multiplies as well. So you don't
have to like run a for loop. Um, you can
compute each of these H copies of self
attention all in parallel if you're
clever and use batched matrix multiplies
all in the right places. Um, so in in in
fact this whole self attention operator
seems like a lot of stuff going on, but
it's really basically just four matrix
multiplies. We have one matrix multiply
where we take our inputs and project
them to queries, keys, and values. Um,
we have another matrix multiply where we
compute Qase similarity. For each Q, we
compute the similarity against all the
all the K's. And that's one big batched
matrix multiply. Now in the multi-headed
case um we have another one called
V-weing where we want to take linear
combinations of all the values weighted
by the softmax entries and that can be
done in another big batched matrix
multiply and then finally we have an
output projection to mix information
across our different self our different
heads of our self attention. So even
though there's a lot of equations
there's a lot of vectors flying around
this whole self attention operator is
basically just four big batched matrix
multiplies. Um, and that's great because
matrix multipliers are a really
scalable, powerful primitive that we can
distribute, we can optimize um, and we
can make this thing highly parallel,
highly parallel, highly scalable, highly
uh, highly efficient. Yeah. Question is
that the x1, x2, x3, they're exactly the
same. Um, but just but um, yeah, but
we're just going to like have separate
cop like basically separate copies of
the self attention layer. They're all
they will all be random. They all have
different weights critically and those
weights will be initialized randomly
different at initialization. So they
will end up learning to process them in
slightly different ways. So this is just
a way to give extra capacity to the
layer. Oh yeah, the only thing different
between the different heads is the
weights. So we'll the architecture is
exactly the same. The computation is
exactly the same, but they'll have
different weights and those weights will
be diff will be initialized to different
things at initialization. Um but other
than that it's all exactly the same.
Okay, there's some stuff there that we
can skip. But now basically we've gotten
to one really interesting place where we
have basically three different ways to
process sequences that we've seen in
this class. The first is recurrent
neural networks. We saw that recurrent
neural networks basically operate on 1D
ordered sequences. Um and they're
they're really cool. They're really
powerful. People like them for a long
time, but they're fundamentally not very
parallelizable because of this
concurrent structure where each hidden
state depends on the previous hidden
state. Then they're just a fundamentally
sequential algorithm. there's no way to
parallelize this across the sequence.
Um, and that makes them very difficult
to scale, very difficult to make very
big. Um, another primitive that we've
seen is convolution. And convolution
basically operates on multi-dimensional
grids. Um, we've seen it in
two-dimensional grids in the case of
images. You can also run them on 1D
grids, 3D grids, 4D grids. And
convolution basically is something that
mixes information locally in
n-dimensional grids. Um, this is great.
is very parallelizable because by this
notion of sliding a kernel around a
grid, each position that we might want
to place the kernel can in principle be
computed in parallel. So this is a very
parallelizable primitive. Um but um it
has a hard time building up large
receptive fields. If we want to if we
want to summarize an entire very long
input sequence or an entire very large
image with convolution, we either need
to have very large convolutional kernels
or stack up many many many convolutional
layers. So that still introduces some
fundamental sequentiality in the way
that we need to process large pieces of
data. And now self attention basically
is a separate kind of primitive that
operates on sets of vectors. Um it sort
of naturally generalizes to long
sequences. There are no bottlenecks in
the way that there are in in in
recurrent neural networks. There's also
no necessity of stacking up many many
layers of them to pro to to let all the
vectors look at each other. In one layer
of self attention, every vector looks at
every other vector. So with just one
layer you can summarize you can do a lot
of computation um and it's also highly
paralyzable as we saw the whole
operation is just four big matrix
multiplies and matrix multiplies are a
great primitive that we can distribute
we can run on GPUs we can run in very
scalable distributed ways um the only
downside of attention is that it's
expensive it ends up having n squ
compute for a sequence of length n um
and n squ or later n o n memory for a
sequence of of of length n and if your n
ends up being like 100,000 million 10
million n squared becomes very expensive
but you can solve that by buying more
GPUs. Um so that's that's basically the
solution that people have have come up
with here. So basically attention has
become this super awesome primitive that
is super powerful for processing very
arbitrary pieces of data and you might
be wondering which of these you should
use. Attention attention is all you
need. It turns out that of the three you
can get a long way using only attention.
Yeah the question is is paralyzable.
What's the advantage of that? Um the
advantage of that is that in the history
of computing um it it get it gets hard
to make processors faster, right? We've
sort of run up against this limit as a
fundamental limit in hardware that it's
become very difficult to make individual
processes faster. But what we can do
very easily is get a lot of processors,
right? So we so the way that we've able
to marshall more computation over the
last two decades is finding algorithms
that do not require running on one
really fast processor. But instead if we
can have an algorithm that can make use
of 10 processors or a 100 processors or
a thousand processors or a million
processors. I want to blanket the entire
Stanford campus with processors and have
all of them working together in concert
to process this big thing. If we can
find algorithms that do that, that's how
we can scale up and get really big
powerful computations. Um, so the
benefit of parallelizability is that if
you have algorithms that can trivially
make use of more and more and more
processors in parallel, then we can
scale up those algorithms without having
to wait for individual processors to
become faster, which they may never
will. Yeah. Is there a trade-off with
the n squ? I I think the n squed is
actually a good thing. Um, so it it see
it seems bad. You're taught in computer
science that higher parameters inside
that n that that those is bad. But in
the case of neural networks for compute
it could actually be a good thing
because more compute means the network
is doing more computation. It has more
ability to think more ability to
process. So actually the more compute
the network does on the input sequence
actually maybe the better answer it
could get it could arrive to. So it
means that you know it's more expensive
but that's not necessarily a bad thing.
So basically the transformer is now a
neural network architecture that puts
self attention at the core of
everything. So our input is going to be
a set of vectors X. Um then we're going
to run all those vectors through self
attention. Um which is as we just said
this amazing primitive that lets all the
vectors talk to each other. Um after
that we'll wrap that self attention in a
residual connection for all the same
reasons that we wanted to use residual
connections in ResNets just a couple
lectures ago. Um then we will take the
output of that residual connection pass
it through a layer normalization because
as we saw in ResNets and in CNN's adding
normalization inside your architectures
makes them train more stably. Um then um
but then now there's something
interesting because the self attention
basically what it does is compares all
the vectors with each other. Um and
that's a very useful primitive that's a
very powerful thing to do. But we also
want to give this network the ability to
perform processing on vectors
independently one one by one. So then
there's a second primitive inside the
transformer which is the multi-layer
perceptron MLP or also called FFN. But
basically this is a little two-layer
neural network that operates independent
that is run independently on each one of
our vectors inside. So then this kind of
works in concert with the self attention
where self attention lets all the
vectors talk to each other and compare
with each other and the FFN or MLP um
lets us perform computation on each
vector independently.
Um we'll also wrap the MLP in a residual
connection put a layer normalization and
put a box around the whole thing and
call it a neural network block. So this
is our um transformer block and a
transformer is just a sequence of
transformer blocks. Um and these things
have gotten much much bigger over time.
Um the architectures haven't changed too
much since 2017 when this is introduced.
Um the original transformer was
something like 12 blocks, 200 million
parameters. And now we're people are
training transformers with up with
hundreds of blocks and trillions of
parameters. So this same architecture
has scaled across many orders of
magnitude in compute and size and
parameters over the past eight years. Um
they can be used both for language
modeling as we sort of already seen. Um
they also can be used for for for for
images. And here the application is
fairly straightforward. Given an image
we basically divide the image up into
patches project each of those patches
separately into a vector. Those vectors
then get passed as inputs to our
transformer. um and then the output
gives us one output from the transformer
for every patch in the input. Now if you
want to do something like a
classification score uh do a
classification problem then you do a
pooling operation on all the vectors
coming out of the transformer and have a
linear layer that predicts your class
scores. So that's then this same
architecture of a transformer can be
applied both to a language and to images
and to a lot of other things as well.
Um, I mentioned there have been a couple
minor tweaks to transformers since they
were first introduced, but we're running
out of time, so I'll just leave those as
extra reading. So, kind of the summary
of where we get to at the end of this
lecture is basically two things that I
promised at the beginning. One is that
we introduced attention, which is this
new primitive that lets us operate on
sets of vectors. It's highly
paralyzable. It's basically just a
couple matrix multiplies. So, it's
highly scalable, highly paralyzable,
highly flexible. It can be applied in a
lot of different situations. Um and the
transformer which is now a neural
network architecture that uses self
attention as its main computational
primitive. Um and the transformer is
basically the neural network
architecture that every every
application in deep learning is using
these days. So that's super powerful,
super interesting, super exciting. Um
they've been transformers have been with
us for like 8 years now and I don't see
them really dying anytime soon. So
that's that's pretty pretty exciting. So
that's that's basically it for today's
lecture. Um and then next time we'll
come back and talk about some new tasks
uh detection, segmentation,
visualization and see how we can use
these architectures to do new cool
things.