Okay. So from the last lecture we
started to discuss some kind of the new
model which is the flow model. uh and
after we started to discuss the flow
matching the thing is that uh it's quite
confusing in terms of the now we are so
you know changing many things in our
basically the uh the terminology and
also the notations but the thing is that
basically in the diffusion model the
context we defined the time range from
the going from the capital t to the all
the way to the zero in the generated
process so that's why we call this kind
of the uh the generation process in the
diffusion model as kind of the reverse
process right uh but in the flow
matching the context we are now changing
the time domain in terms of that the
time goes from the zero to one in the
generative process so when you say like
the x0 that was basically the sample
from the reference the base distribution
and the x1 was basically the sample from
the data distribution right so we are
having this kind of the the time the the
changes
and the also in the context of flow
matching we are discussing basically
three key things like one is the flow
map and also the vector field and the
probability path right and we also
discussed how these are basically
related each other. Basically the vector
field could be computed as kind of the
der the derivatives of the flow map and
also the relationship between the vector
field and the probability path could be
defined uh based on the the focal plank
equation which was basically defined in
this way.
Uh so from this what we could see is
that uh we could consider basically
encoding the information of the flow uh
by training a neuronet network which is
basically implicitly representing the
flow map basically by modeling the
vector field. Then we could basically
see such kind of the neuronet network
which is kind of similar with the noise
prediction the network in the division
model case right. uh so terms of that
now we are having the network that can
predict the velocity for the arbitrary
dxt the intermediate data point and also
the time t there as well the thing is
that uh obviously we don't have any kind
of the closed form expression for the
target the vector field here so that's
why we started to discuss the
conditional the flow matching
so in this context we also discussed
these three things the conditional flow
map and the conditional vector field
built and also the conditional depth,
right? And we and also have seen some
kind of the some special case where the
conditional flow map is defined as some
kind of the linear function with respect
to the x0 here. Uh so given that the
conditional flow map is is defined as
kind of the linear function like this
and when we also assume that this x0 is
basically a sample from the standard the
gausian distribution then we could also
see that the the condition of the
probability path is also defined as kind
of gausian distribution like this and by
taking the derivative of the flow map
you could also compute the vector fields
like this right so this was like one
specific the way of like defining the
conditional alternative flow map and we
also can further specify those kind of
the the two parametric functions right
the sigma function and the mu function
here.
So like one special case uh that we have
seen last time is that basically
simplifying everything in terms of that
we are even making the flow map as kind
of the interpolation
between the linear interpolation between
the x0 and the x1 then everything
becomes like simple like this in a way
that we have the gausian the probability
pass and the linear flow map and also
the vector field. So we can say that
here the the velocity is really defined
as kind of this some the direction along
the straight line between the x2 and the
x1. Right?
And the other option is basically that
we are following the the trajectory of
the diffusion models the the bp the case
in terms of that define the probability
pass as like this then the vector field
was also defined like this from the
relationship between these two.
So given this kind of the two ways uh or
basically this is kind of like more
general form to define the deflow map
and based on that uh we could basically
train uh the the uh the the the neural
network predicting the velocity uh like
this. So this was like quite uh similar
uh with the training of the diffusion
models and this is actually the case
like when you have some kind of the
closed form for the conditional
probability path. Uh so for the more the
general case uh even when the the
analytic form of the the conditional dep
path is not available we can still
consider training the the flow map like
this. So here basically what you can see
is that the small difference is that
instead of like not only just like just
like sampling the x1 here we are
sampling both the x1 and the x0 the
pairs of like these two. uh and based on
that uh we compute the intermediate data
point XT uh using the conditional the
flow map and also compute the velocity
and also based on that we could consider
basically uh training the the velocity
prediction the the the new network uh
using the the L2 loss like this. So this
also becomes some kind of the more
general form of training a the flow map.
any questions on this?
So as we have seen uh last time uh what
we are going to discuss for today
briefly uh is about more like how this
kind of the flow map is basically
related uh to the diffusion the
diffusion models. So actually what we
are going to see for today is that
actually we can consider the the flow
model is kind of the same uh with the
diffusion model more precisely actually
the flow model is kind of the
generalization of the diffusion models.
So in the other the way around basically
diffusion model can be seen as kind of
some specific the special case of the
flow models. So uh the fusion model was
the case that we are basically learning
this core function right and the flow
map is now the case that we are learning
the fl the velocity basically the the
vector field so it's basically matter of
like know which one we see as kind of
the major def factor defining the the
models the diffusion model case we
basically first the modeled the
probability path and based on that we
define the other things basically the
the trajectory and also the velocity as
well in The flow model case we first
define some kind of the we first model
the conditional the uh the flow map and
based on that we can also derive some
kind of the conditional the vector field
and also the the property path as well.
So this is basically uh different kind
of the perspective uh to define some
kind of vision models. But actually we
can see that these two are basically
having some kind of a close relationship
each other which means that like one can
be computed from the other. So which
means that even when you have some kind
of the pre-trained diffusion model uh
from the pre-trained model we can
actually compute the velocity and treat
the pre-trained the diffusion model is
kind of the flow model and perform the
generation the process as well. Uh so
this is kind of the interesting aspects.
So
uh if we also see the varian diffusion
models from the perspective of the flow
matching but actually then we can say
that it's kind of a special case that we
are having a linear the gausian the
condition flow map which is defined like
this. So here the thing is that now uh
so sorry for the confusion with the many
of the new notations but this the sigma
and the alpha function those sigma the
alpha function these two functions are
basically the same functions that we
have seen uh in the definition of the
variational division models uh before
the first test okay don't don't get
confused so these are basically the the
functions that we have used uh when we
define the variational diffusion models
so in the previous lecture Actually we
the positions of like these two
functions kind of the switch it like
this alpha and the sigma here but now we
have the sigma and the alpha and the
reason for that is that now we are also
changing the the time domain right so
here basically uh it can be confused but
x is zero here is the the sample from
the reference distribution and the x1 is
basically sample from the uh the data
distribution. Okay. So after basically
changing the the time range now we are
having this the same the sigma and the
alpha functions here right the same
definition of the version diffusion
models.
So so we are going to basically see the
vary diffusion models from the
perspective of the flow de matching. Uh
and before we get to that let's briefly
recall some kind of the old topics. Do
you remember this the twist sponger? Uh
this is basically exactly the same slide
I've shown in the lecture five I guess.
So when you have some kind of the
unknown the prior distribution and the
gausian the likelihood distribution like
this and the when the marginal
distribution is basically defined like
this. uh the 2D formula is about
basically computing the expected value
of the mu here uh which is the sample
from the private distribution uh given a
sample from the marginal distribution.
So basically here this is the case that
we are have some kind of sample of the x
uh which is actually defined as like
which distribution is defined like this
as kind of the combination of the gaus
and the likelihood and also the unknown
the prior distribution. So given the
sample dx what would be kind of the
expected value of the mu which was
basically the sample from the prior
distribution. Uh and what we have seen
from the 2D formula was that this is
exactly the same slide that we have seen
in the lecture five. Uh so actually the
expected value of the mu given the x
could be computed uh based on this core
function right uh using this core
function like this. So this was
basically the first time we start to see
this core function. So if we have some
kind of quiz here.
So now know we are basically having this
kind of the uh linear function linear
interment of the x0 and the x1 given
these two functions which is now
computing x here right. So given the x
there
uh what would be kind of the expected
value of the x1 here. Basically the
thing is that X0 is basically a sample
from the standard Gaussian distribution.
Right? This is basically the known fact
from the fact that the X0 is basically
the sample from the standard Gaus and
the uh distribution given the X from the
intermediate the data point. Uh what do
we basically expected value for the X1?
Uh can you quickly compute this?
So did everyone get this?
This is kind of the same as like what we
have seen uh in the previous lecture,
right? Uh we only basically use the uh
the only difference is that we are now
using this like alpha and the sigma
functions uh that we used to to define
the uh the the variation models. Uh so
I'm going to basically update the
lecture slide uh including all the
answer after the lecture so you can just
like download again. Uh so yeah so thing
is that this is basically exactly the
same thing uh from the diffusion model
we could see that you know we can
compute before we perform like all the
generation the process we could
basically compute the expected value of
the final output from the intermediate
value right exactly the same thing we
are just like introducing the alpine the
sigma functions defining the diffusion
models and changing the time domain uh
that it goes from the zero to one in the
the generation the process
Then then we get this right. So this is
the part that we basically introduced
this score function here
and also we have seen the basically the
relationship between the noise that we
are predicting using the uh the noise
potential network and also the score
come here having this kind of a
relationship between the so this is
basically the the the quantity that we
are predicting using the neural network
right and from that we could also
compute the score here right so these
are all the same thing as like we
discussed last time but we just using
the sigma and the party functions and
also the change the change to the time
domain. So please keep this in mind uh
the same thing basically computing the
x1 the final the output expected value
of the final the output from the
intermediate value based on these two
things.
So based on this fact what we are going
to do is that now we are going to see
some the connection uh between the
velocity uh basically the vector field
and also this core function. Uh so
basically we can see this connection
between we we can at least like see that
there will be some connection between
these two because we have seen this kind
of the relationship between the vector
field and also the the probably path
from the the focal point of the
equation. Right? So we are basically
going to see the same thing uh without
that. Uh so basically the thing is that
uh from the hourly definition of the
linear the gausian the pass uh the the
the conditional deploy map here now we
can compute the conditional the the
vector field in this way it's just
taking the derivative right so we want
to also this is basically the function
of the x1 and also the intermediate
point of the x right so al so to make
this expression as kind of the function
of the x and the x1 one we are going to
replace the x0
based on this fact that the x0 can be
computed like this right so from our
definition of the condition for map now
we can basically substitute the x0 uh
with basically this expression then now
we can see that the velocity uh the
conditional velocity computed in this
way
is clear uh so this is basically just
like some you know asatic kind of
things, right? And based on this uh what
we are going to do is that now the
margin of the vector field uh this the
UT here. Uh so this is vector vector
field that we are going to obtain uh
through the the neuronet training right
and this can be computed as the
expectation of the conditional vector
field uh over this probability pass
right then this becomes basically
computing this uh but having the
expected value of the x one from the the
given the x the intermediate data point
see then from the twist the formula that
we have seen in the previous slide
We can simply plug in uh these twist
formula here. Then what we can see is
that now we can see the connection
between the uh the velocity and this
curve function here.
So given any kind of the intermediate
data point the x here uh for any kind of
the time t the intermediate data point
uh if you basically have the information
of the core function based on that you
can compute the velocity here right
or the other way around given any kind
of the data point x here if you have the
the velocity here then based on that you
can compute this curve function.
So this means that uh for the linear the
gausian the pass for the continually the
the flow map uh whether you make it the
generic model as kind of the flow the
the model or basically as the diffusion
model you can basically do some
interchange between these two you can
compute one from the other uh given any
kind of the the times the the inter data
point of the x here
make sense
so if we move one more step here. Uh so
we have seen that there's the
relationship between the score function
and the noise the we are predicting the
diffusion models right so based on this
relationship can you also find
relationship between the vector field
and also the uh the noise term as well
you can quickly compute this way
uh can you quickly compute this the
relationship between these
So basically we're going to get this
right. Uh so this basically shows the
relationship between the noise that we
are predicting uh in the diffusion
models and also the velocity that we are
predicting in the flow models. Right?
So from all those like deformulations
basically now you can see so what we
have discussed in this class is that uh
at the very beginning of this class uh
we started uh to discuss the degenerate
model which is defined as kind of the
mapping from some kind of the simple
distribution typically the standard
region distribution to the distribution
right so this was like all about
basically how we are going to define the
mapping
between the standard gausian
distribution to the data distribution.
So at the very beginning uh we started
with the g and debris and after that uh
we make that the mapping is kind of the
iterative process uh through the food
process right for the diffusion process
which is basically uh repeatedly adding
some kind of the gausian the noise in a
way that ends up basically becoming the
sample of the gausian. So this was more
basically define some kind of the
conditional the property path from the
all the way from the data the the sample
to the standard the the gaus and the
sample
and in the continuous time domain uh we
start to see that actually this kind of
the iterative process is kind of like
equivalent with the stoastic basically
solving the stoastic differential
equation. So we could basically find the
equivalent the continuous form the the
formulation in the continuous time
domain which is now defined as the
stoastic differential equation and after
that what we have seen is that actually
we can find and al the corresponding the
uh the OD ordinary differential equation
without stoicity uh which is giving the
the same the marginal distribution. So
for all the division model now we can
basically find the corresponding
deterministic the mapping process uh
through the OD the the uh the equation
and now what we are seeing is that uh
actually we didn't need to first define
the conditional dep we can directly
define the conditional the flow map
first uh in a way that we are seeing now
the diffusion model is kind of the some
special case of those kind of the flow
models. So we can see now this kind of
the connection and also the all the
different perspectives of like seeing
the diffusion models and the flow
models.
Not sure whether this will be clear to
you. uh so and also one more thing is
that uh for the PF OD the part flow OD
we didn't see how exactly this can be
derived uh from the SD formulation right
uh so without getting into the all the
details for that and it's like we are
going to see now how this connection
between the
uh the velocity and also the score
function here uh this connection between
these two is also aligned uh with the
pod D.
So what we can easily see uh is that so
this is basically the vector field that
can be computed from the score function
here right. So this is the equation that
we obtained from the previously the
slide
and given that uh if we go back to the
pod. So the this was basically the pod
de formulation we have seen for the
diffusion model case right and also the
connection between the the relationship
between the alpha sigma function and the
f and the g functions here could be
derived in this way.
So what we can see is that if we plug in
those kind of the some of the
definitions for the f and the g
functions into this equation uh we could
see that we we should see the same
equation with this right. So I recommend
you to check this out uh whether we can
really uh know get the same d equation.
So if you really put all the things the
f and the g functions into uh this part
uh then you want to see that actually we
are getting the same the equation the
same equation showing the relationship
between the vector field and the the
square function.
So the derivation of the the the the
vector field the velocity obtained from
the condition of the vector field and
also from the probability the flow the
od are basically identical.
So basically from this we can see some
kind of all the connections between the
dep models and the flow models and how
these alo related how the the
conditional dep is also related to the
conditional the flow map and also the
vector field as well.
Okay.
So so this is kind of key thing. So
basically the the diffusion models and
the flow models are mathematically
related in a way that if we define the
continuity flow map as kind of linear
the gausian path like this uh in the
form that we have seen in the basian
diffusion models then these two
basically become equivalent uh in the
mathematical deform. The only difference
is that whether we're going to basically
train in your network for the noise or
training the network for the velocity.
Uh but obviously once you train
basically learn one of these two things
based on the noise you can also comput
the velocity and the velocity you can
also compute the noise. So I strongly
recommend you to try this kind of the
conversion uh for the models that you
already implemented uh in the first
assignment. So what you'll need to do in
the third assignment is that the first
assignment was to implement the DDPM and
the DDIM right and also we I I told you
that you could basically and also the
second assignment was basically uh
running the generation the process uh by
solving the OD right using the DPM to
the idea uh now you can basically also
perform the generation the process uh by
switching the noise into the velocity
and perform the OD so it will be
basically equivalent the same as you
have done in the the second of the
assignment and what you'll need to do in
the third assignment is that now even
you are not uh learning the noise
directly learning the velocity and then
based on that you just perform the OD in
the generating the process. So we are
seeing some kind of some old variations
of like in terms of how you know the way
that we can basically train either the
fusion and the flow models and also
perform the generation the process of
the diffus and the flow models
make sense.
uh but this is the thing uh the flow uh
basically these two becomes basically
become the identical when you basically
define the condition the flow map as
kind of this kind of the linear the the
gausian the path uh but the flow map is
kind of the more you can think it's kind
of more the general concept in terms of
that it can basically generalize the
diffusion models in multiple ways the
first thing is that uh the conditional
flow map uh does not need to the that
the linear form. So you can also explore
uh many different options. Uh you can
design your own the conditional flow map
in many different ways and see whether
this can really improve the performance.
Uh also we have some kind of registance
like just playing with some kind of the
nonlinear kind of things like some cod
whatever sort of things and see whether
this can really improve. Uh I guess the
answer was no but yeah you can try many
different op for the condition flow maps
and more importantly uh for the flow the
matching the thing is that uh if we go
into the more the arbitrary the the the
concive flow maps then now we can
consider the case making the reference
distribution
uh as not as kind of the standard
gausian but any arbitrary distribution.
So the good thing of the flow of the
matching is that uh now we can consider
basically mapping two different
distribution
even we can consider learning some kind
of the mapping from like the one data
distribution to the another the data
distribution this is even possible uh in
the the the concept of the the flow
models. So you can think that the flow
model in also the flow model is the case
that we are now using the OD while the
diffusion model has been introduced from
based on the some stoastic
deformulation. So you can see some kind
of the differences and on how the flow
models basically generalize the idea of
the the diffusion models.
Any questions on this?
So I don't know how you would feel it
but actually this is kind of the most
interesting part in this quest. I mean
how all those things are basically
connected each other and how the same
thing can be basically explained in the
all the multiple ways. uh so I recommend
you to check out some more details uh
for those kind of connections
and actually one more reason like why we
uh discuss the flow model is that uh
basically we're going to see that many
recent models are now using the flow
matching uh not the diffusion models and
the one of the reasons for that is that
uh it becomes much easier in terms of
like accelerating the generation the
process through the finetuning. So last
time we have seen the idea for the
consistency model uh which alo kind of
some simple idea in terms like
accelerating the generation the process
uh through the fine tuning. So here
basically we going to discuss the same
thing basically how we can accelerate
the generation the process uh with some
kind of fine tuning.
So for that uh so the thing is that this
is like very new topic. So still people
are using some kind of the mixed the
terminology for the same thing. Uh so to
simplify all the things uh from now
we're going to uh say the conditionally
the flow matching the model is like
simply just like flow model and we also
have seen the two options for the
trajectory right the linear the
conditional trajectory and also the the
diffusion the trajectory. So for the
linear the conditional the trajectory we
are people typically also call this the
term the rectified the flow model. Okay.
So let's assume that we are basically
targeting this kind of rectified flow
model
and for the any flow model the the
training procedure becomes like this. So
this is the same slide that know for the
the general case what we can do is that
we sample the x1 the data point and the
sample from the standard gausian can be
does not need to be standard gausian
distribution it can be any reference
distribution. So based on these two uh
what we can do is that we are computing
the intermediate data point XT uh using
the predefined the conditional flow map
and and also computing the velocity by
just taking the derivative tip and
basically performing computing the L2
loss to train the velocity the neural
network.
So what we can see is that uh in the
training of the flow model uh this
sampling process is basically involved.
we are taking any random pair of the x0
and the x1 the the data point and also
the standard decian the sample. The
thing is that uh even when you basically
train a rectified model which is
basically having the conditioner the
linear trajectory uh the final the
output trajectory may not be linear.
So let me first uh show this slide uh
here. So what you can see is that uh so
these are all the kind of a conditional
the trajectory for any arbitrary sample
from here to here and here to here. So
this is the case that we are taking uh
this as kind of the the two gausian as
kind of source distribution and also the
two red uh the the dots here uh the
groups of the red dots as kind of the
the target distribution.
So if we see the conditional velocity at
this point depending on which pair you
choose the conditional velocity can be
either this or this right can go up and
can go down right.
So which means that if we compute the
expected uh the the uh the the value
here basically if we compute the margin
of the velocity at this point uh the
marginal velocity may not be either this
way or the this way it can be like go
this way for example.
So which means that even when you
basically make the conditional
trajectory to be linear the straight
line between the these two points if we
compute the margin of the velocity at
the end through the trained neural
network uh then the the flow map which
could be computed based on the marginal
velocity may not be strict. It may
result in this kind of the banded the
curves like this
make sense. So the the the linear
trajectory is only for the case like
when you basically take these samples
here and also the another sample here
for any two point obviously the
conditional trajectory between these two
dots would be straight. So that's how we
defined we define the conditional
trajectory is kind of the straight line.
Uh but as you can see like depending on
which the the two points two end points
we choose even the conditional the
velocity at this point can go up or can
go down right which means that at the
end the margin of the velocity can be
something like this at this point and
the the flow map the marginal flow map
that are basically defined based on the
the margin of the vector field may
result in this kind of the curved
trajectory.
Then what will be the issues with the
curved trajectory?
Can you see?
Yeah. So because because like we are now
computing all these kind of the
trajectory by solving the OD right the
trajectory is basically defined based on
the velocity.
So if we had this kind of the some
strict data like this, the good thing is
that from this starting point we if we
know that those kind of case but if we
if there is such kind of case that the
all the the the the margin of the uh the
flow map is kind of a straight line
which means that from this starting
point if you predict the velocity then
you can go straight all the way to the
end point here
which means that now you can make the
onestep directive model you don't need
to have any kind of iteration. The
reason like why we still need to
basically compute the velocity multiple
time is that we are having this kind of
the banded trajectory. We cannot go
straight all the way to the end because
we know that the trajectory will be
bended like this. So that's why
basically we need to basically know chop
the kind of the the time domain know
that basically going uh you know one
step small one small step and just like
going another small step and just repeat
those kind of things in terms of the
solving the OD right
so what we can see is that uh it's
always good to find some kind of the
straight strategy mapping uh between the
points in the source distribution uh and
also to the points in the target
distribution.
The problem is that even when you
basically define the conditional the
flow map as kind of a straight
trajectory the output the margin of the
trajectory may not be straight. So
that's kind of issue.
So some kind of the simple way uh to
make it stricter uh is that uh while
skipping some details here
is that so previously uh to train a
diffusion model what we need to do was
that basically taking the random pairs
from the source diffusion and also the
the target diffusion.
The simple way to make it straighter is
that once you basically have any kind of
the pre-trained uh the the flow model we
are using the pre-trained the the flow
model to take the the pair uh the sample
of the those kind of pairs of the x0 and
x1.
So let's say we uh now know fine-tune
the flow model uh by just not taking the
random pairs of like X0 and X1 but by
performing the generation the process
using the pre-trained model and just
taking these pairs
then surprisingly then what we can see
is that when these are basically the
trajectories that we could see uh from
the first rectified model the activated
flow model after another defined tuning
which is called the two rectified model.
Uh for the two rectified model you can
see that now the tra
become like this straight like this.
If you repeat this one more time uh then
you want to get even straighter the
trajectories like this.
So these are some kind of the very
simple the tricks and obviously there
are some kind of the last of the theory
in terms like know why we are achieving
straighter degun
but after skipping some kind of details
here uh for the flow models the way that
we can basically make some kind of the
uh faster direct model is that you first
uh train a flow model and based on that
fine-tune the models by just taking the
pairs uh from the previous model that
you're going get this straighter and
this straight in trajectories which
means that even with the fear number of
the time steps the OD is over you're
going to able to get some kind of clean
the outputs.
So after some kind of the a couple of
the iterations of like fine tune the
model now now what you can do is that
now we can make some kind of even a
singlestep model which means that from
the sample of the standard gausian we
can directly map this point into the one
of the data point. So this is kind of
interesting right uh we actually started
from the one step model we AE g those
are basically the onestep model right
that we have seen actually there are
lots of kind of the disadvantages uh in
terms of the diversity or the quality of
the outputs so that's why we started to
basically discuss the diffusion model
while basically sacrificing the
competition the the efficiency uh with
iterative process and now we are going
back to the uh the one the
uh basically through this kind of the
fine tuning techniques uh in terms of
that now we can get the fast speed and
also the good quality as well.
So actually if you see the many recent
uh the image and the video generated
models like state diffusion D3 and the
flux uh those things uh you'll be able
to see that those are basically uh not
based on the diffusion the models but
based on the flow models basically these
are basically identical but you can see
that then they are not basically
predicting the noise but predicting the
velocity
and if you remember what we have done in
the first lecture
uh do you remember this slide uh uh so
at the very beginning of like this class
I was asking you to try to make some
there some kind of images using the flux
model. So actually this flux oneel this
one uh this is the model which is
basically trained based on the this kind
of the leaf flow the technique. So you
can go back to this model and see how
this model has been was trained
and also one more thing is that we also
discussed the discussed the concepts
model for the diffusion and also now
define uh discussing the flow the
technical flow models right. So these
are kind of the some rival in terms of
the you know just like competing each
other and see like know now we are
seeing still seeing some kind of the
competition between these two uh in
terms like which one is basically better
uh for the viewep generation. So if you
see some kind of the some comparison
here the CD and the CT those things are
like all based on the constance models
and the FID goes down to four or the
three here and also with the two rectify
flow we are also seeing some kind of
similar DF ID here uh yeah with the one
and the two steps. So you can see that
these are some kind of the two uh very
different approaches uh in terms of how
we can accelerate the generation process
uh using either the diffusion models or
the flow models.
Any questions on this?
Okay.
So this is the end of the kind of
discussion for the all the basics for
the diffusion models and the flow of the
models. So we discussed basically how
the idea has been evolved from the BA
gan to the DDP and DDIM and also the SD
and the OD formulation and also the flow
models. Uh for the rest uh of the three
weeks uh we are going to see more into
the application side. So basically not
only in terms of generating some kind of
like some realistic data points uh what
uh can you do more in terms of getting
something not just like realistic but
something that we want to see how we can
basically inject some kind of the more
the usual pre preference in the
generation process. So for the next week
uh we are going to discuss the inference
time the guidance uh which is basically
injecting some kind of the usual
preference at the inference time uh
without any kind of training and also
we're going to move on to the diffusion
model the case for the discrete data uh
in the week after the next week. So this
is this case.
Okay let's end the lecture here.