Okay. So yeah, let's get back to the
things that you know we have discussed
before. So last time uh while we started
the discussion for the different models
from like DDPM, DDIM like schoolbased
model kind of things and we actually
realized that actually all the things
that we are
uh knowing
basically you know representing with the
the training of the fusion model is that
basically it's all about like is
practicing the mapping from the data
distribution to the later distribution
using the SD formulation. Right? We
could say that actually the both the
fold process and the reverse process uh
the can be represented as the stochastic
differential equation especially when
you define the fold SD into this form.
We could see that the reverse SD also
can be uh you know defined in this way
with this core function here.
uh and then what we also have seen is
that actually it turns out that we can
find the corresponding the OD
formulation uh that basically matches
the marginal distribution which means
that by simply solving the OD
formulation now we can do both ways of
the mapping right so that was the basic
idea for the diffusion models so after
we see this now we can see that like
everything the mapping can be basically
uh you know considered as basically the
OD formulation so this was the tape OD
And the thing is that when he discussed
the PF 4D uh we did not see the details
in terms of like you know how we exactly
can derive this formulation uh from
either the for SD and the reverse SD
right we I just said that like this is
DP 4D right I didn't say like how we can
derive this uh I'm not going to get into
the all the details for that if you are
interested basically how we can derive
like this formulation I strongly
recommend you check out this paper and
see how we can do
But the very high level kind of thing is
that know basically to derive those kind
of things we need to start uh to discuss
this formulation first. Uh this is the
the very basic formulation which is
called the focal plank the equation uh
which is the showing some kind of the
relationship between the SD formulation
and the probability
uh for the intermediate the data point
of the XT. uh so this is the formulation
that shows the relationship between
these two and from this and we can
consider basically dering all the things
for the pod but we are not going to get
into the all the details because it will
take another like one hour uh but yeah
please keep this in mind because like
this is also the formulation that we're
going to keep seeing for the the rest of
the part of the the course so this was
kind of the basic idea and after we
start to see the OD formulation what we
can see is that uh now we consider
making some kind of the some dedicated
the OD solver based on the the structure
of the deformation. So the idea that we
have seen the DPM over the case uh was
basically actually this is like one of
the specific example in terms of like
trying to basically make some kind of
the uh the analytic dissolutions for the
OD while it's impossible to make some
kind of the fully analytic dissolution
for the entire OD but here what we try
to do was basically integrating and it's
like the linear the part analytically
and doing some kind of the better
approximation for the the nonlinear the
part of the integration. So in terms of
that we could say that we can achieve
some kind of the better results even
with the few step. So also especially
the interesting part of the DPM solver
was that uh if we take the first order
the approximation uh for those like
nonlinear part then it became exactly
the same with the DDIM right so we could
see that like why DDI performs better uh
the the non stoastic version performs
better with the few number of steps uh
because it's kind of this first
approximation for the OD deformation
right and we could go further which
means that we could basically If we do
the higher order the approximation for
the nonlinear part in terms of that we
can uh achieve some kind of the better
results with the even fewer the number
of the steps. So I guess may some of you
might now try to implement the higher
the server in terms of like reducing the
uh the number of the the steps in your
decode but we'll see. So that's kind of
the basic idea.
So this is the basically figure that I
have shown from the very beginning of
like this course. Basically the
advantages of the fusion model is that
you can achieve the high quality the
outputs without any kind of mod collapse
the issues. Basically the the limitation
is all about the speed right. So what we
have discussed from the the previous
lectures is like all about how we are
going to uh produce the quality the
outputs uh with the fewer the number of
the steps. So we started from the DDPM
which required like more or less like
typically people use the 1,00 time steps
right and then we know reduced that into
the more or less the 50 to the 200 using
the DDIM and by seeing that the DDIM can
be uh seen as kind of the uh the first
order approximation of the OD
formulation when you have some the
higher order dissolution. Now we could
reduce the in of the time steps into the
10 to the 15.
So that's really kind of the remarkable
the progress in terms like reducing the
competition from the 1,00 to the 10,
right? Uh 100 times of kind of
improvement, right? But the question is
that how can you also improve further?
So if you see the quite recent the image
or the video generated models uh you can
see that their generation speed is
really fast uh actually the very latest
the generation the models for the image
and the videos are just requiring really
few steps one to five kind of steps
which means that they did something
right uh it's not just using the using
those kind of the ideas
so actually there are tons of the ideas
in terms of how we can further
accelerate the diffusion process uh in
the degeneration. The thing is that what
we have seen this uh in this like the
previous lectures are basically all the
ideas that we can directly apply uh in
the test time. So that is also very
interesting point of the diffusion
models in terms of that you don't need
to retrain the model using some kind of
the pre-trained model by simply changing
the formulations of the generation uh
you can achieve this level of the
acceleration almost like 100 times of
the acceleration that was the very
interesting point right uh but also the
idea is that uh you know some kind of
recent ideas are basically also about
like how we can do the achieve the
further the acceleration with some kind
of the fine tuning. So that's also kind
of the some the ideas which is the ideas
is called the distillation. So given
some kind of the pre-trained model you
do some kind of the finetuning of the
neural network uh in a way that now we
can make it as kind of the like one step
generation the model. So we you can
basically get some kind of the the
outputs with some kind of the single
step uh the computation.
So for that like so we are not going to
get into the too much details for the
many acceleration techniques. uh but the
reason that I'm just like you know
mentioning this is that uh one of the
kind of biggest motivation
uh of like discussing the flow models
that we are going to start to discuss
from today uh is also about the
acceleration with some kind of fine
tuning. So that's kind of the reason
that I'm just mentioning this but this
is really important topic in terms of
that we can further reduce the
computation.
uh the most representative the idea for
the fine-tuning based uh kind of the
acceleration is the consistency models.
So we are not going to get into any
details for this but here the the basic
idea for this kind of the the technique
is that
uh you first basically compute OD which
means that you from the some kind of the
noise samples the standard gausian the
sample you perform the OD disorber all
the way that you get some kind of the
realistic data point here right so which
means that you have some kind of the
trajectory from the standard gausian
sample to the data point there Right. So
here the basic idea is that uh we do
some kind of a noise prediction in the
every single point. Right. And we also
have seen that the noise prediction can
be used uh to compute the expected the
final value using the the tweet formula.
Right? So actually we can see that the
new the role of the neuronet is actually
to predict the uh the final the output
the expectation for the final the output
right. So the basic idea for the
constant model is that for all the
points along the way of like this
trajectory
uh we want to basically foresee the
final the outputs from the earliest
stage of the trajectory.
So the basic idea is that we make the
expectation of the final output in the
earlier point here to be close to the
later point here.
So we already know like this kind of
trajectory we already computed the OD
here for the audio point here the XT
prime here. Uh when you see the final
the expectation of the final the output
we make it to be to get closer to the
expectation of the final output the the
next point. So that's kind of the basic
idea. Obviously there are lots of the
details in terms like you know how we
can make this kind of training to be
more distable. Uh there are some kind of
details you can check out. uh the
details in the paper. Uh but without
seeing those kind of details like with
this the relatively the simple idea in
terms like you know having some kind of
the earlier stage of some kind of the uh
you know forecasting for the the final
outputs uh we can achieve some kind of
the results in terms like making some
realistic the outputs even with the very
few number of steps even just with even
like one or the two steps. So that's
kind of the good idea for the constants
models and not only for this there are
lots of some kind of similarity ideas in
terms like you know accelerating the
generation but the kind of the downside
for the all those kind of the ideas is
that they are all requiring some kind of
pre-trained diffusion models and
starting from that uh for the
finetuning. So that's the kind of the
idea. So by so which means that by
spending more time in the training the
phase uh you can basically reduce the
computation in the test time. Uh so
that's kind of the basic idea for those
kind of the acceleration techniques.
So even without like having any
understanding for all the details here
now at least you can see some kind of
the history of like the literature in
terms like how the uh the techniques
have been evolved over time uh in terms
of that we started from the DDPM 1000
steps and the DDIM 200 steps and DPM
servers and all the many other the
dedicated OD servers like going down to
the 10 steps and then consistency models
or some kind of D acceleration
techniques which also goes down to the
one or the two steps while requiring the
distillation the technique with some
kind of pre models. So those are some
kind of the some picture in terms of
that how we can know do some kind of
explorations with the different models.
So the thing is that any other options
uh with the the like all the kind of
things that we can do. So from today
actually we are going to discuss uh
completely uh different digital model
which is the flow matching. Uh but after
discussing all the things actually you
realize that while the idea for the flow
matching stems from the completely
different kind of literature the root
eventually actually that becomes kind of
the identical uh with the diffusion
models. So that's also kind of the very
interesting point while uh it might be
quite know painful in terms like seeing
some kind of the connections between
these two. So we're going to get into
that.
So um so as kind of the some another the
idea in terms of making some
acceleration and actually as kind of the
completely new idea of the gen models uh
so we are going to start to discuss the
um the flow models. The thing is that in
the context of diffusion models
here the key thing is that so please
keep this in mind. So this is the really
important point and this is really
confusing point. Uh in the diffusion
model context we have seen the time
range the time domain from the
perspective of the flow the food process
right. So the time t uh is starting from
zero uh from the data distribution and
through the full diffusion process we
are mapping the x0 all the way to the x
capital t here right so starting from
the data distribution x0 uh and then
going to the x capital t right so that
was kind of the combination that we used
in the models uh the thing is that uh so
it's always good to basically keep the
old kind of the the the denotations
here. But the problem is that for the
flow matching the context as I said this
is completely new gen model which is
coming from the completely new some kind
of the literature and the the root
basically and they are seeing basically
this kind of the time domain uh from the
generation the perspective. So which
means that now the xju starts from the
something kind of the known distribution
which is typically standard gaussian
distribution in our case and then which
is now mapped to the one of the the data
point sample from the data distribution
to the x1. So we're going to switch the
the time the range uh flipping the time
range uh you know starting from the dial
distriution to the gaussian
distribution. Now we go into this way
the gausian distribution to the data
distribution. So now this will be x0 and
this will be x1. Okay.
Oh you're going to see that actually
this is very confusing even I get
confused with this kind of the the
changes of the notations. Uh sorry about
that. Uh but I also had some kind of the
thoughts in terms like what if we just
like follow like one of those things for
the discussion for everything. The thing
is that um all the materials that you
can see for the diffusion models
basically follow those notations and all
the kind of the metrics for the flow
matching follows basically this the time
dange. So that's kind of the confusing
point. So we're going to switch from
this to this in the discussion for the
flow models x basically um one means the
data distribution and x0 basically means
the sample from the uh the gausian
distribution. Make sense?
starting from the x0 to the x1 that's
the reverse the process
don't get confused so keep this in mind
and so based on that uh let's discuss
the flow match
so basically you you're going to see
that know all the discussion for the
every dig model is kind of the same we
discuss we basically set the sort of the
reference distribution uh which is
typically the center gian distribution
and the dution which is p1
uh I'm not going to get into too much
details for this for now but actually
the key distinction between the flow
models and the diffusion models is that
all the things that we discussed for the
diffusion model is assuming that this
reference distribution is the standard
Gaussian distribution right if we change
this into another distribution actually
we have seen that example in our test
right uh not having the reference
distribution as the standard the the
isotropic distribution for some kind of
anastropic distribution, right? Uh but
if we change this like reference
distribution into the very new kind of
distribution in the diffusion models,
then everything will be changed. Uh so
that will be quite complicated.
The good thing of the flow model is that
we can make this to be really anything.
Uh even when you basically make this
like reference equation to the any other
distribution, uh the formulation is not
changed at all. Uh so that's also kind
of the very interesting point of the
flow models. You can see it's kind of a
generalization right. Uh so that's kind
of thing but in any case like we going
to basically set the reference is the P
0 and the is the P1.
Uh and then we going to basically
introduce some kind of the new terms
which is something that we already have
seen. We just like having some kind of
names for that. Uh basically we're going
to define the function pi which is the
flow map. So flow map is basically
representing the trajectory
starting from the point x here. So when
you have the basically pi tx here
basically the input here becomes the uh
the sample from the reference
distriution typically the p 0.
So the input the this function should be
x0 basically a sample from the reference
distribution and the pi t basically
means some kind of the point over the
trajectory at the time step t. So we
always start from the x0 uh we change
the the the time range and then going to
the x1 right and pi t is basically
representing that the trajectory so
there is no stockity here everything is
so this is another basically od based
kind of models which means that zero
stockaticity okay uh so which means that
if you basically determine the starting
point x0 then all the points along the
trajectory will be determined right uh
so we which means that we can now define
some kind of function for that. So
basically the xt starting from the
specific x0 will be denoted as the pi
tx0. Uh so that's the the kind of the
new notations
and the uh the vector field. So this is
the OD based kind of the formulations.
So we're going to uh also uh basically
define the vector field which is
basically defined based on the flow map
right. So you can see that basically the
how the vector field and the flow map
will be related each other. Obviously
basically when you define the OD
formulation based on the vector field
that will basically compute the flow map
at the ability time step t. Uh so that's
kind of basic thing.
So this is nothing but what we already
have seen that you know the flow map
here can be basically defined by based
on this OD formulation uh with the
vector field here. So obviously the
starting point of the trajectory should
be the same with like this point right
uh by definition of the flow map. So we
are defining the flow as kind of
trajectory starting from this. So when
the time t here is basically zero, it
should be basically the same dx0, right?
And if we basically map the x0 all the
way to the time one here, then that
should be one of the sample of the data
distribution.
Yeah. So that's a thing. So every is the
kind of like the single point over the
trajectory basically can be computed by
solving the OD like this starting from
the xio basically integrating the vector
field over the time t uh so that's kind
of thing so we are going to I'm going to
uh sometimes abuse some kind of
notations in terms like having the xt
here which is kind of the using some
kind of things but the notations but
indicating the uh the point at the time
step t starting from the X0
uh so that's the thing
and then uh in the diffusion model the
context uh we have seen some kind of the
uh probability distribution for the
noisy the data point right uh so in the
scorebased models uh we had that the
reference distribution and the data
distriution and then the uh the
probability distribution uh for the
intermediate uh the noise data point xt
do you remember how we defined is the uh
data distribution for the intermediate
the noisy data point. How did he define
for this cool base model
in the langu dynamics like what we have
seen is basically having some kind of
the gausian convolution for every single
the data point uh the samples of the the
data distribution right so the thing is
that we don't have any uh closed
formulation for this that's why we do
all the things right we only have the
samples of the data distribution and
then in the to perform the loungement
dynamics Basically what we have seen
last time for the schoolbased model is
that we are defining the probability
distribution for the intermediate the
noise data point the XT as kind of the
Gaussian convolution for each of the
single data point right. So this is
basically the same thing basically the
probability distribution for the
intermediate data point of XT probably
the intermediate time step the the t
here uh we're going to just have the
name for that in the concept flow the
the matching which is called the
probability the density path or the
property path. So those are some kind of
the some the new name for like those
things.
So please keep these three things in
mind. uh we going to keep discussing
those three things. Uh we going to have
the flow map and which can be computed
by the vector field right. So if you
have this then we can compute this. We
have this and we can this and based on
this we can also compute the probability
path as well the things. So the thing is
that uh in the diffusion models for this
corebased models
uh what we have seen is that actually we
are defining this first right. uh we
defined like this the the you know
probability distribution for the
intermediate data point uh by basically
injecting some kind of the gausian the
noise doing some kind of gausian the
convolution right and based on that we
can basically formulate all the food and
the reversed processes and then based on
that know we can compute the OD
formulation the pfod uh which means that
now we can compute the vector field from
the probability path uh that we defined
right the thing is that in the flow the
matching uh we going to go in kind of
the reverse way. We're going to
basically first define the vector field
and the flow map and based on that how
we going to we're going to see how this
probability path is also basically
defined based on like these two. So
there are some kind of connections in
the three.
So here basically the thing is that uh
it's kind of like more straightforward
in terms of like how the vector field
and the flow map these two are basically
related each other right uh basically
this can be computed by solving the OD
from the vector field right but the
thing is that it's not very clear you
know how exactly this one is basically
related with these two uh so that's kind
of the some complicated part uh we are
not going to get into uh deep of that uh
but this is like the part that know this
equation comes out again and so this is
back to the equation that we can see
some kind of the connections like
between these two. So while this looks
quite complicated, uh the good thing is
that if we ignore this part,
if we see some kind of very simple the
OD formulation, uh ignore this part
because like we see that this is
actually the uh kind of the the OD
formulation of the vector field, right?
Uh so if we ignore this part then
actually this f function can be
considered as kind of the our vector
field. uh as you can see in the here the
very simplified version right uh so when
there's no stockaticity uh the f
function becomes of the vector field
then we can see some kind of the very
simple uh the some kind of the
connection between the probability pass
which is basically the probability
distribution for the the data point at
the time step t and also the vector
field here so actually this formulation
showing the relationship between the
factor field and the probably the
distribution is one of the kind of key
things to see you know to derive the pod
from the focus fun equation but you are
not going to get into all the details
for that but this is kind of thing so
now we can see how exactly the uh the
you know the vector field is basically
related uh with the probability path so
based on that uh what we can do is that
uh with some kind of the derivation Here
once we basically have any kind of
defective field here based on that for
any of the uh the data point over the
trajectory uh we can compute the log
probability.
So now the vector field can be used to
compute like how likely each of the data
point will be there at the time step t.
Uh so that's kind of the the key things
here.
So basically this means that uh if we
can somehow find a vector field that can
maximizes the log probability the uh
here uh for the each of the the data
sample that we have. So x1 so don't get
confused the x1 is the data sample not
the gaussian sample okay we are going
from the x0 to the x1 x0 is the gausian
sample and x1 is the data sample right
uh so for the x1 if we can now compute
the log probability for each of the data
point right uh using the vector field
that we have so if we can somehow find a
vector field that maximizes the log
probability for all all the data point
which means that now we found a kind of
the good mapping right that's kind of
the mapping that we can basically map
the x0 into the x1 uh so which means
that somehow if we can find this kind of
the vector field this is kind of the
information
this is kind of the function that
basically encodes some kind of the uh
the information for the the mapping so
which means that
as we also have done similarly in the
diffusion models we can try to basically
memorize this information of the vector
field that encodes this like mapping
information using the neuron net uh for
the each of the sample of the time t and
also the sample of xt we can consider
basically train neuron net that can
basically predict this kind of the the
velocity and that's kind of similar with
like what we have seen for the diffusion
model case right so as we basically
trained uh the uh noise predictor in the
diffusion models somehow if we can have
some the the information for the vector
field uh we can consider training a
neuron net that basically encodes all
those kind of the vector field
information uh which is maximizing the
low probability for the x1 right then
based on that as we have seen in the
previous slide we can compute the od
that will become our degeneration
process so that's kind of the high idea
in terms of now we can how we can also
define the another type of the od based
derent model uh by directly ly defining
the uh the flow map also the vector
field before we get into the all the uh
the some specific definitions for the
the uh the probability path.
But obviously here the question is that
how we can find such kind of vector
field right. So when you start from the
any kind of x0 and then sending that
into this the the x1 using the vector
field that should be one of the
realistic data point right. Uh so the
question is that how we can find such
kind of defector field that maximizes
the lobby for the all the xy uh so
that's kind of thing one global way uh
is that uh we actually define the loss
function as the log probability that we
have seen the previous slide. So when
you define the log problem like this for
the any point of the x1
the the sample the data point uh that we
basically actually go all the way back
running the OD in the backward in terms
of going into the x0 here then now we
can compute this row probability by
computing this right basically this
means that from the x1 we train the
neuron net over time in a way that we
have the detector field using the vector
field we go the in the backward all the
way to the x0 here and compute the
probability in this way and basically we
are finding the effective field in a way
that we maximizes this. Okay. So this is
kind of global uh with the formulations
here
but
yeah so it is clear for each of the data
point last lot of the data point X1 that
we have actually from starting from the
arbitrary defective field we perform the
OD in the backward uh it's kind of the
process in the diffusion model the case
and then having the the backward
trajectory and based on that we compute
the log probability uh by computing this
in a way that we find some kind of the
better vector field that maximize this
uh so that that's kind of the uh very
early version uh of the idea in terms
like you know how we can uh you know
make some kind of degenerate model by
directly learning the vector field here.
So this is really different with like
what we have seen the diffusion model
case right in the diffusion model case
we somehow defined uh the the
probability pass the the conditional
probability pass actually uh that we can
also see in the next slide and based on
that we could derive all the things of
the the this kind of OD formulation uh
which is giving us the the vector field
here right but here we don't define any
kind of the the property pass and
directly somehow try to find the vector
field here in terms like maximizing
this.
Obviously the conclusion that I'm going
to say is that uh this is not working
that well. So so we're going to see like
how we can make it to be uh similar to
the diffusion model of the case in a way
that we can make it more detractable in
terms of training. But can you see like
what's the problem like this? If we
train the the uh vectoral field uh the
the velocity prediction network in this
way what the kind of issue
you can really implement this right but
what the kind of issue with this
I mean the issue all comes from
basically solving the OD right uh
solving the OD in like very stable way
is super challenging uh unless we have
some very specific form of the OD
formulation but for those kind of
general form the problem is that uh you
know the OD is all basically can be not
only computationally expensive but also
numerically unstable. So that's kind of
the issue.
So the thing is that uh if you trained
in your net in this way then every time
when you compute the loss function you
need to compute the OD right uh and then
the back propagation should be done all
the way through the OD the solve right
uh but the OD sol is basically
computationally expensive and also can
be numerically unstable so that's kind
of the problems so here the question is
that how we can basically learn those
kind of the um vector field uh without
basically making all the load post
function to uh involve some kind of the
OD the soap. Uh so that's kind of the uh
the basic idea here. Okay. But is it
clear?
But can can you say that know how we are
basically evolving kind of things in
terms of that we started from the VDP
and DDM things and then see how those
kind of like mapping can be you know
defined as kind of the SD formulation
and also the OD formulation and then now
we are kind of going the other way
around. Now we are going to basically
define this mapping directly as kind of
the OD formulation uh in a way that how
actually we are going the reverse way
you know now we define the mapping as
kind of the vector field and from this
we're going to see how those are
basically related with the probability
pass and those things so that's kind of
the another interesting idea so let's
try to basically make the other the the
vector field the learning uh without
solving the OD for the loss function
computation
So from this point uh we're going to
start to see that actually what we are
discussing in this kind of the new
generate model becomes slightly
uh actually kind of getting quite
similar with diffusion models but having
some quite different some kind of the uh
the explanation for that.
So what we are going to do is that uh
what we need is basically this right
uh probability the pass for the the time
step t. Uh but instead of like directly
seeing that uh we are going to consider
all the things which is called the
conditional things the conditional
property pass conditional flow map and
also the conditional defective field.
See here basically the conditional
probability pass basically means that uh
when we assume that the data
distribution is basically a simple the
gausian distribution which is centered
at the x1 and also the very small
visions here.
So can you actually see that this is
something that we already have seen in
the previous lecture
something familiar? No.
So this might be confusing because we
changed the the time the range and also
the some of the notations here. But
actually what we are doing here is
exactly the same uh that we have done in
this corebased model. You can see that
you know uh the
what's there? Yeah. So we are basically
doing some kind of the the gausian the
convolution for each of the data point
of the x1. Right. So in a way that we
define some kind of the noisy the the
probability distribution of the time
step t. So this is exactly the same
thing uh basically having some kind of
gausian uh the you know the the this
kind of convolution with some kind of
the by seeing that each of the the point
is kind of the
uh the data point as kind of the the
small decions here. So that's kind of
thing. So for this conditional setup
that basically what we are going to see
is that now we are going to assume that
given any kind of sample of the x1 we
are going to assume that the data
distribution is given as kind of the
very small the gaussian centered at the
specific point of the x1 in a way that
we're going to get back to the the path
of the pt the marginal continue the the
the path uh by taking the integral in
this way. So that's basically what we
are going to do.
So as I said uh can say that this like
conditional setup as kind of the case
that the reference distribution uh is
exactly the same while basically we are
sort of seeing the data distribution as
kind of the some concentrated the
gausian center at the given the the
point of the x1 here. Uh so the reason
why why we are having this kind of
conditional setup is that the good thing
is that now our data distribution became
Gaussian distribution again
which which we know the analytic form.
So once we have some kind of the
analytic form for the the data
distribution then we can derive the
analytic form for the flow map and also
the vector field as well. So all the
computation becomes like more
detractable and visible and after seeing
all the things for the conditional setup
we're going to see basically how we can
compute the marginal the the probability
pass and also the marginal defective
field based on those kind of conditional
things. So that's the basic idea.
So that's kind of things. So basically
when you say the conditional depth of
like this thing uh so don't confuse okay
thing x1 is the data point right from
the x1 given kind of x1 what we kind of
the the the conditioner the probably the
pass for the time t right uh so you can
see this is kind of the similar with the
food process of diffusion models in the
food process we have seen that how we
can basically inject some kind of the
gaussian noise with some kind of the
drift
for each of the data point of the X1.
Right? So this is actually kind of like
corresponds to the the for the jump
distribution uh in the diffusion model
case. Uh so we have seen the bunch of
things right for the the BP case and the
B case those are defined in this way. So
this formulation may look quite
different with the BP case but the
reason for that is that we changed the
the time the range. So that's kind of
the problem, right? uh but this is kind
of something that we have also have seen
in the digital model case the fourth
jump distribution which was basically
adding some kind of gausian noise uh
into the x1 right
so now we can see some kind of
connections between the flow model and
the diffusion models and as I said uh
we're going to keep seeing these kind of
those three things flow map vector field
and the probability pass and see
basically how those are basically
related each other that's also what we
have seen the previously slide and then
uh we can also see the same thing for
the conditional setup you're going to
also see the conditional flow map
conditional vector field and the
conditional depth
uh and the thing is that
in the diffusion model case uh we
started to uh define this one right EVPM
where we are defining the for jump and
based on that all the other things are
defined right uh defining this first and
dering all the other things uh what we
are going to do here is that we are
going to define this First we're going
to first define the flow map into this
simple linear function first uh and see
how the other things are basically
derived based on that. So you can see
how we are basically generalized this
kind of the idea in terms of expanding
our the scope in terms like having some
specific in the previously diffused
models we have some specific deformable
like those things especally the BP
formulation or the B population and
extending this into other things. And
now we want to basically like expand our
scope in terms of like know what if we
first uh define the conditional flow map
and based on that define all the other
things. So that's kind of the case. So
don't also get confused. Uh so this is
the conditional setup. So condition by
the realistic the data point X1 here and
then the flow map always basically take
some kind of the starting point as the
input. The starting point is typically
the gausian distribution but as I said
in the flow model it does not need to be
gausian but basically a sample from the
the starting distribution the reference
distribution and this is basically the
sample that we are taking as the
condition of the data point right
then from the definition like this
you can see right I mean so basically if
this t is zero here what should be
output like
I mean very simple question it should be
ex right why our the definition of the
conditional deployments basically the
flow the definition of the flow map is
that the the trajectory uh over the
space starting from the x0 right so if
the t is zero then this should be
obviously x0 right but this is also
condition the setup that we assuming
that data dispution is pretty tiny
gausian and center x1 right then what
should be the output when the t is one
it should be close to x1 right because
that's the basically only the sample of
the data distribution right uh so
obviously from the this kind of the
conditioning the setup the if we specify
the x0 and the x1 when the t is zero
then the output should be x0 and the t
is one that should be very close to the
x1 Right?
Which means that uh while we see some
kind of the the general form of the
still uh some linear function of the
condition the flow map the our
definition of like those this function
and this function should satisfy those
kind of the boundary condition
we you you can define whatever sigma
here and the mu here it's okay. Uh we
also have seen many generalizations in
diffusion model case right. Uh so we're
going to also see some multiple options
defined in like those two terms right
actually you can lally define anything
uh but whatever you define for these two
things the thing is that when the time t
is zero then the output should be x0 and
the when the time t is one then the
output should be close to the x1 uh you
need to define these two in that way
right
and now you want to see that this is
something that is getting closer to
something you already have seen
>> [sighs]
>> the problem five of the the test was
kind of getting close to this, right? Uh
so that's kind of the things that you
basically see some kind of connection
between the diffusion models and the
flow mapping. So with this kind of like
the linear function, you're going to see
those kind of the some straight
trajectory from the any of the axis here
mapping to the x1 here. So having some
kind of the straight trajectories.
So the reason like why we are having
this kind of simple form the linearity
function of the condition of the flow
map is that uh based on that so once we
define the conditional flow map into
this very simple way
obviously there should be some way
reasons for that right the reason for
like define the conditional flow map in
this like simple way is that then now
everything becomes quite simple then we
can easily define that the corresponding
the the conditionality property pass
also can be defined into the gausian
distribution
We have seen the relationship between
the flow the vector field and the flow
map and also the vector field and the
property pass right in the previous
slides and based on that if you derive
all the things that you're going to see
that from the linear the condition flow
map actually the the uh the conditional
the probability pass given the x1
actually becomes this simple the gaus
and the the the form
this is also very similar with like what
we have seen right the basically our
liberation diffusion model was defined
in this way with some kind of the
conditions for the SNR for those two
functions, right? So while we are also
using another notations like the mu and
the sigma, you can get the sense of like
those things will be somehow
identical with some kind of the the
functions we have seen in the previous
lectures. So sorry for that we just keep
using new notations uh because of those
are coming from the different
literature. But you can see like these
are kind of actually related with the
the terms in the variation diffusion
models. So as I said uh you need to have
those kind of conditions in terms of
that you need to satisfy the boundary
condition that the time step is zero the
out should be x0 and the is one and it
should be the caution this thing. So
that's a thing.
So yeah, so basically we just kind of
the boundary the the the boundary
condition you're going to see that when
the time t is zero that becomes like
this and the time one is that and we get
this right.
So then based on that let's check this
out. Uh so you can just try this
yourself. Uh like doing some kind of
sanity check. Uh so uh given this kind
of like the uh the condition to flow map
the linear function uh with those kind
of some boundary conditions just like
put those things and check what you get
here.
So based on the this kind of simple list
the option for the mu and the sigma
function if we derive the conditional
property pass and the conditional flow
map and the conditional vector field
then you're going to see that we get
this form right uh this is also quite
obvious right with that kind of the the
simple form obviously the condition the
flow map should be interpolation between
these two points making straight
trajectory from the from the uh x0 to
the XY
right makes sense right and also the the
property pass is defined in that way and
also the vector field is defined as kind
of the vector on that in the straight
line that's very obvious right so this
is kind of the lesson uh for now uh you
don't need to take a photo I'm going to
update the slice uh but this is kind of
a lesson here is in terms of that now we
can uh make some kind of the to OD based
model uh by first define some kind of
the conditional the flow map and
everything can be derived based on that.
Uh in the context of like making the the
define the some trajectories the
conditional trajectory to first the
condition the trajectories do not need
to be any kind of some fancy like
complex kind of things. Even the
simplest one uh would be okay.
But also the other option is that what
if we really follow the things that we
have seen in the diffusion model case.
In the diffusion model case we first
defined uh the conditional probably pass
into this way. Right? This is the BP
case uh having some kind of the shift
and also basically adding injecting some
kind of noise right. So the the
condition probably path was basically
defined kind of some fold the jump
distribution right having some kind of
the the Gaussian distribution
and from this obviously we can uh derive
the other things as well. So based on
that the continuity prop now we're going
to see that the vector field is computed
uh in this way.
So while we're going to discuss also the
barger case as well the things is that
uh we are basically seeing some kind of
the conditional some sort of these core
terms uh the diffusion case uh which is
bally used for some kind of long kind of
process right but we now switch
everything is kind of the OD formulation
but instead of the core function now we
are seeing some kind of the vector field
and obviously these two will be somehow
related to each other right uh we're
going to get into this connection
between these two next Right. Uh but we
are basically seeing some kind of the
other types of the quantity which is now
the vector field and based on that we
can define audioation and we can perform
basically the generation the process
and if we also compare this kind of the
condition flow matching with the
previous case uh everything was the
marginal setup in the previous case.
Obviously there's no closed form for
anything for any of the defective field
all the things. uh so we needed to
basically uh learn the vector field with
some kind of very expensive the OD the
computation uh in the loss function so
to avoid that what we do is that we
start to consider some continually setup
uh then basically the data distribution
can be considered some kind of the some
the analytic form it's kind of the
gausian formulation then all the things
basically can be der defined into the
closed formulation so that's the kind of
things uh in terms like why we see the
conditional setup
But obviously at the end uh while we can
directly compute the conditional the
vector field that's not something that
we want right we want to basically get
the marginal detector field right uh so
how we going to compute the the marginal
vector field based on the conditional
defective field so I'm going to skip
some some details here uh actually if we
start to discuss all the detail that
will take another 30 minutes uh so if I
I skip some details here based on like
those deformationations
actually the marginal vector field can
be computed based on the conditional
vector field and also the conditional
property pass like this. So using this
formulation
what we can do is that uh what we wanted
to do in the previously flow matching
case was was basically to learn the uh
you know the vector field here using the
learn net using this loss function. But
based on the previous formulation, what
we can do is that uh we can still learn
the marginal vector field but using the
conditional the vector field by just
sampling the x1 and also the time t.
So these two becomes basically the
identical. So basically what we can say
is that uh we can consider basically
learning the marginal defective field uh
by just computing the conditional
defective field and for this we did not
have the analytic form but for this now
we have the analytic form right so it's
just like
sort kind of things right so we
basically sample the x1 and based on
that we compute like this like close
from this and then basically minimize
this so this is kind of like very
similar with what we have seen
in the the core prediction case the the
the prediction in your network in the
diffusion case but the thing is that now
we basically not learning the cool
function uh but the velocity function
it's like changing the kind of quantity
that we are going to learn uh in the the
context of the flow matching so there
are some connections between these two
that way
that's a thing so we now have the close
form for this
then you can also see the analogy in
terms like training the diffusion models
and the flow models. So in the diffusion
model case we already implemented this
right. uh what we need to do is a
sampling the data point x1 and the time
step and then sample the noise there and
then compute the xt and then basically
having training network that predicts
the noise there right uh it's kind of
very similar the only thing is that
instead of like noise now we basically
compute this right uh xy time that t and
then sample xt and then based on that we
computitionally velod and then we train
the internet that now predicts uh this
quantity not this quantity function and
then after that the generation process
is basically the same. uh here we have
some kind of some complicated
formulations in this core the the the
models right uh well it is not actually
the complicated for the BP case actually
this also quite simple for uh in the uh
the flow matching the case we directly
have the notion of the vector field
which means that the generation process
becomes that we sample the axis here and
just like compute OD
uh using any OD server that you want to
use
and this kind of the OD formulation has
some bunch of the advantages in terms of
the performance and also the
acceleration as well. So at the
beginning of like this lecture I
mentioned some kind of the ideas in
terms like how we can further accelerate
the generation process through the
finetuning right uh using the flow
models we're going to also see some very
simple uh surprisingly simple quite but
effective the ideas in terms of how we
can also accelerate this kind of the the
generation process with the uh the flow
models but even before that uh you can
see that uh so you can see the meaning
of like with the fusion and with the OT
here basically means that this is the
case like we are defining the mu and the
sigma function uh in a way that that
matches the full process of the
diffusion models and this is the case
that we are basically defining the mu
and the sigma function as the straight
the trajectory. So by simply changing
the the part you can see that we can
achieve some kind of the improvement
over some kind of the the readers like
this which means that we didn't need to
make some kind of some curvy the
trajectory with the diffusion models
just make it everything kind of straight
but here also one small thing is that we
are making the conditional trajectory to
be straight. uh but after training all
the things with a treat the contin
trajectory it does not guarantee that
we're going to have some straight tra
the marginal the trajectories after the
all the training uh so yeah we're going
to get into that because everything is
expected value right so we're going to
get into that why we going to we may see
some kind of some kind of still banded
trajectory after the training and how we
can also fix that uh still some kind of
define tuning so that's the idea that we
are going to discuss next Okay,
any questions on this?
Did you now get the idea in terms of how
we can solve the problem five the last
test?
Okay, so let's continue discussing flow
matching uh next Monday.