Claude Co-Work is here and if you understand how to use it you're going to be able to outperform
99% of people on this planet. It is an easy way for you to use Claude Code. You might have heard
of Claude Code, it's gone viral, but the problem is it feels technical. You have to go into the
terminal and it's not fun for a lot of beginners. So Claude has come up with Co-Work and it's a
brand new product that harnesses the power of Claude Code in a UI that is simple, that anyone
could use, that your dad can use, your mom could use, hey even you can use. So in this episode
I brought on Boris, the maker of this product. I'm so excited that he shows you the best practices
for how to use Claude Co-Work and at the end how he sets up his Claude Code to get
the most out of it. You're gonna love this episode.
We are lucky we've got Boris, he's the creator of Claude Code and I would say the co-creator of
Claude Co-Work today. And today what I want to get accomplished is everyone's talking about Co-Work
and I want to best understand what are the use cases, how can we get started,
what are some non-obvious ways I can use it. So Boris, thank you so much for coming on the show
and I have one question for you. By the end of this episode what are people going to get out of it?
Ooh, I think people are gonna start to get some more ideas for how to use Co-Work
and hopefully they're gonna tweet about it and maybe they'll even reach out to me so I
could learn how they want to use Co-Work. It's funny, I feel like for Claude Code
from the beginning it was sort of built to be, it wasn't actually built to be a product at all, but
when we first started thinking about it as a product we thought that the thing people would
use it for is coding, but we learned very quickly that people didn't just use it for coding, they
used it for code. So I think that's a really good point. I think that's a really good point.
I think people are gonna start to get more ideas for all sorts of stuff. So I kind of feel the
journey of Claude Code has been very surprising, and I have been learning so much just watching
how people use the product and how they abuse it and what they actually want to use it for,
and even if it's not designed for that. So I kind of feel the same way about Co-Work. I have some
ideas about what people are going to use it for, I kind of view these as hypotheses, and so I'm happy
to talk about it, happy to maybe I'll do a quick demo to show you some of the things that we use it
for. Yeah. So I think that's a really good point. I think people are gonna start to get more ideas
for what they use it for, but I think that it's gonna be pretty surprising. And I hope that I will
be surprised when we see how people actually use it in the wild. Yeah, I think that's always the
case with platforms, especially if you think about it, like when the makers of the app store
created the app store, you know, the initial apps was like, you know, a beer drinking app and like
a bunch of random apps like that. Did they know that, you know, Uber was gonna come out of that,
DoorDash was gonna come out of that, TikTok was gonna come out of that? Probably not. So I think
that what's really cool about the phase that we are in right now with Cloud Code and also
Cloud Cowork is we're all figuring it out at the same time. And none of us, including the creator,
have all the answers. But I agree with you, like what's, it's a good time to be sharing some,
you know, sharing what's working, what's not working. And, you know, if you're open to it,
let's screen share and get our hands dirty. Yeah, yeah, let's do it.
So what are we looking at?
Right now, Boris?
Yeah, so this is the this is the Cloud desktop app. So you just download it.
Cowork is only available for Mac OS, you know, Windows coming soon.
There's a few different tabs in the desktop app. So there's the chat, that's the default,
there's Cowork, that's the new one, and there's code and that's just Cloud Code.
Cowork under the hood, it's actually just Cloud Code. And so, you know, the agent that makes
Cloud Code awesome, we call it the Cloud Agent. It's also available as the Cloud Agent SDK,
you can use it programmatically, you can, you know, all sorts of companies build all sorts of
cool things on top of it. We actually use that same exact SDK directly in Cowork. So it's like,
you know, it's pretty cool. It's just kind of one way across everything. We have the best agent,
have the best agentic model might as well use it. And so what I'll do is just to kind of show
how to use this thing. And you know, like, when I think about agentic AI, this word agentic has sort
of lost all meaning because it's a little bit more complex than what we're used to. And so, you know,
it's just like used so much. So I feel like probably a lot of listeners have heard the word
agent, but they don't actually know what it means or, you know, they think it's like some like cool
AI or something. But it actually has like a very specific meaning in the AI world, which I think
has kind of been lost because a lot of the products that people have released and called
agentic in the past are not actually agentic. And so like, when you think about the AI products that
everyone's used, you know, like obviously Cloud Code, chat-based apps where you just chat with the
app kind of back and forth. So then, so that's kind of where we're at. So, yeah, it's kind of
kind of like a very specific meaning. So I think it's kind of like a very specific meaning in the
world, which I think has kind of been lost because a lot of the products that people have released in
the past are not actually agentic. So I think it's kind of like a very specific meaning in the
the past are not actually agentic. So I think it's kind of like a very specific meaning in the world.
The biggest difference with agents is it can take action. And, you know, it's not just text and it's
not just like web searching, but it can actually use tools on your computer. It can interact with
the world. And so for Anthropic from the very beginning, since before our models were good,
before like, you know, like Cloud 3 or whatever, this is a thing that we wanted to get really good
at because we felt that it's very important. And so from the start, we were like, you know,
from the start, we wanted our models to be really great at coding and then really great at tool use
and then really great at computer use. So it's kind of cool, like, you know, the last year,
seeing how people have been hacking quad code, it's pretty obvious this is kind of the place
that we should go. And so for people that have used quad code, you know, none of this will be,
you know, like too surprising. These are actually things that you can do. So really,
what we're trying to do is make this something that everyone can use in a way that's safe.
And so what I'm going to do is, you know, here on my desktop, I have this like
receipt of code that I'm going to use. And I'm going to go ahead and type in the code that I'm
going to use. And let's say I have the receipts folder. I have a few receipts in it. So I'm just
going to give Coavework access to my desktop. And you have to pick like which specific folders
I can see. By default, it can't see anything. So you have to kind of opt in to to let it access
specific folders. And so I'm going to say, you know, I can say, I have a receipts folder.
Can you rename the files
match the dates on the receipts.
So I think one interesting thing is when you're using
Co-work, it's really like it's operating with your files.
Like that's a big sort of mindset shift
that people should have.
It's almost like your operating system.
Is that right?
Yeah, exactly.
It's like it has your files, so the ones
that you give it access to.
But actually, the even cooler thing is it
can use all sorts of tools.
And so like files actually is like,
that's useful, but it's not like that cool.
What's actually much more interesting is it
can generate files for you.
So it can make presentations and things like this.
It can interact with any tool over MCP.
And it has built-in support for Chrome-based browsers.
So it can actually control your browser to do stuff.
And so I'll kind of show that a little bit.
So this is kind of the first step.
When you're first getting started with Co-work,
the thing I recommend is do exactly what I just did.
You know, just mount the folder.
Give Co-work access to it.
And just play around with it.
It's super useful for cleaning up files, organizing, things
like that.
And so here, it found these four receipts that I have.
It's asking me if one of the receipts, I guess,
is missing a date.
So should it just rename the others?
So I'll just say for one, it's, let's say it's up to you.
And then for two, I'll say, don't rename it.
And we actually call this reverse solicitation in the AI world.
So what this means is when the model is unsure about something,
it's going to ask you for clarification.
And we've sort of taught the model to be pretty good at this.
So instead of assuming, if it's unsure about something,
it's just going to ask you.
And so yeah, in this case, so it renamed the receipts.
So I'm just going to open this up to double check.
Yeah, cool.
And so the receipts were named a little bit better organized.
And so maybe we can do this.
We can do this.
And then what I can try next is, let's put this in a spreadsheet.
So it takes control of your computer, basically, in that sense, right?
If you allow it to take control.
Yeah, yeah, that's right.
And so we put so much work into safety and making sure
that as this happens, you don't accidentally shoot yourself in the foot
and delete files or whatever.
So there's just a huge amount of work that went into this.
And it starts at the model side, where for Anthropic,
from the very beginning, we were the AI safety lab, and that's the reason that we exist.
And so there's a lot of work into alignment and mechanistic interpretability and all these
ideas to make sure that the model does what you want in a way that's safe, kind of at
the model layer.
And this literally means studying the neurons, kind of the same way that you would study
neurons in the human.
And so you can identify structures, and you can study in a very scientific way as a blackbox
also.
So this is called alignment.
And then we do a whole bunch of other stuff.
So there's actually a whole virtual machine running under the hood.
And this is just to make sure that any actions taken are safe and don't affect your broader
system.
And then as of last week, there's also deletion protection.
So if you accidentally delete something, then you're going to get prompted first.
So the model can kind of make sure that that's actually a thing that you want to do.
Obviously, also, as we start interacting with the internet, something like prompt injection
is quite scary.
And so we built in a lot of protections against that.
Obviously, it's not perfect, and it's something we're iterating on.
But there's also part of the reason that we released this pretty early is we want to see
how people use it.
And a big part of making models safe isn't just studying them in a lab, but studying
them in the wild to see how it's useful.
And so this was pretty cool, right?
So we have this folder.
First it kind of renamed all my receipts.
I asked it to make a sheet.
It just made this spreadsheet.
So it's already here.
Maybe not.
Maybe I don't want a spreadsheet.
Maybe I want a Google Sheet.
So actually, that's so interesting, right?
Because I think where people stumble with tools like CoWork and Cloud Code is because
you can do anything, making it, of course, that makes sense, making it a Google Sheet.
But that's where it's so interesting that you really can treat it like a teammate in
that sense, right?
Go and do this thing.
The world is your oyster.
Whoa, what is happening right now?
Yeah.
So it's opening the browser.
And so here it's going to ask me for permission.
Just for this demo, I'm going to say always allow for the site.
But you can just say allow once or deny.
And so Quad's taking the wheel.
It's making a spreadsheet for me.
This is going to sort of take a while.
And so this is one of the things that we're iterating on is making this kind of computer
use a lot faster.
I remember, man, this is when I first joined Anthropic.
This was maybe...
This is like Sonnet 3.6 days or I forget what we called it, like Sonnet 3.5 new.
And that was the first model that I think we really started to crack computers.
And I remember I was sitting with my team and there was literally a researcher that
ran into the room in the movies and was like, oh my God, Quad knows how to use computers.
And we just had to order a pizza and it picked a pineapple pizza and then ordered it and
it asked us for a credit card.
And then we got that delivered to the office.
But it was tedious.
It took like an hour or something for it to click around.
And since then, we've been improving the model's ability to use a computer.
And so you can kind of see that here.
So here the Quad is typing and it's interacting with the spreadsheet and it can see what's
on the screen.
It can interact with it.
Anything that's in your browser, it can just use.
And could it use like email?
Let's say we wanted to send this to somebody, finance team.
Mm-hmm.
Maybe we'll get into it later.
But with things like connections and MCPs, is that possible?
Yeah, yeah, totally.
Okay.
So let's make this kind of a nice spreadsheet because we don't want to send a badly formatted
spreadsheet to our coworker.
But let's make it nice and then we can ask Quad to send it.
And so here it's kind of cool.
It's like it's still early days and so there's some formatting mistakes.
It didn't paste it exactly correctly, but it noticed it.
So notice that it's not actually split correctly.
And so now it's trying to format it.
Yeah.
So kind of notice this.
And yeah, Greg, to your point, it's funny, these use cases and the way that people are
going to use these tools, like I said at the start, it's going to be so surprising.
I'm just so excited to see how people use it.
And sort of the crazy thing about them is they're so general purpose.
It's sort of like a computer itself or like the internet or something.
Like you said, when you first had an iPhone, you would never have predicted that there
would be an Uber app at some point.
But that's what happened.
And I sort of feel like we're at the beginning of that, but for agents.
Yeah, I think it sounds so obvious in hindsight.
Like of course you have a phone with GPS.
Of course, right?
You're going to have things like Uber and DoorDash and stuff like that.
But I feel like, yes, you're right.
I think like what I'm trying to figure out in my mind, like I'm watching this and I'm
like, this is really cool.
But I'm thinking about like, okay.
Yeah.
So I'm like, you know, how do I audit like my entire company?
Like what are all the tasks that the company is doing?
How are they interacting with files and how are they using the internet and how are they
sending things?
And then what are opportunities I can use to like make my team and also my life more
productive?
That's what's going through my head right now.
Yeah, yeah, totally.
That's a great way to think about it.
And by the way, something that's kind of cool is, you know, as this is running, I'm just
going to make a new task and do something else.
Yeah.
I'm going to make a new task.
So, you know, what are some cool episodes?
Startup.
Cool.
And so while this one's running, we can like, we can let this one go too.
And I often have a bunch of tasks running in parallel too.
But yeah, that's exactly it.
It's like, you should just think about like, what's all like the tedious stuff?
What's all like the tedious stuff that you do every day?
And you can just throw all this stuff to co-work.
And I feel like this happened for coding over the last year because of course, engineers
and programmers are the earliest adopters.
So when the tooling first became able to do that kind of work, engineers adopted it first.
But you know, now this is coming.
Now this is possible for everyone else to use too.
So that's like, that's super exciting.
And when we talk to engineers about the way they like to use quad code, you know, they
run a bunch of quads in parallel.
They use it to automate the tedious stuff.
And I don't know, man, like for me, this is just the most fun I've ever had as an engineer
because I get to do the stuff that I enjoy and I just feel so productive because quad
does all the, you know, the stuff that I didn't want to do.
Okay.
So now we have this like, we have the spreadsheet.
This looks all right.
It's not too bad.
The data looks correct.
You know, one thing that's missing though is...
Oh, yeah.
Yeah.
It's not too bad.
We can add maybe like the totals, but I think for the sake of the demo, what I'm going to
do is I'm going to see if it can email it.
So just reading for audio listeners, can you open Gmail and send the sheet to Amy?
And wow.
Yeah.
So I'm going to say always continue.
So how is it going to know it's Amy, right?
It's going to pull up the contacts within Gmail.
Yeah, yeah, exactly.
So.
So it's going to send it to Amy.
Yeah.
That's exactly it.
It's going to interact with it the same way that, you know, anyone else would interact
with a computer.
And it's the same thing.
It can like click stuff.
It can read the screen.
Okay.
So compose window open.
Let me type Amy.
So you have like multiple...
When you're like locked in, so to speak, you're kind of, you have multiple of these windows
open at or multiple virtual machines open at the same time.
Yeah.
So you can see a bunch of these, you know, like five or five or 10 or whatever.
And so we can see the models, you know, trying to interact with this.
And so it filled out Amy.
And you know, by the way, just because this is, you know, going on YouTube, you know,
you're going to have some haters in the comments.
So we're just going to address them right now.
Someone in the comments is going to be like, but that's so slow.
I can do it faster myself or something.
What is your reaction?
Yeah.
Of course you can.
I mean, I think it's much faster and it's actually the same thing for a lot of quad
code, right?
Like, especially at the beginning, I could do it much faster.
But I think sort of two things happen.
One is that the model just gets better at doing it quickly.
And this is just something I would expect over time.
But then the second thing is because you can do multiple things in parallel, it's actually
a big time saver.
And so usually my workflow is I'll kick off, you know, like a few different tasks in parallel
and I'll just kind of like go back and forth between them.
And then I'll kind of tend to my quads, make sure they're in a good place, see if they
have any questions or anything like that.
So it's really a different kind of workflow.
Like I feel like now is the age of like kind of multi-quadding of parallelism of like not
going super deep on stuff, but kind of being more of a generalist and more tending to your
quads.
And so this was this other chat that we kicked off earlier.
And in this case, it sort of did some research.
So that's pretty cool.
So it didn't just go to, you know, like, oh, I'm going to do this.
I'm going to do this.
And it was like, oh, you know, like startup ideas, podcasts, website.
But it searched the internet, checked a bunch of different places, checked like someone's
notes about it.
Yeah, ten rules for quad code.
Yeah, I'll find that interesting too.
And let's see.
So it seems like this is the email is probably all drafted.
The draft has been saved.
Yeah.
Please send.
And I also use this for like Slack too.
Like a pretty common use case.
I'm doing maybe a couple of times a week is I have a spreadsheet where we track all
the teams work for the month or for the week or whatever.
And instead of having to bug everyone on the team to fill out the status, what I do is
I ask co-work to look at the spreadsheet, any column that's not filled out, just message
the engineer on Slack.
And it does that really well.
So you know, I just ask it to do that.
And then I go get a coffee and I don't have to do that anymore.
Do you think that co-work is going to be the gateway drug to cloud code?
Because for a lot of beginners, non-technical people, cloud code feels a bit overwhelming.
But when I'm watching you do this, this feels approachable.
Yeah.
I mean, I think it's like probably two kinds of users.
And it's also, it's funny.
Cloud code is built originally in a terminal.
And you know, nowadays it's available in the cloud mobile app.
It's available on the website, in the IDE, on Slack, on GitHub.
So you know, nowadays it's available everywhere.
But originally, it was built in a terminal.
And I never thought that most engineers would want to use a terminal because, you know,
it's scary.
It's like this thing that's sort of hidden away on the computer.
Like you know, only the most hardcore engineers want to actually work in a terminal day in
and day out.
And so it's surprising to me that most engineers wanted to use it.
What's even more surprising is a lot of non-engineers started to use it.
And that was the craziest thing.
And you know, looking at like the sales team at Anthropic, like the GTM team, half of them
use cloud code every week.
And looking at other non-technical people.
People at Anthropic, like designers, product managers, data scientists, pretty much all
of them use quad code every day.
So that's been like pretty surprising.
But my hypothesis is what they would prefer is actually something a little bit more like
this where you don't have to deal with a terminal and all that kind of thing.
You have a nice UI because you don't need access to bash and all that kind of stuff
because the model will just do it for you.
Yeah.
I think what I would love with something like this is, you know, automating.
And doing some of these processes.
It's like instead of doing one-offs, it's like any time this happens, I want you to
do this.
That's my dream.
Yeah.
It's a cool idea.
I'm excited to see like how it's tied into skills also.
I think it's something we're thinking about we haven't quite figured out yet.
Yeah.
Because like a skill, what is it?
It's essentially kind of a repeatable way to do something.
And so you saw that a little bit earlier up in this conversation where when quad was generating,
I don't know if you saw, but it actually loaded the skill.
And so we pre-packaged the skill for Excel and that's the way that quad knows how to
do it.
And so if you have some like weird file format, I don't know if you work with like AutoCAD
or if you work with, you know, like Salesforce, whatever it is, the tool that you use, you
just make a skill and then quad can do it for you.
That's interesting.
So if you have more skills, co-work and you're asking it, you know, to do things related
to those skills, co-work is more likely to use those skills.
So you might be able to get a better outcome out of co-work if you, you know, do some upfront
work to actually create some skills.
I think so.
Yeah.
Wow.
I think, I think that's exactly right.
Yeah.
Okay.
Well, that's good to know.
And, and you know, what else do we need to know about co-work?
Cause I know there's, you know, there's, you know, extensions.
There's, there's.
There's skills like walk us through some of, is there anything else that, you know,
we need to know in order to get the most out of, of the product?
You know, we, we tried to build co-work just to be pretty simple.
When we think about the different audiences we serve for an audience, like engineers,
they don't actually like simple, like simple is, is good by default, but engineers love
to hack their tools.
They love to customize their tools.
So that's actually really important.
So quad code is just like the most customizable coding agent.
It has just like so many extension points.
There's like, there's skills, there's custom agents there there's hooks.
There's an insane amount of configuration and settings that you can set.
You know, there, there's a very sophisticated permission system.
So there's all sorts of ways to customize it.
And this is because we know every engineer works different and everyone has different
preferences.
Everyone uses a different tech stack.
Everyone uses a different editor.
Everyone uses a different OS.
So we wanted to make sure it's really customizable for some of my co-work.
I think we're kind of starting.
The opposite direction and just keep it really simple at the start.
And so if you use core work, I would probably not customize too much.
Like if you have core work installed and you install the Chrome extension, that's pretty
much all you need and it'll do everything else for you.
I think over time, as you find yourself using maybe software that core work is not great
at, like that's the point to think about writing skills, but that wouldn't be my starting point.
Just start simple, like, you know, see how it works, see what's useful.
And I think also the other thing, you know, it's just.
It's so early.
This feels to me a lot like quad code a year ago where, you know, we released it before
it was early.
It was not very good yet.
It was like super buggy.
It kind of barely worked.
Like the model was not very good at coding a year ago and it kind of feels like that
to me.
But I think our work is actually a little bit better than quad code was when we first
released it because it's actually useful and you know, it's already a thing that I use
every day.
And yeah, I think in the first week we've, we've seen so much more.
Yeah.
Growth.
It's, it's been like a multiple of the growth that we saw with quad code the first week.
So that's very exciting.
It seems like this is something that people are already finding useful.
You know, we're recording this, what is it?
January 2026.
If we, if we come back here in 12 months, it's January 2027.
How do you think people are going to be using cowork?
You know, I know you don't have a crystal ball exactly, but what sort of use cases and
what is, what does the product look like?
Describe the world in January, 2027 with, with cowork.
Oh, geez, Greg, I plan in like a one week timeline.
The model is just changing so fast.
It's so hard.
And I just feel like, you know, like the model is it's advancing exponentially and just like
my puny human meat brain, like can't grapple with exponential.
It's like we think in linears.
And so I think this kind of exponential is just very, very difficult to plan around.
Okay.
But if, if I had to speculate.
A year ago I made, and I think Dario also made this prediction that by the end of the
year, people wouldn't be writing code anymore.
And I think that was like sometime mid you know, last year or something in, you know,
I, I code every day.
I ship, you know, two, 300 PRS every month or something like that.
And in the last two months, Claude Claude code has written a hundred percent of my code.
I haven't written a single line by hand.
And this is something like, I also predicted this, you know, like, you know, like, you're,
you know, you're looking at this model, you're looking at it, you're looking at it.
You're looking at it.
And I also predicted this, you know, like way back middle of last year.
It was sort of not intuitive because if you just think about kind of the experience at
the time you, you trace it linearly, there's just no way that the model would be at that
point.
So you really have to kind of believe in exponential and just literally like plot it out and kind
of follow the way that the line, the line goes.
That's the only way that you would have predicted this.
And it was just, it was absolutely right.
And so I think for coding, this is a word.
This is something that we're going to start to see in more and more places.
So I would be interested in seeing that if you, if you're going to do something that comes
for more and more kinds of code that the model is able to just do all of it.
And when we think about co-work, I think it's somewhat similar. I think it's a little bit
earlier. And I think what we're going to see is for all this kind of tedious tasks, like
connecting app A and B or kind of shuffling data back and forth or whatever, the model is just
going to be able to do it. And it's going to get increasingly good at it. I think in some ways,
it's a little scary. And in some ways, I think it's really exciting because you don't have to
spend your time on this toilsome work anymore. You can just focus on the work that you enjoy.
And also everyone, I think, just becomes much, much more productive
because you have an army of clods that can do this.
Okay. I like that feature. I like that feature a lot. It's a hard question. It's a hard question.
It's sort of like the genie's out of the bottle and it's hard to predict where the genie's going
to go. So I believe that co-work is the gateway drug to clodding.
Love that Bringing Pack and the Call of Duty editor to that line of work added
to that game a lot. So at the end of this episode, I'll hear stories like this and
some!"
Kyle spherical Hebrew
reibt
Using a Davidそうだ
Pottery Barn
pell
where there's very specific roles that you can hire to people.
And I do think that there's going to be this combination between skills
and these digital teammates that you're going to quote-unquote hire.
Yeah, that's super interesting.
Maybe we should make a bet and just see where it pans out in a year.
I have no idea, but it's definitely interesting to speculate
because I just feel like the way this technology goes
is so different than past technology waves.
It's sort of similar to the internet.
It's sort of similar to computers, maybe like telephones or something before that,
but the speed is just so much faster.
And because it's kind of piggybacking on all of this,
the internet could not exist without telephones
and phone lines being everywhere.
You couldn't have dial-up without it.
Mobile phones couldn't exist without the internet existing.
So it's sort of like every layer of the stack,
it just gets more and more powerful and it spreads more quickly.
And so it's on the back of all of this that AI can exist.
And yeah, it's just...
It's going to be very exciting to see where it goes.
I want to shift gears just for the last 10 minutes
because we mentioned Cloud Code.
You had a post that went absolutely viral.
I think you know what post I'm going to talk about.
99,000 bookmarks, which is crazy.
And I'm going to share my screen.
I want to go over it a little bit.
This is me learning to use Twitter.
I think I made an account like a decade ago and I haven't really used it.
So...
It's funny.
Yeah, it's been fun to learn.
You have just a few tweets, but this one, you figured it out.
You say,
I'm Boris, I created Cloud Code.
Lots of people have asked for how I use Cloud Code,
so I want to show off my setup a bit.
My setup might be surprisingly vanilla.
Cloud Code works great out of the box,
so I personally don't customize it much.
There's no one correct way to use Cloud Code.
We intentionally built it in a way that you can use it,
customize it, and hack it however you'd like.
Each person on the Cloud Code team use it very differently.
So here it goes.
Could you just talk about some of the...
Just expand on some of these and what you were saying on here?
Because I thought it was really interesting.
Yeah, I'd love to.
So this first one, it's very similar to what I was showing in co-work,
where my job now isn't to go super deep on one task.
It's to do a bunch of tasks in parallel.
And so, you know, when I'm working on Cloud Code, I usually work in a terminal.
Okay.
back and forth a little bit. And then once the plan looks good, I usually go into just auto
accept edits right away. Because I think with Opus 4.5, once the plan is good, the model can
just execute it pretty much perfectly. This is definitely not the case with previous models.
And so I think there was a lot of excitement about Opus 4.5 over the last couple months. And I think
this is kind of one of the big reasons. It's just gotten very good at coding, but also excellent at
planning. So once the plan is good, the code is good. And so yeah, my work now is just jumping
between tabs, kind of tending to the clouds, make sure they're unblocked, answering their questions.
With co-work, I think it's actually quite similar now.
I like that. I'm going to quote you on that. Once the plan is good, the code is good. Because
that's so true, right? Because if you nail the plan, the code should, the agents should do the
work. Yeah, exactly. I think sometime last year, there was all this buzz about Spectrum development.
Yeah. And it just feels a little too QT and a little too rigid to me. But I think this is sort
of a form of Spectrum development. It's like there is some kind of spec. I think it's just a plan.
That's all it has to be. It's just a text file. It doesn't have to be in a particular format.
Once you have that, you're good. Number two, you say, I also run five to ten
clouds in parallel with my local clouds. As I code in my terminal, I will often hand off local
sessions to web using and or manually kick off sessions. I'm not sure if that's the right word.
Yeah. I think that's a good one. I think that's a good one. I think that's a good one. I think that's
a good one. I think that's a good one. I think that's a good one. I think that's a good one.
I think that's a good one. I think that's a good one. And sometimes I will teleport back and
forth. I also start a few sessions from my phone, obviously from cloud iOS app. You got to every
morning and throughout the day and check in on them later. What do you mean by that?
This morning I kicked off, I think, like three clause as soon as I woke up.
I just had to like some thought in the morning about, well, maybe I should like build this thing
or fix this bug or whatever. I was like checking Twitter and someone had a bug report. So I just
opened my phone and you know, the cloud app you on the on the left side, you could delete,
there's a little menu and there's a code tab. So you can just like access quad code there.
That's what I use for a lot of my code. And it's funny, I never would have guessed that this is
the way that I code. If you asked me a year ago, I would never have predicted that the way I code
now is like probably half of it is just on my phone and it sort of just works. And then web
is kind of the other part. So once I've run out of tabs, because it's just like, you know, it's
kind of a pain to manage a bunch of different git checkouts, because in each tab in my terminal,
I actually have a totally separate git checkout.
And I don't really use work trees or anything like that. I just keep it pretty simple.
And in web, if I just ran out of terminal tabs, I'll start like, overflowing to web and starting
tasks there.
Beautiful. So yeah, I also, so recommending use iOS, use web, open multiple, like that's,
that's, you'll get the most out of it that way.
Yeah, absolutely. Yeah. And we have an Android app now, too. So yeah, just like use the mobile
app and see how far that can take you.
If it's, if it's a web app, yeah, that's a good way to do that. But yeah, yeah, if it's a web app,
then yeah, you can add apps on it, you can add apps on it, you can add apps on it, you can add apps on it,
If it's not giving you good results, also make sure that you tune the environment setup
and make sure that you invest in your quad.md.
That's super duper important.
And I talk about that in number four also.
Number three, you say, I use Opus 4.5 with thinking for everything.
It's the best coding model I've ever used.
And even though it's bigger and slower than Sonnet, since you have to steer it less
and it's better at tool use, it's almost always faster than using a smaller model in the end.
And cheaper.
It's sort of counterintuitive.
And I had to explain this to people a few times.
But because the model is smarter, it actually uses less tokens in the end.
And it uses so many less tokens, it's often cheaper than using a smaller,
less intelligent model, even though the per token cost for that model is lower.
So a little counterintuitive.
But yeah, just use the smartest thing if you can.
Well, we appreciate that.
You know, we appreciate that.
And we appreciate that.
Number four, our team shares a single Cloud MD for the Cloud Code repo.
We check it into Git.
The whole team contributes multiple times a week.
Anytime we see Cloud do something incorrectly, we add it to the MD so Cloud knows not to do it next time.
Other teams maintain their own Cloud MDs.
It is each team's job to keep theirs up to date.
And the Cloud MD is just a text file.
So there's no special format.
People ask this all the time.
Is there some special format that it has to be in?
No.
It's just like it's just a text file.
So you can put whatever you want in it.
This is a screenshot of our Cloud MD.
This is literally it.
So just really simple.
And, you know, you could format this kind of however you want.
Love it.
And then finally, I think, yeah, number five.
Oh, no, you have a you've got a few more.
So number five, during code review, I'll often tag at dot cloud on my coworkers PRs to add something to the Cloud MD as part of the PR.
We use the Cloud Code GitHub action.
For this, it's our version of Dan Schipper's compounding engineering.
What do you mean?
What is compound engineering?
Yeah.
Oh, my God.
So there's actually like two bugs in this tweet.
I think I think Dan actually calls a compound engineering, not compounding engineering.
And then the at doc file.
This is me writing how to use X.
But it's actually at quad.
There's there's no DAW.
I just didn't.
I think there's like an actual user or something whose name is quad.
I didn't want to tag them.
But yeah.
So so what you do is in quad code, you run this slash command slash.
install GitHub action. And what this does is it installs the cloud app in your GitHub repo.
And what that lets you do is you can then app mention cloud whenever you want and just have
it make changes. And it can just work on PR. So it'll push back to your branch and it'll push
the changes right back. You can also tag it on issues. You can tag it kind of wherever.
I do this multiple times a day. It's really, really useful. I think one of the most common
use cases is just like little fixes. I think the other one is updating the CloudMD to keep
the knowledge base up to date. And you should never have to comment about something twice.
Back when I was at Meta, something that I did is, this is like in a previous life,
in a previous job, something that I did is every code review that I did,
I would keep a spreadsheet of all the issues that came up. And whenever the same kind of
issue came up again, I would just like tally it up in the spreadsheet. And whenever something hit,
I think like five.
Or 10 tallies or something. I would write a lint rule. And what that is, is it's a way to
automate that part of the code review. So I don't have to comment about it again. And that was back
in the days before LLMs and before the model was any good at coding. And so this is the equivalent
nowadays. You just tag cloud and you have it update your CloudMD, which is your team's knowledge base.
So really simple. And what this means is you don't have to point anything out twice. I'm curious to
see what this looks like for cowork. I don't think we figured that out yet, but definitely for cloud
code.
CloudMD is kind of the, this is the one, the one thing that you should all be updating all the time.
Love it. Number six, most sessions start in plan mode. If my goal is to write a pull request,
I will use plan mode, go back and forth with cloud until I like its plan. From there,
I switch into auto accept, edit, edits mode, and cloud can usually one shot it. A good plan
is really important.
Yeah. Like I said, planning is just the most underused feature in cloud code. Actually,
a lot of people use it, but I think, I think it's a good thing.
Yeah. It's, it's a no brainer. So if you aren't already doing this, please do. Do we've got,
you know, we're not going to have time to do all of them. What are the, I don't think,
because you have a hard stop. Do you want to pick one or two to end with?
Yeah, let's do, let's do maybe number 13.
Yeah. Number 13. I think this is probably in addition to using Opus for when people
ask about how to get better performance out of cloud code, there's three things that I
recommend almost every time. Number one is use Opus 4.5 with thinking always don't try
to use a different model because Opus will just give you better results and more efficiency
overall. The second thing is make sure you have a good quantum deal.
And then the third thing is this, this tip number 13, which is give quad a way to verify
its output. And so we just kind of saw with cowork, how good quad is at using the Chrome
extension in order to write email and in order to work with sheets. And it's exactly the same thing.
If I'm building an app, I always use the Chrome extension to have quad test its own work.
And if quad can verify its own output, their result is going to be way, way better.
And it's sort of like, you know, imagine that you're a painter and you're, you know,
you make paintings and they have to be like pretty good.
Maybe, maybe even like photo realistic or something, or just like, you know, some kind
of like very detailed style and you're, you have to wear a blindfold.
You're just not going to be that good. It's not going to come out that great.
Or it's the same thing for an engineer. Like if you have to write code, but you can never run
the code or you can never see the output and you can never see the website, it's just not going to
be good. And so it's the same thing with quad. As the model gets more intelligent, that first
shot is going to get better and better, but really you want to give it a way to verify the output.
And it'll be much better. So this is like running tests. If you're an engineer,
starting a server, also, if you're an engineer or, you know, seeing, seeing the output in a simulator
or in a browser. Amazing. And the ultimate tip, I guess, is just get your hands dirty, right?
I think that's it. Yeah. I mean, there's no right, there's no one right way to use the stuff.
Like, you know, see, see what's useful. See what's not. Find your own workflows. It's sort of,
I heard someone describing quad code as like a find your own path.
Book, you know, like one of those books where you have to like, do you do, do you go to the
dungeon or do you explore the forest? Like this kind of thing, or, or like a, like an old, like
RPG video game. So it's kind of like that. It's like, it's very free form. There's no one right
way to do it. So just see what works for you. Boris, I appreciate you taking the time,
the generosity to spill the sauce and just to, to share with us how we can get the most out of both
cowork and cloud code. Everyone's thinking about it and everyone's trying to, you know,
especially on this podcast, you know, the startup ideas podcast, you have millions of people who are
trying to figure out how I can be more productive and how I can build businesses around some of
these things. So thank you. Thank you for the time. I'll include links on where to follow Boris. He
doesn't tweet a lot, but when he tweets it's, it's worth paying attention to. And I just have,
I want to leave with one thing just cause my audience would kill me if I didn't ask
this. So as you know, Boris, I'm from French Canada and we speak French, obviously in French,
Canada.
And I call Claude, Claude. Am I the only one?
Oh man. You're probably not the only one. A lot of the world speaks French.
Which one sounds better? What feels right to you?
I mean, to me, Claude sounds better. It's like Jean-Claude Van Damme,
even though people would say Jean-Claude Van Damme. It's like, that's my take. That's my
hot take. To me, it sounds better. Oh, you know, Greg, I'm going to,
I'm going to today around the office, I'm just going to call it Claude and we'll see what people
say. I'll report back. Okay. Report back. All right. Sounds good. Boris,
thanks again for coming on and I'll see you next time.
Yeah. Thanks so much, Greg.