So last time we were talking about
generative models and we started off
with some discussion of generative
versus discriminative models and recall
that these are basically both different
flavors of probabilistic models. Um but
it depends on what we're trying to
predict, what we're conditioning on and
really critically what we're normalizing
over. So we talked about discriminative
models where you're trying to predict
the label Y conditioned on your data X,
generative models where you're trying to
just learn a probability distribution
over your data X and conditional
generative models where you want to
model the data X conditioned on some
user input Y um or label Y. Um and
recall that um these differ in that what
you're trying to normalize over uh
because probabilities distributions
introduce this normalizing effect where
all things that you're that we're all
where different kinds of things need to
compete for probability mass due to this
normalization constraint of probability
distributions.
Um and last time we also went through
this taxonomy of different categories of
generative models because it turns out
this area of generative modeling has
been something people have studied for a
very long time come with a lot of
different categories of methods to try
to solve variance of these problems. So
we went through this family tree of
generative models um where we have exp
where last time we talked about these
explicit density models where the model
outputs some measure some quantity that
you can that some quantity P of X um
either either the exact predicted P of X
in the case of tractable density models
or some approximate version of P of X in
the case of these approximate density
models and then in the case of tract
tractable density we saw auto
reggressive as a category of model and
we saw variational auto-enccoders as an
example of something that gives you some
approximate density.
So recall that auto reggressive models,
what we did is we took our our our image
or more generally whatever kind of data
we're working with and we break it up
into a sequence. Um and then for the
case of image data, we typically treat
this as a sequence of pixel values or
even sub pixel values. Um and we usually
want these to be discreet. So you treat
those subpixel values as um 8 bit
integers that can each take a value 0 to
255. you string this out into a long uh
into a long sequence of integers and
then model this in some using some
discrete autogressive sequence model
typically an RNN or a transformer.
Then we also saw the variation
variational autoenccoders which were
another uh um explicit density model but
now they compute not the exact density
but some approximation to the density in
in in particular a lower bound to the
density. Um so by to do this we train we
jointly trained some uh encoder network
which is going to input the data X and
output a distribution over latent codes
Z um and a decoder network which is
going to input a latent code Z and
output a predicted uh piece of data X
and we were able to jointly train these
two networks the encoder and the decoder
to maximize this variational uh to to
max to to maximize this variational
lower bound to our likelihood function.
Um recall that likelihood, maximum
likelihood is one of the key insights
behind all generative modeling that we
of that often our our objective function
for training generative models is
somehow to maximize the likelihood of
the data that we observe that comes from
um from our true data distribution.
So today we're going to continue our
discussion of generative models and
explore this other half of the family
tree um these implicit density models.
So in in implicit density models, we are
no longer going to get access to some
actual density value P of X, but these
models will sort of implicitly model the
probability distribution and even though
we can't compute a density value P of X
for any piece of data X, we will be able
to sample from the underlying
distribution that these models learn. Um
so we'll be able to draw samples from
the learned distribution even if we
can't output an actual density value. Um
so the first such model that we'll
explore are generative adversarial
networks or um usually called GANs.
And it's useful to contrast GANs with
the variational autoenccoders and auto
reggressive models that we've seen so
far. So like we just said um auto
reggressive models are are likelihood
based method. Um their training
objective is maximum likelihood. So you
write down this parameterized function
that is your P of X where X is a piece
of data and then you maximize this uh
over the data that you observe trying to
do maximum likelihood and variational
autoenccoders sort of follow this
similar idea where we can where we write
down this um approximation to P of X and
then maximize that approximation to P of
X. Um and now very generative
adversarial networks will do something a
little bit different. They will give up
on directly modeling that P of X as we
just said. Um but even though they don't
explicitly model the p of x or let us
get out those density values, they will
give us some way to sample from the
underlying distribution that the that
the model is fitting.
Um so the setup here is um that we'll
start by having some finite samples of
data x i which are assumes to be drawn
from some true data distribution p data.
Um and our goal is we want to be able to
draw samples from p data. And recall p
data is something like the true
distribution of the universe. This is
the distribution that the universe uses
to give you samples of your data. And
this is likely a very complicated
distribution. It involves physics. It
involves history. It involves social
political constraints maybe, right?
There's a lot of complication that goes
into all the stuff happening in the
universe that gives rise to the data
that you see. um and somehow we want to
model that fit some approximate model
that tries to match that true data
distribution as well as possible and
then allow us to draw new samples from
our fitted distribution that look like
the original data samples that we
observed.
So the way that we're going to do this
is um by introducing a latent variable
Z. Um this looks kind of like the latent
variable Z that we saw in um variational
autoenccoders where it's going to give
where the this latent variable Z is
going to be distributed according to
some known prior distribution P of Z
that we will write down and control
ourselves and usually this is going to
be a unit gausian or or a uniform
distribution but typically a unit
gausian something very simple that we
know how to sample from we know the
analytical properties of um and now the
setup is that we're going to um imagine
some data generating process that our
network is going to model. So here um
we're going to imagine that we sample a
Z according to our known distribution P
of Z um to get a sampled Z, pass that
sampled Z through a generator network
that G of Z um and then that X is going
to be a sample from some generator
distribution PG. Um and as we vary the
parameters or the architecture or the
training of our generator network that
is going to induce different kinds of
distributions that we sample from in
this PG distribution. So the whole goal
in GAN training is to try to force this
PG distribution which is induced by our
generator network. We want that PG
distribution to match the true P data
distribution as close as possible. And
because if they match then we could
sample a Z pass it through our generator
and now we have a Z now we have a sample
of sampled piece of data that looks a
lot like our P data.
So the the picture for this is something
like the following. We'll imagine
sampling Z from our PZ to get a a
concrete latencer
G and that will give us a generated
image. So the generator network
basically is trained to convert a sample
from a known distribution Z into a
sample of our data distribution. But now
the question is how can we force these
outputs? How can we force the induced
generator distribution PG? How can we
force this to match the data
distribution P data? Um and the trick in
generative adversarial networks is that
we're going to introduce another neural
network to do that task for us. Right?
In the previous versions of of gener of
generative modeling um VAEs and
autogressive models, we tried to write
down some objective function that we
could minimize that would force our fit
distribution to match the data
distribution. Here we're going to
relinquish that control and basically
have ask another neural network to solve
that task for us. Um so in particular
we're going to train another neural
network called the discriminator D. And
this discriminator is going to be tasked
with inputting a ner inputting an image,
sometimes a real image, sometimes a fake
image. And it's going to classify
whether the real whether that image was
fake or real. Um, and then the idea is
that these two these two networks are
going to fight. We're going to train the
generator to try to fool the
discriminator and we're going to train
the discriminator as a classification
model to try to correctly discriminate
or classify between real data and fake
data. And the intuition is that as these
two networks fight then ideally the
discriminator will get better. It will
get really good. The discriminator will
get really good at at determining
features of real data from fake data.
And once the discriminator gets really
good then in order to fool the
discriminator into thinking that the
generated samples are classified as
real. The generator data will need to
get closer and closer to producing
samples that look like true data. Um so
that's the kind of intuition between
generative adversarial networks. So
question is does the generator network
get feedback from the discriminator on
whether it's classifying correctly? U
yes and that's crucial for this whole
process working and the type of feedback
it gets is gradients right this this
whole thing this composite system of the
generator and the discriminator are just
neural networks we know how to compute
gradients through those and those
communicate through that generated
image. So we're going to back propagate
from the discriminator all the way
through the generated image into the
generator. So that's how the generator
is going to learn from the
discriminator.
And then more concretely, we need to
write down some actual equations, some
actual math that we're going to use to
concretize this intuition. So in
particular, um we're going to jointly
train the generator G and the and the
discriminator D um with this miniax
game. Um this equation looks maybe a
little bit daunting, so we'll walk
through each of the terms one by one.
So here we're going to color code this
and say that the generator is going to
be um in blue, the discriminator is
going to be in red. Um and the
discriminator is going to be a function
um that inputs a piece of data x and
outputs the probability that that data
is real. So in particular d ofx equals 0
means that the discriminator has
classified that piece of data x as fake.
Um d of x= 1 means that the
discriminator has classified that piece
of data as real. Um of course those are
the extreme cases. is the discriminator
in practice will output some probability
that gives you a soft a soft version in
between those two decisions.
Now um and now imagine what happens if
we fix the generator G and just imagine
this problem from the perspective of the
discriminator. So then from the
perspective of the discriminator there's
two terms here. One this says this first
term says the discriminator wants d ofx=
1 for real data. Remember d ofx equals 1
means that the discriminator says that
it's real. Um, and this this uh this
expectation basically says we're going
to draw data data samples X from the
true P data distribution. We're going to
pass those through the discriminator and
then take a log because you know we
almost always work in log space when
working with probabilities. And remember
log is a is a monotonic function. So um
maximizing maximizing log of x is the
same as maximizing x. So in this case um
this is saying this this is saying that
the we want to maximize log of d ofx for
real data which is equivalent to saying
d ofx equals 1 for real data. Um now on
the other side um this is saying that
we're going to draw take an expectation
by sampling prior's z uh sorry sampling
latence z according to our known prior p
of z. We're going to take those z's pass
them through the generator um which
should give us a generated data sample
and then pass that generated data sample
through the discriminator. Um and now
the discriminator wants to classify
these as these are fake samples. So the
discriminator wants to classify these as
fake. So we need to somehow invert that
that that that expression on the left.
So here um we want d of xals 0 to be
fake. So one way to say that is uh is to
maximize log of 1 minus d of g of z. So
this term on the right says the
discriminator wants d ofx equals 0 for
fake data. Um and the term on the left
says discriminator wants d ofx= 1 for
real data. Okay. So that's what the
discriminator is trying to do. The
discriminator is trying to correctly
just do this classification task between
generated samples from between generated
samples and real samples from our data
set and try to classify them correctly
as real or fake. Now look at this from
the from the perspective of the
generator. So imagine fixing the
discriminator and looking at this setup
only from the perspective of a generator
uh with a fixed discriminator. Um now in
this case this first term doesn't depend
on the generator at all because this
first term was just about the getting
the discriminator to correctly classify
the real data samples. Um so this the
generator only cares about this term on
the right. Um and intuitively we want
the generator to fool the discriminator
into thinking that its samples are real.
So that means that the the generator
wants d ofx equals 1 for fake data. So
the term is the same. Um we draw a
sample z according to p of z. um pass it
through the generator to get a generated
sample. Pass it through the
discriminator to get the discriminator's
predicted probability on that sample. Um
and now the
now recall the generator wants d ofx
equals 1. So rather than maximizing this
like we did from like the discriminator
wanted to instead we're going to try to
minimize this from for the for the for
the from the perspective of the
generator.
And that gives us this uh this miniax
game. So in particular we can abstract
away all this math by writing it as uh
some some scalar function V as a
function of G and D. Um and then we say
that the the discriminator wants to
maximize V. The generator wants to
minimize V. Um and there's this they're
going to fight against each other in
that way. And then to optimize this
we're going to basically run some
gradient descent loop taking alternating
steps trying to minimize and maximize
this with respect to the parameters of
the generator and discriminator. So um
loop while true forever then update d
acc according to take a gradient descent
step um derivative of v with respect to
d and then step plus that gradient
because remember discriminator is trying
to maximize this. So we want to do
gradient ascent to try to maximize this
this uh this term. Um and then after we
make an update on the discriminator
weights then we'll make an update on the
generator weights by taking derivative
of that um of that uh of that v with
respect to the generator weights g and
now take a gradient descent step on v
because the generator wants to minimize
that objective. Um so that's basically
our our training that's basically the
way that we train generative adversarial
networks. Um, we've got this this thing
V, which is the value of our miniax
game. And we're going to take
alternating gradient ascent and gradient
descent weights on that objective V. Um,
in order it like alternatively up
alternatingly update the generator and
discriminator.
And one thing that's really important to
realize when we're training generative
adversarial networks is that this V is
not a loss function. Um that means there
is no like the the absolute value of V
basically does not tell us anything
about how well the generator and
discriminator are solving this problem
or how well or or really the thing we
care about is how well is that induced
PG distribution matching the data
distribution and just looking at the
value of V doesn't really tell us
anything about that right because the
value of V sort of depends on how good
the discriminator is right if the
discriminator is really bad then it's
really easy for the generator to fool
this and get good get good numbers or if
the discriminator is really good then
the generator has to be really good. So
there can be sort of different settings
of D and V D and G that will lead to the
exact same value for V. Um and that
means that generative adversarial
networks are often really hard to train.
Um and even hard to tell when they are
doing a good job at training. Right?
Normally when you train neural networks
you have a loss. You try to minimize the
loss with respect to the parameters of
your network and you want to see that
loss go down over the course of
training. But you don't have that with
generative adversarial networks. You
have the generator loss. you have the
discriminator loss. You can try to plot
them, but in general they're pretty
they're pretty meaningless. So with
generative adversarial networks, they're
really hard to train. Um one I think one
this objective is sort of fundamentally
unstable. You're sort of trying to do
jointly maximize and minimize the same
quantity with respect to different parts
different sets of parameters of the
network. So that's kind of inherently a
difficult optimization problem. And then
even worse, you don't have any value to
look at to tell whether or not you're
making progress towards a good solution.
So generative adversarial networks um
they're they're pretty effective but
they're really hard to train and really
hard to tune and really hard to make
progress on.
So um that's that's sort of the main
takeaway for generative adversarial
networks. You know there is um one
little trick that is kind of useful to
think about for when training GANs is
that um just to kind of imagine the
training dynamics of these things. So at
the very start of imagine at the very
beginning of training your generator is
randomly initialized your discriminator
is randomly initialized. What's going to
happen? Well, at the very start of
training, then your generator is
producing completely random noise. That
completely random noise is going to look
very different from real images. So, at
the very beginning of training, when the
generator is terrible, then the
discriminator has a very easy problem.
So, typically within a couple
iterations, um the discriminator can
like really immediately pick up between
real images and these totally garbage
random fake images that the random that
the random generator is giving you. So
that means that at the very start of
training um the generator is the
discriminator is quickly going to learn
to classify these real these um real and
fake pretty quickly with pretty high
probability. Um so then it's interesting
to plot what is d of g of z uh sorry
what is the what is the what is what is
this term um as a function of d of g of
z right because that's basically the
loss fun that's basically the loss
function from the perspective of the
generator. So then from the perspective
of the generator, um we're we're we kind
of at the beginning of training are
somewhere all the way over here. So the
discriminator is doing a really good job
at treating generated samples as fake,
classifying them as fake at the
beginning of training, which means that
from the discriminator's perspective,
it's trying to optimize a loss function
that looks something like this. Um and
if you'll notice something, this loss
function is flat um or very close to
flat at the place where the generator is
trying to optim optimize its parameters.
So this means that in like in practice
when you use this naive objective for um
training GANs then the generator has a
really hard time learning at the
beginning of training. Oh good question
is um how do you assemble the data set
like how do we generate a photo of a
unicorn if if nothing no unicorn exists.
So so this um this P data that that's
kind of your choice of P data right so
whatever data set you happen to assemble
from your training set that's you
choosing what is the P data that you're
trying to model. So in general, if you
want to generate a sample of a thing
that looks nothing like anything that
you've ever seen before, you're out of
luck. It's not going to happen. Um, so
the only way that you're generally going
to draw samples is if you have something
in your training data set that looks
kind of like that. So these networks do
like all generative models and all
neural networks really do generalize a
little bit, right? So then the hope is
that you know maybe you've never seen a
photorealistic image of a unicorn
wearing a Santa Claus hat, but you've
seen photorealistic images of horses.
You've seen photorealistic images of
Santa Claus hats. You've seen drawings
of unicorns. You've seen drawings of
horses. And somehow you've got enough
stuff, even if you've never seen the
exact composition of attributes that you
want to generate. Um you've seen enough
stuff that's close enough to it that the
model can generalize and give you
something new. And that's always the
hope here. What does this look like from
the discriminator's perspective? So then
like well then if I generated this image
of a photorealistic unicorn wearing a
Santa Claus hat then maybe all the
textures are really perfect like the
lighting is perfect the shadows are
perfect the leaves are perfect. So
there's no real evidence in the data in
that sample itself to say that this is
obviously wrong. Um maybe if the
discriminator was really really smart
then the discriminator could somehow
know that unicorns don't really exist
and having a perfectly photorealistic
image of them isn't likely to happen.
But that's a like that's a pretty hard
semantic problem to solve. So in
practice generator discriminators tend
not to really be that smart. Yeah, good
good question. The cost the idea is why
don't we look at two curves? Why don't
we look at one curve saying how good the
discriminator is? Why don't we look at
one curve saying how low good the
generator is? Feel free to plot them.
They tend to look really useless. Um and
there's probably literally hundreds of
research papers of people trying to
solve this problem and figure out how do
we tweak the GAN objective? How do we
not use a log? How do we use a a wazer
sign something a something something?
like put all kinds of crazy stuff into
this to make those curves more
interpretable. Hundreds of papers
written about it like 5 years of of
thousands of people's time I don't think
anybody came up with a with a good
solution. Um so still even after like
hundreds thousands of papers training
GANs that kind of they ended up a lot of
people still end up using this vindilla
formulation which tends not to give you
very interpretable curves even when you
split it up that way. The question is,
is it really is is what happens to the
discriminator early in training really
important? And the answer is no because
this is unlike any other classification
problem we've ever seen before because
this is a non-stationary distribution,
right? When you train an image
classifier on imageet or cir or
something like that, the data set is
fixed and the and the model is just
trying to classify that static data set.
Well, but in the case of GAN training,
the data set that it's trying to fit is
changing under it during the course of
training because you know even at the
beginning of training, maybe it's the
the generated images look really bad.
it's easy to solve the problem, but then
the generator gets better and now the
data set that it's that the
discriminator is trying to discriminate
changes under it during the course of
training. So that means that it's a
non-stationary problem and you know with
very complicated learning dynamics.
>> Yeah, good question. Um can you does do
these get caught in local minima? Are
there way to kick them out of local
lumina train for a while kick them out?
I think again hundreds of papers,
thousands of papers, lots of heristics,
nothing really stuck
correct. So you have to train the you
have to train this end to end. So
gradients from the discriminator always
propagate into the generator. Um if you
did like so in particular through this
term on the right. So the the only way
that you're ever getting gradients onto
the generator's parameters is actually
through the discriminator. Right?
There's I mean unless you have some
regularizer in here, but there's no
auxiliary term that's telling the
generator what to do other than the
gradients that gets through the
discriminator. And that lead that's
again leading to part of the the
unstable learning problem. Correct? So
the that that P data distribution that's
going to stay fixed over the course of
training. All right. So we said um you
know there's this problem that the
generator gets low gradients at the
course of training. There's a little
hack here where rather than um minimize
rather than trying to maximize log of 1
minus d of g of z, you can instead
minimize minus log of d of g of z
instead you can convince yourself
offline that those are roughly
equivalent. Um but the tlddr is then it
gives you a better curve for the
generator to get better gradients at the
start of training. Um so that's really
important. And whenever you're training
GANs from scratch using this sort of uh
log objective, then this uh this trick
to use the modified loss for the
generator is really important in
practice. So that means that there
actually is a a one V that you're
computing for the generator, one V that
a different V that you're computing for
the discriminator. Um and they aren't
quite the same.
Okay, there's another question of why
might this be a good objective. Um and I
used to have slides that walked through
this proof um step by step, but I don't
think we have time for that today. So
I'll just give you the TLDDR and uh we
can refer you to something offline to
check. Um but the the TLDDR is that this
objective is good because you can write
down this optimal discriminator, right?
So you know this is a this is a nested
optimization problem where there's an
inner maximization over D and outer
minimization over G. So if you do a
little bit of math, you can actually
solve this um in this inner maximization
problem and write down what is the
optimal gener what is the optimal
discriminator. This should actually be
the op this is the optimal discriminator
with respect to a particular generator
G. Um and you can just write this down
of course even though you can write it
down. You can never compute it because
it depends on P data. Um and you can
never compute P data because if you had
access to the P data density you'd be
done. So you can write this down as an
equation on a slide or on a piece of
paper but you can never compute it. Um
and then uh once you have this inner
objective once you have um sort of
maximized this inner objective by
writing down the optimal discriminator
then you can show that the outer
objective is minimized if and only if PG
PG of X is equal to P data. So at least
theoretically um kind of the the optimum
state of both the discriminator and the
generator actually occurs uniquely when
PG is equal to P data. Um so that that
kind of makes us feel good but there's a
lot of caveats to that theoretical
result. Um the one is that they both
assume of infinite potential capacity
for G and D. Um that those those both
assume that your generator and
discriminator can in principle represent
any function which of course they can't
because they are neural networks of a
fixed size and capacity. Um this also
tells us absolutely nothing about
whether or not we will converge to this
solution. So even though there is this
optimum point in this objective
landscape um you know there this tells
us absolutely nothing about whether we
can ever reach there via gra v via this
gradient descent gradient ascent um
especially with a finite number of data
samples. So there's this weak there's
this um sort of comforting theoretical
results that there is some theoretical
justification to GANs but in practice
you know this doesn't really hold or
give us very strong guarantees.
Um, so these GANs, you know, in
practice, the your your generator G and
your discriminator D both are going to
be parameterized as neural networks. Um,
and they used to be CNN's. Uh, the GANs
kind of fell out of favor before before
VITs became popular, but I'm sure they
would work with VITs as well. Um, and
the first GAN that really gave
non-trivial results was called DC GAN
that had this five layer comnet
architecture which gave these pretty
what were at the time pretty exciting
samples. Um, and I mentioned DC GAN
because the first author, Alec Radford
at all, you know, for most people doing
DC GAN would have been a highlight of
their career. But for Alec Radford, it
wasn't nearly enough for him because the
next project he worked on right after DC
GAN, does anybody know
>> GPT?
>> GPT. Um, so Alec Radford, you know, DC
GAN was kind of a lowlight in his
career. He went on to do uh GPT1 and
GPT2 um as well as some other amazing
work at OpenAI. So I think there's this
really cool connection between um you
know people that were working on
generative modeling of images actually
jumped over to do generative modeling of
discrete text data and did some of the
really important work there.
Um and one of the you know the only
other GAN um paper that I'm going to
highlight is called style GAN. Um I'm
not really going to walk you through the
details of this one other than to kind
of point you at it as like a good one to
read if you want to know kind of the the
best practices of GANs. They use a much
more complicated architecture um but
they get pretty good results in
practice. And one really nice thing
about GANs is that they actually tend to
learn something smooth in the latent
space. So what I mean that is that if we
have two latent vectors Z0 and Z1 and we
interpolate between them that is you
like draw a sample Z0 from your from
your from your gausian you draw a sample
Z1 from your Gausian then you
interpolate some kind of curve between
Z0 and Z1 then for every point along the
curve we're going to generate a sample
um using through our uh using our
generator. Then if we do that, we tend
to get smooth interpolations to this
latent space, which is something really
cool with GANs. And here's an example of
this latent space interpolation from the
style GAN 3 paper. Um, so you can see
that like these are all generated
samples um by smoothly varying that
latent Z and then passing it through the
generator to generate these different
samples. And you can see that these uh
these animals sort of smoothly morph
into each other. Um, so that means that
the model has somehow uncovered some
useful structure and stuffed it into the
latent space.
So that's uh that's pretty cool. So I I
used to talk a lot more about generative
adversarial networks. Um the the pros is
basically they have a really fairly
simple formulation and if you tune them
right like we saw with style GAN 3 then
they can actually give you very nice
results. Um very beautiful images, very
high resolution. Uh very good stuff. Um
but the cons like one like we talked
about they're they're fairly unstable to
train. You have no loss curve to look
at. You have very unstable training.
They tend to blow up at the drop of a
hat. Um so you end up with like um mode
coll what's called mode collapse. All of
a sudden you might get nans you might
get ins your generator your your
discriminator starts going crazy your
generator starts producing complete
random garbage all the time you have no
loss curves to look at to tell to
diagnose this they're kind of a mess. So
even though that GANs can give you
really nice results if you very very
carefully tune them um and very very
carefully control the normalization the
sampling everything about them um they
have been in practice they've been
fairly hard to scale up to really big
models to really big data um so GANs
were basically the go-to category of
generative models from around 2016 to
maybe around 2020 2021 something around
there um and in that 5 years there were
like literally thousands and thousands
of papers um people both trying to use
different GAN formulations, different
loss functions, different mathematical
formalisms as well as applying GANs to
all kinds of different generative
modeling tasks that you can imagine. So
like this was basically the go-to
generative modeling framework for about
five five or six years. Question is um
would we just expect this? Would we just
shouldn't we just expect these smooth
latenc? Um I think not necessarily
because one thing that can happen with
GANs is the generator might just might
just memorize a fixed number of data
samples, right? So what if your
generator ignores the latent Z and just
memorizes 10 samples from the training
data set somehow and then no matter what
Z you give it, it always gives you one
of those 10 samples from the training
data set and it never gives you anything
else. Then in that case, the disc you're
going to fool the discriminator because
the generator is always giving you
something which is maybe bitwise
identical to one of your real samples.
Um and then in that case the generator
would have basically piled on sort of
durac delta density like in the
immediate vicinity of a couple finite
samples. um but put no probability mass
anywhere else. So that actually is kind
of a legitimate solution for the
generator. Um and that would definitely
not give you smooth latence at all. So
that's just one example of how these
things can collapse into unintuitive
solutions that are not what you want.
Oh, good question. Um what is the
relationship between your training data
set and your latence? Um so this is
actually something very fundamental
about GANs is a great question. So you
you can map one way. So the generator
gives you a mapping from latent space
into data space maps from Z to an X. But
with GANs, you in general have no way to
map back from an X to a Z. Um, and
that's that's something very uh
different between GANs and VAEs. So VAEs
will learn an explicit mapping from X
back to Z, but with GANs you have no
such thing. Um, you can try to invert
you can try to um compute an inverse um
analytically numerically via gradient
descent. There's papers that do that.
Um, but there's actually like no
explicitly enforced relationship between
X and Z. Um instead the you can think of
the discriminator as trying to just
enforce a distributional alignment
between the distribution of all the
outputs coming from the generator and
the distribution of all the data samples
without any kind of explicit supervision
between them. Um of course like when it
comes to GANs anything you probably
think about there's probably at least
like a dozen papers about so there's
also a lot of papers about GAN variants
that try to learn birectional mappings
both ways but those never really took
off. Oh good good question. What have we
gained? So when we when we went to VAE,
we gained latent vectors, but we gave up
density. And now with GANs, it seems
like we gave up latent vectors that we
couldn't control. What you gained was
much better samples. Um so when it comes
to VAE, like VAEs tend not to give you
very good samples. Um VAEs are sort of
characteristically always kind of
blurry. They never really look good. Um
VAEs on their own just never tend to
give you very clean, crisp samples. But
with GANs, um some of the as you saw
with some of the examples, you can get
very crisp, very clean, very good
samples.
Um but what you lost was the ability it
was like your sanity in trying to tune
these systems. Yeah. At inference time
you throw away the discriminator and
just do the generator. So at inference
you'll just draw a sample Z um draw a
sample Z from the prior pass through the
generator get your sample from your
data. So it's very very efficient at
inference time. All right. So I
mentioned that GANs used to be the go-to
um category of of generative modeling
for about five or six years. Um, so what
displaced them? And what displaced them
was a very different category of models
called diffusion models. Now, um, I need
to put some caveats here. Diffusion
model literature is crazy, right? Like
you read these papers, they go through
like five pages of math before they tell
you at all what's going on. And there's
like three different mathematical
formalisms that lead to diffusion models
that are all very different
mathematically. And there's very
different notation, very different
terminology, very different mathematical
formalisms between papers. So like this
this is a sub area that's crazy. Um so I
need to put a big caveat here that I'm
not going to cover fully all the
different variants of diffusion models
with all of their proper mathematical
formalism. Instead, what I'm going to
try to do is give you an intuitive
overview of diffusion models as well as
an intuitive geometric understanding of
the most common form of diffusion models
today which are called rectified flow
models. Um, and you could really you
could teach many many lectures about
diffusion models and get into all the
interesting mathematical nuance of all
these flavors, but we just won't have
time for that in in three in two-thirds
of one lecture unfortunately.
So, um, with that caveat aside, the intu
the intuition behind diffusion models is
actually kind of easy. So um you know
like with all generative models we want
to draw samples um and we we like kind
of like GANs we want to convert samples
from a noise distribution um Z um into a
data distribution PX. But the way that
we're going to do that in diffusion
models is totally different. Um GANs
learn this deterministic mapping through
the generator to map a Z directly to an
X. With a diffusion model we're going to
do something more implicit, more
indirect. So what we're going to do um
first off the first constraint in
diffusion models is that the Z the the
noise distribution the noise always has
to have to have the same shape as our
data right so if you have an image
that's like H byW3 then your noise
distribution always has to be H byw3 as
well they have to be exactly the same
shape now what we're going to do is
consider um v different versions of our
data that are corrupted by increasing
levels of noise so here if we have a
data sample which is this picture of a
cat then under the t equals Z then and
then t is going to be our noise level um
which is ranges from 0 to 1. So at t
equals 0 that means no noise that means
a totally clean data sample. Um t
equals.3 is a little bit of noise. We
add some of our noise z into we mix some
of our noise z into our data x. And if
we go all the way to t= 1 we get full
noise and those are going to be samples
directly from our noise distribution. So
somehow this ted parameter is going to
interpolate smoothly between our data
distribution and our noise distribution.
Um and this is something and we can we
and the and the the noise distribution
again is going to be gausian um almost
always gausian something simple that we
understand and can sample from. Um and
now what we're going to do is train a
neural network to do a little bit of
incremental denoising. So the neural
network is going to receive um some
inter some some uh sample which is a
piece of data which has been corrupted
with some intermediate amount of noise.
And now the neural network is going to
be trained to try to clean it up a
little bit, remove just a little bit of
the noise. Um, so the training objective
here is going to be neural network
inputs
some an image of some amount with some
amount of noise and it tries to remove
some of the noise. Then at inference
time, what we're going to do is do an
iterative procedure where we first draw
a noise sample directly from our noise
distribution PZ and then iteratively
apply the neural network to remove noise
from that sample one at a time. So um
you know the very first time we do this
we're going to draw a complete sample
that's complete noise and then the very
first application of the neural network
the network will be trying to remove
noise from full noise. So it'll
basically be forced to hallucinate just
a tiny whiff of data structure in that
noise. And then once we get to some like
slightly less noisy example, we're going
to pass it back to the neural network
and again ask it to remove just a little
bit of noise from this now slightly um
slightly dinoised slightly generated
image and then it'll get a little bit
less noisy and it'll get a little bit
less less noisy and it'll get a bit
little bit less noisy. And eventually if
we set up all of this stuff correctly,
then we want to get to a situation where
we can draw a complete noise sample and
then ask the network to remove noise
from that complete sample Z of complete
random noise until eventually we we've
removed all the noise and come up with a
generated sample from the system. So
that's kind of a weird setting. It's
kind of a weird thing. Um but that's
kind of the intuition behind diffusion
models is the number of steps of fixed
hyperparameter. It depends. So on this
slide, I've intentionally been I I was
sort of forced to be very vague about
all these things. Um what is the noise?
What does it mean to corrupt the data
with respect to the noise? What does it
mean to remove a little bit of the
noise? What does it mean to apply
iteratively at inference? Because like I
said, there's so many different
formalisms of diffusion. There's a lot
of different variants about exactly what
these mean in different situations. So
this slide is intended to be a fairly
highle overview of diffusion and then
different specific implementations of
diffusion models will have different
concrete choices for what all these
terms specifically mean. So um does this
uh does this highle picture of diffusion
kind of make sense? Okay. So then let's
make this more concrete. So now we're
going to now we're going to jump from
you know general diffusion models to a
particular category of diffusion models
called rectified flow models. Um some
people may argue with me and say that
rectified flow is not diffusion. They
might be some people might say that
they're different things. I don't really
care. Um to me, rectified flow is a kind
of diffusion model. Fight me. Um so with
rectified flow, um the intuition is
basically this. You know, we have this
same thing. We have our P noise. We have
our P data. And we're going to draw this
geometrically because I think that's a
nice a nice way to gain intuition
geometrically in two dimensions in
particular because that's all that fits
on the slide. But of course, these are
going to be super super highdimensional
images um and gausian um which is an
easy way to get led astray, right?
because you know that intuitions that
hold in two and three dimensions go like
totally out the window when you go to a
lot of dimensions. Um it's really sad.
It's it's sort of sad that we live in
such a low dimensional universe because
our intuitions that we build in this
universe just don't really transfer to
like 100 dimensional spaces, thousand
dimensional spaces. So always be aware
but you know it is what it is. We're
stuck with the universe we got. So you
know the setup in rectified flow is that
we've got you know our distribution P
noise, our distribution P data. P
noiseis is something simple that we
understand, we can sample from, we can
compute integrals of. It's a very
friendly distribution. P data again is
something crazy. That's what the
universe is using to give us images.
Now, at every training iteration, um
we're going to sample a Z from our prior
distribution and sample an X from our
data dist data distribution. um you know
we can draw a sample e analytically
because um pz is something simple that
we control and drawing a sample from the
beta distribution just means picking an
example from your finite training set.
Now what we're and you're also going to
choose a a t to be uniform on 0 to 1.
Remember t is our noise level where t
equals 0 means no noise t= 1 means all
the noise. So now we're going to draw
now we're going to draw a line that
points from our data sample x directly
to our noise sample z. Um, and this
line, this vector pointing from X to Z
is we're going to call it V. Um, this is
this is going to be the velocity of a
flow field. Um, and then in and then we
set XT to be a point along this line,
which is a linear interpolation between
X and Z. So now we've got um we've got
our our noise sample Z, our data sample
X, we've got the velocity vector between
them V, and we've picked a noisy uh a
noised version of our data XT. Um and
this is what this is you know in the
previous slide when we said um get noisy
data. This is what that means in the
case of rectified flow models. It's a
linear interpolation between a data
sample and a noise sample. And now the
training objective is very very simple.
So now we're going to train a neural
network f theta. So that's f with
learnable parameters theta. Um that
neural network is going to input the
noisiest sample xt as well as the noise
level t and it's going to try to predict
the green vector v. So that's that's it.
That's all we need to do in rectified
flow. Um the code for this is very
simple. Um you would be shocked like how
how much obscurity there is when you
read papers here and it boils down to
this very simple code. Drives me crazy
that this is not made more clear in in a
lot of presentations of this. So then
the the training loop for rectified flow
is extremely simple. Um you loop over
your data set at every iteration. You
get um Z which is g unit which is unit
gausian of the same shape as X. You
choose a noise level T which is uniform
0 to1. You compute XT which is a linear
interpolation between X and Z. Um you
give XT and T to your model and then
your loss is just the mean squared error
between um the this ground truth V and
the model prediction. Um and that's it.
That's your training objective for
rectified flow models. Um contrast this
with GANs. Um when you train rectified
flow models or really any kind of
diffusion model, you have a loss that
you can look at during training. When
the loss goes down, the model is
generally better. So like for those of
us that went through half a decade of
GAN madness, the first time you train a
diffusion model and like there's a loss
to look at, it's like, oh my god, this
is an amazing thing. Um like how many
hours have we spent looking at GAN plots
and they look like this and you have no
idea. It's like reading tea leaves to
tell whether or not the model is working
well. You train a diffusion model, you
get this beautiful smooth exponential
loss curve and it just makes you so
happy. Um so that's great. So then
that's training for that's training for
diffusion models. Now what do we do at
inference? Right? Because you the you
know gans are kind of easy at inference.
GANs you just have to take a Z pass it
through your generator you get a data
sample very straightforward. But now
with a diffusion model or rectified flow
model in this case the model output
itself is like kind of useless. Like we
get this XT we get a V. Like what are we
going to do with this? Not super clear.
So then at inference time um is where
diffusion models get a little bit more
complicated compared to uh compared to
GANs.
So um you know at inference we first
will upfront choose a number of steps t
um which is usually a fixed constant um
and in the case of rectified flow models
t= 50 um is usually a good number to
start with. Sometimes you can get down
to t equals 30 and that works okay. Then
what you're going to do is um sample an
x directly from your noise distribution.
This is going to be pure noise that's
sampled from your known noise
distribution.
Then you're going to evaluate the then
you're going to loop from t equals 1.
you're going to march backwards to t
equals z. This is your noise level. Um,
and in this case, in this simple
version, we're just sort of marching
linearly from full noise one back to
noise zero, perfectly clean. Then at
every iteration,
we're going to take our our um our XT
that was at first full noise, pass it to
the network along with the current noise
level, and get the network's predicted
VT. And remember what this VT is
supposed to be in the case of rectified
flow. This V remember was supposed to
point from a data sample all the way to
a noise sample. So then it's kind of
geometrically obvious what you should do
in the case of rectified flow. You
should take a little step along that
predicted V vector. So you but right
because the problem is this rectified
flow model it's not going to that that V
is not going to point you all the way to
a clean sample. Um it's just going to
get you started. It's going to set you
on a trajectory towards a clean sample.
So we take a little step along that
predicted V from the flow model to get a
new X2 which is now a version of the
data that has had a little bit of the
noise removed from it by the model. And
now we iterate this. So once we have
this X this X2/3 then we pass it back to
the model and get another predicted V
vector from the model. Um and remember
the V is supposed to point from clean
data all from a from a clean sample all
the way to a noise sample. So then again
we can take a gradient step take a
little step along this predicted V to
get another um X1/3. Repeat this thing
again. Um re evaluate the model again to
get another predicted V and then take a
step in this case all the way to no to
to no noise all the way to the end of
that vector uh to get our predicted X0
and then that is our sample from our
diffusion model. So um you know the then
the inference procedure you see here got
a little bit more complicated compared
to GANs. Um but what we gained here was
um s sanity when you're training. You've
regained that. Um and they tend to give
you much better samples and they tend to
scale really well to to large data sets
and large models. And the code here is
really simple, right? So we um we start
off by taking a random sample, make it
be perfectly random, then march
backwards for t from one back to zero.
At every noise level, you get a
predicted V from the model given your
current sample as well as your T. Then
you take what looks kind of like a
gradient descent step on the model's
predicted V and update the sample and
just repeat this whole thing in a loop.
So then you can see like these diffusion
models aren't so scary after all. Um you
can actually fit a complete
implementation of training and sampling
from a rectified flow model in just a
couple lines um on on one slide which I
think is is very nice.
Okay. So you might be ask so so this is
this is pretty nice. I'm I'm pretty
happy that we're able to get to a full
right this and this will actually work
right like if you if you take this code
you plug it in like you plug it in a
reasonable model architecture like this
will actually this will actually work
like this will actually convert to
something kind of reasonable in a lot of
cases you're kind of hitting on the core
problem in generative modeling that I've
been thinking about a lot the last
couple days while reviewing these slides
right the core problem in generative
modeling is somehow you have a prior
distribution which is Z's that you know
how to sample from you have a data
distribution which is X's that you want
to generate and kind of the core problem
in generative modeling is figuring out
how to associate Z's and X's. And all
your different categories to generative
modeling kind of do it in different
ways. Right? In a VAE, you say, I'm
going to have the model predict a Z and
then predict an X and then try to force
that Z to be something I know how to
sample from. Um, which doesn't super
work that well. In a GAN, um, you're not
supervising that relationship. Like the
generator is kind of figuring out its
own mapping from Z to X in a feed
forward way through this distributional
matching objective that the
discriminator is giving it. um in
diffusion it's kind of figuring out by
what what ends up and it ends up having
to integrate these curves. Um and
there's some there's a lot of different
actually like several different
mathematical formalisms as to why
objectives that look like this end up
matching probability distributions in a
reasonable way. Um but again like the
whole core problem is that we have no
way ahead of time to get to pair up
samples Z from our prior with samples X
from our data. If we knew how to make
that pairing and also knew how to sample
from the prior like that would be that
you'd be done. And in some sense, all
these different forms of generative
modeling are different ways to square
that circle and come up with a way to
learn an association from Z to X even
though we don't and and be able to
sample from Z even though we don't have
that association at training time.
There's a lot of different
interpretations of this that that can
get very very heavy very quick. So I've
tried to avoid them.
Right? So um but we we said a couple
lecture we said last lecture that um
unconditional generative modeling is
kind of kind of pointless. So what we
almost always care about is conditional
generative modeling and that's easy to
accommodate in in rectified flow. So we
can do to do conditional rectified flow
we kind of imagine that there's
different subp parts of our data
distribution. Here I'm saying it's
categorical. Maybe our data is actually
squares and triangles. Um, and then we
have our our whole data distribution P
data as well as our two sort of
subdistributions P data X given that Y
is a square and P data P data X given
that Y is the label Y is a triangle. So
this is kind of the the picture you
should have in mind when you think about
conditional generative modeling. Then in
the case of of rectified flow this is
very easy to accommodate. So you just um
sort of your data set now has pairs X
and Y and your model now takes Y as an
additional auxiliary input somehow. Um
and then during sampling same thing you
get your predicted V's uh according and
you you get your predicted V's you know
the model takes as input this extra Y uh
and you use that. So this all kind of
goes through. Um the difference is that
now Y is actually hopefully some
conditional signal that the user can
control. Maybe this is a text prompt.
Maybe this is an input image. Maybe this
is this is some kind of user input that
you're expecting at inference time. Um
which actually make these models
controllable and useful in practice.
Um, but then there's another really
interesting question is um, is there any
knob you can tune to control how much
the model pays attention to the
conditioning signal, right? It turns out
if you train these things naively, a lot
of times they don't often follow the
conditioning signal quite as much as you
would like. Um, so there's a trick
called classifier free guidance or CFG
um, that changes this a little that
changes our diffusion uh, training loop
just a little bit. So, what we're going
to do is we're still going to train this
conditional diffusion model that inputs
your XT um inputs your Y, but we're
going to every on every training on
every training iteration, we're going to
flip a coin. Um, and if that coin is
heads, we're going to delete the
conditioning information. So, we're
going to set it equal to some kind of
zero value or null value. Um, basically
destroy the conditioning information 50%
of the time. That could be a
hyperparameter, but 50 is a pretty good
one that most people use in practice.
So, we're going to flip a coin. If the
coin is heads, delete the conditioning
information. So that means that the
model is conceptually now forced to
learn two different kinds of velocity
vectors. Right? Um
right. So then the same the the model is
sort of forced to learn two different
kinds of velocity vectors. Right? So in
the case where we pass it this uh this
null value for y that is that that has
destroyed the conditioning information
then this is basically an unconditional
generative model. Now um now that that
predicted velocity vector V is sort of
has to point back towards the the meat
of the whole data distribution P data.
Um but when we pass a real conditioning
uh input Y that's non-destroyed,
non-null, non-zero um then we're getting
sort of a conditional velocity vector
that is pointing us back towards not the
full data distribution but towards the
conditional data distribution which is
conditional on that conditioning signal
that we cared about. And then the dumb
trick is we're going to take a linear
combination of these two vectors to kind
of push it more towards the uh more
towards the conditional velocity vector.
So in particular, we'll have a scalar
hyperparameter w and take a linear
combination 1 + w * v y minus w * v uh v
null. So that's going to be a vector
that now kind of points kind of points
even more towards the towards the
conditional distribution than it does
the data distribution. Um and then the
idea is that during sampling we're now
going to um right then during sampling
we're now going to step according to
this uh this this uh vcfg vector rather
than the rather than the raw vectors
predicted by the model and then setting
w equals 1 um setting w equals z here
will recover exactly the the the
conditional one and you know the higher
your w is then the more you're
overemphasizing the conditioning signal.
Um so this is this is and then this is
pretty easy to implement right so uh
then your inference code doesn't really
change too much now you but now you
evaluate the model twice at every
iteration to get your vy and your v 0 um
and then you take this this linear
combination and then step according to
that and this is called classifier free
because of a stupid reason there was an
earlier paper called classifier guidance
that I don't want to get into and then
they remove the classifier and even
though there was only like 9 months
between those two papers and it's now
been 4 years since the second one we're
still stuck with the name classifier
free guidance. So it is what it is.
Okay. So that's actually really
important in practice for getting high
quality outputs. Um and that's uh that's
CFG. That's really important. That's
used everywhere in diffusion models. Um
it does double the cost of sampling
though because now you need to hit the
model twice on every iteration which is
kind of a problem. Okay. Uh this there's
this thing on optimal prediction. I
think I'll skip that. That's not so
interesting. Um I mean it is interesting
but we're running out of but but I'm
worried about time. So um but one thing
that we sometimes need to do is tweak
this uh this uh this this this t
distribution. So we saw in particular
that we were sampling t according to to
a uniform distribution in a raw in like
a raw rectified flow model. Um and the
thing about that is it kind of is going
to put uniform emphasis on all noise
levels. And intuitively when you're at
full noise the problem is very easy
right? When you're at when you're at
full noise the problem is very easy.
then the model like the optimal
prediction from the model is basically
to point towards the mean of the data
distribution. Um and similarly when
you're at um zero noise then the optimal
prediction is actually to point towards
the mean of the noise distribution. So
actually the model like the the the
optimal prediction from the model at
full noise and full data and no noise
are actually very relatively easy
problems. It just needs to learn the
mean of those two distributions. Um but
when you when you're somewhere in the
middle it's actually really really hard,
right? because when you when you when
you're somewhere in the middle and you
sample that XT, there might have been
multiple pairs X and Z that could have
given rise to that same XT in the
middle. Um, and then the network
basically needs to solve this
expectation problem and figure out what
is that optimal direction to predict
that kind of integrates over all
possible X's and Z's that might
intersect at this point XT. So somehow
those points in the middle are
intuitively much harder for the network
to solve. So um but when we sample
uniformly from 0 to 1t then we're kind
of putting equal importance on all
levels of noise which doesn't really
match this intuition. So in practice
you'll often sample from different noise
schedules. Um and one very popular one
is this one called logic normal sampling
which basically um looks kind of like a
gausian puts relatively little weight on
the zero and the one with a lot more
weight in the middle. Um another thing
you'll see sometimes are these so-called
shifted noise schedules that are
asymmetric that shift more towards one
direction or the other. um and those are
important as we scale to high resolution
data. The intuition being that when you
have a very high resolution image then
there can be very strong correlations
across neighboring pixels. When you have
a low resolution image then there then
the correlations across neighboring
pixels tend to be smaller. So depending
on how strong of correlations you have
in your data, you actually may need
different amounts of noise level to
properly destroy information in a nice
way. So um these things don't naively
scale to different resolutions,
right? All right. And that's actually a
big problem with these diffusion models
is that they are, you know, they're a
beautiful formulation, but they don't
but they're hard to get them to work
naively on high resolution data. So, um,
that leads to actually, you know, I said
diffusion models are the most popular
form of generative modeling. That was a
little bit of a lie because what's
actually most popular are these
so-called latent diffusion models, which
is a variant that actually gets used
everywhere. Um, so here it's going to be
a multi-stage procedure. So, what we're
going to do is first train an encoder
network and a decoder network. The
encoder network is going to map from our
image into some latent space um which
I've colored in purple and ideally that
that latent is going to spatially down
sample the image by a factor of D um as
well as uh convert from three channels
up into C channels and a pretty common
setting is to get 8 by8 spatial
downsampling and to increase to 16
channels. That's kind of the one some of
these most common encoder decoders. Um
these encoder decoders tend to be CNN's
with attention but um more some more
recent papers have explored bits for
these. Then what we do is we're going to
train a diffusion model not on the raw
pixel space of our images but instead on
the latent space which is discovered by
this encoder decoder model. So then the
training procedure kind of looks like a
training for training the diffusion
model. We're going to sample an image
pass it through the encoder that we
learned in the first stage to get a
latent um and then add noise to the
latent and train the diffusion model to
dn noiseise the the noised latent. And
really importantly, you freeze the
encoder. So you do not prop you do not
propagate bit gradients back into the
encoder. We're only using it to extract
these latents and then training a
diffusion model directly on the latent
space which is learned by the encoder.
Then at inference time once you're all
done training then we'll sample a random
latent pass it through the diffusion
model many many times to remove all the
noise to get a clean sample. But that
clean sample is now a clean sample in
latent space. So then we need to run the
decoder to convert that clean latent
into a clean image. Um, and this is
actually the most common form of most
diffusion models these days. So, you
might be asking, okay, we've knocked
this diffusion model, um, this encoder
decoder. How do we train an encoder
decoder? Any ideas?
Have we seen encoder decoders?
How about a variational autoenccoder?
Um, so in practice, whenever you're
training these latent diffusion models,
this encoder decoder tends to be a
variational auto-enccoder. But we just
said there was a big problem with
variational auto-enccoders is that they
give you blurry outputs, right? And if
this encoder decoder is going to give
you blurry outputs, the quality of the
reconstructions you get out of the
decoder is going to bottleneck the
quality of the generations you get out
of the downstream diffusion model. So if
your encoder decoder is giving you
blurry, ugly reconstructions, that's not
going to fly. That's not going to get us
good clean samples. So anyone have an
idea for cleaning up the sample quality
of a of a of a VAE? put something after
the decoder in particular um we can make
again make it again. So what we tend to
do is actually um train this encoder
that encodes from an image into latent
space a decoder that goes from latent
space back to image a discriminator that
tries to tell the fake images from the
re from the real images and then a
diffusion model that uh generates these
things in latent space. So this is
basically why we have to walk through
all of these different formulations of
diffusion models of generative models in
order for you to understand the modern
pipeline. Like basically the
state-of-the-art in generative modeling
is you know is it a VAE is it a GAN is
it a diffusion it's all of them right?
It's all of them. The modern the modern
generative modeling pipeline involves
training a VAE and a GAN and a diffusion
model. I'm sorry it's a mess. Okay so
then you might ask what what what do the
neural networks actually look like under
the hood here? So um thankfully there is
some sanity here the last couple of
years. So relatively straight it turns
out that relatively straightforward
transformers actually can be applied to
these diffusion models and they work
really well. Um these are these are
typically called diffusion transformers
or DITS but basically these are just
standard diffusion models uh standard
transformer blocks that really don't
really have much special sauce in them.
Um there's a couple questions uh the the
kind of main question you needed to
solve in the architectural side is how
do you inject the conditioning
information? Um, and in particular, the
diffusion model now needs to take like
three things as input. It needs to take
your noisy image. It needs to take your
time stamp t. It also needs to take your
conditioning signal, which might be
your, um, like your text or something
like that. So, um, and then you have a
couple different mechanisms for
injecting that conditioning signal into
your into your transformer blocks. Um,
so the first is, um, to predict a scale
and shift, um, that are going to be used
to like modulate some of the
intermediate activations of your of your
diffusion block. Um, and that's
typically the way that we inject the
time stamp information into diffusion
models. Um, another thing you can do is
transformers are just models of
sequences. So you can jam everything
into the sequence. Um, you can jam the
time stamp into the sequence, you can
jam your text into the sequence, you can
jam whatever you want into the sequence
and have the the have the transformer
just model that sequence of data
altogether. Um, and you can do that
either via cross attention or joint
attention. And different models um sort
of do both. And typically we're going to
typically in modern diffusion DITS we
inject the time stamp through this scale
shift mechanism and you inject the the
text or other conditioning signal
through um sequence concatenation
usually cross attention but sometimes
joint attention as well. Um so then how
can you actually apply this to different
problems? So one task that people care
about a lot is the is the task of text
to image generation. So here we're going
to input a text prompt. This is one that
I wrote yesterday. A professional
documentary photograph of a monkey
shaking hands with a tiger in front of
the Eiffel Tower. monkey is wearing a
hat made out of bananas. Tiger is
standing on two legs and wearing a suit.
Um, and this is a really this is a real
sample. Like it's crazy that the stuff
works now. Um, but I'm sure you've all
seen these kind of things before. Um,
and the way that this works is you'll
take your text prompt. Um, pass it
through usually a pre-trained text
encoder, right? So, actually I lied.
Like there's actually more models you
have to train in addition to an encoder
and a decoder and a VAE and a
discriminator. You also need to train a
language model secretly to get these
things to work. Um, so you'll actually
typically pick up a pre-trained text
encoder, usually T5, clip, something
like that to give um, text embeddings
and usually the text encoder will be
frozen. Then those text embeddings um,
you pass your text embeddings together
with your noisy latence into your
diffusion transformer that also gets
your diffusion time step. That's going
to output clean latence and this thing
will kind of go iteratively and that'll
go through your your VAE decoder to give
you your final image. And just to put
some numbers on this to make it
concrete, um, one pretty a pretty
powerful open source model right now is
called flux one dev. They use the T5 and
clip encoders. Their encoder uses 8x
down sampling. They train a 12 billion
parameter um, transformer model on this.
And that transformer has an additional
layer of downsampling on top of the VAE,
which is kind of messy. So it ends up
having a sequence length of 1024 image
tokens.
Another task that people care about a
lot is text to video. So we can input a
text prompt and then output the pixels
of a video that follow that text prompt.
And the pipeline basically looks kind of
the same. So you're going to input a
text um through your pre-trained text
encoder, get noisy latence. Importantly,
the only difference is that your latents
are now have an extra dimension to
accommodate the time. So in addition to
two spatial dimensions, HW, you'll also
have a time dimension in your latent and
that will give you clean latence. And
then your decoder um this is typically
going to be a spatial temporal
auto-enccoder now. So it will downsample
both spatially and temporally. Um, so
then it will take your latence and then
upsample them into pixels which will
give you a video. Um, and this is
actually a this is actually a generated
video from Meta's movie gen paper that
came out uh in last year.
Um, okay. And that's putting some that's
putting some particular numbers on this
thing. Um, and the key takeaway of these
video generation models is that they get
very expensive to train due to the
sequence length, right? because if you
want to generate high FPS, high
resolution, high frame rate video, it
just ends up with a lot of tokens. So,
we said that with um kind of a a fairly
state-of-the-art um to text to image
diffusion model, that transformer ended
up working on a sequence of 1024 image
tokens for this um for this texttovideo
diffusion model. Even though the overall
architecture looks pretty similar, the
biggest difference is in the sequence
length. So now rather now they actually
need to process um 76,000 um video
tokens to process this to create this
high resolution video with a lot of
frames. So that's where the expense
happens in these video diffusion models
is actually processing these really long
sequences.
So um I I think basically the last year
has pretty much been the era of video
diffusion models. So um there was there
it basically seems like every week
almost for the past year there's been a
new interesting video diffusion model
coming out. Um, and these have been a
mix of open source models, uh, models
that have technical reports, um, so they
they give you some details about the
model architecture and the training. Um,
and you know, purely industrial models
where they don't tell you anything, but
they'll take your credit card number,
let you generate samples from it. So,
um, I I'm not going to go through all
these in all of these all of these uh,
one by one, but I just wanted to give
the sense of like this has been a really
hot topic the last like really the past
18 months. Um and in particular this uh
there was this really influential blog
post from OpenAI called Sora that came
out in March 2024 which was not the
first um diffusion model on videos but
it was the first one that gave really
really really good results. Um and they
kind of adopted this modern sort of
diffusion transformer plus rectified
flow. Um actually I don't know if they
were using rectified flow in Sora. I
don't know if they said um but they were
they were one of the first to really
scale up these diffusion transformers um
and get this thing to work really well
and then kind of that was the 4-minute
mile sort of moment in video diffusion
models and then all the other big
companies took notice of that and
quickly tried to replicate Sora. So, I
said it's it's felt like for the past
year and a half that like almost every
week there's been a brand new
state-of-the-art video diffusion model.
And today is no exception because an
hour and a half uh at 11:00 a.m. this
morning, Google announced Veo 3, which
is almost certainly the best video diff
which is almost certainly the best
generative model of video out there
right now. Um, I literally like read the
blog post while I was in the car on the
way here, but it seems cool. Here are
some samples from Veo3.
So like these are actually generated
videos from a text from a text prompt um
in Google's new model. Kind of crazy.
Also, this model joint also models sound
jointly. So they can output like audio
along with the video frames. This is
another generated one. So you can kind
of tell what you want to happen in text.
It'll fly over here and like looks
crazy.
Okay. So I thought that's just fun to to
incorporate new stuff.
Okay. So one big problem with um with
diffusion is that during sampling it's
really slow right we said that sampling
was this iterative procedure and these
models are can be really big these can
be models with tens of billions of
parameters potentially operating on
sequence lengths of tens of thousands or
or more so these things get really slow
at inference time because even with
rectified flow you need like you know
tens tens of iterations of the model at
inference time so the solution is a
category of algorithms called
distillation which we don't have time to
get into I just wanted to put a couple
referenc here make you aware that this
exists as a set of techniques. So
distillation algorithms are basically
ways that you can take a diffusion model
that normally would take you know 30 50
100 iterations at inference time to get
good samples and then modify the model
in some way such that you can take many
many fewer steps on inference and still
get good samples. Um they tend to
sacrifice sample quality. So the whole
trick in distillation methods is trying
to maintain the sample quality as good
as you can while still letting you take
fewer samples at inference time. Um, and
some distillation methods let you get
all the way down to singlestep sampling,
which is really cool, although they tend
to take quite a hit on the on the on the
um generation quality when you do that.
So, that's kind of uh that's kind of,
you know, I'm not going to go through
these, but I just put some references
here to different papers on distillation
if you want to take a look. Um, and this
is a really active and evolving area of
research. So, if you look at these
references, these are um, you know, from
2024, from 2025. So, like these are
stuff that people are working on right
now is how do we get better
distillation? And how do we get uh how
do we get diffusion models to be more
efficient at inverse time? So another
thing so I I kind of mentioned that
diffusion has this like black hole of
math that you can get sucked into. Um
and we intentionally sidestepped that by
just walking very intuitively through
rectified flow models kind of giving you
a geometric intuition for the problem
without really diving through any math
that proves anything. Um so I wanted to
give you just a brief sense of like what
some of these formalisms are. Um but
we're not going to be able to go through
them in detail. Um so here's kind of
restating the rectified flow objective.
We said that during training we're going
to sample um our X's and our Z's
according to our data distribution and
our noise distribution. We're going to
sample T according to some distribution
PT that we choose either um uniform
logic normal or shifted something like
that. And then we'll set XT equal to the
linear interpolation between X and Z.
We'll set a now now we've changed we've
written this a little bit differently in
in this slide. Now we're writing down a
ground truth velocity VGT that we want
the network to predict which is Z minus
X. Um we compute a predicted V from the
network by passing it our noisy XT and
RT then compute an L2 loss minimizing
the V the VGT and the predicted V from
the network. So most um when I said that
there's a lot of different formalisms a
lot of different flavors of diffusion um
what a lot of these look to is sort of
different functional hyperparameters in
this general setup in this general
setup. So in the in more generalized
flavors of diffusion, usually you'll
you'll you can you might vary what is
this PT distribution. Usually you don't
vary the noise distribution. This is
almost always gausian um at least for
for continuous models. Um but what you
will vary is like how do you compute
that noisy XT and in general that will
be some functional combination that will
be some linear combination of X and Z.
Um and the that the linear combination
weights will in general be some function
of T. But what exactly that function is
kind of depends on the diffusion
formulation. Then what also varies is
what is that ground truth target that we
ask the model to predict. It's always
going to be some linear combination of
our data sample X and our and our um and
our latent Z. Um and again the what are
the linear combination weights might be
functions of T in some formulations. So
basically and then uh you know we're
going to ask the model to we're going to
give it that noisy XT and the T um get a
predicted Y and then always compute an
L2 loss between the two. I mean not
always but usually. And then what varies
is basically what are these different
functional forms? What are these
different functions that we plot that we
slot into these different these four
different spots in this thing. So in the
case of rectified flow it's fairly
simple. Um a these all take these really
simple forms and um ct and bdt are
actually just constants. Um there's a
kind of another another flavor of this
called variance preserving um where a is
where you kind of collapse these two
into one scalar hyperparameter um called
sigma of t. Um and now you have these
linear linear combinations in this
particular way and you choose this
because if X and Z are independent and
have unit variance then your output also
is guaranteed to have unit variance. So
that kind of collapses these two
functional hyperparameters into just one
noise schedule and then you still need
to choose that somehow. Um in
combination with variance preserving
there's also variance exploding is
another one where you'll set a t equals
1 bt equal to again some sigma of t and
you need to choose that somehow. Um
there's a lot of different way a lot of
different targets that people will
choose. Um sometimes they'll predict
sometimes they'll ask the network to
predict the clean data. Sometimes
they'll ask the model to predict the
noise that was added. Sometimes they'll
ask the network to predict some linear
combination of the two. Um and in the
case of of rectified flow, you are just
predicting the that velocity vector that
points from a data directly to a noise.
But in more generaliz in more in
different flavors of diffusion, all of
these can kind of change. Um then you
might be wondering you know how how you
know choosing hyperparameters is bad
enough. Now we need to choose
hyperparameters which are themselves
functions of t. Like this is crazy. Um
you're never going to set these
intuitively. So you'd have to be guided
by some some kind of math. Um and
there's basically three different
mathematical formalisms that people um
you that people think about when
training diffusion models that again we
will not walk through in practice. I
just want to get you the to know the
existence of. Um the first is that
diffusion is a latent variable model,
right? that we're going to we have our
clean data samples X0 but then
associated to every clean data sample.
There exists some sequence of corrupted
or noisy samples like that that
correspond to that clean sample and we
can't observe them. We don't know what
they are but we need to figure them out
somehow. So that's a latent variable
model that ends up looking a lot like a
variational autoenccoder. Remember in a
variational autoenccoder we had a Z and
an X. We didn't observe the Z. We wanted
to train this thing somehow. Um then it
turns out you can turn a very similar ma
use a very similar mathematical trick um
as we did in variational autoenccoders
and maximize some variational lower
bound of the likelihood of the data and
that gives rise to this um latent
variable model interpretation of
diffusion.
Another another a totally different
interpretation of diffusion is that it
models something called the score
function. Um so given a data given a
data data given a distribution p data of
x um there's this nice thing called the
score function of the distribution which
is the derivative with respect to x of
the log of p data of x and intuitively
this given a distribution the score
function is a vector field that points
towards areas of high of high
probability density. So um you know for
any point in the data space the score
function is going to be a vector that
points you towards areas of high data
density. And now another interpretation
of diffusion is that diffusion is
learning the score function of the data
distribution and in fact learning a set
of score functions corresponding to
different levels of noise on the data
distribution. So there's another
interpretation of diffusion which is
that it's trying to learn a family of
score functions corresponding to a
family of noised distributions that
corrupt the true data distribution with
increasing amounts of known noise. And
that's a totally different mathematical
formalism that gives rise to very
similar looking algorithm at the end.
And then the third one that's come onto
the scene a little bit more recently is
this notion of diffusion as solving
stochastic differential equations. And I
got to admit like I don't fully
understand this one myself. So don't ask
me too many questions. Um but the idea
is that you want to learn some you want
to write down some differential equation
that's going to write down you know some
infantessimal way to transport samples
from a noise distribution into samples
from a data distribution. And then it
and then it inference. Then the neural
network is basically learning some kind
of numeric integrator, some numeric
integrator to this stochastic
differential equation that we can write
down. Um, and this opens up a whole new
way of thinking about it, right? Because
from under the lens of stoastic
differential equations, then we get
access to whole different categories of
functions to to to whole different
categories of methods to sample from
these things at inference time, right?
And from this perspective, the kind of
like naive gradient descent type um type
approach that we saw in rectified flow
basically corresponds to a forward oiler
type of integrator on top of a sta
stocastic differential equation. And
then under this interpretation, you can
imagine doing all kinds of more
complicated integrators to maybe do a
better job at mar at marching along this
score function. So again, like these are
these are these are deep waters. Like
there's there's there's papers that go
into great detail on all these things.
Um, and a blog post that I really liked
is this one by Sander Deman on
perspectives on diffusion, who actually
gave um eight different perspectives on
different ways to think about or view
diffusion models. So, this is an
excellent post. I would highly recommend
I would actually highly recommend
everything he's written about diffusion
models. All his blog posts are amazing.
Um, autogressive models actually come
back. We can do the same thing in coder
decoder um and put an autogressive model
on there too. So the other the other you
know just sneaking this in there at the
end in addition to diffusion models the
other you know modern recipe for
generative modeling is to train an auto
reggressive model on discrete latents
that are computed by a discrete
variational autoenccoder. So you know
you know that's why we did the four
generative models that we did right um
GANs ves autogressive models diffusion
because it turns out they all get used
in in in modern machine learning uh
pipelines.
So that's basically the summary of
today. Uh today we did a whirlwind tour
of two different categories of
generative models. We talked about
generative adversarial networks as well
as diffusion models. And we saw kind of
their their modern full pipeline
instantiated in latent diffusion models
which is kind of a nice way to wrap up
this generative modeling section because
all the generative models that we saw
basically come back and come together to
form these big modern pipelines. So
thanks and next time we'll talk about
vision and language.