um hello thank you for joining
cs25 uh Transformers today's the last
class today we have lumna who is a
machine learning engineer in the science
team at hugging face working on large
language models for code and synthetic
data generation uh she's part of the
core team at the big code project and uh
has co-authored the stack data set and
the star coder model for code generation
thank you so much for coming to our talk
today and um as always attendance link
and the slido questions are on our
website and we'll be taking questions
after the talk thank you and uh you can
take it off
now hi thank you for the introduction um
cool so I'm LNA I'm a machine learning
engineer at Hing face in the science
team and today I'll tell you about the
behind the scenes for training large
language models and I will use the star
coder model that our team has trained as
a use
case um so today's plan is very simple
we're going to try to answer this
question what does it take to train a
good llm so it's one question but it's
very loaded and it has a lot of
follow-ups and as you will see my slides
will be a series of questions and
answers um so a few years ago a lot of
people thought that there was some mten
Secret SCE to the strong closed models
like gp4 and that it will take the open
source Community a lot of time to catch
up because the open source models that
we had back then were much smaller and
less performance uh but now it seems
that the community kind of figured out
most of the pieces for getting strong
llms as it was predicted in this Google
memo that was leaked and released on
semi
analysis for example today we have a
llama 370b instruct which has almost the
same performance as GPT for but it
unlocks so many use cases because the
model weights are open the model can be
quantized and can even run on consumer
desktop it also allows the community to
build very cool use cases on top through
fine tuning so we've made a lot of
progress in the open field and this is
not the only model that's out there um
we're now observing kind of a rise of
open LMS uh and the company more and
more companies are embracing releasing
models that was the case for example
with deep mind's Gemma models and with
mistral's models and also other models
from DEC k um here I put a plot from uh
the LMS Arena which is kind of uh the
go-to leaderboard for comparing instruct
models nowadays it uses human
evaluation and uh you can see in this
plot that as we went from 2023 to May 24
the G in performance between the closed
models and the open models is shrinking
and becoming smaller which is very
promising um so we're on a very great
path uh but there are still a lot of uh
limitations uh for this and this is
mainly due to uh releases missing out
important details about how the data was
process and how the models were trained
and this is usually the case for two
main reasons uh the first one is to
avoid legal scrutiny uh because when
companies publicly disclose the training
data if the training was not done
properly and the copyrighted were not
respected they Lisk they risk facing
legal investigation the other um reason
for not disclosing the details can be to
maintain a Competitive Edge so some
companies want to be the best at
training LM so they don't want to give
all the details for their
training um nevertheless because we have
a lot of releases I think we can still
answer this question and put a lot of
pieces
together um so what do we need to train
a good LM the first thing is probably
the model you need to have a good
architecture and I think now
Transformers are kind of the default but
there are also other interesting
architectures like Mamba she's a state
based model or you can use mixture of
experts which can be multiple
Transformer models um but I'm not going
to spend a lot of time in this lecture
on models because I think it's a topic
that's already thoroughly explored and
there are other aspects that maybe uh
deserve a little bit more
attention so that was it for models then
for gpus I don't think there's much I
can tell you about that except maybe ask
Jensen um but the part that they were
the most
interested uh of is data which I think
is the backbone of LMS um because now
almost everyone is using the same
architecture and the same training
techniques and for a given budget data
is what makes some models better than
the others so it's really worth spending
time exploring this data and
understanding how to get higher quality
samples so now we're going to try to
answer our previous question of how to
train a good Al by how do we get good
training
data um and I think the answer to this
is three F first we need to understand
how much data do we need and then once
we figured out the size of the data that
we need where can we get this data and
to clean it which filtering techniques
make more sense and will give us the
best
performance so to answer the first one
um uh the answer to that is the scaling
lws you want to know which data how much
data you want to train your model on but
also what is the optimal size of the
model and the scaling laws uh try to
study the allocation of a computer
budget between data size and model size
this means should you take a smaller
model and train it longer or take a
larger model and train it on less
data and um I'm going to present a brief
history of the scanning law uh because I
think it's really interesting to see how
the sizes of the models progress through
time and also how the size of the data
sets and the number of tokens we train
on them have changed because there were
really some drastic changes in that I
think the first um to establish the
scaling laws were kapan from open Ai and
they tried to fit um the law as a
function of uh the loss as a function of
the data size and model size and they
found that if you have a 10 per times
increase in your compute you should
increase your parameter count by 5.5 but
your training tokens you should only
increase them by 1.8 uh this means that
if you have more resources to train your
models you should make the model much
larger but the data it's fine you
shouldn't increase it that much um and
this is what led to models like gpt3
which
is5 billion parameters but it was only
trained on 300 billion tokens which if
we think about it now is really small um
other models also follow this for
example like opt which was the same size
as gpt3 and trained on a similar amount
of data there was also Bloom um so all
these models are actually very
undertrained um then the chincha scaling
loss came after and they kind of
Revisited the scaling LW and they found
that the reason capan thought that data
should not be as scaled as model size is
because they used a fixed cosine Schuler
for all their experiments so although
they were changing the data size the
cosine scheduler was fixed this meant
that for some models they were
underestimated because they were not
using the correct cosign that
corresponded to the data size uh this
led to kind of false conclusions and the
chinchila can now give us new scaning
laws that say that you should scale your
data and your model size equally and uh
in their paper uh they train a 65
billion model uh on 1.6 trillion tokens
which is the chinchilla optimal point
and they outperform much larger models
like gpc3 and gopher which was over 200
billion
parameters um so here for example I have
a plot which shows what the scanning law
TR to do for example here you have isof
flop curves which each curve uses a
fixed budges and then you try to find
The Sweet Spot which is like the optimal
for your budget allocation and it tells
you what your model size should be and
what your data size should be
and as you can see here if we try to fit
the loss we can see that there's a
linear increase for data and also model
size um in this uh scheme I tried to
show um how we've moved from the
chinchilla scanning laws to today's
models um and you can see that for
example the chinchilla model which is 60
billion parameters were strained on less
than two trillion tokens but then after
that we have llama which was released
last year and it was just a 7B model and
it was trained on um as much data as the
chinchilla model so it was trained way
past the chinchilla optimal point and uh
we might be wondering why is that the
case uh did metal not use their compute
but just in an optimal way uh and the
answer to that is that compute optimal
is not always optimal um because when
you train a model you don't only care
about your what you're going to spend in
training but you also care uh about
inference and the model is trained one
time but inference is for more the model
is going to be served so you want to
save some cost in that this makes it
that people prefer training smaller
models longer than actually using much
larger models that are trained onless
data so that was the case for llama one
for other models like Mistral but also
for llama 3 which went even further and
train not on 1 trillion tokens but on 15
trillion tokens and if you check the
archive paper the loss kept going down
and also the downstream evaluations as
the model kept training it kept
improving I think this is really
interesting because some people
misunderstood the chinchilla SK laws as
like compute optimal is optimal but
that's not the case um because inference
cost is not considered so for example
this is the cost for training gp4 it is
said that it's estimated that's $100
million but also the inference is very
expensive and the larger the model
becomes the more time it takes to
process
tokens um so infra the scanning laws
don't take the inference cost in
consideration and if we do take the
inference cost which is um the case for
most people because they want to use
these models in inference you might
prefer using smaller models and training
them longer and we do that we're not
respecting the chin sking loss so we're
choosing to pay what we call a compute
overhead it kind of a sacrifice that you
do during the training you choose to pay
more but this will have a benefit during
inference because you will save a lot of
cost and
money and um there's a this very
interesting blog post about Harm's law
which tries to uh measure the compute
overhead that you will be paying when
you choose to train a small model uh for
example here there's a space on hugging
phas where you can input the model size
and what data says you want to tr TR on
and it will show you where where you are
regarding the chin optimal point so for
example if we take a 7B model and which
fin on 1 billion tokens you can see that
we are here it's the Red Dot and it's
before the chinchilla optimal model and
this gives approximately I think uh 40%
overhead but then during inference as it
shows here in the table sorry it was
133% overhead but there's 50 almost 50%
saving costs so that's something that's
almost everyone is doing now which is
why we see models that are much much
smaller than one or two years
ago um for further reading there are
some very interesting papers about
scaling laws for example this paper
called scaling data constraint language
models um which shows that if you are
limited in your data size let's say for
example you want 27b on 10 trillion
tokens but you don't have these 10
trillion tokens
this paper says that you can basically
repeat your data up to four times so
four AO and you will get similar
performance as if you use the unique
tokens so for example instead of using a
trillion tokens unique you could use
just two and repeat them four times you
get almost the same performance of the
as if these tokens were unique um this
is especially useful for some domains
where we almost exhaust all the data
that's publicly available as I will show
you later the stack V2 which is a codee
data set that we released uh I think it
has almost all the code that is
available publicly so it's going to be
very hard to scrape and get more code
and if want to train models longer the
only option is to actually repeat the
data during training and um this is good
news because repeating the data up to
four times is actually
significant um another paper that I
think is interesting when it comes to
scaling laws is the the SE llm um they
try to establish new scaling laws that
are suited for the data because they
find that the scaling behavior is highly
dependent on the data quality so they
tried different data subsets different
filterings and they found that the
scaling laws were changing so this is
very important because up until now we
were using the chinchila but the CH sh
was using fixed data set they are not
necessarily the ones that we are using
now so it's important to be aware of
that and this is why DC try to come up
with their own skinning laws that work
for their data sets and they also
conclude that when you have higher
quality data sets maybe more compute
should be allocated to the model size
and not to the data size so these are
interesting things to keep in mind when
it comes to scaling
llms um so we have answered the first
question I hope how much data to train
llms um so let's say now you have your
compute budget a fixed number of gpus
for a certain amount of days and you
also know approximately how much data
you want to use uh the question is that
where do you find this type of data um
for example Lama 3 was trained on 15
trillion tokens but where do you get 15
trillion tokens that's a huge
number um to get this data uh the two
sources where you can actually get very
large volume of data are the web and
then GitHub code there are some other
curated sources that are of high quality
but are much smaller like Wikipedia
books archive or Stock Exchange you can
also get um data a new type that's been
very trendy recently which is synthetic
data but let's first start with the
sources where you can get very large
volumes
the first one is web data uh so that's
basically web pages um and usually
people to create these data sets they
start from common craw which is a public
repository of CW web pages um comeon C
CS Pages regularly and they publish
dumps every few months um but if you
start from there you will need to do
some heavy filtering at a very large
scale for example just the latest dump
has over 400 terabytes and they have
almost 95 dumps so that's not a very
easy task and um you will need to have a
lot of resources and a team to be able
to do that craw in uh the other option
is to use an existing uh filtered web
data set where researchers already
filtered come and craw and release them
and luckily we do have data sets that
are very large and well filtered one of
them is the the way web data fine web
that was recently released by hugging
face and it has 15 trillion tokens of
web
data um it's also it's not just a large
data set but it also has the best
performance among the publicly available
data sets and here for example it shows
the performance which is an aggregation
over multiple popular benchmarks for NLP
like H swag mlu paa and others and it
averages them and compares to other dat
set like C4 refined web SL pajama and
the
pile um so that was for web so you can
get 15 trillion tokens easily and then
for code data um we have released the
stack data set which is um the largest
data set of uh open source code uh this
data set comes in two versions version
one consisted of six terabyt of
permissive code and um how we built this
data set is that we first cloned all the
public repositories on GitHub so this
gave us over 130 repositories and 100
terab of data uh but we don't want all
of that data because a lot of it can be
configs or extensions that we don't need
or languages that are no longer
maintained so we did some file
extensional filtering and we ended up
with almost 90 terab of data after that
we filtered repositories based on their
licenses so we can have permissive
licenses like Apache 2 or MIT you can
have more restrictive licenses like GPL
so we filtered all the repositories that
did not have a permissive license and
after that we did the D duplication to
remove files that are similar so we
ended up with almost 3 terabyt of the
duplicated
data um this tack comes also with a very
cool tool for opt out um this tool is
basically a space where you can go you
can type your GitHub username and it
tells you if you have any of your GitHub
repositories in the data set um and if
that's the case there's also an option
to fill a form and request to be removed
from all the future trainings of the
code um so we did that for the stack V1
but also for the stack V2 um in the V2
is a much larger and enhanced data set
compared to the V1 um this time instead
instead of cloning GitHub repositories
we went through software Heritage which
is an archive of code they already did
the scraping and we just extracted the
data from their archive and we we ended
up after all the filtering with almost 1
trillion tokens which is a lot compared
to the V1 where we got around 200
billion tokens at the end we also added
some high quality resources like kab
issues uh math and code data sets polar
requests so these data sets the stack V1
the stack V2 can be used to train llms
on code or to train General LMS and
include code as a subset of the general
web
data um this shows how the stack V2
compares to the V1 and you can see that
before filtering it's almost 10 times
larger and after filtering it's four or
five times
larger um so I talk about how to get web
data how to get code data and then also
mentioned synthetic data and um it's
this year and last year that synthetic
data became very important for LMP
training and I think that in the next
few years it will become even more
important and I think this was mainly
sparked by the Five series of models by
Microsoft uh their first paper was
called textbooks are all you need and
they basically generated synthetic
textbooks using GPT 3.5 and GPT 34 and
they tried tried to build a new
pre-training Corpus that is synthetic
and they were able to match and
outperform models that are trained on
web data sets um so this model was
trained on almost entirely synthetic
data but now some of the very popular
llms are using synthetic data as part of
their P trining mix for example Cloud 3
uh in the model card they say that they
generate data internally and they
include it in the pre-training uh this
is also the case for 3 where they used
the llms to build classifiers that would
annotate samples and only keep the high
quality ones but they also generated
synthetic content to um uh improve
performance on coding and reasoning and
long
context so synthetic data is a very new
topic but it seems really
interesting um I'm personally working
also on that as hugging phase we
recently released a data set called
cosmia which was the largest data set of
synthetic text and it had almost 25
billion tokens and instead of using
closed models like gp4 it used an open
source model which is mixol
887b and um we also released the block
post that explains how we created this
data set because it can be very tricky
to get very diverse samples um so we
used an approach where we had 80% of the
data that's comes from the web and then
we try to use these web samples to build
new prompts that ask models to generate
textbooks that are related to these web
samples but while giving them more comp
context so we can uh limit the
generations for example we can have a
topic that is the mathematics and then
we have web samples that are related to
mathematics and each time we give the
model of prompt generate a textbook in
the field of mathematics that is related
to this web sample and the more web
samples we add the more diversity we add
uh we also used some curated sources
like Stanford courses and Wiki how where
we use extracts from these pages to ask
the models to generate content that is
related to them you can find more
details in theopedia blog
post um so I guess now we also have the
answer for our second question which was
where to find the data and if you're
following we have one question left
which is how can we filter this data
because for example if you use common
craw and you need to filter it and even
if you use this stack we did not train
our models on the stack directly we did
a lot of filtering to get a data set
that is smaller but has a higher
quality and um for this data set I will
site the slide from Tom Thomas Wolf's
presentation this lecture is very
interesting by the way you can find it
here um and this is from the e paper
where they stat that a high quality data
set might exhibit very Advanced
capabilities for a standard architecture
and this is actually the focus of um
many recent papers and we can see that
in model releases the sections about
data sets are becoming smaller and
smaller because people are realizing
that the data set is actually the
backbone in is the one that is making
some models much better than others so
it's really important to spend a lot of
time creating these dat data sets and
trying to remove all the outliers and
data sets that can hurts the model
during the
training um this is the pipeline from
the e paper for filtering their uh C web
data set so first they do language
filtering so I guess in these case they
kept English and some Asian languages
then they apply some filtering
techniques to remove local quality
samples uh for example there are some
metrics like um you look for files that
have a lot of lines repeated and then
remove them that's also rule based
correction you also can use perplexity
filtering where you compute something
like a loss and remove samples that have
a very high one then after that they
also did a very a step which is very
important D duplication um because there
are a lot of papers that study the
effect of duplicates on training and
they find that keeping duplic in the
training data can cause models to
memorize and they have less space to be
creative um so this hurts the
performance of models and it's always uh
advised to remove duplicates using
exactly duplication to remove files that
are exactly identical but also near the
duplication to remove files that are
similar and this uses techniques like
Minash the
duplication for ye after that they also
did more filterings on top like semantic
and topic filtering uh but usually you
can do like the classic filtering and
duplication and then be more creative
for the other
filters um that was also the case for
fine web the reason it is better than
other data set is that because they
spent a lot of time trying to come up
with better filters and also they
duplicate the data set
well um now the question is okay we can
do the apption I think we have methods
that are established to do that uh we
can also do language filtering and but
then if you want to filter the data to
remove garbage and lower quality files
how do you come up with good filters um
you can for sure suff find some filter
filters in the literature but if you
want to really build a data set that is
better than what exists you need to
invest some time is trying to find more
techniques that work better for your
case this can be done with manual
inspection
um which is always a good idea to look
at the data and see what it actually
looks like and you can come up with
filters to help you during the training
uh but that is usually not enough
because you might have an intuition uh
for a filtering that works better for
your model but then when you train
actually this filtering doesn't help and
for example for us when we were
developing the star coder series of
models um we were thinking okay what are
the best ways for us to filter code so
we use some standard filters for example
to remove autogenerated content but we
try to come up with a little bit more
complex filterings that could help us
like looking for files that have a lot
of commment because code that is usually
well documented is probably of a higher
quality than another code file that
doesn't have any comments so we
implemented this filter that looks for
files that have almost no comments and
then REM moves them and um we train the
model on that inter the performance
Improvement was really negligible it was
not as much as we thought we also tried
to use another filter which is using the
stars of repository as an indicator of
quality so we tried removing all the
files from repository that have less
than five stars and this ended up
removing over 70% of the data set and
then when we trained on it the model was
the worst model that we trained in all
our ablation experiments simply because
it removed too much data it was not not
worth using this U uh filtering
technique this is why it's very
important that when you have a filter
you should run what we call an ablation
model the ablation is basically you take
a subset of your data set after you
applied the filtering and you train a
small model on it and see how it behaves
with and without the
filtering and um you might be wondering
okay if I use a small model but does it
really extrapolate to larger models I
think that's a good question but
generally from our exper expence we
found that this it does extrapolate for
most of data
ablations um when when you're doing
these ablations you should select a set
of high signal benchmarks uh that could
show you some U give you some
conclusions about the effect of your
filtering early in the training uh this
can be some of the popular NLP
benchmarks for llms for example H swag
or
mlu um you should also uh sorry here
it's not try it's
with different seeds to reduce the noise
because sometimes you can have filtering
techniques that don't give you a very
big difference but if you train with
just one seed um you must draw
conclusions but they're actually just
noise so if you can and you have the
compute it's always better to run the
same experiment with two or three
different seeds and then maybe do
something like the averaging so that you
reduce the noise and you have more
robust conclusions about the effect of
your
filtering for for example for the fine
web data set uh the authors run over 200
plus ablations these were like 1 billion
models trained on I think 30 billion
tokens and this is how they were able to
find filterings that worked better for
their data
sets um now let's uh go back to our star
coder use case um and I will tell you
about how we filtered the stch data set
so for the version one um
if you remember we had six terab of
source code and then but when we trained
star coder we only used 800 gigabyte of
these six terabyte so a lot of this data
was filtered out after our
filtering our
curation the same happened for the stack
V2 where this time we started from 32
terab in 600 programming languages and
after the filtering we ended up with
only 6.3 terab of code
and uh for filtering code um the
approach is a bit similar to just
filtering web data but the filtering
techniques are a bit different so first
we wanted to include a lot of
programming
languages um and we looked at them and
we didn't keep all of them we only kept
the popular ones and excluded for
example configs and languages that are
no longer maintained so this was for V1
for Star coder 2 we included more
languages over over 600 and then we
added some other sources that could be
interesting for a code model to learn
from uh which are GitHub issues git
commits and Jupiter notebooks uh we also
added for the V2 kagle notebooks and PO
requests um the second step after we
selected the languages we wanted to
train on was Data Quality Inspection um
so basically as I told you we had some
filters to remove um low quality files
and autogenerated content um an example
is the average line length so if you
have an average line length that is too
high there's probably something wrong
with this file or it's probably
autogenerated but since we had like
almost 100 programming languages we
should not use the same threshold for
all the languages for this filter
because some programming languages just
have longer lines so it's important to
do some inspection and look at some
samples from these languages in our case
we have the big code Community which
helps us look at 100 samples per
extension and derive the appropriate
thresholds in filtering horis
stics um the uh second third the
duplicate uh sorry filtering step was
near duplication um we found that near
duplication was the filtering that gave
us the most performance boost it's also
very easy to apply because it's language
agnostics even though we have 86
programming languages we don't need to
change the duplication for each language
we can just apply it to the whole sub to
the whole data set and here I show you
some results of the effects of the
duplication for example here you can see
this model python all license if the
filtering is none you get a pass at one
which is our code metric of 13 but if
you apply your duplication you go from
13 to 17 that's a very big uh
performance bump the same goes for other
subsets like per license so we decided
to use um the duplication for our data
set and to use strong the duplication to
really remove all the files that could
be
similar um another step is in our
pipeline is to remove personal
identifiable information so this could
be names emails or keys or passwords uh
because we create code from GitHub and
although GitHub has some tools to detect
secrets and prompt users to remove them
that's not always the case and we found
that there was still a lot of secrets in
the data set and we train a model you
don't want it to be trained on that
because in inference it might generate
sensitive or personal data um so our
approach to removing it was to First
annotated data set for pii um we uh
collaborated with an annotation company
to annotate some samples so the
annotators were tasked with labeling
thep when they found it for example if
they find a name they give it a class
name if you find an email they also
label it as an email so it was a named
entity recognition task and then we
train the star Pi which is our ner model
to detect this pii and then we run it on
the whole uh star coder training
data um this took almost 800 8100 GPU
hours because it's a more it's a neural
network and it needs to run on gpus um
the last step in our filtering was Data
decontamination um because you should
make sure to remove the benchmarks and
test sets from your training data
otherwise your evaluation numbers will
just be inflated so we made sure to
remove the benchmarks that we use for
evaluation from our training
sets the last step in the data curation
of the stack was to format the data so
now that the data is filtered and
because code is different from test from
text we can allow ourselves to apply
some nice formatting that could help us
during inference for example for Star
coder we had the code file but before
the code we added some tokens that
indicate that this is the repository
name and another token file name that
indicates the file name and another one
for stars and this is interesting
because this model for example star
coder and other code models I guess
their main use case is to be plugged in
an IDE for example vs code and when
you're using them it could be
interesting to append the code file with
like the name of the file for example I
don't know file dopy so that the model
would know this is a python file if it's
in another language when you add the
file name and you have the extension it
could know that this is detect the
language that it should generate code in
we also added GitHub Stars token and we
try to play with it like to say this
file has 100 stars and see if the model
would generate higher quality code than
if it would to generate for zero stars
um we didn't find any differences really
during inference but it was fun to add
all this
formatting for Star coder 2 one of the
improvements was that star coder 2 was
repository aware um because when we have
GitHub repositories it's repository so
we have some files that are in the same
repository that are related to each
other but when we built the stack V1 we
just shuffled files so we kept we didn't
keep this repository structure and we TR
the model we just shuffled them and the
model did not know if two files belong
to the same repository but when we did
start coder to we tried to keep files
that are in the same repository next to
each other and how we did that is by
concatenating them with some special
tokens like file SE which basically
separates files and this way the model
can kind of um
uh know which files are need the same
repository and try to find links between
them 3D parallelism and then you have
also light Evol for doing the evaluation
so this is kind of Stack to be able to
run your full trainings but also your
ablation models you can apply a filter
from data TR and then train with nron
and Evol with light evolve and they're
well integrated together and they make
one
ecosystem so that's for general llms for
code llms we also released the code we
used for both this tag and star coder
models under our big code repository on
GitHub and I think we just answered our
third question which was how to filter
the data so now you know how to First
how much data you need and then where
you can get this data both web and code
and synthetic and curated and you also
know how you can properly filter the
data and you can test the filtering
techniques that you have in mind um so
now uh let me tell you a little bit more
about Cod LMS because uh that's kind of
what I'm working on um and I'm trying to
give you a little bit of an overview
about these models so that you know how
to train good llms but you also know how
to build very cool code assistance and
completion
models um so how all of this started was
um when GitHub calet was released uh and
it was was very interesting because it
was so much better than all the other
code completion models that were before
it which were very small and much less
performance and GitHub copilot was using
the Codex model by open AI um and they
just showed that you can train a code
llm in the same way that you train an
llm for English for example you just you
can just take a large Transformer model
and give it a lot of code data and it
will learn this code uh because before a
lot of people were trying to treat code
very differently for example by using
abstract syntax trees uh but what codex
model showed is that you can treat code
like text and if you want to predict the
next line you predict the next text you
just do next token prediction and you
get your code it works very well much
better compared to the more feature
engineer
techniques and that was like um over two
years ago and we didn't have any good
open code models uh but today if you go
to the hub you can find that we have
over 1,700 models that are trained on
code so these are models that are either
trained only on code or llms that
included code as part of their training
um so you can see that we've made a lot
of progress in this code generation
field which is
amazing and um this is the work this is
the result uh of the community's work to
build very good instruction tuned models
and base models for example here as you
can see in the leaderboard we have some
very strong models that score almost 80%
on the code evaluation Benchmark which
is human eval which means they get
almost 80% of the problems right which
is a very large
number and uh when talking about the
landscape of open code llms in big code
we have released the stack data set
which is now the default data set for
training on code and also star coder one
and star coder 2 family of models and
other instruction tuned models with the
ag4 team like Star Chat 2 um meta also
released some very good code models
which are the code llama series of
models that go from 7B to 70b uh there
are also the Deep seek models which are
also very strong and you have also other
models like the recent Granite models
from IBM uh code quen code Jen and Sable
code so there are different providers
for code
llms and also for data sets for
code and um the main reason we started
the big code collaboration and to train
St coder models was to kind of have a
collaboration where we have full data
transparency uh we released all the
details about the training but also the
data is public so that people can
inspect it and use it and we also have
the code for the processing and the
model weights and the collaboration was
open we had over a thousand resources
ERS joining our like and following the
journey with
us and this kind of created a big code
ecosystem where the stack was used in
the pre-training of a lot of prominent
code models like um code gen and stable
code and the star coder models were used
as basis for a lot of community fine
tunings um and I think it's very
important to be aware of um what makes a
release of an llm whether it be a code
llm or General llm open and
responsible um and I think this is like
for fold first uh it's really good for
the community and for research in AI in
general if you can make open access data
sets this uh will help this will means
having data inspection tools but also
opt out tools to respect people's wishes
regarding their data sets for example if
they don't want to be included in
trainings they should be able to opt out
uh it's also important to remove
personal identifiable
information so an open release does not
mean just releasing model weight and
stopping there but also making your work
reproducible by fully documenting the
pipeline for using these models and also
releasing tools for evaluation um and
Technical reports that documents the
whole
Pipeline and um for us in the code we
kind of went from stanta coder which was
part of our oblations to understand how
to filter the stack data set uh and then
we went to Star coder which was released
last year a 15 billion code generation
model and then uh this year we released
star coder 2 which was trained on much
more programming languages and had a
much higher uh evaluation
score and the star coder was also rated
as the most transparent model by the
Stanford Foundation model transparency
index which uh which is really hardw
given the offers that we put into Data
governance and into making the model
release as transparent as
possible um regarding evaluation so for
example star coder 15b when it was reled
released it was the state-ofthe-art code
model and this was also the case for
Star coder 25b among other 15b models
and it was even close or better than a
Lar models um I think I don't have the
plot here but it was better than it was
matain code Lama 34b uh and it was close
to deep seek 33b on some benchmarks and
here for example you can see the results
on different benchmarks um because when
releasing a model it's really important
that you don't just give a wait on one
Benchmark but you should add as many
benchmarks as you want in case you had
contamination although we Tred to avoid
this one Benchmark there's a very low
chance that you also have contamination
other benchmarks and it also allows you
to fully understand how your model
behaves if you add more evaluation
benchmarks and I think that's just a
good practice that everyone should be
doing with their
releases um so with the star coder
models we also released some tooling uh
like vs code
implementation which also has a
membership test that tries to see if the
generated code was in the training data
and highlight that to the author so
that's part of our code
attribution uh efforts for these code
models um maybe you're interested in
using these models to build your own
personal co-pilot and fine- tune in Star
coder or codam or other models on your
personal code basis uh to do that
there's a very nice blog post by S and
sayak where they try to take a code
model and train it on the hugging face
internal libraries and then deploy it in
ama and have a local code assistant and
the pipeline is very similar to what we
did in pre-training first you take your
data set you try to filter out the
things you don't want to keep and then
you do the duplication and you train
your model so in this case it will be
just a fine tunity so it will be much
quicker you can use libraries like PFT
uh which do parameter efficient fine
tuning where you don't need to train all
the parameters of your models but you
only inject few trainable parameters um
this makes the training much faster for
example 7B model can be trained in a
Google
cab um now let's go back to
evaluation so for example for llms
there's the open llm leaderboard uh that
evaluates models there's also the LMC
Arena which Compares instruct models and
uses human evaluation uh for code models
one of the most popular benchmarks is
human evil and it's basically a
benchmark where you have a um function
that the model has to autocomplete and
then when the function is completed you
take this solution and then you run it
against multiple unit tests and you
count how many solutions pass and how
many solutions fail and then you count
what we a metric that we call Passat one
for example this is the one that's been
reported in this leader
and this gives you the human eval score
um there's also a translation of this
Benchmark to 18 other languages here I
show Java and JavaScript in C++ and
Benchmark is called multiple so it kind
of allows you to see how each how well
each model does on which programming
language and choose the one that's the
most interesting for
you um but um these benchmarks usually
have an issue of uh contam ation and
overfitting uh especially instruction
tuned models I don't know if you've
already checked what these data sets
look like but usually for code they are
um an instruction that asks the model to
generate an exercise and often if you
look at them they look really similar to
human evil which is like function
implementations so it there's a very
high chance of having contamination
which means having some like um files
that look like human Evol uh exercises
in your instruction tuning data set um
so here for example this plot is from
the life code bench leaderboard and they
kind of find that on benchmarks may be
over fitting on human eval and so their
solution was to have a leaderboard
called life code bench uh where they
regularly scrape new problems from um
platforms like uh code contest and Lead
code and they evaluate the models only
on the problems that were released after
the model release date this way they are
sure that there is no
contamination and for example that was
the case here they tried to evaluate
these models on all the data they have
and then they compared the performance
to the data that was only released after
the model release and they found that
some models were not consistent in their
results um so that's one interesting
thing to keep in mind
and this is the uh this is also another
leader board that could be interesting
to compare not just open models but also
closed models like GPT for and see where
the open source Community is standing
compared to these code
models uh so that was my presentation
thank you very much for your attention
um if you have any questions I can
answer
them yes thank you very much for the
great insightful talk um so we have some
questions here on slido I'm s I'm not
sure if there are any inperson questions
or else I will uh get started with the
slider
question
sure okay guess not so we um I'll ask
some of the questions online I think I
had submitted some of these as well um
it seems like there's some questions
about synthetic data let me see um I was
also wondering about this um so
someone's asking what are the
consequences of training AI models on AI
generated synthetic data do you foresee
any problems with this and there's a
related question does synthetic data
closely represent the natural
distribution of language I assume some
low quality data from humans is
necessary for things like learning
robustness and so
far yeah sure these are very great
questions um so about the consequences
of training uh models on AI generated
data I can think of two main ones first
is like enforcing some biases uh because
models already have some biases and if
we train on data that is generated by
them we might be enforcing it even more
um the other thing is for example
contamination um these models might be
trained might generate content that
looks like the evaluation benchmarks and
when you train on that you will have
contamination in your data so for
example one of the critics of the five
models that people because they did not
see the synthetic data and the models
were very good on the benchmarks they
were very skeptical are these models
really good or are they just overfitting
on the benchmarks so I think
contamination and enforcing biases are
uh one of the main things to keep in
mind and U regarding synthetic data and
not being the same as like web
distribution uh I think that's a very
good point and for example when we were
developing cosmop media first we found
that like it was worse than the web and
which was like surprising because we
spent a lot of time trying to curate
this data set which looks so much
cleaner than the web and then I adding
some web data and trying to add like
more topics was able to help us
compensate some of the gaps but adding
some web Al always like gives you a
performance boost so yes there's some
noise and some specific patterns in web
data that will probably need to be
included in the training mix to keep uh
like a whole coverage of um what natural
distributions look like so it sounds
like you're saying a good training set
would have a mix potentially of
synthetic and natural data is that
correct yeah I think so like some
experiment for on show that that's the
case um because you can try to spend
some time to carefully curate the topics
but we'll probably be missing out on
some things and the human intuition that
we have is not always what works for
training models it seems that's keeping
some filtered web helps and also if you
see the F technical reports for example
in 53 they insist a lot on filtering the
web and including it in the pre-training
and I think that now seems like um maybe
the best way to
go right that makes sense great um
another question is is rhf type
preference data more important than
unsupervised pre-training data should we
spend more resources on rhf data
um yeah that's a good question uh so for
example the unsupervised pain is mainly
to get based models but then you can use
these base models as chat assistance you
need to do another step so you could
either do rhf but uh nowadays people are
just doing instruction tuning without
needing to go through RL uh where you
just train the model on pairs of
instructions and solutions and that
seems to work very well and there are
now some methods that don't use
reinforcement learning but work as well
for example DPO or orpo so I think if
you want a chat assistant you definitely
need to run like a supervised training
on top of the unsupervised one but it
doesn't necessarily have to be earf
there are some other algorithms
now great great and here's a
multimodal question does multimodal
grounding for example including images
and videos along with the text reduce
the need for so much text only data
yeah what do you mean I'm sorry oh the
question is asking does multimodal
grounding help basically if you have
images and videos along with the text
does this reduce the amount of text only
data required to train
models um so I can't probably answer
that because I haven't tried but I guess
all for example the multimodel model for
example eix that we recently released uh
there's always always a significant text
portion that seems the case for most VIs
language models um but yeah I don't know
really about the percentages for each
right okay
um a more general question you probably
touched upon some of this but are there
any major differences between training
text versus code models other than the
training data being
different yes that's a good question so
like the training data is different
regarding the training itself um we use
a similar architecture for example start
C it was like a llama or M architecture
I think one thing that you probably want
is long context uh because if you want
to use these models for example in vs
code and you want to add all the
neighboring files in the context you
should be able to fit a very large
context so we try to do some long
context extension but again people also
do this for llms um we also care a lot
about inference so we use the gqa first
mqa and then gqa to have faster
inference but these are also techniques
that are implemented for LMS uh so it's
say overall it's very similar but yeah
maybe you should prioritize some things
like having a smaller model uh this can
be used for um for example IDE faster
than actually a much larger model that
would need more
deployment um yeah all great and here's
also a general question um I guess
they're asking for advice so if you have
a very tiny compute budget for example a
single GPU um what would you recommend
prioritizing um let's assume you are
fine-tuning a
model yeah so I think for example now
there are some great solutions for on
device uh deployment and uh fine tunings
uh for example you can run quantized
models with llama CPP or other
Frameworks and uh with the techniques
like PFT you don't need to do full model
fine tuning and you should be able to
run this on one GPU even a 7B model uh
so I think you should just like find the
very well curated data set because
quality is more important than quantity
and then use one of these techniques for
easy fine tuning um and that should
work all right great
um here's a question asking I guess
different from pre-trading but um
they're they're saying I'm guessing the
optimal amount of training data depends
heavily on the domain as well as the
task at hand right
um yes probably um now we're following
the CH scaling laws I think they tried
to compare like English to code and they
found that the findings still hold uh
but maybe if you go to another domain I
know like medical things could change
that's why I mentioned the Deep seek
paper where they mentioned that like
it's really heavily dependent on data
and for them it was the same domain they
just changed data sets like going from
one generic data set to another Well
curated one and things started changing
so so I think that's that's probably the
case but it's underexplored how these
scaling laws change depending on domains
so it's good to be aware of that When
developing models for domains that are
not explored by these speaking of
different domains code versus Tex
someone's asking what are some of the
interesting differences between
tokenizing um for general purpose like
text versus for
codenation yeah so for when we were
training uh the token er um think one
thing that was important to keep like
number
splitting uh and we used the standard
bpe and we were training it we trained
on our data set that we were using for
the training data so like our code
mixture and we did some analysis to see
if there are like any outliers
any tokens that were under represented
or over represented as sanity checks uh
but overall it's very close to uh the uh
text uh training and now most llms have
like a significant code portion in their
tokenizers so they're also trained on a
lot of code and at the end you can use
like either one to another for LMS for
code or the other way because even on
code you have a lot of markdown so
there's a lot of English so you end up
representing all the English tokens for
example in your code
tokenizer great and here's the question
of fine tuning I guess compared to
pre-training so um they're ask do the
same principles apply um for fine-tuning
or would you make different or
additional
recommendations um so yeah for fine
tuning I think when you're preparing the
data it's probably a different thing
you're not going to train on like all of
the stack you probably want to continue
training on specific language uh so
maybe you could invest more time like to
even heavily filter because for fine
tuning you don't need as much data as
for pre-training uh for example for us
the
tried for example star they didn't work
because they removed a lot of data and
we did not have enough for our pre
training while for fine tuning for
example for instruction tuning there was
like the Lima paper where they
instruction tuned only on a thousand
instructions and they had a model that
was much better than TR on millions of
samples so I think that cation is even
much more important when it comes to
point
tuning great great one last question I
guess um so you might have also touched
upon this briefly but what are some
considerations to make when publishing
very large data sets and more nuanced or
less known things to be aware
of yeah so um maybe on uh the technical
side um releasing tools also for
filtering and documentation that's what
we try to do with the stack and um maybe
more on the governance side be aware of
like where the licens is respected where
the copyrights respected do you have an
opt out tool for your dat Set uh and
maybe try to release it on the Hub to
make it easily accessible for people if
there are some concerns you could try to
add a gate for example for us we
released the data set that we used for
pi detection but we add some gating
mechanism because it was sensitive
information so it's good to think of
this kind of things in advance before
releasing a data set um but yeah in
general these are my
advice right great do we have any
in-person questions
um if not then we can probably conclude