Okay. Uh let's get started. So actually
the topics that we have discussed so far
are kind of the basics of the diffusion
models. So if your goal is to basically
make your own diffusion model uh and
also if you want to apply those like
some kind of the train the diffusion
models for some applications the things
that we have discussed so far would be
kind of sufficient for many
applications. And now what we are going
to do is that we are going to go deeper
into the some the theory of BB models.
And I think that this is actually kind
of the key part uh key concept in the
deep models in terms of like basically
having some kind of a different angle in
terms like understanding different
models. So as I mentioned at the very
beginning of this class uh we are going
to basically see the diffusion models
from the very different angles all the
time of the this class. uh and this is
kind of the uh the time that we are
switching all the gear into that you
know we are basically now seeing the
understanding the future models in the
uh continuous time domain
for the today's topic uh probably I
guess the today's lecture would be short
uh there's not much things that I can
tell you but I'm going to show some kind
of lots of the formulations here uh so
the but the point would not be basically
just like understanding like the the
formulations the line by line uh I'm
going to tell you introduce some kind of
be some high level the ideas in terms of
how we can basically view the diffusion
models in the context time domain and
based on that basically what we can do.
So previously basically what we have
seen in this class is that uh we have
seen this kind of like some basic
formulations for the DDPM right. So once
we basically define the uh fold the
transition distribution in this way into
the Gaussian form then based on that we
uh this is like the default distribution
that I call as the jump distribution
jumping the xt from the x0. This also
could be defined as some kind of another
decision distribution.
The another form of the diffusion model
that we very briefly have seen uh in the
previous slide which I uh call that as
kind of the NCSN but also was called the
other name the SMLD. This is another
kind of the different way that we are
defining the F transition distribution
into this way which corresponding the F
the jump distribution is kind of the
defined in the other way like this
right. So this was basically the other
another way of basically defining this
kind of the B process of the diffusion
models right. So based on that basically
we could see basically how we can
perform the reverse process which is
also like performing you know like the
iterative way and as I also discussed in
the previous the lecture the downside of
the vision model is that it's basically
taking too much time because of the
iteration. So that was kind of the
motivation that we started to discuss
the idea of the DDIM uh which is
basically turning the uh stochastic
degeneration the process of the DDPM
into the deterministic process uh in
terms of that we can now reduce the
number of the uh dening steps up to the
50. Uh so that's also something that we
need to basically test using in your the
first assignment
and the kind of the good thing of the
advantage in terms of understanding the
future models in the context time is
that now we're going to also see uh not
today but until the week of the next
week uh we're going to see how this the
the number of the time steps can go down
to almost the 10 steps like this. So
this is kind of this score uh which
called FID. So lower means basically the
better which means that the image
quality and the diversity is better when
this score is basically the lower. So
what we can see is that as we obviously
increase the number of time steps for
the DDPM uh at the very beginning is
basically nothing but right but as we
basically goes to the 1,00 and now we
can start to see some kind of the some
polish images for the DDIM uh even from
the very beginning the steps uh we are
basically starting at this kind of the
better position here and getting much
better as we basically go to the 1,00 uh
but if we use some kind of a different
idea Here for example like this one. Uh
then what you can see is that uh even
with the like almost like 10 to the 15
the steps uh we are achieving very uh
the nice quality of the output images.
Uh and this is like all done uh without
basically training some kind of a new
diffusion models but just like changing
the uh the generation the process of the
diffusion models. So that's was very
interesting point in terms of
understanding the diffusion models.
So what I briefly mentioned last time is
that uh basically uh in the continuous
time domain the full process of
diffusion model uh can be formulated
into this type of the stoastic the
differential the equation. So basically
you can see that this is like one type
of the differential equation in terms of
that we have the xt function here is the
first derivative is basically also
represented as some kind of some
function of the uh the linear function
of the the term itself. But while we are
basically having this term uh which is
basically kind of like injecting some
sort of batistry. Uh so you can see that
if we basically visualize the process of
like how this XT goes over the time you
can see that you know the point here is
basically map to the other point here
basically with some kind of some very uh
jaggy some perturbing some kind of
trajectory. So this kind of the the
trajectory of the XT can be represented
into the STD. Uh so that's the alo the
kind of the main idea in terms of seeing
the different models in the uh the
context time domain. Uh actually this
can be basically some kind of the
function of the XT. It does not need to
be this kind like the linear form but
we're going to basically start to see
some kind of the simpler deform in terms
of that we having the linear function
here. And when you see basically this
kind of the form what we are going to
call is that this term will be called as
kind of the drift the coefficients. So
it's basically like sort of like moving
the mean of each of the the trajectory
and this is the diffusion coefficients.
So this is about basically the amount of
the some kind of the stoaticity that we
are injecting over the time. So and this
is kind of the uh default process
and without having basically having any
kind of a proof uh the one of the key
things uh in the when seeing the
different models in the contest time
domain is that uh once we basically have
some kind of the uh SD this differential
equation basically define the full
process of division multi in this way
then we can directly find uh the SDE
for the reverse process which is now
defined in this way.
So you can see that the formulation is
kind of very similar uh with the def
case right and this is also like quite
interesting point in terms of that uh
once you basically define the for SD in
this way then we can directly basically
find the SD for the reverse process
which is now defined in this way using
the same the division the coefficients
here and also the drift term uh the here
but you can see that we are basically
having another the term here uh which is
basically involving this core function
that we keep seeing right uh so this is
kind of the point so what we can
typically do is that in the deep models
so it's basically exactly the same as
basically what we have seen for the DDP
case so in those DDP case we first
define the the uh default process right
and based on that we once we can assume
that the noise can be basically
predicted this core can be predicted
using this core prediction the network
then process is also automatically
defined right so it's basically exactly
the same thing in the continuous the
case as well once we define the fold SD
while basically we assume that this call
function is kind of known kind of like
the the predicted then we can directly
perform the SD the reverse process with
this SD as well so this is exactly the
same thing
so here the thing is that so basically
how we are going to define these two
terms right so this is the main
how we are going to define the the drift
term and also the diffusion the coence
term and what's the meaning of like
these terms. Uh so these three things
are basically the main things that we're
going to discuss today. So let's go
first go with the uh the last term here.
So basically uh this is kind of the the
term in terms of that we are injecting
some kind of stock. Uh so this term is
basically typically uh they called as
kind of the winner process or the the
brown the motion. So which is basically
some kind of the real value some kind of
the uh the function which has some kind
of some following the characteristics.
So basically this is the function which
is starting with the zero right. So
every time basically the time is zero is
starting from the zero. So here
basically almost surely means that the
probability like starting from zero is
basically the one. So that's kind of the
mathematical the meaning of the almost
surely
and then what the meaning of the brown
the motion is that the increment of the
each of the the time step also follow
some kind of the normal distribution. So
that's the secondary characteristics
and the third characteristic is that uh
it's basically independent uh which
means that every increment from the the
previous step and also next steps are
basically independent each other. So
this is the third characteristics and
the last one is that uh also is the
continuously function almost surely
which means that the continuity is
basically the the the probability for
the continuity is basically the one for
the all the time t. So you can think
that this basically brown and multi
motion is basically the the function
that has those kind of the four
characteristics and you can see that
basically this function is already kind
of the one single kind of the SD
basically having some kind of the
stoaticity over the time. So here the
question in this default SD formulation
is that how much we are going to inject
this kind of the uh some sort of the
soeticity while basically somehow like
moving the the point of the XT using the
drift term here. So that's the meaning
of the for the the process.
So based on that uh what I'm going to
briefly go over is that you know for
each of the case of the SMLD and also
the DDPM uh we are going to see what we
kind of corresponding the for SD. So
from this formulation can you guess what
be some kind of corresponding the FT
term here and also GT term here?
images.
Uh
once you see the derivation, you're
going to see that actually the
derivation is not that kind of difficult
here. Uh but uh before we get into
basically how we can basically derive
the the default SDE uh let me quickly
just know uh you some kind of
background. Everyone knows the Taylor
right? uh so Taylor C is basically
nothing but no we are basically uh
approximate some kind of increment of
the functions with the first and the
second and the third order kind of
derivatives right so that's kind of the
basic idea of the the taylor
uh based on that let me ask you like
quick question so based on the this
Taylor here
uh given any kind of function f when the
t plus delta t can be approximated in
this way uh what kind of the first order
the approximate uh for this function
when the epsilon is very small.
Do you have any answer for this?
>> Uh 1 minus epsilon
1 / two. Yes. Uh but yeah try yourself.
Uh let me give you some time to work on
this.
Uh did everyone get something like this?
Let me know if you find some kind of
typos here. But basically yeah uh using
the daily this if we just take some kind
of the first order approximation for
this term then without the root then we
can compute this right. Uh so these are
some kind of some basic things. So yeah
based on those kind of things what we
can see is that uh from the uh fourth uh
the transition the distribution for the
uh smld here which is defined in this
way uh now what we do is that the same
kind of the for the mark of the chain
just like replacing uh t and the t minus
one into the t plus or the t right so
then we going to basically see those
kind of the formulations
so basically what you can see is that
these are for some kind of the discrete
the time steps right given some kind of
the time range from the zero to the
capital T when you have some kind of the
discrete the finite time steps then
we're going to have those kind of the
vault the mark of the chain the question
is that what if we increase the number
of the time test steps into the infinity
right uh so that is basically that the
case that we are finding some kind of
the corresponding the uh the continuous
formulation like this Then in the case
that we have some kind of the infinite
number of the time steps uh the the
continuous formulation will look like
this right. This is basically very is
straightforward and from this based on
the tailor the the there is the first
order approximation what you can see is
that this can be basically approximated
into this form uh that looks like that
we are resulting into this formulation
right. So this is kind of like the one
specific deform of the full SDE in terms
of that the drift term uh becomes zero
uh while basically we are basically
adding some kind of the more distortity
over the time. So that's the kind of the
board SD for the SMLD and which is quite
some aligned with some kind of the
definition of the SMLD in terms of that
uh we we saw like the the meaning of
like this was basically some annual the
long dynamics basically the data
distribution was defined as some kind of
some gausian the smooth version of the
distribution. So at the very be so we
are basically gradually increasing some
kind of the variance of the the gausian
for each of the point in terms of that
in the reverse process at the very at
the very beginning we can get some kind
of the rough idea for this core function
every error in the the space and
especially we run over time for the
reverse process this core function
becomes like more the precise near each
of the data points right so that was the
basic idea for the
the long demand dynamics. So in the for
process basically the idea was basically
increasing the variance for each of the
gausian without really moving each of
the point right. Uh so basically this
for SDE is kind of really aligned with
some kind of the what we have seen for
the annual the long body dynamics right
so this is basically the one specific
form
of the the SD
but then how about the DDPMD case
in the DDPM case uh the f the transition
distribution uh was defined into this
way so in this case uh what we kind of
corresponding default SD. So basically
what we can see here is that uh what we
can we can basically need like the guess
uh is that in the smld
the mean of the uh the this the
transition distribution was just exactly
xt minus one without having any term
right uh so from this basically you can
see that the uh the drift term here
would be kind of basically zero so
basically no drift in here xt the the
mean of like this region becomes xt tas
right so every time basically there's no
kind of the drift here so that's the
kind of the uh the idea in terms that
we're having the fourth SD without the
uh fifth term here
but this is kind of different right uh
so we can see that over time we are
basically moving the each of the point
in terms of that this one becomes get
closer to the zero right so that is also
the basic idea for the DDPM which means
that probably the corresponding the in
In the corresponding port SDE the drift
term would not be zero right there would
be some kind of the moving force that
each of the point to get closer to the
the zero while adding some kind of
stoasticity.
So in this case if we also start to see
uh the corresponding the folddity
then what we can see is that this is the
corresponding the the mark of chain in
the discrete time domain and here
basically one the small thing is that if
we define the beta t in the continuous
time by multiplying this like the delta
t quantity here uh then we can also find
the continuity formulations like this
then using the taylor's uh that we have
seen the previous slide Right? Then we
can basically approximate the function
like this and we know that beta is kind
of the smooth function right. So we
define the beta in terms of that is
basically not making some big difference
basically for the consecutive time the
the time domains. Uh so we can also
approximate in this way. Then from this
uh actually it boils down to this very
simple uh deform of the for SDE and you
can see that there is some kind of the
moving force in terms like you know
moving to the point uh to get closer to
the uh to the origin while basically
having some kind of the
uh the stocketista
with some kind of diffusion equations.
So which basically shows that uh we can
find some kind of the corresponding uh
default SD for each of the cases. So we
define the SMLD and also DDPM with some
kind of default detion distribution and
also default the the jump the
distributions. uh based on that we can
now derive some kind of the
corresponding the for the SD formulation
which means that uh by solving this
formulation actually we can perform the
B process uh in the contents time domain
and more important thing is that given
this kind of the uh B SDE now we can
also directly define the uh the reverse
SDE as well so which means that the
reverse process can also be performed by
the solving the SD deformulation
so that's the kind of the basic idea.
Uh one also kind of a small thing is
that uh while basically skipping some
kind of proof here uh the meaning of
like this formulation is that if you
basically compute the coariance for each
of the xt for the intermed the the data
point actually the coariance of the
intermediate the data point can be
computed in this way. Basically the
meaning of like this is that if at the
starting point for the data point if the
coience was basically the one with the
identity then we can see that the coance
will be basically preserved as some kind
of the identity. Uh so that's kind of
the meaning of like this formulation.
So that's the reason like why we call
basically this uh the for SD as the uh
the variance preserving SD. So we're
going to use this term for the rest of
the lecture in terms of that this
formation called the BPSD the rest
preserving DSD because uh if the initial
decodence was basically the identity
then this will basically keep going for
the old DXT here because like this will
be the cancel out here uh actually this
should be zero here this is typo so
that's the kind of the case that we
having the uh the variance preserving
the SDE
uh for the uh the other case uh the
thing is that for this formulation the
coency is basically growing over time.
So this is the case that the be
basically exploding. So the fourth
process the port SD of the SMLD is
typically also called the PE SDE. So
those are some kind of terms that you
need to remember for the uh the rest of
the lectures.
So now we are basically seeing the same
the SMLD and the DPM in the content time
domain which for the process is now
defined as kind of the BSE and the
prepsd. So those were basically the two
formulations
and then here there might be some kind
of questions. So these are some kind of
the two specific deforms of the for SDE
right? Then the question might be is
that then what be some kind of the other
cases are these the only cases that we
can define the diffusion models where
can you basically have any random the
kind of default as the SD formulation
for default process. Do you have any
kind of the guess? Would there be some
kind of only two equations or would
there be some more other cases as well?
Basically this kind of two formulations
basically you know bring up this kind of
question. What do you kind of the other
possible cases like defining diffusion
models right? Uh so I mean obviously
these two are not the only case that we
can define the different models.
So that's was kind of the key idea that
we are going to discuss for today. Uh we
are going to see some kind of the more
the general form of the diffusion
models. Uh which is now defined in this
way.
So before we get into the SD deformation
uh we are going to uh now see some kind
of the family of the diffusion models
that's basically is typically called the
variational diffusion models and
actually the previously two cases are
basically some special cases of like
these forms.
So basically the the family of the the
variation diffusion models is basically
defined in this way. For any cases that
when we are defining the uh the for the
jumping the distribution the distriution
into this gausian form with some kind of
the alpha function here and also the
sigma d function here. uh if this the RP
sigma function satisfies uh some kind of
the uh satisfies some kind of the
conditions then we're going to call this
as kind of the one of the some the cases
of the variation of the division models.
So you can really check out whether
basically the hourly the definitions of
the SMLD and also the DDPM are really
basically satisfying those kind of the
conditions. So here the kind of
complication is that we are basically
also having some kind of the new
notations here. Uh we are going to the
thing is that these are also basically
very new things right. Uh so we are
basically following some kind of the
very recent papers as you can see some
references here. The problem here is
that every paper uses some different
notations that's the problem. So we are
going to use these specific notations.
The thing is that when these like the R
pi and the sigma functions uh so we
always first going to define the this
term the signal to be noise ratio. Uh so
this is about the signal right because
you basically define some kind of mean
of this uh this distribution. This sigma
term is basically define some kind of
noise. This is basically the amount of
the the some kind of stockicity that we
are injecting every time when we sample
the XT. Right? So when you basically
define the signal to the noise ratio as
kind of like this kind of term and when
this basically this term is
monotonically decreasing over time then
these are all the cases uh that can be
basically seen like one of the cases of
the variation models. So the meaning of
like the that the SNR is basically
decreasing over time is that over time
we are basically adding some kind of the
more noise right because at the end
basically what we want to see is that we
want that uh the basically after like
injecting all the noise in the for
process uh the the output of the
sampling should be basically aligned
with the the standard the gausian
distribution right see the purpose of
the fold process is to inject the noise
into the all of the points that we step
in terms of that the finally EB is
basically aligned with the standard
Gaussian distribution in a way that in
the reverse process we can go in the
reverse way right we sample from the
standard Gaussian distribution and
basically d noiseise over time in terms
of getting back to the the data point
which means that as we basically
increase the the time in the forward
process we need to inject more noise
right uh that makes sense so in a way
that we can basically you know make all
the out final the outputs to be the
samples of the tender the gaus and the
distribution. So basically that's the
meaning of like basically decreasing the
uh the the the signal to noise over the
time. So basically you know when you
basically define the arp signal the
functions in this way uh then we can
basically have the results. So like
basically aligning the final outputs to
be uh to the the standard the gausian
distribution.
So for all the cases, so this might kind
of the one specific way or define
different models for basically for all
those kind of the cases of the variation
diffusion models. Uh if we can basically
uh so yeah let me just get into that. So
before we basically how we uh see how we
define default process SD uh from the uh
the this definition of default the
distribution uh we're going to first see
kind of the opposite here. So let's say
like given the fourth process SD uh here
when you have some kind of the f
function and the g function here uh then
the fourth distribution uh here this
these two terms are basically defined in
this way. So this is kind of the the by
definition but you can based on this
what you can see is that we can go in
the other way around given the fourth
distribution which is defined in this
way we can also consider driving the
full SD. So we basically we're going to
get into that later.
So what basically based on this what you
can see is that now we are seeing some
kind of the connection between the fold
SD and the fold the jump the
distribution right and what we have seen
for the SMLD and the DDPM case in the
previous slide was basically the seeing
the connection between the uh default
jump distribution the detention
distribution uh into the this SD right
so now what we are going to briefly see
is that basically how basically these
three things are basically aligned each
So what you have seen in the previous
slide is the def the fold trench
distribution and deriving default SD and
now basically this like process the def
the SD we can also see that the fourth
the jump distribution is defined in this
way right and for the DDPM and also SMD
case uh we know these two terms the for
the jump distribution and the for the
for the Tion distribution and also the
for the jump distribution so let's
quickly check that out whether these are
aligned.
Uh so recall the the SMD the transition
distribution was defined in this way and
this like XT conditioned by the XU was
defined this way right. So from this
uh we derived the P SD right and from
the F SD we can now see how the fold the
jump distribution is defined in this
way. So which means that these all three
things are basically align each other
right
so let's quickly see so you can download
those slides from the selected workspace
uh so these are basically what we have
seen for the SMLD case so this is the
our default SD and also which was
derived from this right
and then based on this what you can see
is that uh if we compute the alpha and
the sigma uh this alpha and the sigma
functions then the fourth the jump
distribution should be defined in this
way right
makes sense
so let's quickly check this out so given
this the f and the g function uh what
should be the alpha function here and
also the the thing is that
this might be confusing but actually we
already have this like the sigma t terms
here are this is the same the sigma
function that we are seeing in the
definition of the variation diffusion
models. Uh so let's quickly check this
out.
By the way these notations can be
confusing but we are having this sigma
and the d sigma right. uh so what I mean
from this sigma is basically sigma
function defined in the SMLD so which is
basically aligned with the the the
variance that we are basically having in
the the annual the lang dynamics the
annual lang dynamics we are basically
increasing the we are having some kind
of gausian comb some kind of function
right so we are basically gradually
increasing the the variance of that the
gausian in terms of basically some kind
of the uh some kind of the some
approximation of this core function over
the time, right? So this is the the uh
the the the variance that we are
basically uh you know having some kind
of in the uh the longitudinal dynamics
and this sigma function is coming from
the hourly definition of the uh
uh the variational diffusion models that
we are using here, right?
And basically the key things that we are
uh seeing here is that while we have
seen some kind of the two specific cases
of defining diffusion models. Now we are
seeing some kind of a general form for
any cases that when we can when we
define default this the distribution
into this way. uh with this single
condition then the SNR basically
monotonically decreases over time with
for any alpha and the sigma functions
defined in this way then we can say that
this will be like one of the one
specific case of the defining the
process of diffusion models.
So that's kind of the one key thing
right. So this sounds like you can now
make your own uh the version of the
dependent models uh that basically
satisfy this and then the question might
is that then how can you also see uh the
possible kind of options for the fourth
SD right uh so if we can derive the
fourth SD from this formulation then
basically we can also find some kind of
the some family of the fourth SD that is
basically aligned with the definition of
the variation diffusion models right the
thing is Now we are first seeing some
kind of the opposite. First uh given the
fourth SD how we can derive the alpha
and the sigma functions. given the uh
dip term and also the difficulty
equivalence term how we can define the
rpine the sigma function and what we are
going to do see in the the next slide uh
the later slides basically given these
two functions how we can define these
things right then now what you can see
is that uh we can uh see some kind of
some class of the some sd formulation uh
that is basically uh sending all the
data points into the standard decion
points
So the thing is that while we basically
uh had the the sigma functions uh coming
from the different sources like this is
coming from the SMLD this is coming from
the the definition of the uh the
variation diffusion models. What we can
see is that actually these two are the
same right basically what we can see is
that obviously the alpha t here should
be d1 in this case and from the
derivation we can see that actually the
sigma function that defined that we
define in the smld is basically aligned
with the sigma function that we are
talking about uh in the deviation
diffusion models. So that's kind of some
sort of the the amount of the noise the
the noise that we are injecting over the
time.
So it's kind of like straightforward in
the SMLD case. So we could see that from
the B transition distribution we derived
these two things and from the previously
the the kind of the formulations uh from
this we can also define the the default
the jump distribution and these two
distributions were basically aligned
with the definitions for the SND. So
this is kind of the clear uh it might be
slightly more complicated for the DDPM
case.
So in the DPM case we have seen that the
transient the distribution is defined
like this and the full distribution is
like this right both of them are the
gausian distribution. So what we are
going to briefly see is that uh given
the this definition we also derive the
fourth SD right uh and from the fourth
SD now we can also derive this right and
the things that we are deriving from the
fourth SD should be aligned with like
this definition right uh so we're going
to briefly check this out uh so the
thing is that uh if you plug in all the
things into the our deformationation
so from default the turn distribution we
could see the f_t and the gt functions
are defined like this right but if you
just put those things into the hour
formulation then the alpha t function
becomes this which is kind of like
different than what we have seen in the
previous slide right uh so alpha t the
meaning of the alpha t function if we go
back to the division model was the some
kind of the coefficients for the x0 here
right
the x0 here and which should be uh the
same
with the zoom.
Yeah, should be same with the this time.
Uh which means that the alpha t function
should be basically should look like the
product of the one minus beta t
something. But now what we are seeing
based on the our formulation is that it
becomes like something very different
right some kind of exponential term. Uh
but actually it turns out that actually
this uh the alpha t function is defined
this way is kind of the good
approximation of like this exponential
determ. So I'm not going to go into the
any details here but actually if you go
down to some kind of the approximation
the formulations here you can see that
uh the the for the jump distribution
that we have seen in the previous
lecture is kind of the uh aligned in
terms of that it's kind of good
approximation actually of like this
formulation
actually it turns out that the alpha t
function which is the coefficients for
the x in the for actually should be this
exponential form uh precisely in the
continuous domain uh not some kind of
the product. So that's kind of thing but
actually this product is al kind of some
kind of good approximation of the the uh
the the the exponential function.
The other thing also might be is about
some kind of the sigma the function
right. The sigma function should be
basically like having this form. Uh here
basically the one fact that we know is
that the the squared the sigma function
uh should be the same uh with like this
term. Can you see why this is coming
from the our definition or the uh not
definition the the derivation of the uh
default the jump distribution of the
ddp. Can you see why this should be the
same?
No idea.
Because this is basically what we have
seen uh will the distribution of the DDP
right and this is corresponding to the
alpha t function and this is
corresponding to the uh sigma squared
right.
So from this relationship between these
two terms we can see that actually this
should be the same with the 1 minus the
alpha t squar right
make sense uh this is what we have seen
in the previous and from this what you
can see is that this should be the same
with the 1 minus the r t so this is like
the only thing that we need to check on
so I'm also going to uh skip some kind
details here but you can also see later
some details here in terms of like how
we are basically uh deriving this one.
So I mean with this kind of like all
kind of the details uh I'm going to skip
some details uh but what you can see is
that in the BPSD case in the DDPM case
the alpaka t function and the sigma t
functions are basically defined in this
way. So which kind of like looks
slightly different with the some default
the jump distribution that we have seen
the previous the DDPMD lecture but
actually you can see that these are
quite good approximation
basically what we can we can derive in
this kind of the the case. So this is
the case that now we are starting from
the definition of the for detention the
the distribution and deriving the fold
SD and based on that we are now deriving
the alpha function and the sigma
function in a way that we can derive the
for the jump distribution right uh which
is kind of the line with the for the
jump distribution that we have seen uh
in the previous lecture
but here the thing is that uh this
definition of the alpha and the sigma
function should satisfy the basically
the out condition which is the that the
the signal to noise ratio the SNR should
basically decreasing over time. The
question is that uh it is really true in
this case. Can you see that whether this
SNR is decreasing over time for this
stepping of the alpha and the sigma
function
maybe yeah let's take some time uh
actually we define the beta t as some
kind of the nonde function if you uh
recall you already memory about the what
we have seen in terms in the ddpmd
lecture uh you can see that actually the
beta t we defined t as some kind of
nonding function over times. So this
might be actually something that you are
implementing in the the first assignment
I guess. Uh but basically given that the
beta t is defined as kind of the
non-dequisite function and also greater
zero or greater than the zero over time
uh can you see that the sn comes kind of
non-dequing function
make sense?
So basically this term is nondereasing
and also like all the positive which
means that the integral of like this
function would be also increasing
function right
make sense
this whole part should be increasing
function which means that when you take
the exponential min of like this
increasing function this should be some
decreasing function right
make sense
and since now sigma is basically 1 minus
d alpha t then this should be increasing
function right
so yeah decreasing function over the
increasing function becomes another
decreasing function right make sense so
>> sorry
>> I think we don't need
>> yeah yeah it should be this one it
should be all all basically the the
positive some kind of
make sense. So yeah, while we basically
define the DDPM without any knowledge
about basically uh any kind of things
about the variational diffusion models
and also the the concept of the signal
to noise ratio naturally our definition
of the DDPM is bally satisfying this
condition the signal is equation over
time. So we can see that DDPM becomes
like one of the some specialty case of
the varian diffusion models.
Uh so yeah that's the thing. So what we
have seen in the previous slide is that
given the fold SD we could derive the
fold distribution like this. Actually we
want to do the opposite right given any
kind of the our definition of the fold
distribution uh what would be
corresponding the food process DSD.
So this is the the main quiz.
So I if there's no typo here then
everyone should get this
answer right? Did everyone get this
empty?
If you didn't get this answer, uh check
this out later and see how we can also
derive this.
Um yeah, so that's kind of thing. So
kind of the summary here is that uh you
know while we basically have seen lots
of some kind of formulations uh what I
wanted to uh deliver for today is that
uh how we can basically connect the
board the trenchion distribution and
also the boot the the jumping the
distribution and how these also
connected to the SD formulation how we
can go back and forth between these two.
So basically all the fault the
deficiency process can be described into
the SD deformationation in the contest
time domain and for the specifically for
the SDS SMLD and the DDP case uh based
on the fold tension distribution we
could see how we can also derive the the
fold SD right
then also uh the thing is that
uh the fold could be basically derived
from the our definition of the fold
distribution and the other way around.
So this kind of the conversion can be
done uh in the both ways and uh from
this definition of the SD we also could
see uh started we started to see some
kind of some general diversion of the
division models for all the cases like
when you define the alpha and the sigma
functions in a way that the SNR is
decreasing over time. said that that
will be all the cases that we are
defining division models mapping all the
data points into the standard decian
distribution and for those kind of cases
now we can define the fold SDE uh which
also the most important part here is
that given the fold SD we can always
basically find uh the reverse DSD
deformation we can immediately basically
uh they derive the reverse SD
deformation from the SD uh the meaning
of like this is that uh given the SD
formulation now we can do the sampling
the process uh with some kind of the
discretized the time step. So actually
what you can see in the uh the kind of
the the other way to basically see the
DDPMD reverse the the sampling process
uh basically is to basically see that
it's kind of the discretization of like
this SD deformation.
So basically the meaning of like this is
that uh we can discretize this SD into
this way with some kind of the some
finite number of the time steps and the
meaning of like this formulation
basically becomes that uh it's exactly
the same like what we are doing in the
DDP case every time when you basically
predict the score uh so when you have
some kind of noise predictor we could
say that how we can compute the score
from the noise predictor right and then
every time we are basically computing xt
minus delta
in the discrete time step which is
basically computed in this way. So one
thing that would be quite interesting to
see is that how this formulation exactly
aligned uh with the reverse process of
the DDP pair. So that can be some kind
of some dirty math but you can try
yourself how this process this
computation exactly aligned with some
kind of the reverse process of DDPM uh
that we have seen uh in the previous the
the lecture.
So these are like all the connect in
this way. So even when you basically see
the diffusion models in the with the SD
formulation uh with some kind of the
time domain discretization uh basically
the the solving the SD can be basically
approximated by the performing this
iteratively with some kind of the
Gaussian noise here and this will
basically align with some kind of the uh
the reverse process of the DDP with the
with the hourly definition of the f
function and the g function.
So this is likely the different angle of
like seeing the diffusion models uh from
the perspective of the context time
domain make sense. So I strongly
recommend uh trying this yourself
basically reimplementing uh DDPM in this
way. So with the hourly basically
derivation of the f and the g function
of the ddpm uh we can really just try to
compute uh the reverse process in this
way. Then we realized actually this
becomes exactly the same uh with reverse
process of the DD pair
makes this kind of interesting point
actually. So this was kind of the one
thing the more important thing uh that
we're going to start to discuss in the
next time uh is that uh without any kind
of like the proof here uh the thing is
that for any kind of some SD the the
formulation which is making this kind of
trajectory for the ST here the question
is that can we find any kind of the OD
formulation the ordinary differential
equation without the the brown and the
motion without the we know the process
in terms of that after the mapping from
this point to the other points here the
marginal distribution of like those
points uh become the same right so
basically all the like SD formulation is
all about the mapping right so given the
samples uh from the given the data
distribution what we want to do in from
the process is that all the samples are
basically mapped to one of the points of
the standard the gausian distribution
and the reverse process basically also
the mapping the other way around right
uh through this kind of the SD
deformationation and adding some kind of
the stockaticity
and the question is that would there be
some kind of the uh OD formulation
without the stoatisticity uh which is
basically having some kind of the same
mapping so not exactly mapping this to
the same point but basically kind of
like uh mapping the whole distribution
here into the same distribution here
that's what we want to do right uh
basically the purpose of having the SD
formulation is basically to map the data
distribution into the our latent
distribution and the other way around
right so given the SD would it be
possible to find some kind of the any uh
some OD formulation without like zero
the brown and the terms in terms of like
having some kind of the same mapping of
the like data distribution to the uh the
latent distributions
the answer is that surprisingly uh the
corresponding the OD E formulation uh is
basically defined in this way uh without
any proof here. So the you can see that
actually the formulation is even uh is
quite similar right especially for the
reverse process when the SD is like
defined in this way with the drift term
the F here and the diffusion
coefficients the G term here uh you can
see that this OD formulation just having
the one over two here uh without the the
winner the the process term here uh
becomes the corresponding the OD
formulation uh which is basically the
case that Now we are basically having
those kind of some uh JG some kind of
trajectory but having the much smoother
uh the trajectory without kind of the
any kind of random noise but alo it's
basically not mapping the point to the
same point but the mapping the entire
distribution to the same the latent
distribution
then what we kind of the interesting
point of the having the OD formation
so in the previous slide uh given the SD
formulation uh we could see basically
how we can solve this kind of SD with
some kind of the time domain
discretization right uh basically having
some kind of XT over the time
uh we can do the same thing for the OD
formulation
it's exactly the same type of the the
oil the discretization that we are so uh
predicting the score every time and also
updating the XT through this the same
same formulation but without the the
Gaussian noise injected here. Right?
So this also can be done in the same way
in the OD formulation. The thing is that
uh for the OD formulation
uh this is basically subject that has
been uh studied like more than I guess
like 100 years right so there are lots
of some kind of the numerical methods uh
that we can solve the audio formulation
in a much faster way uh without having
lots of the the time steps. So the good
thing of like having the uh the
corresponding the OD formulation is that
once we have the reverse SD and
converting this into the corresponding
the property flow the OD the PF OD here
now we can use some kind of the OD
solver uh to perform the reverse
process. So that's kind of the key idea
in terms of how we can basically achieve
some kind of the uh much faster speed.
So this is the first slide I've shown
the last lecture. No with DDI we are
seeing this kind of trend. What you want
to do is like having this right even
with some kind of very few step we
already get some kind of very really
good results right. Uh so we are
achieving this kind of speed up uh by
basically converting the SD and finding
the OD corresponding to each of the
reverse SD and using some kind of the
fast solver for the OD.
And this can be done for the OD because
for the SD formulation because of the
the stockaticity uh basically we need
some kind of the loss of the the time
steps to get some kind of the accurate
the approximation of like this
formulation uh because of like this term
but when when we do not have like this
term uh there are lots of some kind of
the techniques that we can solve the
formulation much faster. So that's the
basic idea in terms of like how we can
make some kind of the faster solver uh
for the pre-trained models.
makes sense.
So in the summary
uh so each of the diffusion process the
SE has some kind of the corresponding
the OD which basically matches the uh
the same the marginal distribution.
So what this means that uh the reverse
process now can be done basically by
solving not the SD but the corresponding
DOD using some kind of any of the
defers.
Uh so this is really important idea. Uh
again this is also the case that uh we
are achieving all those kind of the
things uh without like retraining
diffusion models for any kind of the
pre-trained diffusion models. Now we are
going to see the same the generation the
process as solving the SD actually even
not solving the SD actually solving the
OD uh with the same pre models just like
changing the perspective of the the
generation the process and basically
introducing by uh by introducing some
kind of the faster the OD disver uh we
going to achieve some kind of
acceleration uh in the generation the
process
so that's the basic idea and we're going
to get into deeper into that in terms of
how we can find some kind of the fastest
the OD servers uh specifically for this
type of the DOD formulation.
So before we wrap up the 2D this lecture
uh we have seen like the fourth SD
formulations for the SMLD and the DVPM
right and also for the generally the
case of the Ford SD we also could see
how we can derive the reverse SD for all
the cases which means that now we can
really derive the reverse SD uh for each
of these two cases.
Try to derive the reverse SD yourself
and especially for the DDPN case. uh
once you derive the reverse SD
formulation uh with the time domain
discretization that I have shown in the
previous slide uh you can reimplement uh
the reverse process of the DDPM based on
the reverse SD. So I also strongly
recommend try this yourself. Uh this is
not the part of the assignment. Uh the
but reason we are providing some kind of
the base code for the diffusion model is
that you know you know you can play
those kind of things yourself. So what
you are going to see over the second and
the third assignment is that from the
same base code for the same data set
every time when you change some kind of
the generation the process how you can
basically get some kind of the almost
the same the outputs but with some much
figure the step of the computation that
would be quite interesting point in
terms of understanding uh the diffusion
process uh like all the things that we
discuss here any questions me.
Okay.