I think at the beginning of the course
we announced that we would have um a few
guest lecturers, people who previously
taught the course to come and give uh
sort of a single guest lecture about a
topic that they're very familiar with.
And I'm very happy to announce we have
the first one of those lectures today.
So uh I'll introduce Dr. Rohan Gao. He
is an assistant professor in the
department of computer science at the
University of Maryland. uh College Park
and he leads the multiensory machine
intelligence lab there. He was
previously an instructor for CS23 uh 1N
from 2022 to 2023 and he this is while
he completed his posttock with uh uh Fei
Jajin Wu and Sylvio Saves. So without
further ado, I'll leave it to Rohan to
give the presentation today.
>> Okay. Thanks. Uh hello uh hello
everyone. So it's really uh exciting to
be back to the class of two thes 231N
and I'm Rohan uh just like Zen
introduced. So as you can tell I'm very
interested in multi model stuff. So a
lot only vision but also how we can make
use of other sensory modalities like
audio tactile or other modalities just
like with humans to uh perceive
understand and interact with this
multiensory world. But of course uh
vision is the most important modalities
right that's why we have this course uh
deep learning for computer vision and
I'm sure up to this point that you guys
are very familiar with image
classification right given a 2D image
like this how to you know uh give a
class uh label to see whether it's a dog
it's a cat or it's a truck a plane
that's a 2D based image classification
and from the last lecture I'm sure you
have also learned some other tasks that
you can do on images not only you can
just assign a single label to see it's a
cat a lot. And also you can do semantic
segmentation to segment you know the
picture into different portions
components and also have some semantic
meaning like where is grass, where is
cat, where is tree and also you can also
put a bounding box on top of the objects
uh you detect in the image uh to see
where the dog is, where the cat is and
also do instance segmentation that you
not only you want to know the categories
but also you know uh for each category
if there are two dogs I want to have a
se segmentation pass for each category
that's instant segmentation. There are a
lot of like tasks classification
recognition task you can do uh based on
2D images but that's not u the only
thing that we can use for computer
vision system to do right and also our
world is not just static like this so if
we look at this image hopefully at up to
this point you have uh you know learned
a lot of tools that you can uh train
some models to know detect this classify
this is a kneeling room right you have
also have uh tools you have learned that
to put a bounding box to see that this
is a dog and this is a baby and also
even you can even have a you know
segmentation mask to segment them out to
see where uh those objects you detect
are uh in the image. So today we're
going to f focus on video understanding.
So more formally what is video?
Basically video is just like this 2D
image plus time. There's an extra time
dimension. So we now we are uh tackling
things not only in this 3D image but
also but now in 4D we have this uh uh uh
three * t t is temporal dimension and h
and w are the spatial dimension. Now we
are uh considering this kind of image
and videos as like a volume of images of
of video frames. So an example task is
video classification just like image
classification right. So we are given a
video like this uh some some person is
like running right we want to take this
videos as input and also we want to
train some model right a deep learning
model we want to classify whether this
person is doing swimming or running or
jumping or what actions that he's doing
right just based on this uh temporal
streams of video frames so we also we
have from the previous lectures I'm sure
you have already learned some you know
loss functions like cross entropy loss
and you and train a image classifier.
Similarly, you can do you can use the
similar tools, you know, just train a
video classifier. You just get some
features and use the same loss functions
and train a video classifier. So now the
problem on video understanding is that
how can we uh get features of videos
that you can apply the loss functions
you have learned from the previous
lectures. Right? So uh and also another
kind of difference between image
classification and the video
classification video understanding is
that now the things the task you want to
do might be a little bit different just
from the previous example in images for
example for image classification usually
you care more about the scenes the
objects right you want to just uh uh
doing a classification what is the
object category for videos usually just
like this example I'm showing here
usually you want to classify actions
it's often actions like where the person
what activities the person or some some
animals are doing in the in the videos
that's what we care about usually in
video understanding. So nature of things
to recognize can be a little bit
different.
And another problem that uh we want to
be careful about for video understanding
is that videos are usually very big.
Right? Well you talk when we talk about
images it's just like three times H* W.
It's a single you know matrix of some
you know RGB RGB numbers. But now we
consider videos it's a sequence of
frames. It can be like 30 frames per
second. So in movies it can be sometimes
we can have even higher like uh
resolution uh and also temporal uh
resolution uh video frames and so if you
consider uh space to store videos you
for example if we consider standard
definition videos it can take about like
1.5
uh gigabyte per minute if we store this
video. we consider even high resolution
like 19 uh 1,920
times uh 10880
and now it takes like 10 gigabyte per
minute. So it takes a gigantic space in
order to store this kind of video data
and also there's no way for us to just
fit this kind of data directly to GPUs
right if we we just have the input then
we can have have a lot of storage to
store them to source this kind of data
and also there are other things you can
have to store like the weights the
activations in your convolution neural
networks so then uh your model uh will
be uh very huge
and uh the solution what solutions we
can have to you know to make videos
smaller to make them you know
processable. So one simple solution is
that we just make videos smaller right u
so although the high definition videos
and also the original videos are long
when we can shrink things both
temporarily and uh spatially right we
can just u for example for 3.2 two
second videos like this. We can for
example we can maybe for each for each
second we don't maybe we don't need all
the frames. Let's just take five frame
because there are a lot of redundancies
uh in the video frames, right? If we
take five five frames per second uh and
also we just have uh smaller spatial
resolution like 112 * 112 and now we can
make the videos uh slightly smaller. For
example, it's 5 588
uh KB uh for this uh simple video. But
definitely we can also do uh larger
resolution. We have the compute right
just like images and also how to uh
train a model on this long videos we
cannot usually like in the previous
slide I showed that we are training this
video classifier on 3.2 in two second,
right? But videos can be very long, can
be minutes, can be hours, right? So, one
one way that people do is that we train
on clips just like uh we train on kind
of chunks of this video frames uh using
a video classifier. And what we do is
that we train models to classify short
clips with some low of uh FPS, frame per
second. And we just use a sliding
window. We, you know, sample a lot of
different clips and use them as training
data and we train a classifier. And then
during testing, during inference time,
we just run the model on different
clips. We sample a few clips, right? We
made 10 clips and then we average the
prediction results. And that is our
prediction for this long video.
And uh then what is the same post like
video classification model uh we can
use. So I have mentioned basically
video is just like a sequence of images
right a sequence of video uh image
frames. So one simple thing is that we
just treat them as images right that's
the simplest kind of uh tool uh we
already have right we just run single
frame convolution neuronet networks
because we already have all the tools
right we have learned that we can train
an image classifier if we just take our
image classifier to just run on top of
those kind of video frames to treat them
as images we can indeed get uh decent
predictions right especially like a
video like this you can see that there
are not many changes across videos right
the person is running maybe there are
some different movements uh on body. But
generally it looks pretty similar,
right? Maybe we just you run a image
action classifier and uh on the every
frame maybe all of the frames will tell
you it's running and you if you average
the prediction results from each image
each video frame then you'll predict uh
running for this uh particular video. So
actually also it's a ve it's usually a
very very strong baseline right for this
simple image classifier u for especially
for video like this because there are
not too many changes across uh videos.
So if you are trying to design some uh
video classifier you should always run
this first uh because that's kind of
simple things to try and maybe you can
already get pretty decent results. So
the question is uh whether we just run
on single frame or we run on chunk of
frames. So for this simple uh single
frame state and basically we just uh you
have a video of like 30 frame maybe you
just maybe sample a few frames and just
use a image classifier to run on those
like sampled 10 frames and just treat
them as images and you just directly
average the results. That's basically uh
the per frames they in. So I think you
ask a very important question is how to
sample the frame that's a very key
question because we're given a giant I'm
I'm I'm talking about we want to sample
some frames and want to run a CN on the
frame. So how to get those frames? So
that is actually also an active area of
research. Uh one simple way is that you
do random random sampling. If you have a
one hour video, I don't know where where
the interesting part where the important
parts are, right? We just sample maybe
every one minute I sample one frame and
then I run image classifier average
results. But obviously maybe this is
it's a gives some good results but maybe
this is not the smartest way to do the
sampling. There are other methods trying
to propose smarter sampling strategy.
Maybe you can sample one frame. you can
then use that decision to decide where
where else to sample. I actually also
have some examples later uh in later
lecture slides.
Okay. So this is uh a very very simple
kind of uh video classifier just like we
just adopt image classifier single frame
CN and uh similarly just uh maybe we
take one step further instead of
directly just uh run single frame CN and
average the prediction results maybe we
can doing some fusion right across the
you know features uh on the uh using the
uh single frame CN so this is often
called late fusion Basically the idea is
that we still take some 2D ends and we
have some input uh maybe t frames and
for for each frame we uh use a 2D and
then we extract some feature vector u
and then we get u maybe a feature
feature map of b * h prime time w prime
and then we get because we have t frames
right then basically we have t feature
feature uh feature maps and then the
simple thing that we just uh uh flatten
all the feature maps to vectors and then
concatenate them. Then we have a giant
like uh feature vector that basically
contains all the information all the
features across all the frames right and
then what we can do we can use tools
that we have learned like fully
connecting networks right we train a MLP
that maps this uh vector to some ner
dimension and then we train a classifier
on top of it made to map it to class
score C right so this is uh uh called
late fusion because basically you can
see that we extract the feature maps and
we process them very independently And
then at the very late stage we
concatenate the feature vectors and run
some fully connecters to doing the
classification. So uh this is uh uh uh
this is useful but uh one drawback that
you can you can already probably tell
from this uh example from my description
is that this fully connect right it's
it's going to introduce a lot of
parameters because if you if we
concatenate a lot of we flatten them and
across time and this feature vectors
depending on how long how large t is
then you can have a giant feature vector
and you use this giant feature vector
you want to map them into some lower
dimension and you have a very large
fully contracting
layer and that will introduce a lot of
parameters. So it's not very efficient.
So another way to do this is that
instead of concatenating them right we
we we don't do concatenation we don't
use uh just use the giant feature vector
and then doing fully then have a fully
concatenator to map them to scores. We
can actually just do a simple pooling
right doing pooling we don't you don't
increase the the you know the length of
feature vector basically if you have
feature dimension some feature dimension
for a single frame and you pull across
time right for this t frames you just
doing a pooling to do a tempo
aggregation and then based on this uh
clip feature d and then you uh instead
of now instead of d time t you just you
still have a feature vector of time d if
you do pulling right and then you have a
linear layer to map d to some uh uh
dimens C that match the cast score and
then you train the uh cross entropy loss
on top of it and that's also late fusion
but now we are using pooling and the and
the the the good side here is that now
you have you don't have to have a very
large fully connect but the pooling can
also you know uh get rid of information
that may be important so that's kind of
the downside of this operation
so the the reason I'm calling late
fusion right The important part is late,
right? Uh and when it's late, maybe
there's some information that has
already been lost when you have using
this 2D convolution networks to process
images, right? For example, for example,
as shown in this red circles here. So,
what uh is very important to recognize
this video is actually the the motion of
this uh this man's feet, right? It's
moving up and down, up and down, and you
can maybe tell that he's running, right?
So if you if we just use a single 2D CN
to process them indiv independently as a
uh 2D image and extract some feature map
and maybe up to you know very late stage
of the feature maps you it doesn't
actually already contain uh it doesn't
contain the information of this move
movement of this of the feet of this man
anymore right at this very late stage.
So, so some information this fit up and
down is like showing these red circles
which should be useful cues right but
now it's not there in the feature maps
the intuition is that if you you think
of if you if you extract features from
the early layers right it's very close
to the original video frames so it's so
it will it will be there's larger chance
it will contain this no- level kind of
information there's no movement like
from the video frames right and also you
can if you concaten them or pull them It
will come across time. It will analyze
the motion across time. But because we
are processing a lot of convolution
pooling, convolution pooling up to a
relate stage you at a very late stage it
contains more high level information
like demand information instead of this
low-level motion information. So that's
why it's most likely it's lost there. So
uh that's the downside of late fusion.
So instead of doing late fusion then we
actually we can do early fusion. Right?
So to do early fusion if we want to make
use of the feature vectors more closer
to the actual video frames we can just
you know take this uh input uh and then
we we get we we directly you know
reshape them to 3t * h * w right we just
directly aggregate the information
temporally uh from the very beginning
and then we use some uh 2D convolution
the first 2D convolution just directly
map them uh to from from channel
dimensions 3T to D basically we use the
2D convol solution to process this
temporal information uh in the first
layer to map uh the the channel
dimension from 3D to D to process you
know the the video frames of all the
information from the frames uh in the in
the very beginning of the convolution
neural networks and the rest of network
is then in standard 2DC end and uh uh
the only difference that now we destroy
and collapse all the temporary
information into a single uh single
using a single layer and then the rest
is just like image classification and
then you're doing uh this classification
using standard cross entropy loss for
each frame we get a features like D
right and each frame each each each each
each single frame will give you a
feature D so you have T this feature
vectors D so for pooling we are pulling
over the features basically we can do
mean pooling to average the features or
we max pooling we max over the features
then after that we still get a feature
that's D so it's pulling over the
features not the frames
okay so that's early fusion Um so then
the downside of the early field is that
u uh although we explicitly trying to
handle you know the motion from the
early layer but then the but then we the
we are we are trying we
we are too ambitious we're trying to you
know capture everything in a single
layer right we just concatenate all the
frames and then collapse all the temp
information a single convolution network
maybe it's not uh going to achieve what
we wanted to achieve right so then
another solution is that we uh instead
Instead of doing late fusion or early
fusion, maybe we should do something in
between, right? That's kind of like slow
fusion. That's exactly what uh this 3D
convolution 3D convolution network is
doing. So in the intuition is that we
want to use this 3D version of
convolution and and pooling. We want to
slowly fuse information over the course
of the network. Instead of doing it at a
very late stage or at a very early
stage, we gradually shrink over, you
know, temporal dimension and spatial
dimension to get this 3D feature maps.
So that's the idea of uh 3D convolution
neuronet network. We just use 3D
convolution and a 3D pooling operation.
So what is 3D convolution? 3D pooling.
So you have learned the 2D convolution
right for 2D convolution there uh
basically if you you take an image like
this 32* 32 * 32 * 3 uh uh image and if
you if you use 2D convolution basically
uh you have learned that you can for
each kernel you have this uh uh filter
right you can you can have like this uh
convolution kernel that is maybe 5* 5* 3
that that runs like in a sliding window
approach just you know slides across
across space and uh goes all the way ac
for for each uh uh for each computation
you you know you map that uh uh to a
single value in that final activation
maps and then finally you obtain this
activation map uh of 28 * 28 * 1 in this
case you come over all spatial locations
right and map this uh channel dimension
the depth step go all the all go all the
way over the channel dimension and
uh map three map from three to to one in
this case. So that's 2D convolution. So
the difference uh is that for 3D
convolution now uh we just have one
extra dimension. So here uh you can
think that uh uh here the input is c * t
* h * w right the the extra thing is
this t dimension that is a temporal
dimension. So, but what I'm showing here
because we can only show things in 3D,
right? We cannot show things in in 4D.
So, there's actually one dimension that
is not shown here that is the C
dimension. The channel dimension is not
shown here. So you can think that uh for
each grid point in this feature map
there are um many features there are uh
C features uh in that spatial in that
grid point and then for this uh 3D
convolution basically if we if we are
talking about like a 60 6 * 6 * 6
convolution because it have one extra
dimension now instead of slide over you
know the spatial dimension just just in
the H and W dimension over the images
now we are sliding over this you know
cube right we are sliding over uh this
uh cube of dimension t * h * w. So
includes both the spatial dimension and
the temporal dimension and also it goes
all the way uh along the channel
dimension. So then it will uh gradually
you can you know uh just like 2D con the
other part is just like the uh 2D
convolution it just to have this extra
dimension and then you get the 3D 6 * 6
* 6 3D convolution and maybe another
layer of five* 5 and finally after you
process doing this 3D convolution
operations and you flatten the feature
vectors and then you use a 4D connecters
to map them to the class scores. So that
is uh basically the idea of 3D
convolution.
So let's walk maybe through some toy
examples to you know to better
understand it to compare uh the early
late and uh uh the uh 3D convolution
neuronet networks right just to just to
give you a flavor how it works uh uh in
practice actually definitely it's the
better can be much larger and more
complicated but here I'm just trying to
show that uh a toy example to to walk
through you know the the size of the
feature maps and also the receptive
field to give you a sense about what's
the difference between early fusion late
fusion 3D convolution neural networks.
So for
uh uh late fusion right you can think
that for example in this case maybe
originally it's of uh the input is like
3 * 20 20 is a temporal dimension and
6464 is a spatial dimension and you use
a two you use a uh 2D convolution
basically we we we we just because we're
doing late fusion we we don't do
anything over the temporal dimension
initially right we just keep the 20 the
the temporal dimension we just build up
the receptive field spatially right now
we have the uh conute com 2D layer to
map the channel dimension from 3 to 12
but just keep the temporal dimension 20
and then gradually maybe we use some uh
pooling layers still we you know we
didn't do anything with the tempo
dimension so it's still 20 right but we
because of because of the pooling
operation we build up the receptive
field in the spatial uh dimension and
then gradually we maybe use another 2D
layer and we now the facial map is 24 *
20 * 16 * 16 and we also we gradually
increase the spatial receptive field But
we still keep the temporal dimension 20.
So we did we didn't do anything over the
temporal dimension. And finally just
using a single like a global average
pooling we pull across the feature maps
20 * 16 * 16. So we pull over both time
and and the spatial dimension. And now
we get from this 20 * 16 * 16 we get a 1
* 1 * 1 feature point. Right? So
basically we collapse everything in the
final single layer and we build up the
temporal receptive field in the single
layer. So that's late fusion. So then
for early fusion what's the difference?
So now instead of building slowly in
space or at once in time at end now we
are building slowly in space and all at
once in time at the very beginning.
Right? So so so the input is still that
3 * 20 * 64 * 64 but now we're just
using a single com 2D layer. Now we just
treat this 3 * 20 as a single you know
the the channel dimension. we just map
everything this three * 30 uh just treat
all of them as channel dimension and
then map them to 12. So basically we use
a single con convolution uh layer 2D 2D
convolution air to map uh to collapse
all the temporal information from the
very beginning. So we build the uh
temporal receptive field in the first
layer. So now the temporal receptive
field becomes uh uh from 1 to 20 and
then the spatial receptive field
gradually builds up and we use pooling
and count 2D to build up you know the
spatial dimension just as late fusion
and finally we use a global average
pooling now with glob average pooling is
only just trying to you know uh doing
the averaging doing the pooling across
space. So we build a slowly space but
all at once uh at the very beginning. So
that's early fusion. So then what is uh
3D convolutional networks? So for 3D
convolutionary basically we build slowly
both in space and time. So that's why we
call it uh slow fusion. So the input can
still be like the same 3 * 20 * 64 * 64
but now we are using 3D convolutions. So
we uh uh in the first layer uh we we
just uh uh uh to map things from uh
three time to to 12. We also just keep
the temporal dimension in this case. And
then we build up a little bit temporal
receptive field and spatial receptive
field. And then we use a pooling layer.
And then uh like four times four times
four pooling layer. And then we you know
we pull a little bit of this temporal
feature and also spatial features. And
then we further build up both this
spatial and temporal receptive field.
And we have another con 3D layer and and
then to further build up the spatial and
temporal receptive field. And finally
we're using a global average pooling but
now we're pulling over this four * 16 *
16 feature map and then to further
increase the uh temporal and spatial
receptive field. So we are building up
gradually in both space and time. So
that's kind of the difference between uh
early fusion late fusion and 3D
convolution neural networks. So you can
see that uh for the early fusion and 3D
convolution neural networks. So both of
them builds receptive field over time,
right? But what's the actual difference?
So let's look at it uh more more closely
here. So if we think of it as like a a
feature vector uh for each spatial grid
point. So the uh the count filter
uh if it's a 2D convolution, right? for
this grid point it it will consider
all the temporal uh along the temporal
dimensions t t is equal to 16 right so
so it is local in space but extends
fully in time right that's like the the
the filter in 2D convolution uh neuronet
network but but what what is the problem
think about it so if you if we directly
just go all the way through time
dimension in this 2D dev convolution
what problem uh it's going to happen so
the shortcoming of that is that there
will be no temporal shift in variance
because uh the 2D the future now extends
fully in time right so if we want to ner
some like global transition in color
have different time for example if we
want to uh uh because it's it's a temp
it's a video right it's a some when we
recognize temporal information if there
if there are some changes from like blue
to orange at different time step. Maybe
there's some change uh that is happening
at time step four. There's another same
change that is happening at time step
15. But it's the same change like from
blue to to to to orange. Right? If you
if we go all the way through through uh
through time, the future extends fully
in time. Then if we want to learn the
global transition at different time,
then we have to have a whole separate
future in order to learn this, right? So
we have to you know learn a different uh
this kernel in order to learn this
different transitions across uh at
different time stamp. So there's no
temporal shift in variance. So uh so how
to recognize uh this kind of blue to
orange transition just anywhere in space
and and time right just like when we are
doing image classification we want to
you know have some spatial invariance.
We want to okay be able to recognize the
cat the image contains a cat no matter
where the cat is on the right corner
left corner right we want to to share
the you know the the the kernels to be
able to you know to recognize things at
different at a different spatial
location here we want to be able to
learn this different types of motion
different time this temporal patterns at
different you know temporal time steps
so that's kind of similar idea so then
the that's exactly the benefit of 3D
convolution neuronet networks right Now
instead of extends fully in time right
in this that t dimension originally for
this uh early fusion t extends all the
way in the temporal dimension t is
equals to 16 but now t t is equal to
three and we can slide over the temporal
dimension right just like uh we learn
this uh spatial invariance using filter
on local regions now this count filter
only span a local window in time and
slide over in the time dimension. So the
then the the benefit is that now we can
have some temporal shift invariance
because each filter slides over time. So
we can reuse this filter to recognize
different motion patterns uh across uh
these dimensions. So the transition from
blue to orange can now be recognized at
every moment in time. Right? Uh and then
the benefit of of this is that we don't
have to have separate filters, right?
Then now we are more efficient, more
representation efficient. we don't need
to know separate futures anymore. So
that's basically the main difference
between 2D con early fusion and the 3D
convolutional network.
And also uh in the last lecture I think
uh you have already also uh seen some
examples of some tools that we can use
to you know visualize what we have
learned right in a in a 2D convolutional
networks. Similarly, we can also
visualize uh uh filters just uh for this
3D convolution networks as this kind of
video clips. You can see that uh uh
there the I'm not you can see it. Okay.
The learner filters from the 3D
convolution neural networks uh because
now the filter extends both in space and
time. So uh we can see that in in in in
uh as a video clip and you can see that
for this filters uh some of them are
just like those like um filters you have
simple im image classifier right you can
have this kind of color patterns and
also the different edges but you can
also see that there are some other
filters there's some temporal transition
right from from one color to another or
from some one edge pattern to another
So, so that's uh uh and some some
doesn't learn motion and some maybe
focus on just like the image p uh the
color patterns but some learns motion in
like different uh directions. So, we can
just visualize these kernels uh like
this to to interpret them. Basically,
the main there are two two difference.
One is like this slow fusion right
basically in terms of convolution
operation. Yeah, indeed. Basically 3D
convolution but 3D convolution
definitely and 2D convolution are
totally different, right? It's a you you
you have another dimension of
convolution. You have this temporal
dimension. So the main difference you
have this temporal dimension in the
convolution operation but uh practically
uh you if you use 3D convolution your
networks it kind of gradually builds
this receptive field uh over space and
time. Yeah.
So uh we have talked about this uh
tools 3D convolution networks or
architectures right but what data we can
uh use just like image network what data
we can use to do video to train a video
classifier. So one kind of example data
set uh challenge data set that uh people
have been tackling is this uh data set
called sports 1 million which was
introduced uh in uh 2014. So for this
data set you can see that what what kind
of task we can do we can do very very
fine grain uh sport cateory
classification right you can see that
the here the blue shows the ground
truths and uh the
uh below uh the it shows the top five
predictions and the green shows the
correct prediction and the red shows the
incorrect prediction. You can see that
uh uh the action categories is that it's
very very fine grain right there are 487
different types of sports like there can
be like marathon ultra marathon actually
don't know the the difference between
them but it's kind of very kind of fine
different types of sports categories in
this data set
and uh here are some results uh if we
you know train this different types of
classifiers we have talked about on this
uh sports 1 million data set so One very
shocking results you can probably see
here is that uh for this single frame
model that I ask you to try uh for if
you want to develop some video
classification model uh uh is that it
actually has a very good performance
right you can can see that the single
frame model if you just train trade at
the image classifier uh it actually
gives you like 77.7 uh classification
top five uh accuracy and for the early
fusion we talked about it actually has a
slightly worse performance and for late
fusion is slightly better and if we use
3D convolution new networks in this case
on this data set it gets like a 2% uh
two to 3% kind of boost
uh so the takeaway message here is that
uh definitely you should try the single
frame model it can usually actually
works pretty well and uh uh and the 3D
convolution by the 3D convolution new
networks uh I showed here is the 3D
convolution neural network used in 2014
right but over the past 10 years we have
seen a lot of advancements so the
members are also uh getting much much
better as I'm going to talk about in the
later slide yeah for both training and
testing it's just treating videos as
images and train image classifier that's
exactly what uh single frame is doing
basically if I understand question
correctly it's it's it's using image
classifier but it's training a lot of
frames on videos it's not a single frame
each video yeah
uh and also uh because this data set is
a huge data set because like I mentioned
Videos are very huge, right? When people
sharing data sets uh video data sets, we
cannot just share them uh just like as
like imageet we have people can can
download from some database because
videos are really huge like this data
set has like maybe 1 million videos,
right? It's not very uh doable to
download all of them to going to share
it. Actually, this video actually
originally when it was released is
shared as a list of URLs, YouTube URLs.
But one thing can you can expect from
this YouTube vial URLs that people you
know modify their videos and delete
their videos, right? And so so that that
original list maybe have one million
videos but now maybe the I I guess maybe
the list maybe half of the videos are
already gone or maybe not there. So this
data set is not very kind of stable
because of this reason.
Okay. So
um
another kind of uh like I mentioned 3D
convolutional networks have been like
improving yeah gradually right since
maybe 2014. So one early kind of popular
version of this 3D convolution network
is this model called 33N networks. So
basically uh it's actually very very
very simple. Basically it's uh uh it's
very similar to the VG architecture we
use for 2D image classification. uh but
it's now we just con we just convert
things uh to three dimension uh
convolution network right uh and uh for
example for the 3D CNN uh it you use
three * 3 * 3 and 2 * 2 * 2 pooling and
except maybe for the first layer has
some changes uh it's so over
architecture it's very similar to like
VG uh architecture it's now just we have
this extra dimension and uh for this so
it's so that's why it's called the VG of
3D ends and it's uh the model uh it was
trained on this sports one mini data set
that uh uh I just mentioned and because
it uh it was introduced like in 2014
right and that that time uh imagine that
you want to train such uh model it needs
a lot of compute right because this uh
uh not so many people have access to you
know a lot of GPUs at that time so
Actually this model was trained at
Facebook and they uh they and they
literally released this model this the
pre-trained weights they they train this
3D model on sport and release the
feature um pre-trained model as a
feature extractor. So many people
actually who cannot afford to you know
train a video model themselves actually
started to use this model as a feature
extractor. So you can just take a video
and extract features from from this uh
from this uh uh using this uh
pre-trained model say 3D model and then
maybe train some other classifier. So uh
people start to to to you know use it uh
that's why how it get got popular. So so
the question basically is about uh when
we're talking about media classification
about how many frames we should take as
input in terms to extract the features.
So basically for all this uh models we
are talking about we assume that we are
just passing a clip a predefined length
like 16 frames right and or 32 frames
you train a single model that always
takes 16 frames or 32 frames as input
and there are other techniques we're
going to talk about how we're going to
aggregate this kind of clip level kind
of prediction but for for now we're just
doing clip level kind of feature
extraction. So the the downside of this
uh 3D CAN is that uh it's very
computationally expensive right
basically we just directly in a bootstro
way we just make to make this VG kind of
style from 2D to 3D and uh you can see
that uh for Alex that uh for this for
this G-flop basically what what it means
is that it's it's it's the ga flops it's
trying to measure how many floatingoint
operations you need for a single forward
pass basically just trying to measure
you know whether the network is
efficient or So for Alex net it takes
0.7 g flops for VG16 it takes like 13.6
six g flop but for C3D right you
directly doing this kind of mapping from
2D 3D to 3D now it takes like 13 uh 39.5
g flops so it's 2.9 times VG so it's not
very efficient right so uh that's the
kind of the the downside of this kind of
network
uh and if we look at the performance on
sports 1 million uh uh this just 360 now
uh gets uh about like 4% uh gain in
terms of it top wide accuracy. uh but
uh so this is just like one example of
the 3D convolution network we can do
right but there are definitely can be
other things right we have talking about
a lot of tricks that we we we can do for
2D image classification right we can
have this residue connections like you
you have seen in in ResNet right but
definitely we can also do that just
improve say 3D to adding some residue
connections or other techniques we
talked about in 2D convolutions and
indeed there are also a lot of work on
trying to improve this different 3D
different types of 3D video convol uh
video uh architectures and also papers
on that but apart from that let's think
maybe a little bit more on whether we
should treat space and time in a
separate way right because that indeed
very very very different things right
spatial kind of information temporal
information so maybe we should actually
explicitly try to model things that is
uh exists there temporally that is
motion right so we humans actually can
incredible job uh processing motion. So
maybe uh take a guess what actions the
the humans are doing here in this uh
simple video.
You can yeah say it out if you want.
What's this
seating?
Yeah, just from this very a few points
you can actually do pretty good good
job, right? This is to recognize what
actions uh that this person is doing,
right? Or maybe two person, right?
Yeah. Now there are not any appearance
information, right? Just a few points,
right? Just motion. We can actually have
a very good understanding about some
activities that is going on in this
videos, right? So how to pro so that's
why how we process appearance and motion
might be very different. maybe we should
have separate kind of uh networks to
process them. Right? So indeed that and
that's kind of motivation uh for this
work that uh was introduced in 20 uh uh
14 and uh uh they are trying to propose
uh a two stream network to process
appearance information and and the
motion information separately. So
basically uh one way to measure
explicitly measure of motion is to use
this uh concept called optical flow. So
for optic flow basically the idea is
that uh we want to measure the the
motion the changes uh of the the motion
of the pixels uh in adjacent frames.
Basically the for the first frame for
every pixel how it's going to move in
the second frame. So it calculates kind
the velocity for points within the
frames and kind of provides an
estimation of where the points could be
in the in the next frame sequence. For
example, in this in this case like for
frame t and t plus one basically this
flow field right here are two two
dimensions and tells uh whether where
each pixel will move in the next frame.
So fxy is equals to dxdy and then the uh
i t + 1 x + uh dx that's where uh you
know the the pixel in the last frame is
equal to you know ix ity uh in the
current frame. So it's trying to measure
uh a way to measure explicitly measure
motion of the pixels. Right? So there
are many papers actually on doing
research and also how to actually
compute object flow uh given a pair of
frames. There there are ways to make
different types of assumptions like some
some work assume the object flow uh just
assumes uh brightly stays constant as
things move and then trying to propose
some techniques to compute this object
flow. But once you get it, it basically
captures the motion information for two
adjacent frames. And also you can
because there are two dimensions, right?
Because it's trying to uh capture how
pixels move horizontally and vertically.
So you can actually also visualize it
separately. You can visualize it the
horizontal motion horizontal flow dx and
also you can visualize the vertical flow
dy. You can see that there capture some
you know horizontal motion and the
vertical motion. Uh so we capture this
kind of low-level motion cues. So once
you have a way to capture this kind of
motion cues as optical flow uh then
people trying to you know propose a
two-stream networks to se uh to train a
motion classifier and appearance
classifier. So this is a famous
twostream network for action
recognition. So basically it has a one
single frame uh model that that's doing
appearance classification to tell what
action it is and then you have a
separate uh stream that's the temporal
stream come that takes this uh uh
multi-frame optic flow for two for every
two adjacent frames it computes the
optical flow map and also uh it
separately traits the horizontal uh
motion optical flow and the vertical
vertical flow and stack them together
and then they process them using a
temporal stream convolution neuronet
network and doing make a prediction and
then they aggregate the prediction
results uh for both the motion stream
and the appearance stream to get a final
prediction. So that's the idea of this
two-stream network and it actually works
pretty pretty good. Uh it's it's on
another data set called UCF 101. It's
there are 121 100 101 action categories
in this data set. So you can see that uh
one surprising thing you can see that is
that using only motion actually works
very well surprisingly well right uh you
can you see the performance of 3D cycle
network and the spatial only that's only
the appearance uh stream and the
temporal only that's a motion stream you
can see that motion stream actually is
uh works uh much better compared to this
the spatial only stream right the the
appearance string so my hypothesis is
that uh uh it's less easier to overfit
because you Uh for the motion uh there
are a lot of like background information
which may be not important for for the
background uh for for the action
classification but uh but but for the
motion stream it actually contains the
queue the very the the key information
right the movements which are less
easier to overfeit actually you can get
better results on this data set. So so
far uh uh we have been talking about uh
short-term structures uh in in videos.
So um and also we have uh earlier I
think uh the uh folks asking about uh
you know how where how many fra how many
frame we should use actually to doing
the classification right so definitely
it's very important uh to modeling the
long-term uh temporal uh structure uh to
to recognize more more distant in in
time right so uh we already know
actually we already have the tools we
have to handle sequences uh to you know
to use rec uh recurrent networks right
to process a sequence of words to doing
some you know uh uh it's like caption
tasks and some some some prediction
tasks right so we can also use similar
like tools right just recurrent new
networks uh we just have a convolutional
networks right we can uh not no matter
whether it's a single frame convolution
networks to get a 2D feature vector or
uh use a 3D convolution network to get a
feature vector from a clip but if you
have a much longer video. We can get a
feature vector and then we just use like
uh the RNs or LSTMs we have talked about
to model the long-term temporal
structure, right? We just process uh the
local features using this recurrent
networks uh and uh uh make maybe make a
final prediction uh at the last time
step, right? We want to do a single
video level classification. Uh we just
doing a many to one mapping, right? one
uh output at the end of the video or we
can also do like uh one to one mapping
uh like we talked about right uh so for
each uh for each frame we can make a
prediction maybe there are some
predictions we can want to make for each
video frame and we can also get this
output for uh from like LSTM or recurren
new network
and uh uh
actually this kind of idea is is already
has already been explored in 20 2011 11
actually that's kind of way ahead of it
time right because Alex that was
introduced in uh 2012 right so but it's
more popularized by this 2015 paper so
uh you can also if you want to train
this kind of recurring architectures for
for modeling long-term temporal
structure uh you can often only back
propagate through this RN layer right
you can fuse the CNS you can pretend
them on maybe on some clips on some
image classification and you just uh
otherwise you have a huge network
recurrent part is a convolution part
then it's it's very hard to kind of
train them uh in end to end so you can
just use this in C3D as like feature
extractor and train this recurrent new
networks so and we have already seen two
approaches right uh to model the
temporal structure right how about we
can combine uh this kind of two two
approaches right this convolution
networks and this recurrent new network
both of them has some uh advantages we
can maybe just combine them in a single
kind of architecture to process the kind
of video data, right? So indeed we can
take some inspiration from this
multi-layer recurrent new networks we
have talked about right so each time
stamp can takes this previous hidden
time stamp from the same layer and also
the output from uh the same time stamp
from the previous layer right that's
basically the idea of this multi-layer
RN but similarly we can just do do it
for videos now we introduce you can
introduce use this recurrent convolution
neuronet networks right uh it's it's
very similar um it's just like now we
build this grid of features right where
Each one is kind of a three dimension
vector like two are spatial dimension
and one is a channel dimension. Uh so
each uh d so each feature vector uh it's
uh uh like uh of dimension c * h * w. So
each depends on two inputs for each
vector for each feature map it depends
on the feature map from the same layer
by the previous time stamp but it also
depends on the feature map from the
previous layer by the same time stamp.
Right? Uh
so if we record in 2D convolution
network right where we uh we just map
this feature map from some input feature
to a output feature right but here for
this recurrent convolution network uh we
can just use as input this two 3D
tensors right one from the previous
layer and uh previous uh same layer and
previous time stamp and one from the
previous layer and the same time stamp.
So you recall a recurrent uh uh network
it has this uh form uh form of like it
has some hidden uh hidden layer uh
feature map HT minus one. It takes input
of this current time stamp, right? It
have some uh some function with some
parameter W and then process new state
uh feature vector HT, right? That's
basically R the the key of RN. So now
instead we just change this vectors
forms of RN. We just replace all this
matrix multiplication in this uh in
recurrent new networks with 2D
convolutions. Right? Now we get this
recurrent convolution networks. So you
have the feature map you do 2D
convolution instead of have this matrix
multiplication we get another feature
map right and uh for also for features
from uh the previous layer the same time
stamp we also do this and then we use uh
uh after doing this 2D convolution we
add them together use another 10h layer
and we get the picture map for for for
the current uh uh hidden uh hidden layer
so that's basically the the idea of
recurrent convolution network we com
combine convolution operations and
recurrent operations and we can also
actually do this for any kind kind of
recurren network of coal variants like
GRUs and LSTMs. Maybe you have already
learned from previous class and uh so
now we can successfully combine the
benefits of the two right we have this
uh both spatial and temporal fusion uh
inside this recurrent convolution new
network. So but this model is not uh was
not used too much and because uh there's
one uh large downside of recurrent
neural networks which you have already
learned that iron unit are very slow
right for processing non-sequence and
videos are usually very very very long
and you have to pro you have to be
processing in parallel but irons are
very hard to to to be paralyzed
but there's uh another thing another uh
important model you have learned like uh
I think in the previous lectures right
what we can We can also use uh uh
operations like the self attention right
to uh process videos right for self
attention you have this kind of key
queries keys and values and you uh and
you you can you can use self attention
here as a standalone kind of operation
to process images here we can also do it
for videos right and and one one very
large advantage of self attention is
highly paralyzerable right and all the
alignment and this attention scores for
all the inputs can be done
completely in parallel. So indeed people
are trying to you know use self
attention also in videos right so they
just pause self attention directly to 3D
right maybe you have some 3D
convolutional network you get some
feature map like c * t * h * w and then
you can similarly you can you want to
get some query query feature maps right
you can use some 1* 1 * 1 3D
convolutions to uh change the channel
dimension to map them to query feature
map that is c prime* t * h * w similarly
for keys you get this feature map for
values you get this feature maps and
Then you want to get some tension
weights, right? Basically, you're doing
some transpose of this feature map from
queries and you're doing this uh uh uh
vector wise uh multiplication. You get a
attention score for each query and key
uh feature uh kind of pair and then you
can get this attention map and then use
it to you know condition the values,
right? And you can uh them to you can
get another value kind of feature
feature map and then you can map them
you do another one times one time one
convolution to map them back to you know
the same dimension C so that you can be
concatenated with the original feature
input. So that is a resid connection. So
in total you can see that it's very
similar to the self attention uh uh
operations but now we move things to 3D
and this is some one block that is very
you know independent it can stand on its
own right you can so that's so in this
uh paper it's called looo neuronet
network it introduces kind of block and
call local block you can use it as uh a
kind of building block for uh processing
videos to do video understanding for
example you can just add this unknown
local blocks uh into existing 3D
convolutional network architectures and
uh to you know to have some 3DC and have
non-local block and another and another
block of 3DC and add non-local block and
each non-local block basically has is
very powerful to fuse across both space
and time and finally you do into this
classification.
So but one thing we haven't talked about
is what is this 3D convolutional
networks right what what what what we
should use here. So uh another very kind
of u interesting idea that people have
explored in the past that is can we
reuse the 2D convolution neural network
many successful architecture we have we
have been we have talked about or have
learned right directly to 3D right we
can we just doing some inflation of this
2D networks so we can you know then we
can get a 3D convolution new networks so
for this work uh it's called I 3D
architecture the idea is that uh they
just take a two 2D say and architecture
they replace each 2D uh convo pool uh
layer uh the layer that originates of
dimension kh * kw but now we would we we
replace with a 3D version that is a kt*
kh* kw right they just inflate it
basically and they use it uh on top of
the inception block uh uh and then the
after they doing this inflation uh bas
uh then you you have architecture uh for
processing videos right directly just
reuse the existing architectures and uh
al we now we can transfer the
architecture that works pretty well in
2D to work uh also in 3D right but what
one taking one step further people also
have been uh uh trying trying things
that not only we can transfer the
architectures but actually also we can
transfer the weights right because we
have already trained pre-trained a lot
of architectures models on image data
sets right maybe we can actually use the
weights we have learned there there are
some maybe some good prior information
so they so one thing you can do is that
you can just initialize uh uh the
inflated CN with weights train on images
for example you have maybe from from
from for for from for from for for from
for from for from for from for from for
from for for one originally uh uh you
have you have this 2D common kernel
right uh you just uh copy the kernel by
KT times and you divide it by KT and you
just uh now you originally takes one
single image as input now you take this
video of three times KT* H* W as input
because we have divided them by KT if
you just use this inflated version and
use a copy the weights by copy the
weights by uh KT times and then you
you'll get the same output if you just
uh input a single frame or like a video
of constant uh frames. So now we have a
way to recycle this kind of existing 2D
image based on this architecture uh and
weights from uh 2D uh image
understanding. So and actually it works
uh pretty well. So if you look at the
performance if you inflate them uh
compared to this two stream convolution
network actually has better performance
and you can also inflate actually not
only in the appearance stream frame you
can also inflate the you know motion
motion stream. So you actually get gets
uh some further improvements. Basically
this is just like a technique you can do
to reuse this kind of independent from
the 3D convolutional networks. Those are
you can you can you can build this kind
of long local blocks and but this part
I'm what I'm trying to say is that uh we
can we have a lot of 2D convolutional
networks uh the weights successful
people have have you know shown that
they are very successful and if we want
to reuse them people have shown that
that they can actually copy the weights
and reuse them reuse their weights so
directly oper uh use them to operate on
on videos so So that basically that's
the kind of highlight idea and you just
you can you can after you're doing this
initialization you can still fine-tune
right on the video data but you have uh
the pre-trained weights from images. So
then we can give you some good
initialization for training the video
models. So this is this idea of this I3D
network basically is trying to copy the
weights and doing the inflation.
Uh okay. Uh so there this is also just a
one example of this video understanding
uh net uh model and there are also a
many other video transfer model proposed
for for video understanding that is uh
uh for example there are some uh this
work uh space-time attention is trying
to doing more factorized attention to
transpose uh space and time and also
there are some other method trying to be
more efficient in terms of this
transformer architecture or have some
mask autoenccoder you heard about to
doing more efficient scalable video
uh level kind of pre-training uh to
doing video understanding. So I'm not
going to talk uh them uh here in the
class but if you are interested you can
check out our papers because there are
also a lot many progress has been made
to have better you know video
understanding models and if you look at
the performance of progress that we I
think we start here from like single
frame model 62.2 two for on this uh on
this this is another data set kinetics
400 it's a large video data set and then
you can see that for this video muscle
encoder now it already gets to 90% uh
accuracy so there are some other uh new
transformer model has been proposed
so so we are doing uh very well on
classifying the the videos uh and
similar to the image classification uh
in the last class we can also use
similar tricks for visualizing uh video
models. So we can taking this uh two
stream network uh as an examples we can
randomly initialize the appearance image
and the flow image uh doing a we doing a
forward pass and then compute the the
score and then we can back propagate
with with respect to the score of a
particular class and you gradient ascent
to you know maximize the classification
score just just like we were doing the
visualization for for the image based
model right so if you then it's through
this way that if you can we can
visualize you know doing some
visualization interpretation of what has
been earned right so this is uh the left
is the optimized image for appearance
stream maybe it's hard to you know to
guess what is maybe happening uh in the
in the video stream on the right uh it's
uh it's optimized
image for the flow stream one has like
some temporal constraints to you know to
pre prevent the temporal stream to
change too too fast so there's so you
can capture slow motion and the other is
capture 's right motion. So you can
guess what the action it is. Uh maybe
this in this case is pretty clear. So
what action is this?
So this is a uh weak lifting. You can
see that the maybe the single the middle
one is doing some bar shaking, right?
And the the right one is doing some uh
pushing uh overhead the the motion,
right? So it's indeed actually you can
see that this uh video models action
models uh are learning something about
this motion.
Okay. So uh so so far uh I have been
talking about uh how we can classify the
short clips right uh the swimming
running uh uh but another very important
thing is that how we can other task is
that uh this is called temporal action
localization is that uh not only we want
to you know just doing clip level or
classification sometimes we want to
localize just we want to doing object
detection right now we want to localize
where in the video the action is
happening right maybe sometimes the
person is running sometimes is jumping
so this is another there's another task
this is another class called temporal
action localization it's a uh you can
also use similar maybe ideas from like
fast RN right you can just generate some
temporal proposals and then doing the
classification
and uh also there you can also do both
right this is a spatial temporal
detection basically you can uh local you
want to localize not only in space but
also in time where the action is
happening in space where the hashing is
happening temporally. So this is another
task called spatial temporal uh
detection.
Okay. Uh so so far uh I have been uh
talking about you know the temporal
stream and uh uh how architectures we
can use to you know doing 3DC and
twostream neuronet network spatial
temporal self attention and uh we have
already talked about some tools uh to do
that but yeah uh maybe in the final 10
minutes let's just uh revisit I hope to
yeah finish uh in time uh let's revisit
example that we started today right we
we We I showed you a video, right? But
that's still uh maybe not the full
picture, right?
>> So looking at video, we are doing video
understanding there's another very
important dimension that we have never
covered till now, right? That is this.
There's sound, there's audio, there's
another modalities in videos, right? If
we we miss that ingredient, you not lose
a lot of fun, right? There's emotions
you can perceive. There's another you
know interactions you can do if you
combine this visual and motion. So if we
have this audio in mind and we have this
vision stream then people also have
proposed many other interesting tasks
and also we have explored other tasks to
doing video understanding. Here's
another example that maybe uh you in
videos that maybe there are some multi
multiple objects multiple speakers and
you can actually one task example task
uh that I I also personally have
explored in the past that we only guided
audio source separation and you can
actually understand trying to process
things visually and acoustically you can
use a visual information to guide the
source separation you want to separate
the sound components right because
originally maybe there's a mixture you
want to use a visual information to
separate into some sound components this
is called visually guided also
separation ation to just to give you an
example for this task. For example, here
is a speech mixture. Maybe sometimes we
want to hear the sounds for each person
individually, right? Then we can use
their visual information, audio
information to process them together to
separate their sounds. So here is a what
we can do. We can separate the voice for
the live speakers. So only we can do
this for for people for speech right
when we have to process audio and speech
and visual strength. But we also have do
this for other types of you know sound
like muted instruments. Here's another
example. We can even do music
instruments separation by analyze the
motion the object central information
with the audio stream and doing the
separation. Yeah. So this is another
example for this task and also there
have been since since once we introduce
this new modality of audio we just want
to do video understanding classification
we can audio can also be useful cues
right so there are indeed there are
other work audio visual video
understanding work proposed from
transformer attention based models
trying to not only we want to map images
to patches but also we map those audio
spectrum to patches and use some
transformer architectures to doing the
classification or even we want to we can
do some uh um mask autoenccoder style.
We want to predict the patches for the
images and also spectrograms doing video
understanding. Uh so and and also
another aspect people have been uh
exploring is how to do efficient video
understanding. So I will just quickly
give some examples. So here uh uh
throughout this class I think many focus
on clip clip level classification right
just giving a clip how to doing this uh
classification and after we classify a
lot of clips and we want to aggregate
information to get a video level
predictions right that's action
recognition in non videos so so for for
efficient video understanding why we
want to do efficient video understanding
because you know videos are very long we
don't we cannot afford to process every
clip one by one right so there we're
trying to increase the the efficiency
for a single uh clip just building like
this X3D is trying to build better 3D
convolution your network but also they
are trying to you know this like this uh
SD sampler trying to you know predict
which which which clips are the most
senior most useful and then you can com
uh combine the predictions only run your
clip classifier on those important clips
and also they were trying to doing
policy learning trying to you know
predict which which modality we to use
in order to doing this uh action
classification. We can select oh whether
we want to use video, how many videos,
how many video clips or whether want to
use audio or other sensory data. Um so
here's one example that yeah we we can
also use audio trying to as a preview
mechanism we can uh to to predict or
which which uh where are the important
uh moments and then we use that uh as a
guiding crew to process the clips and to
average the results. Um so that's about
the efficient video understanding. So
that's also uh one area of research. So
and also nowadays there people are
moving to VR and AR right the smart
glasses right and uh for this and also
now in the future I'm I'm guessing there
are a lot of like egocentric video
streams that's another aspect of video
understanding so not only you have this
egocentric videos but you have also have
this multi multi microphone microphone
array multi- channelannel audios so then
you can so how to doing better on video
understanding from this egocentric
multimodal egocentric stream video
streams is also a hot topic maybe uh we
I've explored that uh we can do like use
process this video streams the audio
multi channel audio and the vision
information to doing you know to predict
who is speaking to whom and who is
listening to whom imagine whe in the
future you wear this smart glasses you
want to to use it to help you to
understand this different type of social
interactions right so that's a ego
egocentric video understanding so my
final slide yeah definitely for LMS
right now uh there also a lot of ongoing
work trying to build video level
foundation models, right? How to connect
the video understanding to Loom. So
there indeed there are works trying to
you know just map the videos to some
tokenize them and map them to the LM
embedding space and use maybe you can
ask prompt the video uh foundation model
you know where the person is uh what the
person is doing in the in the video and
then you output some you know uh uh text
to you know uh to describe the videos.
So there are many work trying to connect
video understanding LMS. So that's also
a hot topic right now.