Um
okay guess you are yeah um yeah before I
start with with my talk um I would like
to uh first share a bit about myself so
I've been working on 3D reconstruction
and generation ever since my PhD in 2018
uh where I mainly worked on
self-servised 3D reconstruction uh and
appearance modeling and between now and
then things have moved very fast so I
joined Google in 2022 uh where I then
worked on generative 3D reconstru
construction as well as generative 3D
relighting uh before video models
changed the the research landscape uh
and what is possible and the progress in
our field has been so fast and
impressive um that 3D reconstruction
methods with the help of generative AI
actually work at scale. So our team at
Google was able to convert some of that
research into product. Um yeah, so first
we we focused on reconstructing shoes
where we used image models to help with
3D reconstruction and landed at uh on
Google shopping and then later we
started to work on video models which
helped us to expand to any kind of
object category uh on Google shopping
and the progress in our field over the
last couple of years has been incredibly
exciting and in today's talk uh I will
be discussing 3D generation methods and
how to put them into perspective with
general video models.
But first, let's define what a general
feed model is. So, at its core, it's a
system that takes as input uh a control
uh like a text prompt or an image and it
uses a generative model uh to produce a
3D representation.
However, to actually see the content on
on the screen of a 3D model, it must be
rendered into 2D images so we can
actually look at them. And early works
on generative 3D modeling used GANs in
2016 uh where we had a pure generative
model with a noisy latent that was then
trained to produce 3D voxels with a 3D
discriminator and here we had no
specific control over the inputs and
needed 3D ground truth uh data for
training
and some follow-up works like platonic
gun address the 3D data problem by
removing the need for 3D ground truth by
adding a differentiable renderer and a
2D a 2D discriminator
and this allowed to train models
directly on 2D internet data and
platoniggon also introduced an image
encoder to enable 3D reconstruction from
single images
and building on the idea of image based
reconstruction works like pixel nerve uh
focused on multiv- view inputs and the
core innovation here was to aggregate
encodings from multiple input images
fusing them into a single consistent 3D
representation in the form of a nerf
And now all of these method I've
mentioned have something in common like
they all directly predict a three a
consistent explicit 3D representation
and this has a sign significant
advantage because once you have that 3D
model you can render the model from any
view which is very fast and cheap and
this makes it perfectly viable for
real-time applications on mobile devices
like phones and tablets.
But the downside is that the over
quality the overall quality of those
results uh is quite low. So maybe we
should ask ourselves well why is the
quality low and if we recall a satin
splitter lesson the answer might lie in
two limiting assumptions. So first high
quality 3DS data is very scar uh and
secondly um that we shouldn't use any
strong inductive biases like in our case
uh rendering.
But if on the other hand we look at 2D
generative models like image uh or video
models, we realize that those models
actually scale with data since we have
billions of 2D images or videos on the
internet. Uh and furthermore, these
models have a limited have limited
inductive biases since they directly
produce uh 2D pixels.
So over the years these model have been
have been becoming better and better um
since we have more and more compute. Um
and so yeah we can train them on on on
bigger models with bigger compute.
Um but the question is do those video
models produce realistic and also more
importantly physically correct outputs.
Um and in one of our recent works we
were interested in exploring this
direction and wanted to see how well do
video models understand 3D.
Um so and to answer this question uh we
investigated a video model's knowledge
to understand the pose.
So here as you can see for two images A
and B of a scene with very little
overlap we ran an off-the-shelf pose
model such as Dusta uh to predict camera
poses.
And we know that off-the-shelf uh pose
estimators that rely on v visual
correspondences struggle to accurately
to accurately predict the pose.
Um so to find out whether video models
can understand the pose between two
images, we use several video generation
models to interpolate a video connecting
the two images.
So assuming that the video model can
understand the post between two images,
it should generate a physically correct
path between both of the input images.
And to verify this, we feed the
additionally generated images along with
the two input images to this
off-the-shelf uh post estimator and
check if the post estimator improves.
And we found that this is actually the
case. And these additionally generated
frames from the video model actually
enhance the pose estimators. Um and as
and as a result this means that video
models are capable of of actually
implicitly modeling the physical world
uh correctly.
So if you look uh if you look at video
models or like if you look at if I look
at the latest video models um we can
convince ourselves that these models
produce highly realistic results. So for
instance here uh this video here was
produced by the V3 model uh which shows
us the diverse camera motion scene
motion uh as well as highly realistic
physics
and furthermore interactive video models
like Gen3 already allow us to navigate
3D worlds. So as you can see here we're
not just watching a clip but we can
actually actively navigate through
through a classroom. So here each
keystroke like forward, turn left, turn
right uh prompts the model to generate
new frames and we can freely navigate uh
and inspect different viewpoints and
eventually walk towards the window and
look outside. And here is the critical
part. When we turn back the classroom
looks the same as before and it actually
remains consistent.
So the question becomes why do we even
need to explicitly model 3D? If if those
purely 2D video models are already this
good, what's the argument for for
explicitly modeling 2D?
Uh and the answer is well while those
video models scale with data and compute
the inference cost also goes up which
prevents us from serving these models on
phones and tablets currently.
So how do we overcome this issue? Um and
if you look at this uh point from a 3D
perspective, uh we already know tools
like Nerf that can model 3D content
given hundreds of images. So once we
have hundreds of images, we can capture
3D scenes in great detail, which then
allows us to render arbitrary uh novel
viewpoints. Um and this can be achieved
at a very low cost uh compared to image
and video models.
So let's look at an example. So here is
a fly through of a large complex scene
and it's a house with multiple rooms and
in a large garden. And what's important
here is that this is actually fully
interactive which means we can control
the camera arbitrarily and choose any
viewpoint we want. However, this scene
was generated many by by manly capturing
many images of this house uh from a
diverse set of views.
So but the good thing is that it seems
like we have two pieces of a puzzle uh
that we can combine. So on one side we
have generative image and video models
that produce highly realistic 2D images
and on the other side uh there is nerf
models that can distill those images
into an efficient 3D representation that
can be served and rendered efficiently.
And this is exactly the combination uh
that we explored in in CAT 3D.
So, CAT3 is a method that can take in a
text prompt, a single image or multiple
images and generate 3D scenes.
So, let's have a look at this uh method
in more detail. So, Kathy first uh takes
as input observed views which contain an
an input image and the corresponding
camera parameters.
uh and we then encode the image using a
pre-trained VAE into image latence uh
and while those uh and while the the
pose and the camera information is
encoded into a per pixel ray coordinate
map which basically just contains each
pixels uh ray informations. So simply it
it just contains like the origin and the
direction per pixel
and the model also takes in novel views
uh and for those views we don't actually
have an input image uh so we pass a
noisy latence instead of encoded latence
uh to the model uh as well as the post
information.
And to help distinguish between the
observed and the novel views we also
feed in a mass that tells the model
which views are observed and which views
are not.
So the input to the model can be any
mixture of these two different types of
inputs and they're treated exactly uh
the same by the model. So it's just a
large set of views uh that may be known
or unknown to the model.
And so the model takes all of this
information in and then simply produces
a set of generated novel views for the
spec for the specified uh target views.
And we train this on a large set of post
multiv- view images. Um, so it's
supervised to produce multiple
consistent frames at once. Um, and so
because this model has a tension between
all of the different frames, we can
actually get really consistent samples.
So once our diffusion model is trained,
uh we then proposed a 2D two-stage setup
uh to reconstruct uh the results. So
here given some input views uh we we use
the multiv- view model to generate a
dense set of views of the desired scene
as you can see here and then we simply
reconstruct those views using a
relatively standard nerf pipeline
and while the samples that we generated
are not entirely 3D consistent uh
they're consistent enough that the nerf
reconstruction pipeline is able to
consolidate them into a consistent 3D
output
and end to end uh our method
is able to produce full 3D scenes in as
little as 1 minute from any uh number of
input in inputs like three images or
even just a single image.
So if we go back to our overview
uh we see that we can use 3D methods
like nerf to combine uh to combine
generative 2D models uh to generate 3D
models that are fast and cheap to
render.
However, having an optimization step in
this loop is still a bottleneck for the
inference speed. And we asked ourselves,
well, um, can we replace this
optimization step with a feed forward
model? And the answer to that question
is given another work which is called B
3D
and B 3D lets you generate 3D scenes in
less than 7 seconds on a single GPU. So,
let's have a look how we achieve this.
Uh the key idea here is based on
splatter images where the goal is to
reconstruct per pixel gausian splats
given a single image.
However, this method uh was a purely
reconstruction based method and could
not couldn't handle handle any unseen
parts of the scene since it wasn't a
generative model.
uh but however in both 3D we proposed uh
to also so yeah so in both 3D we
proposed to also represent the 3D scene
as splatter images but instead of a
reconstruction model we proposed a
generative model
and compared to splatter images both 3D
allows us for hallucinating unseen
regions of the scene since we're
actually proposing a generative model
and in B 3D the generation process um
consists of two parts so first we have a
latent in the fusion model that
generates multiv- view appearance and
geometry in the form of images and point
maps. And if we go back to cat 3, for
cat 3D we only predicted RGB latance.
And here we additionally have uh point
map latency.
And then in the second part, a gausian
head then jointly regresses the
remaining properties of the 3D gausian
uh namely the scale and the opacities
given the images and the point maps. And
the output of uh the gausian are multiv-
view splatter images which hold 3D
gausian that then together represent an
entire 3D scene.
And the reason uh for this 2D for this
two-stage pipeline to first generate RGB
colors and XOZ positions which is then
followed by predicting opacities and
scales is that we can robustly obtain
supervision for both the appearance and
point maps from multiple uh from for
multiv- view data sets.
uh and for obtaining super super vision
for positions we simply run uh structure
for motion pipelines on existing multiv-
view data sets which are which are
pretty robust.
However, it's not actually trivial to
obtain good quality vision uh for
opacities and scales of pixel and
gausian. Um so it's not easy to train a
diffusion model to output them.
Uh and on top of that, a recent work
showed that given colors and uh position
information, it's uh much easier to
regress opacities and scales uh than to
generate them. Um and this is this um
explains uh our design choice uh to
first generate uh to first train a
generative model of RGB and XYZ which is
then followed by requesting the
remaining uh properties.
So let's have a closer look at how we do
this. Um the generation process is
implemented using a multiv- view latent
diffusion model of appearance in
geometry. Um and then the input model
similar to K3 is a set of scene and
unseen views of the scene. And the
observed views contain a clean RGB
latent and this time also a noisy
geometry latent and the camera uh pose
of the observed view. And the unobserved
views contain a noisy RGB latent, a
noisy geometry latent and the camera
pose of the target view. So compared to
K3D here we additionally have like
geometry latence for both the unseen and
seen views.
And then the diffusion model uh outputs
a set of clean image and geometry
latence. Uh and this it does it by for
for each pair uh one pair for each view
sorry. Yeah.
And then the the image and the geometry
are then decoded independently to full
resolution RGB and XYZ images.
And an insight here is that simply
autoenccoding point maps using
offtheshelf uh RGB autoenccoders results
in very low quality reconstructions. Um
and I'm not going to go into detail
right now, but we will talk about uh the
geometry autoenccoder later.
So next we then train a so once we have
this we train a multiv- view gausian
head that takes in all of the predicted
per viewpoint maps and RGB images to
produce a set of splatter images. That
means we transform each view into
gausian.
Then here it was important to have cross
attention between all of the views so
that the network could reason about uh
all the splatter images together um to
ensure 3D consistency.
And then finally we can render these
better images to view our final output.
And to to train this model uh we created
a large data set of 3D scenes. Um and we
ran master a recent 3D structure for
motion pipeline on all scenes from CO3D,
R10K, MV imageet and D3DV.
And this uh was necessary so that all of
our data has dense xyz notations for
every image u making this data then
suitable for diffusion model training.
Um and together with synthetic object
data sets this allowed us to to train
our generator on a large scale data set.
So let's have a look at some of uh our
results. So here we see two scenes uh
that were faithfully reconstructed by
just a single image. Um, and we can also
see that the model here, um, can
actually hallucinate unseen regions.
And we also have more examples on our
project web page. Uh, and there's even
an interactive view where you can
explore our scenes in real time. Um, so
please take a look yourself.
Um, yeah. So, but one thing that I would
like now to talk about now in more
detail is this geometry autoenccoder.
Um, because learning to operate a
geometry with a latent diffusion model
has proven surprisingly difficult
initially. Um so we found that uh VAE
VAE pre-trained uh for for image
autoenccoding were not really
appropriate for autoenccoding geometry.
Uh and we found this to be the case
regardless of this uh scale of the scene
and but actually observed that uh for
bigger scenes we get even more
catastrophic failure um failures. Yeah.
And this is likely because the
objectives for compressing images are
not really appropriate for compressing
geometry. Um, for example, perceptual
losses don't really make sense uh for
for geometry.
And another reason is the scale of the
data because input images are always
within 0 and one. Um, but this is rarely
the case for geometry.
And something else interesting or like
another interesting insight that I would
like to share is that we found that the
decoder uh in the VA for XZ data
actually needs to be a transformer. Um
even though that so yes so it it should
be a transformer even though
qualitatively quantitatively uh a
convolutional decoder performed similar
to a transformer decoder but when you
actually look at the convolutional
decoder or like the results of the
convolutional decoder um it leads to
perceptually jarring artifacts like not
actually maintaining straight lines as
you can see here on this slide.
And this can also uh be seen like those
artifacts can be seen across a big range
of scenes uh including those bathroom
shelves here.
So and since uh fine-tuning geometry VAE
for both of you was quite crucial. Uh I
would also like to share another line of
work in the VA space with you. Um and
this is actually something that we
recently submitted to CVPR. Um, so
you're actually the first uh to hear
about this work and since since it's
still under review. Um, so let's take a
quick detour into the VA land and then
we're going to get back to to generative
3D again.
So the paper I'm going to present is
called vision language models as
perceptual judges for human aligned uh
image compression.
So usually when you when we train out
encoders, we use losses such as PSN or
SSIM. Uh, however, these losses really
poorly align with human perception. So
for instance, humans are very sensitive
to pertubations to faces and text, but
less so to natural textures such as
grass or fur or other patterns like in
this example here, the flag on the top
right in the image um that is shown here
on the slide um or the text uh on the
window.
And to to address this problem uh we
propose a method that uses an
off-the-shelf vision language model as a
per perceptual judge to improve current
autoenccoder training to focus more on
human aligned image compression.
And as you can see here on the slide uh
our method improves the text on the
window and if you look closely it also
improves the pattern on the flag despite
not being actually correct pixel wise.
So instead our method uh produces a flag
pattern that to us human looks kind of
the same but if you took a but if you
take a very close look um you can see
that the white points on the flag are
actually not identical but located in
different positions
um I'm not sure if you can see this
through through the through zoom um but
yeah you can see this on on our web page
later once we upload it so the question
is like how how can we achieve something
like this um so let's have a look at at
this method. Uh so the the idea here is
that given the original image, we're
using a diffusion autoenccoder
and decode it twi and decode the
original image twice using two different
noise seats to get a decoding A and a
decoding B. And we then prompt a VLM to
evaluate which of the two decodings is
preferred. And based on the response of
the VLM,
we then use a diffusion DPO to improve
the diffusion autoenccoder.
And in theory here, any reward function
could be used to determining to
determine uh the losing and the winning
decoding. Um but in our case, we we
chosen VLM to do so. Uh which is the
novelty of this method. So let's have a
a look at our method in a bit more
detail. So again given those two
decodings A and B as well as the
original image we prompt the network to
analyze those two different samples from
the AE
and the VLM is then tked to produce a
numerical rating between minus 5 and
five indicating whether the
reconstruction A or reconstruction B is
closer to the original image. And here
ne negative numbers means that A is
better which is the case in this example
shown here. [snorts]
And since VLMs are prone to
hallucinations, we use the following
three strategies to make our loss more
robust. So first, instead of just
feeding in A and B always in the same
order, uh we also reverse the order of
the input uh images to the VLM.
And secondly, uh we run the VLM for
multiple seats for A and B and then sum
them up uh to reduce the noisiness uh of
the outputs of the VLM.
And then thirdly, I mentioned earlier
that we can also use any kind of um
metric here to determine which which of
the two images is better. Um so what we
did uh in uh for the third one is that
we additionally use an L pips metric to
determine which reconstruction is more
accurate.
And if the VLM and the LPIPS agree, we
then pass the rating to the diffusion
TPO and otherwise we just discard the
the sample.
And we also ran ablations uh and tested
the LPIPS and the VF
sorry the VLM preferences independently.
Um and while using each preference
scheme independently improves the
results using both schemes together or
like combined results in in the best
performance.
So comparing our method uh with other
competitors uh we can see that our
method allows us to correctly decode the
text as you can see here. And when we
look at the building in the background,
we can also see that it improves the
high frequency textures of the of the
windows or like the the smaller yeah
smaller parts of the windows. And then
furthermore, in the second example at
the bottom, we can see that our method
improves the face reconstruction uh as
you can see here uh if you look at the
woman on the on the right uh and as well
as the patterns on the wall in the
background.
And we also evaluated this uh method
quantitatively quantitatively against
multiple competitors uh on multiple data
sets. Uh and most of the methods are
trained on varying bits uh per pixel uh
which we don't denote as BPP. Um so we
also train our method on two different
BPs. Uh one model was trained on 0.07
and the other one was trained for 0.21
BP.
And when we look at the numbers, our
method actually performs quite poorly on
PSNR PSNR as you can see here on the
right. So our method is shown as a blue
line and a higher value for PSNR means
the results are better. But you can see
that our results actually have the
lowest and therefore worst numbers. Um
but this is well but that's actually
that wasn't really our goal to improve
the PSR here. Uh but we were rather
cared about the the human perception
since yeah since this is what like what
we wanted and to get a better sense for
this uh we then also ran a user study
and computed an ELO score for all the
methods
and as we can see here our method
actually performs quite well on the MSCO
and the click 2020 data set. Uh however
our method actually underperforms
compared to the PO EIC uh method on the
click 2022 data set. Um, and this is a
little bit unfortunate, but here it's
actually hard to say why this is the
case. Um, because POE didn't really
didn't actually release their code and
the click 2022 that set also only
contained 30 images uh which then can
also potentially lead to to noisy
results.
But then looking at other perceptual
metrics like FID, FID dyno and the LPIP
score, uh we can see that our method
actually performs quite well across the
board.
Okay, so this brings us to the end of
our VAE detour. Uh, and while this
wasn't really directly focusing on 3D
generation, uh, I would be very
interested in seeing how we can use VLM
post training similar to what I talked
here um, talked about here for 3D
related tasks. And with that being said,
let's hop back to generative 3D again.
So earlier I presented Body, which was a
method to generate 3D scenes in a feed
forward manner given 2D generated
images.
And so far uh we've talked about a lot
of uh 3D generation uh of of sorry of 3D
generation of content but an important
factor uh for content creation is also
to allow for fine grain control of the
outputs and one such control is
lighting.
Um so in the next chapter we will talk
about how to enable light control for
generative uh 3D models
and we address this in in in this task
in in our method called ROA. And here
given post images in a target
illumination
the goal is to produce a 3D model under
novel illumination.
And to achieve this, we train a multiv-
view relighting model similar to the
multiv- view models for CAT 3 and BD,
but this time for real lighting. And the
difference here is that the input is not
only a set of images and their
corresponding poses, but also has a
light condition.
And we then train this model to produce
a to produce readed versions of the
input views for each available
so for each available light from from
one to light M.
And the goal of this multivv model is to
produce a data set of n by m real images
that then that then can be used as a
data set for a light conditioned nerve
optimization
and the goal is um to relight an object
under lots of different illuminations so
that we that we can then train a nerf um
to condition on a target light. So here
think about a light stage where we turn
on and off arbitrary lights. And the
idea is that if we cover a dense enough
or sorry a diverse enough set of
different illuminations, the nerve
should be able to generalize to unseen
target illuminations.
So let's start first with a standard
nerf setup uh where we condition the
nerve for every pose here. So for every
pose I and we comput a rendering loss on
the image corresponding to the input
pose. And to train a light conditioner,
the task is to encode the input lights.
So we can also feed in uh a target sorry
an input light as an as an additional
conditioning. Um and then the next
question is well how do you pick the the
right uh representation
to encode the lighting because this is
non-trivial. Um and in our case we opted
uh for an environment representation and
we feed this environment rep environment
through a transformer encoder
to get a light embedding. And while in
theory this should be sufficient uh to
represent the lighting we found that the
encoder wasn't powerful enough to always
take care of all the specular uh
regions.
So to address this issue, we
additionally created a specular
embedding that explicitly encodes the
incident light uh from the specular
reflection direction.
And instead of only sampling a single
value from the environment map uh at the
reflection direction, we sample locally
around the nth map to handle different
roughness values. And the way we do this
is by pre uh by pre pre-b blurring the
end mapap uh so that we can then sample
a single location as embedding.
So once the n once we train this nerve
um we can then condition it on any
target lighting to relight the 3D model.
And on this slide here we show that
different lighting target so that
different target lightings uh for a
given source lighting.
And we can see that our model faithfully
recovers uh specular highlights while
competitive methods struggle to do so.
And the competitive methods either
misses to fully produce the specular
highlight as we can see in the top row
or it overcompensates for the specular
highlight as you can see on the bottom
row.
So as you can see this method fits
nicely into our generative 3 setup and
extended the number of controls.
So what we learned from this type of
method setup where we have a generative
part and then a 3D distillation part is
that we can see that the 3D part will
only ever be as good as a 2D generation
part as the 3D part is dependent on the
good on good generations.
So if you remember Richard Sutton that
says assume abundance of data and
compute and limit the inductive bias um
we should assume that truly generative
methods um will scale whereas 3D models
will not scale but the 3D models are
cost and time efficient.
And one work that demonstrates the
dependence of a strong 2D generator is
uh one of our works called captive.
And in captive we address the task of
360 panorama generation given text or a
single image. However, three 360
panorama data is actually quite limited.
Um so the task is how can we scale a
method to generate 360 panorama images
despite the limited amount of data.
And the key idea here is that we can
treat 360 panorama images as cube map
with six faces. So treating them as six
different sides of a cube means that
each individual image is a perspective
image that belongs to the distribution
of most images that exist on the
internet. And now if we stack up all of
those six images along their channel
imagine, we can train a 360 panorama
panorama generation model using the same
architecture as a standard 2D diffusion
model.
And the way we do this uh is by feeding
the stack of those images to a 2D coder
and then almost entirely
we re using the architecture of existing
2D models and in our case here we're
just using a pre-trained stable
diffusion model
and since uh such a pre-trained model is
already capable of producing the the
distribution of all the perspective
images we don't actually need to further
train the existing layers of the model.
So we keep those frozen.
However, what is important here uh so
however what the model is not capable of
doing yet is to reason about the three
layout of this cube map and how those
six input images uh belong uh belong
together.
So what we did is uh we added tension
layers between all the residual blocks
that are then trained to learn the
spatial relationship of the different
images contained in this cube map. And
since the task of understanding the
relationships between the six images is
significantly easier than learning the
entire uh distribution of images, a
small data set of panorama images in the
order of the magnitude of tens of
thousands of images was enough to train
the generative 360 panorama model.
And although our panorama data set as I
just mentioned is limited h sorry so and
although this panorama data set is
actually limited to natural images our
model can generate outputs beyond this
distribution as you can see here. Uh and
this is possible because we freeze the
foundation the the 2D foundation model
or the 2D foundation network which
retains its ability to generate any kind
of perspective image.
And yeah, this example here just
illustrates the out out of distribution
capability. [clears throat]
So getting back to the bit lesson,
overall it seems quite untrivial to
train 3D methods to be independent of 2D
models just due to the pure lack of 3D
data.
So should we be focusing on making 2D
models more costefficient and speed
efficient? Um, and our friends at World
Labs have been working on an interactive
3D model that is capable of real-time
next frame prediction uh on a single
GPU.
And while the results are not really
perfect, it's it's like a it seems to be
a very promising direction.
So this gets us to or like Yeah. So this
gets us to like answering the question,
why is 3D still important for content
generation? Um, so while while 2D
methods are already producing highly
realistic videos and have already shown
interactive capabilities such as camera
control, we do not yet have a full and
precise control over them yet. And more
importantly though, these model cannot
really be served uh currently. So we
still require 3D distillation um for
serving at the moment. And whether that
will change in the future um well I
guess we will see.
Uh and with that I would like to
conclude uh and thank you for listening
and also thank uh say a big thanks to
all of my collaborators.