All right. Uh, welcome everyone to CS25,
I believe week eight. Um, today we're
very excited to have Isa Margaret who is
a neuroscientist and ML researcher
working to understand biological systems
with AI. He completed his PhD in
neuroscience here at Stanford where he
constructed self-supervised neural
networks that incorporate biologically
inspired constraints to explain the
structure, function, and development of
primary visual cortex. He's currently an
ML scientist at NOTC, a AI native
biotech startup focused on curing
cancer. In his work, he develops novel
transformer model architectures and
tasks that learn from large multimodal
data sets of patient tumor biology and
applies these models to drug discovery.
As a reminder, please fill out the
attendance form. And if you're online,
you can ask any questions on Slido. With
that, I'll let you take it away.
Awesome. Thank you for that
introduction. I feel like that covered
it all. So, we're done here. We can wrap
it up. Um, I'm going to talk today about
kind of a mix of basic ML ideas about
how to do multimodal learning and a
little bit of the kind of research we're
doing at Noetic where I work now. Um,
I'm going to talk really in three parts.
You can tell I'm fond of alliteration
here. I'll do multimodal model madness
and tell you a little bit about ideas
for incorporating information streams
from multiple modalities. Then I'll
focus more specifically on cancer. So,
in that first part, you know, if you're
not interested in biology or cancer,
one, I'll convince you otherwise, and
two, um, you'll get a lot out of that
first part, I hope. And then I have a
few random things I threw in at the end
about work in progress that might be
exciting.
So, um, just to put it out there, my
assumptions about this audience are that
you're interested in research on
transformers given the course title, um,
and specifically maybe novel transformer
architectures that you haven't
encountered before. I I'll assume that
you're curious about how we're actually
trying to use transformers outside of an
academic context and to bring it into a
clinically useful context. Um I will
assume that you're kind of familiar with
the basics of transformers in machine
learning, but not necessarily experts.
There will be no pop quiz about
equations or formulas or architecture
diagrams today. And I will assume that
you don't have any familiarity with
cancer immunology. So this will
hopefully be friendly to people that
have never really thought about that
world. But I hope you all agree that
curing cancer is a worthwhile thing to
do. And I'll tell you about the ways
we're trying to bring these worlds
together.
Um, what you should know about me, this
was covered a bit in the intro, but um,
I did my PhD here at Stanford in
neuroscience. So I am actually not a
cancer immunologist by training or
background. I'm new to that field. Um,
my background is in computational
neuroscience and specifically visual
cortex and how the primate visual system
works. And when I was here, I mostly
studied how we can build in biological
constraints into at the time
convolutional neural networks um to make
them more brain-like. And my broad
interest is in understanding how complex
biological systems get put together, how
they work when they're working, and how
they don't work when they stop working.
Before I go further, I should call out
the other people that I work with at
Noetic. We're a pretty small machine
learning research team, but the stuff
I'm going to show you today is due to
their efforts as much as mine. Um, and
I'll do my best to call out when they
contributed specific things, but in case
I forget, these are their names and
faces.
Okay. And the last bit of housekeeping,
this is kind of my plan for roughly the
next hour. Might try to go a little
faster to save time for questions at the
end. Um, I'm going to try to convince
you primarily that there's a lot of
really exciting and creative work to be
done in multimodal machine learning,
especially with transformers. And two,
something that I became convinced of in
the past year and a half really, that
cancer biology is just a really
fantastic place to do that kind of
research that the kind of data we're
generating is really unique and
something that I wouldn't have
considered as a substrate to do basic ML
research. For bonus points, I'll also
try to convince you that we're actually
making progress on drug discovery for
cancer at Noetic. Um, and then the way
that I normally prefer to give
presentations is I'm super happy to have
clarifying questions. So, please if
something doesn't make sense, it's
probably I forgot a sentence or a
definition. Do let me know. Um, if you
have larger philosophical questions
about why we're all here, I'd also love
to talk about those, but I'll try to
save a little time at the end for the
more freewheeling discussion.
Okay.
So with that said, let me jump into my
conceptual framework for thinking about
multimodal model madness.
I think a unifying goal for much of AI,
I won't say all of AI, but much of it is
to build world models. And by that I
mean a system that can simulate the
future state of the world conditioned on
observations of the current state of the
world and also being able to simulate
forward the effects that that systems
actions will have on the future. So this
necessarily means you have the reality
that is out there. You have sensors that
collect information about that reality.
you perceive it with your world model
and ideally you're able to run a
simulation of okay well if I take this
action how will the world change in the
future and that is a very powerful and
generic framework for being able to
reason about why the world is the way it
is how you should act it obviously plays
into planning and perception
so one thing that I think is obvious is
that the world is perceived at least by
us and the world models in our heads in
a multimodal way so you know you have uh
visual modality that will tell you, for
example, that this roundabout that I
biked through many times on my way to
lab is very dangerous and chaotic when
people are running late to class and
panicking. Um, but you're not just
getting the visual information. You of
course also have the audio modality
which comes from a different sensor, a
microphone for a machine or ears for us,
and you get an audio stream. And often
when you encounter video or image data,
you could also have a text
representation. Someone might have
written a caption under their video
saying, "Whoa, this roundabout is
extremely chaotic and I'm going to try
to avoid it." My thesis or my assumption
is that the best world models are going
to be able to incorporate all of these
modalities and make decisions about what
to do based not just on one of them, but
all of them in a productive way. So when
you're running the world model in your
head where you're perceiving the data
from all these modalities, you might
have a question like what will happen if
I start walking forward into this
roundabout. And because you have the
combination of maybe someone warned you
ahead of time, you can hear what's going
on, you can see what's going on, you're
able to predict that you might get
crashed into by somebody on a bike who's
running late for class.
The task of that model is effectively
multimodal learning. You need to know
how to integrate these various
information streams which natively come
in many different formats and you need
to learn from them in a way that gives
you the best chance of making accurate
simulations of what's going to happen in
the world.
I want to make a distinction that I
think is important and will come up a
couple times in this talk about two
reasons you might care about combining
multimodal streams. One of them is the
idea that you could do multimodality as
translation. You could say there's
information in the visual domain.
There's information in the audio domain
and what I want to do is have a
representation of the world that merges
those things so that I've captured all
of the information about one modality in
the other modality.
The other thing that you might want to
do is disambiguation. So there could be
information that just is not available
in one modality. And so you kind of have
a blind spot both figuratively and
literally here where if you only had a
camera, you wouldn't know everything
about the state of the world. and you're
going to need to incorporate this other
uh modality to get a full picture of
what is happening in the world around
you. So I'll try to talk a little bit as
I'm giving examples in the literature
and in our work about whether I think
we're doing translation or
disambiguation.
Okay. So translation has um a very
familiar shape. It's about capturing all
of the information in one modality and
another modality. So when you're
building for example a text to image
system um what you want is for all of
the information in the prompt that
you're sending to the system to be
reflected in the image. You want to uh
basically push these things together so
that when I include a bit of information
in the text stream, I want it reflected
back to me in the image stream.
And when I talk about disambiguation,
what I mean is that you need to piece
together information that is only going
to be available in one modality or
another. So for example, let's say
you're approaching this building and you
see everyone sprinting out of it. Now
there's some ambiguity here. There are
actually many reasons why people could
be running out of the building. Now if
you combine that with your sense of
hearing, you might hear that there is a
fire alarm going off inside. And that
rapidly disambiguates which state of the
world you're in. that there's a fire and
everyone's running away from it. But you
could also have a second scenario where
you hear an announcement that there's
free boba for the first 10 students that
get to it and now everyone is sprinting
out of the building and your world model
should update. Right? If you want boba,
you need to turn around and go one
direction maybe to where the
announcement is saying to go. If there's
a fire, you know, you head to the
nearest evacuation point or whatever it
is we're all supposed to do if that
happens.
Okay, the next few slides will be kind
of a tour that I will acknowledge is
both brief and incomplete about how
people have tried to incorporate
multimodal streams um in the literature.
And I'm really going to go over five
things here. You don't have to memorize
them now. I'll go through them one by
one. But one thing that I want to call
out is when people talk about
multimodality or merging streams from
one modality and another. Um there's
often this nomenclature of whether
you're doing early fusion or late
fusion. And what people usually mean by
that is are you bringing the modalities
together kind of as soon as possible and
then running your processing forward
from there or do you process each
information stream separately and then
bring them together at the very end when
you actually need to make a decision
about the state of the world and your
actions in it. So I have to admit that
this framework doesn't help me think
about this space too much but I've tried
to map onto these five things where I
think they fall. And there's kind of a
range here from super early fusion to
what I would think of as late fusion and
everything in between. So we'll see if
you agree with me as I go through it.
Okay. The first thing I'm going to talk
about is learning joint embedding
spaces. So a model that many of you
might be familiar with is the clip
approach for combining the modalities of
image and text. Um the primary idea here
is to do contrastive learning where you
have two encoders, an image encoder.
Let's see if my mouse shows up. Um, you
have an image encoder that pushes images
down into an embedding. And you have a
text encoder that takes corresponding
captions and pushes those down into an
embedding. And the objective for the
model is to make the embeddings for
corresponding image and text pairs as
similar as possible while pushing away
the representations of mismatched pairs.
For example, the similarity between the
embedding for image two and caption one
should be as low as possible while
increasing the similarity between the
embedding for image one and text one.
And this is kind of explicitly trying to
learn a single joint representation
space where if you pick a point in that
space, there should be kind of an image
that corresponds to that point and also
a text sample that also corresponds to
that point. And that way you can kind of
translate between the text modality and
the image modality. You can see this
explicitly in the paper. Um on the right
of this figure, you can see that what
they're doing is taking an image,
figuring out what the embedding of that
image is with the image encoder, and
then searching over many possible text
inputs that will bring you as close as
possible to that point in the
representation space. So I would
consider this actually relatively late
fusion because you're learning the image
encoder pretty much separately from the
text encoder. Those don't interact until
there's pressure through the loss
function to make those embeddings as
similar as possible.
Um I would say kind of like I don't want
to call it the grown-up version of this
but an expanded version of this is the
image bind approach. And if people
aren't familiar with this, it is still a
contrastive learning objective between
modalities, but instead of just doing
images and captions, it uses images as
kind of an anchor and learns pair-wise
contrastive between images and text,
images and depth maps, images and audio.
And the underlying objective here is the
same that you want a single
representation space where it doesn't
matter which modality you came in
through. Once you know where you are,
you can kind of back out what all the
modalities should look like. And in fact
in this paper they do some interesting
uh demonstrations of that space by doing
things like embedding space arithmetic
or prompting with one modality and
seeing where you fall in that space on
other modalities.
Okay. The other option that um I have
done occasionally but I think is not
popular for technical reasons is super
super super early fusion where you can
just directly concatenate raw inputs. So
consider if you had for example a 3D RGB
color image and you also had a depth
image. What you could do is just staple
on the depth image as a fourth channel
and then train a connet or train your
vision transformer and pretend that you
had four channels all along. And that is
a totally valid way to incorporate
information from multiple modalities.
The reason that I think it is not super
popular is it requires that there's
something to concatenate on. So people
typically will first kind of project raw
inputs down to tokens and then
concatenate token streams which I'll
talk about in a second. But if you want
to jump really really really to the
front of that encoding stack, sometimes
you have, you know, your height and
width dimensions on images line up, you
can just concatenate directly.
Okay. The third option that you could do
is cross attention. So now we're getting
much more transformer specific. Um the
idea here is you have two token streams,
one from each modality. Um in the
example from the LU at all 2019 paper,
you have one token stream that comes
from images and then you also have a
second token stream that comes from
text. So those are your two modalities.
You can have as many self attention
layers as you want within each stream.
But then you can also have these cross
attention layers which are uh shown here
in the diagram where you're basically
giving each modality the chance to be
kind of the primary. The primary will
generate the keys or sorry the queries
in the attention operation and the
secondary stream will provide the keys
and values. And because that is an
asymmetric procedure uh you will often
see these cross attention layers uh
duplicated on either side of the
processing stream. So that you know in
one example the images get to provide
the queries and in the other side of it
the text stream gets to provide the
queries.
Uh I broke this out just because when I
was first implementing this it was
helpful to think about but if you look
at what is actually happening in an
attention layer right you have your
input X you will have a linear
projection to your queries Q your keys K
and your values V and then those go into
your scaled product attention operator.
Um and then you know linear projection
and dropout. All you're doing in a cross
attention layer is you're taking input
from another stream Y and you're using
that to generate the keys and values,
but everything else stays as is. This
gives you a chance to have the two
information streams mingle somewhere in
the middle of the network. So I would
call this like intermediate fusion
depending which layers you're doing it
in.
Okay. The fourth option which I alluded
to when I was talking about
concatenation is you can just slap
tokens onto a stream. Like I think one
thing that has really resonated with me
is as we move into using transformers in
more and more domains, the fact that
everything is just tokens all the way
down makes it really easy to add more
tokens to a sequence and they can come
from other modalities if you'd like. Um,
one way that this happens all the time,
but I think we don't really think of it
as multimodal learning is if you have,
for example, a vision transformer,
you might add on, uh, in this case,
you're prepending a class token that
really is like you could think of it as
text, I guess, because the class is
literally a text label. Um, but you have
an embedding for the text and that just
goes and participates in the stream of
tokens and participates in the self
attention operations. And there you go.
you've integrated a text label with your
image data.
Uh the other place you see this is
actually in the dolly one
implementation. So the way that this
worked is you have text tokens which are
captions for images. Um you also have
image tokens which in this case come
from learning a codebook with a discrete
VAE and you concatenate on the image
tokens after the text tokens and then at
inference time you can provide only the
text tokens and auto reggressively
predict what the image tokens should be.
So again you've solved the multimodality
problem by first boiling everything down
into token space and then once they're
tokens you know your decoder doesn't
need to know which ones are image and
which ones are text.
Um, and finally, something that we have
increasingly been using at Noetic is
this adaptive layer norm idea. So, I
really like this figure. This is from
the diffusion transformer paper. Um,
what I like about it is that they also
talk about two other things I've already
mentioned. The middle column there shows
how you might do this with cross
attention. I guess I should back up and
say in the diffusion transformer case,
the extra modality you're feeding in is
a conditioning token. You want to guide
the diffusion in a particular direction.
So you I don't know have some text
label. Um and you want that to interact
with the main transformer block that is
going to be doing the diffusion. Um so
you could do that with cross attention
which is shown here. You could do it
with what is called in this paper in
context conditioning. Um which is just
the concatenation approach. You can
actually see that here. Concatenate on
the sequence dimension as we just saw.
Um but the thing introduced in this
paper which is very parameter efficient
and cool that it works is you can take
that conditioning information and use
effectively a linear layer to push it
into small scalar parameters. So here
what they're doing is predicting an
alpha beta and a gamma. They actually
predict two triplets of alpha beta gamma
and use those in the layer norm
operation. So this is just kind of
another way as far as I understand to
push information from one modality and
have it steer or influence or guide what
is happening in the processing of the
primary sensory stream.
Um I have a little code snippet here
probably not worth lingering on but it's
just striking how straightforward this
approach is. But really all that's
happening is you have a single linear
layer in here hiding after a
nonlinearity and then you're using that
to determine the parameters for shifting
and scaling operations in layer norm.
And this turns out to be a very
effective way to get information about a
textbased conditioning label into the
image domain.
Okay, this is a pretty good place to
pause and see if anyone has any
questions before I move on.
Yeah. Yeah. Particularly when you're
talking about the cross attention,
can cross attention and neural norm can
one could be used as the other in the
layer norm as a linear
uh
reference to
yeah I understand correctly. Um, I think
you can and the thing that you run into
here that's both a blessing and a curse
is like you can do pretty much anything
like at some point if you think that
there's more useful processing to do
before you derive these layer norm shift
and scale parameters. This doesn't have
to be a linear layer. It can be an
arbitrarily complicated function. It
could be a cross attention layer that is
you know using the information from two
streams that way and then also doing a
layer norm. The question is is it
parameter efficient? Does it work
empirically and do you have a good
principled reason to do it? And I think
often that third thing is missing in a
lot of these approaches which is just
like yeah it seems to work so we're
going to roll with it. Thank you.
Yeah. Um can you speak in a complex
level maybe in a big conceptual level um
why in the cancer research space that
transform is important in the sense that
does it combine let's say image of a
patient or the let's say biopsy and
maybe the text description of it. So
what what makes a transformer so so
relevant for cancer research in a
different context? Yeah. So the question
is why why are transformers important
for cancer research? And I think the
answers could have basically two shapes.
One of them is if you format your data
and your task properly, I think
transformers are both simpler to scale
and empirically scale better than other
approaches. The second reason I would
say is not all data modalities are
amendable to other architectures. So
sometimes you do have image data and
I'll show examples of that in a second.
Sometimes you have data that looks a lot
more like text and so you want to use
the approaches that have been successful
in modeling text. And then the third
thing I would say is that specifically
for multimodal learning, it's extremely
helpful to be able to push everything
into token soup and bring it back
together however you want. So it turns
out that transformers are just a very
good substrate for combining kind of
arbitrarily creative ideas about how to
integrate various measurements. But in a
couple slides, I'll show exactly what
those measurements are and I'll walk
through architectures we're using to
learn from patient data.
Cool. Okay, I will go ahead and do that.
Okay, so uh as a reminder, this is kind
of my mental model for how things work
in the macroscopic world. And I think
the analogy in the microscopic world is
now we want to understand the world of
cancer biology. And the queries that we
want to pose to this world model are not
things like what happens if I walk into
a roundabout. They are things like uh
what will happen if I give this drug to
this patient? Will the tumor go away or
not? And you want effectively a
simulator that can help you answer those
questions. I will fill in the question
marks momentarily about what these
sensors are and what the data looks
like. But I want to put this up front as
like our goal is to take this world
modeling approach and to build a system
that we can use to simulate answers to
clinically relevant questions.
Okay, this is my like crash course in
cancer immunology. I was talking to a
card carrying immunologist this morning
and apologized for trying to boil down
their entire career into a few bullet
points. So please know that this is a
gross uh simplification. The basic idea
behind cancer amunotherapy is that we
know that in some cases your immune
system can detect and destroy cancers.
But tumors are sneaky and they evolve to
either hide from the immune system or to
actively suppress the immune system so
that the immune system can't do its job
and destroy the tumor.
The idea behind imunotherapy as a type
of treatment is you want to basically
get rid of those immune evasion
mechanisms or the immune suppression
mechanisms and help reactivate immune
cells to help them do their job. So you
already have the machinery in your body
to fight cancer. It's just losing that
fight and you want to find a way to tip
the scales so that the immune system can
start winning.
The way that we do that could have two
shapes and we're interested in both of
them at Noetic. One of them is you just
find new drugs that no one has thought
of before. Um, but the other thing that
I was interested to learn when I started
working in this space is actually
there's a lot of drugs that have
progressed in various clinical trials
and they fail because there's just a
mixed response. For some patients, they
work really well. For other patients,
they don't work at all. And we don't
have the right way of targeting the
right drug to the right patient. So for
both of these, the thing you would want
is again a world model that can help you
simulate the answer to the question
given what you know about the world of
this patient's biology, if I take this
action, does the tumor go away or not?
Okay, so here's the oversimplified
schematic again of you want something
that tells you given a patient's data um
you want to be able to simulate kind of
rapidly a bunch of different treatment
options and get a reasonable prediction
of whether they'll be effective or
ineffective.
So our approach to this is first we need
to deploy our sensors and collect a
bunch of data. This is a video of our
lab up in South San Francisco in action.
So what we do is we get uh human lung
tumor specimens and a few other tumors
from a few other organs. These numbers
are also a little bit outdated at this
point. Um but we source our tissue
blocks. We have a lab that processes
them. We punch out these cores from the
tissue that are about 1 millimeter in
diameter. So, they're very tiny, but
I'll show you in a second that there's
an unthinkable amount of data packaged
in that small 1 millm core. Uh, and then
we will basically put those through four
different data processing pipelines that
I'll show you in a second.
One of those pipelines um which is a
fairly common one to run on tissue
samples is we collect these H and E
images. H& has the benefit of being
relatively cheap and easy to acquire and
a lot of people have it. So, you know,
most hospitals and research centers are
sitting on a ton of H& there's a lot of
public h&
RGB image that you can work with. Um
technically it's like a twoch thing
because there's two elements at the same
but you can devolve them if you want.
It's not super relevant to the rest of
this talk. The other thing that we do is
um instead of just looking at the gross
morphology which is what you mostly get
out of this H& stain is we have a 16plex
protein amorlloresence panel. So that
means that we're able to detect
proteins, 16 different kinds of proteins
by designing fluorescent antibodies that
bind to them. And we can see the
composition of this tissue. So in this
pseudo color map, what I'm showing is
green are T- cells, which are part of
your immune system. Blue is B cells,
which is another part of your immune
system. And then the red blob in the
middle is a tumor. So we're able to go
ask what's actually in this sample. Um,
this is kind of like an RGB image but
with 16 channels instead of three
channels.
The other thing to call out here is
you'll notice that the white box has
moved with us. So these are spatially
aligned samples. And if you remember
what I was saying about RGB and depth,
you might already be thinking, oh well,
you could just staple these together in
the channel dimension and do multimodal
learning that way.
One of the cooler kinds of data that we
have is spatial transcrytoics. So on
again these exact same samples, you'll
see the white boxes moving with us
again. Uh we are able to detect in a
thousand plex panel. So we're looking
for a thousand different genes worth of
RNA transcripts. And those transcripts
are spatially localized. So we don't
have to boil down the sample into soup
before feeding it in and asking which
RNA is in the sample. we get an XY
coordinate and well it's really like an
XY by gene tupil that tells us this gene
has RNA expressed at this location and
you'll get anywhere between a few
thousand to a few million such
transcripts in just one millimeter of
data which I'll try to show in a second
if it doesn't crash my computer um this
data is very rich it's also very
complicated it's also very expensive so
uh collecting this data is the hardest
and it's the that the fewest people
have. In fact, on one of the previous
slides, I had mentioned that we at
Noetic estimate that we have well over
1% and probably over 2% of like the
world's spatial transcripttoics data
using this platform which is called
Cosmix.
Okay. And the last thing we do is uh
genetic sequencing. We do whole exom
sequencing of the patient's data. So we
know if they have genetic mutations that
could be relevant to understanding their
tumor biology.
Okay. So this is the data that lives out
there and the question is how are we
going to learn from it. Um before we do
that I just want to talk a little bit
more about the spatial transcripttoics
data because it's so cool. Um so these
are what the raw transcripts look like
in 3D. This is we do actually detect
them in XY and Z but the Z plane is four
micrometers four microns. So it's very
very thin. It's effectively just XY. And
the colors here are different genes. Um,
I'm going to try to run a live demo of
just what this raw data looks like
because it's a lot of fun to play around
with. But there's an overwhelming amount
of data jammed into this 1 millm
diameter chunk of tissue.
I promise this computer is not
underpowered. It's just loading 11
million points. So this is what it looks
like at the micro level. You know, you
have this incredibly rich tissue and we
are actually showing here um one of the
first whole transcriptto runs we've been
able to do. So instead of detecting a
thousand gene panel, we're able to try
to detect over 18,000 genes. And you
know, we ran out of colors after the
first 20 or so, but you'll have to take
my word for it that So, what the colors
do not here? The colors are different
genes.
Yeah.
Okay. I will spare my computer from
trying to render that for too long. Um,
here's another example from our thousand
plex panel just to give you another
sense of the kind of data that we work
with. So, at the local scale, now we're
talking about tens of microns. you have
these highly localized reads of what RNA
is being transcribed where in the cell.
And I'll try to render the labels, but
again, the the plotting software
struggles a bit with it.
Okay, that's kind of an aside. I just
think those data are so cool that I I
like showing it whenever I have the
chance. Okay, so let me talk about how
we're trying to model this data and the
kinds of world models that we're trying
to construct. So we have thousands at
this point over 10,000 uh cores from
different patients. Each of those cores
is one of those 1 millimeter diameter
circles. In each core there will be
thousands of cells. And we can assign
these transcripts to cells with a
segmentation algorithm to say in a given
cell you can count up you know how often
do you get a read of this gene CD3E
within the borders of a cell. And so the
data you get is effectively tabular.
It's also very very sparse. most cells
don't express most genes. Um, and we're
going to try to model this so that we
can simulate things and ask, well, does
this tilt the tumor immune micro
environment in a more or less favorable
direction?
Our general approach is to use masked
autoenccoders. Um, this ends up being a
transformer backbone. The thing worth
calling out is that it's not auto
reggressive transformer processing. So,
there's no real sequence to the genes to
care about. Um, it's more like masked
language modeling where what we'll do is
take the input, we'll mask out some of
the tokens and we predict the tokens we
mask out. I'll show on the next slide
what that actually looks like
operationally.
So if this is your input, imagine this
has a thousand rows, soon 18,000 rows.
Um, you have every gene and how often it
was detected in a single cell. So the
input is one cell here.
uh we have a tokenization process that
assigns a token to each combination of
gene identity and the expression level.
So you're encoding both how much of that
thing you have and also what the
identity of it is. And then we do
partial masking. Um in our work we tend
to do pretty aggressive masking. So the
number you should have in your head is
like north of 90% of the tokens are
removed and replaced with a learned mask
token. So almost everything is removed
from the sample. And the job of the
model is to predict the things we
removed. This is intentionally a very
hard task. We want it to be basically as
difficult as possible while still
learning the biology. Because if you are
able to do this, what it means is that
you're able to use a very small amount
of context to infer, okay, well, I see I
have a lot of CD3. I don't get to see
how much CD8 I have because that got
masked out in the masking process. So, I
have to guess based on my knowledge of
biology from learning from this data
set. Is it likely that I express CD8,
which would make me a cytotoxic or a
killer T- cell, if I express CD3, which
is kind of a more generic marker for T-
cells that may or may not be killer T-
cells.
At inference time, what you can do with
this kind of model is provide a couple
of things that are not masked, like two
tokens worth of information, and then
staple on a bunch of mask tokens, you
know, the other 998 genes in this panel.
And then you can predict everything
that's masked out. So you can say given
that you're conditioned on knowing
you're a T- cell and you're not a tumor,
what else do you think is happening? And
you know, if you've learned from this
huge data set, you might think maybe the
best you can do is say, well, okay, what
does the average T- cell look like?
Because all I've told you is you have
this T- cell marker CD3E, and you're
definitely not a tumor cell because
you're expressing none of this keratin
marker.
I don't want to say that this model is
boring. There's a lot of interesting
stuff you can do with it, but it's
distinctly not multimodal. And I
promised you multimodality. So, I'm
going to keep going um with this
background in mind and tell you about
one kind of model that we have gotten a
lot of leverage out of which is to say
this task is very hard and there's a lot
of ambiguity. And if you remember, I was
talking about multimodality as a way to
resolve ambiguity in predictions. So one
thing that we do is we will take the
local spatial neighborhood of a cell,
the one we're trying to make predictions
about. We'll ask who are your eight
nearest neighbors and we will force the
information about what those eight
nearest neighbors are expressing through
a bottleneck. Um that bottleneck is just
another transformer. But it is required
to boil down basically all of that rich
spatial context about what's happening
in the local environment down into one
token. And then we use this adaptive
layer norm approach or we've tried the,
you know, append tokens thing. We've
tried cross attention. They all seem to
work. Some are just more efficient than
others. Um, and that feeds in as an
additional input to what we refer to as
the backbone. So now if you have a
prompt in your training that's
ambiguous, you have a little bit of help
because you might say, well, I don't
know if I'm a killer T- cell or not, but
seven of my neighbors are killer T-
cells. Maybe I'm also a killer T- cell
and that should help you do a little bit
better. And the thing that I should have
added here and forgot is showing that if
you're just monitoring like the training
loss of the backbone, it really likes
having the spatial context. It helps
quite a lot in lowering that loss curve.
Um once you have a model like that, you
can do very large scale inference with
it. So what we will do is take a real
patient sample. We'll pick a location in
that sample, look up the eight nearest
neighbors, and then we will ask the
model to do inference with a specified
prompt. In this case, I'm telling it,
you are a killer T- cell. You express
these markers for regular T- cells and
for cytotoxicity. Um, and I'm asking it
to predict the other 990 plus genes
conditioned on the spatial context. And
on the right, I'm going to slowly build
up at each position here what the model
thinks is happening for one such gene,
IL7R.
And you will already get a sense once
this starts to speed up of how many
simulations we're doing here. Um, as of
last week, I think we had run on the
order of six billion virtual cell
simulations like this. So we are able to
ask basically arbitrary queries about
what is happening in patient tissue by
saying hypothetically if this cell type
were in this location in the patient
tissue what do I think it's doing and to
close the loop in a second I'll tell you
about how you can do counterfactual
simulations that will help you think
about potential drugs but for now just
appreciating that once you have this
additional input stream to the model you
can pull out a lot of richness about
what it's learned about how spatial
context affects what is happening at the
single cell level.
Um, we built a little web UI that lets
you explore some of this data. I won't
spend too long in it, but it lets you
kind of pick a cell type, fly around a
real patient sample, see what the cell
identities of those nearest neighbors
is, and then see how the model's
prediction of different genes changes as
you move around the space. So, I could
spend all day kind of mucking around in
this, but it's public. Feel free to poke
around. Let us know if you find anything
interesting that we should turn into a
drug.
Yeah, the link is teleporter.ai.
We think of it as like teleporting cells
around in patient data. May I ask a
question? Sure. So masking seems like a
really interesting approach and strategy
that is that narrow it down to that one
particular pathway is why 90% masking so
you can actually like trace like every
single one. Is that the core function of
masking? I think it buys us two things.
The first is that at training time it
makes the task very very hard. So that
the only way you could answer it is by
learning about fundamental patient
biology. If you provided you know go to
the other extreme you provide 999 genes
you only need to predict one. You will
probably identify that oh I can usually
predict this gene by the combination of
these other two. The other thing that it
helps us do is I'll show this in a
second, but if you train with a very
high masking ratio at inference time,
you can bump the masking ratio to 100%.
And the model doesn't freak out. It's
like, oh yeah, I'm used to seeing almost
nothing. And then you can do interesting
things like, well, what if I give you no
information about that center cell and
you only get to use the local spatial
context, which is a mode we actually
operate in quite often. Yeah.
Okay. Um this is another kind of thing
we would do with these virtual cells. So
the thing that I showed on this slide
is the surrounding context is real data.
We go to a real location in a real
patient's tissue, look at the nearest
cells, feed that expression in, but the
model doesn't know what's real data and
what isn't. So you can go create a
synthetic neighborhood and say, "Okay,
I'm gonna start from the real data and
I'm going to simulate the effect of a
drug by knocking down a particular
target I'm interested in and say the
neighborhood is basically the same
except that I've removed a target of
interest. I've done a synthetic knockout
in the surrounding context and I want to
know when I do that knockout, do I make
this hypothetical center T- cell more or
less likely to be in tumor killing
mode?" And that's what this animation
shows.
The gene identities are redacted but the
y-axis is the increase in the production
or predicted production of granzyme K
which is part of the T- cell cytotoxic
arsenal for attacking tumors. And we can
do these simulations for each of these
10,000 plus patient samples for each of
the thousand genes in the panel. And you
start to see how with the right scale,
you can very quickly search over
hypotheses for what's happening in the
patient tissue.
Yeah.
[Applause]
simulation
of that 8,000,000.
Yeah, good question. So the question is,
is 8,000 patients worth of data enough
or do you need more?
Yeah, could you augment with synthetic
data? I think the answer is maybe. Um, I
would say if you are staying within a
single indication, like we often think
about non small cell lung cancer, it's
possible 8,000 patients covers the
diversity of different patient biology
or different modes that the tumor might
be using to escape the immune system.
Uh, I think there are things you could
learn from expanding to more
indications, different cancer types in
different organs that could be
generalizable even back to non small
cell lung cancer. And so we are actively
collecting right now more data and more
indications and more organs to make sure
we're not ignoring a pocket of how the
tumors might be learning to evade the
immune system. What can we generate? um
generatively something like
who they are.
Yeah. Um I think there probably are ways
to generate some data. I'm not sure
learning from it directly would help.
Like if you're using a model that has
trained on real data, I'm not sure if
it's going to do better when it's
generating its own synthetic data. But
there are ways you can use your own
knowledge about the biological system to
produce things like these synthetic
neighborhoods where you're saying, I'm
going to go make a targeted change and
then run inference and see what the
model thinks will happen when I do a
very specific perturbation in the data.
Thanks. Okay.
Um, the thing about this data that I
mentioned earlier is it's expensive and
it's rare and it's hard to collect. I
also mentioned that this H& data is
image based. It's pretty cheap. It's
fairly ubiquitous. A lot of people have
it. Um, and one thing that we've been
doing increasingly is seeing if we can
use our model, which we call octo in
part informally because it kind of looks
like an octopus with a bunch of arms
that sample different modalities to just
translate from one to the other. So now
we're back to multimodality as
translation.
The way that you do this is take this
model that we're now familiar with. And
now this diagram should look very
familiar except instead of gene
expression data from the local
neighborhood, we're passing in the
surrounding h& morphology of what is
happening local to that cell in the
patient's tissue. You know, we can only
do this because the samples are
spatially aligned as precisely as they
are. And now the model gets to use this
additional input as help. It's saying
I'm facing ambiguity. What can I do? Oh,
well, I can look at the morphology of
the cells around me and try to
understand if that makes me, for
example, a cytotoxic T- cell or not.
Once you've trained this model, um, you
can then go to full masking. Just say,
okay, I'm going to effectively ablate
the primary input and just pass in a
thousand mask tokens. And now the only
thing the model can do is use the local
spatial context to say, well, I don't
know anything about what the expression
should be. I have to use this local
context to try to make a prediction of
what the gene expression of a
hypothetical cell at the center of that
spatial window is doing. And because
we've trained it at a very high masking
ratio, you know, the model is not
totally clueless about this. And we are
curious if it makes reasonable
predictions. So what we will do at
inference time is take one of these H&
images which again are fairly easy to
acquire
pick a spatial window and run the model
forward in inference mode and say okay
I'm not going to tell you anything about
the expression of the cell in this case
because I don't have it like we don't
know what's going on there. It could be
someone sent me this H& image and they
never ran spatial transcrytoics.
The model will make a prediction about
what the expression of all thousand
genes in our panel is at the center of
that spatial window. And here it's
giving me some value for keratin 19
which is a tumor marker. And you can
just run this as many times as you want.
So in practice we'll run this a thousand
times. Yeah. Uh one question online is
are you only predicting the
transcrytoics of non-cancer cells?
Uh no, we are predicting the
transcripttoics for every cell including
immune cells, tumor cells, fibroblasts,
normal cells, whatever's in the data.
Yeah.
So if you run this process a few
thousand times, you get basically a
prediction heat map of where is it
likely that there's a tumor because
you're asking the model to predict, you
know, one of the thousand things it's
predicting at each of these locations is
a tumor marker. So here's the heat map
you get and then this is now going back
and for this core we actually do have
cell typing from transcrytoics data and
the red dots are where there's actually
tumor and you can see that the model is
predicting where there's tumor markers
pretty effectively. Um I won't pretend
this is perfect. There are definitely
examples where it doesn't do a great
job. So here's another sample um that
has a ton of B cells. That's the blue in
this diagram. And it does, you know, it
mostly predicts that there isn't a lot
of tumor marker, which is mostly
accurate. There isn't a lot of tumor in
this sample, but it's still missing the
few areas where there is. But for other
markers, even within the same sample,
it's doing a very good job of predicting
from just this morphology image what the
expression of various genes is. And you
know, there's imagine 997 more columns
of this diagram and then 10,000 more
slides with other samples. And that's
how we're evaluating the ability of this
model to do that translation from the
images to the rich spatial
transcrytoics.
So essentially this is what you call
mask where the taken images are and so
you size
right we're leveraging the fact that we
have the paired data in house. So we can
teach the model to do that translation
and then at inference time it's the
model is happy if you mask everything
out it'll just use
the other one
that
yeah yeah totally so the thing I'm going
to show on the next slide is actually
I've been playing with ideas for you
know what would an interface look like
for you have h& data you don't have the
ability to generate space facial
transcrytoics.
You can imagine an interface where
someone uploads their own H& you predict
a full thousand dimensional panel of
what the expression is of a bunch of
different genes at every location. Um,
we know what different gene programs
look like and you can actually use a
large language model to find for you,
you know, common areas where things are
popping out and descriptions of what's
happening. So you get a fully endto-end
automated, you upload a sample, we
predict what the gene expression would
be in that sample and then you can go
explore the data, talk with an LLM,
explore whatever you want, ask questions
about it, and eventually run simulations
in browser.
Okay, so basically what we have built
here is a system that attempts to
translate relatively easy to acquire
data into rich patient representations.
Um, this is kind of a pretty PCA
projection of the first few principal
components of the thousand-dimensional
signal at each location. Um, but what we
will actually do with that is then each
dot in the diagram to the right is one
sample from one patient and we're
embedding it in a two-dimensional space.
In this case, I think we're using PEN.
And uh we're putting patient samples
together if their predicted gene
expression profiles are similar. And
what I'm labeling by here is actually
the patient genetics. So the model has
no idea about whether a patient has a
genetic mutation in cancer driver uh
mutations. But it turns out that because
the model has learned patient biology,
when you cluster together predictions
from different patients, the ones that
have common genetic mutations end up
clustering in this space. And so you can
recover patient biology starting again
just from this H& image because we have
trained this model on a bunch of paired
data that has h& spatial transcrytoics.
Interesting classification.
Yeah, that we spend a lot of time asking
what the structure of the space is
telling us about the data. Um, I'm just
going to give a quick tour of another
kind of model that will look familiar
because it's using similar masked
autoenccoding. Um, this is using that
protein data. So, in this example, the
model is not predicting gene expression.
It's predicting protein images and we're
feeding in the other three modalities as
extra tokens. So, this is now not the
adaptive layer norm thing I mentioned.
It's just stapling on bonus tokens into
the token stream and letting them
interact with the primary token stream
which comes from these 16 channel
protein images.
So can you show me is the data that you
are able to create? We also collect we
collect all of these all of it. Okay.
Yeah. Yeah. So into this model if I'm
creating new data set given the earlier
process can that become another input
that's it? Yeah. So you could only
collect h& impute or predict what the
spatial transfer filaments would have
looked like if you collected it feed
that in the question is if that helps
you learn anything and I don't have an
answer to that we're exploring it but
it's an interesting idea. Yeah.
Okay. So what we do in this space is ask
questions like well how do we want to
simulate the effect of a drug? you know,
the effect of a drug simulated might
look like modifying the spatial
transcrytoics data where you say this
drug suppresses um this protein. And so
you could say that the way that would
look in the spatial transcrytoics data
is suppressing the reads of one gene or
a combination of genes. And you're going
to run this counterfactual a what if of
well what if I had applied that drug
change the spatial transcripttoics data
in this way and run that forward to a
prediction of saying well how does that
change the output of the model trying to
predict the protein image on the other
side and I have a small animation
showing how that might happen. So this
is a sample from a patient. The yellow
here are immune cells the pink is tumor.
Now you can run two whatifs.
In one what if simulation you're
cranking up the expression of this gene
whose identity is redacted here. And in
the other one you're suppressing the
activity of that gene. So now I'm back
to creating synthetic data on my
multimodal input arms. And I'm going to
now run both of those parallel universes
forward. And what I'm looking for is the
readout is one of these 16 channels
that's being predicted. In this case,
I'm looking for a tumor immunogenicity
marker where higher would indicate more
favorable. And you can see that the
simulation is telling us, yeah, you
should crank up the expression of gene
one if you can because it leads to a
more favorable outcome on the other
side. So one way that we often are using
multimodal models is to say we want this
backbone that makes predictions to tell
us what would change if we could impart
a delta or a modification or a
perturbation on another one of the input
streams.
Does it tell you how perform?
Well, if you have a if you're able to
express your hypothesis for what a drug
should do in the input space of the
model and you have a readout on the
other side of what is good or bad, then
yeah, you could compare multiple
different ideas and see which one looks
like it'd be most effective.
Okay. Um I showed like a relatively
small fraction of the research that
we're doing here. Um but in general,
we're very open about sharing the
science we're doing. So, we have three
blog posts up. You can get to them at
noetic.ai/ressearch.
Um, this first one is about the protein
image based models that I just showed.
There's more detail on how we're
generating data in lab. And then some of
this new spatial transcrytoic stuff is
in a more recent post.
Okay, I just have a couple of more
slides and then it looks like we'll have
a bit of time for further questions. Um,
one thing that we're moving toward
doing, if you'll excuse kind of the
chaotic animation here, is instead of
trying to assign these RNA detections to
cells, we're just going straight to the
raw data and seeing what we can do with
that point cloud of 10 million points
that my computer choked on earlier. Um,
and so we're training models that are
able to look at the local spatial
context in this raw point cloud of RNA
transcripts and predict what is going to
happen at many points spatially in the
sample. So we're breaking free of the
need to think about cells as the atomic
unit of simulating the biology and going
basically as close to the raw data as we
can get. So this trajectory, you know,
in biology a cell would not drive
through a sample like this, but for a
visualization, I'm showing at each
position here, we're running one
inference step. So I ran this model a
few thousand times, moving this
hypothetical cell a few microns at a
time and then simulating what the
readout would be of saying, okay, well,
when you're surrounded by this cloud of
transcripts, you're probably also seeing
this cloud near you and this other cloud
over there. And so this is now the kind
of simulation engine where basically any
hypothesis you have about you know what
a drug might be doing or what's
happening in patient biology if this
model has really learned about the world
of the patient's biology you should be
able to get a reasonable simulation out
on the other side.
So in summary uh oh I had one more slide
I noticed last week was on the biology
of a large language model which is a
paper I really like. So I have a tongue
and cheek slide on the biology of a
large multimodal model for biology which
is uh just a little teaser. I don't have
a kind of time but we've been doing some
interpretability research on these
models to try to understand what it is
they have learned about um the patient
biology. So we've used things like
sparse autoenccoders to pull out
consistent beans that keep popping out
in the data and have used those to build
interfaces for biologists at the company
to basically do things like automatic
semantic segmentation with text labels
from identifying persistent concepts
that keep appearing in the data set. So
again this is starting from just the a.
So you upload H& and you get back
semantic segmentation with the different
parts of the sample and what's happening
in each of those.
Okay. Um this is basically my last slide
which is just saying I hope one thing
I've communicated today is that this is
just a big playground. There's a ton of
data. There's a ton of ways you can try
to combine that data. And especially in
biology, you have data spanning many
spatial scales, many levels of
abstraction and also many modalities. So
we talked today about really three of
them. The H& imaging, the
amunofllororesence and RNA sequencing.
There's more to be done in looking at
the patient genotyping. There's
imuninohistochemistry.
The field of OMIX keeps getting bigger
and bigger. And so the question that I
think we have to solve and that I don't
think has a concrete answer yet is what
do you do with all of this? What how do
you build a world model that
incorporates all of this information?
And how do you craft your training
tasks, your information bottlenecks, and
your fusion points so that you're forced
in a model to really learn real patient
biology that is specific to each
patient. And I won't pretend to have
that answer today. We don't know. We're
trying a bunch of stuff and kind of
throwing a lot of ideas at the wall and
then having a lot of fun playing with
it. But I just want to leave people with
the idea that there's just a ton of
things to try here and I think it's
going to be a very exciting few years
ahead. So um with that I'll now fill in
the picture. This is our idea for
building a world model for tumor biology
and I'll save the rest of the time for
questions.
[Applause]
there's a lot of uh you know there's
HIPPA there uh there's a lot of privacy
protection laws that prevent um let's
say for like researchers like you to
probably have access to real data. So my
question is how uh let's say if data is
localized at each hospital how do you
see the future of research in this area
can leverage the vast data set in that
is siloed in different hospitals so that
the this can event so speak to a place
that can be diffused into a healthcare
space. Yeah. Yeah. That's a a very
important question. I think there are a
few different answers. One of them is
open sourcing of methods that you could
say, you know, we aren't going to ask
you to send us your confidential data,
but we're going to tell you how you can
run it yourself. Um, there's probably
also ways that I'm not familiar with to
just secure uh endpoint basically and
say we're going to as a service process
this data for you and we'll be compliant
with the privacy regulations about how
to get the data from your hospital to
the servers and back. It's very much not
my area of expertise, so I don't know
exactly what that looks like, but I
imagine someone is thinking very hard
about it. Um, and I think the third
thing is partnership that you can always
have, you know, a hospital or research
institution say, "We want access to a
bunch of these models. we're going to go
into a formal partnership where we have
access to the compute and the models
that you've trained and we're going to
work together to run these samples so
that it isn't just kind of an arbitrary
like yeah email us your H& data and
we'll process it. Yeah,
amazing. Uh I just can't wait to see if
it can be expanded to larger data set
than just 8,000 patients. Um my other
question is I know cells and molecules
and protein there are so many models
beginning to happen. Are we able to
leverage a lot of the the alpha 4 models
that already exist in the protein layer
data set and also exoomes in fact the
two new things which are getting to be
very interesting is biollectrics
you know which is like beginning to be
another holy grail not just cells. uh is
there any way to kind of also capture
that data set in you know early
experimentation out of the four but add
like two other layers
uh and exoomes particularly with
communication channel that can add value
yeah I think that's a great question one
thing I've come to believe is that most
forms of data can be jammed into these
frameworks
fairly easily and the question is
empirically does that help with anything
or not and I don't know but I think you
know to be totally candid we're at a
place in research where we can try a lot
of stuff very quickly and see what helps
us make better predictions. In some
cases, I think what we're doing is
probably upstream of models like
alphafold where you know once we have
run our simulations and said well okay
our world model is telling us if you
could only make reality look like this
then this patient would respond to
treatment then we might still have a
challenge of okay well what is the
actual pharmacological path by which we
get there and then you might need to
engage with something at the molecular
level. So um yeah, I think it's possible
that one of the big challenges that I'm
thinking about is indeed how do you
integrate across these spatial scales
and we've tried some stuff but we have
not spanned this entire uh range yet in
a single model. So is your approach
right now research to start with patient
data first or just to a broad predictive
model then you know I can figure out
later who the patient is you know
because there's so much of the early
prediction that's happening where you're
not a patient yet right you know there
are no markers there's no tumor yet but
you're able to predict yeah long shot
yeah right now we are working from
patient data and one limitation of that
data set which I think is what you're
pointing out is that healthy people
don't get parts of their bodies removed
and sent to hospitals or to you know
research. So really the thing we would
want in a world model is evidence of
well what does it look like when
everything's working when there's no
tumor when the immune system has
identified a threat and eliminated it
and we just don't know because what
we're getting are these snapshots of a
battlefield and if we're lucky we will
see a snapshot and then find out that
that patient received some treatment and
responded well to it. But we're missing
probably the vast majority of the system
operating in kind of normal operational
mode. And I don't see an immediate way
out of that challenge other than
acknowledging it and recognizing that
you know what we're trying to do is
learn as much as we can about the
snapshots we get of disease state and
learn from that as a starting point.
Broad Institute has some really
interesting projects where they just
taken like dead tumor specimens and
they're just doing a bunch of
computation modeling. It'll be really
cool to see, you know, if that can
integrate into this.
Yeah. Our attitude is very much like as
much data as we can get, we're going to
throw it at this thing. So, very cool.
Thank you. Thank you.
Any other questions? Oops.
So, is Noetic just a model company? Do
you outsource the drug discovery to
other people and just let them use your
service as a platform or how does it
work? No, we are effectively as full
stack as it gets. We generate our data
in house. We do the machine learning
inhouse and then we have biologists and
immunologists in house. And I didn't
talk about this at all, but we have an
invivo platform with mice where you can
actually go test hypothesis about saying
here's a mouse model for this patient
population. We think that this drug will
be effective. Let's go test it. So we
right now actually do not provide any of
these you know even if you wanted to pay
me today to go use one of these I don't
have an API endpoint for you but we are
using these internally to do drug
discovery and basic discovery every day.
So the model is is like a lower latency
version and then the mouse is just to so
you you do most of your testing with the
with the model I assume and then the
mouse is just if you after you do the
initial filtering with the AI model or
how does that work? Yeah. So the the
model can tell you two things. In the
best case, it tells you, hey, you should
go try this drug in mice. And then, you
know, we don't pretend that this model
is going to understand all of the
complex biology that happens when you
administer a drug. So you still need to
go to that invivo test case and say, is
this actually working to get rid of
tumor? The other thing the models tell
us is maybe there's already drug people
have tried, but they're trying it in the
wrong population. like they're enrolling
too broad of a clinical trial because
they don't know that actually this small
sliver of the patient space is the one
that's going to respond well to your
drug. And so we are using the model in
that capacity to give us ideas for
things to try in our invivo platform or
to reexamine clinical data and see if we
can understand why clinical trials have
failed where other people are kind of
shrugging and going well I don't know
like 10 people were totally cured but
the other 190 weren't and we don't know
why. That makes sense. And so is the
endgame to completely replace clinical
trials or
I I don't know. I mean maybe in many
many years. I think ultimately you know
safety and efficacy proven out in humans
will need to happen at some point. If
anything I would assume that the earlier
part of that funnel is going to be
increasingly done synthetically that
maybe we say you know you can in some
cases skip a mouse model if you have a
very clear mechanism of action and you
want to go straight to checking for
safety and efficacy.
Thanks. Yeah, thank you.
[Music]
Scenarios of simulations to test with
many different combinations. I'm
wondering how you narrow it down to like
prioritize like which one to test first.
Yeah, that's a fantastic question. So I
think of what we're doing is like let's
say you had a really good world model, a
simulator of the world. Even in the
macroscopic case, you still need an
agent to tell you what is worth
simulating. You can't just try things at
random. And I think there's two
promising things here. One of them is
you still have subject matter experts
that say, "Oh, great. You've given me a
perfect simulator of patient biology. I
know the first 30 things I'm going to
try because I'm familiar with the things
that have been considered in this space.
We have hypotheses for how the tumor is
evading the immune system and we want to
go see if we can disrupt those." The
other thing that I
don't know how much weight I want to put
behind right now, but is would be a
little foolish to dismiss is that we
have these LLMs now that are trained on
basically the entirety of scientific
literature know about a bunch of studies
and if they have access to effectively
tool use and say okay uh what
experiments do you want to run and start
thinking about you know virtual
scientists or AI scientist agents that
are trying to decide this is the next
experiment I would And maybe at some
point you close the loop and you say,
"Great, we're going to go run that
experiment and we'll be right back to
you tomorrow. Then tell me the next
thing to try." But either way, you need
somebody who's familiar with the domain,
whether that's an LLM or a scientist to
make the decisions about how to use the
simulator.
Got it. Thanks. Yeah. Thank you.
Yeah. Um, so I know your grand vision is
to cure cancer. Do you have some
thoughts on cancer prevention
like probably vaccines or stuff like
that? Yeah. Um that is a good question.
I'm not sure I have a fantastic answer
about you know how are we thinking about
cancer prevention. It relates to this
problem of we don't have healthy data to
look at. And if there isn't an indicator
right now in the clinic of yeah, like
you look healthy today, but we're still
going to go biopsy this and send it off
and fit you into this framework, then I
think you're going to be limited in what
you can do about simulating the patient
biology of patients that right now are
totally asymptomatic. I could imagine
that changing. I mean, it's possible
that data acquisition is going to be
broad enough and cheap enough that it is
just routine to have a little bit of H&
taken and maybe there is information
kind of in the latent space of this
model that says, hm, yeah, this looks
like it's over in this part of the
patient distribution. Maybe we keep an
eye on this patient over the next few
years.
Same question. Great. Well, I have a
follow question. Um, Google scientist
and all this stuff. Yesterday, Microsoft
released a co-pilot or semi-autopilot
for science discovery to I'm very
curious how we can run a billion
experiments autonomously. Maybe um
modeling instead of modeling what
scenario maybe model a person right as
an agent and figure out what drugs could
potentially um you know cure it.
context, we just lost someone like two
weeks ago to cancer. So, this is a very
big thing for me. How do we prevent or
cure in the intermediate um cancer? So,
that's the way I'm thinking about where
agents and signs um intersect. Right.
Yeah. I have a few thoughts here. I'm
not sure how coherent they are. One of
them is um I am not sure yet that speed
and scale is the bottleneck on running
these simulations. I have not also seen
an example yet of an agent come up with
a really brilliant experiment that our
scientists didn't write down in like the
first four minutes of thinking about how
to use this thing. That doesn't mean I'm
not optimistic about it. I think these
systems are going to get better and if
anything I have been wrong every time on
saying like yeah that's 5 years away and
then 5 months later it turns out that we
can do it. So I would like to remain
optimistic that we're going to be able
to frame these problems, integrate
things like tool use in a way that does
allow agents to go run a bunch of
experiments and then you know for us we
probably still go test those out in mice
and then think about them in that
capacity. But yeah, it's a very
interesting direction to think about.
Yeah, give another hand to Mishad for
the very interesting talk.
Yeah. So you'll notice this talk was um
sort of different from a lot of um the
more recent talks or work just focusing
more on LLMs. But I think this is a very
important um space um and an area
application area where machine learning
and AI can make a lot of impact and save
the world um change the world positively
impact the world and save lives. Um so
we should definitely um encourage more
work um for machine learning and AI for
this um area of cancer research and
healthcare in general.