Welcome back to CS231 lecture 11. Today
we're going to talk about large scale
distributed training. Um and this is a
pretty exciting topic because this is
basically how all neural networks get
trained in practice today. When you look
at large models from from startups, from
industries, even academia um really
large scale is kind of the new norm in
deep learning nowadays. Um and that's
actually something that's changed quite
a lot in the last 10 years since we
started this class. Um 10 years ago it
was really well it was actually pretty
common to train all models basically on
one GPU one device um and it was fairly
uncommon to train on multiple devices
but as we'll see nowadays the new norm
is to train models on tens hundreds
thousands even tens of thousands of
devices concurrently so we need to
develop new algorithms and new ways of
thinking in order to do that.
So, as a and and then as a as a bit of
running example through today's lecture,
we're going to be talking a lot about
Llama 3 405B. Um, not because this is
the best model or the most interesting
model, but because this is a model that
this is a fairly close to
state-of-the-art model that actually
shares a lot of the implementation
details of how it was trained, the model
architecture, everything like that. Um,
there's a lot of really amazing powerful
models that have been trained in the
last couple of years from Google, from
OpenAI, from Anthropic, from others, but
basically they don't share any details
whatsoever about their models anymore.
Um there's a very famous quote that just
sort of marked a sea change in the
industry to me that was in the GPT4
paper um back in 2023. So when they
released the GPT4 model they said um
given both the competitive landscape and
the safety implications of large scale
models like GPT4 this report meaning the
paper they wrote about GPT4 contains no
further details about the architecture
including model size hardware training
compute data set construction training
method or similar and that's basically
the new that's basically been the
state-of-the-art for um large scale
models the last 3 years since this since
GPT4 they're not they don't tell you
anything about anything they'll tell you
nothing about the model you'll be lucky
if they'll tell it's a transformer. They
might tell you that much. Um, so Llama 3
is sort of notable not because it's the
best model out there, but because it's
one of the most open models out there.
So this is a large language model that
was trained by Meta um and released open
source about a year ago in April 2024.
And unlike OpenAI, the paper actually
does share a lot of the details about
the the model training, not too much
about the data set, a lot about the
system infrastructure that was used to
train it. Um, so this is something that
we and this gives us a sort of a peak
into how large scale LLMs are actually
trained these days. Um, and by the way,
there is a new Llama 4 model that just
came out from Meta uh, last month, April
2025. Um, so there are slightly better
models out there in open source already.
Um, but there's no paper on Llama 4 yet.
So I'm excited to read that one
hopefully when it comes out in a couple
months and see um, what can we learn
from the new generation of llama
training. But as just as a as a running
example through today's lecture, we'll
be pointing at a lot of examples from
the llama 3 405b model um for this
reason.
Okay. So there's basically two things
that I want to talk about today. Um one
is a bit about GPU hardware and the
other is how to train on lots of GPUs.
So I want to give you a sense both of
what actually is the hardware that these
things execute on as well as the
algorithms that we need to use in order
to train on a lot of them. So first
we're going to talk a little bit about
GPU hardware. So GPU um for those of you
that don't know is graphics processing
unit. These were specialized
co-processors that were originally
developed for computer graphics. Um and
they turned out to become to be very
useful generalizable parallel
processors. Um it's actually very
fitting to be giving this lecture in
this room cuz this is the the Hang
auditorium. Jensen Huang is the CEO and
founder of Nvidia um which is sort of
the biggest company right now and has
been for the last couple decades in
producing GPUs both for gaming and for
uh and for ML. So these things started
off basically for graphics because if
you think about it when you're doing
computer graphics you need to generate a
lot of pixels on the screen. You need to
process a little lots of little pieces
of primitive geometry to produce those
pixels. So it's kind of very natural to
do a lot of computation all in parallel
when you're doing computer graphics. Um
so they people quickly figured out that
this hardware that had been built
intended to use in computer graphics
could actually be used for much more
general pieces of parallel computation
um as well. So researchers kind so in in
the early days in the sort of early
2000s researchers figured out how they
could contort these graphics cards into
doing general generalizable parallel
programming. And then moving on towards
the end of the 2000s and into the 2010s
um Nvidia really picked up this and sort
of developed these things, marketed
them, built them with the intention of
being generalized parallel processors.
Um they didn't quite know at the time
what exactly they were going to be used
for. think I think they had this general
idea that parallel processing was going
to be important and they really
capitalized on deep learning when it
came when it started to take off in the
early 2010s. Um much to Nvidia's credit,
I think they really realized the
potential of this research area very
early um even in the early 2010s and
started putting a ton of resources into
making sure that their hardware was
really useful um for deep learning
training and it's basically been the
like the main way that people train deep
large scale deep learning models for
more than a decade now. um that's
starting to change as we'll see a little
bit, but um it's their their their chips
are kind of the the main one that people
use. So I think it's I always like
looking inside these things and seeing
like what's in them. So this is a
picture of the Nvidia H100 which is sort
of the the the sort of the mainstay of
deep learning training right now today.
Um there's a next generation that just
came out but it's not really accessible
yet. I haven't trained anything on it
yet. Um so this is this is kind of the
state-of-the-art right now. Inside this
Nvidia GP, inside this H100 GPU, in the
middle here are these compute cores and
surrounding that are 80 GB of HBM
memory, high bandwidth memory. Um, so
you can see the memory is separated from
the compute cores. They need to move
they need to talk to each other over
this over this bus to move data back and
forth from the GPU memory into the
cores. Um, and it can do that at at a
speed of about 3 terabytes per second,
which is a lot of bits moving around.
Now, if we dive deeper inside the the
GPU cores, um we see that in the middle
in that compute core part, we've got a
smaller piece of memory about 50
megabytes of L2 cache um that is much
much smaller than that 80 GB of um of
HBM memory, but it's very very close to
this to the GP to the actual computing
elements. So, they can be accessed much
more quickly from the compute cores. Um
and then the real heart of the thing are
these 132 streaming multipprocessors or
SM. Um these are kind of like
independent parallel cores. Um, they're
a little bit more powerful in some ways
than a typical CPU core because they can
do a lot more parallelism, but they're a
lot weaker than a typical CP CPU core
also in a lot of ways because they tend
to have slower clock speeds. They can't
do as much instruction prediction, as
much branch prediction. So, it's it's
really hard to make exact apples to
apples comparisons between these GPU
cores and the CPU cores. But, I usually
think of these um streaming
multipprocessors as roughly akin to a
CPU core. Um, also for I I know
someone's going to go back home and
actually count all the little boxes on
this screen and you'll see that there
are actually 144 of them when I've said
there's only 132. Why is that? It's
because all GPU hardware uses a process
called binning where making these
things, they have so many transistors,
so many little computing elements, no
matter how much money they pour into the
process, they just don't come out
perfectly. Um, some of them always end
up a little bit messed up. So, they kind
of plan for that in the development of
their products and they say, "We're
going to try to make a chip. The full
chip in theory has 144, but none of the
chips are perfect. But we know we'll get
a reasonable number of those that have
at least 132 that are functioning. So
they tend to use this process of
binning. So then they actually only um
you know can sell a much more larger
proportion of the chips they try to
produce by um you know only only
promising that 132 of them will be will
be um turned on.
um then we can dive even deeper inside
one of those streaming multipprocessors
and then we can see uh even more what's
going on inside of these GPUs. So this
is just one of the 132 active streaming
multipprocessors inside an H100. And
there's a couple interesting elements in
here to look at. Um first we see we have
um 256 kilobytes of L1 cache and
register files. So this this continues
the trend of the memory hierarchy in the
GPU. We saw that you know in general you
know you you thought you were learning
deep learning, you're actually learning
computer architecture. Sorry, it's a
surprise. Um, and it turns out that that
memory hierarchy is really important for
deep learning and for all all kind of
high performance computing. And the
general trend is that you have larger
bits of memory that are farther away
from the compute cores. And the closer
you get to the compute cores, you have
smaller bits of memory but are much much
faster. And it's really important to
write if you're writing the low
low-level algorithms that run on these
things, it's very important to be aware
of this memory hierarchy and to be very
diligent in passing data between
different phases of this memor memory
hierarchy. And if you're writing
performant GPU kernels, you spend a lot
of time try trying to optimize that. So
just to give you a flavor of that, you
know, you see that we see the three
levels of memory memory hierarchy in the
H100. You've got 256 kilobytes of L1
cache, 50 megabytes of um of L2 cache,
and then 80 GB of um HBM memory. So
those are the three primary levels of
memory hierarchy in the H100.
Then we've also got 128 of these FP32
cores. Um these are little arithmetic
units that can do sort of generalized
floatingoint operations. Um and in
particular each one of these 128 FP FP32
cores can compute ax plus b where ax and
b are all scalers. It can perform that
that bit of computation in one clock
cycle. So then if you um add this all up
that ax plus b is basically one multiply
um one addition and you've got 128 of
these cores. Um so you can do this this
whole SM can do 256 floatingoint
operations per SM uh per clock cycle of
the device.
Then we'll also see that in red we've
got this is where the real magic
happens. Um in addition to these uh FP32
cores, there are also these four tensor
cores. Um I think the name is a little
bit miss a little bit of a misnomer.
These are actually matrix cores. Um what
these what each of these little tensor
cores does is they are special circuits
that are designed they only do one
thing. they do matrix multiply. So each
one of these little tensor cores can do
a single chunk of matrix multiply. Um in
particular I believe the H100 ones can
do a 16 like input matrix A is 16x4. Um
input matrix B is 4x8 and then plus a
bias matrix of for of a size 16 by 8. So
it basically does ax plus b where a x
and b are little matrix chunks of this
fixed size. And it can do that that one
little ma chunk of matrix multiply once
per tensor core per clock cycle. Um so
then if you kind of multiply all these
numbers out you see that um you you know
that little matrix multiply of ax plus b
of that particular size is 1,024
floatingoint operations where we that's
counting each multiply each ad as a
single floatingoint operation. We
multiply that by the four uh tensor
cores in the SM and we see that the
entire S the entire SM if it's going
through the through the tensor cores can
do just over can do 4096 floatingoint
operations per SM per clock cycle. Um,
and this we need to compare with a 256
that we can get from the FP32 cores. And
here we see that just like the tensor
cores are where all the magic happens.
This is where the main throughput of the
device comes from. And if you're writing
code that wants to run on these GPUs and
make maximum avail make maximum usage of
them, you need to make maximum usage of
these tensor cores. Another interesting
thing about these tensor cores is that
they actually operate in mixed
precision. um rather than traditional
floatingoint numbers which are normally
32-bit, uh the tensor cores tend to use
a mix precision procedure where the
inputs are usually 16 bit. Um and
there's a couple different interesting
16- bit formats that they can use that
we can't get into today. Um and they'll
do the they'll do the multiplications in
this lower precision 16 bit and then do
the additions, the accumulations in a
higher precision 32-bit. So these tensor
cores take a low precision 16- bit input
and then produce uh and then do some of
the intermediate computation and produce
the outputs in a higher precision
32-bit. Um and this is important because
um at the PyTorch layer if you forget to
cast your model into into 16 bit it will
run on the floatingoint coes instead it
will be 20 times slower than you expect.
So this is uh you know seems like a
little bit of minutiae but it becomes
very tangible when you mess up that data
those data types in your pietorch code.
Um, and then not so GPUs are really fast
and it's really crazy just how fast how
much faster they've gotten over the past
decade or 15 years or so. Um, so when I
first started my PhD um, and was working
on deep learning, the state-of-the-art
GPU that we were all using was this K40
GPU um, back which was released back in
2013. And this thing could do just uh, 5
teraflops of FP32 compute um, for the
whole device. Uh, all right. So I should
explain the graph. So the x- axis is uh
time ranging from about uh 2013 up to
present day and then the y-axis is the
peak throughput of each of these devices
measured in terms of uh teraflops per
teraflops per second per device. Um and
you can see like the graph goes up a
lot. Um but there's something salient to
notice here is that um from the K40 to
the P100 something really amazing
happened in the V100 which came out uh
towards the end of my PhD in around 20
2016 2017 and that the V100 was the
first device that introduced these
tensor cores. Um and since then um the
the the since then more recent devices
have gotten more tensor cores, bigger
tensor cores, more of the device area
allocated to tensor cores and this has
resulted in a gigantic increase in the
throughput of these devices over the
past 10 or 15 years. Um and the most
recent device is this B200 um that was
uh you know formally announced. It's
slowly rolling out now. Um this one in
theory has about you know five uh has
about um 83 83.3 uh teraflops per second
of FP32 compute and 5,000 teraflops per
second in theory of um mixed precision
compute on the tensor cores. So if you
step back like this is this is like
literally we've been living through a
1,000fold increase in computation um
over the past you know 12 years. Um and
that's just at the per device level. So
there one explanation of why AI has
gotten so good in the last 10 years.
What has happened like this is the
answer. Um there's now a source of
computation that we're taking advantage
of and it's gone up by 1,000x in the
last decade. Anytime anything in the
world changes by 10,000x you should step
up and pay attention cuz that's going to
that's going to cause major changes in
our technological capabilities. And this
1000x improvement I think is the major
driver of improvement in deep learning
over the past decade. So the it's it
does not have 5,000 does not have 5,000
tensor cores. That's 5,000 teraflops of
compute on the tensor cores. Okay.
>> Yeah. So we always try to distinguish
between the compute on the tensor cores
versus the compute on FP32 cores.
Right. So like this is already crazy,
right? It's already crazy that there's
been a 1,000 increase in like a device
that you can hold in your hands. Like
I've held a K40 in my hands and I've
I've not held I've not had the
opportunity to hold a B100, but like
they feel like the same physical object.
It's like about the same size, about the
same weight, like kind of looks the
same, but the one from today is 1,000
times faster than the one from 12 years
ago. That's insane. Um, but it gets even
crazier because we don't train on one
GPU, right? I said that when when the
K40 first came out in 2013, it actually
was common to train a lot of models on
just one GPU. But today, we're training
not just on one GPU. We're training on
thousands, tens of thousands, sometimes
hundreds of thousands of GPUs all
working together to train one model. So,
so, so, so stack that on top of this
1,000fold increase in per device
throughput and something truly insane
has happened in the past decade.
So, then um you know then we can know
we've we've looked inside the GPU. Now,
from here I want to zoom out and and put
that GPU in context not looking at
individual devices but thinking about
the modern GPU clusters that we build
that stitch a lot of these things
together. So we've already seen a single
H100 GPU. Um we saw right and here the
and here we can think of it as another
level of memory hier hierarchy. We
already saw inside the H100 there were
sort of three layers of memory hierarchy
as we got closer to the compute elements
and as you got farther away from the
compute elements the bandwidth the
memory bandwidth the ability of the
device to move bits around between
different parts of the system um gets
slower and this trend actually continues
if you once you escape the bounds of a
single device and imagine these in the
context of a full data center. So here
we saw a single H100 GPU gets about 3
terabytes of um memory bandwidth. That's
sort of the GPU memory talking to its
from its own HBM memory to its own
compute elements. 3 terabytes per second
it can move bits around. Um but these
things typically live inside a GPU
server. Um almost all GPU servers have
um eight devices in one big box. Um and
those GPUs can talk to each other. Um
and they typically talk to each other at
a rate of about 900 GB per second from
any one GPU in the server to any other
GPU in the server. So you can see that's
like a 3x less memory communication
bandwidth compared to the GPU talking
from in inside one device. Um and here
things here we again turn to llama 3. Um
a lot of major players don't publish a
lot of details on their training
clusters but the llama 3 technical
report did actually give a lot of
details around their training clusters.
So from here some of the specifics
probably vary a little bit from cluster
to cluster. Um but these are now numbers
from the llama 3 cluster that was used
to train their their their models. Um,
so they given one GPU box, they stack
two of those box into one server rack.
Um, and a server rack, if you haven't
seen it, they're, you know, about 6 ft
tall, like about the size of a person to
just kind of get a mental picture of one
of those things. So one server rack has
two servers inside of it. Total of 16
GPUs.
Then we connect a lot of server racks
together into a GPU pod. Um, the Llama 3
cluster has GPU pods that are composed
of 192 racks. um and which is a total of
3,72 GPUs. And these things have really
high bandwidth connectors between all
the different racks. Um and as a result
um any pair of GPUs inside that pod can
talk to each other at a rate of about 50
GB per second. And now you see this is
another sort of 20x decrease in memory
traffic between what an individual um
server can talk and then what any GPU
across an entire rack can talk to each
other. So 3072 GPUs seems like a lot of
compute, but it's now it's nowhere near
enough. Um, so we're going to stack
those GPU pods together into a full GPU
cluster. Um, so this is actually the
full GPU cluster that um, Meta built to
train their Llama 3 models. This thing
combines eight GPU pods together for a
total of 24,576
GPUs. Um, I could not find exact numbers
on the memory traffic between these
things. Um, but it's definitely less
than 50 GB per second. And by the way,
this is not the largest GPU cluster in
the world by a long shot. Um, it's the
long it's the biggest one that I could
quickly find precise numbers on, but
there are definitely GPU clusters out
there in the world that are, you know,
50,000 GPUs, 100,000 GPUs. They exist
and people train models on them. Um, and
like the way that this works is it sort
of scales out naturally. So, you would
just sort of cluster together more pods
together to create a bigger a bigger
cluster. Or you might have another level
of hierarchy where you might have sort
of a super pod that connects to other
super pods to get you another level up.
uh how long do they train with that GPU
cluster? Um I I don't remember offhand
for the llama 3 models, but there's been
kind of a rule of thumb um for the past
decade is that the longest models that
people train are usually on the order of
months. Um and that I think has less to
do with technology and more to do with
people. When it comes to like making
like having progress, like making plans,
like having people work on things, it's
very difficult to have training runs
that are that are very very long. Um so
the longest training runs, the biggest
state-of-the-art models I think are
typically measured in months. Um, I
would not be surprised if the very very
largest models, the GPT 4.5s, the GPT5s,
if those are like pushing closer to a
year at this point. Um, but it's pretty
common to see training runs that are on
the order of a couple of months on these
really long, really big training
clusters. The question is, um, why do
you organize servers into a rack rather
than in a pod? You got to put them
somewhere, right? There's physical
constraints on these things. Um, so
server racks are kind of a stand have
been a standard unit, um, in just like
data centers for for decades at this
point. So when they when new these new
devices came onto the scene of GPUs that
that gives you a different kind of
server, they're a lot physically bigger.
They have a lot more power. Um but you
can't redesign the whole data center
from scratch overnight. Um so as a
result, the server rack has been kind of
a standard unit um with standard
hardware sizes and everything that the
that data centers are typically built
around.
>> How much physical space does like a
cluster typically?
>> Oh, that's a great question. Um,
so a a single you should think of a
single server rack as being like around
6 8 ft tall, something like that, like
about this big. So maybe like a server
rack would be like around the size of
this podium and like about as tall as
me. Um, then you then you've got 192
racks in a pod. So imagine like 200 of
these podiums. How big would that be?
And then multiply that by eight. Um, but
it's actually that's actually a little
bit of an underestimate because you
typically organize these things in rows
so people can actually walk between
them. Um, and there's more hardware that
you need to pack into the cluster, not
just the train, not just the the compute
racks. Um, so in addition to the compute
racks that have the physical GPU
servers, there'll be other racks that
contain networking hardware, we've got a
lot of a lot of a lot of bits that need
to fly around between all these devices.
So there'll be dedicated racks that only
hold networking hardware. There will
also be dedicated racks that only hold
storage hardware um because you need to
store the training data somewhere and
get that into your devices. So these
things uh can take up quite a lot of
space. Oh yeah question is um the when
you go to these big clusters do the
smaller units of compute maintain the
higher throughput and yes they do and
that's part of this that's part of the
secret and the challenge of designing
for these systems because you ideally
want to take advantage of the fast
communication when you can get it but
also fall back gracefully to the slower
communication on the larger units um as
you as you scale up. Oh, how hot does it
get? Um pretty hot. Like if if anyway if
any of you is a gamer and has a 4090 GPU
or 5090 GPU in your in your desktop at
home, like a single 4090 GPU if you're
playing games will heat up your room,
like make you want to open the window.
Like it will make a make the room
physically warmer. Um so imagine like if
that's what a single gaming GPU can do
to an averageized room. Yeah, there's
some serious cooling requirements for
these things once you stack tens of
thousands of them in a big in a big data
center.
Um although another interesting thing is
about I mean the cooling gets crazy,
right? So a gaming desktop will
typically be air cooled, sometimes water
cooled, and then like you can design
different different cooling systems and
you can go nuts on the hardware here to
try to optimize all this stuff. All
right, so I I think this stuff is super
cool. Just like imagine imagining like
these GPUs are not just mythical
creatures that are floating around in
the cloud. These are like actual
physical atoms that someone built and
stacked up in a room somewhere. And it's
really interesting to imagine what they
look like. Um and so basically one one
one kind of mindset shift when we move
to these big GPU clusters is actually
thinking not so much about the
individual devices about the individual
servers. I basically try to think of the
entire data center as one big computer.
Um and this big computer has in this
case has 24,000 GPUs 1.8 pabytes of HBM
memory on the GPUs 415 million FP32
cores 13 million tensor cores and this
whole thing can do 24 exoflops of
compute per second. That's 10. That's 24
* 10 18. That's a lot of flops. It's a
lot of flops, but I guarantee you 5
years from today, it will not feel like
a lot of flops, which is the even
crazier part. Um, and our goal here is
actually to think of this entire block
of 24,000 GPUs as one giant supercomput.
And then the question is, how can we
train one neural network for months at a
time on this one giant supercomputer and
train a really gigantic neural network
that's really powerful that can soak up
tons and tons of data? Um, and that's
basically the the question and the
paradigm that we've moved to in deep
learning.
Um, and by the way, um, I I I keep
saying GPU, I keep saying Nvidia because
they are sort of the most dominant
training architecture and and hardware
today, but there are some others that
have sprung up. Um, the biggest
competitor, I think, right now to to
Nvidia training hardware is Google.
Google has their own hardware called
tensor proing units, TPUs. Um, and these
are really good. Um, these are uh they
they've gone through six generations of
these already. Um, these are the stats
of the V5P TPU which you can rent in
Google Cloud today. Um, and it's sort of
roughly, you know, same order of
magnitude, kind of similar specs as the
H100 that we just talked about. There
are some interesting design decisions in
the TPU that are quite different from
the GPUs, which I find fascinating, but
we just don't have time to get into
today. Um, and someone was asking how
big are these things. This is an actual
picture. Just like GPUs, uh, these TPUs
are arranged into pods. Um, and the V5P
TPU TPUs can be arranged in pods of up
to 8,960
chips. Um, and this is a picture
actually of a V2 TPU pod which has only
256 chips. So then that kind of gives
you a sense of how big these things are.
Each one of those um, then you see
there's four racks here. Those racks are
kind of like I said maybe about as a
little bit taller than me and there's
four of them side by side for 256 TPU
chips. And now imagine this thing is
going to get a lot bigger in the more
recent pods that have up to almost 9,000
chips. Uh yes. So Google's Gemini models
are almost certainly trained on TPUs. I
would be I mean of course they don't
tell you, but I would be astounded,
absolutely astounded if they um were
not. And like I said um the TPUs are
actually very good. Um most I I I assume
that most large scale Google models are
trained on these things and those are
very competitive models. Um so this is
really good training hardware. Um the
difference with Nvidia is you can't buy
it. the only way you can access TPUs are
either by working at Google or by
renting them on Google Cloud. Um, but it
is very good hardware and a lot of
people are making use of it, but I think
it's still a little bit less popular
today um than H100 than uh than Nvidia
GPUs. Um, and of course other companies
obviously know that this is a very
important thing. So there's a lot of
other companies that are trying to build
competitive training hardware, but I
think like my honest assessment right
now is that probably Nvidia and TPUs are
the like the two big ones. they're
they're way ahead of everyone else right
now today in terms of usability,
performance, just like market share, but
there are a lot of others that are
trying to to catch up here. Um, two
notable ones are AMD. Um, AMD has been
sort of the second major GPU
manufacturer for many decades. They also
have um a training accelerator called
the MI3 325X. On paper, it actually has
really good stats that are pretty
comparable to an H100, but it just has
not had the same impact as the H100
right now. Um AWS also has their own
training chip that they've developed
called trrenium. Um I don't know too
much about this one. I've never tried to
use it myself, but I know that Enthropic
uses it for some of their training. I
don't know how to what extent their
training is entirely tranium versus um
GPUs.
Um so we should expect to see more. But
like today I think G Nvidia GPUs are
probably the most dominant and Google
TPUs are like right there. They're
really good as well, but probably not
quite as widely used as GPUs from
Nvidia.
Okay, so that's basically part one. um
what is what are GPUs? How do we arrange
them into clusters? Just give you a
sense of the physicality of these
machines that we're building and
training on. Then the second question is
how do we actually write algorithms that
can make use of this giant GPU cluster
with tens of thousands of GPUs? It's
going to require us to develop new
algorithms, new ways of thinking about
our compute, um and new ways of
parallelizing and splitting up our
neural networks. So the basic strategy
here is going to be split up your
computation. These things are giant
parallel devices. They have a lot of we
saw they have a lot of GPUs, a lot of
CPU cores, a lot of GPU cores that can
all operate independently and they can't
talk to each other too much. If you
think about what a computer really does
like at a high level, a computer
basically does two things. It does
computation which is taking input bits
and computing new output bits from those
and it does communication which is
taking bits and moving them from one bit
of memory in one place to some bit of
memory in some other place. And the
whole trick is how do we make use of all
of these multi- scale multi multiple
scales of memory hierarchy across the
entire cluster to overlap the
communication with the computation and
also to split up the computation and
parallelize paralyze it so that in the
process of training a giant neural
network we have useful work for all of
those tens of thousands of individ
individual GPUs all of those millions of
individual compute elements we have
useful work for all of them to be doing
in parallel and then get them to
communicate their work to each other in
a way that achieves training a giant
neural network all on this giant
cluster.
So to that end um one way I like to
think about it is there's basically five
degrees of parallelism that people
exploit when training neural networks
large scale neural neural networks
today. Um a lot of this is specific to
transformers because those are the
dominant architecture that people are
using for large scale training. So if
you think about a transformer, a
transformer is basically a stack of L
layers. And each one of those L layers
is operating on a threedimensional
tensor of size mini where we're where
one dimension is the mini batch
dimension. We've got a bunch of
sequences all operating in a mini batch.
Um a sequence dimension, you know, we're
operating on sequences or sets of tokens
and a dim dimension. So each of those
tokens itself is a vector with some
dimension. So our tensor our our our t
our um our transformers are operating on
these threedimensional tensors and they
operate through a stack of layers. So
that gives us four axes to parallelize
on. Um we can access we can parallelize
on the layers axis which is pipeline
parallelism. We can we can parallelize
on the um batch dimension which is data
parallelism. We can split on the
sequence dimension which is called
context parallelism. And we can split on
that dim dimension which is called
tensor parallelism. So all of these have
kind of funny names, but if you think
about it in this way, they're basically
all different ways of splitting up your
computation across these four axes of
compute inside your transformer. And
then we're going to step through each of
each one of these in more detail because
there's a lot of interesting nuances
with all of these different meth
mechanisms of distributed training.
So the first one is data parallelism um
or DP. And the the basic idea here is
kind of simple. So remember when we're
training neural networks, we're always
operating on mini batches of samples,
right? like we're always, you know,
taking a mini batch of of elements.
We're computing a loss for every entry
in our mini batch depending on what our
whatever our training task is. Then we
compute a gradient where the gradient is
actually typically an average of the
gradients of the losses for the
individual elements in the mini batch.
So um in most neural network
architectures, the computation of
computing the loss and then computing
the gradient is independent for each of
the elements in the mini batch. So this
is something that seems trivially
parallelizable. So the basic idea is
that if you have if you can fit a mini
batch of n examples on a single GPU and
you have access to m GPUs, then we're
going to train our model with a giant
mini batch of m* n examples where we
split up that giant mini batch into a
little tiny smaller mini batch of n
samples that goes on each GPU. Um, and
if you think about mathematically why
this makes sense, it's because gradients
are linear. So in practice, you know, if
you're kind of computing a single scalar
loss L, which is going to be the average
of some individual losses computed on
each of our so these Xig are all the
entries across your entire macro batch,
I guess we'll call it. And then the W
are the weight matric weight matrices of
the entire network. Then typically the
loss that you're computing um at the end
of the forward pass is an average of the
losses on each of the individual mini
batch elements. And then if you take the
gradient of the loss with respect to the
weights of the network, that's the
that's the that's the thing we need to
compute in order to make a weight
update, then that is actually going to
split. Um and you can because gradients
are linear, um you get you get to sort
of choose in what order do we want to do
the sum, do we want to do the gradient,
do we want to do the averaging. So in
particular, it becomes convenient to
arrange the gradient in this particular
formulation. um where there's this inner
term that we've highlighted in blue
which is um which is basically a normal
for backward pass on n elements and
these can be be computed in parallel on
different on different GPUs and then
there's an outer sum where we need to
take an average of the gradients across
our um m different devices that we are
that that we're operating on. Um so
that's kind of why what what what's
happening from a mathematical
perspective and we see that this is
perfectly mathematically sound. This is
basically exactly the same
mathematically as training on um a
single device. Um we've just been clever
with our algebra and changed the order
of doing our averages and our
summations. But this is not an
approximation. This is exactly the same
computation as we would have done on a
single larger GPU.
So kind of what this looks like at the
GPU perspective is that we have um n GPU
m GPUs. Here I'm showing m equals 3
because that's all that can sensibly fit
on the slide but you know think that
this is much larger than three in
practice. Then each one of those GPUs
actually maintains its own separate copy
of the neural network weights um of the
optimizer state um and of the gradients.
So then what we're going to do each GPU
will load in parallel a different mini
batch of data. Um here we're showing
each GPU loading three a mini batch of
three elements. And crucially the the
different GPUs need to load different
mini batches of data. Um I've had bugs
in in my code in students code where
they accidentally load the same mini
batch in all the GPUs. That's not going
to help you. That's not going to be
good. Don't don't make that mistake. Um
so you it's crucially important that
your and that your different GPUs
actually load different mini batches of
data. Um then each GPU will
independently do its own forward pass on
its own mini batch of data to compute
its own local loss on its own local mini
batch of data. And these these these can
all operate totally independently. It
does not require any communication
between GPUs. Then the the each network
will do its own backward pass to compute
the gradient of its own local loss with
respect to all the weights of the model.
And again this can happen totally
independently because each model
remember has its or each GPU has its own
independent copy of the model weights.
It can do its own forward backward pass
um completely independently.
But now after the backward pass is done
this is where things get tricky.
Remember we said we needed to compute an
average of those gradients across all
the devices that are participating in
our training. So then we need
communication. So this is where we do um
an an all reduce operation and every GPU
needs to needs to send its gradients to
all the other GPUs and each so like
there's sort of two things happening
simultaneously. One each GPU needs to
broadcast its gradients to all the GPUs
and then two each GPU needs to collect
the gradients from all the GPUs in the
that are participating in the training.
Um so this is an all reduce operation.
Um and there's uh that this kind of
happens in sort of logarithmic time
typically depending on in the number of
GPUs. Um but at the end of this all
reduce operation then each GPU now has
um an an average of all the gradients
across all the devices. So at this point
the communication has happened. Um each
GPU now has an identical copy of the
gradients that have been all reduced
across all the devices. So now um at the
beginning of the training iteration we
assumed that each GPU had its own
independent copy of the model weights.
Now at this point each GPU has its own
independent but identical copy of the
gradients across the entire macro batch
of data. So now at this point um each
GPU can make a weight update on its own
local copy of the weights. And because
they started with the same weights and
they had this and they applied the same
gradient, they're going to have the same
weights after the local weight update
assuming the arithmetic was
deterministic.
Um and also by the way um and this is
really important, steps four and five
can actually happen in parallel. We said
that there's two things that there's
actually two things here that can happen
in parallel. One is the backward pass
where each GPU computes its own backward
pass to compute gradients and the other
is the communication of the gradients
across the GPUs and these things in
practice will typically happen
simultaneously. So that means that each
model will start off doing doing
backward pass over the last layer in the
network and then compute its own local
gradient. Now the model will move its
compute on to computing backward pass
for the second to last layer of the of
the of the model. And while the compute
elements are busy computing the backward
pass on the second to last layer, then
the the GPUs will simultaneously be
doing an all reduce of the gradients of
the last layer. So this means that these
things kind of chunk along um
communication for layer L+1 and backward
pass for layer L and they can just chunk
along in parallel so that hopefully by
the time we've gotten to the end of the
network and by the time the backward
pass is done, the the gradients have
already been all reduced across all the
devices. Um and we can make our weight
update all at once without waiting. Um
this is really important because like we
said with the communication is
relatively slow. So the whole trick in
these things is figuring out ways to
hide the communication costs and do them
at the same time as the compute. The
question is is four or five going to be
the bottleneck? And the answer is yes.
Um it depends entirely on how fast your
device is, how big is your model, how
big is your mini batch, how fast is the
inter interconnect between the devices.
Um when you get to this lower scale
distributed trading the answer is always
it depends on your situation and you
need to benchmark for your situation.
Ah, why not take m different gradient
steps on each of them? That's actually a
really cool idea. Um, there actually was
a popular uh set of algorithms that
people used a while back called
asynchronous SGD where they would
basically do that then basically have a
bunch of different model replicas all
take a bunch of independent model steps
and then try to average them every once
in a while. Um, and those were popular
like there were some like actually
Google used to do this before they
developed the TPU pods. Um, and some of
their earlier networks in the early
2010s were trained in this way. Um, but
one, it tends to just be a lot more
unstable. Um, and two, it's very hard to
debug and reproduce. Um, so it and it it
just tends to work a little bit worse.
So it it does feel like a more scalable
approach, but in practice, um, if you
can do everything synchronously, then
your algorithms are easier to debug,
easier to understand, easier to reason
about. Um, and if you can get basically
if you can get away with with
synchronous gradient updates, it's
probably going to work better. Um, but
actually I would personally not be too
surprised if we see a resurgence of
async SGD methods in the next couple of
years at some point because I think they
are a lot more friendly to distributed
training. There's no one computer that
can orchestrate all this stuff. All
these things are independent devices
with their own independent stuff.
There's no there's no driver that can
take a god's eye view and and take those
steps. All that computation has to
happen somewhere. Ah, great question. I
I said like as you're overlapping
communication and compute, do you need
to write code for this or does the
hardware do this automatically? You
definitely got to write code for this.
The hardware is not smart enough to
understand what you want to do. Like the
hardware, like we said, it's sort of
understands these little matrix multiply
chunks. It understands pretty low-level
stuff. Um anything that you want to do
to schedule that communication um the
you need to take care of in software. Um
but thankfully um for a lot of these
common use cases, um PyTorch ships with
it for you. So, for example, in this
case, there's a there's a PyTorch class
called distributed data parallel um that
will do this for you and make this uh
this sort of happen relatively
transparently on top of um otherwise
straightforward PyTorch code that you've
written.
>> Although that actually that is really
interesting to contrast with the
individual devices because um if you're
programming an individual GPU in CUDA,
which is Nvidia's language for
programming GPUs, then actually the
hardware does take care of a lot of this
async transfer for you automatically. Um
but at the cluster level, um it
typically doesn't. then you typically
need to do it in software. So there
there actually is a little bit of
interesting asymmetry here between
parallelism on the individual device
level where a lot of that is does happen
automatically in hardware versus at the
cluster level where it needs to be
orchestrated in software. Yeah. So so
typically these are these are
heterogeneous systems where different
parts of the system are written in
different programming languages. So
there's going to be low-level device
kernels that actually are the code that
executes inside the GPU and those are
typically written in CUDA which is um
you know it's a C like language that is
Nvidia's language for programming their
own GPUs. Um, and but then those
individual GPU kernels will get wrapped
up and you can call those GPU kernels
from Python. And this is basically how
PyTorch works. PyTorch is sort of like a
collection of a lot of GPU kernels that
can do lots of interesting stuff on the
GPU and then a lot of C++ and Python
code that wraps around those GPU kernels
and makes it more user friendly to
program. So in this picture, each GPU is
computing its own gradients in black um
on it by itself and then the gradients
in red get computed via an all reduce
across all the GPUs in parallel. Oh, the
backward pass at the lower layer is
dependent on the gradients from the
previous layer. Um, but crucially, um,
each network is each GPU is only doing
backward pass locally on its own mini
batch. So then there's basically two
different variants of the gradient at
each layer that you need to think about.
Now there's the local gradients about
like the gradient of the local loss of
my mini batch with respect to my network
weights and there's the global gradient
which is the derivative of the total
loss of the of the macro batch with
respect to the network weights. So each
GPU can only in order to compute a
backward pass each GPU only needs the
local version of its upstream gradient
but then the computing the global
version of the upstream gradient
requires communication.
Um so this is data parallelism and
there's actually a bit of problem here
which is this is a great way to paralyze
G GPU computation and this was the first
way that people started paralyzing GPU
computation in neural network training
but we quickly hit a bottleneck on the G
on the model size. So here remember that
each GPU is keeping its own independent
copy of the model parameters and this
becomes a bottleneck when you want to
have really big models. So in particular
um now each weight in your neural
network you basically need to keep track
of four numbers the weight itself um the
gradient of that the the gradient of
that weight uh and the optimizer state.
So if you're using atom that's typically
a beta that's a beta 1 and a beta 2 per
parameter in the network. Um and
sometimes you'll also have an
exponential moving average of the model
parameters as well. So typically you'll
have you know four to five scalers that
you need to keep track of for every
weight in your network. Um and if you're
training with 16 bit precision which is
pretty common these days what some some
of these you'll sometimes keep in in
higher precision but let's talk about 16
bit as a lower bound then you need two
bytes for each number. So that means
that we need you know four numbers two
bytes we need six we need uh eight bytes
per scaler in the in the network um to
to keep track of which means that 1
billion parameters um 1 billion model
parameters is going to take about 8 GB
of GPU memory to store all that stuff
and we said the whole GPU only has 80 GB
of memory for an H100. So that means
that the biggest model you could ever
hope to train in this scenario is
something like 10 billion parameters and
that's not big enough. We want really
big models. We don't want to be
constrained by the tyranny of our GPU
memory size in telling us how big of
models we're allowed to train. So we
need to fix this somehow. And the fix
for this is actually relatively easy. We
want to split we need to split the model
weights across the different GPUs. So in
addition to splitting the batch of data
across GPUs, we're also going to split
our model weights across the GPUs. And
this leads to a variant of data
parallelism called fully sharded data
parallelism or FSTP. Um, and this is
relatively simp conceptually what we're
going to do is each model weight in the
network, each weight wii, we are going
to assign it to a owner GPU. So each
weight will be owned by a unique GPU
among the MGPUs that we're training on.
Um, and that the GPU that owns each
weight will also be responsible for
managing the global gradients for that
weight and the optimizer state for that
weight. Um, and typically you would
split this up by layer like you're not
managing individual scalers. This W you
should think of as like the lay like the
weight matrix for an entire layer of the
neural network.
So now what but now so now what's so now
the the picture on the right changes a
little bit here we're only showing two
GPUs because spoiler there's going to be
a lot more arrows flying around here in
just a moment. So here we're showing a
four-layer network that we're
distributing across two different GPUs.
We've we've assigned the first two
network the weights for the first two
network layers W1 and W2. Those are
owned by GPU1. um the weights W3 and W4
are owned by GPU 3, GPU 2. So that means
that you know at the start of each of
each batch the network weights are split
up across the GPUs in this way. But it's
it's still data parallelism. It's still
the same basic idea that each GPU is
going to load its own independent batch
of elements, do a full forward backward
pass on that batch to compute its own
local gradients. Then I'll reduce the
gradients and take a gradient step. Same
basic algorithm, but it gets tricky now
because the model weights are split up.
So here we need to introduce extra
communication. So when you're doing
fully sharded data parallelism now at
the beginning of forward before you
start doing the forward pass of the
first layer um whoever owns that weight
for the first layer needs to broadcast
that weight matrix to all the other GPUs
that you're training on. So in this case
um GPU1 owns W1. So it broadcasts that
to GPU 2. So GPU 2 now has a copy of W1.
Now that all the GPUs have a copy of W1,
they can run a forward pass through the
first layer of the network and compute
the activations at the first layer of
the network. And now um after you run
the forward pass um each GPU that does
not own that W1 is going to delete its
local copy of the W1 weight matrix to
save memory. So then after we've run the
first after we run the forward pass for
the first layer we're back in the state
where the model weights are split up
across the GPUs. But now all the GPUs
have also have an activations in in GPU
memory that is the result of running the
first layer of the network. And now now
it's time to do the second layer and we
do the exact same thing. So then the GPU
that owns the weight matrix for layer 2
is going to broadcast that to all the
GPUs that we're training on. Now they
all have their own local copy of W2.
They can uh and they can go go forward.
Um and by the way, we also have an
opportunity to interle computation and
communication here as well. So that
while we are computing the forward pass
for layer I, we can be prefetching the
weights for the next layer. So in
practice, this will happen in parallel
um during the forward pass of an FSDP
run. So then we'll be computing for
we'll be computing uh layer 2 at the
same time we are fetching the weights
for layer 3. Um and once we get to layer
3, note that now GPU 1 owns layer 3. So
then GPU1 will be broadcasting the
weights to all the GPUs that we're
training on. And this will repeat until
we've gotten to the end of the network.
And now at the end of the network, then
all models now we now each model has on
a full forward pass computed its local
loss on its own local mini batch and has
all the activations for all the layers
in memory all ready for backward. Um and
now we need to do the same thing in
reverse in order to compute the backward
pass. So um at the beginning of the
backward pass for the for the last layer
whoever owns that last layer weight will
broadcast it to all the devices. Um once
the devices have that weight then they
can perform the backward pass and this
whole we'll do a similar kind of
procedure in the backward pass. Now
there is a little bit of optimization we
can do on the la very last layer in the
network which is don't delete the me
like keep the have the all the GPUs keep
the the weights for the last layer in
memory. So, this is something that
you'll usually do in practice, right?
Because at the end, um, all the all the
GPUs already have a copy of the last
their weights from the forward pass.
They'll just keep it in memory and just
because they they're they know they're
about to reuse it for the backward pass
anyway. So, we just won't delete the the
the weights from the very last layer.
Um, so now there's basically but now
there's basically three things that need
to happen during the backward pass. Um,
one is that you know once the GPUs have
computed the backward pass for their
last layer of the network now that they
have a copy of the weights now at that
point each GPU has computed its own
local backward gra it own local
gradients for its local loss with
respect to that last layer weights. Um
then we need to we need to communicate
those gradients back and we said that
the GPU that owns the weight matrix is
also going to be responsible for
managing the gradients for that weight
matrix. So now rather than all reducing
the gradients as we did in the data
parallelism case, instead we're going to
um just just the one weight matrix that
owns just the one GPU that owns that one
last layer weights is going to gather
and take take a sum across all the local
gradients across all our devices. So in
this case, GPU1 is going to send its
last layer local gradient to GPU uh to
GPU 2, which will then have the full
gradient um DL DW4 of the entire macro
batch with respect to the last their
weights. What happens during the
downtime? You got to get all this stuff
happening in parallel. Um so in this so
then you know there's basically three
things that need to happen during
backward. During backward we need to
communicate the weights. So whoever
whatever whatever GPU owns the layer
owns the weights for that layer has to
broadcast them. Two we need to all the
GPUs once they get that weight need to
compute a backward pass for that layer.
And then three um after each GPU
computes its backward pass then it needs
to send the result of that the gradients
with respect to the weights of that
backward pass back to the GPU that owns
it. Um and we can and then after that
then the owner then once the owner of
the weights has that full gradient then
only the owner of the weight matrix can
now make a gradient update on that one
weight matrix. Um but I I think at this
point we actually do not need to
communicate the the updated weight
matrix because it will get
recommunicated to all the GPUs on the
next forward pass. Um so that that's a
little bit different from the from the
from the DP case maybe. Um and then
basically all of these things can
actually happen in parallel as well. So
they will repeat this for every layer of
the network and then basically we in the
steady state of a very deep network all
three of these things will be happening
simultaneously. Um so so while we are
computing the backward pass for layer L
we will be um aggregating the gradients
and performing a weight update on the on
layer L+1 and we will be pre-fetching
the weights for layer L minus one. So I
said there's three things that need to
happen. we need to get the weight um run
the backward pass and then uh update the
weight and then aggregate the gradient
and update the weight and these things
can all happen in parallel. So we'll
basically in general be operating on
three consecutive layers and doing all
three of these things in parallel over
the over the course of the backward
pass.
Right? Right. So then like during the
and then as we chunk backwards over the
network um then by the time we then
hopefully if you were properly able to
overlap all that communication and
computation then by the time you get you
finish your backward pass then all the
gradients have already been communicated
all the GPUs have already finished doing
their update on all the weights and
we're ready and also hopefully your data
loader that's loading data is al also
happening asynchronously usually on the
CPU cores of our servers. So then the
CPU is like ready with a fresh batch of
data to go forward again. So these
things are basically parallelization
machines. We have a lot of stuff that
needs to happen um both within a GPU and
across GPUs and we need to overlap all
of that as much as possible. So we can
always feed the GPUs and have them
running on those tensor cores as as
densely as possible.
Um right so then we're basically ready
to do our next batch after after that.
So this is great. This is fully sharded
data parallelism. Um and this is this
can get you a long way. Um but there's
actually a slightly uh slightly fancier
variant of data parallelism that people
sometimes use called hybrid sharded data
parallelism or HSDP. Um and in this case
we're actually going to imagine
conceptually dividing our GPUs into a
two-dimensional grid. So in the previous
examples we said we had sort of n GPUs
and the way that we parallelized our
computation was kind of the same. We had
sort of one axis of parallelization um
in the previous variants of data
parallelism. Once we get to hybrid
sharded data parallelism, we now are
going to have two separate axes of
parallelism that we will do at the same
time. So the first axis is we will do
typical FSTP um fully sharded data
parallelism along one axis that we just
talked about. Um so we'll have sort of
groups of KG GPUs. Um and each group of
KGPUs will be doing um fully sharded
data parallelism that we just talked
about. So within each group of KG GPUs,
the model weights will be split across
those KGPUs and they will be interle um
sending weights and gradients back and
forth to each other during the forward
and backward passes. But we will have
now um m M copies of those K groups
operating in parallel. So in this case
we have um two groups of four GPUs. So
each group of four GPUs you see has the
weights split across the four GPUs but
we have the entire the entire the entire
uh setup duplicated a second time on a
second group of two GPUs. Um and the
reason and and then when you do this now
you know then they do typical data
parallelism across the groups. So within
a group we're going to do forward
backward um and at the end of the
backward each group will have computed
its own local gradients and then after
the backward then each group needs to
all reduce the gradients across the
groups so that we now have like the full
like macro macro batch gradients across
the two groups and then each group can
make an gradient update independently
once they've received the full gradients
for the macro macro batch.
Um so this is called multi-dimensional
parallelism because now there's
basically two different axes, two
different strategies that we're using to
paralyze our computation simultaneously.
Um and why this might be useful is
because there's different amounts of
communication required for these two
different kinds of parallelism. So if we
think about fully sharded parallelism,
you know, we actually need to what do we
need to communicate for during fully
sharded data parallelism? During FSTP,
during the forward pass, remember we
were copying the weights all over. So we
sort of copy like during the forward
pass we end up doing a communication of
one full copy of the network weights.
Then during the backward pass we need to
recommunicate the network weights um and
we also need to communicate the
gradients. So basically when it comes to
when you use fully shredded data
parallelism you b like during a single
forward backward pass you need to
communicate three times the network
weights across everything participating
in an FSDP group. But when you do normal
data parallelism um where each where
where you each group keeps its own
independent copy of the weights you only
need to all reduce the gradients. So
that means that across multiple data
parallelism groups, you only need to
communicate the network weights once
over a forward backward pass. And this
plays into this idea of multiple levels
of hierarchy inside of our GPU clusters.
So what you'll what you might do, for
example, is have um a GPU server where
it has eight GPUs with higher
interconnect inside a single machine.
Those might be an FSTP group because it
requires more communication inside an
FSTP group. But then you could have
multiple servers that are, you know, on
this other axis. So you have sort of one
server with a full copy of the model
weights then another server with another
full copy of the model weights and
remember communication across servers is
going to be slower than communication
inside a server. So then this is our
first example of you know take designing
algorithms to take to make to take
advantage of the network topology that
we know our devices are connected into.
Question is um would you rather have g
like the these things are impossible to
tune. It's very very hard to say. Um
right so you know and then basically but
once you have data parallelism once you
have this this DP FSTP and HSTP this is
actually a recipe that can take you a
long ways. So for example um you know we
a model with 100 billion parameters
would take 800 GB of memory to store um
and and if you split that over 80 GPUs
it only takes 10 GB of memory per GPU.
So you can have you know a pretty big
model once you have FSDP.
Um, but there's another problem that the
model activations themselves now start
to fill up memory. So if we go back to
llama 35B, um, it's a transformer with
126 layers, model dimension of 16,000,
sequence length 4096. Um, so if you kind
of imagine how much GPU memory it takes
to just store the hidden states during a
forward pass. Um, that's going to be a
lot. So that's going to quickly cause
your GPU to run out of memory once your
models and sequences get really big. So
that leads to another trick is called uh
activation checkpointing which means
that we're actually not going to store
all the activations in memory. We're
going to recmp compute them during the
backward pass. So to to to see how this
works like we it's useful to think of
your neural network in a different way
where there's actually two different
layers in the neural each each layer in
the in the neural network does two
things. It does a forward pass that
computes activations for the next layer.
Then it has a backward pass that
computes gradients that take both the up
upstream gradients and the activations.
So normally you know how much compute
and memory does this all take. Um if we
assume that all of these are constant
then typically a forward backward pass
will take sort of 1 2 3 4 four step
string forward you'll remember those
activations during the forward pass then
1 2 3 four step string backward. So in a
normal forward backward pass it sort of
takes um compute and memory for an end
layer network. Um but as we just said
this is going to run out of memory. So
instead what we can do is imagine
recomputing the activations during the
backward pass. So what that looks like
is something like this. So we'll start
with the activations. We'll run the
first layer and then immediately throw
away the activations for the first well
run the forward pass for the first layer
and then immediately throw away those
activations and sort of do this four
times. So now we've sort of gone through
the network once got the activations at
the last layer. At this point we can
compute our backward for the last layer.
But um now we're kind of out of luck. We
we don't have the activations from from
A3 to compute the next backward pass.
But we can recmp compute them. So we
recomp compute them. Now we can do the
backward pass. Now recomputee some more.
Now do the backward pass. Now recomp
compute. Now do another backward pass.
So if you kind of add this all up, this
ends up being n^2 compute and constant
memory for a layer for a network with n
layers cuz it's sort of sum n minus 1 n
-2 n -3 blah blah blah down to one.
That's quadratic time. Um and you can
split this up. You know n squed compute
is pretty bad for deep networks. So
instead let's not recmp compute
everything. Let's instead imagine taking
a checkpoint of activations every C
layers. So we'll only sort of compute
like recomp compute within blocks of uh
within tinier blocks of the network.
Then in that case um if you take C
checkpoints where you remember your
activations c times over the course of
your network then it's going to take n^
squ over c compute and o of c memory. Um
and a pretty common thing to do is to
set c equal to root n in which case this
becomes n root n compute and o of root n
memory. Um so this is a pretty common
way that you can trade off computation
and memory um to train even bigger
models.
Okay so now at this point once we have
FSTP activation checkpointing HSTP we
actually this can we can do a lot of
damage here. We can start to train some
really big models. Um and the recipe for
that is basically as following. Um so
your scaling recipe that will take you
quite a long way from here is first use
data parallelism just raw data
parallelism roughly up to 128 GPUs um
and roughly up to models of around a
billion parameters. You can just do
normal data parallelism for models of
this size. It tends to work pretty well.
Um and another thing that you almost
always want to set the local batch size
per GPU to max out the GPU memory.
That's almost always the right thing to
do. Um, and then once your model starts
to get big, then the model itself will
take up a lot of memory inside your GPU.
So that'll that will start to give you
problems. So you know, it kind of
depends on how much memory your GPU has,
how fast your interconnects are. But in
general, once your model starts to be
more than a billion parameters, that's
when you want to start thinking about
switching from data parallelism to fully
sharded data parallelism. Um, and then
at this point you can scale up quite a
bit, but then you'll run into the memory
bottleneck for your activations and
that's when you turn on activation
checkpointing. Activation checkpointing
kind of sucks because it makes
everything a lot slower, but it does let
you train much bigger models. Um, and
once and this this will scale like up to
several hundred GPUs and then there's
some point usually depending on your
cluster topology maybe around 256 GPUs,
maybe around 512 GPUs. Once you get to
like on the order of multiple hundreds
of devices, then FSTP becomes too
expensive and you need to and you need
to start switching to HSTP. Um, and then
this is basically going to let you get
up to models that are roughly tens of
billions of parameters training on maybe
a thousand GPUs. Um, that's on like
pretty long sequence lengths. So that's
pretty good. Um but if you have maybe
more than a thousand GPUs, uh more than
50 billion parameter models, sequence
lengths more than more than 10,000 or
so, um this is when you need to turn to
these more advanced strategies, context
parallelism, pipeline parallelism, or
tensor parallelism.
And then there's a big question. It's
like, oh my god, there's a lot of nubs
to tune here. Like how am I supposed to
optimize this? I need to set the glo the
global batch size, the local batch size,
the HSTP dimension, the FSDB dimension.
Like how much to recomputee? Like I'm
lost here. What do I do? There's so many
knobs. I don't know what what what what
do I do? Um the answer is to optimize a
very important metric called model flops
utilization MFU. Whenever you get lost
in the sea of GPU parallelism like model
flops utilization is your guiding light.
Follow this. It will tell you what to do
um to optimize your training stack. But
before we get to model flops
utilization, we need to talk about
hardware flops utilization. So remember
we said in theory an H100 can do 988
989.4 t flops per second of compute on
the tensor cores. But that's
theoretical. How much can you actually
get? Um the question is how much can you
actually achieve in practice? Um and
that's the metric of hardware flops
utilization. You know, you're running
some compute on the device. How much
compute do you actually realize of that
theoretical maximum? Um and this is not
hard to do. Like you can write a couple
lines of PyTorch code and just like
benchmark this. So this is a benchmark
that I wrote that I ran on an H100
yesterday. Um and you can see what it
does is basically X-axis. It just does
dense matrix multiply in in a loop and
then times how long did the matrix
multiply happen. how long did the matrix
multiply take? Um, we can compute how
many flops the matrix multiply takes.
Then on the x axis, we're plotting the
size of our matrix um going from uh 512
up to 32,000. And the y-axis is this
hardware flops utilization, which is
basically the fraction of the
theoretical maximum throughput of the
device that we actually realize from
these matrix multiplies. And you can see
that on this, you know, pretty
straightforward PyTorch loop, we're
getting about 80% HFU on an H100 once we
get to large matrix multiplies of around
um 8,000 by 8,000. So that's pretty
good. But the problem is that HFU does
not account for all the other stuff that
your model needs to do, right? We're
doing we're maybe doing activation
recmputation. We're maybe running some
other models on the side. We're maybe
doing data loading, data augmentation.
There's a lot of other stuff your GPU is
doing other than just forward backward
on your raw model. And that's where we
move from hardware flops utilization to
model flops utilization. So model flops
utilization is basically saying um what
fraction of the GPU's theoretical peak
flops are being used for forward
backward in my model. Um and this is the
thing you always want to optimize for.
So then to make this more concrete, you
basically compute um you know based on
your model architecture, the size of the
number of the layers, the size of the
layers, you compute how many flops does
it take to do a full forward backward
pass of your architecture on your mini
batch of data. Then you look up
somewhere the peak theoretical
throughput of the device you're running
on. And then you divide those two and
that tells you how long should a full
forward backward pass take if you were
achieving the theoretical maximum
throughput of the device. That's like
the theoretical fastest you could ever
do a forward backward pass on your
model. Then um you actually time a
forward backward pass of your model. You
know your your training loop is doing
all this other stuff. It's doing data
loading. It's doing it's doing
augmentation. It's doing communication.
It's doing um maybe activation
checkpointing. So it's doing recmp
computation during backward. Your
training loop is doing a lot of stuff.
Just time see how long it actually takes
and then divide those two numbers. that
gives you a number between zero and one
which is like what fraction of that
theoretical maximum are you actually
achieving in your training loop and that
that's your MFU your model FOPS
utilization um and again we can kind of
benchmark this with some relatively
simple PyTorch code here's an example
running forward backward on just a like
a like a short multi-layer perception
with uh with a relu nonlinearity and
with really big with really wide MLP
layers and a gigantic batch size on a
single uh H100 this is getting around
50% MFU
Um, but and then in in general whenever
you're trying to tune knobs for
distributed training, you always want to
try to tune whatever knobs you can to
maximize MFU because that's the one
metric that we typically care about when
trying to optimize training throughput.
Um, and in general, you know, an MFU
these days, generally above 30% is
pretty good. If you're way under 30%,
you've probably got some gigantic
bottleneck somewhere and something is
going wrong. Um, and above 40% is pretty
pretty excellent. And that's basically
state-of-the-art. Um, and here's some
numbers that we can pull from a couple
papers. In particular, this is that
llama llama 3 405b paper that we talked
about. Um, in their in their final
training step, they have a couple
different variants of their of their
training phases where they train on
between 8,000 and 16,000 GPUs
simultaneously. Um, and across that,
they're getting MFUs roughly in the low
like high30s, low 40s. And that's pretty
that's pretty good. Um, you're never
going to get really much higher than
that on an H100. Um, and actually
paradoxically, more recent devices
sometimes get worse MFUs. So on on the
previous generation devices, the A100's,
you could sometimes get MFUs above 50%.
And the reason for that is because GPUs
are getting faster faster than they are
getting faster at communicating. So when
we moved from the A100 to the H100, we
got roughly a 3x improvement in the
theoretical throughput of the compute,
but we only got a 2x improvement in the
theoretical memory bandwidth. Um, so
that that there's there there's this
growing gap between making GPUs are
getting faster really fast, but it's
harder to scale the communication
between the GPUs and as a result, we
tend to sometimes get worse MFUs
actually on more recent generations of
devices.
So that's um that and I I intentionally
spent wanted to spend most of the time
on those points because those are the
ones that you guys are probably going to
use in practice. Um I don't think anyone
in this room likely has access to a
10,000 GPU cluster. If you do, like come
talk to me after class. I would love to
be your friend. Um but uh so like those
are the ones that you're likely to
encounter in practice like up to many
hundreds of GPUs. Um but there are these
other ones that I I just like there are
slides here that are pretty that I think
are pretty nice, but it's okay if we
don't go through the full details of
these. You can ch you can check it
offline. Um so we said context
parallelism is basically splitting on
the sequence dimension. So we said
transformers are operating on sequences.
Um and basically the idea is you've got
a long sequence, you know, make
different GPUs handle different parts of
the sequence. Um, and for if you recall
your transformer block, this is actually
easy for large parts of the transformer
because the layer norm, the multi-layer
like the the FFN, MLP, um, and the
residual connections, those all operate
independently across the sequence
anyway. So, it's relatively
straightforward to ask to chunk up that
computation across the sequence
dimension. Um, things get I mean it does
get a little bit hairy inside the MLP
because there are weights in there. So,
you have to have some some reduce of the
gradients like we did in the data
parallelism cases. The attention is
where things get hairy for sequence
parallelism because if we remember um
attention we need to compute the sort of
all pairs interaction between every pair
of elements inside the sequence. Um the
QKB projection is easy um because that's
sort of trivially paralyzable over the
sequence. But that core attention matrix
that actually gets pretty tricky to
paralyze. Um the the most like the the
first version of this that people
developed was called ring attention
where you basically take that full
attention matrix um chunk it up into
blocks and then a have your your your
GPUs sort of work on those blocks
independently in parallel in the right
order to make sure everything works out.
Um there's a lot of details in there.
You can check out the paper for more
details. Um the second which is a little
bit conceptually easier is called um
ulysus attention. Um where you do
parallelism over the heads. So remember
in a transformer you're almost always
doing multi-head attention where you're
sort of computing attention over like
multiple attention matrices all in
parallel. Um so in ulysus attention
we're going to parallelize that
computation of that core attention
operator paralyze that over heads and
then everything else all other parts of
the transformer are paralyzed over the
sequence dimension.
Um and as a as an example like um cont
this this context parallelism becomes
important once you scale up your
sequence length to be quite large. So if
we go back to this example of llama 3
pre-training, they actually train the
model in two stages. The first stage
they go um sequence length of 8,000 with
no context parallelism whatsoever. Um
and then they have a second stage of
training where they crank the sequence
length up to 130,000. And then that
point at at that point they do 16-way
context parallelism. So that means that
each of those um 131,000 long sequences
has 16 GPUs operating on one sequence in
parallel. And that's kind of like saying
the batch size is like 1 over 16 because
now like each batch each GPU is h is
working on like less than one element.
Um so that's context parallelism.
Pipeline parallelism we're going to
split across the layers dimension. Um
intuitively what you want to do you have
you a network with a bunch of layers and
we're going to just divide the layers
across the GPUs. That's actually a very
intuitive thing to do. The problem is
that there's sequential dependencies,
right? Because each GPU like it needs
the activations from the previous GPU to
continue running the forward pass and
during the backward pass I need the
gradients from the upstream layers in
order to compute the backward pass. So
we can draw a diagram like this where
the the vertical axis are GPUs 1 to 4
the horizontal axis is what happens over
the course of time. So then you can see
that GPU run GPU 1 runs forward then
passes the activations to GPU 2 which
passes activations to GPU 3 which passes
activations to GPU 4. GPU 4 is lucky it
can do forward backward all at once then
pass gradients back to GPU 3 back to GPU
2 back to GPU 1. So from this graph like
there that's obviously really really bad
right because the GPUs are mostly
sitting idle um and in fact if you have
n GPUs like only you're only getting
useful work out of them one overn of the
time. So that means that if we had like
8-way pipeline parallelism, your maximum
possible MFU at that point is like 12%.
Which is terrible. So like that's really
bad. Um and by the way, there's a cute
name. These are sometimes called the
bubble. Um is like that chunk of where
GPUs are waiting for work and they
they're like waiting around for the
communication. So the trick in pipeline
parallelism is to shrink the bubble. You
want to have less bubble and the way
that we do that is running multiple
micro batches simultaneously. So now
like rather than running running one
batch of data through all the GPUs
forward and backward, we're going to
have multiple batches of data in play
simultaneously and shuttle these things
across the GPUs um in parallel.
So there's a lot of different
interesting patterns you can try to
design for this, but here's a relatively
simple one where we have um four-way
pipeline parallelism. So there's four
GPUs that are all working in parallel
and then we we have four batches of data
that are all active at the same time. So
then and these batches are colorcoded.
So then we see that GPU1 runs forward on
the on the blue batch, then forward on
the yellow batch, then forward on the
green batch, then forward on the red
batch. And while GPU1 is going forward
on the yellow batch, um we've passed the
activations of the blue batch to GPU 1
or to GPU 2 and GPU 2 can now do forward
on the blue batch. So these things can
all sort of cascade down and happen in
parallel. And then the same kind of
pattern repeats during the backward
pass. We can kind of interle these
different mini batch, these different
microbatches as we pipeline them through
the different GPUs. Um and in this case
with um you know four-way pipeline
parallelism with four microbatches our
max the like the max theoretical MFU is
just like the fraction of this graph
which is not white and that increases
now to 57% which is pretty good. So with
pipeline parallelism in theory if you go
to like lots and lots of microbatches
then your MFU is going to be good
because you can do a lot of work in
parallel but the more microbatches you
have they need to store all the
activations in memory. So now we need to
do activation checkpointing. And then
you think like, oh crap, like how do I
tune these things? Should I have more
pipeline parallelism? Should I have
fewer microbatches? Should I have more
aggressive activation checkpointing? And
then should I also layer data
parallelism on top of that? I don't
know. What are you going to do? Maximize
MFU. You're going to try to turn tune
all of those knobs to maximize the MFU
of your of your of your training
pipeline.
Then the last one is tensor parallelism.
So this one um you're going to split on
that dimension on that on that um model
dimension. So basically what we're going
to do is we have a lot of weight
matrices in our model. All those weight
matrices um are like computing XW equals
Y. That's basically what we're doing
over and over again inside of our trans
inside of our transformer. Now the idea
is we'll split each weight matrix across
GPUs kind of and now this is different
from FSTP because we're actually
splitting a single weight matrix across
GPUs and now there's no communication.
Each GPU now we we do a block matrix
multiply. So we um each GPU is now
computing a slice of that matrix
multiply on the full input. So in this
case we split our weight matrix into W1,
W2, W3, W4. Um and then each GPU just
computes a slice of that matrix multiply
to compute a slice of the output. And
then a problem is that now you know
after you do that forward pass then you
need to gather the activations across
all the GPUs to do the next to do the
next forward pass. Um there's a slight
trick which is if you have two of these
layers in sequence, you can actually get
away with not computing with not uh not
gathering in between two layers. So if
you have two layers, you can sit down in
a quiet place and work through this. You
split the first matrix into
column-shaped chunks, then you split the
second matrix into row-shaped chunks.
And if you do all this, then it all kind
of works out magically because of the
magic and mystery of block matrix
multiplication. And you see that the
final output you can kind of compute as
an inner product like structure of these
um of this block of these block matrix
multipliers of Y and U. So then you
basically can have two layers of matrix
multiply um and the that are split
across multiple GPUs and then they only
need to communicate at the end of every
two layers. Um and this actually works
out nicely because remember transformers
have a two-layer MLP in the FFN. So this
is a really nice trick that plays really
nicely into the two-layer MLPS that
transformers always have. So it's pretty
common in big transformers to use tensor
parallelism. This this two this like two
layer tensor parallelism trick um on the
MLP in a transformer.
Um so that's basically all of our
mechanisms for splitting up computation
across GPUs. Which one is the best? The
actual answer is all of them. So in
practice we're going to use ND
parallelism. We saw already an example
of two dimensional parallelism with
HSTP. In practice, you know, the current
state-of-the-art is like
four-dimensional parallelism. If we go
back to Llama, we see that they are
training with their on their biggest
training run with 16,000 GPUs. They're
using 8-way tensor parallelism, 16-way
context parallelism, 16-way pipeline
parallelism, and 8way data parallelism
all at the same time. Um, and if you're
careful in like these different meth
mechanisms of parallelism have different
communication requirements. So if you're
careful in how you arrange these GP how
you arrange these different axes of
parallelism along your cluster, you can
try to take advantage of that varying
speeds of communication across your your
whole cluster.
And that's basically and that's
basically a whirlwind tour of large
scale distributed training. So the
takeaway for today is that an individual
GPU is basically a generalizable
parallel computing machine. A GPU
cluster is a giant massively parallel
machine with tens of thousands, maybe
hundreds of thousands of individual GPUs
that we want to program as one big unit.
And then we talked about multiple
different mechanisms of paralyzing our
computation across big clusters as well
as one trick, activation checkpointing
for saving memory. And then the one
guiding light metric that you're always
trying to optimize when you design these
pipelines, which is model flops
utilization. So, the next time you're
going out and training on tens of
thousands of GPUs, hope you keep this in
mind. Um, and let me know so I can
borrow your tens of thousands of GPUs.