Hi everyone. Um, my name is Zayn. I
realized I actually didn't introduce
myself on the first lecture I gave uh,
which was lecture three, but I'm one of
the co-instructors for the course. My
name is Zane Dante. I'm co-advised by
Essan and Feay. I'm a fourth year PhD
student uh, at Stamford. And in this
lecture today, lecture six, we'll be
talking about training convolutional
neural networks and also um, CNN
architectures.
So um you know I would say this lecture
is really broken up into two different
components. The first one is just
telling you how to piece together all of
the different building blocks that we've
learned like convolutional layers uh
linear layers or fully connected layers
together to create uh CNN architecture.
We'll go through some examples and then
also we'll talk about how you actually
train these and all the steps uh
involved there. So as I mentioned before
we'll have basically two different
topics. The first one is how to build
CNN's and by this I mean how do you
actually define your CNN architecture to
set it up to be trained and then the
second set of topics today is how do you
train CNN's. So starting with the first
set of topics here we'll go through the
layers in convolutional neural networks.
And if you recall from last lecture we
learned about the key layer in these
models which is the convolution layer.
And the way that these layers work is
they have these filters. um you have a
predefined number of filters per one of
these convolution layers. In this case,
six. Um they match the depth of your
input data here. So in this case, we
have a 32x32 RGB image. So we have three
depth channels. Each of these filters
slides across the image and calculates a
score at each point. At that location in
the image, you take the dotproduct of
the values in the filter with the values
in the image. Uh so you multiply all
these values together, you sum them
together, and then you add a bias term.
And this is how you calculate each um
value in your output activation map on
the right. So you have these sliding
windows that go across the image. They
calculate a score at each position and
that's how you get these uh activation
maps and you have one per each filter.
Normally we'll do a sort of relu or a
nonlinearity activation function at the
end here. So this is from last lecture.
I won't spend too much time on it. The
question is for images the depth is
equal to the number of channels RGB but
here the depth is six for the output
here. So if we had a second convolution
layer afterwards they would need to be
filters that uh go across all six of
these uh activation maps. So the next
layer would be a depth of six. Okay. And
then the second layer we talked about
which is much simpler than the
convolution layer is this idea of a
pooling layer. So here um it's still
this sort of filter that we're sliding
across the image uh you know 2 x2 filter
with stride two. So we're skipping over.
We're not doing every single location.
And here is a max pooling. So we're just
taking the max of each of these areas.
And that's the value we get here. Or you
could do an average pooling. Um you know
these are both commonly used I would
say. And depending on the architecture
you would probably just if you're
creating new architecture you would try
both of them and see what performs
better here. But the basic idea is to
consolidate among the height and width
dimensions for your image.
Okay. So um we've basically gone over at
this point in the course all the the top
row here which is convolution layers,
pooling layers and also the fully
connected layers. These are the first
layers that we talked about in the uh
neural networks lecture where it's
basically one matrix multiply followed
by an activation function. And for the
rest of this lecture, I'll talk about
the remaining layers that you see in
CNN's at least the the commonly used
ones which include normalization layers
uh which I'll go into those and then
also dropout which is a regular uh
regularization technique that's used
actually in the model architecture
itself and then finally we'll revisit
the activation functions and I'll tell
you about you know here are the most
commonly used ones both historically and
in the modern era of deep learning. Um,
so starting out with normalization
layers, the basic idea here is we're
going to be calculating statistics like
the mean and standard deviation for our
input data and then using those to
normalize the data and then we'll uh
we'll basically learn what is the uh
optimal distribution for the model to
learn at that point. So so very
concretely we learn parameters that will
scale and shift our input data by a
learned mean and a learned uh standard
deviation. So how all of these
normalization layers work is there's two
steps. The first is to normalize the
data coming in to be a unit Gaussian. So
mean zero, standard deviation one. And
then we will scale and shift it. So
multiply by some value to increase or
decrease the standard deviation and then
shift it to change where the mean is.
And all normalization layers do this
technique. But the way that they differ
is how they calculate the statistics. So
how are you calculating the mean and
standard dev standard deviation and
which values are you applying these
calculated statistics to but all
normalization layers are doing this
highle process.
So um I'll talk about layer norm which
is the most commonly used uh
normalization layer I would say today in
deep learning and it's really commonly
used in transformers specifically um and
so you can imagine you have some data
coming in X which is a batch size of N.
So we have n samples coming into our
model and each of these are vectors of
dimension d. So what it layer norm does
is we calculate a mean and standard
deviation for each of our samples
separately. So we're calculating what is
the mean among the along the depth uh or
or the dimension d here and what is the
standard deviation. Then we learn
parameters and so these are learnable
parameters learned uh through via
gradient descent in our model. uh to
then apply to each sample. So after we
calculate our statistics in this way,
treating each sample separately to
calculate the mean and standard
deviation, we then apply these learned
uh scale and shift or uh parameters
here. So we subtract the mean and divide
by the standard deviation within our
input data to normalize it and then we
apply the scale here but with
multiplication and the the shift. So um
this is the idea behind layer norm and
at a high level layer uh had a high
level idea all of these different uh
normalization layers are all are are all
computing very similar things but the
main difference is how are they
computing the uh the mean and standard
deviation. So this is a really nice
visualization from a paper called group
normalization that introduces a new way
to normalize. um it's I would say not so
commonly used these days but this is
actually a really great way to gain
intuition about how these different
normalization layers are different. So
for layer norm um I described the really
simple case where we just have vectors
that we're normalizing but in the in the
case for convolutional neural networks
we have a channel dimension or the depth
uh we have the in the height and the
width or the spatial dimensions of the
image. So what layerorm does is for each
sample we're still processing it
separately and we're calculating the
mean across all of the channels all of
the heights and all the widths. So if we
look um sort of back into this diagram
here um you would basically be counting
calculating one uh one mean and one
standard deviation over all of these
over all of these values. So um we're
for each of our input uh data points
we're calculating one mean and one
standard deviation across all of the
channels all of the height and width
dimensions. So this is what layer norm
is doing. But you could imagine feasibly
that you could calculate these
statistics differently. Batchnorm uh
you're you're taking each channel so
each channel is being calculated as one
mean and one standard deviation and
you're applying it just to that channel.
Uh and so you're averaging across all
the data in your batch. Instance norm is
even more granular and then a group
norm. So I just want to point out all
these layers are kind of trying to do
the same thing where you're a you're
you're basically normalizing your data
and then having these learnable scaling
and shifting parameters but the way they
do it is different because they're
calculating the statistics using
different variable uh different subsets
of your your input data. Yeah. So the
question is for layer norm are we
calculating one mean and one standard
deviation for each image or input data?
Yes, they're all calculated separately.
>> But for batch norm it's they would not
be the case in this example here. Yeah,
for batch norm it's actually within the
mini batch when you're, you know, you're
doing gradient descent, you have a small
batch of data you're looking at, you
feed it into your model. Um, you're
calculating the per channel, uh, mean
and standard deviation based on all of
the data in your batch.
Yeah, I think this is like a good if you
can understand this diagram, I think you
understand what all of the different uh,
normalization layers are doing. So it
might be worthwhile after lecture if you
still don't fully understand it just to
like go through and make sure you
understand what you know the and shaded
in blue these are the values we're both
calculating our statistics over and then
applying the mean and standard
deviations to uh yeah one final question
and then we'll go on is channel same as
like the layers
>> so channel here is the is the depth here
so the the number of uh spatial
um the different spatial values you have
at each spatial the number of values you
have at each spatial location.
Okay, cool. Um, so this is uh we talked
about normalization layers. The key idea
is you're calculating these statistics,
applying them to your input data and
then uh learning a scale and shift uh
parameter that you then apply. So um the
next type of layer we'll talk about is
called dropout. And this is a
regularization layer in CNN's. This is
the final layer that you'll need to
learn in order to basically we can start
going through all these different CNN
architectures that people have created
over the years. Um so with dropout the
basic idea is to add randomization
during the training process that we then
take away at test time and the goal is
to make it harder for the model to learn
the training data but then it will
generalize better. So this is a form of
regularization.
The way we do it concretely is that in
each forward pass of our layer, we'll
actually randomly zero out some of the
outputs or activations from that from
that layer. And uh the main parameter
you have for this dropout layer, which
is just a fixed hyperparameter, is the
probability of dropping out the values.
And 0.5 is probably the most common or
0.25 is also commonly used here. Um so
you're just dropping out a fixed
percentage of the values here. And so uh
you know going forward to the next layer
these would be zero. Um and so you don't
you don't really need to calculate the
um the values here. So um I mean
basically all the all the outputs here
are zero at this point. So you can get
there's some tricks you can do with
masking. So you don't even need to
calculate the values because 0 times any
value will be uh will be zero. So um I
think in general uh you might ask why
does this work? And um I would say this
is more of an empirical thing than a uh
well wellstudied from a um from a
theoretical standpoint. But um there are
actually some ways you can view what
dropout is doing to gain intuition of
why this might be useful. So um it it
basically forces your network to you can
imagine it forces it to have redundant
representations. So if we have a list of
features that we're learning at a given
layer, say the the layer right before
the output of our model, and we have a
CNN that is basically extracting each of
these features. So it can detect if
there's ears in the image or if there's
a tail, if it's furry, it has claws. And
you want to uh your model to output the
probability of a cat score. So um one of
the things that's useful about this is
because some of these values might
randomly be dropped out during training,
your model can't over rely on certain
features being present. in in uh some of
the classes and actually needs to learn
a more broad uh set of correspondences
between your features and your your
output classes. So the model can't just
you know hard focus on uh okay well if
if it has an ear and is furry these are
and you know it just so happens that
these are always cats uh or something
like this or if it has claws um and it
has an ear it'll it'll almost always be
a cat on your data set. So it'll
actually help you generalize better to
new new features despite the fact that
in your data set there might actually be
really strong correlations between the
codependency of certain features in your
output class. By having dropout you're
essentially making it so the model can't
rely on these during the training phase
because it won't always see the pairs of
features together. So this is an example
for for for cat and the question is if
we had something like tree instead how
would you determine which features to
drop out? So, uh, the dropping out part
is actually completely random. So, we're
not making any choices about this. It's
just in this case, 50% of your your
features at any given step will be
dropped out and set to zero. Um, so
yeah, you don't have to make choices
about it, which is kind of nice. Um, but
it is completely random.
How would the model know if you're only
seeing a subset of the features like
tail and claw here? Um, the point is you
will actually do worse on the training
data because you're only seeing a subset
of the features. So it does make the
model worse by not having all the
information. Uh but then it does better
at test time is the idea. So worse in
training time and better in test time
because at test time um you're basically
no longer having this dropout. So the
final component here which maybe I
should have explained first before
fielding questions is the idea at test
time you're no longer dropping out any
of the values. So this is randomness
that we're adding during the training
phase only. Then at test time we're uh
ne we're never masking any of the output
activations and we're removing this
dropout uh idea altogether. Now one
thing we need to note is that because if
we were dropping out 50% of the
activations uh during training time at
test time you're basically having 50%
more values that are being input to uh
each of your uh layers. And so this can
cause issues if you don't scale it. So
what you need to do is multiply by the
probability of dropout so that the um
the sort of magnitude of the values
coming into each layer is preserved
during training and test time. Otherwise
if you're dropping 50% of the values and
then at test time you just include all
of them you'll get really weird behavior
because um you'll be seeing much larger
magnitude of inputs than before.
>> Yeah. So what about for backward prop?
Uh so for back prop when you have these
zeroed values yeah it's sort of like uh
you don't uh you you don't need to
traverse that uh path of your directed
graph anymore. It's very similar to relu
if you have a a zeroed value at that
point. Um the gradient becomes zero. So
um anything be sort of uh further back
in your computational graph uh there's
no gradients calculated at that point.
If you're dropping out um certain values
or activations, the weights associated
with those specific activations will not
be updated uh during gradient descent if
you're dropping them out. Yeah. So the
question is um maybe I'll reframe it.
What are we doing at test time? So at
test time we are using all of the um
output activations. We're not dropping
them out anymore, but we need to scale
by the probability of dropout. So we
multiply each of our output activations
by this p value because now we're using
all of them. Uh so otherwise the uh you
can imagine you have each node is sort
of seeing a significantly higher number
of inputs than it did during training at
test time. So you need to uh multiply by
this p value to maintain the same uh
magnitude of your your your inputs
coming in and uh the variance stays the
same and all these different properties
it works very nicely if you do it like
this. Yeah. So the question is can you
just add noise to the image instead? The
answer is yes and we'll go over how to
do that in future slides. Yes, that's a
great idea to add noise to your image.
Okay. Um, some specific code here. I
won't go over this because we already
mentioned this, but you know, you're
dropping a um a p percentage of your
activations here and then you multiply
here at test time.
Okay. Um the the next topic I'll talk
about is activation functions. So, you
all have basically learned all of the
key layers now in CNN's and now we're
going to be talking about these
activation functions. If you remember,
the whole point of these activation
functions is to introduce nonlinearities
to our model. So, um right now with
these convolution operators, the kernel
sighting across the image and the simple
layers without act uh sorry, the fully
connected layers without um activations,
they're all just linear operations
because they're multiplications and
additions. Um and the whole point of the
activation function is to add
nonlinearity. So um historically sigmoid
is a really commonly was a really
commonly used activation function but
there's actually a key problem with
sigmoid that is the reason why it's no
longer used today. And so sigmoid if you
graph it looks like this. You can see
the equation in the top right of the
slide here. And um the main issue is
that empirically what happened was after
many layers of sigmoids you would get
smaller and smaller gradients as you're
computing back props. So starting from
the end the gradients are fairly large
in magnitude and as you undergo multiple
layers of back propagation go to the
initial early layers of your model um
you would get smaller and smaller
gradients as you do this process. So
I'll actually open this question up to
the class um you know this isn't a a
phenomenon we see that occurs with
sigmoid and so in what reason reason uh
regions in our graph does sigmoid have a
really small gradient? Yeah so very
negative and very positive values is
correct and this is actually a huge
issue. I mean you can visually see here
in the graph the gradient's very flat at
you know you're taking the derivative
here it's very small um and so basically
for almost all of our input space uh
from negative infinity to positive
infinity you have very small gradients
and it's only this narrow range in the
middle where you have something that's
uh non non zero so it basically
approaches zero very quickly on both
ends of the extremes and so this means
that if the values coming into sigmoid
are very large or very small then your
gradient will be uh very
So this is one of the main reasons why
relu became super popular because now in
the positive region we don't have any of
this behavior. Um it's just a derivative
of one here. Um but in in practice you
still have this flat portion here on the
left where um you know your gradient is
zero. Um so so now we basically have
half of our input uh domain here. we we
get a gradient of one and the other half
is zero which is better than almost all
of it being zero or very close to zero
except for a small region in the middle.
So in practice these work better also
it's much cheaper to just compute a max
operation between zero and your input
value than the sigmoid function. So for
those two reasons, Railus became super
popular. Um but you still have this
issue where for any negative input, you
get a zero gradient. And so um more
recently, there's been uh popular
activation functions that avoid this um
by basically having a non-flat section
of the activation function in the nearby
neighborhood uh to near zero. So um this
is Gaoo and there's also Celu which I'll
show in a slide but I won't go over the
formula. They look very similar. Um the
basic idea is to smoothen out the this
uh non non smooth jump here in the in
the derivative from 0 to 1 at 0 for RLU.
So um no you know this is a very sharp
uh uh and non smooth function with RLU.
But the nice part about Gillu is we
actually have nonzero gradients here.
And in the limit as x approaches
infinity or negative infinity, it does
converge to uh relu as well. But you get
sort of more smooth behavior in the
middle here. And specifically what GU
calculates is this um Gaussian error
linear unit. So this is the uh
cumulative distribution function of a
Gaussian normal. So if you imagine the
area under the curve of a Gaussian uh
that's what this 5x is at any point x.
So if you have a really uh negative
value here you'll have a value close to
zero which is why it sort of converges
to relu zero here and then a very uh
high positive value it gets very close
to one the area under the curve so it
converges to x here. So um this is gau
it has these nice properties and it
converges to relu at the extremes too
and this is the main uh activation
function used in transformers today.
Um if you look at all of them and you
kind of squint a lot of these kind of
look the same. The basic idea is
something relatively flat and then it uh
in the limit it approaches x equals uh
sorry f ofx equals x um and and sort of
it becomes a linear line. Um so celu is
actually x * sigmoid of x um which also
has this property of for a very negative
value you have something close to zero
and for a very positive value uh it's
close to one. So it's actually similar
to the um cumulative distribution
function for the unit Gaussian that is
fi here. So that's why the the shapes
are actually really similar looking too.
Okay. Um so you might ask where are
these activations used in CNN's and the
general answer is that they're placed
after linear operators. So almost
anytime we have a feed forward or a
linear layer or a fully connected layer,
these are all words for the same layer.
So matrix multiply followed by
activation function. um or if we have a
convolutional layer pretty much after
these is where we place the the so after
the convolutional layer or after these
linear layers we'll put the the
activation function.
Okay, so you've learned everything now
about all the components of CNN's and
I'll now go through some examples of how
we put them together and how people have
created state-of-the-art convolutional
neural network architectures.
Um I think this is a really neat slide
because it plots two different values.
So on one hand we have the error rate
which is these blue bars and this is
over time. So these are different models
people have trained on imageet and then
you have these orange triangles which
represent the number of layers uh that
models have and you can see at the same
point that we have a significant drop in
error where we actually surpass human
performance for the first time we see uh
a huge increase in the number of layers.
So we'll go over in class today how they
were able to achieve this and what were
the design challenges and goals for how
they how they did this. Um historically
AlexNet was the first sort of CNN based
paper that worked really well on imageet
and they used they were able to train it
by using GPUs. We talked about this
earlier in lecture, so I won't spend too
much details around AlexNet from a
historical lens, but I do want to
compare it to another architecture
called VGG, um, which was a really
standard and commonly used uh,
architecture in the 2010s. And I think,
uh, I can plot the two, uh, CNN
architectures together side by side
here. So in general in AI, we like to
plot our model architectures using block
diagrams where each block represents a
different layer or a group of layers
that are stacked together. And it also
helps you gain intuition about you know
what are the general differences just at
a at an initial glance. So these orange
blocks which are the common ones here
are 3x3 convolution layers. So these are
convolution layers that have filters
that are sliding across that are size
3x3. Uh their stride is one. So they're
visiting every location in the image,
not skipping over anything. And they add
padding of one around the outside so
that we're we're not shrinking as we do
these convolution uh uh layers. And so
um they also add these pooling max
pooling layers throughout here too. And
you'll notice that for all of these they
have um after a pooling layer they'll
start doing two sets of fully connected
layers of dimension uh 4096 followed by
a dimension of a thousand. And the
reason we have a thousand at the end is
because imageet was a thousand different
image categories. So we need to have
scores for each of these categories. So
the final layer is always uh equal to
the number of classes you have for for
image classification problem.
Um, and so you can see it actually looks
extremely similar. It's sort of just
like a scaled up version of Alexet with
more uh layers here. And also they're
now doing some uh sort of three groups
of convolutions at a time followed by
pooling rather than uh two layers in a
pooling or even one. Um so it is
actually pretty remarkable that there's
only basically uh three different types
of layers right in these models but they
they perform extremely well compared to
anything people had tried before at this
point. Um so these are I would say the
simplest layers. You might uh simplest
models we're going to discuss today. But
you might ask why are they doing three
by uh 3x3 convolutions like how do they
pick this this value? And um there is
actually some intuition behind how they
chose 3x3. So um and specifically they
have groups of three or even four of
these. So I'll ask you all a question.
Um what is the effective receptive
field? So we we looked at receptive
field um last time but it's it's
basically the idea of the parts of your
input image that a particular value in
your activation map has seen before. So
what values have been used to compute
the final activation map after many
layers of your model. So we have three
of these layers that are all 3x3
convolutions with this sliding filter
with stride of one. What is the
effective receptive field of each value
in our activation
map A3 here? So this is after the third
layer.
So I'm showing one of the layers here.
You can see for each value in A3, it's
computed by looking at a 3x3 grid of
values in A2. And then conceivably for
each one in A2, it's a 3x3 grid in A1.
And for each of those, it's a 3x3 grid
in our input. So uh I'll let you all
think about this for a little bit. Uh
maybe it will help to see the next uh
layer here. So it is actually really
helpful to visualize this. So at A1,
each of the corners here, you know,
we're calculating a new from a new 3x3
grid here. Um, so from our input, how
large is this overall square? 7 by 7.
Yeah, exactly. So this first one is 3x3,
this next one is 5x 5, and then the next
one is 7 by 7. And we can visualize it
here uh pretty easily. So the nice thing
about the 3x3 convolution with stride
one is that uh you're basically always
adding two to your receptive field at
each layer because um you know each
point here you're looking to the left
and to the right and above and below it.
So after you have many blocks of those
you're just adding two each time.
Okay. Um so we basically just showed
that a stack of three of these 3x3
convolution and stride one layers has
the same effective field as one 7 by7
layer.
>> Yeah. So the question is how much of
this is justification after the fact
versus how much of this is intuition
that they then use to say design the
experiments. Um I think it actually
probably depends on the architecture. So
for some of them it's more intuition
focused. And actually the one we're
going to cover next I think really was
uh the whole research direction was
spawned by an empirical finding that
there's a thought experiment about. So
that's resonates and I think for there
there's actually pretty good intuition
that led the whole investigation into
what will work well. Um, but then for
this one, I mean, I I I can't say for I
can't speak for the authors um whether
it's justification after effect or um
you know, based on empirical findings or
um or if it was involved in the design
choices because I haven't seen them
speak publicly about that yet. But for
resonance, I do know it it was the the
hypothesis that led to the creation. Um
but this is actually a really nice
property. So three of these 3x3's have
the same effective receptive field as
one 7x7 layer and it actually has fewer
parameters too. So um we have if you
imagine our channel dimension is saying
stay staying the same. Uh you have these
3x3 grids where um you have you know
your input number of channels. So 3 * 3
* c would be the number of values in
each of these filters. And if we have c
of these filters it's 3 * 3 * c * c or 3
c ^ 2 and we have three layers total. So
um sort of if we look at it through this
lens, it's actually um it's actually
fewer parameters and we're having a more
complex um and more nonlinear model uh
that we're building here. So fewer
parameters and it can model more complex
relationships among your input data. So
this is maybe why stacking these 3x3
layers together um could be better than
having just a larger filter that you're
sliding across. So fewer parameters and
then also you can model more complex
relationships.
Okay. Um I'll now talk about resonance
which I I guess I'll very much bring up
the thought experiment that someone just
asked a question about. So um there was
actually an empirical finding that
spawned a lot of the um conversation and
thought around designing ResNets and the
idea was um actually shown that if you
keep stacking deeper layers on a plain
CNN network like something like this and
you just keep adding layers to it, you
build it larger and larger. What
happens? So what we found and what they
found is that um the 20 layer model will
actually have a lower test error than a
56 layer model. And you might think that
this is because of overfitting, but it's
actually not because if we look at the
training error, the training error of
this 20 layer model is also lower. So it
has a lower training and a lower test
error. Basically means that the model is
doing better on all accounts. Um so why
is this 56 layer model performing worse
than a 20 layer model? it doesn't you
know you might it might be confusing and
we know as I mentioned right before it's
it's not caused by overfitting
so these deeper models have more
representational power and theoretically
they should be able to uh represent any
model that a more shallow network uh can
can model. So the the set of possible um
uh mappings between your inputs and
different values for your larger
networks is a is a superset of for your
smaller networks. Uh because
theoretically you could imagine that um
you basically are just setting some of
these layers to be the identity function
where um they're the layers doing
nothing and then you would have if you
set half your layers to do nothing you
have exactly the same representation
power as a as a model one half the size.
So the idea is not that um these models
are worse, but we're in terms of the
representational power, but they're
actually harder to optimize because this
the set of possible models for your your
deeper networks is larger and it
contains all of the possible models that
your your your more shallow networks
could could learn.
So I sort of hinted at it before, but
how specifically could the deeper model
learn to be at least as good as a
shallow model? It's by setting. So if we
have a two-layer model versus a one
layer, uh so one layer here and two
layer on the right. If we set one of the
layers to just essentially be a identity
matrix or you know this is just an
identity function, the the the model
should be at least as good as the
shallow model.
Um it should be at least as good as a
So how do we actually build this
intuition into our models? We want them
to be able to be just as good as a
shallower model if they want to be uh
during optimization. So the way that we
do this is actually by fitting what's
called a residual mapping instead of
directly trying to fit a desired
underlap underlying mapping. And what
this looks like is we basically take the
value x and we copy it over past our
convolution layers. So that um the value
at this point is already receiving x our
original input as well as the output of
our two convolution stacks. So um
basically at this point this f ofx or
which is called the residual map here um
it could just learn uh zero values for
the uh all the com filters and the
output would be zero here and then we
would just add x uh along here and we
would get x. So it allows a very simple
way for the model to bypass these layers
if it doesn't need to learn anything for
the layers. And what this means is you
can really easily now learn uh basically
this identity function that we talked
about earlier by just learning uh zero
zero filters. So your filters all are
filled with zero values for example
or uh in this case more practically what
happens is they just need to learn very
small values because instead of learning
the uh this entire mapping from x to h
of x they just need to learn this
difference which is f ofx. So um you're
now just learning this sort of
difference between your desired output
here and um the the copied over block.
This is called uh residual block or
residual connection residual connection
when you copy over values from an
earlier layer into a later layer in your
model and then you just add it to the
the values at that point.
So that I talked a bit about the
intuition which was this observed
phenomenon that these larger networks
were achieving worse training and worse
test error because they were harder to
optimize. So the intuition was we need
to build a model that can really easily
model the shallower networks so it can
be at least as good as a shallower
model. The way they did this was by
adding a residual connection so that you
can just copy over the values easily um
build that into the architecture itself
rather than trying to learn some
identity mapping among the convolutional
layers. And empirically this showed to
work extremely well too. Yeah. So what
does the residual block carry? Um so we
have our input X. We pass it through two
different convolutional layers and we
get our output f ofx. Um x is lit is
just copied over here. So this is
exactly the same as X and we add it to
the output of uh these two blocks which
is f ofx. Yeah, x is the output of one
of the previous layers or if it's the
very first layer of the model it would
be the the image.
>> Yeah. So the question is if maybe you
just don't have enough data and if you
added enough data then maybe you could
train a model without these blocks. Um I
think these blocks actually do extremely
help you with learning from more data.
Um I think the issue it was really an
optimization problem. So transformers
use residual blocks for exactly the same
reason because uh and I think it
actually helps you model these more
complex models and it actually enables
you to use more data. So um I I think
it's very good residual blocks help you
use more data more efficiently because
you're able to model a greater number
you're able to more easily model a
greater number of uh functions.
Yeah. So the question is that um maybe
if we just trained for longer um the
performance would eventually converge to
the value of the smaller network and
maybe it's just harder to optimize
because it takes longer to train a a
larger model. Um and I think the answer
is no that these um these these were not
uh like they were not converging to the
performance of the smaller model
regardless of how long you trained it.
And the reason is because it's being
stuck in essentially local minimum uh
and when you add these residual
connections you're uh avoiding these.
This is the actual explanation why this
is the case is still I would say being a
more active area of research. Um it's
really hard to understand exactly what
causes these models to um avoid local a
global minimum or sorry to avoid local
minimum and not get an optimal solution
or to uh what causes them to not train
uh and find better solutions. And often
times this is really an empirical
finding but there's some intuition
behind it. And in this case the
intuition was that uh we want to enable
our models to do at least as well as the
shallower models which we know were
performing better at the time. Um, so
it's not that you could just train it
for longer and it would uh do better.
Um, it was actually a limitation where
it was no longer it was un just
completely unable to achieve as good as
the shallower models.
Okay. Um,
so here's the overall ResNet
architecture. Um, we have these stacks
of residual blocks now. So that's what
these two blocks here together mean. um
it's a residual uh block. So we have a
3x3 convolution with a relu followed by
another 3x3 convolution and we're
copying over this x value here. We're
adding it to the outputs here and then
we're having a relu afterwards. So each
of these pairs of blocks is one of these
residual and that's why you see this
line skipping over here because the
values getting added forward. Um the
cool thing about ResNets also um is that
they uh basically had a lot of these
different um depths that they created.
So they created a whole family of
models, some smaller and some larger.
And they showed that as they increased
the number of layers, their performance
was increasing, albeit the the sort of
the difference in performance as you got
to the larger and larger models became
smaller. So it was sort of reaching a
point of given the data set uh they
weren't able to scale any significant
amount by adding more layers further
than that but you they saw significant
improvements in performance among
especially the earlier models and then
101 to 152 is where the performance it
wasn't really change it was marginally
better but uh performance change was
maybe only like 1% at that point. Yeah.
How did they get the number of 152? I
actually don't know how they got the
number of 152. Uh I think they wanted to
try different values here and you can
see that I mean they're not exactly
doubling but you know there's sort of
you know a significant increase in each
time. I don't know how they picked 152.
I I that's a good question. Maybe they
showed it somehow worked better than
other I actually don't know though. So
generally when you're trying multiple
different uh number of layers for your
model like given that say these are the
number of layers you want to try um what
you'll do is you'll sort of first train
the smallest model see performance and
then add more layers see if your
performance increases and go on so
forth. So that's probably why they
stopped at 152 is because performance
wasn't increases as much anymore. Um and
also there's GPU memory limitations. So
as you get larger and larger models, it
becomes harder to train from a hardware
perspective because you need to fit more
parameters into your GPU memory. So um
there is like a limit for given your
compute setup how large of a model you
can train. Um I think you need to train
these models separately though. So um
you have one model run for 18 layers and
one for 34 etc.
So the question is um how to think of
intuition of CNN blocks given we're
using these residual connections because
um you can still think of it as higher
levels of abstraction and this is shown
to be true in the layers. So um you're
you're not in instead of learning the um
within the block itself instead of just
learning the higher level features
you're learning the delta from the
original image to get the higher level
features. That's what you're learning in
the block. So you're learning the delta
but you're still achieving these higher
level representations at each step. So
that part is the same but the actual
functional way of doing it is we're
learning this uh right you learn this f
ofx that you add your your your previous
input to. So it's like you're learning
the delta. The question is if you do
addition does that require you to have
the same tensor size? The answer is yes.
And uh it's part of the reason why it's
really a nice property that all of these
ones have this 3x3 convolution with
stride one so that you maintain the in
one padding so that you maintain the
same size uh at every at every layer
going forward. So after you had say a
pooling layer, you wouldn't I mean you
could maybe come up with a way to do it
where you double the you know you
increase uh you sort of unpool the
values. Uh but after a pooling layer for
example you couldn't do a naive addition
anymore because the size of your tensors
are different. So these are done within
you know before a pool
at least the regular one. I mean you
could get around it by just having each
value be spread out on into multiple
values for example.
Okay. Um so these are basically the main
takeaways for ResNets. Um one other neat
trick they do is they basically
periodically after a certain number of
these blocks they'll uh double the
number of filters and down sample the
spatial dimension. Um so basically you
can imagine if you start with a really
flat uh image as the activations get
pushed through the network it becomes
smaller spatially but then the depth is
larger. So um this is how to think of it
and then at the very end it just becomes
a vector that you then use for
classification. So that's how you should
be like visualizing what's happening to
the values in the network itself and the
shape of them. And then one other sort
of thing that's somewhat unique to
ResNets other architectures do this too
but before all these uh layers with the
residual blocks they have uh this
relatively larger convolution layer and
here is just empirically shown that it
did better if they added this here. So
this one is purely empirical finding.
Okay. Um I think um yeah basically to
highlight you know it did extremely well
these larger models. It was the only it
was the first time they were able to
train 100 plus layer models
successfully. So it was a really big
deal and basically resnets were used in
a huge variety of computer vision tasks
afterwards. Almost every task in
computer vision was using a resnet at
the time because they performed so well
because of these residual connections.
Okay. Um so we talked about some CNN
architectures the main ones being the
main one being ResNet and then uh also
VGG historically. So we talked about why
the smaller filter size is useful and
having many layers of these is useful.
So the final thing I'll talk about in
terms of how we actually construct the
CNN's and prime them to be ready for
training is how do you actually
initialize the weight values of the
individual layers.
So um you know depending on what values
you choose you could either put values
that are too small or too large which
would cause significant issues for your
model during training. So here we're
it's basically a um six layer network
where we have uh 4096dimensional
uh features and this is just a fully six
layers of fully connected model and we
initialize them here. This is getting a
unit gaussian random and then we're
multiplying it by 0.01 to get very small
values close to zero and we have you
know ru at each layer too. So if you
plot the forward pass of this model, uh
you would actually see that at the
beginning you get a relatively high you
know cuz it's rel so all the means are
going to be positive. Um but you'll have
a mean and standard deviation that is
relatively high but as each layer
progresses because we had a really small
weight initialization um it becomes
smaller and smaller mean and standard
deviation. And really ideally we would
want basically all these to be the same
for each layer. Um because it makes our
optimization problem much nicer to
solve.
Um so if we say use 0.05 instead of 0.01
uh can anyone imagine what might be the
issue here if we set it to too large of
a value. So what's too when it's too
small it goes to zero basically. What
happens if it's too large? Yeah.
Basically the activations get larger and
larger at each layer. So uh if you plot
it here you can see that you know by the
end there's just a massive mean and
standard deviation and if you're
training a 152 layer ResNet and you know
you can imagine this becomes quite an
issue very quickly. So how do you
actually uh do this? So in this case um
you know maybe the the optimal value I
think is 0.022 or something but how
would you actually know that and how
would you do this more generally across
any layer? Um, there are a few different
ways you can initialize weights. And
I'll go over the most commonly used one
today in class, but know there are other
ones. And generally what they're a
function of is the dimension of your um
of your of your values here. So you'll
have a different value for a 4096
dimension uh fully connected layer
versus a 2048. And the specific formula
we'll go through um is called Kaiming
initialization is actually the same
person who created uh resonance. So
Kaiming Hu he was you know very famous I
mean he still is a very famous computer
vision researcher. I think he's one of
the most widely cited computer
scientists of the last uh 10 or 15
years, maybe the most. Uh so he he's
extremely well known in the computer
vision community and he also came up
with uh this idea of initializing the
values to the square root of two over
your input dimension size. And I won't
go over all the details for how they uh
derived this and showed that with a relu
activation this would cause the standard
deviation and mean to be relatively
constant throughout the layers. But if
you do uh plot it, you see this does
have the effect. So you can almost think
of this as a magic formula where if you
plug it in, you get the desired
properties. And if you want to know the
derivation, you can actually uh we link
the paper here. So feel free to look
into that, but you can just sort of uh
take our word. I won't go through the
details here, but um it does this
desired effect where the mean and
standard deviation is unchanging. And
you can also imagine that for any given
setup, you could also just through
testing try to find what is the what is
the value here.
Okay. Um, so these are how you we
discuss how you initialize weights, how
you combine these different layers
together to form a CNN architecture,
which activations function, which
activation functions people use, and
then all the different layers and CNN's.
So I think already we covered quite a
few topics. So I think I'll pause very
briefly to see if there's any questions
about these. In the second part of the
lecture, it's actually much less dense
than the first part. So we'll be mainly
going over a lot of nice practical tips
for when you're training these models.
So the question is how do you do weight
initialization for CNN's? So you still
use this same uh initialization but your
dimension in here is the size of your
kernel. So if you have a 3x3 kernel with
channels uh say six it would be 3 * 3 *
6 that is but it's the same idea. It's
just you calculate your dimensions
differently depending on the layer the
type of layer. Yeah.
It's you can think of it's the number of
values roughly in each operation but it
does depend on the layer and and some
layers use different uh weight
initializations but this is specifically
for CNN's how this timing initialization
applies to it.
>> Yeah. So the question is why do your
activations expose explode if you have
too large of an initialization value? So
um if you so you you imagine at each
layer of your initialized network you
have um a set of randomly initialized
values and if they're very large then um
when you do your um you know you have a
RLU activation afterwards and that
doesn't actually cap the um the the
outputs of your layer right you can go
to infinity with RLU so if you have a
too large of a set of values that you're
essentially repeating the same operation
on because you're initializing all the
weights uh to the same set of uh random
values. Then at each layer, you'll be
multiplying one set of large values by a
set that's been initialized too large so
that it becomes larger at each uh
iteration afterwards. I I I mean you
could think of it as it's sort of like a
recurrence relation where u because
they're all initialized randomly at the
start where it's being multiplied by a
value and you would want in a simple
recurrence relation you'd want it to be
one, right? But because we have a vector
of values that are being multiplied by
our matrix um it depends on the
dimension of the vector what your
average uh output would be and what the
uh sort after the relu because um you
have basically a standard deviation for
what is your activations then you you
remove all the negative ones and you're
left with what are your outputs at that
point and if you have a really large
values you have a really large standard
deviation so when you remove the the uh
the bottom half of it you get your your
starts moving more positive and more
positive. Uh, did that make sense? It's
sort of I didn't have slides to show it,
but okay. Mostly sorry. Yeah, you can
see more details in the paper. It's
actually not too bad to read, I think.
>> So, the the conclusion of the discussion
here is that normalization will solve
this activation
issue where they're blowing up, but it
still might be harder to optimize. Um
maybe we can we should probably do a
follow-up post on Edge explaining this
in more detail, but I think it's a
really good question actually. Yeah. Um
it would solve I think this particular
issue, but maybe it's still hard to do
something like this in the discussion.
Yeah, it's a good question.
Okay,
cool. Um so I'll talk about these steps
now. So how do you actually train your
model? And uh the nice thing for data
prep-processing is it's really easy for
images. So if you have your giant image
data set, the standard way to do it is
you calculate the average red, the
average green and the average blue pixel
along with the standard deviations and
you take your input image, you subtract
the mean and you divide by the standard
deviation. And this is how you this is
how you do uh data normalization for
images. It's actually very
straightforward. Um so it does require
you to premp compute the means and
standard and standard deviation for each
pixel channel. Um so sometimes what
people will do is they'll use means that
have already been calculated like a very
common one is to use the imageet uh
means and standard deviations and uh
apply those to your input images even if
you're training a model not on imageet.
Um so it it is very um data set
dependent is is is the way to think of
this and different models will use
different values here depending on their
data set but the most commonly used one
is just use the mean and standard
deviation from image net. Yeah. So any
input image you've apply this operation
before the model sees it.
Okay. Um so yeah that one was really
quick. Um and then in terms of data
augmentation, so someone had a
suggestion uh earlier in the class, why
don't we just add noise to our uh image?
And that's a great idea and we'll talk
about the different ways you can add
noise to your image here. This helps
with regularization and helps prevent
your model from overfitting.
So we talked about it before um but this
is sort of a common pattern with
regularization where during training
time you add some kind of randomness and
then at testing time you then average
out the randomness. So um sometimes this
is approximate but you know for example
for dropout we saw that during training
time we'll randomly drop say 50% of the
activations and then at testing time
we'll use all the activations but then
we'll need to scale it down by this
probability of dropout P. Um so this is
a really common pattern and it's also
used for data augmentation. So um you
can imagine this uh being a this
cylinder here is like your data set. you
load an image and a label. So we have a
cat label and we have our original image
from our data set um before we actually
pass it into our model. It's extremely
common and basically always in in modern
deep learning people will always use
data augmentation for training uh
computer vision models. But the basic
idea is to apply some transformations to
the image to make it look different uh
but still recognizable for the category
class and then pass that to your model
and you're computing the loss here. So
one of the nice benefits of this is you
can effectively increase the size of
your data set because instead of seeing
each image multiple times, it will be
seeing different versions of the image
with different transformations that all
still are the same category label. So
you can basically get more data and
therefore it increases your
generalization capabilities, but your
training loss will be higher because um
you're not just seeing the same example
over and over again. So it makes it
harder for the model to just memorize.
So how do we know the weight
initialization is just right? So we know
it's right in this case because the
means and the standard deviations are
relatively constant throughout the
layers of the network and we're not
seeing uh in this case we saw sort of uh
mode collapse to zero. In this case it
was sort of blowing up to infinity as we
increase the number of layers. So the
way you can ensure it always happens is
by using the formula. This will always
initialize them. Well um so in practice
that's how people do it. If you were
creating a new layer um that maybe does
some different kind of operation that no
one's done before, then yeah, you
probably would need to try a bunch of
different weight initialization schemes
and see what works best. Um but
generally for these linear layers or for
or the convolutional layers, you can use
this uh formula here which is called the
kiming initialization. Yeah.
Okay. Um so back to data augmentation.
Um, so what are the different
augmentations you can do specifically?
So one of them is horizontal flipping.
This depends on the problem. Um, so if
you want to have a model that reads
text, this would be a very bad
augmentation to use because the text is
now it's like you're looking through a
mirror and you can't read it properly.
Um, so this is sometimes useful for
everyday objects. It's usually pretty
good because most objects are
symmetrical. So this property uh
actually works pretty well. Um, and then
you could also imagine if you're looking
maybe at images from a microscope or
overhead that you could also do a
vertical flip and that would make sense.
But for everyday objects, vertical
flipping actually doesn't really make
sense because a cat is almost always
seen in this position. But maybe if you
had a data set where cats were in all
different orientations, you could
imagine that flipping or rotating or all
these things would make sense for for
your data set.
Um, another type of augmentation is this
resizing and cropping idea. So what
ResNets and many um different image
models in uh deep learning do is they
basically take a random crop of the
image and uh then resize that to be your
image size. They might even take another
crop afterwards. So the most common
strategy is you pick the length of what
is basically the short side of your
image. Um so if you have a input image
size to your model of 224 x 224 pixels
you would pick a value larger than this
first and uh find sort of find some crop
of your image that contains these uh
this larger scale L uh and this these
are commonly used values. You crop the
image um so you you you uh sorry you
don't crop you resize the image to be uh
that scale. So instead of say this is a
800 by 600 image if we used 256 here um
we resize the short side. So 600 would
be 256 and then 800 would be scaled
correspondingly. So we scale it to this
L. We scale the short side to L. And
then we crop a random patch of 224x 224
pixels from that image. So you're
scaling the image by first preserving
you preserve the relative resolution but
you make it smaller or larger to fit
this L and then you take a random crop
of that. And this is like by far the
most commonly used uh rand random
resized crop is what it's called in most
libraries. So this is used in most
problems because it works pretty well
and it reserves the relative uh
resolution of your of your images. Um
and then there's another neat trick you
can do with augmentation called test
time augmentation. So if you really just
want to get the best performance
possible, you can basically get a bunch
of these different crops and resizes and
run them all through your model and then
average your predictions at the end. And
for ResNets, people will often try a
bunch of different scales, um, a bunch
of different crop locations, and, uh,
maybe even flip it. And usually you'll
start getting diminishing returns, but
you can get actually pretty good like 1
to 2% performance boost by using this
sort of test time augmentation. So if
you're in a setting where it really
matters, you're trying to eek out every
last bit of percentage points, then this
is actually a really great trick that
you can use for any almost any computer
vision problem.
Um, okay. So a final sort of few
augmentations. One is color jitter. So
here we're specifically randomizing the
contrast and brightness and scaling the
image correspondingly. So maybe images
look more muted or more sorry the colors
look more muted or more um brighter. But
these are sort of very traditional uh
image processing techniques. And usually
with all these different augmentations,
you'll try different values and see
which ones make your images still look
in distribution and look normal to you
as a human. And that's like a pretty
good way to judge what values you should
pick for how much jitter you should
have, how much brightness variance, uh,
etc. So, normally when I'm starting a
problem, I'll try a bunch of these
different augmentations. I'll see what
is making the data look different from
the original data, but then still
recognizable to me and still very easy
to recognize. And that's like generally
a good set of augmentations to use. Um,
final one is you can imagine just like
cropping out parts of the image where
you just are basically putting a black
or a gray box over it. Um, and I think
this one's maybe less commonly used, but
it kind of shows you how you can get
creative with the augmentations
depending on your problem. Like say
you're in a setting where things will
get covered, like the the the camera
will be oluded, so it won't be able to
see the objects fully. This could be a
really neat trick you do to make your
model more resilient to stuff blocking
parts of your objects. So, you could
almost imagine for your given setting,
what augmentations make sense? what ways
can you uh transform your your input
data so that it's still recognizable to
you as a human but it makes it harder
for the model to memorize the training
examples.
Okay. Um so the final set of topics here
are basically extremely practical. So
when you're say doing a project or uh
training a model say for your course
project um I think you should basically
do the exact things we're going to be
describing in the coming slides. Um but
this also applies outside the course to
any computer vision domain you could be
uh practicing in. So um in practice in
many times we don't actually have so
much data. You know imageet the original
version had a million images. Uh maybe
you don't have a million images for your
problem which almost none of us do
unless you've been collecting vast
amount of data with a huge team. So um
if you don't have a lot of data can you
still train CNN's and the short answer
is yes you can but you need to be a
little bit smart with how you do it.
So um I think in one of the I think
maybe it was last lecture we showed how
the different uh filters in your CNN are
sort of extracting different uh types of
features. So this goes back to someone
asked about like the hierarchy of
features in convolutional neural
networks. So at the beginning it's more
of just like edges or patterns or or
really small shapes. And then at the
highest level um you can imagine uh if
we put an image into our CNN and we get
this uh final uh vector right before we
get our class scores and we compare that
to other images in our data set. Um
you'll actually see that these these
values uh of the vector of our image are
actually really close. So this is sort
of like you can think of this as sort of
like the nearest neighbors thing we did
before, but instead of it being the
pixels of the image, we're we're looking
at the uh the vector at the very end of
your CNN right before you you have the
classification layer. Um so this would
be like the the 4096 or the 2048 layer.
And if we look at the difference here is
the L2 distance. Um you'll find that for
a given image if you put it into your
model and you look at the other images
that are close to the model in this
vector space right here after you uh go
through all the layers except the last
one that you'll find the images are
extremely close to each other when the
items are in the same category. So
intuitively what this basically means is
that these features here are actually
really good at at uh you could build a
linear classifier on top of them and
then be able to or or a K nearest
neighbor classifier and be able to
classify objects extremely well. Um so
so how could you use this in practice?
So um what you would do is you would
first train your model on imageet or you
would just grab a model someone else has
trained on imageet or one of these
really large uh web internet scale data
sets and you can just uh freeze all of
these layers. So you don't train any of
them. You keep them exactly the same as
before and you replace this final layer
instead of it being in the in the case
of imageet a thousand classes you
replace it with the number of classes
you have in your data set. And then when
you're training the model, you only
train this layer here. So if we think
about um we talked about how there sort
of in the old paradigm of computer
vision, you had feature extractors which
was a predefined set of operations to
get stuff like color histograms and
other uh predefined features. Um you can
almost think of uh the frozen model as
doing this. It's a predefined feature
extractor that we're not changing in any
way, but we're using it to calculate
features that we then train a model on
top of. It's actually extremely similar
under that paradigm because you're not
training it here. And if you have a
larger data set, what tends to work best
in practice is to actually train the
whole model, but you're initializing it
from these values that are that were
pre-trained say on imageet or some other
really large internet scale data set. So
I think pretty much for all of the
problems I ever work on, I'm doing this
step three here because my I have maybe
a million or 10 million training
examples. So I'll start it with a model
that was trained on billions that I
don't have the compute for and then I'll
fine-tune the model uh on my relatively
smaller data set and I'll get better
performance than if I just try to train
a model myself uh because the model's
basically seen more data. that's uh
created a better feature extractor and
then when I fine-tune the whole thing it
can still be specific enough to my
problem. You're basically taking say say
say say say say say say say say say say
say say say say say say say say say
let's use a very concrete case where
we're training a model on imageet um
we're taking this model and we're
replacing the final layer so that it's
no longer outputting a thousand classes
it's outputting um you know the number
of classes in your data set and we're
initializing this randomly using the
kiming initialization we talked about
before but the rest of these layers are
maintaining their values uh that they
they had before so we're not changing
these values and during gradient descent
we're never changing these values. So,
um these values are unchanged. We
basically take our image, we pass it
through our model, and now it's just
like we have a it's almost like you're
just training a linear linear classifier
where your input are these 4096 vectors
for each image that we calculate by
passing it through the whole model. Then
we have our vector of 4096 and we're
just mapping that to the number of
classes and we're only training this
mapping at the end.
>> Yeah. So the question is uh will you
have some bias in your model because
it's trained on imageet? The answer is
definitely. So um the the model if you
do this uh number two like this uh way
of training um then it will do best on
data sets that look very similar to
imageet. So these would be like pictures
of everyday things like laptops or uh
maybe a classroom or a person things
like this where imageet is everyday
objects but if it was say photos of Mars
uh it would do a lot worse. So there's
definitely bias based on the training
data of the pre-trained model and you
want to get something that is in the
same type of distribution or you're
seeing the same kinds of objects or
locations or things like that. So um the
question is what do you do when your
data set is out of distribution? Um I
actually have a um a slide here to cover
some of that. So it's a great question.
Um so um if you have a very similar data
set but very little data, you can use
the linear classifier strategy we just
mentioned. If you have a similar data
set, quite a lot of data, you'll get
best performance by fine-tuning all the
layers. These are strategies two and
three on the slide that I mentioned
earlier. But what about when you have a
very different data set? So, um if you
have a lot of data, you might just want
to start from scratch. Um or you could
you might get better performance if you
still initialize here. You would test,
but there's no guaranteed way to know
that performance would be better or
worse. Um and then yeah, if you have
very little data or a very different
data set, you probably want to try to
find a model that's trained on something
close. There are specific techniques
that researchers have looked into for
out of domain generalization and um you
know this basic idea of you have one
domain, you train a model on one domain
and you're trying to learn a new domain
that's different in some ways. So this
is an active area of research, but I
wouldn't say there's like a general
technique that always works and it's a
bit problem dependent in that setting.
Whereas this is for everything except
the upper right quadrant here. It works
pretty well in practice. So there are
actually techniques for this and it's a
pretty active area of research and
certain models generalize better. Like I
think language models are pretty good at
learning a lot of different domains for
example. Um but yeah it's it's it's
definitely the worst scenario to be in
where you have a completely different
problem that anyone's ever worked on
before and you don't have a lot of data.
It's by far the hardest to train a model
in that setting. So the question is do
you ever do anything between training
one file layer and all layers? Yeah,
people have actually done a lot of work
looking into training a subset of the
layers. Um, there's also a technique
called Laura, which we might go into in
the transformers lecture. I'm not sure
if it'll make it this year, but the
basic idea is to fine-tune all the
layers in a way where you're not
changing all the values exactly, but
you're learning uh basically low rank uh
uh differences between the different
layers. um where you're sort of
fine-tuning the differences between the
original layers rather than fine-tuning
the layers themselves. So um yeah,
there's techniques you could use Laura
uh and it would need more explanation,
but the basic idea is instead of
fine-tuning the actual values, you're
fine-tuning uh these differences between
the value layers. Sort of like how a
ResNet, you're learning the difference.
Loras are like that, but you do it with
a very small number of parameters. I
think the question is uh how did they
basically decide how many layers to
pick? Why did they pick a large number
of layers? Specifically, why are there
two convolution layers of each size
instead of one? Um, so it's actually
really similar to the example we showed
earlier with VGG where if you have three
of these 3x3 convolutions, you're able
to uh have the same receptive field as a
7x7 convolution, but you're able to
model more nonlinear relationships
because you have these three activation
functions rather than just one
activation on the 7x7 filter. So
basically 3x3 is more expressive, but
you're still looking at the same set of
values as long as you have enough of
them. So a a larger set of smaller
filters is more expressive than a
smaller set of larger filters.
Okay.
Um okay. So we'll go on. Um yeah,
basically try to find a large data set
that has similar data. Uh get a model
that was trained on that and then
fine-tune it on your own data. Uh some
good links. Uh PyTorch image models has
a bunch of models that are trained on
imageet and other data sets. Um and then
also just in the PyTorch vision GitHub
repo, you'll find some too. Okay. Um
I'll talk over very briefly at the end
for hyperparameter selection. So um if
you're having difficulty training your
model and it's not working right away, I
think the best thing you can do is to
overfit on a small sample. So this is
like the default debugging strategy in
deep learning where you just have one
data point and you want to see your
training loss basically go to zero. Your
model should be able to memorize one
training example and if it's not able to
do that, you have a bug somewhere in
your code or you're not picking the
right kind of model to model your
problem. Um, so this is a really good uh
training problem and it'll also tell you
like what learning rates work or what
ones don't work and you'll get a rough
idea of the neighborhood of learning
rates you should explore. So this is a
good way to make sure your model's
correct, make sure your learning rate is
reasonable and also to make sure you
don't have any other bugs that could be
impacting your code. So this is like
always step one if you're having issues
just uh running some code. This is how
you debug. Um the second thing you would
want to do after you get this is maybe
you try a very coarse grid of
hyperparameters. So I would first try
with different learning rates and see
how if you train model on different
learning rates what are the training
losses look like. You want one that has
the most sustained uh decreasing in the
training loss over maybe one epoch.
That's like a pretty good estimation but
you can train for longer. Um once you
get a good set of learning rates you
could then look into other
hyperparameters too. And specifically
besides the loss, you'll also want to
look at the accuracy curves.
So you have your training accuracy and
your validation accuracy. Um if they're
still going up, it means you want to
keep training. Uh pretty reasonable, but
you might have a scenario where the
training loss is going up, but your
validation loss is going down. Uh this
is overfitting. So um we need to either
increase the regularization or if we can
get more data, that could also work. But
you need to do one of the two um in
order to improve your performance
further beyond uh the peak right here I
guess would be the best model you have
so far. Um if you're seeing very little
of a gap here then you can probably
train for model uh for longer because
generally we you do want to just uh get
to the point where your validation loss
has been maximized. So if you could just
keep training uh you know you could keep
training. So uh even if there's not a
significant gap here or anything um if
you see uh the validation loss is
similar to the training uh sorry the
validation accuracy similar to the
training accuracy you can probably keep
training until your training accuracy
starts diverging from your your
validation accuracy
and you basically can repeat this
process over and over again. Um one
final note is in terms of for
hyperparameter search normally people
think you know you have two
hyperparameters or more that you're
searching over should you try every
combination of the hyperparameters or
what is the best way to do it I think in
practice a random search over their
hyperparameter space works a lot better
than a like a grid search where you're
trying every set of a predefined set and
the reason is mainly because you can
imagine you have one axis which is an
unimportant hyperparameter where
depending on the value your performance
will be roughly the same versus an
important one. If you do random values
across all of these, you'll actually
search the hyperparameter space of your
uh important parameter much more
thoroughly. Whereas you're sort of
wasting time uh doing on on the grid
search rechecking multiple values for an
unimportant hyperparameter. So in
practice, you should define the ranges
you want to try and then just uh
randomly collect hyperparameters with
values from those ranges. And that's
probably the best way to do it. And you
just keep running till you get the best
model. Okay. Uh that's it. So we talked
about layers and CNN's activation
functions, CNN architectures and weight
initialization. How do you actually
predefine and build these models and
then we talked about how do you actually
train it? How do you change your data to
be input to the model? How do you
augment it? Uh transfer learning is a
really neat trick for improving
performance and then how do you pick the
best hybrid parameters. So uh yeah, we
covered a lot in lecture today. Thank
you all so much. Uh yeah.