Okay, so welcome back to the uh DP and
flow model the course. So last time we
are discussing some kind of the boring
things that probably most of you already
know about some Dan and DB uh which are
basically the some very the basic idea
in terms of how we can make some kind of
the models. So what we start to see from
the last class is that given some kind
of the large collection of the data how
we can make some kind of the model that
can allow us to basically uh produce
another kind of sample that looks like
one of the data points that we have. Uh
so we started to see this kind of the
problem from the statistical
perspective. Uh in terms of that uh if
we see those kind of the data points as
kind of the samples from some certain
the probability distribution and if we
have some kind of the certain form of
the uh the probability distribution that
we can consider directly like sampling
the data point from that specificity
distribution. So that was kind of the
basic idea uh especially if the given
the distribution is a form of the
gausian then we have seen like how we
can do some kind of sampling from that.
uh so that is kind of the basic thing
the problem is that obviously the given
the set of the data points uh not from
the typically from the gausian
distribution so and also we don't know
the underlying the form of the uh the
distribution for the data points that we
have so for that like the basic idea
that we discussed last time uh is to
basically find a mapping uh from any
kind of a simple distribution typically
that's the standard the gaussian
distribution but it does not need to
this specific form but we are basically
using the Gaussian distribution because
of the simplicity for many things right
and so we are basically finding mapping
from the simple distribution with the
our data distribution in a way that the
generation the process can be uh defined
as kind of like sampling from the given
the simple distribution and then mapping
that data point uh to the one of the
data points that we have right that was
the the basic idea and we started to
basically use this kind of the uh some
kind of the terms and some kind of
notations. So we are going to call this
kind of the some simple distribution as
kind of the latent distribution and also
using the Z as kind of the variables for
that and X denotes the hourly data point
right. Then here also the question is
that how we also going to find this kind
of the mapping from the latent
distribution to the data distribution
and for that basically we are going to
use the neuron net and then we discuss
the two ideas like one is the gen and
the the other one is the boo right so
for both of the cases first we are
defining a net that is like mapping the
latent the variable into the data point
right uh that's typically called the
decoder or the generator uh but the Key
idea is that uh we cannot just like
solely training the the decoder or the
generator. We also need to jointly train
the another network in a way to find a
kind of the property mapping. And do you
remember the other network for the gen
and
uh the other network for the GAN the
case was basically having the
discriminator right? So we are making
the decoder or the generator and also
the discriminator making them to be
compete each other in a way that the
output can be something that is like uh
nondist distinguishable from the real
kind of data point and the ba case
instead of like discriminator we are
having some kind of encoder which is
learning the our proxy of the posterior
uh the distribution. So that was the
basic idea that we discussed last time
and to get into the idea about the the
variation of the posterior in the BAE.
uh we discuss some kind of basics about
the statistics like the margin
distribution and the expected value base
rule all the things right I guess you
remember all those things right so these
are really basic things that we're going
to basically keep seeing in the rest of
the all the lectures in this class
especially for the base rule uh we are
basically having those terms uh the
prior distribution that's the basically
our the latent distribution the simple
distribution that we basically starting
the sampling from and then based on this
uh we also learn the generator which is
basically the conditional distribution
from the latent three data points here
right uh that's the called the
likelihood and based on that we are
basically basically we want to capture
this right learning the the probability
distribution for the data points uh
which is called the marginal
distribution uh and based on all those
ratings we can also define the another
one which is the posterior distribution
define some kind of the mapping from the
data points uh to the latent points
right so those are also the terms that
we're going to keep using over the all
the lectures in this class
uh so as I mentioned from the uh the
class last week uh we're going to have
some kind of quiz every lecture so the
touristic quiz is that so basically we
review some kind of the basic things
here right the marginal thing
distribution the base rules and many
things and given these things actually
this was kind of the homework last time
uh given the these two distributions P
and the Q both are the Gaussian
distribution. Uh especially here this is
the case that Q is the standard Gaussian
distribution. The mean is zero and the
the variance is basically the identity
matrix. Uh for those two distributions
uh can you compute the K diverance
between these two?
So you
I guess uh got this answer right. So
this is slightly more general form for
the cases like when you have the two
isotropic the gaus and the distributions
right. Uh yeah, I'm going to post this
on the the the link so you don't need to
take photo of this but basically yeah
you can see this
it's all based on the definition of the
Kness right and the question was some
kind of for the special case when the
the Q is basically the standard Gian
distribution but in this case now we can
define the K diverance like this right
so it's kind of like simple DM uh you're
going to keep seeing the K divergence in
the today's lecture and also for the
rest objects in this case. Okay. And the
basic idea for the BA if we go back to
the BA uh basically we want to uh
basically define the mapping from the
latent to the data distribution as kind
of the uh the sampling process. So now
we are uh this the decoder becomes like
basically you know predicting the mean
of that the likelihood distribution the
z conditioned by z right. Uh so given
this kind of the prior distribution and
the likelihood distribution based on
that from the marginalization uh now we
can compute the marginal distribution
for the data pointed x right uh then the
purpose of like learning the likelihood
distribution with the decoder here
should be basically maximizing this kind
of the marginal distribution for the
given the data point of the x right so
here the question is that how can you
train basically our the decoder in a way
that that becomes
learning some kind of the likelihood
distribution maximizing the likely uh
the marginal distribution there right uh
so with only this like uh um you know uh
single the decoding the network it is
not possible basically to compute this
so we can also actually consider
computing this like marginal
distribution by just taking some kind of
the Monteal estimate in terms of the we
are sampling lots of the Z and taking
the sum like this part of all the Z
right but this will basically involves
like huge computation because like to
approximate this integral we will need
to have some loss of Z here right so we
are not going to get into that way we
are going to choose the other way around
which is computing this marginal
distribution in this form right uh using
the base rule but here the problem is
that now we don't know this kind of
posterior distribution as well right so
that's the problem so given that we
don't know the posterior distribution
what we are going to do is that instead
of like directly computing this uh in
this case that when we don't know this
information we are going to consider
this the lower bound for the log the
probability of the px like this so why
why is this the the lower bound uh we
can bally easily check this out uh from
the uh the the the Jensen inequality
that we have seen last
So this is nothing but we are basically
multiplying the same thing from the
denominator and denominator like this
and then now this is basically
converting this into the form of the
expected value while taking this
probability as kind of the ways right so
these are also the same thing and from
the fact that the log is the concave
function uh from the density inequality
that we have seen last time now we can
see that these two should have this
inequality relationship. So now from
these like four lines we can easily see
that actually this become the lower
bound for the low probability that we
are going to compute. So what this mean
is that our goal should be basically
finding the uh the you know the
likelihood distribution the decoding
network uh defining the likelihood
distribution in a way to basically
maximize the px right for the all the
data points that have we have here right
uh but since we cannot directly compute
the marginal distribution what we are
going to do is that we are going to
introduce another linear network uh
which is this one, right? This is called
the the variation of the posterior which
is not exactly our the posterior
distribution. It's kind of some sort of
the proxy distribution that kind of
plays the role like the the posterior
but not exactly the posterior in a way
that we can compute the lower bound like
this. So given this kind of the any
arbitrary distribution that we are
learning here we can see that like this
will basically form the lower bound and
we know we can basically consider
maximizing the px uh not exactly exactly
maximizing the px but basically
maximizing this like lower bound in a
way to basically learn the both the uh
the variation of the posterior and also
the likelihood as well.
So if we see some more details about
this like elbow function
the elbow function we can decompose the
uh the joint distribution here uh into
these two forms
right uh deco composing this into the
these two and then we can also decompose
like this and then we are seeing that
now the elbow function have the this
kind of the two terms right uh so again
we are seeing the k divergence here and
also I think another the terms there so
The first term is called the
reconstruction term. We are going to see
like why is the reconstruction term and
this is the term that we are going to
maximize and the other one is basically
the some sort of the regularization the
care the diversity regularization which
will be basically minimized uh through
the the the training. So here basically
the uh interesting thing is that uh this
is basically the lower bound function
that we are going to maximize over
training that basically means that we
are maximizing the first term the
reconstruction term and also the
minimizing the second term. So
minimizing this term uh can you see the
meaning of like minimizing this term?
>> Yes. So basically we are going to make
these two be the same right and Q is
some kind of the some plate distribution
that we are going to learn and PZ what
is PZ is the latent distribution that we
set as kind of the the standard gausian
distribution.
So the meaning of this is that actually
the maximizing the elbow basically means
that we are finding some kind of the
variation of the posterior distribution
uh while making it to be close to the
standard gausian this region as much as
possible
make sense. So somehow we first need to
find a kind of the mapping uh with this
kind of like the variation of the
posterior while making this to be close
to the standard decian distribution. So
as this gets closer to the standard
decian distribution uh that becomes
basically we are maximizing the elbow
function which basically means that we
also maximizing the the marginal
distribution
make sense that becomes the minimizing
the meaning of the output function here.
So basically what you can see is that uh
we have the uh the decoding the network
here uh which is defining the likelihood
distribution. So we said that the output
of this network to be the mean uh of the
uh the the likelihood distribution. So
basically we are setting everything is
kind of the gausian here for the
simplicity. Uh so when you set the
likelihood distribution is kind of the
another the gaussian distribution uh the
output decoding becomes the mean of that
the gaussian distribution
and what we need to do is that we also
need to learn the another the the proxy
distribution the variation of the
posterior here which is also modeled as
another gausian distribution and then in
this case now we also predict both the
mean and the variance like this. uh and
what we have seen in the previous slide
is that uh we are basically learning
this uh in a way that these two becomes
closer uh to the uh the the the standard
decion this region and then now we can
see that actually this becomes quite
close to the uh the typical autoenccoder
uh which is in terms of that we are
having the encoder uh mapping from the
given the data point into the uh the
mean and the the standard deviation of
the three.
So this the variation of the posterior
is basically uh is learned by the the
network which we call the encoder
basically mapping from the data point to
the latent the variables and the other
way around from the latent variable to
the data point is the decoder right uh
so that's the learning the likelihood
distribution. So you can see that in the
structure wise of the neural network
it's quite similar with autoenccoder we
are just having the encoder and the
decoder uh the only difference is that
using the encoder we are not directly
mapping the data points to the one of
the points here but actually mapping the
data points uh into the uh with the the
the variation of the posterior like this
and then given the variation the
posterior here we are going to sample
one of the data points here and then
that will be decoded through the
decoding uh the network. Right? So
that's the only difference. So we are
not just directly mapping one of the
data points here into the latent
variable but actually mapping this into
the some variation of the posterior and
b based on this like variation of the
posterior we are going to sample one of
the the latent variable that will be
decoded back to the data point. So
that's the basic idea. So in the
training time how we are going to
maximize the elbow function. So the
elbow function was defined like this and
we have seen how we can compute this
right. So that was the quiz. So we know
that this is the standard gausian
distribution. This will be another
decian distribution right exactly the
same form that we have seen the quiz. So
in terms of that we are having the k
divergence. We know how we can compute
this right. So the only thing is that we
just need to maximize this term and for
this like what we are going to do is
that we are going to simply approximate
this expected value by just taking uh
some of the samples of the Z from that
the duration of the posterior
distribution. So given the lots of
samples of the Z uh typically we just
take some few samples but uh to get some
like better approximation actually we
need to have some more samples of the Z
here right so which is this becomes
computing this right
and then the question is that how we can
sample the Z here right so Z was
basically uh the sample from the
variation of the post here which is
defined with the mean and the uh the
standard deviation here right so what we
can do is that uh from the V parameter
entric that we also discussed last time.
This Z can be simply computed by just
sampling the standard Gaussian sample
and then computing this formulation.
Right? This is basically the mapping
from the standard Gaussian distribution
to the any other the arbitrary gausian
distribution. So z can be basically
computed based on the mean and the uh
the standard deviation that we are
predicting using the encoder and also
computing this through the the standard
gausian the the sample there. So given
this kind of the Z uh what we can see is
that if we plug in uh this into the like
PDF of the Gaussian distribution then we
can simply see that the log of the
probability becomes uh the form of like
this what you can see is that actually
this was basically some kind of
parameter that we set right so this is
kind of the constant value so we can
ignore in the loss function
the only thing we are basically getting
is that basically this point right
uh so That's why basically this term is
called the reconstruction term. So what
we can see is that given the kind of
data point of the X we are basically
learning some kind of D distribution.
From that we are going to sample the Z
here and from this sample when you
decode this back into data point uh we
are going to see whether we can
reconstruct the given the input data
point uh here X here. So that's is
basically uh exactly the same loss that
we are seeing in the training of the
autoenccoder right.
So from this basically what we can say
is that uh this becomes like quite the
same with the training of the
autoenccoder if we only see this like
reconstruction term. The only difference
that we are seeing is that we are
basically having this like KD divergency
like addition. Uh so the two differences
uh with the from the autoenccoder to the
version of the autoenccoder is that uh
we are not directly predicting the
latent variable uh but the post the
version the posterior like this in a way
that Z can be sampled from that but from
the sample Z we still want to basically
rec construct the given the data point X
here right so in the sense that is
basically quite similar with the
typically autoenccoder this structure
and And here basically we having some
kind of the process like sampling Z here
right uh so why is that the sampling is
still like differentiable because like
we are not just like directly just
sampling Z we are going to compute the Z
using the mean and the variance that
mean and the the variance that we are
predicting using the net. So still the Z
become some kind of the variable which
depends on the prediction like these two
right. So when you compute some kind of
the reconstruction the loss uh with this
the uh still the kind of the loss will
be back propagated uh through the
prediction of the mean and the variance.
So that's why basically we can uh train
both the encoder and the decoder
and the generation the process uh we can
basically so this is kind of the proxy
the distribution that was basically
playing the role uh to learn the better
the likelihood uh in the generation the
process we don't need to use this right
uh the basically the only purpose for
this encoding part is basically to learn
the proper likelihood distribution so in
the generation the process uh we can
ignore this we just need to sample from
the uh the standard gausian distribution
and just like map this sample without
the decoder. So that's the basic idea of
the
so here one question is that should the
dimensions of the input data the point x
and also the latent variables the z be
the same
or not?
Yes or no? Yes.
No.
uh it does not need to be the same right
uh because like all the mapping from the
data point uh to the latent variables
and also the other way around these
mappings are all defined by the neuron
net right uh so in the sense uh it's
okay to have the uh lower dimension
space or the higher dimension space for
the latent space uh typically for the VA
training we set the lower dimension
space for the latent space right uh so
that's the basic idea Any
questions for the page?
Many of you would already know about the
right. So what's the what are the
limitations of the BA
if you have tried to train the BA
before?
>> Sorry.
>> Yeah. Uh so typical the output that
we're going to get is would be like
this, right? uh looks like some
realistic devices but uh I mean some
blurry kind of the office right uh what
we kind of the problems of degree in
terms of the formulations
so the thing is that uh we are still
basically modeling here everything is
kind of the Gaussian distribution right
but we are also making the likelihood to
be Gaussian distribution and also making
the the variation of the posterior to be
the Gaussian distribution right but here
the question is that is it okay to make
it everything is kind of the gausian
here. So that's the question typically
we we know that we set the uh this
latent the distribution to be gausian
right uh but for the typically for the
data distribution that we are going to
learn uh the merger distribution even
will not close will not be close to the
any of the gaussian distribution will be
much more the complex distribution right
uh the thing is that so the basic idea
for the b is that we are maximizing uh
this low probability not directly But
basically by maximizing the lower bound
right then the question is that when
this when does this like the lower bound
become the same with the low probability
that we are actually going to maximize.
Can you guess like when these two be the
same?
>> Yes. Uh that's the right answer. uh but
can you also derive like when these two
become zero? uh so I recommend you to
try to really derive all the things and
see when these two exactly become zero.
Uh so yeah you can check this out later
but basically if you basically rewrite
this kind of be this is called the
density the gap. So basically you know
when you have some kind of the density
inequality this become the lower bound.
But the question is that when these two
become the same. Uh so if you rewrite
all the things that you can see that uh
the difference between these two terms
becomes another the KD divergence
between these two basically the
probability distributions.
Uh which means that all the uh the you
know the lower bounds become the tight
the bound when the the learned the
variation of the posterior become the
same with the true posterior. So that's
the case. But then here the question is
that uh would it be uh possible to
basically have the both the likelihood
distribution and also the true posterior
distribution as the gausian for the most
of the cases. So in general uh when you
have some kind of the very complex the
data distribution uh when we make
everything as kind of the gausian
distribution both the all the latent
distribution and the posterior and the
likelihood uh it is typically not
possible uh to really bally making both
the likelihood and the posterior is the
gausian. there will be some specialty
cases but in general it's impossible to
basically having the gausian
distributions both for the likelihood
and the posterior distribution. So
that's the thing in the ba case we are
basically kind of like oversimplifying
everything in terms of the making the
likelihood also as the gaussian and also
the uh the posterior to be kind of the
gausian as well. uh but for some kind of
the complexity data distribution uh it's
it's actually impossible to making uh
making the likelihood and the post both
both of them is kind of the gaussian
distribution. So which means that this
will be basically very bad approximation
uh for most of the cases like when you
have some complex the data distribution.
So that's basically why we are basically
seeing some kind of the some uh
limitations of the BA.
Then here the question is that uh what
else can he do? Uh we are using the
gausian for the simplicity. Uh but it
sounds like we need to do have some kind
of the better some kind of the
parameterization
both for the likelihood and also the
posterior distributions not as the
gausian but in other the ways right uh
but what can you do in terms of having
some kind of more like the complex
parameterizations for the both of them.
So that's basically what people have
explored as kind of like making some
kind of the loss of the variance of the
BAE. Uh and also one of the ideas in
terms of making the BA to be more
complex uh is to make some kind of a
recursive debate like this. So this is
the part that we are starting to see
some kind of the new uh denotations
here.
But here the basic idea is that now we
are going to introduce not only a single
the latent variables but the multiple
the layers of the latent variables
starting from the x1 to all the way to
the x cap t. So now we are going to
slightly change our denotations in a way
that we use the x for the data points
and also the z from the latent
variables. Right? But since now we are
going to have some multiple the latent D
variables we are going to switch the
notation like this. Now X0 indicates our
the the train data the data points and
then we are having some kind of the
multiple the latent variables from the
one to capital T. Uh it depends on like
how many kind of layers that we are
going to have right. uh so we are having
the x0 to the x1 to the capital t and
the when the the mapping from the data
points all the way to the in the gausian
distribution is defined with some kind
of the multiple the mark of the process.
So still while we have some kind of the
multiple layers we are still going to uh
simplify this in a way to assuming the
marovian process. So here the meaning of
the marovian process is that uh it's
like all the sampling the process right.
So basically what we are going to do is
that when you sample any of the
intermediate the latent variables here
the x2 for example uh the sampling of
the x2 will depends only on the x1 only
from the previous one uh which means
that uh the any of the intermediate the
latent variables will not depends on the
any of the previous ones like the x0
there only depends on the one right
before the the step. So that's basically
the assumption of the mark of D and the
process.
So we are basically adding this kind of
rules in terms of to uh like making the
process to be simpler right. Uh so this
means that uh if we think about the our
degeneration the process the generation
the process is basically the mapping the
x capital t all the way to the x0 there
right uh it was represented with the
single the conditional distribution in
the b case right but now we are going to
have some multiple the steps like this
uh and then the sampling of the xt minus
one will only depends on the xt not any
other kind of the the previous steps uh
which means means that now the
generation the process can be modeled
like this. Uh so we sample from the x
capital t first and then we are
basically taking the product all the all
the transition the distribution from the
all the intermedate steps uh in terms
like determining the probability for the
output the x0 here
make sense.
So that's basically and you can see that
now uh this part was basically simple
the gaussian distribution the previous
array in the previous right but now you
can see that it becomes like more
complex in terms of that now we are
taking the products of these
distribution
so still what we are going to do is that
we are going to still define this like
tion distribution as the gausian uh but
when you see the entire some kind of the
likelihood distribution this becomes
like more than more complex more
something that is more complex than
negian in terms of that we are now
taking the product of the multiple
decision distribution
make sense. So that's kind of like one
way that we are modeling some more
complex distribution with the more
parameters. So it's not just having like
one single pair of the mean and the var
the the variance right we are having
some kind of the multiple the transition
distributions. uh so even when the like
single the transition distribution is
basically simple the gaussian
distribution if we see some kind of the
product of like this uh this will
becomes a more complex distribution
so that that's the basic idea
and also the our posterior will be now
defined uh basically by taking the
product of the all the transition the
distribution uh so the that's kind of
the same thing but it's kind of like
another way to basically parameterizing
both the likelihood and also the
posterior the variation of the posterior
distribution.
>> Yeah.
Uh otherwise basically when you uh
define this uh this xt should depends on
the all the previous states then this
will become much more complex. So now we
can we are basically simplifying all the
process in terms of that the xt is b
sampled only from the xt minus one
without seeing any kind of the previous
kind of things. Uh so this will
basically make the whole process to be
much simpler. So you can see that
without the mark of the the assumption
here this transition the distribution
should not be sampling xt only from the
xt minus one but from the all the other
kind of the previous states. So then
that becomes like we are modeling the
trenchion distribution uh in a way to
see all the previous record to sample
the xt then the training becomes like
way more complicated.
So the marovian process is to make
everything to be simple. Uh the thing is
that we are also going to see the
non-marovian cases uh probably sometime
next week.
Let's see. Any other questions?
only the one previous step.
I mean
there is a
separate X1 from the X2.
So the question is that like why do we
need to model both the Q and the P as
the microbial processes right? Is that
the question? Uh so actually we going to
see but here the the thing is that both
the P and the Q these both of them are
something that we are going to learn
using the neuron network. uh so as we
basically make make them as kind of a
non-markive process the training
learning of like these two the
distributions will become more
complicated in the BAE setup uh so
that's a thing so now we just because
like yeah in the BA setup like both the
P and the Q are learned using the
decoder and the encoder uh for both of
the cases if we start to making the X2
sampling to be dependent to the all the
previous the steps
uh that will be much more the
complicated kind of training. Uh so
that's the basic idea
and
but as I said uh we're going to also see
some non-marcomic case as well. Uh but
let's make our lives easier for now in
terms of like everything is kind of the
mark process. uh for those of the cases
we can still define the elbow function
as well and start to basically train the
all the the recursive BAE through the
same process. But still kind of the the
challenges in terms like making the BAE
in the recursive way like this is that
uh for the BAE basically the idea is
that we are learning both the Q and the
P right joint training of the kind of
the uh like the the decoder and the
encoder. uh and this joint training is
another actually the difficulties uh in
terms of training the uh the BA
especially the recursive deba so
actually that's the kind of the one of
the motivation that we are seeing the uh
diffusion models here uh you can so over
the entire the class uh over the the the
this semester we are going to see all
different kind of the interpretations of
the diffusion models uh different kind
of angles of like see how the the why
the individual model basically works and
the like one specific way to see the
diffusion model is to see it kind of
like one specific some kind of the some
variant of the hierarchical degree the
lucrative deba so let's get into that
the basic idea first
so from the context of the hierarchical
deba uh we are going to see a kind of
special case we disc like two kind of
things first uh we are going to match
the dimension of the latent the piece to
be the same with the dimension of the
data points. We didn't need to match the
dimensions in the B case, right? Because
all the mappings are basically done
using the new network, right? Uh for
this specific case, uh we are going to
match the dimensions for the all the
kind of the things including all the
latent variables and the data points
everything is in the same dimensional
space, right? Uh also making our the
life easier. uh and one more thing is
that because this is kind of the key
part
so the problem the VA was that we are
basically jointly training both the
operation of the posterior and also the
decoding network as well right so that's
kind of the things how we're going to
jointly train both of both of them now
the thing is that we are not going to
learn the variation the posterior uh we
are going to use some kind of the
predefined the variation the posterior
distribution so we are dropping the
neuron the parameters here right uh so
this is like not learned uh this will be
predefined
then the question might be is that even
any predefined the variation the
posterior will this kind of the
predefined uh the variation the
posterior will minimize the elbow
function uh so that's basically the
things that we are going to see uh today
and given this kind of some specific the
the assumptions uh I'm going to
introduce some kind of some new terms
here.
Uh by the way uh so this is the part
that we are going to see some some kind
of more complex kind of things and
actually even more kind of issues is
that uh so this is for the diffusion
model case right and also we are going
to discuss the flow models uh after some
few weeks
uh for the interpretation of the flow
models uh even we going to start to use
some kind of the different notations uh
so basically all the notations here are
basically coming from the the papers
first introducing uh these ideas okay
even the paper was introduced in just
like four years ago so these are
basically as I said very new this
subject and every paper is actually
using all the different notations so
that's the kind of big problems uh so
here uh in the context of the models we
are going to use like those notations
please keep these in mind uh this is
something that you're going to keep
seeing uh in the explanation of the uh
the diffusion models we are starting
from the x0 that's the data point all
the way to the x capital t is basically
the mapping from the data point to the
sample from the initial decion
distribution. So that was the uh based
on the posterior distribution right. So
we're going to call this process as kind
of the for process. Okay. So the for
process is coming from the data points
to the all the way to the the data
points.
uh the reason why we call this as
default process is that uh that's kind
of the process that we call as kind of
like diffusion like uh like adding some
kind of noise. Uh so that's basically
what we are going to see. So that's kind
of the main thing and as I said uh this
is the trenchion the distribution that
we are going to predefine. uh so let's
see how we are going to predefine
and the other way around uh the mapping
from the latent to the data points there
uh is the reverse process and that's the
kind of the process that we are going to
learn so still that we are learning this
distribution uh not this one uh so this
transition the distribution will still
be learned and this is basically hourly
generation the process rightly generated
process is basically the reverse process
starting from the x capital t all the
way to the x0 by be doing some kind of
recursive decampling through the uh
reverse the transition uh distribution
here. So that's basically what we are
going to learn uh through the neuron uh
using the neuron network
and here the key idea uh in the teacher
model is that basically how we are going
to define uh this fourth detention
distribution here in a way that the our
variation the posterior will be defined
as kind of the product like this right
and that specifically variation the
posterior should minimize our the elbow
function. Uh so here the key idea is to
how we define the uh distion the
distribution in a way that this uh the
maximizes the our elbow function. So
that's the key thing. So actually the
thing is that there are multiple ways to
define this like for the internusion.
So let's see the uh single case first.
Uh later we are going to see more cases
but let's first see the simple case. uh
so this is the kind of the our
definition of the for the transition. So
over the time over the kind of the uh
the for process uh we are basically
seeing that the t is kind of time uh
time is increasing from the zero to
capital t in the for process. So you can
see that it's kind of like you know over
time some kind of the some uh the some
like the the the process some iterative
the process and then over time we are
going to set some kind of parameter of
the beta t here and based on the beta t
we are defining some kind of the some
another the gausian distribution like
this. Oh, still we are making everything
as like the gaussian right. Uh so we can
see that uh the meaning of like this
kind of the transition the distribution
is that uh so basically the beta t is
basically increasing from the uh zero to
uh some kind of the numbers. So the
thing is that the beta t is basically
non-deing function over time the beta t
will be increasing but still we are
going to keep all the numbers to be
small enough like 0.0 zero something but
we will be some kind of the non-zero
number and also keep increasing like
this. Uh so when this is the zero what
you can see is that this is nothing but
just like having the the same the uh the
the standard gausian distribution right
so if the beta t is zero uh is basically
oh it's not the standard gausian
distribution so it's basically zero then
it's basically some kind of the direct
delta distribution in a way that the
sample of the xt should be the same with
the xt minus one right
but as you basically increase the beta t
here what we are seeing is that we are
adding some small degA noise. Uh while
basically shifting the mean to be closer
to the zero, right? So this is kind of
doing some kind of shifting to get
closer to the zero. The mean is getting
closer to the zero, right? While
basically slightly adding some more kind
of the gausian noise.
So you can see that this is kind of the
process that we are repeatedly adding
some kind of the gausian noise while
increasing the variance like this. uh
and also moving that the kind of the
terms to be closer get closer to the
mean but not exactly to the mean right
because like all this kind of beta t to
be some small numbers right so this is
correctly one specific way that we are
defining the for the process and you can
also still see that there are some kind
of the parameters of the beta t uh
actually you will need to implement this
in the assignment one so you need to see
what's the meaning like this and
depending on how exactly we also set the
beta
you see some kind of a difference in the
Pokemon. Uh so there are lots of kind of
options for the better t but basically
if you satisfy this condition that these
are basically increasing non-creasing
decreasing function number so making all
these number to be small enough then it
should work. Uh but there are still kind
of the bunch of the options.
uh even you can consider like the all
the betterity to be kind of some neural
networks of the the variables in terms
of the we are learning over the
training. We can set these like better
to be constant and also linearly
increasing and also linking the cosine
functions and so there are the bunch of
the options but in any case uh you know
the only condition is that we just need
to make all this to be small enough
while making to be nonquent function
so keep this in mind. So this is the
hourly definition uh for the fourth the
transition did this
>> why this should be non decreasing. Uh so
we we going to get into that. So yeah
this
uh so we're going to discuss some kind
of the more details of like those
definitions probably also the next time
as well. There are so many kind of
things to discuss. Uh so here basically
all the kind of the uh the idea is that
we are defining predefining the uh the
for the transition the distribution in a
way to make it the all the the variation
the post here uh to be something that is
minimizing maximizing the elbow
function. So let's actually see whether
this exactly really maximizes the elbow
function.
So if we get back to the elbow function
actually once we have some kind of the
multiple kind of the layers in the
recursive kind of bae the elbow function
becomes quite complicated like this so
I'm going to skip some details here some
for more details please check out the
references there uh but the thing is
that if we decompose the elbow function
into the as we have done in the b case
that we can still see some these kind of
like three types of the terms the first
one is the reconstruction term that we
have seen in the B case and the other
one is the the priority matching term
which was the same with the K don term
and then we're having some one more term
which is the consistency term which is
basically uh basically nothing but uh
sorry making these two uh the
distributions to be the same. So that's
basically the why we are calling
basically this kind of the consens. So
we can consider basically computing this
constance term. The problem is that as
you can see uh this term is basically
involving two random variables. Uh we
are basically having the two latent D
variables here. Uh and it's basically
maximizing this term to be quite uh
computationally very expensive.
Actually we are not going to uh exactly
compute this term. uh we are going to
consider the other way around uh to rec
uh decompose the elbow into the other
kind of terms uh based on this fact. Can
you see like why these two are the same
in our case?
Yeah, because of the marovian
assumption, right? So since we assume
that all the process kind of the
marovian process, we are going to treat
these two be the same basically now xt
becomes independent of the sample of the
x0. So that's kind of good thing like
having the marov assumption otherwise
actually the x these two cannot be the
same right xt should be dependently all
the kind of the previous kind of states
this making the competition to be much
more complicated.
So with this kind of the marovial
assumption and having these two be the
same uh what now what you can see is
that now we can decompose the same the
elbow function into the different way.
So having different three terms from the
same di function.
So what you can see is that we are still
having the reconstructed term here. So
we are going to see these like the one
by one. Let's see the person uh things.
So this is the same decon and this is
basically reconstructing the x0 from the
x1 while we having some all the other
kind of the lats from the x capital t
right. So this is like only for the
final step of the the reverse process
and also in practice the magnitude of
like this loss term is like much smaller
uh than the other terms. So we are going
to simply ignore this term. Uh so that's
a thing.
The second thing is about the uh this
scal diverance. So this is kind of the
main part. So what we are going to see
is that now we are going to basically
see so this is basically the de
composition of the elbow function which
means that this is the negative the
elbow function which means that we are
going to minimize this.
So can you see the meaning of the like
minimizing this term?
What's the meaning of like minimizing
this term?
So we are basically going to minimize
this term right the thing is that
actually all the traditional
distribution for the uh default process
was predefined right and this is like
sampling x capital t to the x0 so
sampling the the last one from the very
beginning one of the for process this
will be also derived from the our
definition of the for the tention
distribution.
uh then what we need to see is that so
this becomes our deviation the posterior
and we need to see whether our debation
the posterior uh will be the same with
the pxt
what's the pxt
is the standard gausian distribution
right so this is our latent distribution
we are going to so our generation the
process is like sampling the xt here
sampling the gausian the standard
gausian the the sample and the mapping
to the X0 right uh so this is the fourth
process uh sampling X capital T from the
X0 right the fourth process and this is
from based on the hourly definition of
the transient distribution uh we need to
see now whether this uh the variation
posture based on the hourly definition
should be the same with the uh the
standard the gaussian distribution
so let's see whether we define in that
way.
Uh so the question is so whether these
two are the same, right? So let's see.
So uh so basically recall that we
defined the the full definition like
this. Uh we going to do some kind of the
simple math here.
Uh let me why we use the beta t. Uh let
me just quickly replace some of the
better with the one minus beta t the
alpha t here. So when you see the alpha
t here instead of the beta t now we can
see that this is the non-increasing
function right it's basically uh
decreasing over time
and based on this
what we are first going to see is that
so let's see like we only defined this
like the one step of the transition the
distribution
right we we we know how to sample the xt
from the xt minus one right uh but when
Please think about some kind of the
accumulation of this kind of like the
trenchion distribution. Can you directly
sample the XT from the X0
which means that would there be some
kind of the closed form of the this
condition distribution XT conditioned by
the X0 from the all the the sequence of
the our default uh the transition
distribution.
Do you think that we will be able to get
some kind of close for that or not?
uh we we should have the correspond to
basically see this match distant gian
distribution.
So actually uh the answer is obviously
yes. Uh we going to derive some kind of
a code from this for uh this uh the
conditional distribution
and for that basically what we are going
to quickly see is that
so let's get back to some basics of the
gausian the distributions. So basically
let's consider like we having the sample
from the x1 which is from this specific
gausian distribution and x2 from this
specific distribution. Then can he also
uh express x1 plus x2 as kind of the
sample from the another regression
distribution?
Yes.
Yes. The answer is yes. Basically we can
see that x1 plus x2 as kind of a sample
from this specific gausian distribution.
Uh so now you can see like why we are
using the gaussian distributions right.
uh there are many kind of good
properties in the the gausian
distributions in a way that we can uh
play like this. So, so you can see here
like when you have the x1 and x2 both of
them are basically sample from the
different gausian distributions right
and if you take the sum of these two
then we can see that that is kind of the
sample from the another the gausian
distribution
and how about this uh now you have some
kind of the two uh the samples from the
same the standard gausian distribution
and then scaling them to define the x1
and x2
Uh in this case, what's the distribution
for the x1 plus x2?
You know the answer, right? Yeah. So
basically uh actually we can see that x1
x2 is also kind of the sample from the
uh some the another gausian distribution
not having the the identity as the
variance but the having this like the
square sigma 1 square sigma 2 is kind of
the variance for in this case from the
the the things that we have seen in the
previous slide we can see that x1 plus
x2 is also the sample from this specific
gausian distribution right
so these are some kind of very basic the
properties the Gaussian distributions
and based on that
uh let's see this.
So this was basically our definition
uh for the transition distributions
right uh sampling the x1 from the x0 and
sampling x2 from the x1
good thing is that we define everything
is kind of the marovian kind of
assumption in a way that the x2 does not
depends on the x0 here right so making
our easier right uh so based on that can
also define the uh get the closed form
for the this conditional distribution
sampling the x2 conditioned by the x0.
Uh so just m to plug in all the things
that we have seen in the previous
slides. So let let me give you like the
five minutes uh three minutes to see uh
you can get some kind of answer for
this. Uh try yourself what you can get
from this.
So if we see like what you get and this
is thing right uh no from the
[Music]
so yeah you can basically derive all the
things in terms of the we are here
replacing the xt minus one with the uh
this formulation and then if you like
rewrite all the things you can see that
combining the two the uh uh these two
terms these are all some kind of the
gausian samples from the gausian
distributions. Right? Uh from this you
can see that actually the uh
I think I missed some of this light
[Music]
Yeah, from this uh just rewriting x1
with the formulation and just like
combining these two gaussian
distributions then what we can see that
actually this conditional distribution x
two condition by the x0 can be written
based on the gausian distribution.
Okay. So this basically shows that uh
for any kind of the while we defined
this like onestep the transition
distribution from this now we can derive
the closed form of the this what we I'm
going to call this as the for jump we
are jumping from the x0 to the xt here
assembling directly xt from the x0 and
this can be done by this like this
specific gausian distribution.
So that's you can see like now we are
basically define the fourth detention
distribution in this way.
So
as you can see like basically the X key
XT can be now directly sampled from the
X0. So actually you can see that while
we define the F process as kind of some
sort of iterative process actually it
doesn't need to be iterative sampling it
can actually directly sample the XT uh
from the X0 for the forward process. uh
probably not fully reverse process. So
that's kind of a thing. So based on that
basically what you can see is that so
what we want to see is that whether this
uh the vation the posterior is not the
variation anymore right basically
whether this posterior the x capital t
from the x0 whether this becomes close
to the standard gausian or not right. Uh
so this will basically define like this
and then what we have seen is that we
set the beta t to be some kind of the
small number in the 0ero to one range
right and when this is defined like this
when you take the product of some kind
of the number in the range from the 0ero
to one smaller than one if you take the
product of the loss of such kind of
numbers uh you're going to see that this
will get closer to the zero right which
means that as we have some kind of the
loss of the some kind of the multiple
steps in the for process. Naturally by
definition of the our default to the
tradition distribution uh this posterior
distribution will get closer to the
Gaussian distribution the standard
Gaussian distribution and that is
aligned with the hourly elbow function
right so by the finish of the default
process that is basically naturally
maximizing the elbow function
so you can see like why we defined for
the process in that way
so next time I'm going to continue
basically So what we are going to do how
we are going to deal with like this term
but you can see that here the all the
basic idea is that we are starting from
the BAE we are modeling the likelihood
and the posterior is kind of the gausian
distribution uh which are basically not
sufficient for the many complexity the
data distribution so that's why we start
to see some kind of the hierarchical
recursive way making the bae uh but the
thing is that we still don't want to
learn the post the likelihood and the
posterior
So now we are going to fix the post
error in a way that that naturally
basically maximizes the out function and
then we're going to only learn the uh
the likelihood decision. So that's
basically like one specific angle to see
interpret the the diffusion models and
we're going to keep discussing this idea
in the uh next Wednesday.