we're both very thrilled to be here
super happy thanks for the invitation
again it's already uh the midpoint
lecture seven the midpoint in this
amazing series of lecture so so far all
of you have had the opportunity to learn
a bit about the building blocks for
agentic systems things like how we do
reasoning or tool use with AI agents so
today we want to frame agents a little
bit about how they can be used used in
an Enterprise context in the context of
people trying to get actual work done
with agents
and the the focus will be really about
understanding what are the use cases who
are the users the human users for those
agents what role do they have what kind
of work are they trying to do and what
is the context in which uh these AI
agents should be deployed to help the
human users in the context of their uh
work activities for context both Alex
and I work at a company called service
now you may or may not have heard of it
it's a global company 25,000 employees
the headquarters are just down the bay
in Santa Clara and really workflows are
the bread and butter of what service now
does we build a platform to automate
Enterprise workflows we have products in
areas like it service management Human
Resources customer support and service
now is also a developer platform to help
both professional developers in line of
business regular people build new
workflows and to to give a sense of of
how this platform is used today and the
same for for all Enterprise workflows
platform one way to think about how
these platforms work is that they bring
together people
who need to get work done in the context
of their daily activities with people
who are doing the actual work so suppose
for example that you had a bad morning
and you spilled coffee on your laptop
your laptop is no longer working what do
you do well if you're at a modern
workplace you may hop onto your mobile
phone and open a ticket for your it help
desk and request a new laptop to be
shipped to you today this ticket is
going to be processed by a human user by
a human agent who will read the step
follow instructions to get the new
laptop shipped to you there's a lot of
manual steps that are involved in this
process this resolution of of everyday
issues that people in the the workplace
experience and what we will see is that
there are huge opportunities for AI
agents to help automate partly some of
this
work so before we go further both Alex
and I uh work for service now research
and of course uh our team works a lot on
agents and we have multiple sub teams uh
sub teams that work on various aspects
of of agent development but we also
think about all the other layers of the
stack so for example we have a team that
trains and fine tunes Foundation models
this is the team that worked with
hugging face for example to release the
star coder model that some of you may
have heard about and at the other end of
the stack we have a lot of people that
worry about things like AI
trustworthiness governance safety
security and the kind of practical
concerns that we will touch on a little
bit today in the context of Agents but
that are absolutely necessary if you
want to deploy AI
successfully and uh before moving into
uh the topic for today our friendly
legal team asked us to display this
disclaimer so here you
go and a quick note of the uh about the
agenda what we're going to be covering
today so we're going to start with a few
words of background of course this is
not the first lecture you have heard
many many things about AI agents so I
will not give uh any kind of uh of
explanation again but just set um um
explain the vocabulary and make sure
that we agree on the terminology and I
want to discuss a little bit what's the
matter with Enterprise workflows and how
a lot of work is happening in businesses
today then we're going to be talking a
bit more about API agents somewhat about
architectures but more deeply about a
new framework that we released as open
source just a couple days ago called
tape agents that offered a very
principled way to develop agents and
optimize them we're very excited about
uh this this new piece of work then I
will pass the button to Alex who uh will
talk to us about web agents how we can
develop them showing that building a
simple web agent is actually pretty
simple to do to do if you know what
you're doing but measuring their
performance making them better is
actually much harder so how can we do
that in in a more principled way and
what does the tooling to build develop
optimize web agents look like then I
will uh conclude by talking a little bit
about the potential for agents in the
workplace and the kind of large scale
Transformations that AI agents could
bring to us in the future
so let's start with a quick
definition again this is a class about
llm powered agents we uh assume that
this is clear and just a couple uh words
of definition we assume that those
agents have a degree of autonomy that
they can plan they can take action in an
environment they can receive feedback
from the environment and they can
execute goals that that are given by a
human user and usually this process
happens over multiple iterations so you
have certainly heard variant of that
definition earlier in this series of
lectures now maybe to to make things a
bit more crisp and a bit more precise
llm agents we really need to distinguish
them from what if you come from a
machine learning background is an
earlier generation of Agents agents that
are a bit more narrow in scope more
restricted architectures that are
typically that typically have a fairly
restricted action space that could be
trained using techniques like
reinforcement learning and that would be
very good at playing games for example
sometimes at superhuman performance
we're not going to be talking about that
today those agents although they are
really really good at playing Minecraft
for example your gam playing engines
would be terrible at right an email to
your boss and in contrast the the llm
agents what is really nice about them is
that the large language model at the
core of those agents has been trained on
a large fraction of the
internet and in doing that it has seen a
lot of instructions about common
software that people use every day there
is a lot of web page that talk about how
to use PowerPoint how to use Excel and
even business software like Salesforce
sap and even service now there's a lot
of documentation and News Group posts
about these things so those llms already
have a good sense of how to use software
that people use everyday and the goal of
an llm agent to a big extent will be to
leverage this kind of knowledge to get
uh to execute tasks that people want to
get done
and we will within llm agents we're
going to further distinguish two types
of uh of Agents one is an API calling
agent so it has a a tool set that can be
described using a somewhat formal
specification let's say a formal
specification of of a set of apis or
endpoints and those would be primarily
exchanging textual information and on
the other hand we will uh also talk
about web agents and those are able to
use the web pretty much like you and I
would by by pointing and clicking on
buttons on web pages by filling out
forms by navigating from page to page to
gather information to memorize little
pieces of information that can you can
reuse elsewhere in the task that you
need to do so of course each of those
has pros and cons we will uh touch upon
uh both
today and to frame this within the
context of uh uh work that folks need to
get done in their daily activities as as
employees of of big
companies imagine that we're facing an
issue where a user called John is not
able to access a particular knowledge
based article on the company interet so
John is a good employee he will file a
ticket with his it held desk and this
ticket gets assigned to Sandy and Sandy
looks at the ticket and tries to solve
the issue for John so what does sh Sandy
do well she uh first start by seeing if
there's an existing knowledge based
article that shows how to resolve this
issue maybe she doesn't find any so she
looks it to see if there are earlier
incidents that looked a little bit like
this problem is that she's trying to
solve maybe she finds one and in it she
sees that she needs to check the access
control that John
has and she will change the access
control to give the right permissions
because John didn't have the right
controls she changes the the
permissions and finally she resolves the
case and since Sandy is working in a
very um Advanced workplace she has a
brand new gen uh generative AI
capability that just got deployed in the
last year and lo and behold the
generative AI
capability is able to do the the
incident summarization for her write
resolution notes uh and finally close
the case Okay so as you can see there
are many many manual steps even if
you're helped with some generative AI
capabilities there are many many manual
steps that remain uh in solving everyday
work items that people need to do in in
the course of their uh daily work and
this kind of incident is replicated
millions and millions and millions times
a day across all the companies in the
world and to to give a sense of um how
the the the landscape of Enterprise
automation has evolved
what we see is that there has been a a
progression in the past couple of years
going from systems that are very
scripted that are very manually
programmed with a very low degree of
automation things like either manual
scripting or robotic process Automation
and gradually we have seen increased
degree of automation that require
increased degree of intelligence going
with classical AI workflows about
recommender systems for example
conversational workflows that have
become more prevalent in the past couple
of years especially with generative Ai
and today agent at workflow that require
the most intelligence but also have the
most promise for
Automation and what's the what's the
promise for agents in the workplace or
in Enterprise automation is that they
really have a unique opportunity to
automate the masses of low volume low
value tasks that people encounter every
day so what are those you may ask well
let's start by looking at what are not
low value low volume the big rocks of
Enterprise automation things that have a
lot of value or that occur very very
often those probably have already been
solved because people found find it
valuable to sit down and figure out how
to to program an automation for those
use cases so things like employee
onboarding workflows for example and
things that that occur quite often that
are predictable replicable a good chance
that there is existing low code no code
environment or uh robotic uh process
automation processes that have been put
in place to automate those but again
think about everything you do every day
all the little grains of sand that are
too unique to be scripted or to be
automated they never occur twice in
exactly the same way so it's very very
hard to say oh I'm going to automate
scheduling my tweets or answering my
emails or filling out uh updating uh
customer relationship management system
or even organizing a meeting for 15
people across four different companies
those things are are very hard to
automate you using classical
Technologies and this is where agents
have the potential to really shine and
help do a much better job at all those
little grains of sand that individually
each of them is Tiny But in aggregate
they represent a massive amount of work
that people need to get done every
day so let's take a look at a simple
example of a web agent that we will be
developing and expanding on a little bit
later later today a couple months ago we
were invited to give a presentation at
the big conference that Nvidia puts
together the GPU technology conference
GTC and of course we did not know how to
get there so we asked our web agent for
help and the web agent that you're going
to see on the left side of the screen is
the the interaction that me as a as a
human I was having with the web agent
and on the right is everything that the
web agent is doing automatically through
a a chrome like web browser so let's
let's get this rolling so I'm asking the
web agent hey I'm attending GTC 2024 how
can I get there from the Nvidia
headquarters so the agent goes off and
okay well it's starting with Google it's
asking Google uh how to get there good
progress it's getting to maps and Google
Maps says hey I don't know uh anything
about GTC it's not an item on on the map
so we're going back to uh so the agent
is asking me hey can you give me a bit
more instructions there and I tell it
I'm I want to attend actually the GTC
conference so the agent now has done
some replanning it's using Google to
figure out the location of the
conference it's finding it as the San
Jose Convention Center and this is what
it is entering into Google Maps now to
figure out the way to get from the
Nvidia headquarters to the San Jose
Convention Center okay so this is an
example of the kind of interaction that
we soon will be getting or that we hope
we should be getting with our agents as
systems that are allowed to ask more
questions to humans but that have some
smarts in terms of planning and
replanning of their
own okay so let's uh shift gear now and
talk a little bit about API
agents the typical architecture this
slide is probably going to be a repeat
uh of some of the work that was covered
earlier but again just to set the uh our
minds in the in the right uh in the
right state so we start with an llm
agent that is able to emit some actions
and those are sent to an environment and
the environment sends back observations
back to the llm
agent the agent has access to some
short-term memory so what have been the
past actions taken and the past
responses from the environment it also
has access to some planning processes so
things like react and so on so there
there are many different strategies that
have been proposed we're not going to
get too much into those today and of
course
for agents to be useful it has to access
some tools and the tools there can be
quite varied uh including uh simple
calculations running code accessing the
web and so on and some more advanced
agents also have the ability to
synthesize new tools and those can be
store in in some kind of long-term
memory but the Beyond those basic
concepts we want to have the right
software framework to help build agents
okay just like it would be crazy for
anyone today to try to program machine
learning algorithms from scratch
everybody uses pytorch because it's so
much faster it's so much easier so we we
want to have the right framework to
build agents and I want to talk about a
new framework for holistic agent
development so both the tooling to help
Bill and debug agents but also the
tooling to optimize a Agents from
optimization
traces we introduced this framework
called tape agents just a couple days
ago in fact the QR code is uh is the
link to the the resources all of that
will be given again at the end don't
worry and what we're trying to
accomplish with tape agents is that is
to get a little bit of The Best of Both
Worlds so on the one hand we have
Frameworks that really address the need
for the software engineering part of
Agents we want to be able to spit
specify those agents to a very fine
degree of granularity to have pre-made
components to have uh facilities like
concurrency and streaming from the
llm and um you you've heard before about
Frameworks like uh L graph autogen and
so on so so this is great for developing
agent and on the other hand we have a
need to optimize agents okay those
agents they all are are uh the result of
prompting an llm so whoever says
prompting says prompt
optimization prompt engineering some of
it is done by hand but you can do a much
better job if the machine can do it on
your behalf and in some context you may
even want to optimize the llm itself to
make it a really good Agent llm so we
have Frameworks like dspi that is very
very nice for doing this kind of
optimization work
but until tape agent there was no
framework that was really good at doing
those two things together okay so really
what we hope to accomplish with tape
agent is this best of both World type of
situation where we have great tools to
build and engineer and debug agents
while at the same time getting the right
Primitives and the right Concepts in
place that enable both prompt
optimization and uh fine-tuning of the
underlying llm
so as a as a framework tape agent itself
Builds on a single unifying abstraction
that we call the tape so what is a tape
it is simply a log a recording of all
the thoughts and actions that all agents
in the system we assume we can have more
than one agent so all the the the agents
in the system store their thoughts and
their actions to the
and whenever the environment is is is
called and and we make we place an
action in the environment whatever
results from the environment is also
added to the tape okay so we have this
single unifying log and and uh record of
of things and you can say okay well it's
just a dum log what is so special about
it well first it's not a Dom log it is
it has quite a lot of structure and
importantly it is is a piece of data
itself and we can have agents that take
as input the tapes that result from the
execution of other agents for further
processing okay so this introducing this
notion of having a tape as a full-blown
data structure that is very very rich in
the content of its metadata and can be
processed by further Downstream
algorithms is really where the the power
of this framework applies so in terms of
just the the execution model to set
things uh clearly in your mind uh bring
your attention to the agent on the right
Agent B and this one um gets a read of
the entire history of the tape so far
and the Agents select which of its
internal nodes it's going to execute at
a particular point in time and the nodes
again just from an abstraction
perspective they are the little pieces
that decide how to prompt an llm an
agent can have as many nodes or as few
nodes as you wish it's really up to you
as as an agent developer to decide on
the internal structure of those agents
but the nodes then call the llm the llm
either suggests a few prompts sorry a
few thoughts or a few actions don't get
those get added to the tape and we have
an orchestrator that can then go call
the environment for executing any
unprocessed actions get the reply Li
from the environment and the loop
continues okay so it's it's a fairly
straightforward execution model but in
that you will notice that we have the
ability to have multiple agents and each
agent can get can delegate work to some
sub agents as well so it's very modular
uh it leads to a very flexible structure
of agent and furthermore we can have
very very nice things that result from
this tape as data idea of course we have
full-blown auditing and debugging
capabilities that are very very obvious
and we can have some algorithms that
take the tape as input and do uh cycles
of prompt optimization to it to get
better prompt and we can have also
agents that distill the work of some
fairly complicated teacher agents and
enable building much more cost effective
effective student agent as a result so
we can have an optimization of the
underlying llm as a result of that we'll
see in a minute what this looks
like so a very simple example of that
Loop that I talked about there is a a
full technical report the link um was
provided in in the pread to this lecture
so I will not get too too deeply into
the details but this is more to give a
flavor of what's going on
here assume you have a simple two agent
system very uh uh straightforward
question answering assistant about the
financial status of companies for
example so we have the assistant itself
that talks to human users and this agent
is able to rely on a sub agent that will
perform web searches for it okay so this
simple two agent setup here we combine
it it with this quite straightforward
execution Loop that we described earlier
and this gives rise in this very
detailed granular tape record recording
of the the interactions between all the
agents their internal monologue their
internal reasoning traces the action
they take and how the environment
responds and of course uh the tapes in
practice are quite uh um involve you can
reproduce this example through the
introductory notebook that you can run
on your laptop this is super easy to run
and what this all gives us though is the
ability for agents
to process tapes in um in in a way that
enables easy
optimization we we have uh we don't have
time today to go deeply into the details
uh of this this example but at a high
level what we want to do is to uh
provide agents that
have a high degree of sophistication
that can provide very very high quality
user interaction but that are also quite
cheap to run run so we run a case study
where we built on the the notion of
having to um having an assistant that
helps you fill out complex forms to
request work to be done in the context
of your daily work
activity and the this this process is is
about enabling a very complex agent to
be distilled down into a simple agent
what this lets us do is to create very
coste effective great conversational
agents okay and great of course I did
not uh misspell it on purpose it uh
stands for the attributes that we want
to monitor in the agents that we build
and
we uh selected really these attributes
as covering all the quality attributes
that would make great conversational
agents okay so things like we want the
agent to be grounded to never
hallucinate to always tell the truth we
want the agent to be responsive to be
accurate to be disciplined transparent
and helpful and all those attributes can
be measured independently and we can
optimize for all of those together so in
a case study that we run that is very uh
very much detailed in in the technical
report we
built um we built a set of agents to
fulfill a task which is helping human
users fill out those very comple very
complex forms that they sometimes
encounter in the context of their work
and making it a lot easier to fill out
the the forms and what we want to do is
to build a fantastic conversational
experience think about GP 4 level
quality or better but much much more
deeply and we run a case study by
inventing fictitious
companies having a few companies to
train the model and a few companies to
test uh for outof distribution e
effectiveness of of the model and the
the methodology that we followed there
is to have a very complicated very
High parameter count agent that is
running on Lama 3.5 3.1 405 billion
parameter model so very costly to
execute generate a lot of
data um to uh that is recorded in the
form of these discrete tapes these
discrete uh uh execution traces and
using this data we fine-tune a Lama 8
billion parameter model to recover uh
the performance of the much much bigger
parent that was used as a as a starting
point and I will go straight to the to
the graph
there um we achieve substantial success
in doing that what we see on the chart
there is on the x-axis how much it cost
to run a million conversation turns uh
with those agents and on the y-axis is
this measure of quality this great score
that we introduced previously and that
can be um computed quite um that can be
computed uh quite
crisply
and with no surprise on the the the
upper right hand side we have the
largest agents available so we have a a
Lama uh four or five billion parameter
model that is having a great score
and a zero shut GPT 4 o model that is
also having a great score but both of
those are very expensive to run uh we're
talking about 30,000 to 40,000 is
dollars per million conversation turns
so though those are very expensive
agents but by using the methodology that
is enabled by this concept of of saving
tapes and treating them as data to
generate fine-tuning data for a simp
simpler agent we see that we're able to
fine-tune an 8 billion parameter model
that has the same performance as the
much larger model but is more than 300
times cheaper to run okay so a huge gain
in performance
there and if you're familiar with other
agentic framework we also have a quick
table but I will uh go quickly over that
uh comparing tape agents to other
Frameworks now time is flying I will
pass it to Alex who will shift gears and
uh tell us about web agents great thank
you nikar hi everyone um yeah so nikar
just told us about API agents those are
great when you have apis available when
you have tools that that can do some of
the execution for you um but now I'm
going to talk about another kind of
agent that promises to be more General
than that and this is web agents and
basically this is uh a great improvisor
right so when there's no apis available
um you could expect an agent to be able
to interact with the user interface just
like you and me would do uh when using
some
software oops that doesn't work okay so
what's a web agent uh to be original
I'll show you an agent Loop that I'm
sure you've seen many times uh right now
uh except it's going to be style
transferred for web agents so suppose
you have a user uh with a goal in mind
and then the web agent is just a policy
that perceives an environment which in
our case is a web browser and uh
perceives observations from the
environment and then decides which
actions to make okay so it's a simple
agentic Loop where the web agent here in
our case will be an llm who's choosing
to do an action based on whatever
observation comes from the browser so
this is actually quite challenging um
because first of all you need to
understand the go you need to understand
what the human wants uh you need to
understand the you need to be situation
awareness basically you need to
understand what you're seeing in the
browser what's the user interface
showing and long-term planning is really
challenging here because most of the
time what you want the end result is not
on the current page right so you need to
transition navigate some menus and then
ultimately you'll end up on the right
page but this is not necessarily
perceivable from the current set of
observations that are available to the
agent um yeah and then once you've made
a plan and you you know what you want to
do you still have to execute the actions
correctly and as we'll see in in the
following slides even this is quite
challenging for current agents okay so
how do you make a basic web agent okay
this is the most basic thing you can do
uh suppose you have a human who's asking
for something so fly me to Yellowstone
for the next long weekend and there's a
browser now what you could do is take
your favorite llm and build a prompt and
in this prompt you could put the task
description so you you can put the goal
uh you can put the observation which
here would be for example the HTML of a
web page uh you could put the ra HTML
directly in the prompt if you have a a
long enough context window and then you
can you can Define what the action space
is so is the agent allowed to click on
controls is it allowed to fill some fill
some forms for example uh and then you
would give this to an llm and then ask
for the actions it wants to make based
on the observation and then you want to
actually go and apply those in the
browser uh so often what people use is a
combination of python and playright
which is a browser automation Library
you also have selenium that can do
similar things um so that's a very basic
web agent and concretely what you could
do here is an example from the mini wob
data set uh so I could build this prompt
like that I could say uh the task is to
enter Enola in the in the text box and
then press submit uh so I would put the
content of the page there in the prompt
uh I would say the action space what
you're allowed to do here is fill a
field with its ID so you would say fill
ID number one and it would fill that
field uh move the mouse and so on right
and then I would ask the LM what do you
want to do now output your actions
between those brackets here and the LM
would potentially answer with this so
fill the field with Enola and then click
right so here you can see gp4 a gp4
based agent that's actually doing that
uh when prompted with this kind of promt
so this seems very simple but it's
actually already quite powerful
surprisingly so what you're seeing here
is a a very basic agent done pretty much
like what I just showed you um and it's
based on gp4 and react style prompting
so we're asking the agent to Output its
thoughts and then actions it wants to
make you can see that at the top and
it's actually filling out the expense
reports of Nicola when he traveled to a
conference recently
um here you can see it actually filling
out the form this is gp4 that's acting
with the very simple prompt that that I
just showed you okay so you can see how
this this already makes at least for me
it makes me dream right you can say like
wow this is great we we could imagine
having assistance like that that will
automate tasks for us in the browser
this is uh the next evolution of user
interfaces and so on right so um we were
quite excited when we saw that um so the
truth is is that this is very brittle
right so this is a prompt it works right
now um we have some great anecdotic
examples like that where it works really
well but we need it for for this to be
adopted in practice it needs to work
robustly right so it needs to work most
of the time we need to be able to ensure
that it's not going to be jailbroken or
hijacked by injections in the web pages
right so uh this needs to be reliable so
and by the way this is also one one
other limitation of this kind of agent
right now is that it's quite slow so
here the video I just showed you was
sped up by eight times right so so in
practice you really need to wait like 15
seconds for the the the mouse to move
from one point to the other which is not
not yet what we want for a smooth user
interface but you can see it has
potential okay
so given the fact that we need this to
be very robust for it to be actually
applicable in practice there's been a
lot of effort on building benchmarks so
you may have seen some I'm going to
outline a few recent benchmarks but this
has been a trend mostly because we want
to know beyond anecdotes how those work
in practice uh so here you are seeing
the mini wob data set um which are very
simple web tasks like filling a field
clicking submit or just dragging a a box
from one side of the screen to the other
um this is great it's a good start but
it's not realistic so people have
started to propose benchmarks based on
real world websites uh so first kind of
Benchmark are Trace based benchmarks and
these are mostly based on traces of
actions that have been performed by
human annotators so they receive a goal
and they have a website and then uh
their actions are recorded So they
clicked on that they filled this field
and so on um so this is nice it's more
realistic but the evaluation here is
mostly based on gold traces so these are
gold standard traces basically you check
if the agent is doing similar actions to
what the human it um this a limitation
of that that is that it does not account
for the fact that there may exist
alternative solutions to a problem and
also when you store those traces on the
internet there's a risk that they will
be memorized by llms that are trained by
crawling for example so oh yeah one
exception here um is a a brand new uh
kind of Benchmark by moral um where an
llm is used to generate traces so
basically it's dropped randomly on the
internet at some point acts acts uh by
performing random actions and then
retrospectively annotates what a goal
could have been that would have led them
there so it's a way to generate
thousands of those traces without having
to rely on human annotators I thought
that was pretty interesting idea and you
can use that for evaluation but you can
also use it for fine-tuning um we'll get
back to that
later great so beyond Trace based data
sets there's been a trend on making live
benchmarks so instead of annotating
instead of evaluating based on traces of
actions you evaluate based on the end
result so for example you could say well
I expect that if this task is solved
correctly the database will be in a
certain State and then instead of
checking trace of actions you actually
just check if the database is in the
correct State uh some other benchmarks
rely on question answering and they
check if you return the correct answer
instead of checking the set of steps
that you took to to get to that answer
um this is nice because it allows for
alternate Solutions and it's also um
there's a lower chance of memorization
right because the traces are not stored
uh in a public repository so two good
examples of that are the web Arena and
the Visual Web Arena uh benchmarks so
web arena is actually a set of tasks
where you receive a goal and uh you need
to perform some actions in software like
Reddit or gitlab and uh there's certain
terminal conditions that are checked to
see if the agent was able to solve the
task correctly um these are actually
great because you uh the way you you
Benchmark on this kind of Benchmark is
that you run uh a local server and then
uh everything is served locally so it's
great if you want to do parallel
experiments you don't have bandwidth
issues uh it's really nice the the only
issue here is that it's limited to open
source software and you need some
complex installation you need to set up
your own server locally so another kind
of Benchmark uh are based on remote
servers and these are really on the open
web they're more realistic because
there's latency uh which is the reality
when you when you go over the the real
internet um and it's also nice because
you can support websites that are not
necessarily open source you don't have
to host them locally um the downside of
that is that they can be unreliable uh
there can be network issues you need an
internet connection to be able to
Benchmark um yeah so different kinds of
benchmarks here um work arena is a
benchmark that we proposed it's based on
the actual service now product so I'm
going to dig a bit deeper in that but
work arena is a remote hosted Benchmark
so nothing happens on your local machine
um so what work arena is is a is an open
source Benchmark so The Benchmark is
open source the product is not open
source but the Benchmark is um it's 600
work related tasks that are performed on
a service now product so um we thought
that by having access to service now and
the fact that millions of people use it
every day in their daily job uh we
thought well that's a that's a great
tool to make a benchmark to see how web
agents are able to to help people in the
workplace um so what we did we started
by making some tasks that are really
simple this is just we call it work
Arena level one uh this is just
interacting with those six basic
components so for example sorting a list
or filtering a list in the product uh
searching a knowledge base to find the
answer to a question like what's the
Wi-Fi password for the office uh reading
a dashboard saying which item do we have
the most in stock for example
so these are the kind of tasks that we
have in the level one of work Arena and
we go from that all the way to really
complex realistic workflows uh and I'll
show you some examples in the coming
slides but before I move on I just want
to explain how this remote hosted
Benchmark Works how do we make it work
um obviously we cannot ship you a Docker
image that contains service now because
this means we would be giving you the
codebase of the product um so what we do
here is we rely on something called
developer instances and these are clones
of the product that anyone can get you
just go to a website called developer.
servicenow.com uh you request an
instance and you got your own copy of
the product that you can use for uh it's
used for developers to learn how to
program custom tools for the for the
product and so the Benchmark is built on
that basically um you give the
credentials to your instance and then
the agent interacts with the front end
so it interacts with the web pages and
we do all the validation by using
backend dpis so we check if the agent
correctly solved the task by going to
check the state of the database um so
yeah it's it's based on a real product
that people use for Real uh but uh
everyone can access it the tasks in The
Benchmark are open source just not uh
the service not
product great so uh just to give you an
to make this a bit more concrete here's
gp4 actually solving some tasks in work
Arena uh you could see it ordering an
Apple Watch you can see it reading
dashboards uh filling out some forms uh
sorting some lists uh so these are all
tasks from work Arena level one this is
the simplest kind of tasks that we have
in the
Benchmark um now I want to give you a
more a more difficult task an example of
a more difficult task this is actually
what we call work Arena level three it's
pretty hard um so here what you see is a
ticket okay so it's an interface that
shows a ticket that's assigned to the
human uh in this case the agent is that
human and they have to solve the task so
basically what they have to do here is
to go check a dashboard and need they
need to find which item is the lowest in
inventory and then order uh some items
to replenish it from a service catalog
um so you can see that all the agent
receives as instruction is please solve
this and it's it starts from this page
basically which is a ticket um and then
it says if you're not sure what to do
you can always refer to the knowledge
base for further instructions and it
gives it uh instructions to which
article they could check so the first
step for the agent here is to go to the
knowledge base so it needs to use the
menus and navigate to this knowledge
base find it find the right article
extract the information on how to
proceed for example how to get to the
dashboards then it needs to go open the
dashboard read it find which item is the
least available in stock and then it
needs to navigate all the way to a
service catalog where it's a ble to
order this item so three highle steps
but with many many lowlevel steps in
between there's navigation involved it's
not clear imagine if I drop you in a
room with multiple doors and you don't
really see what's behind them you need
to get to the right spot but you can't
explore too much right because you have
a limited number of steps so this is
actually a a really hard task um and so
in addition to this example we have all
kinds of capabilities that are being
being evaluated in these tasks um one of
them I'll give you one example it's
planning and problem solving so for
example um one of the tasks in work
Arena involves looking at a set of
employees seeing who is the most busy
and taking some work from the most busy
employee and reassigning it to the least
busy one so basically workload balancing
across employees um there's other ones
like scheduling with constraints so
scheduling some events with some
constraints um we have tasks about
budget
management um all kinds of things so
sophisticated memorization tasks
basically basically involve collecting
bits and pieces of information across
many pages and in the end solving a task
based on everything you gathered and
finally we have some tasks that are just
infeasible and uh the agent needs to to
say hey this this cannot be done right
so uh it needs to use some critical
thinking to be able to say that no this
this doesn't have a solution uh if
you're interested the paper is here and
you can take a look it's also in the the
pre-reading for the course so okay now
I'll show you how well the agents that
we have right now uh do on this
Benchmark the title is a bit of a
spoiler um but um what you see okay what
what you see um on the right here is the
scores from a human evaluation that we
performed on work Arena level two and
level three and these are the really the
realistic workflows the ones I just
showed you um so so you can see that
humans have a really high score the
average score was roughly
94% uh across all our humans human
evaluators on those tasks um and so when
we look at work Arena L1 unfortunately
we don't have human eval for that but
you can see that our best agent does
roughly 40 it does
42.7% success rate which means you give
it a task 42.7% of the time it solves it
um so that's working aren one and this
is a good agent because it achieved a
very high well the high one of the
highest scores on web arena is
23.5% this is how we know it's a decent
agent um okay now let's look at what it
does on work Arena level
two a lot of zeros there unfortunately
uh so we we have some success you can
see that there is something there but
most of the tasks are not solved
correctly and when we move it to level
three which is the example that that
you've seen before um we get zeros all
across the
okay uh despite the fact that humans get
94% success rate on those tasks so what
you what you see here is that um the
example I showed you in the beginning
was was exciting like it's it seems that
there is potential there but obviously
there seems to be some work to be done
by the community uh and and we think
that this Benchmark will really help in
making progress towards that so you may
be curious like why doesn't this work
why why do we have zeros everywhere um a
lot of time it's failure to plan so the
agent um only perceives what is on its
local page and fails to explore um
sometimes we have hallucinations
hallucinated controls the agent will
imagine imagine a button that's it's
called solve task and the action it will
make is Click solve task basically um so
it invents shortcuts for itself uh or
basically incorrect syntax when it's
outputting which actions to
perform Okay so
work arena is not the only Benchmark
that has been proposed recently as you
can see there are many uh there's tens
of thousands of tasks in those
benchmarks all for web agents uh and
each of those evaluates different
aspects um but what's unfortunate is
that um all of these benchmarks are not
necessarily being evaluated with the
same protocol the same kinds of Agents
so it's quite hard to compare so um we
are making tools to try to unify
everything uh so we we made this uh
framework called browser gym and
essentially it's a unified evaluation
platform and we tried to regroup most of
the major benchmarks and we're still
adding some uh if you want to contribute
to that actually we accept bull requests
so if you think there's one of those
benchmarks that you think is interesting
uh feel free to to we'll work with you
to get it into the into the platform so
essentially what browser gym does is
that it gives you a standardized
observation space um so you see this
agentic loop on the side uh well
essentially at the top you have HTML but
you have accessibility tree which is a
shortened version of the HTML a bit
refined uh and then you have screenshots
we have a chatbox modality so there's a
bunch of different observation
modalities that we provide in browser
gym and we also provide a standardized
action space so you can see examples at
the bottom here um so you can do a mouse
click you can do a click on it says
click bid something B is a is a
numerical ID that we assign
automatically to every control on the
page so basically to to click on
something the agent would say click
number two and we would go and roll it
out using python playwright so this is
browser gym um and again we regroup most
of the of the major benchmarks and we're
still adding some in there um what's
also cool is that browser gym allows to
do human evaluation this is what we use
to do the the the human eval in work
Arena uh essentially uh you get the same
kind of chatbox interface with the web
browser uh except you get this thing
where uh you can assign a curriculum of
tasks to a human and then they can ask
for validation or they can simply give
up H go to the next task for example so
all of this is in browser gym you can
pip install it or you can use this QR
code to to access
it cool so in addition to to browser gym
we propos agent lab uh which is another
set of tool for for building web agents
here agent lab the goal of it is to uh
it's to be a toolbox to build web agents
so we provide simple building blocks to
build web agents but also tools to
understand their behavior so why they're
not working debug their performance for
example and a lot of tools to um to run
large scale experiments and ensure
reproducibility so one thing that we
propose is called Agent x-ray here you
see that um I'm selecting an experiment
that I conducted I click on a task from
one of the benchmarks and I click on a
random seed then what I see is
essentially what the agent was seeing I
can see the screenshots of what the
agent was seeing uh can see um basically
this is the accessibility tree of a web
page uh you can see the reasoning traces
of the agent you can see which actions
were performed and you see also this
kind of um this kind of timeline here at
the top this is giving you profiling
information on how much time was spent
reasoning how much time was spent
performing the actions how many how many
steps the agent performs so this
basically agent x-ray the goal is to
help you understand what's going on with
your agent and try to improve it
great so in addition to that we proposed
agent lab um and uh sorry we propos
Tools in uh for reproducibility in agent
lab and essentially um One Challenge we
tried to address is the fact that it's
really hard to Benchmark on Dynamic
environments that we don't control um so
websites are updated
continuously um llm API based llms can
be silently updated we don't really see
what's going on in the background and
python packages evolve so how do you
make benchmarks that remain comparable
Through Time right um so what we're
trying to do uh in agent lab and this is
work in progress uh there's already
something uh in our GitHub repository
but we're building that uh as we speak
so we're trying to find ways to extract
standardized observation traces so you
got observations actions observations
and so on um and try to propose public
repositories for the for those traces to
be stored but with the properties of the
agent that was used with the versions of
the Python pack packages um with the
dates and everything so we're trying to
make it as reproducible as possible uh
and make mechanisms for this to be
automat automatic as much as possible uh
in addition to that we're trying to make
leaderboards for the major benchmarks
with uh using these traces and the
experimental information with mechanisms
that allow to reproduce the results and
check if they still um remain valid
through time right since the environment
is
evolving okay and so by combining agent
lab and browser gym we think there's a
great opportunity because um first of
all we have a standardized observation
space standardized action space
standardized traces uh and public
repositories to store those traces so we
think that um with this mechanism we
could we have the potential of um doing
basically distributed Trace collections
so everyone could help us gather traces
of web agents acting on the open web and
we might be able to use that to collect
a big repository of traces that we could
further use for for fine-tuning and
making better agents in the future so
agent lab and browser gym provide the
tools we need to do
that okay so uh before I hand it over to
Nica I just want to finish with uh the
challenges of web agents okay um there
is hope I think we'll make great
progress on those benchmarks uh in the
coming year uh I just want to to review
the major uh hurdles here so long
context understanding the websites are
huge so we're talking about tens of
thousands of tokens hundreds of
thousands of tokens uh easily even for
the accessibility trees which are
supposed to be shorter than the ra HTML
uh this makes huge observations the
amount of relevant information in those
in those contexts is very small so it's
already a challenge to be able to pick
it out correctly long-term planning as I
said um it's quite hard to be on a page
with no information of what is uh two or
three pages away and try to reason uh
about okay I'm going to go to this menu
and then I'm going to click on that and
eventually I'll end up in the right
place we have intuition for that um we
are used to using Amazon for example so
we know how to search that and navigate
that and we can analogous websites are
not um are not obscure to us but for
another it could um so there's work to
be done in that space uh this myal paper
that I mentioned is is a good step in
that direction by collecting uh traces
of random actions at a very large scale
this might help um for for um fine
tuning LMS to better understand where
they could get in a few steps um
learning and adaptability so we need to
be able to learn from observation learn
from
demonstrations uh and mistakes so
there's some work in that direction I
wanted to mention the agent Q work that
uses uh Monte Carlo research and DPO to
try to find tune agents and do inference
time search I think this is an
interesting work
um there is multimodality that's very
important uh actually the Visual Web
Arena Benchmark uh proposes a set of
tasks that you simply can't solve if
you're not looking at the vision
modality so um if I give you a task that
is order me a shirt like that well you
need to be able to see what the shirt is
to be able to solve it right um cost and
efficiency uh as I said the videos that
we we showed you were sped up by by a
lot right so we need to make this fast
we need to make it efficient uh I think
shrinking the context size is One
Direction uh there's a potential to use
retrieval to retrieve only the relevant
elements from the observation space um
there's potential for uh using
multi-agent architectures where uh you
have for example the date picker agent
which is a very small llm that is only
used to do a very small task of filling
out date Pickers for example right so
perhaps there's some multi-agent
architectures that could be used there
um and finally fine-tuning smaller lmm
um so one that is very crucial so I'm
finishing with this one um is safety
okay so no one wants to roll out an
agent that can be easily hijacked um and
current agents the ones I showed you in
the demo actually it has been tested if
you put white on white text on the page
that says hey GPT follow these new
instructions it will follow those new
instructions right so we need robustness
we need uh agents that are able to be
robust to injection on the web page uh
not only in the HTML but also in the
text box right you don't want people to
be able to write instructions there um
and I think this challenge is even
bigger now that we have multimodel
models because you're uh subject to
attacks from both from all modalities
essentially so it amplifies the problem
um and so this is one of Nicola's
example on 2000 it was 2030 but we
switched it to
2026 uh because I think it's it's not so
far away but you can imagine malicious
Chrome plugins or malicious browser
plugins that detect when you log into
your bank's website and inject using
JavaScript some instructions on a web
page to hijack the agent and get get
them to do uh wi transfer to some to
some account right so the these seem
farfetch but they're they're they're
quite real when you start to think about
web agents so we really need to be
robust to these kind of things all right
so that's it for web agents and I'll
hand back to Nik thank you
Alex we're uh coming on to the last part
of this presentation where we take a
step back and look at what is the
potential impact of those agent
Technologies in the the broader
workpace and there is no question that
AI agents are on their wi will soon be
on their way to change completely the
nature of work and to go back to the
example we gave earlier it was only uh
the the beginning we uh if you remember
Sandy was uh struggling to get the the
the knowledge based permissions for John
to to to see this article and and at the
time she was only able to get a little
bit of help from generative AI to to uh
make her job a tiny bit faster so let's
see how AI agents will be able to
tremendous ly help Sandy be much much
more
productive so with in a world where AI
agents are deployed first Sandy will not
even look at the ticket right away so so
there will be a ticket that will be
coming her way but but before she even
opens it a set of AI agents will already
have tried to do a partial solution of
the ticket itself so we'll be getting a
uh an agent that looks at the ticket
itself and tries to solve it and it's
going to propose the the solution as a
set of steps and the steps are going to
be well maybe uh we can start by finding
what permissions John has access to then
we can um fix the find the right
permissions for the knowledge based
article and allowing John's permissions
to where he needs to access the KB
article and then once this plan is done
maybe we want to ask the human for
confirmation so we have an orchestrator
agent that is asking Sandy for
permission Sandy says looks at the plan
and says yeah it looks all right to me
let's proceed so once Sandy gives her
approval then we have another bunch of
AI agents that will each solve the
little soft tasks that need to be done
then uh is pass to a user access agent
that is contemplating giving John the
right access but before doing anything
destructive is asking again Sandy for
confirmation hey Sandy are you okay with
me giving John permission to access this
knowledge base s says yes of course and
finally the ticket is closed okay so we
see a much more Grand and and a lot more
work that's being undertaken by a team
of AI agents all working together to to
help out Sandy I will in the interest of
time skip quickly on this uh beautiful
chart saying the state of web agents and
how they can automate
but once we take a look at the very
granular ways in which agents contribute
to specific workflows we can ask
ourselves what's the potential for them
to have an impact on the broader work
world of knowledge
work and before we do that we need to
ask ourselves what is knowledge work of
course knowledge work is not a single
thing it's many many many different
things we have uh meeting scheduling and
coordination ethical hacking language
localization we have literally thousands
and thousands of tasks in the economy
that are broadly categorize as knowledge
work so so how do we get a sense of the
impact that that AI agents are going to
have on this very very broad spectrum of
occupations fortunately there are tools
that we can use to help get started
doing this kind of assessment in
particular in the US the Bureau of Labor
Statistics has already compiled a big
database called the onet database that
is literally a um a list of all the
occupations in the US economy and for
each occupation each job description it
has a set of tasks that uh need to be
done in the daily activities of this job
okay so to take one example if we have
software quality assurance analyst and
tester we see the job description that
is coming from the onet database this is
free you can download it there's no
problem there and then the set of tasks
and the skills that a person needs to do
okay so if we want to assess the impact
of AI agents one way to go is to take a
look at the database like this and try
to understand is each task that this
software quality assurance is doing how
far can it be automated through AI
agents okay this is one way to proceed
of course some people have thought about
it before and and we have um technology
adoption curves this uh this is coming
from u a McKenzie report from a um a few
months ago that takes a look you know
across uh oecd countries in this case
what is
the anticipated adoption curve for the
broads set of generative AI Technologies
of which AI agents are subset across the
economy with both expected adoption and
and uh worst case adoption curves
one thing to keep in mind is that when
we um try to analyze adoption curves
like this we there are many many factors
that are gating the adoption and
technology is only one of those the the
the process of assessing technological
maturity only reflects a partial picture
of where we are going at the level of
the
economy and broadly speaking we can
think about about two ways of assessing
impact there is a topown way that is
coming from a top- down analysis of a
database like the onet database and
trying to ask GPT to guess for each task
of each job how much you think the uh
generative AI will um help automate this
task and there is a bottom up assessment
in which we can use a benchmark like
work Arena to track at a very very
granular
level the real actual automation rate
for um the state of technology today as
it pertains to specific tasks okay so
none of those approaches is perfect one
is fuzzy the other is incomplete but
together they can help us triangulate a
little bit and get a sense of what is
the the anticipated or the likely rate
of um technology adoption how fast the
job descriptions will change because
part of them will be done by AI agents
and this kind of analysis can be used to
help decision makers and companies plan
for reskilling programs for employees
for example and make sure that we can
navigate technology readiness in a way
that benefits uh uh all
people but all in all this is uh getting
to be very exciting we can already see
ways in which humans and machines are
working together in new ways there is a
very uh influential study that came out
a few a few months ago from Harvard
Business School and uh BCG the the
consulting firm that looked at the ways
in which people were um
working jointly with Advanced generative
AI Technologies and they found that the
there were two main patterns in the
division of labor between human and
Mission One pattern is broadly called
the centor pattern in which there is a
strategic decomposition of Labor the
human is planning the high level task
and big chunks of work are outsourced if
you will to AI systems and the second
way is called the cyborg in which there
is a very intimate very granular
collaboration between human and machine
to solve uh task and to get work done
and it's still very much early days
there are enormous opportunities for
user experience and computer human
interaction research there to really
figure out what will be the most
productive patterns for each person
maybe it depends on the personality type
certainly the kind of work to be done
and so on so finally it's already time
to conclude we uh leave it with a couple
of resources to dig further we made a
timeline of the influential work if you
want to dig further in the realm
of llm agents and
benchmarks so on the top are various uh
Frameworks that have been
introduced uh prior to 2024 along with
benchmarks and um we have the stuff that
came out this year there has been a ton
of activity in the space this is for
benchmarks uh and on the web agent front
we have the early research starting with
the mini uh the mini wob work in
2017 um and continuing this year with a
ton of uh
new agentic Frameworks for web agents as
well as new benchmarks that Alex
described so so with this it's time to
ask our lecture agent to create the
slides for our presentation next
year and it's also time to thank uh our
amazing colleagues at service now that
made all of what you saw today possible
QR codes for everything we talked about
tape agents work Arena browser gym agent
lab are there if you're interested we uh
take PLL requests all of that is open
source for you to uh to study and learn