Abdullah here who is the who leads the
ministry of communications and uh
information technology for the Kingdom
of Saudi
Arabia and what makes Abdullah so unique
is that he's he's an engineer more than
he is a public service um or nation
state leader he started his career not
too far from here at Cisco in the Bay
Area San Jose 20 minutes from here
that's right yeah so you 10 for those
who are familiar with if you if you've
got your favorite restaurant I'm curious
which one it was there but we we can
cover that part in a couple minutes
we'll do it through the Q&A cool um but
it's it's really rare to have somebody
who is in government who starts off a
conversation with you as we were having
yesterday with debating whether the mlu
Benchmark is the right eval for Frontier
models or not oh yeah um
and I think that's a great you know sort
of metaphor for the fact that he's much
more an engineer at heart and technocrat
at heart than he is a typical Public
Service individual now at the same time
you're not that different because if you
go throughout history and look at when
today's leading countries had their
phases of modern infrastructure buildout
it was often led by folks who had a
career in actually building or
engineering or they came from the Civil
sector right the idea of a modern
bureaucrat is who whose whole job is
actually just to administrate has never
had any experience as an engineer is
quite new so in that sense you're
actually a sort of Back to the Future
classic technocrat you know whether it's
the early days of sing Singapore or even
in that for that matter America where
many of the nation's leaders started
out as leaders in the private sector and
then went into public service so why
don't we just start by talking about
your history and how you got to where
you are
and then we're going to go deep into the
data centers in the Kingdom well first
of all it's an absolute pleasure to be
at Stanford and among some of the
brightest leaders of the Next Generation
or leaders in their own sense
today but my journey had the three
chapters an opportunity to learn and to
be able to acquire knowledge and then a
little bit of earn earn when it comes to
expert expertise experience prove
yourself and then this is an opportunity
to return and this is why I'm coming
back 20 years later to the valley right
now to talk to you guys and hopefully
over the next 20 or 30 minutes I'm going
to be able to inspire at least a few of
you to create the next big thing because
you should be very appreciative of where
you are you're talking about 140 years
of really transforming Humanity I mean
the company that I worked for started
from Stanford it was a couple of folks
like yourself trying to solve a
communication issue fast forward it has
fueled the internet economy which is
today in trillions of dollars and this
this ecosystem alone have created what $
2.73 trillion worth of value and I'm
confident over the next couple of years
we're going to see some unicorns
decacorns or even trillion dollar
companies here going back to my journey
I I started in Cisco at you know in San
Jose in building 10 writing codes for
iOS at that time and iOS for us at back
then 20 years ago was it your iPhone
operating system but it was really the
operating system for how networking
works and it was really a parallel you
could drw from today's time Cisco at the
time was the most valuable company in
the world H close to half a trillion
dollars if you adjusted to inflation
today it's close to a trillion dollars
today in today's dollars right and we
really s similar waves I mean as an
engineer I have a big I'm a big fan of a
ratio called signal to noise ratio and
as long as the power of the signal to
you as an individual as a leader is very
clear and more powerful than all of the
noise that is surrounding you because
with what history have taught me that we
live always in times of change and the
rate of change and uncertainty is going
to follow us so I'm hoping that you can
get some signals signal number one that
I want you to really get it through is
that what we're observing today in the
AI world or in the intelligence age as
marketeers like to to call it we have
seen it firsthand in the internet Age
first a lot of hype and excitement about
hardware and I remember we were pushing
Cisco routers and switches to client
bases Without Really realizing what was
the applications or how it could diffuse
across Industries and only when we had a
few Innovation triggers where really we
shifted to the line of business where
networking was able to empower and
change the way we work live Play and
Learn tele medicine T education govtech
and reform bureaucracies from red tape
to Red Carpet this is really where the
magic happens right so the first signal
that I want you to appreciate is that
we're seeing this first time right now
there's a lot of hype about hardware and
I know that this is Hardware course so
we're going to talk extensively about
what we expect from you as the Next
Generation to do these unlocks to
transform the industry well it's a
systems class so you can feel free to go
up and down the stack if you want indeed
indeed but what we have seen is that for
every dollar made in Hardware there was
10 to 20 bucks being made in software
and services right and we're seeing this
right now with a little bit of a gen Ki
mirroring back then what used to be
called SAS for B2B how the diffusion
across Industries and verticals is
really making the difference so let's
talk a little bit technical so what are
some of the
unclogs challenges technical challenges
that I'm expecting a Stanford Graduate
to work on number one is Energy
Efficiency you can appreciate as the
energy leader in the world we power up
20% of the energy mix but we're still
looking for inefficiencies to be solved
first one the Cur current architecture
for compute whether CPU or or even GPU
conforms to the van noyman architecture
which is practically you have a
component that does execute and then you
need to fetch from memory the data and
the instruction set this is creating a
lot of inefficiency because every time
you have to call memory that's PCO jeels
and if you multiply by the billions of
axes that's Watts so every time you call
on memory that's a single watt every
time you call on Solid State Storage
that's 10 watts every time you call on
interconnect that's even multiple of
Watts so the first problem statement
that we have to solve for is how you
could guys engineer for us the Next
Generation compute architecture I'll
give you some food for thought again I'm
expecting from Stanford over the next
couple of years we see a couple of
startups in this space first of all the
Silicon architecture is
outdated the the the Gap when it comes
to the number of voltages that you could
push to make sure that you can
appreciate a one and a zero is roughly
um you know when you're talking about e
EVS you're talking
1.1 we need to make sure that we work on
compound silicon compound semiconductors
so we need to transition from for
example silicon to gallium nitrate
because it has a bigger band and you a
big quicker as an analogy think of the
number of transistors that you can you
know fabricate on a wafer think about
the switches could be either what rubber
valves that they have a leaky current
versus a metal valve that is able to do
fast switching so the first problem see
that we have to solve we need a new
compute architecture 40% of the cost of
gpus and npus and lpus today is in
memory high bandwidth memory is the
biggest unlock and no wonder that
Stanford came up with the memor memory
wall uh you know white paper which
articulated that if you look at the past
20 years Moors law T flops the number of
transistors have been doubling
significantly in 20 years 60,000 times
but when it comes to memory and when it
comes to the interconnect we're only
doubling every 2 years 1.7 1. 6 1.4 that
has created for us a big challenge if if
we're investing and trust me guys we're
putting a lot of billions of dollars
into startups and into funds if there is
a startup that tomorrow can tell me we
can work on compound semiconductors to
make sure that we can improve the
efficiency in compute we we're going to
invest and we can t team with a6z for
that matter as well right uh so that's
the first unlock that I want you guys to
work on
second we need a new architectural
approach to optimize for how we look at
even accessing memory there are three
right now major archetypes there's a
memory on the chip next to the chip and
on the side of the chip we're working
with all of them so one one company that
actually spun out out out of Google
called Gro with a with a que Jonathan
Ross have done a fantastic job language
processing units but there's a
limitation it's only good for Tex it
leverages SRAM which is quite fast
that's why we're working with the likes
of Qualcomm with neural processing units
how we can work with Dam which is memory
next to the chip and then with the
nvidias and the amds we're working
through the hbm architecture Calling On
Solid State Storage so first one
compound semiconductors that's a big
business opportunity that all of you
should be working on today to make sure
you create the next unic corn and DEA
corn memory architectures we're overdue
to Pivot from the van nment
architecture Third unlock
interconnect I've worked on infin band
back in the 90s we're still working on
Infinity band photonic AI architectures
are overdue every time we convert from
Optical to electrical you you guys know
this best we hit we hit losses there's
leaks and so forth we need to do these
unlocks so semiconductor
development memory architectures
interconnect architectures I'm telling
you from today these are the next
hundred billion Doll Market
opportunities that you guys can work on
let's talk right now about other types
of inefficiencies that we have in the
system so we've been trying to work with
liquid cooling immersion Cooling and all
of these types of coolings so you you
you asked me for the session about how
many gws we're building so for the time
being we're building anywhere between
1.5 to 2 gaws worth of compute capacity
my challenge is that we want as much
power to go to the gpus so far the tax
is 50% so every time we build a data
center if it's one one gaw 100 Meg will
go to translation for stepping up from
high voltage to low voltage that's out
of the way then to cooling then to
networking and storage and all of these
equipments if you can help us create the
next big compute architecture to make
sure that as we pump those gigawatts or
megawatts they go straight to gpus
because this is the highest Coast the
highest Coast what we have been able to
do is for a shell data center without
the compute is anywhere between 8 8
million bucks to 12 million bucks per
megawatt when you overlay compute it
jumps to 20 to 30 megawatt or sorry 20
to30 million depending on who you work
with if it's the grocs of the world the
sambanova of the world the nvidias and
the amds we need to make sure that we I
see a couple of smiles when I said San
NOA you guys familiar with that so samb
NOA let me let me give them some credit
helped us work with aramco one of the
energy leaders in the world today on
making sure that we realize it's one of
the real use cases of AI
within identic AI a billion dollars
worth of savings and the way they have
done it is helped us first develop a
generative AI that looks at the paracity
of an oil will how many runs we can do
that and DeMark tize that wisdom to be
able for the CEO of aramco and the
engineering team to appreciate the
savings that we can do and guys remember
that's the second signal or the third
signal I want to talk about which is
it's all about a adoption and diffusion
of these Technologies I I'm I'm I'm
sorry to say that mlu there's a lot of
startups right now from the Silicon
Valley they could help us gain the the
data sheet for five to six million bucks
they were good enough in the early days
to flick some muscles about how the
models can be able to win and game a
certain number but right now what does
it mean for GDP what does it mean for
productivity so hard challenges we need
to work on secondly how we transition
into diffusion and adoption if you're
not able in this classroom to articulate
to me in very simple terms how your next
technological breakthrough can create
for me jobs GDP productivity Topline
bottom line efficiency you're not
relevant to a decision maker so I I'm
I'm hard to say that so I'm going to so
I'm going to I'm going to go deep dive
on that for a second because when you're
talking about moving GDP oh yeah the the
time Cycles on which you're you need to
plan on are decades right oh yeah but
the time cycles of a compute
architecture can be anywhere from 18
months to 24 months before you know we
had Jensen here the the black Wells have
basically essentially made a two and a
half times performance gain on the h100s
just from 24 months ago so now you've
got to build two gaws of data centers
which literally nobody else has done yet
the use it takes 18 months to at least
rack stack and bring that data center up
and then the use 18 months to 36 months
depending on the site location right and
which and what you're permitting looks
like in which country you're in but in
the Kingdom it's generally a little bit
more accelerated than the rest of the
world because of how we got the grock
node in four months yeah but but that's
the exception we call that founder mode
over here but if you're planning GDP
movement on decades but your compute you
know you have got to you got to make
that decision for a data center on six
to eight years and the the Leading Edge
moves every 18 months how do you break
down the infrastructure planning cycle
how do you make sense of the short
medium and long-term decisions you got
to make without basically throwing up a
data center that's largely obsolete by
the time it even comes
online in every this is going back to
history in every technological wave you
had folks that shaped the market and
people who responded to a market and I
think in today's time you have to be
agile to do a little bit of both so you
can't really deploy all of your Capital
by saying I'm going to build it and
hyperscalers are all going to come okay
and then the use cases will follow I
think it's a little bit of both and
that's why in the Kingdom right now in
gen AI generative Ai agentic Ai and
physical AI we're really pushing the
needle and the envelope on three major
use cases as a matter of fact the world
economic Forum have called them as one
of the biggest real use cases right so
in generative AI we had startups work on
tackling CLE cell disease for those who
are not familiar your blood blood red
blood cell turns into a sickle and it
basically clogs into vessels
unfortunately it causes loss of Limbs
and lives for 20 million folks in Middle
East and Africa
predominantly this specific startup
called nanop pal from Saudi Arabia and I
I run the National Labs for Saudi Arabia
and he has happens to be a scientist
there he said I will take drug
formulation which typically takes for a
specific you know for a CLE cell disease
10 years to two to three years be able
to look at the different permutations
and characteristics and attributes of
how to design the right
nanorobot with crisper technology that's
Gene editing technology to be able to
take out that Gene called sickle cell
and be able to save lives and right now
this is one of the most promising use
cases of generative AI across the globe
and we take huge pride of it a few
Lessons Learned there you can cut
Corners with generative AI but when it
comes to governance you still need to
conform to the risk-based assessment per
industry so since this is health care we
could not cut corners on clinical trials
you still needed to go to stage one for
toxicity and side effects s you know
stage two which is aexy stage three full
approval so even though we Shrunk the
time that it requires to formulate this
drug from 10 years to 2 years we still
had to go through the clinical trial
governance in the context of healthcare
and that's I think it's a very good
problem statement for Stanford graduates
to work on is how we can create that
balance between that risk-based
assessment approach for governance
versus not stifling Innovation got it
okay and so if if you're it sounds to me
like one of the ways you think about
managing your infrastructure buildout is
you work backwards from use cases that
you're excited about like the one you
just mentioned instead of trying to plan
out there's two two more but I'll keep
for your next question but no that
basically you know if you're working
backwards from use cases and workloads
as opposed to trying to predict where
the you know compute architecture might
go to then as long as the workloads get
handled especially the use cases that
are important to the government then
you're essentially resilient to the risk
of going obsolete is that roughly the
right way to think about about how you
prioritize what infrastructure to invest
in indeed
so there's an in Inside
Out look and an outside in so from an
inside out we looked at our economy our
economy we're transitioning from a
factor-based economy predominantly
energy to Innovation so it was natural
for us and I'll talk about the other use
cases to deploy agentic AI for managing
corrosion within a pipeline operation
managing drilling runs and and
optimizing a billion dollars worth of
savings for ramco right it was also very
critical for us similar to the US us if
you look at the current spend of Health
Care expenditure as a percentage of GDP
the current system is not working it's
going to bankrupt a lot of economies if
we don't do anything so it was very
natural for us to pick up the signal
that we need to focus on Healthcare
right and that's the physical AI use
case which is the world's first fully
robotics heart transplant where um to do
an incision and to make sure that you
operate a heart transplant typically you
would need to admit a patient from 6 to
8 weeks within the ICU and in some cases
the CCU and you need to cut about 20 to
30 cm where with fully robotics
leveraging AI you're only cutting 2 to 3
cm and be able with hand robotics be
able to do the Hat the the heart
transplant in less than four hours and
the patient can be out in less than 48
hours which is remarkable and think
about what we can do to close on the
gaps when it comes to heart surgeons
remote surgery deliver some of the
promises of the early days of my
networking days so what um I'm I'm going
to pull on that thread a little bit many
of the use cases you you've just talked
about are fairly Mission critical use
cases oh yeah one of the the speaker we
had here last week is uh Guam LEL who's
the chief scientist and co-founder of
mstr oh yeah you know which is a company
you're familiar with the kingdoms
invested in Mistral yeah we're big on
mistr go mistr
well why is open source been so you part
of I I my understanding is part of why
mrr has been exciting to the kingdom is
because it they built solutions for
Mission critical Industries like the one
you just talked about why has open
source been the the solution or why is
open source finding so much of a fit in
the kinds of use cases you talked about
my original signal history is a great
predictor of the future you don't need a
crystal ball to predict the future just
go back in history and you'll be able to
appreciate that we're competing
protocols IP at the time for networking
and other protocols right and then IP
prevailed and there were some
proprietary systems that still existed
but through standardization and think
you Nest from the US and all of your DOD
certifications IP prevailed right
similarly I think when it comes to
models we're going to see both closed
and open open source models and at one
point within the industry there will be
a standardization to approach and really
from an end user perspective and we
spoke about this last night we're we're
model agnostic so whatever model helps
me save lives improve efficiency create
GDP and productivity we will use uh I
remember back in the day at Cisco we
used to say no technology religion I
should say right now there should be a
no model religion so some f folks are
too attached to a specific model and
right now models can borrow brilliantly
from each other so if we look at what
deep seek did they really borrowed from
mistral's mixture of experts uh you know
implementation within their Mixr and was
able to implement it so I think the
world is going to converge to a world of
many models closed open small large Y
and hence my coaching and guidance to
the the brightest folks that we have
here in the room is don't be too
attached to a specific approach because
the market is so agile the change that
we have seen in the past two years
actually dwarfs the change that I have
seen my past 20 years I don't know if
you can relate to
that um it it feels you know there's
this there's this meme I love which is a
it's a it's a comic from Tintin where
the captain hadock is saying gosh what a
week huh and tinon says Captain it's
only Monday oh yeah you know that's what
every day feels like an infrastructure
in AI right now oh yeah oh yeah the
changes that are happening but again
it's the expectation of this room to
really create the next breakthrough well
speaking of this room we've got tons of
questions piling up so we're going to
switch to student questions um I'm all
yours shall we take the first one any
questions yeah so our first question
comes from Brian woo Brian woo raise
your hand there you are up for take time
to talk to us today more interested on
your involement with the s space agency
more about for Space Program how you you
know collaborate with like other
companies space programs f for the
recording if you could just repeat the
question so the question was regarding
space which is my next favorite topic uh
if you asked me pre gen it used to be
space space space then technology now
it's ai ai ai then space and I would
deem that the space industry if they
want to achieve the promise of a two
trillion dollar industry they must
evolve into the convolution of AI and
space so if you for those who are not
familiar with the space economy it's
split into two ends similar to the stack
that we work on in an AI you have your
Upstream which is predominantly space
exploration lunar Mission now we're
talking about going into Mars and then
you have the downstream which is the
commercial applications space
communication Leo Mio Geo Earth
observation how we could make sure that
we monitor the climate and make sure
that we have a safe planet and then you
have navigation which by the way affects
11% of the EU economy our own stud is
about 6 to 7% of our own GDP and this is
right now where our laser focus on so
Brian for your question the kingdom is
laser focused right now on building
space communication Technologies we're
working with everybody Leo Mio and we
believe it's the in intersection of
these technologies that really going to
provide to you the most robust
breakthrough in next gen generation
communication we don't believe that you
should rely purely just on Leo and Gio
is too outdated to be a standalone
offering secondly Earth observation so
one of the use cases where Ai and space
have intersected in the Kingdom one of
the biggest challenges that we had is
random farming so we had farmers do
random farming all over the place it
affects 75% of our desertification
uh effect which is basically making sure
that we don't have enough vegetation and
and green land within the kingdom and
hence we leverage geospatial data
putting it in in an AI model with with
you know convolutional networks and so
forth to be able to appreciate where can
we nudge and pivot this random farming
to be able to cut down on
desertification effect on on polluting
the environment and on wasting
underground water so in one year with
random farming we used to consume what
we needed in one year we used to have 3x
of that usage just because of the random
farming so we were able to save
significantly bring that that leakage to
thir to you know down by
66% uh leveraging data Ai and space so
for us it's it's very key we're we're
aligning and working with everybody
we're working with SpaceX we're working
with your um space 1.0 2.0 player
the the Locking Martins of the world
your defense system integrators and we
we look forward to collaborate with you
Brian on that all right should we take
the next one next question is from ai ai
ai want raise your hand there he is go
ahead all
right the question is how did you get
the opportunity to go into public
service and the government and how do
you think about making the transition I
have to think the Silicon Valley his
Royal Highness the Crown Prince made his
first Silicon Valley tour back in
2016 and I was still working for Cisco
and it was me and John Chambers de
demoing to his Royal Highness how dig
digital Technologies can transform
Nations and we will share with him our
digital India experience our digital
Australia Germany and all of these
digitalization Journeys around the world
and his Ro H stopped us and he said guys
I want to talk about digital Saudi and
then three months later I was called
into the office and his Royal Highness
asked me to make a leap of faith and it
has been the biggest blessing to me
because it gave me an opportunity to
really deliver on my leadership impact
plan this is a plan that it took me a
while I I I came to this realization in
2011 where it took me a while to
appreciate what was my sense of
belonging and purpose in life and it's a
saying in our culture and you guys need
to do your own Discovery and it's okay
if you don't have the answers right now
but you're going to come to it at one
point in your career and you're going to
appreciate that you need to work for
something bigger than life have a sense
of meaning to everything that you do the
reason why you wake up and that saying
that says this life's journey will stop
unless you do three things acquire and
disseminate knowledge build the Next
Generation and give back and then when I
met his Royal Highness it hit me it says
this this is my opportunity to share my
knowledge help build a nation and with
with his leadership and guidance we went
to
$135 billion digital economy growing by
60% in 7 years we've doubled our Tech
force from 150,000 to 381,000 mind you
in the valley today you sit around 3 320
so we were able to do and be me be be
part and I'm very blessed a lot of my
colleagues are here uh at nura tibo
abdalah SWA all of them I'm very
fortunate that I'm blessed with a team
that is much smarter than me to help me
achieve this Vision to his Royal
Highness but it has been the biggest
blessing my guidance to you as much as
possible because life is about
opportunities so never turn a good
opportunity H but I would recommend you
stting entrepreneurship working for a
big AI big tech company a good lab and
then then you would realize at one point
you want to give back to the to your
Society to your nation you want to help
build the Next Generation leaders when
that comes you will have predominantly
two choices either an NGO and I know
that all of you are are part of your job
and part of you're giving back your your
and and that gives me a huge sense of
Pride to partner with you you know my
dear
friend either into an NGO or a
government so that would be my guidance
so to me um it was the phase of as I
said learn earn return it was my return
phase an opportunity to give back to a
kingdom that gave back to a region as a
byproduct of the growth that we achieved
in the kingdom it Tak me a huge Pride to
see the growth in Africa and the Middle
East that happened with entrepreneurship
out of the 15 unicorns that took place
in that part of the world seven were
fueled by the kingdom across the region
and then helped the world and right now
have an opportunity to team up with some
of the brightest minds of the Next
Generation to be able to change Humanity
with
technology next question all right let's
that yeah next question these are good
questions were the were these
planted no but clearly next time should
have them some of them sub in for me
these are these are um you know I think
I think your answers are inspiring
better questions so we try to get
through as many of them as we can what's
the next one let's extend let's I'm
loving this we'll extend yeah next
question is from Anton Alonso Antonio
where's Antonio
at do you think the return on the
invested Capital will be or do you about
overinvestment the question is do you
worry about overinvestment in
AI I think the market will correct and
we just have seen a few small Winters
not even a winter few Springs if I could
call them um similar to the old days a
lot of Nations have doubled down on
fiberized the nation building networking
kit and so forth but down the line as
the use cases of the plural foration of
these Technologies and the unit of
Economics have come down they will pay
off so these infrastructure plays by
Design they're mostly developmental they
help economies Thrive I mean there's a
wonderful study by the international
telecommunication Union the itu that
suggests for every 10 percentage points
of growth that you achieved back in the
day in Broadband you see one to 2%
growth in GDP in in two to to four years
similarly I believe this is the
infrastructure that will fuel the
intelligent age what we cannot afford is
sensible Nations and the kingdom is
aligning with the US beautifully on this
because we have shared values that this
has to be a safe responsible technology
to benefit Humanity what we cannot
afford is a repeat of the failure of the
digital age let's remember the digital
age promised us that it's going to be
the biggest social equalizer and
economic multiplier but let's look at
the world today for every dollar made in
the global South and I come from the
global South $3.5 to4 doll are made in
the north and we cannot say that this is
going to be an exclusive cup of the few
because even my dear friend SAA did the
podcast a few years ago and he said he
can't grow if the world keeps growing at
2 to 3% GDP growth so it's even critical
for innovators and entrepreneurs that
the whole world is healthy and
prosperous and peaceful and successful
so to
me infrastructure Investments whether in
training and inference I see them as a
no regret for Nations that have the
following comparative advantages if you
have the energy advantage and we do we
we we bring online 20 gaw worth a
renewable we're tendering right now we
have one of the lowest price point for
solar and wind at the generation level
as cense per kilowatt hour if you have a
captive market and the threshold
surprisingly for SAS for back in the day
in the internet age for internet
businesses and for AI is 30 million so
if you have a 30 million population
what's the population of California I
don't know um the the Baya we're at
about uh no I know the San Francisco
Metropolitan region is 800,000 but
California I it's one of the most
somebody want to look us up7 million 37
million so if you have so if you have if
you have if you have 30 million-ish
folks you have the capital you have the
energy investing into infrastructure is
a no regret what we're seeing here today
is 70% training 30% inference as the
diffusion of this technology and the use
cases come live it's going to flip so
the question is when not if so I'm going
to take a bit of a detour here for you
to talk about what it so so the fact
that history Rhymes so in you joined
Cisco in 2003 yeah right after the crash
right and and it wasn't thank you thank
you for reminding
me some some scars are worth drawing you
know battle lessons from and I think
there's one really important one you
just mentioned which is we've seen this
story before oh yeah there was a it was
very common to open up a headline in 20
two or a newspaper and see the headline
that there was an overbuild out of
server infrastructure a lot of fingers
were pointed at Cisco but the reality
was the cost of infrastructure in that
case in that time it was bandwidth
falling is what it was required to allow
a bunch of new use cases like Google
like search and do you see that
happening again or do you think
something different is going to happen
if there is actually a glut of inference
this time around if it wasn't for the
internet buildout and the economy we
would not have the intelligent age that
we have today we would not have the
quantum age but my reservation is those
general purpose Technologies if we say
we can't afford for anybody to be left
behind we need as governments leaders
Business Leaders entrepreneurs academics
to really collaborate to deliver on this
promise if we're saying that AI is and
and it's as critical as a general
purpose technology as the steam engine
as electricity right we can't make this
an exclusive Club of the few things as
they Trend today by
2030 the pessimist 700 million folks
will come online within the intelligent
Age The Optimist a a a billion to two
but that leaves what 7 billion people
behind right that's not acceptable so
that that says by the time you hit the
market and you develop your you know out
of 10 each one of you eight will be left
behind and two will flourish that
doesn't sound to me like a general
purpose technology that is supposed to
deliver productivity and prosperity for
all and that's why we had a productivity
challenge by the way for the past
decades I mean the world econ economy is
not growing as fast as we want it to be
I I have a follow-up question for you
which is um which which I think would be
helpful for folks to understand which is
the concept of virtualization and
digital embassies yeah right so if the
kingdom is building out infrastructure
that allows like you're saying Equitable
access to the L low cost inference oh
yeah and you've got startups developers
from around the world who want to access
that but need the policies that the
compute workloads need to adhere to to
be local you know one the solution last
time around in the Cisco era and the
internet era was to virtualize the
workloads away from where the hardware
was running oh yeah do you see something
like that happening oh yeah the same ter
will I mean remember back in the day we
were talking about microservices and
containers right and so for example X
today with Twitter if you look at your
notification engine it could be sitting
in Amsterdam if you look at your
analytic system it could be sitting here
somewhere in the US and you would
optimize to where these microservices
can give you the best advantage and some
of them if they're latency sensitive you
want them to be as close as possible to
your client base right same thing is
going to happen and that's why in terms
of you mentioned data embassies in terms
of Regulation we're working right now
with governments like the US on giving
them sovereignty over their instance to
make sure that us-based entrepreneurs
big AI companies can use take advantage
of our energy captive market and capital
to join hands together to deliver both
training and info services for the world
so does that mean a workload that a
startup is running from the US in a data
center in the kingdom is actually ading
to almost like a US Embassy in that data
center oh yeah so it's ading to to
policies and we've seen that with Cloud
if you remember the Safe Harbor Clauses
so we invoked those so we said similar
to how goods and services are in transit
in the physical world sometimes if you
have a truck you don't have jurisdiction
as a government to inspect that truck
because it's really passing by Saudi to
another Nation similarly we had the Safe
Harbor clause for the cloud in which
certain workloads and instances right uh
so for example for a Netflix some
content might be allowed in the Kingdom
some content might be allowed in Europe
right if it if it's serving Europe from
the kingdom it's not of our business our
next speaker is um Matthew Prince the CE
of cloud Flair ah there you go so you
can this is a great segue into some of
the you know what they've done with with
on the edge tell them to put more CDN in
Saudi I'll let them know you can stick
around and tell them um all right next
question yeah next question is from
tamish tamish raise your hand thank you
so much for being here and for your
Insight no than question was in regards
to Smart cities naom is often described
as a tested for aien living um what are
some of the most ambitious sort of
cognitive incense of being able to sense
analyze and adapt um to the needs of
residents in real time uh features you
expect the residents of naon to expect
in the next few years and sort of as a
part two to that question how does that
scale to the rest of the question is
about
neom for for neom his Royal Highness
wanted to create for us a true north and
a rising star to really rally the nation
if you look at any Innovation problem
statement you have an incumbent that is
sustaining innovation a low-end
disruptor and a new market disruptor
neon for us was that New Market
disruption to really push the society to
push the boundaries so far it has
wielded for us big results I mean in
terms of green hydrogen we have 4 gaw
worth of green hydrogen for those who
are not familiar with green hydrogen
it's your opportunity to use
electrolyzers from the Red Sea split
hydrogen from oxygen and be able to use
hydrogen as fuel and that helps us as
the kingdom move from thermal energy to
Green photons electrons and hydrogen
completing the whole cycle so it became
for us a test bed for the biggest
innovators around the world of how can
we Crack the Code of the unit of
Economics of green hydrogen and right
now that green hydrogen plant is
actually fueling one of the uh soon
announced with data volt Investments a
1.5 gaw shell data center not a core a
shell to be able to host hypers skills
so surprisingly right now neon from for
us it's becoming the true north of how
we could lead with training and
inference look at Urban Design Urban
Design the Urban Design that we live in
is really built and designed for cars
and not people look at the cities around
us even here in the US within neom right
now we're saying no we need to really
reverse it to build it for own people so
one of the biggest things that we're
trying to crack code and this is really
an innovation problem statement is how
can we build a city in which within 5
minutes you could work live Play and
Learn and that would be fantastic and
that's why it's a a 20 30 year years old
problem statement because so far it's
since the beginning of the industrial
revolutions about roughly 300 years ago
cities has been built for cars not for
people and that's why we're very excited
and we look forward where we want we
want to collaborate more with Stanford
within neom and uh we have a lot of
exciting other news coming up awesome
all right next question yeah next
question is from the caran raise your
hand where you at
there I guess my question was
about questions about widening access
access to Tech so we made we made
recently the partnership with Gro
available to everybody around the world
it's the most cost affordable tokens
that you could access globally on
inference on a Gro instance and day one
we made all of the models available the
llamas of the world even deep seek
similar to your hyper scalers right it
was it was uh enlightening to see that
deep seek right now is alive on all of
the major hyperscalers as well although
it did not come from the US us I think
sabba which Arthur was telling us
launched the Arabic language model that
they released which mrr trained on
Monday was live on Gro 4 days later oh
yeah oh yeah so mral is is up and
running right kohir Lama we're working
with everybody and it's right now the
the most affordable and as a matter of
fact even when we did not even make the
grand announcement at leap which by the
way you're all invited to join us it's
one of the largest tech events we have
more than 200,000 folks join us and
roughly 13 to 14 billion worth of
announcements and 2,000 startups it's
very exciting for so this is an open
invitation to everybody to join us next
leap in next Fe February of uh
2026 but again Gro is is available so
we're walking the talk on making
inference cheap and affordable and we
have right now many nations many
startups that could not afford uh the
price points of Legacy
architectures um now within the kingdom
leveraging again our
energy captive market and capital to
deliver these Technologies at
scale
great next one yeah next question is
from sh sh where are you at thank you um
I guess I wanted to zoom back into the
um Computing Paradigm topic we talking
about I feel like there's a lot of
companies a lot of research groups work
on different um topics such as phonic
trips Hond brain inspired sem super
conductors for transistors whatever I
guess um are there any areas and super
new paradigms that the kingdom is
investing in and what would they be
which ones are you particularly excited
for the question is which new compute
paradigms are you most excited about one
one Paradigm that I'm personally
invested in uh within within my
professional capacity but I have a
strong interest in is in memory
Computing if you look at the Von yman
problem statement separating execution
from data and instruction set in memory
Computing can bring it all together in
memory and you could save billions and
create a lot of efficiency so if your
h00 consumes depending on the
configuration and the floating point of
the Precision Point anywhere from 600
you know watts to even greater than that
in if you do the same type of compute
the same amount of T flops it will be at
least 50% less energy and that that's
why in memory Computing we're seeing
right now Publications academic work and
I think you guys have a unique
opportunity to create the next big thing
in inmemory Computing there's right now
inmemory Computing and near memory
Computing so these are very exciting
architectures because they really shift
it's a paradigm shift we're stuck in a
the Von nman was 1945 I I I if if my
memory serves me that's a while back um
we're still working on cisk
architectures risk architectures x86 we
all have seen without naming names what
certain companies because they were too
religiously attached to a specific
architecture it can create bloess and
inefficiency and it does not help
anybody including themselves and their
shareholders so in memory Computing near
memory Computing again we're watching
that space AI photonics a compound
semiconductors those are areas right now
we are seeing them emerging from Labs
but if I if I would correlate we're
seeing the trend between Publications
prototypes earning calls by certain
startups so there's something going on
but if something can correct the code
it's somebody like you from Stanford we
have time for one last question let's do
two let's do two I love this Crow I love
this Crow there's
next question is from song song raise
your hand where are you
at no thank you
very discussion no thank you
we
students can I get all of your CVS no
I'm just
kidding our question is like you talk
about Rob
memory we already covered our question
is like uh what do you think what kind
of area you exciting about robotics
the AI what area of Robotics are you
most excited about so we we spoke about
Healthcare and I think the promise of
remote
surgery with AI can see light so that's
something that we're very excited about
something else that I think the whole
world is talking about and and the value
PS are there Robo taxis so right now
we're working with a lot of Stanford
based startups the who's who to make
sure that Robo taxis can be delivered
because if you think about it these
repetitive tasks we're better off
offloading those work you know
workforces and those workers on more H
you know high value uh generating um you
know segments of the economy so Robo
taxi uh is is real and it's it's it's
here to come um robotics in healthcare
is Big this this we're seeing it
firsthand with the heart transplant
story that I've shared with you and um
to me it's it's it's very exciting we're
also working with a company called
intuitive machine going back to your
space example on building Rovers for
water extraction from the moon but what
we're really solving for is how we could
solve these harsh environments in lunar
you know in the moon but really solve
them for one of the most water scarce
companies across the world so these are
also very exciting uh opportunities for
us all right we're going to take one
final question because then to be let
Abdullah go next question is from J J
thank you so much for being here taking
no thank you I really enjoyed your is
that liquid AI shirt yeah from for
ah good company yeah um I really enjoyed
your take on like compound
semiconductors and new memory
architectur have SE the next big thing
and I was wondering what do you think is
the biggest misconception about the
future of H Ai and you think there's too
much of an empis of software over
Hardware is the question is what do you
think about a ai agentic
ai we we have a project and by the way
this is an open invitation it's a public
request for information we've done it so
I can talk about it freely we're working
on an agentic AI project how we could
enhance and augment productivity for
civil servants within the government of
Saudi Arabia and as a matter of fact we
believe we could create billions of
productivity as a as a result of that so
I had the pleasure of really scanning
the
market what's happening is that you have
two types of players you have your AI
native players and you have your AI
enhanced AI enhanced is those companies
that used to be in B2B SAS so without
naming names because I don't want to
promote for a lot of companies here so
they would be they have vertical
expertise in a specific domain let's be
generic um you know Health Care Human
Resources finance and right now they
think because of their proprietary data
supply chain integration within their
Fortune 500 companies they could just
throw it at any model and come up with
an agentic Ki some success stories at
the task level but at the workflow level
and at the multi-agent level we haven't
seen a lot of results there then you
have your native AI players which are
really presenting some really unique use
cases without again promoting a lot of
Brands so the AI native players we're
seeing them take a completely totally
different approach because a lot of
people think the challenge is in the
model it's not in the model it's in the
data and the business model so so and
those companies they know how to create
data cleanse data better than anybody
else so your legacy B2B SAS players
they're making some runs some some
successful task level
augmentation but I'm really excited
about the AI native players that are
really tackling the human in the loop
problem statement the data layer problem
statement so I'm very excited about it
all right well that's a
great uh not to end on thank you so much
for coming no thank you for the
invitation and hopefully folks will show
up to LEAP next year in the middle of
finals thank you thank you thank you