Welcome to the last lecture of the
quarter for CS231N.
And it was great to see you guys uh at
the beginning and now at the end. And
this lecture is a little bit of a
departure. We're not going to teach any
new materials in terms of algorithms.
It's more a talk that I'd like to give
to students to put a perspective both on
um um on a a more longer term research
evolution but as well as a another
dimension that is important to today's
AI which we would call it the human
perspective. So um for the completeness
of the material there's a little bit of
a overlap uh that you might see from
other parts of this course but uh
hopefully you it it makes sense in a in
a fuller in a fuller way. So the title
of this slide or this lecture is what we
see and what we value AI with a human
perspective. And I know that some of you
have already heard about this is really
the beginning the origin of vision both
in terms of evolution as well as in
terms of our technology. And we did talk
about um the first light that came to
the animal world back in back 540
million years ago. And uh that was when
uh animals or trilobytes to be specific
developed uh a photo a photosensitive
cells to glean what the outer world is
about. And according to zoologologists
like Andrew Parker, um what happened is
that because of this um uh first the
onsite of vision, uh it set off an
evolutionary arms race where animals
either evolved or died. And that arms
race gave rise to the speciation or
explosive speciation of animals which
now zoologologists call the Cambrian
explo explosion or the big ban of
evolution. And of course um you wouldn't
be surprised that vision is still to
this day a primary sensory intelligent
system in many many animals. Not all
animals use vision. uh admittedly but
many do and that's uh also one of the
primary sensory systems for uh humans
and uh we use vision to um to you know
do everything from survival to work to
entertainment to socialization to
learning development and many other
things. So that's the the the
recapture or summary of evolution. And
we also uh briefly talked about um
computer vision being a summer vision
project back in the 1960s as an attempt
to use a couple of undergrads to
construct the significant portion of the
visual system. And that was very in line
with the history of AI where we tend to
um have clarity of the northstar but
underestimate how long it would take. We
are still probably experiencing that
today. But a lot has happened, right?
Like um you don't need me to tell you
that from empowering self-driving car to
understanding images to the generative
AI uh revolution, we're seeing vision is
uh playing a huge role and and also in
many parts leading the wave.
So
maybe it's time to just take a different
look at this both historically and going
towards the future is where have we come
from and where are we going and this is
an important uh topic to to uh discuss
because a lot of what has happened will
inform what will happen. Uh so I'm
organizing this talk in three chunks is
um first of all building AI to see what
humans see and that's where we came from
that we were so inspired by human
capability that we want to m make
machines that do the same and then we'll
talk about building AI to see what
humans don't see and then we'll finish
with building AI to see what humans
would like to see. Uh let's just start
with the first one. Building a to see
what humans see. Again, just a little
bit of a review. Humans are so good at
seeing. We know this. This is a very
half a century old um uh experiment
showing us that even
watching a video you've never watched
played at 10 hertz, which means every
frame is only about a on the screen for
100 milliseconds. You've never seen
that. It's still no problem for human
eyes to detect a target. In this case, a
person in a in a in this complex scene
where you have no idea a prior knowledge
about what this person is. It really
underscores the sup s uh superb ability
of human visual understanding especially
object focused understanding. We also
have briefly mentioned that around the
turn of the century uh neurosych uh
neurohysiologists are measuring the
speed of light uh speed of vision in
terms of uh humans seeing complex
objects in um in in in the form of brain
signals, brain electrical signals
measured from EG caps. And we see that
differentiating or categorizing animals
versus animals is a very complex task.
Yet humans are capable of doing that at
150 millisecond after the onset of the
stimuli. And this is remarkable speed
given the the wetwware we have between
our under our skulls. Also
neuroysiologists
have taught us that uh objects is a very
important functionality in our visual
intelligence in humans. So important
that there are neuro cororlates in our
brain areas that are dedicated to object
understanding such as face areas or
place areas or body parts areas. This
shows that evolution has really spent
time to hone in our visual intelligence
skills when it comes to object
recognition. So all this built up the
history for the field of computer vision
that a few decades ago object
recognition became a fundamental
building block for visual intelligence
and we want to empower machines with
that. And in order to do that, we define
the problem or at least the original
problem as given an image, how do we
empower enable a computer to call out
the objects or what what the uh what the
object is in the image. That's such an
effortless task for humans. But if you
think about it now that you've learned
enough computer vision to know that
mathematically there's infinite
possibilities to um to actually uh
recognize any object because of
different lighting, texture, background,
occlusion, uh viewing angle, scaling and
and you know whatever you name it. So
this is actually fundamentally a a
difficult tasks difficult task.
Um the history pre-deep learning is also
very interesting. There were some pretty
heroic attempts at solving the problem
of generic generalizable object
recognition and the first wave of
attempt was actually very inspired by
psychology itself. We self-introspect
sometimes uh sometimes even to the
detriment of over self-introspection.
We think that humans compose parts,
right? Like we look at objects, we can
see geometric parts and then we can
compose them into different objects. And
that idea of using pre-desated
parts or shapes and to you know compose
them in specific ways was the first wave
of object recognition. So these are
different um work or models coming from
the 70s, 80s or even going all the way
to 90s of using different parts and
configurations to recognize objects. Of
course, it didn't really work. It's
mathematically beautiful and simple, but
it didn't work. So a second wave of
object recognition pre-deep learning was
actually a really important um uh era in
in the field of AI is really the
beginning of machine learning
statistical m machine learning. It was
the marriage between computer
programming and statistical modeling.
And with that marriage, we start to re
realize the world is so complex. These
problems, this intelligence problems,
whether it's visual intelligence or
language intelligence or other kind of
intelligence, uh in order to generalize,
we need to learn um learn the
parameters. It's very hard to use
hand-tuned models to to um to uh um you
know get good good uh learning. We now
know we need data even though we didn't
at that time know how much data but we
also know that we need to uh design or
architect statistical models so that
they have the capability of learning
through different uh through different
learning rules. And because of that we
saw a blossoming of models in that era
where we're learning you know random
fields or base nets or support vector
machines and all that. Um and in fact a
lot of progress was made um by the time
we are in the first decade of 21st
century in object recognition that we
even have international benchmarks of a
small number of object classes to
encourage everybody to um to to to
compare their algorithms. So we're
inching together. The last unlock for
object recognition as we have learned
again goes back to cognitive science. So
this particular psychologist Irv Beerman
had long conjectured that humans can
recognize a huge number of objects and
this is intuitive for our common
knowledge. But he actually put a number
on it. I I personally call it the
Beerman number which is that by you know
age six or seven children he conjectured
were able to recognize about 30,000 to
100,000 different visual categories and
he used this where did he come up with
this number is a combination of looking
at dictionary the number of nouns as
well as visual studies of how kids uh
recognize different uh uh objects
But it's a number that's pretty daunting
and pretty sobering for the field of
computer vision because up till now this
is middle of the first decade of 21st
century we were working with tiny number
of object categories and a tiny number
of uh images to work with compared to
what humans experience. And this was as
you know the onset of the uh the the
motivation for image net project which
um took this beerman number really
seriously and um constructed uh we
constructed this data set that is on par
with what the psychologist beamman
conjectured which is around 22,000
object classes over 15 million images
and of course that's the beginning that
you start to come into this uh class is
that because of the large data provided
by imageet we start to see that powerful
algorithms like neuronet network at the
beginning it was convolutional neuronet
network of course now we use
transformers and all that uh start to
really show their power through big data
and uh and I'm this is a generic uh
slide for those of those people who
didn't learn about this, I'm going to
skip this because you all know this. So
the the the the quick history is as soon
as we have imageet, as soon as we use
convolutional neuronet network a few
years after the uh beginning of imageet,
we saw this door blasted open in terms
of uh uh solving the problem of object
recognition. Now we have algorithms that
we can take to look at any picture in
the world and be able to recognize
objects in the big or small and and in
any kind of you know orientation. It's
not is it 100% soft? No. There's always
longtail problems we can solve. But as
far as industrial application goes, this
has come a long way and really has been
um a a a matured problem. And of course
all of you know and all this came at the
convergence point which is the year 2012
where the image that challenge provided
the data for the convolutional neuronet
network and they used two GPUs at that
time and the three ingredients come
together and brought uh brought the
moment of uh deep learning um uh the
birth of deep learning and uh in this
class we also talked a little bit about
different various architectures that
image net challenge engendered u
throughout the past uh decade or so in
terms of you know convolutional neuronet
network or restnet and and so on. So
that's um that's um you know that's the
beginning really about deep learning
revolution. And of course, in terms of
the quest for visual intelligence, we're
not going to stop at just being able to
label objects in a scene. For example,
in this two scenes, right? If you just
label objects, you'll think it's just a
llama and a person. But if I show you
the second scene with the llama and a
person, the story is completely
different. Even though you have the same
object, you have very different
relationship. So, cognitive scientist
once again was a head of computer
scientist uh and and inspired us to
think about um visual intelligence
beyond just naming objects or
categorizing objects. In this particular
paper, Jeremy Wolf, who is a pretty
prominent uh psychologist um wrote this
beautiful paper that called out that
relationships between objects must be
coded as part of our understanding of
complex natural things. And inspired by
that work, the field of computer vision
start to look at how do we uh understand
relationships. And this is uh early
work. You guys got a lecture from Renjay
and uh uh last week or or yeah last week
this is was his PhD thesis looking at
learning object relationships using
scene graph as a representation. In this
case, scene graph is defined by these
entity nodes that are objects and their
relationships are uh defined by the
connectivity between the nodes or
sometimes they have attribute
relationships that defines the the
particular objects. And even a scene as
simple as this with mostly just two
people, you know, um, one feeding a cake
to the other, you can form a very dense
scene gra scene graph because of the
richness of the visual scene. And this
was Ren's thesis after the the the image
that object recognition um era where we
try to we build a data set uh uh called
visual genome where we try to uh put
together object relationships object uh
and also story descriptions. And uh one
of the work that Ranj did I thought that
was really fun was zero shot learning of
unusual uh object relationships. For
example, it's not unusual to see person
riding a horse. It's not unusual to see
person wearing a hat, but it's unusual
in general to see horse wearing hat. And
in the era of big data training, it's
hard to get this kind of data repeatedly
because you just don't have too many of
that. But using this compositional scene
graph representation, we're able to
learn the more common relationships and
then derive uncommon relationships um in
that representation. And again this is
another um example of zero shot learning
where you know person sitting on chair
and and fire hydrant on the lawn or on
the field are all common relationships
but person sitting on fire hydrant is
the one that would not you know it's
hard to get data and we're able to do
that uh uh to make that happen and this
is just a figure from the paper that
shows that wrenches work at that time
achieved state-of-the-art recognition
rate compared to many other um uh
methods.
But relationship is not enough, right?
The ability to actually tell a story
that is a lot more richer or also using
natural language is actually um the next
big goal. So around the year 2014
201 around 2014 we start working on that
problem. And think about it. That's just
two years after the image that uh Alex
that moment. But the field was starting
to evolve so fast. We're so inspired by
um by what we can do using uh a
combination of u convolutional neuronet
network as well as a a uh um a language
model called LSTM. And this is the
thesis by Andre Kapathy that uh we were
one of the first uh teams that um showed
how to do image captioning or
storytelling as well as dense captioning
which is also part of the work that
Justin Johnson did and and I know he's
he's one of the co-hurs of this course
and that was around the time between
2015 to 2018 a lot of work has happened
um to to solve the problem. Of course,
today using a multimodal LLMs, we have
taken the solution of this problem even
to another uh another notch. But this is
the beginning of that line of work and
uh uh frankly I myself as a computer
vision scientist who entered the field
at the beginning of the century was very
surprised by how fast uh our field was
able to solve this problem. as soon as
we've got data as well as neuronet
network algorithms.
But a much harder problem is actually in
dynamic scenes. In dynamic scenes, we uh
we tend to have much more complex
relationships, much more complex uh
movements and the camera also the camera
uh movement or or the the the um the
entity the actors within the scene can
do a lot of different things. So in this
work that a collaboration with Isan and
um a bunch of students in our lab uh we
call it multiobject multi- actor
activity understanding. This is a much
newer work. We only published this a
couple of years ago. uh to capture the
relationship between these actors and
their activities in dynamic scene is
still I would say an unsolved problem
and this will have profound implication
you know that you're in Silicon Valley
so you you're hearing so much um um um
excitement of robots for example if we
ever dream to have everyday robots that
work amongst us robots costly to solve
solve this problem. Understand how
complex the scene is, what people are
doing, who is doing what, what is next
and this is an unsolved problem. Um so
also you know in addition to what I have
shown you you you have learned a little
bit in this class and and and related
computer vision problem uh but not we
didn't have time to elaborate for
example 3D computer vision or human pose
understanding and of course generative
uh AI and generative models. So this is
just to show you that the field of
computer vision uh since the rebirth of
modern AI has been just moving
extraordinarily fast.
But the take-home message in this
section for me is that um two things.
One is that data compute and neuronet
network algorithm truly have converged
about 10 years ago or 13 years ago and
that was the moment that modern AI or
deep learning revolution has happened.
But the history of that and so much of
the problem that we have been working on
is truly inspired by cognitive science
and psychology and neuroscience. And
that to me is a um is going to continue
to to uh happen is that we will continue
to be inspired by what the brain can do
or how the brain does things and also
we'll continue to use AI to help our
brain brain research. So there is a very
intimate relationship between today's AI
and cognitive science, neuroscience,
brain science and all that. So that's uh
that's the first section and of course a
lot of people students and and
collaborators have contributed to what I
have just presented.
Now let's talk about going beyond just
building AI to see what humans don't
see. This is where pushing AI beyond the
capability of humans or you can call it
superhumans. For example, most people
don't recognize a ton of dinosaurs. You
can probably name a few. Some kids
really can name a lot. Well, let alone
thousands and tens of thousands of bird
species
or tens of thousands of car categories.
So, this is the the the line of work
that I call fine grained object
categorization. humans are just not that
good at it. And um this is still a
problem that I don't think we're fully
solved yet to be honest. Um uh in this
generative AI era especially we're
talking a lot about multimodal LLMs.
this problem has somewhat be um
neglected or or it just is not a
mainstream problem but it really will
you know still will come and and play a
important role. So in this early work of
fine grain bird species recognition, we
put together you know a data set
actually we used a data set of 4,000
birds and as you can see as we go down
the tree of the species the uh the um
the the eras actually as we go up the
species as we have generalizable um more
general names the error decreases but
which means it's a convoluted way of
saying by the time you're in the fine
grained uh um um level we still make a
lot of errors the the algorithm are
still not totally u totally u u ready um
another work that I find fascinating is
that a few years ago a group of students
uh and and in my lab um train a fine
grained car classifier in terms of mod u
make model and year. It turns out after
1970s there are thousands of car make
car models that are defined by different
make, model and year. And then you can
tea take we took um Google Street View
images from 200 or 100 I think major
cities across the country and then we
use the uh fine grain car detectors to
detect what are the cars on the street
of these uh cities and we use it as a
lens to study social uh patterns. For
example, um what is the pattern here? I
showed education patterns. You know, car
models and education patterns are highly
correlated or uh or uh income patterns
highly correlated. In that paper, we
show voting patterns highly correlate uh
correlated or even environmental, you
know, patterns highly correlated. So
it's a really interesting way of using
computer vision as a lens to study our
society and no human no individual human
not even a collection of humans uh can
do this easily at all. So so AI is
really pushing the boundary of what uh
humans can see. Um
to drive home this idea let's do a
couple of tests. Humans are actually
have our limitations, right? I just
talked about celebrating humans ability
of seeing, but we also have our
limitation. This is a very famous uh uh
visual illusion test called Stroop test.
And the idea is that you all can read
the words, but if you if I ask you to
read the color of the word as fast as
possible going from right, left to right
and top to down, you find it's it's not
that easy, right? Try to read it like
red, yellow,
green,
purple, blue, black, orange. It it it's
it's it it's fighting with you. This is
the fight between visual attention and
and all that. Here's another example.
Um, there are two alternating images of
the of the uh picture and there's one
change, a pretty big change that's
happening between the two alternating
pictures. I don't know if you spot the
change. Do you spot it?
>> The engine.
>> Yes, it's the engine, right? So, it
takes a while to to spot it. So, this is
a very famous psychology uh experiment
called change blindness. Now all this is
fun. Stroop test is fun. This is fun.
But this is not fun. That human
attention is limited. And in some
situations in our work and life, that
kind of attention limit can be dire. For
example, medical errors are the third
leading cause of death in in America's
health care system. And of course
leaving this pair of scissors in the
body of the patient is kind of the
iconic image of medical errors. But
there are so many medical errors,
pharmaceutical errors, there's uh you
know um procedure errors, clerical
errors, u diagnostic errors. So so one
has to be very careful. For example, in
surgery rooms, um, honestly, scissors
don't get left in the bodies typically,
but much smaller, uh, things like suture
needles or a piece of gauze and all
that. So, we uh, and today
most of this is still just track by
hands, right? Like we have these
checklist to to uh to to track in the
surgery rooms. If something is missing,
the surgery has to be paused. On
average, that pause is close to an hour.
And think about the danger for the
patient, the exposure to bacteria and
the bleeding and all that just because
we have to search for that item. So if
there is a way to use AI to help our PA
uh our uh doctors surgeons to track item
that would be so powerful and this is
just a demo this is not a deploy system
were not there in terms of fidelity but
this is a demo to show that we can use
AI to count in this case goss you know
uh and and all that and um and this is
just an example of pushing AI to see
what humans don't see. Here's another
example um that is really fun. I don't
know if I showed this before, but this
is one of my favorite visual illusions
where I'm just giving you the answer. If
if you look at the two square A and B on
a checkerboard
on the top, it is so hard to believe
they have the same grayscale or
luminance. And then you look at the
bottom, you're like, "Ah, of course they
do." But why? Even though you have the
bottom picture in front of you, seeing
the top is still gives you the illusion.
Why? Because evolution has pre-wired us
in in conjecturing or understanding our
world in its common way with the common
physics of the shape of objects,
lighting source, how shadows are made
and all that. This is this is so deep in
our evolution in our visual development
that it's hard for us to see see it
another way. So what I'm trying to get
at is there's bias in our visual in our
human visual system. The bias might come
from evolutionary construct. The bias
can come from our social um uh
experience. The bias can come from the
data we're exposed to. But some of these
biases can be harmful. Right? when the
bias happens that became unfair uh to a
group of people a community and we have
to be aware of this. A few years ago
face recognition algorithm was not good
and and it tends to recognize uh certain
skin color and and even gender better
than others and it has consequences.
Think about self-driving car think about
you know um many other uh medical use
cases. So um so we have to be vigilant
about this. Um I do believe that um
AI bias has been a problem that people
now are carrying. You know a few years
ago this problem was so new that many
people are not even paying attention.
But fast forward to 2025. I'm not saying
we have solved this problem. But I'm
personally a lot happier to see that so
many people are paying attention to
this. Not only just in academia but also
in industry.
And then there's another kind of not
seeing and this is interesting.
Sometimes not seeing is exactly what we
want
because you want to respect privacy. So
how do you create AI that helps people
to see yet you still want it not to see
what people don't want you to see? This
is a very deep. It's a technical problem
as well as a human problem. So from a
technical point of view, there are many
ways to consider ML machine learning
privacy. I'm just listing here from a
visual approach point of view a few
years ago. Our lab wrote this paper
about um using smart cameras in patient
rooms or patient homes to help doctors
to see better. uh but even there we have
to recognize issues like faces or just
full body information and and even homes
and this is a list of potential
solutions. For example, you can do
blurring or you can do masking, you can
do dimensionality reduction, but you can
also, you know, try to do uh different
approaches for example, federated
learning so that you don't send all the
data to the server or encryption and and
other things. So, I'm not going to
belabor this, but there's one work I
want to show you. It's not even my work,
but I really like this work. And um it's
a work about taking videos of people and
try to recognize the action of people
but yet respecting the privacy of
people. How do you do that? Right? For
example, in this case um you want to
take a video of this kid uh moving in
the scene. Um there are ways to do this.
If you blur this you or defocus this or
do some of these it kind of yeah you can
you can provide uh you can protect
privacy but you also lose enough
information that you might not even know
what this person is doing and for many
applications the whole goal is to know
what this person is doing. So in this
particular work uh led by Hong Koen's
students they actually did a combination
of hardware and software approach where
they handcrafted a lens that is actually
um that that that actually filters uh
visual data in a particular way. so
particular that if you look at the top
row, the lens, what the lens captures
into the camera protects the privacy a
lot. You don't see the person's face,
you don't see the body and so on. But
because it's a lens that's particularly
designed in connection with a piece of
software, it can help to back out the
movement information or the the the
human activity information without
backing out face information. So that's
a really interesting approach. That's a
hybrid between hardware and software
aiming towards important applications
that you want to see people to protect
them but you don't want to see too much
because you want to respect privacy. So
that's that's a work I really like. I
really like the spirit of that work. So
okay. So in this part of the lecture I
shared with you a number of things just
considerations of building AI to see
what humans don't see. Sometimes we're
pushing AI like fine grain recognition
of birds to go beyond human ability.
Those are superhuman ability. Sometimes
we know humans are not good. We have
bias or we have attention issues and
then we want to use AI to help us. And
then sometimes we generally have
situations we don't want anyone to see.
And then how do you use AI to continue
to help without violating those privacy
concerns. So you can see that AI is a
very interesting powerful tool. It can
both help but amplify
us. And if we have bias, if we have
issues, AI can amplify us too. So when
we build AI, it is so important not only
to take that technology perspective but
also to take the human perspective to
commit to study, forecast and guide AI
to understand its human impact and and
respect human values. So that's that's
the second message take-home message and
again a number of collab collaborators
and students participated in this work.
Okay, now let's talk about building AI
to see what human want to see. And in
fact, we're going to go beyond seeing.
We're going to connect seeing and doing
together.
So if you think about today's societal
anxiety about AI, one of the biggest
anxiety is labor. Uh a lot of headline
news will say labor is under threat.
robots taking over jobs.
The truth is the the the picture is
complex. You know, denying job change is
wrong. Every technological shift in
humans history has caused labor market
change. And some of them are very
painful. Some of them can lead to even
civil wars and wars. Um but so but but
also that change sometimes is inevitable
and uh
a tiny digression a lot of the labor
threat rhetoric that we have been
hearing think about physical labors but
today in the past two years if you look
at genai's impact is white collar u jobs
that are drastically uh being impacted
especially software engineer engineering
and uh and uh analytical work in in
offices. So, so there's just definitely
uh labor change, but in the meantime, we
also need to recognize that AI also can
be helpful. We actually fundamentally
have human labor shortages in many
situations, especially in elderly care
as well as health care. First of all, as
modern medicine improves,
uh, human life expectancy increases and
that just inevitably pushes the society
towards um, uh, longer living and that's
a good thing. But in the meantime, we
have shortages of labors. Young people
need to work and that's how to make this
uh, society uh, vibrant, economy
vibrant. But who is taking care of our
elderlys? who are taking care of our
chronically ill. Uh even in America's
hospital, we have such a attrition of uh
health care workers especially nurses um
that uh we don't have enough h hands,
ears, eyes to to help our patients. So
instead of thinking about this word
replace, we actually can think about AI
augmenting. And you got a glimpse of
that in my surgery room example. Indeed,
in health care, there's so many spaces
in our health care that we don't have
enough pairs of eyes. And that's what I
call the dark spaces of health care from
surgery room to patient room to uh
pharmaceutical to homes and and so on.
So, how do we make AI help? And this is
something that uh Isan has been leading
a ton of this work also with Zing. um is
that we have been looking at this
problem of ambient intelligence for
healthcare where we combine smart
sensors with machine learning algorithms
to glean health critical insights from
these situations in healthcare setup so
that we can alert the patients or family
members or doctors in time to help uh
patients and again the fuller paper is
in this particular paper we published a
couple of years ago. Let me just give
you a couple of examples. One example is
this hand hygiene project which actually
started way before co um and uh hand
hygiene turns out to be really important
for keeping hospital um infection low.
Hospital acquired infection is actually
one of the leading causes of American
patients fatality in our hospitals. It
kills more than three times more people
per year than car accidents nationwide.
And it is really hard to control. Most
of these germs are passed from patient
room to patient room and then they they
kind of just brew together. So what do
we do? The hospitals try to use human
auditors but we just talked about we
don't even have enough nurses let alone
hiring auditors and also this is you
cannot hire enough of them. There's
human fatigue we just talked about human
detention problem. So this is not a
pretty prohibitive uh solution. There
were some technological solution like
RFID, you know, put the badge if the
badge or the person wearing the badge is
close to the u sink or the hand hygiene
uh hand sanitizer dispenser, it gives
you the hint that the person or most
likely the doctor or the nurses is
washing their hands. But that's very
non-specific. You cannot guarantee and
the hospital rooms are pretty small.
Corridors are small and just standing
next to something doesn't mean you're
doing it. So a few years ago we did this
project where we put smart sensors that
provides p protects privacy by just only
gleaning depth information like the blue
screen and the blue uh video there. And
then we use vision computer vision
algorithm to classify actions. Is the
person washing hand or not washing hand?
And uh the result is that if you compare
ground truth with the uh algorithm
output versus human outputs or human um
detective detection results, you can see
algorithm is so much better and more
consistent than than humans. Uh you have
to almost show the same video to four
humans to get almost as good as AI. And
this is just not plausible. If it's one
person, you can see how sparse the
detection is and that's not good. So
this is one application. Another
application we uh we worked on is ICUs.
ICU is where patients fights life and
death. ICU is also where um 1% of US GDP
is spent. So making ICU as effective as
safely as possible is a top priority.
One of the goal well the goal of ICU is
to to get our patient safely out of ICU
and go into step down units or even go
home. So uh one of the most important
thing people have learned in ICU is to
help patients to move
proper movement which we call
mobilization. It's actually important
for recovery. But this is a very dicey
situation. You have to get nurses to
help. Doctors have to give orders. You
have to move properly and it has to be
in different time like designated time
and you have to assess the movement and
all this is not easy right so we
collaborated with Stanford as well as
Utah's inter mountain hospital to put
these smart sensors in ICU units and
help doctors to monitor patient movement
in this particular case four different
kind of movements getting out of bed
getting in bed getting out of chair
getting in here. These things are so
important for ICU patients. I know that
it's for us it's a no-brainer, but this
really is uh is is critical and you can
see that AI can help to do the kind of
detection and prediction that uh that is
so helpful for doctors especially when
there is a labor shortage. Last but not
the least example is aging in place. And
this is just so important for you know
many many reasons. People uh seniors
want to live home independently and
healthily. And uh uh remember during the
beginning of co when we had so much
fatality among the aging um seniors a
lot has to do with hospital overrun and
and overtaxed hospital system. So
putting and keeping seniors safe and
well in their homes is really critical
and using smart sensors we can help you
know early detection of infection
especially using thermal cameras or
mobility we just talked about in ICU
similar here or understanding sleep
patterns or understanding dietary
patterns all these are realms of
possibilities by AI and smart sensors
And then last but not least, what if
there's still short labor shortage after
smart sensors? The thing about smart
sensors is that their their information
gathering system, but they cannot go
there and help to turn a patient or
bring water and medicine pills to the p
uh elderly. So this brings us to to the
last technical topic which is inbody AI
or we would call a a large part of
inbody AI is robotics and this is where
I find it extremely exciting because it
closes the loop between perception and
action and if you think about the
Cambrian explosion of evolution when
eyes when there's onset of eyes, animals
start to move. So we uh the area of
robotics is where we can close the loop
between seeing and doing. But it's not
easy, right? Robots, as much as we're
very excited by them, still are very
very slow. They are very very clumsy.
It's very hard for them to uh adapt to a
generalizable situation.
And uh in today's robotic research we we
as a field have have made a ton of
progress and and Stanford is definitely
one of the centers of robotic learning
but still most of these work are kind of
constrained in their setup are are short
horizon tasks like pick and place and it
it has you know it it has anecdotal
setup and lack of clinical sorry lack
lack of standard uh benchmark. So let me
just share with you a couple of work in
our lab. Uh one work is uh a few years
ago we're looking at how to bring robots
to the wild. If we have to pre-desate
the set of tasks, it's kind of
unsatisfying. On the other hand, if you
look at today's LLM, it's totally in a
while. You can talk about anything. So
my student Wong and a few students want
to close this gap. So this idea is that
um how do we give an open instruction to
a robot any instruction without
pre-training
everything in a in a in a closed world
and the robot can do some tasks. So
let's say your training set is open a
drawer like that. in the wild you have
doors like that. So how do you how do
you make some uh progress in that
problem and uh so the the goal is is is
in the wild generalization and here's an
a a result um you know or or overall
algorithm
um I don't know if this is so glitchy
but whatever what you're saying is we
want to tell this robot arm to open a
drawer
by planning a motion path that avoids
knocking down that flower and all this
is all this instruction were not
pre-trained. So what we do is actually
we borrow uh the latest advances in LLM
as well as in visual language model and
the idea is that we use LLM and V uh uh
LLM to give us a instruction set and
then we use visual language model to
help us to recognize or understand the
environment and then we turn that into a
motion planning app so that the robotic
arm can execute. And because we're using
LLMs as well as VLMs, we don't have to
we we are we get rid of the problem of
training robot in a closed world and
bring them to a more generalizable or in
the wild. And the details is the
instruction of open top drawer comes in.
LLM turns this into like literally codes
and then because of these instructions
like drawer or handle um the uh we send
this information to a VLM model and that
model detects drawer and handle in the
scene and then because of that it
updates its information and then it
updates a motion motion map. This is
presented by a heat map to show you
where the robot arm should focus, where
it should not focus. And with that, then
you get give it another instruction. But
watch out to the uh for the vase. Again,
it goes through the same thing with LLM,
writes the code or or um generates the
code, send it through a VLM model. VLRL
model detects the object and then
updates the motion planning map. In this
case, it's the negative, not the
positive because you you want to avoid
that. And then combining with the
previous map, you get a heat map of
knowing where to avoid and where to go.
And uh eventually
um what we do is we do this for the
motion planning map. We do it for
rotation to gripper velocity. And then
this is the result. Um actually let me
just show you this. Um this is the
actual result of a of the of the robot.
And then we do this for many different
tasks, right? We we can do it for
articulated object manipulation.
We can do it uh um we can you know here
just many different examples you know
napkins or sweeping the floor. uh what
is this getting toast the setting up
table um
and also dealing with online
disturbances and so on. So, so this is
one work. Another work I want to just
show you um quickly um is that um
overall uh robotics um research is still
in lacking good benchmark.
And while we're still experimenting in
the in the labs, we know real world is
so much more complex, so much more
uncertain, have large variability, is so
interactive and social and is has a lot
of multitasking task. And then we know
that both natural language and computer
vision has benefited a lot from setting
up important largecale data sets for
both training and benchmark. So in our
lab we have been working on this project
that is towards an ecological robotic
learning building an ecological robotic
learning environment and a uh and and
and try to encourage researchers to
benchmark against a large and diverse
set of activities. And that's the
behavior uh benchmark which is benchmark
for everyday household activity in
virtual interactive and ecological
environments.
Now here's a question because this
lecture has a lot to do with human
values is who is to say which tasks
robots should do. I know that every
graduate students who are working on
robotics just want two task. One is
laundry the other one is dishwasher.
That's great. Let but moving beyond
grasu what are this what are the tasks
we should get robots to do for us. So
instead of us coming up with this task
list we actually did a human- centered
survey to ask robots sorry to ask humans
that what would you like robots to help
you? Let me let me test this. Um would
you like a robot to help you to clean
the kitchen floor?
Say yes or no. Okay, good. Um, normal
people would say yes.
Shoveling snow.
>> Okay. Folding laundry.
>> Okay, good. Cooking breakfast.
>> See, we're getting mixture answers,
right?
>> What about opening Christmas gift?
>> Right. Exactly. People are different.
Like I actually think robot can do this
pretty well but we don't want it and
there is we even ask one of the task we
ask is buying wedding rings. Can you
imagine that? Um so so what we did is
actually we want to respect human
preference. So we took a a bunch of
government surveys from uh uh labor
office in US and Europe and so on and
clan together uh put together thousands
of everyday activity tasks and then we
went online to find people. We want to
be as diverse as possible, but I I think
we have room to improve. But we found
1,400 people and to answer these tasks
and tell us which task they want robots
to help. And then we rank that. And you
can see that just like glass students,
people want robots to help with
cleaning, a lot of cleaning, toilet
cleaning, floor cleaning. But people
don't want robots to play squash for you
or to buy a wedding ring or to even mix
baby cereals. There's a lot of tasks
that matters to us as humans emotionally
or socially or whatever. So we our goal
is first we decided we doesn't uh we we
have a principled way to uh decide which
are the thousand tasks that we want to
train robots for and those are the tasks
that's humans prefer to get help and um
with that in mind we have to actually
build a ver uh virtual environments. So
we we act we scanned or or or acquired
3D scene from 50 different uh real world
environments from restaurants to
apartments to to uh grocery stores to to
offices and so on. And then we acquired
um this number is actually outdated. We
require more than 10,000 object assets,
3D assets uh that has a lot of
properties whether it's articulation,
deformability
and all those properties. And then we uh
we have to build a simulation
environment. A lot of people have built
simulation environment. Let me just fast
forward. But uh our particular
simulation environment was a
collaboration with Nvidia's Omniverse
group and we were going for building a
physically, perceptually and also
interactively
high quality simulation environment and
this you know especially taking account
for example physical effects like
thermal transparency, deformability and
so on. We also tested our uh behavior
environment against other environments
in terms of perceptual realism for from
human user study. And you know here are
some of the examples of physical
interaction uh such as cloth or or
liquids and so on. So there's a lot of
nuance that has gone into this work and
let me just fast forward and um and
these are some benchmark we did compared
to other uh other work. Okay, let me
just fast forward. Um
so this is ongoing work actually in in
our lab and because of this we're able
to you know uh we are using behavior to
help us to learn robotics to help us
actually to push us to gather more
interesting data and also to to use that
for um for even cognitive studies. Let
me just fast forward. Um
uh one thing I want to share with you is
that let me let me just share these
numbers is today's algorithms still
cannot do behavior tasks. And the of all
these roles the top role is what we wish
robots can do. Give them no privilege
information. they have to be dropped in
the environment and do these tasks and
we benchmarked three behavior task using
today's uh robotic algorithm and the
performance is just zero. And once you
start to give more priv uh privileged
information or make assumptions that
make the task simpler like magic motion
or some uh you know uh perfect memory
and all that things start to get better.
So this is this is if you look at it um
you know uh only look at the top row you
get pretty depressed by today's uh
robots but as a grad student I hope
you're inspired because that means we
have a lot of room to uh to grow. Um
okay uh these are just different papers
from our lab. I'm going to actually fast
forward because I think uh we've talked
enough about this. Um
uh well uh by the way we're also doing
digital twin of behavior in the digital
environment as well as in the in the
real world environment and that's that's
a great way of test uh testing real to
sim transfer. Again, this is a unsolved
problem and um and uh there's a long way
to go. And this is in this particular
case, we're showing you that this robot
without speeding up. You can see how
slow it is is trying to clean up this
room. And uh uh you know, okay, hooray.
Um this is actually uh some of the
mistakes that this robot uh makes in for
example it cannot pick up uh the bottle
or earlier it just went the wrong way
and uh um placed it in the wrong place.
So there's still a lot of uh mistakes.
Okay, let's uh let me um let me fast
forward. Uh we're actually we're also
using this environment to study visually
impaired patients and this is a great
way of uh putting patients in a safe
environment to um to to study. Uh, one
last thing I want to show you is really
super cool and and this is the last um
technical work I want to show is that we
also now are collaborating with um
psychologists and doctors to study how
we can use brain waves to control
robots. So what you're seeing here is a
demo where a grad student I think is
wearing this EEG cap and that just is
sending instructions and the robotic arm
is cooking a Japanese meal purely from
thoughts. There's no invasive brain
control. This is from electrical
signals. What we had to do is to
pre-train these thoughts. You have to
pre-train the robotic arm with say lift
or place or or drop or or whatever. And
once you do that, this is an entire meal
cooked based on the the wave. This is
really sci-fi. And this this has
happened last year. So I'm pretty
excited by where all this is going.
Combining vision and perception and
robotics and also, you know, helping
helping people in clinical setting. This
is really uh the future of this is
helping severely paralyzed uh patients.
Okay. So, so behavior project is really
aimed at augmenting people. It's a large
scale and diverse benchmark and it has
realistic and ecological you know
physics and perception. And this is the
last part of what the last take-home
message is that we not only want to
build AI to just do things or see
things. We really want to build it to
help people. AI being an augmentation
tool or enhancing tool for humanity is
very important instead of a tool that
replace us.