today for our talk we have Professor
Jake Williams from Drexel University he
is an associate uh professor at
information science at Drexel
University's College of computing and
informatics in Philadelphia Pennsylvania
Dr Williams has a background in physics
and math with degrees from the
University of Vermont and his research
leverages a quantitative Linguistics
perspective the amp uh applies math and
statistical methodologies to analyze and
improve linguistic Learning Systems um
following a one-year postto appointment
at the University of Berkeley uh
studying large language large scale
machine learning in 2015 Dr Williams
became a data science faculty at Drexel
where he drove the foundation of a dsms
program and develops and instruct uh
data science coursework including non uh
including natural language processing
with deep learning
um so uh welcome and thank you for
coming today for your talk and you could
do a quick introduction of yourself um
before you great thanks so much I got
the mic here um nice to see you all here
thanks for coming out and also for
showing up online it's a pleasure to be
here um as uh was mentioned my name is
Jake and my background is in math and
physics so the perspective that I'm
coming from towards this work might be a
little bit different than the standard
and that'll be a theme throughout the
discussion um the purpose of this
discussion is to go through a relatively
long uh term development a project that
I've been working on um and uh as
mentioned my background is in
quanitative linguistics which means my
uh history of focus on language has
primarily been to uh develop uh
General uh theories and descriptions of
phenomena That You observe with regards
to linguistic units whatever those might
be um it's a statistical approach uh
based on theories of language generation
that are statistical in basis and over
the course of my time as a researcher
I've um explored and ventured into
language modeling itself and ultimately
into neural networks as they approach
language modeling themselves and that's
what brought me here
um through quite a bit of other work so
um if you look into my profile you'll
see a lot of different subjects in
either applied NLP like I said
quantitative
Linguistics um and neural networks is a
natural transition for me into um
inferential
work so let's get
started so um well this is how we'll
start the conversation today it's not
exactly how we got here in my lab um we
came at this this subject from a
different approach trying to think about
um layer initializations in neural
networks and um this subject that we're
discussing as a front for this talk uh
is specifically focused on Transformer
architecture components the self-
attention component that's uh pivotal to
the success of the Transformer
architecture and uh it focuses on the
fact that self attention requires a
Quadra comparison of vectors in order to
produce the feature weights of those
vectors needed to model longrange
dependencies in text commonly parameters
for self attention are based on a
transformation matrix two usually
queries and
keys that are responsible for
dimensionalizing input vectors and I
describe it this way because generally
speaking when you're at the point of a
self attention layer you already have
low dimensional vectors but the
parameters in a standard self tension
layer are changing the dimensionalities
and the structure of that dimensional
space they are like an embedding layer
which is factorizing the embedding
Dimensions this redens is the primary
means by which self attention creates
feature weights it really just computes
similarity in that shared
space large and similar inner products
really just result in strongly weighted
features so it's up to that
dimensionalization to produce good
similarities for whatever purpose
purpose your prediction
requires however an alternative strategy
for future weights might ask given a
basis so in other words you're stuck
with your low dimensional
vectors what is the optimal way to
convert those comparisons of the vectors
you're looking at by a matrix
transformation to modify the vector
similarities that you are stuck
with that correspond to the best weights
for features in other words treat this
as a feed forward layer to produce self
atten weights as opposed to try and
transform to some basis that produces
good future
weights the use of this modified self
attention mechanism will be part and
partiel the substance of this
talk it's worth noting that this
alternative mechanism is entirely
compatible with the traditional
dimensionalizing version of self
attention in other words you could still
change the dimension and compute
similarities and then convert that with
a second feedforward layer to produce
optimal feature weights this is not
exclusive in any way this is exploring
how useful that
alternative prediction of future weights
can
function however we'll avoid the
standard mechanism for two reasons first
we have no
solution to the standard parameters for
self attention as an initialization and
this will be discussed at length in
slides to
come likewise it would
create an additional model complexity
that would model the effects of the
modified form of self attention that we
wish to study so having that
dimensionalization as a way to produce
good feature weights would confuse
whether or not the feed
forward computation of feature weights
is functioning well there's a catch to
this however which is that these
features these vectors that we use for
such a self attention layer better be
good in other words their comparisons
must be consistent and meaningful in the
first
place so to get it out of the way here's
an architectural diagram for the
relatively simple near shallow
architecture pattern that we're using it
doesn't seem like there are many neurons
in a network of this type and that's
because all of the activations are soft
Max which means despite the fact that
the U Matrix for example is an entire
layer it's really just going through a
single prediction nonlinearity the
softmax function
so you can think about this is
essentially a three- layer Network that
might be creating an encoder decoder
kind of
design likewise the difference in
presentation here over self attention
which is parameterized by the Matrix W
here is intending to show how
a whether you consider it the query or
the key um one vector is the pivot for
the comparison that will produce the
feature weights which is then fed
forward in this model through W this is
the case for standard self attention too
in other words you can reduce it to a by
prediction diagram in this way where a
gray Vector such as is depicted here is
that pivot the attention distribution
coming out of the W Matrix and the
softmax function is indicated by the
vertical Red Bar there which weights the
block of vectors in Black that includes
the pivot Vector in
Gray which has then passed through a
feed forward layer often called the
values of a standard self attention
Matrix
U we then since we use you as a way to
reduce the dimensionality of the
prediction that we're trying to make we
then feed that forward through another
layer and then to output and that's
essentially the relative shallow that
we're talking about here W is a self
attention Matrix
which means there's really only two
layers in effect here and the activation
functions are strange and you might
wonder for example why we're using a
different activation function the
softmax instead of any of the
dimensionally independent activation
functions like a legistic function or
anything else and that's because we have
additional insight into the softmax
function and the parameters that it
optimizes which is very
useful so let's talk talk about those
vectors first though before we get to
layer
initialization optimizing the keys and
queries of standard self attention Bears
substantial similarity to token and word
embedding this is because the key and
query matrices have a common Dimension
that they project to much like you'd see
with the factorization of an embedding
layer on its own think word Toc
something like that
these normally there might be multiple
self attention heads and because of the
indeterminacy in creating a different
dimensional space in other words there
are multiple equivalent reshufflings of
those different dimensions which will
produce the same output that
indeterminacy is something that we
hypothesize has bearing on what is now
referred to as the lottery ticket
hypothesis in other words that multiple
or this is the way that I would state it
but um that multiple different
embeddings which produce different
Vector spaces can be leveraged in
parallel to create further robustness
for the model or in the way that it's
implemented that if a random
initialization doesn't do that well you
can eliminate it from the network and
that subnetwork will do just as well
even after it's totally
trained in other words having multiple
clones self attention heads which have
no difference in the outputs that
they're trying to predict is that at the
root of the lottery ticket hypothesis
and ultimately that invocation of the
lottery ticket hypothesis is really a
justification for eliminating parameters
whose substantial costs of training are
essentially wasted as a result of random
parameter
initialization you might ask questions
like well what is a good initialization
what is a good set of word embeddings to
use
so how can lottery ticket HP hypthesis
interactive effects of randomly
initialized embedding layers be avoided
when constructing language models is
another question that is embedded in
this
discussion but we shouldn't say that
dimensionality reduction isn't needed
it's incredibly necessary for language
modeling you absolutely have to work
with reduced Dimension unless you're in
a very small vocabulary for example
like um 26 Latin characters or something
something like that like a wave to
VEC the inherit input dimension of a
large vocabulary model presents many
computational intract abilities when
designing NLP systems something that
you're probably all very aware of
likewise though the distance from
embedding layers to learning information
the loss at outputs puts them in a
challenging position to train it's
really hard to learn embedding layers
because of the indeterminacy in the
space space that you're trying to learn
you could swap dimensions and it's
equivalent but the distance means that
they receive learning information
last this is a real Challenge and it's
present in the history of NLP and deep
learning
to um Vanishing gradient
stuff and this is exacerbated in the way
that we have to actually learn embedding
layers in standard models where
we might modify learning rates to be
lower all the way back at the bottom of
a network to be gentle with those
embedding layers and help them learn
effectively but this is really trouble
because if we had a good embedding layer
at the start those subsequent layers
could be much easier to
learn so
ultimately in order to approach this
challenge um
we came along with a discernability
hypothesis in other words this boiled
down to the theory that low dimensional
vectors more than anything needed to be
able to discern features and that
doesn't sound um like a very strong
assertion and we started with a really
really really low bar and um assume that
the most common features needed to be
the most discernible features so if
we're stuck with a lower dimension and
we can't give everything a one hot
Vector to be told apart very well then
we might want to give the more clear
vectors which have more dimensional
independencies to those features which
appear most frequently and could stand
to confuse models the
most this hypothesis led us directly to
develop the bit Cipher algorithm which
is really just a scheme for assigning
vectors of zeros and ones nothing too
crazy in terms of what we're attempting
to do in the figure at right here the
order of vector assignment is by Row
from top to bottom and this is on a five
dimension five bit Vector
system the first five from bottom are
those one hot
vectors past that point you'll see two
hot vectors but they're a little bit
less Darkly shaded indicating the way
that we actually utilize the system in
other words we normalize them to have
unit
sum what I hope you can see from this is
that the bit Cipher algorithm
generalizes one hot vectors to low
dimensions and as a result we can work
from a very sparse feature set and
explore dimensionalities as a controlled
phenomenon and this assignment is
incredibly naive too that's the other
thing that I want you to see is as well
that this discernability hypothesis does
not create any meaningful correlations
between tokens that behave similarly so
if you've got the upper and lower case
of a word their vectors aren't going to
capture those similarities according to
the bit Cipher it's really just going to
try and make sure that those features
are distinguishable in a low dimensional
space and that the most distinguishable
features are those which appear most
commonly this was enough to do a
surprising amount of work
so with some scheme for a determin
deterministic low dimensionalization
procedure we were then able to utilize
this solution that we had actually
developed previously so this was
actually the real motivator for a lot of
the work that you're seeing today while
it might seem like it's just a
checkpoint in the
middle provided bit Cipher produces
decent embeddings we can ask can other
layers be non-randomly initialized in
other words without gradient descent or
back propagation or other gradient based
iterative
algorithms this equation came about from
analysis of word Toc with the original
softmax activation
function and um much like other um
articulations of the word Toc family of
embeddings uh came up with differential
solutions that depended on cooccurrence
matrices we formalize this as a question
is there a way to take a cooccurrence
matrix F in this equation
here and convert it with some weights
some denominators by row into something
that warms up a single layer feed
forward in a neural
network and ultimately this K minus one
overk term here and this sum
is really just expressing something like
conditional
probability like conditional probability
because Kus 1
K is a wrinkle that says that as the
number of features increases in other
words the context window increases in a
block
Transformer then the warm start that we
could apply to start off a neural
network without a Randomness Randomness
entirely determined by the vectors
underneath
near nearing whatever Direction it's
going all we have to do is compute some
cooccurrences between inputs and outputs
and I don't mean necessarily standard
co-occurrences that you might have
learned about a long time ago which
depend on a radius I mean whatever your
inputs are whatever your outputs are you
take their sum of outer products and you
get a cooccurrence matrix of inputs and
outputs and that can then be utilized to
initialize your layer in that neural
network to be vastly more performant
than what you'd get by a random
initialization this was a strong
motivator for us this was just for a
single layer
model but it depended on the softmax
function for
Activation and the softmax function as
an activation function we knew is also
necessary for self attention features
and this meant that if we could put self
attention into some kind of a standard
form with this equation just like a
single
layer then we could apply the same
solution with one catch that catch is
specifically that we don't know what the
targets are for self attention there's
no target Vector y you know the thing
that you're trying to predict which
which position is the one that you want
to wait most
strongly and so in order to apply this
solution for a self attention model we
had to do some more
analysis and that's in the reference
number one um which is all the way back
up in the first slide if you want to see
it but that derives a differential
Criterion an analog for the single layer
solution that tells us what the targets
of that kind of self attention actually
are the hidden targets the weights that
you're trying to create which really are
just about making sure that the the
layer above self attention has some um
unsurprising things coming towards it
the self attention layer is really just
trying to massage the vectors so that
way they look like something that the
next layer above
expects aside from that though it's a
much more in-depth
conversation the point though is that
for the
model in this picture
here we can now
start off with vectors
X that are not
random we can use those vectors X to
initialize non-randomly the parameters
in W the self attention Matrix and then
use that going up the network to
initialize the parameters in U since
it's just a feed forward layer with
whatever self attention is giving it as
weights and then whatever that produces
the hidden State H we can use that
with the actual targets after the output
layer to warm up the Matrix
o and you might say okay well how did
you figure out what those hidden targets
are like you had to have an output for
the U Matrix to try and hit that too is
something
that the bit Cipher can provide in the
form of label embeddings in other words
low dimensional targets of the thing
that is Downstream that you're trying to
hit the language model's output so
similarly we can warm start the U Matrix
in terms of those bit Cipher label
embeddings so in this view the aim is to
show how simple and general the single
layer softmax activated solution is to
apply it's really just no more
challenging than Computing conditional
probability given inputs and outputs
it's fast it's something that you can
distribute in terms of
processing and it's very very
general so um this is essentially the
process that we're using in order to
warm up the W and U
Matrix
there's the U Matrix there starts out as
zeros so in other words nothing no
random values no weights anywhere
over the data which is just borrowing
the dimension of this gigantic y Matrix
that has all of the Targets in it for
the entire data
set we simply just take the outer
products of whatever the hidden State
the input to that layer is assuming that
the lower layers beneath it are also
warmed up with whatever the targets for
that layer
are following that it's really just
about normalization and a logarithmic
transformation and that logarithm really
just emerges as a result of being an
inverse to the exponential function
which is a part of softmax pretty much
all of
softmax and that's really what brought
us
here so what does warm starting a
network do this is going back to
before we had the bit Cipher algorithm
for dimensionality reduction and we
started out by just saying okay if we
take a s simple simple language
model that only looks at a radius of
traditional cooccurrences as
features we can compen those vectors and
feed them forward for a language model's
output a completely random start a cold
start to a language
model is really just the size of the
vocabulary in
perplexity and those three lines here
for a few different radi are
demonstrating that point with the point
all the way at the top leftand corner of
this figure cold
starts in any of those cases when the
warm start is applied the perplexity is
immediately automatically
lower
and
furthermore the trajectories that the
updates follow continue in the same
learning rate and the same same time to
perform better than models that were
started
cold if you have a warm if you have a
early stopping Criterion similarly early
stopping will more than just generally
uh engage
first and with a higher
perplexity so this was the first
indication that we had figured out
something that's very useful
so some folks on slid say they're B
confused they're asking are we talking
about an alternative approach to self
attention we are and that's all the way
back at slide
one and it is the premise of this whole
conversation so here in this modified
version of self attention you might
normally expect to do a comparison of
your inputs The Matrix X whatever your
inputs are they might be a whole block
of vectors or they might be this is self
attention it's not cross attention where
you have different vectors that you're
trying to
attend and forgetting about the
values which for us is the U
Matrix the keys and
queries which are the parameters for
self attention are in the middle they're
in
between the two copies of the inputs
X each of those you can view as some
kind of a project ection down to a
dimension where they can interact and
this is necessary for something like
cross attention where you might have
different dimensionalities like X1 and
X2 and two separate groups of vectors if
you're doing something like machine
translation that's not necessary to
think about when you're just looking to
do a standard language model that has to
predict the next output according to the
inputs which are also outputs from
previous iterations
two insights here one that multiplying
the key and query matrices w k and
WQ it's just another parameter Matrix
that's
implied there aren't two parameter
matrices there in the middle for self
attention in any effective way there is
a common dimension of comparison and
that kind of just moves stuff around it
creates degrees of freedom so that
optimization can figure out what's the
best waiting from comparisons but the
soft Max function is strictly operating
on
similarities of that comparison
space it's not doing anything with those
similarities it's just soft maxing them
it's just activating so if it was a big
similarity it's a big attention
value in this
equation there's no transformation
happening before those vectors are
multiplied together inner products
so those vectors better be good vectors
that you're starting with x and x
transpose the same
thing they better be vectors that are
comparable they can't be vectors from
Cross attention where you're trying to
translate from one language to another
and they just don't inter product
they're different dimensions you could
force it through if they were two
differently trained embedding layers and
they had the same Dimension with this
mechanism and if you didn't you could
put those key and query matrices back in
between the two x vectors X blocks of
vectors but a lot of what's going on
here in this talk is trying to simplify
and make more
efficient the architectures that we need
and the mechanisms that they
utilize given what we know about how
language
functions and that's a critical piece
there we have assumptions that we can
make If all we're doing is auto
regression we don't need cross tension
dimensionalization in
between that'll be the theme in other
words
that can we use knowledge that we have
about the way language functions to
design better versions of architectures
that meet the needs of language instead
of being simply
General is this good this is important
so if there are any questions here it's
a good time
we
are there and
there so we just talked briefly this was
for language we're thinking about
language models it's a really simple
language model there's no self attention
here
yet this is really just evaluating that
a warm start in either the blue green or
purple case does better than its partner
which is a cold start of the same
architecture same hyper
parameters orange reddish and
brown so three different models
regardless of how long your context is
in each case here we see that a model
which has a non-random initialization by
the equation presented two slides back
from
here starts a network off with a much
lower
perplexity the requirements to apply
this solution to a feed forward layer of
parameters is simply
that your inputs should not have
negative
values that's really all we have to
worry
about so it becomes really easy to ask
questions like well what happens when
you apply this to other data with non-
negative
values well there's one little catch
that we had to think about here in this
case and that is
with the bit Cipher or one hot vectors
we're controlling the Norms of the
inputs with standard embeddings with
mnist for example when you're trying to
predict a handwritten digits 0 through 9
value you don't get to assume
necessarily that all inputs have the
same
Norm you can normalize the inputs but
doesn't necessarily make sense to
normalize them to one when you're
looking at images
for example they're non- Negative they
have 0 through 255 for example in
mnist and as a result we can put these
data through that same warm
start now one little caveat here I've
alluded to about the Norms of vectors is
that we don't know what that value of K
is in other words let me go back
could look at it here or here that's the
number of features per
prediction which if you're looking at
unit normed word vectors is however big
your context window is
K because they all have unit norm and
there's K of them but if you're looking
at just an image it's not clear if it's
a composition of multiple vectors if
it's one vector and how many it is if it
is a composition it just has a
norm in application to data like that
that is what K becomes the average norm
of an input and I'm regretting not
putting a graph in this but the paper
that discusses this shows that in the
Mist data set the exact optim optimal
value of K is the average norm of the
inputs however you've pre-processed them
and that's how we generally apply this
rule when we're warm starting systems
and we don't have unit normed vectors
and it was learned from studying this
model's application this solution's
application to nonlinguistic data but as
mentioned the purpose was always towards
language so longer context windows in
principle should provide models with
more information than shorter context
Windows this means one should expect
that models perform better when context
window length is
longer
theoretically and this is essentially
the reason for why self attention was
initially developed researchers wanted
to improve language models and context
Windows providing more information were
seen as the key to that in other words
the more features the more information
the more flexibility a model can have
have and
expressivity however without feature
weights models didn't simply get better
with long context windows and feature
weights and self attention were
hypothesized to be needed and this was
proven back in 2017 with the Transformer
architecture in moving towards self
attention and Transformer though the
Primacy of the Transformer
architecture's block context model
a shadow over the use of other context
models so for example if I were to ask
here is it clear to everyone
that the standard self attention block
model of context is different than the
traditional notion of co-occurrences
which use a radius that is not
positionally anchored it is the context
model the positional anchoring of the
block context model that gives it its
information
it is
not in all likelihood anything
else now what you do with that context
model matters you can't just take those
vectors in a block add them together and
expect a feed forward to do well that's
where self attention is needed in order
to figure out which Vector needs the
best weight most
weight so what you'll also see in the
architectures that are based on what
I've already presented is that we're
interested to explore how different
models of context for language models
can be integrated in
general because they each provide
different information and we all know
that the standard Transformers block
model of context requires a ridiculous
amount of information and data in order
to become effectively
trained so the
current um Spate of contexts that we
use top there might be the standard
Transformer context that has a fixed
positional block and it takes the first
10 tokens for example the second 10
tokens and the third 10 tokens each in
different
blocks and each of those is a group of
contextualizing
vectors the second one there that you
see with the r as a subscript is a
radial model because those do different
things in other words rather than assume
you're looking at the first 10 or the
nth 10 features you pick a radius and
you say what are the last R features the
last R vectors that can also have an
attention distribution a self attention
distribution according to the exact same
model that's being
presented it produces an entirely
separate context hidden State whatever
you want to call it which can be
conjoined with the block model to
articulate features
and be given to an output layer that
knows what to do with them when each has
different
values the concatenation of those
different context models keeps the
information separate so the output layer
can decide which portion of the context
is useful for the
prediction this last one is getting
really traditional at the bottom it's
what I refer to as a document
model if um you've ever implemented
something like a naive based classifier
or a term frequency inverse document
frequency model that's essentially what
a document model is add up your vectors
you get
something is it going to be the best for
predicting the next token absolutely not
however it's always different and what
that means is that even if you wrap to
the next block between the radial and
the document models you have a unique
context Vector even if you're looking at
the exact same block because the
document has grown and the radius just
says what are the last three what are
the last
10 as a result when you incorporate
different models of context you don't
really have to say that there's a finite
context window it might not be very good
to make predictions past the first block
but that might be about how much data
you've
used and it might be about the hyper
parameters for each one of those models
that you're applying in other words
radius the block size like
usual so far the only embeddings that
I've suggested are from this bit Cipher
algorithm and as I've expressed they're
um they don't capture any useful
similarities between similar tokens the
bit Cipher algorithm it doesn't care if
you're looking at the uppercase or the
lowercase version of a word it doesn't
see them as aing any similarity even
though they're might be used very
similarly so how can you
utilize the bit Cipher to create vectors
or tokens that have meaningful
similarities between words that are used
similarly and this is just backing off
to the traditional methods once again
taking cooccurrences of bit Cipher
vectors with whatever is there at the
middle or center of a co-occurrence
model
normally if you think about one hot
vectors A co-occurrence Matrix is really
just the same thing except now we just
have smaller vectors with different
dimensions on so to
speak and we
normalize after concatenating these
blocks of different radi from the bit
Cipher to match the original input
requirements that we discovered
for the warm start
solution and that enables us to use
these just like we would the original
bit Cipher
vectors except now just from the usual
co-occurrent statistics you'll see that
Capital word and lowercase word have a
lot of common usage and you know this
works because you've seen co-occurrences
for a very long time and while they
might not normally be useful in our
applications the these days with deep
learning they can be imparted through
the bit Cipher algorithm to prescribe
vectors as
well so here's where things start paying
out in terms of speed and
efficiency if you only have one layer of
self
attention then that means that you don't
need to worry about whatever weird
expressive stuff is happening that you
know similar inputs might have slightly
different hidden
States since that first layer is just a
set of static word
embeddings the self attention layer is
working off of static word embeddings
and that means each pair of words have a
fixed comparison given static word
embeddings and that means if you want
want to compute the quadratic features
of self attention you can just
pre-compute them and pull them from
memory this caching of vector
comparisons is
essentially reducing the self attention
layer cost from quadratic to linear
since those values that we're using to
weight the vectors for the feed forward
layer no longer require comparison
across the block they're already
compared
so when our vectors are static which is
at inference time and if we're
not learning the embedding layers
parameters with iterative differential
updates then not only do we have to not
track gradients for the embedding layer
but we don't even have to compute the
vector comparisons we can pre-compute
them and just load them which is much
much faster
so we can reduce a lot of in all the
inference in training costs not all of
the training costs some of the training
costs because if we want to update those
vectors then we can't assume cach
comparisons um but it's a huge cost
savings this means that we can train
these self-attentive feed forward unit
models very
quickly and with good initializations
but there are some other things that we
immediately observed while developing
these models and that is the lack of
randomization produced models which were
quite effective even on small data now
it doesn't mean that training on small
data will let you generalized to
everything else that's out there in the
world in other words training on a small
data set might produce a model which has
a surprisingly low perplexity on its
training set but it doesn't mean that
you're going to be able to generalize
and have a language model that's talking
well from just hearing a couple of
thousand tokens it does mean it will
know that couple of thousand tokens very
well very
quickly but there's a challenge with
using self attention
still and that is the fact that the
block model of
context often is not fully utilized
since many um documents are shorter than
long context models or long context
windows and these days there are
exceptionally long context Windows I'm
not even talking about those uh many of
the language modeling benchmarks simply
don't even go out to a thousand words
when it comes to contexts and you're
looking at a a document to
predict so
um this has been a problem for a while
and it means that if you're going to pad
your short documents you're going to
waste a lot of prediction on those
paddings
um a lot of computation gets lost just
for null information
essentially and the way that this is
often
relieved in some groups and to great
effect is by packing long contexts so
for example if you've got a 100,000
token context window most documents will
not be 100,000 tokens long what do you
do with the rest of that long context if
you want to use a thousand tokens of
good training data
you fill out the other 99,000 tokens
with a bunch of other random documents
that don't belong anywhere near the
first one that's called
packing packing can be utilized without
um
impacting different documents with each
other without contaminating the
information between documents and that
takes a lot of work but it can be
done
however um there are different
strategies that we could employ
different engineering tricks that we
could employ to
make our operation of self attention
more effective at any length of document
without having to deal with this packing
problem and that comes
about by dynamically changing the
context length from some Maximum value
that's what you would normally
set just use the context that you have
but you still have to create batches if
you want to train models quickly and
what that means is that there's still
some padding if you use this
approach but you can pad those short
documents
to set lengths batch short documents
together batch long documents
together this means that we don't need
to pack documents together to make use
of a long context window when a document
is long you can let its context be long
when a document is short you can put it
with other short documents and just use
a subset of those self attention
parameters and with traditional self
attention parameters keys and queries it
would never be a subset because it's a
low dimensionalization that that Matrix
provides with this modified self
attention though there's a different
shape to the weight Matrix and that's
why it's a subset of those parameters
that we have to utilize and that might
be something worth discussing afterwards
in other words how does the difference
in shapes of dimensionalities
between this and the standard self
attention
weights shake
out but we want to get to a different
point for the sake of this
conversation what is a model like this
useful for that should be a question
that you're asking it's a question that
we've been
asking
um we're not entirely certain yet how an
extremely large model like this will
function on trillions of tokens for
example in other words um can you expect
the same kinds of outcomes like
a chat GPT kind of thing from some of
these models human interaction and rhf
and all the rest of that though it's
something that we're considering but
also at different scales too since
those are performant on their own as
well but for
what so the point is is that from what
we've stress tested into the billions
models can be trained very quickly on a
relatively small
GPU in ways that we expect when we cach
Vector comparisons we see really big
speedups when we don't cach those
comparisons you see all of the um growth
in computation time that you would
expect from longer context
Windows this one here though we're
trying to make it really really really
small the one called
potato that's because we want to see if
we can train a model from scratch since
on very little data these models can fit
effectively with the initializations
that we've
developed and with the purpose of
starting from scratch starting with no
data we're thinking about Edge Computing
cases where we could deploy a language
model with a microphone so that a person
can talk to it and just train it from
their own data train it from their own
speech to understand their
speech so between these we've explored a
lot of different configurations trying
to consider similarities to what some
standard configurations might look like
couple thousand tokens in a context
window for example to look something
like a gpt2 style model thinking about
bit Cipher embeddings that are 500
dimensional or thousand dimensional to
be something like a gpt2 that's again
pointing towards like the big SL large
category of models that we've
experimented with beyond that we haven't
really touch those scales because our
first objective is not to make big big
language models and train chatbots we
want to know what can we do with a small
model since this is a relatively unique
capability so what does training look
like to the best of um our ability so
far it's kind of hard to see but the
first step is that warm start where you
train the bit Cipher and
you take a couple of splits of data and
you compute that warm start for the self
attention layer and feed forward
layers in this case which is really just
using a 100 million token data set from
the baby language model challenge which
has as an objective
to see what language models can do on a
relatively human scale of data in other
words 100 million tokens is something
that a person might hear in 10 years of
their life
in 10 years of life people become pretty
proficient speakers and can a language
model be trained at that
scale the second stage after the warm
start happens is where the majority of
training time occurs and yet um is also
where training operates the most
quickly at this stage we find that
freezing vectors is important one
because it means that we can train much
quicker so we can have the subsequent
layers optimized beyond their warm
starts very very fast using that Vector
caching the vector comparison caching to
avoid the quadratic costs of self
attention this articulates the
parameters in the middle layers of the
model for you know taking 100 million
tokens making five passes over the data
here um a lot quicker than any of the
other stages and the comparison that
you'd make to this is the training time
once those embedding layers are unfrozen
where everything slows down to the
normal speeds where you have to do all
of your vector comparisons on the Fly
since you can't assume that the same
comparisons will always result in the
same numbers since model parameters
might be
updated this is the best procedure that
we've figured out so far and in order to
make those vectors update we find that
learning rates have to be adjusted
dynamically inside of the network like
normal and that the embedding layers are
really tough to make progress
on and you'll notice here in this
picture that the slowness and the lack
of stability for example in learning the
embedding layer once it had been
prescribed
earlier makes it really hard to train
over the entire data set compared to
five passes for example
in the middle phase when the middle and
upper parameters are being updated still
with back
propagation and the other thing that I
would highlight before leaving this
slide is in Phase One how the warm start
saturates pretty quickly so if you have
100 million tokens you really only need
to apply the warm start to something
like maybe 10 million tokens not that
much more you don't see that much gain
from that much more data
that's not a bad thing um because it
means that we don't have to apply that
process for any longer I mean it would
be great if it gave us all of the
optimization that we could hope for but
it's not something that we could
necessarily expect since it's just an
approximation of where the parameters
are
headed so on the back of an envelope
thinking about how the systems that
these that example was trained on as
compared to other examples that are out
there and thinking about models that are
kind of sort of similar
size we're talking about a 12 GB GPU a
relatively small single
chip specifically when referring to
these training
times okay so that's 12 gab
GPU just working off of eight chips each
having roughly four times the
scale and comparing to this time that it
took to
train something with maybe an additional
order of magnitude although we have
trained models up to around 50 million
parameters to which is getting towards
gpt2
scale we see training times that if we
scaled up to the relatively large
systems that um present us with how much
work we should expect to have to do for
a model that large we can expect to be
able to train much
faster but as mentioned the initial
objective here is not to Simply figure
out um how well we can do something
that's being done well already it's to
figure out what these alternative
strategies are useful for since they
give us access to different regimes of
model scale as
effective so
um as mentioned we've gone to relatively
large amounts of data I wouldn't really
call them big data at this time even
though just a couple of years go a
billion tokens would be a relatively
large amount of
data it's really just a stress test at
this point gives us something like do we
continue to see models getting better as
we continue to give them more data do we
we continue to give them longer context
windows and the answer to both of those
questions is absolutely yes so nothing
is telling us that we can't train bigger
models with these but will those bigger
models be as good as a standard self
attention model I don't know it's a
different self attention parameter
Matrix than what you see in a standard
self attention model you could integrate
the two and in theory that should be
Overkill because you'd have more
parameters and more power through them
and we can see from this work that the
alternative self attention parameters
are reasonably
effective we're getting close to
time so I'll go quick through these
since this is the work that we're
approaching uh right now
and this is the idea that um we're
seeing as a use case for such a model
like this in other words no
pre-training just training on the target
data whatever the data of interaction
are and this example you'll see that
this relatively smaller Precision
language model just needs to predict
whether or not a light should go on or
off you know a lamp that listens with a
microphone and a switch and you can use
that switch to train the
[Music]
lamp so that's the goal here um can
pre-training be eliminated and we want
to anticipate whether or not you're
going to flip the light on or
off that's the task that we're going to
try and
approach or that rather we're currently
approaching there's a few different
processes that integrate into this
approach there has to be a microphone
that's listening to you recording audio
there has to be a transcription
algorithm and we use wave Tove at this
point because there's a very small
version of it that's character-based and
as a result doesn't even require you to
use consistent or it does require to use
consistent language but it doesn't even
require you to use words since it's
strictly
phonetic there has to be and this is the
bread and butter of what's going on here
a process which anticipates what you
want and that process is responsible for
creating good training data so this is a
smart data collection
algorithm that figures out when you flip
the switch is that the target for
something that you just said is that the
transfer learning objectives from text
that was
transcribed that it anticipates you
want following this there's also two
other processes one which operates on a
different uh time cycle and that's
training so always train a model always
be training a
model whenever there's new data is
essentially what that fourth process
says and the last one is operation in
other words if you flip the switch there
has to be a process which operates the
light bulb it always has to be a lamp in
order to be useful it always has to be
able to just be a
switch however that operation process
likewise needs to see a directive from
the anticipator if the language model
predicts that you just said a thing that
means you want there to be light that
operator then needs to receive the
signal from the
anticipator and execute the directive if
the user then though within some time
scale changes the switch back after the
model created a prediction that was bad
the operator is also responsible for
issuing a correction to the anticipator
to correct the training
data what this looks like as a process
is in this diagram
here and you can see um the flow here
from stage one a verbal command maybe
gets recorded transcribed turned into
text and if there's no model that's yet
trained that text is just stored as data
along with any directives given by the
user in the form of a light switch going
on or off
once there's any data the learning
process says okay time to train a
language
model and integrate it with these
targets once a model is done training
it's sent over to the anticipator who is
responsible for using the language
model that small language model then is
now empowered to make predictions every
single time it receives a text
command and those predictions are sent
to the
operator which then does whatever it's
told and the last thing that can happen
step six is if the wrong prediction was
made and the user fixes it by turning
off the light because they didn't want
the light
on that corrects the data that was
transcribed and the next model which is
trained will be able to avoid that
problem and there's some dialing this in
in terms of the time scales that you
want based on the way humans interact
with the light switch so there's a lot
of development that goes into figuring
out the right way to set this
up the data that you collect from a
process like this how do we organize it
this actually is not transfer learning
so I kind of lied there a little bit
this is strictly language
modeling it's a conversation between the
human and the lamp you say something
lamp says here's what you
want and it's just an extending context
window like you'd see with a decoder
only kind of architecture these days a
chatbot kind of thing a human uh
personal assistant human assistant
dialogue and you might also suspect then
that well couldn't you let the lamp talk
yes you could absolutely let it use
other tokens and that is something which
is on the horizon for us in other words
how to determine once the model is
learned enough and knows when you want
to hear it talk and knows what you want
to hear it say which requires other
smart data collection currently in
development and there's three tags here
if you don't see it although what they
really are tokens since they're
integrated within the language models
vocabulary I want the lamp lit I want
the lamp dark or nothing if no switch is
applied during
transcription so what do the models look
like that go into to a
lamp um they're a little bit smaller
than that micro model in terms of having
a long context window the the block
size they still use these other features
like a radius which help them to do well
with only little data those other
context
models and the embedding size
is around 50 or 10 and something and
this is small enough to fit on a
microprocessor on a c GPU of a
microprocessor including training no GPU
whatsoever and the first time we ever
got the interaction right the right time
scales from no data
whatsoever creating this data and 20
minutes of it was enough and you can see
there's loads of misspellings here
because the transcription is not
required to produce known words known
tokens it's strictly character based so
you can say whatever you want to say you
can whistle and as long as wavec thinks
that's tokens it'll figure out what to
transcribe that's enough 20 minutes of
talking to it to have it know pretty
well when you want the light
on this is what the numbers look like
for that prediction and you see lots of
zeros there but that's because there's
no positive instances yet in the data
until you you flip the switch there's
nothing to
predict once there is enough to predict
we see an immediate jump in the model's
ability to figure out whether lamp
should say on off or
nothing and while we trained this first
model for example in 20 minutes on L
potato which is a really really really
small
microprocessor it's incredibly
frustrating to utilize because the
processing time is a couple seconds and
it feels like it's going somewhere even
though the data is entirely localized
there's no Wi-fi there's no internet
connection um it just takes the model on
this tiny chip a minute not really a
minute like couple seconds to flip the
switch on because it has to transcribe
it interpret it issue the directive ask
the operator to operate it and so part
of what we're doing is figuring out at
what scale of microprocessing do the
models that we're developing really make
a good realtime system that a user can
make use of
well
and as you can see the larger the model
in terms of hyper parameters and so
forth the more performant it
gets so um we see these as potentially
useful in Edge scenarios but not just
for operation for training so go to Home
Depot buy a light switch installed in
your house start talking to it
um but this isn't really the stopping
point that we want to get
to
um we want to eventually get to the
point of talk back we want to treat
these as language models that
essentially have a bit of you inside of
them that you can converse
with and that's important to know when
the model is aware of what you want to
hear said in other words it needs to
know what is a good thing to say back to
what you just said the lamp has never
heard a lamp talk before so there are
challenges to figuring out the lamp's
role in
conversation and choosing a lamp though
is arbitrary we don't have to make it be
a light bulb which goes on and off this
could be a controller for anything which
is a binary
switch and you could imagine like others
are looking at right now there's a lot
of opportunities with predicting the
action on your phone that you want to
take which thing you want to push
and with a system like this micro sizing
on to your cell phone for example
assumes better Hardware than what we're
already using but would be entirely
localized including
training but this is also really just
getting to the point of feasibility it's
not getting to the point of a well
optimized system which we're still
developing there are principle different
modifications that we could make to the
self attention layers which include
traditional self attention parameters
that's just one
example then there are updates to the
very naive scheme that we have for bit
Cipher the vectors that we're using to
initialize our
models and a lot of other minutia that
need to be
approached so this isn't really work
that's done it's a work in progress and
in addition to what I just described
where moving towards larger models and
evaluations that compare better to
Modern systems which will eventually
come
online um will most likely participate
in this year's baby language model
challenge although that challenge
assumes you're working with a standard
architecture which is already developed
for all of the evaluative needs so
there's a lot of work to
do but that's really all I have prepared
for you to discuss today in this
conversation I've gone over a lot of
details and if you'd like to talk about
any of these I'm certainly happy to
questions that you might have as well
and if you have access to the slides
there's some links to the different
papers I've
referenced that's all for today and
[Applause]
thanks hey so thanks Jake uh for the
great talk and now we'll have some time
for questions uh so if anybody here has
any questions uh feel free to raise your
hand and ask otherwise we'll go to some
questions on
slido yeah some folks are asking so
we'll be posting the slides um later but
I've also pasted um these references in
the zoom chat as well as Discord in case
anybody uh wants to uh see
them I was wondering in the plots that
you showed for warm warm start versus
cold start does the cold start use the
modified self attention or the standard
self
attention yeah sure um so the question
was in this picture comparing warm
starts to cold
starts um what self attention was used
here none this is strictly a feed
forward experiment where we take a
single layer and all we do is feed
forward with one hot vectors from some
context window
and concatenate them together and the
general property that you'll see is by
concatenating vectors there's very
little for attention to do normally with
a block you're adding the vectors
together and that superposition of the
dimensions smears them and that's why
self attention is needed in order to
weight that superp position so just the
right ones stick out and it's not
muddled if those vectors are instead
concatenated a waiting of those is
really just appealing to the
sensibilities of the Matrix
above when they're superimposed there's
a lot to work on since you're smearing
separate information together when the
information is already
separated there's not that much reting
can
do and in this case there's absolutely
no reting going on and what I've
described to you is really just
something
that's become very clear from a lot of
small scale experiments in between the
models that we've
developed and moving towards self
attention took additional time and we
didn't have a solution for that layer
yet when this work was
done I had a question in regards to so
you're doing this with like bondage
controllers right what um but you're
doing with like oned controllers right
you're doing training with for oned
controllers so like this could be for
like iot devices right could be um and
you talked about how this also could
work for image data
right yeah um have you conducted any
tests with image data like with these
small models for like iot devices or do
you plan for in the
future
so image data work best on not just
feedforward architectures they have for
example convolutional things bits and
pieces that are useful to them and um
that means if we want to apply some kind
of a warm start for for example a
convolutional layer to create a
performant image classifier or something
that's working with images we'd want to
develop an initialization for that layer
too it has weirder activation functions
which means we need to Branch out from
softmax as an activation function but
surprisingly similar convolution is to a
radial model it's really just saying
what's near where I'm trying to create a
feature so I would say yes it seems like
it's something that we could do but
currently it's in the phase of future
work
that it fits in one bullet
here at the
bottom different layer types need formal
derivation for warm starts so if we
wanted to do this kind of a thing with
uh performant architecture we would be
probably uniforming or randomly
initializing some of those parameters
that we don't have warm starts for yet
and as a result we would re receive a
lot of just sort of like noise in where
things are going and if we started to
utilize the activation functions whether
it's even just logistic activation a
logistic activation is not really
fundamentally different than a softmax
Activation so you might say for example
well why can't you just apply that to
logistic function like a two-dimensional
soft Max and the reason is is because if
we treat it like a standard logistic
then each Dimension is independent each
Dimension is trying to predict the same
thing and there's a lot more questions
about how you can get different
information out of different dimensions
so it's a question that's really worth
spending time on in my opinion
separately and it's not the first
question that makes a lot of what we've
developed
practical on one of the slides we had
the dialogue between the user and the uh
I'm wondering does that imply there is a
speech DET Tex system inside the mic
yeah so uh audio goes in and there's a
process here which accepts that audio
and it utilizes a pre-trained wave to
vet that's really just fitting a need
with a pre-train model that's what we're
doing right now um although
transcription is something that we would
like to move into in our future work for
the purposes of training from scratch
because one of the real benefits of a
system like this is that it doesn't come
with any biases from other people's
data aside from the fact that there's a
pre-trained transcription system which
means that it's pre-trained towards
whatever phonetics were within the
language that was there for pre-training
in the wave Toc algorithm so there is
external you know utility here coming
from a pre-trained model but the text
itself and the language model that we're
presenting is only working from what
gets transcribed
I have a followup on my previous
question you you said that the feed
forward worm start is independent of the
choice of self attention does that mean
that the warm start strategy can be used
for any um Network that uses a fe
forward layer not just plms but any llm
or any other network yeah so that's
going back to the war start
solution here and what it says is that
in terms of any layer beneath if you
assume that those layers parameters are
what they are you're not going to update
them and assuming that you know what the
targets for that layer are which for
Middle layers there's some questions to
be
answered then this initialization will
do better than random for softmax out
that's really important at this stage
that there's a soft Max as a part of the
activation if there's not
then you know more map
basically but the point at which it
becomes clear should that whatever type
of prediction scenario in as long as you
have non- negative
features and a soft Max for activation
like in this case with a single layer or
even two soft Max layers whatever that's
doing on mnist you can get a really good
initialization doesn't have to be
linguistic
data this could be mixed data too you
know you could do like a image caption
generation system that has both features
from images and text and warms them up
with the same solution with entirely
different data in two
places could you point out which part of
the process requires the values to be
non- negative
yeah what happens when you put a
negative in a
logarithm not saying you can't but it's
not going to start making probabilities
for you at the other end of the soft box
anytime fast so you have to start with a
different premise
essentially and and that premise is
something that requires more
derivation you'd want to assure if
you're going to use a logarithm anywhere
or assume that inverse that you're able
to um probably modify every parameter
independently instead of whole rows of
parameters okay get to a couple
questions on slido that folks asked um
the the first is what's the difference
in performance between naive assignment
and optimized or omniscient assignment
for packing tokens into bid vectors and
any experimental
results what's the difference in
performance
between naive assignment and optimized
assignment for packing tokens into bid
vectors um the performance differences
are going to
speed the systems which utilize packing
for contexts have at Great length gone
to make sure that information from
different portions of the context that
have nothing to do with each other don't
bleed information if you're going to
pack them together that creates a lot of
logistical challenges in terms of
defining
models and it's still just doing the
regular self attention thing so it's
quadratic so if you have the same length
of context window it's going to be the
same computational cost
however um if you pack all of your small
documents together they don't need the
whole context window worth of quadratic
comparisons and that's why you pack
something in to the empty end I guess it
should be over here from your
perspective but token or document
packing isn't exactly even though it's
well known as a mechanism to make
training much more efficient in other
words you only need fewer batches if
more documents are packed
together it's not something
which is for example entirely accepted
as a published accepted form of
pre-processing so what I would say is
just document packing is not a correct
model of context it is an efficiency but
requires the same level of quadratic
comparison whereas dynamically batching
and izing a block size that is dynamic
preserves the model of context it does
something that is true to the objective
and unwavering in that and it reduces
the complexity for smaller
documents but a direct comparison of the
two is something I've not done because
um it would require having that Oracle
and utilizing those algorithms and where
are they used they're used with insanely
big models which means we would likewise
have to compare two insanely big models
to create the same of expectation that
people have from
packing so that's in the future great
thanks for your detailed response um we
have a question quickly that's um asking
are there any implementations of safu
available that one could experiment with
um well once we publish there will be
but that requires a lot of work on
developing systems for evaluation since
the evaluation systems rely upon
standardized functions within the
architectures that you're all very
familiar with like gpt2 that are easily
taken for granted even though you do
lots of work in training them you have
to do a lot of work in creating those
functions that meet the needs of the
separate prediction tasks and
fine-tuning that evaluations
perform all right great makes sense I
think I think we're pretty much out of
time so uh thanks thanks uh Jake for the
great talk and um thanks for uh coming
to another lecture all of you