okay um well uh welcome back to cs224n
it's welcome back for me to
cs224n um too since I was traveling for
a couple of weeks I hope everything went
smoothly in the meantime um so today I'm
delighted to introduce our first invited
speaker Nathan Lambert um so Nathan um
did his PhD at UC Berkeley so you're
allowed Boo and hiss for that
but um but um since then um he worked
first for a couple of years at hugging
face and now he's working at ai2 the
Allen instit the Allen Institute for
artificial intelligence um in Seattle um
so Nathan um comes from a background in
reinforcement learning like quite a few
other people who are now applying
reinforcement learning to language
models he had an early background
applying reinforcement learning to
robots but it turns out it's more fun to
do it with language models um um no it's
not um okay um but anyway I mean he's
been very influential in both developing
ideas as to how to do posttraining with
rhf and other ideas that come since then
including DPO that he'll definitely
mention in today's talk um and so he's
one of the so best experts on the
posttraining um phase of language model
development which has just proven as
time is passed by that more and more of
the action of the large language model
companies is happening not in the the
initial um pre-training language model
training phase but this subsequent
posttraining phase and Nathan will have
a lot to say about that today thanks a
lot for coming to do this yeah thanks
for the wonderful intro um you can see
my talk is life after DPO which is a
little bit of a unclear title so I
apologize about this but it's trying to
capture like what is the moment that
we're at in alignment and Alignment
research and really DPO is the paper the
story of last year which is this paper
that came out and I'll get to the math
and now a lot more people are interested
in able to do alignment and it's
building on from there so it's like what
what are we going to be interested in
after DPO and a tidbit talking with
Chris that isn't explicitly in my slides
is like what we're trying to close and
the labs like meta and people with the
amount of data that they're using for
this kind of post
training um fine-tuning there's all
these words all defined is so big that
like the amount of data points that meta
bought in llama 2 from one of these
providers is much more data than all of
the data that's been collected on
chatbot arena for mmis so chatbot Arena
has like 800,000 data points that have
been collected and metat 2's paper says
they bought about 1.5 million
comparisons and these are years outdated
and chatbot Arena's data is that's as of
a few weeks ago so you can only imagine
what op AI anthropic Etc are buying at
this scale and this is the kind of
reality that we need to adapt to is like
what is different like we don't have
that type of resource doing research and
what are we going to do so this lecture
is some history on things that lead up
to DPO that I saw that I think are
important to remember and then really
we'll kind of go zero to 100 and talk
about Recent research that we're doing
to try to answer this question and
Define what is happening
so I'll start with a heavily abbreviated
history of language models I won't go
through all of this there's a bunch of
this in the class already this is late
in the lecture I like to talk start with
Claude Channon and then you skip a whole
bunch of stuff where this Auto
regressive loss
function shows a lot of promise and this
was not fast you can see how many years
that it took to build language modeling
as a field here and deep learning is
brewing in the background of one of many
things that went into this
and then you have these years with like
2017 the Transformer paper that you hear
about 2018 with gpt1 Elmo and Bert kind
of these foundational topics in language
processing and how embeddings are
created and then with gpt2 and scaling
laws become this kind of key idea that
people are looking at and tracking and
how these models are improving and then
in 2020 is when people really started to
wake up to how useful these large scale
trained language models were at this
time I was wasn't even a language
modeling person but for a lot of people
in AI this is when the kind of gravity
of the situation was starting to suck
people in and there's a lot of cadence
to these things in 2021 we had the
stochastic parrots paper which before
chat gbt is raising the warnings of what
are actually what are we actually
putting into these models and what are
they learning like are they actually
learning something meaningful from
language or are they repeating the
language that we have and this is a kind
of philosophical debate depending on
where you land on what language is what
these language models are doing today
but it's important that it came out
before chat gbt and it's like these
foundations of debates of what language
models are doing in 20 end of 2022 is
when chat gbt actually came out which
was supposed to be this kind of quiet
launch of a b like a demo from open Ai
and it has since captured the attention
of the world that we have seen and the
simple question is can C chat GPT exist
without rlf I think it's it's important
to acknowledge that so much of this is
from pre-training but at every point of
the line and chat GPT and then a lot of
these popular models since then rhf and
these human related or other fine-tuning
Technologies seem to be necessary but
not sufficient like you need the
pre-training but you also need this kind
of rhf or this post training to really
shift the needle and what the most
important models are at that certain
moment some examples you can list so
many of them where rhf has replied
relied upon I like to look at these
plots from the anthropic constitutional
AI paper where they kind of show this
iterative Improvement of their different
rhf methods it kind of shows of how you
have these multiple model versions that
are evolving over time as you add more
fine-tuning data this is a a dense paper
but one of the most representative
figures of kind of what rhf can do
there's a lot of information in here
that you don't need to follow right now
and then like meta's llama 2 paper is
pretty funny where they're they have
this quote this like reinforcement
learning known for its instability
seemed as some shadowy field for those
in the NLP research Community however
reinforcement learning proved highly
effective particularly given its cost
and time Effectiveness so this is like
this is from the technical report
directly which I find really
entertaining is this is back in the day
when we were like oh we don't know if
rhf is really going to take off this is
July of year 2023 is like in this
building period and it's just directly
from the report and that's aged really
well where people are still using this
today but there's just a lot of
interesting hints in kind of history of
culture of rhf in the releases of these
models where the people these companies
like to talk about it and give us kind
of these cultural details to what's
going
on so I'm going to kind of go through
some definitions and I don't spend too
much time on saying doing rhf 101 and
like exactly what is happening with
these kind of mathematical terms but
it's important to get on the same page
of what some of these things do and
don't mean um there's a lot of
definitions I think some of the
interesting ones that if they don't make
sense right now to come back to is like
what's the difference between
instruction find tuning and supervise
fine tuning I think like instruction
fine tuning is what's become really
popular where it's like you're training
a model to follow instructions and I
have another slide on this after and
supervis fine tuning is like this domain
specific thing and we want to do both of
them I think instruction fine tuning is
more linked to rhf it's about making
these models really useful and really
engaging and kind of easy to work with
and then there's other things like
alignment which is like super vague but
it's in the word it's align it's
training a model to be
mirrored to what a user wants and
there's a lot of things that you can
align to rhf is a mouthful which is one
specific tool for doing alignment where
you have this kind of human feedback
data which is like feedback is a really
loaded word there where there can be
like preferences and learning to rank is
related to actually putting feedback on
preferences there's a lot of little
things I tried to make preference
fine-tuning a phrase at one point but
didn't really double down on it I think
it's a little bit clearer than rhf
especially in the context of DPO but
there's just these lot of spheres that
are overlapping in this kind of post
trining or fine tuning space of models
these days instruction tuning
instruction fine tuning is the kind of
it's still the foundation of a lot of
this this is where things called system
prompts are added where we're like
making the model ready for a specific
style of input um open AI is still kind
of inov innovating on this they have
this model spec document they released a
few weeks ago where they said they're
going to have like a second level system
prompt here which this just adds some
structure to how the models can take in
data so that you can do a lot more of
this fine tuning down the line and how
user data actually gets passed to the
model or how the developer passes
information that the user doesn't
see so what this can often look like is
like stack overlow Reddit data where you
have a a question at the top and then an
answer and this is still I think a lot
of what is happening behind the scenes
there's a lot of data sets of stack
Overflow out there Reddit has these data
Partnerships and this still uses the
auto regressive loss function that we
started with we haven't branched out
into kind of different loss functions
yet but it's still super important a lot
of academic research shows that this is
like all you need in some ways which I I
think is a much more mixed bag but it's
it's the simple method and it's the
right place to start and where we kind
of go is then we go to this rhf
objective which this looks really
familiar to people that are trained in
reinforcement learning I think this is a
little different to from the NLP loss
function um on the left side is like the
standard reinforcement learning
objective which is you're learning a
policy pi to maximize some reward which
is a function of something depending how
you set of the problem and then on the
right side is going to be this kind of
KL constraint this um it's a distance so
that the policy doesn't change too much
it's related to this whole idea of over
optimization that I don't go into too
much of this talk um but the key ideas
is that we want to optimize a reward but
not over optimize it and the primary
questions when doing our LF is like how
do we Implement a reward function like
what is our reward actually going to be
and then how do we optimize it you see
this abstracted later as like we train a
specific reward model and then we have
specific policy updates and DPO direct
preference optimization handles this a
little bit differently so to get before
we get there it's like the actual
preference model that people use for rlf
is well I find this interesting like
it's from this Bradley teror Terry model
which is from economics in like the
1950s which is essentially a probability
distribution over a pairwise choice and
what ends up happening for various
technical reasons is that if we train a
preference model it needs to Output a
scalar value and by some coincidence
that I think is still very convenient
they just take the output of this
learned probability distribution as a
reward they say that okay our reward is
going to be proportional to this
probability and it's going to work and
it ends up doing so but that's like even
a big leap to accept that it's like we
have this par wise preference
probability that's saying the
probability that one answer is chosen
over another and then you have to kind
of this mental crazy step of saying we
just pass in one number or one piece of
text and we're getting the probability
that that one piece of text is chosen
over any arbitrary other one so there's
a lot of like assumptions that make this
there's like kind of deep Concepts in
here but what we're getting is a model
that's giving us the score
out and the kind of question is if we
why do we have to do this and like what
if we can just take our original
objective and use gradient Ascent on
this equation Ascent because it's a
maximum and this is really what DPO does
I'm blurring through a ton of math it's
a great paper to learn a lot of this
math of language modeling where you
learn how these probabilities of
different pieces of text are handled by
the model and how it's ends up being a
lot of these like log probability ratios
and seeing how the prompt and the
completion are handled differently it's
worth digging into and understanding the
derivation but the core idea is like why
can't we just do gradient descent or
gradient Ascent to solve rhf
optimization and this is like it becomes
be incredibly simple so if you look at
the code on the right is the um
reference code from the original
implementation it's extremely simple to
implement and it has this characteristic
where if you work with something like
Transformers before it's pretty easy to
write a loss function that uses DPO
rather than building an entire
infrastructure stack to start with when
you do something like a PO and this full
rhf stuff that open AI does you normally
need almost entire new infrastructure
stack but you can get started with DPO
in a much much simpler way and there's
some kind of characteristics that I'll
get to later which is DPO still has a
reward model which is really important
to the math actually checking out
whereas you're using your original
language model as a different type of
reward model but that quickly takes us
down a whole bunch of derivations that
is probably at least not the lecture
that I think is as fun to give and the
key thing is which is why this lecture
is called what it is is that the first
two points mean we'll see more DPO
models than anything else like DPO is
where everyone will start with if they
want to do alignment research and it's
for good reason like it is the right
place to start if you're thinking about
doing this it scales more easily on
compute it's easier to debug it's even
easier to learn so like it's it's not
really worth second guessing that and it
is a good place to
start but it also leads into these
ridiculous conversations online where
everyone is trying to figure out like is
DPO better than other RL methods pop
which is this older popular deep RL
algorithm which John scholman wrote
reinforce which is a slightly different
parameterization of policy gradient
they're very similar and DPO ends up
being much simp like it's just simpler
to work with so there's this
meme where it's like if you you just do
gradient descent it'll work in reality
they're pretty they're they're different
loss functions and they're doing very
different things but you can get similar
results with both of them which is why
if something is much easier to do you
should just start with it and I come
back to this much later in the talk
which is like what is fundamentally
different about these RL algorithms and
whe how your data is processed and where
the signals actually come from but for
now it's like we don't need to say one
versus the other we can do both and they
are different
so that's kind of the quick one-on-one
of what the core ideas are I'm going to
kind of take a path to where we how we
actually got to training models with DPO
because I think this slide was from a
different talk where this subsection is
reduced from but DPO really came out
months before we started getting popular
models trained with it so it's like how
did we actually get to the point where
the community was training models with
DPO which is much more recently than the
paper was actually released
and this comes all the way back to these
first instruction tuned models that you
saw so the alpaca the vuna koala Dolly
of the world all in April of 2023 and
these are all built on kind of similar
things and slight iterations so there's
kind of figuring out how to use
synthetic data building on this first
llama release there's some other things
that I'll talk about but this is where
we started they're all using instruction
tuning most of them use synthetic data
and what vuna actually did was they used
this thing called share GPT which was
the first time that people working in
kind of this academic alignment space
had access to data that was from humans
it ended up being a bit of a legal gray
area because it was logging data that
people used in a Google Chrome extension
called share gbt to like make it so chat
gbt had a share button but this data was
really important to things like vuna and
a lot of the other models that came down
the line and is still used in models
today as like one subset of the training
data set so just having access to these
human prompts was unlocked a lot of
potential back in the day and is still
something that were seeing thankfully
now we're starting to get data sets like
this that were collected in more
permissive ways like this kind of lmis
data has prompts that are collected and
with consent and wild chat which was a
project from ai2 which essentially gave
people free access to chat gbt and
exchange for their
data the thing that came after Shar GPT
was the realization that we need more
human data and this open Assistant
project is one that um we honestly need
more of it's It's shows how hard it is
to create human data that we haven't
seen more things like this this was run
by a few people in a Discord Community
working extremely long hours to generate
prompts responses and preference pairs
to kind of common requests the language
models and this was from April of 2023
and we haven't seen anything like it tra
gbt or lmc's data is similar but there's
not the same level of controls and
voting and ranking that they went into
this open Assistant data and it again is
a data set that we're still training
models with and many people still train
models who I think come up time and time
again so it's just like these one or two
influential data sets from over a year
ago are still what are used to trade
models so you'll you'll get the theme as
I keep going there's actually rhf models
trained in April of 2023 as well um this
was from Carper AI that was doing a lot
of work in the space they've kind of
Taken they've Fallen back a bit in
recent times but there were people that
were doing the similar methods to what
I'm going to talk about at the end of
the talk that kind of knowledge and
infrastructure was not translated into
things that were easy to use so there's
also this vein of like even if things
are open it doesn't mean that it's going
to immediately catch on and be useful
you have to have the resources the data
and your codebase setup in a way that
people can build on it which is what DPO
did really well this like RF model from
Carper was successful it was better than
the vicuna model but no one really built
on it right away which I always find
confusing then kind of later in the year
another key thing for this open
alignment was the Llama 2 backlash where
the Llama 2 was asked to kill a Linux
process it it would refuse and this kind
of bred a whole series of models which
are kind of called we are still referred
to as uncensored which I don't think is
the best name CU I don't think there was
ever actually any censoring to the model
wasn't intentional censorship but the
goal is to make models that don't refuse
any request which is useful as a
research artifact which is like what do
you get out of a model if it answers
every question like what are the limits
in that regard there are other ways to
use that which are up to you but like
what ended up happening is a lot of
these like um shared gbt data sets
because they're from chat gbt there's
data that says oh as a language model I
shouldn't answer that so people started
filtering all of that out and there you
still see a lot of people releasing
these like uncensored models today as a
popular area of
development I think that we should
understand what people need when doing
research and researching a model that
doesn't refuse is reasonable but if
you're to deploy a model for free use to
users you should consider whether or not
everything should be answered so it's
like as a researcher how your artifacts
are used kind of depend on the work that
you're actually going to be
doing then in the alignments there's
this long series I'm almost done with
the end lens but there's this long
series of models that are really
interesting to people like me that never
really broke through the narrative where
they're saying their things like we used
rhf where the first model to beat gb4 on
alpaca Val and these other V tools
they're scaling things up but they don't
always have papers they don't always
have code bases and it's like things are
happening around I just like it's not
just like the hugging face of the world
there's a lot of different organizations
in the US and elsewhere where that we're
aligning models and getting similar
numbers or beating these kind of
mainstream tech companies and these
places that you look for models to these
so these are all in the summer of
2023 and this is kind of all this like
these I bring these up because this
comes before like the first big splash
of DPO so this Zephyr model was really
the first model that I remember Making a
Splash with DPO and this is when it took
until this time which was in September
after the May release of the paper for
people to really be like o DPO is the
real deal like it took four months and
now like the paper has best paper
everyone uses it there's tons of
derivations but in industry and people
trying to train models there was a lot
of skepticism until this moment so this
is like a classic academic story of
needing to wait a bit until your um
until your work is Vindicated in some
ways but the two crucial things here was
new data set the ultra feedback data set
which is a data set of um synthetically
generated text labeled by gp4 so it's
again this kind of new ways of making
data where it's a preference data set um
we didn't make it it was made by um open
BMB I think they're based in China and
should know more and then we also just
had to do a lot of experiments to make
it work there's a weird really low
learning rate that was needed to make
this kind of chat model work with DPO
which is like 5e minus 7 if you're
really plugged into AI you'll know that
like 3 e minus 4 is like the lore of the
best learning rate so it's many of
magnitude lower so that's kind of what
it took to get this to work we probably
could have done it months earlier if we
just did more hyperparameter sweet but
like this is the random happen stance of
the stories that people now like
backcast as being like this is the super
important bottle it's just it's it's
somewhat random and then at the same
time I was switching jobs to the Allen
Institute and they were already working
on this project which is trying to do a
systematic study of instruction tuning
data along with some of this preference
tuning recipes that were coming out
because once this Zephyr model came out
there's always Skeptics of like oh doing
it at 7B is easy like that's a small
model so it's like oh is it going to
actually scale to the real deal to
bigger models to be what like Chad gbt
does so it was like okay we have some
more compute and we tried it on this 70
billion parameter scale and we showed
similar gains we all we did was use the
same Ultra feedback recipe the low
learning rate and it largely worked so
this is within two months and then this
is when in since then is when there's
tons of new DPO models anyone all these
startups that are releasing their own
models will release an instruct version
that is a DPO thing and that kind of
continued for 6 months I think just
today I'm starting to see less DPO
models which is interesting I've been
keep tracking keeping track of them for
another evaluation project and it has
finally kind of slowed down a little bit
I don't know if that's alignment at
large but there is so many I I I should
add a slide that's like a list of the
ridiculous amount of DPO models after
them after these two but this is really
when the floodgates kind of started and
when we're like okay DPO really
works so this is kind of why I say like
what comes next it's like we could
retrain models on data sets that we have
we don't have that many data sets but it
kind of feels like we're fishing in the
dark like Zephyr was built on the
success of needing the low learning rate
this Tulu 2 model is actually trained on
tpus because we have the Google tensor
research Cloud so we have bigger tpus to
train these models and it's like how do
we do this more systematically and
that's kind of where most of what I talk
about today on the technical matter is
the recent research that we've been
doing to just kind of make sense of this
and answer the fundamental questions of
like what do we need to change about DPO
is po better and so
on so this is kind of the the the
reality that I back go back and forth in
between which is we don't really have
the human data to do rhf like industry
but it is getting much easier to do
alignment research so you can kind of
choose your narrative I think sometimes
because I'm so close to Industry and
hear about people have I'm like too
often on this side but there is a lot of
opportunity to do things it feels
crowded but being crowded at this point
when there's so much investment is just
because you're in the right area and
most people in this room aren't trying
to be professors so if you get scooped
it's it's okay but um it's it's I find
it very fun and so like how do we
actually understand what we're doing
with alignment and can we improve on
these models like we have to 2 it has a
number because we want to keep releasing
more models so it's like how do we get
better evaluating what we're doing to
try to understand this process and then
how do we train better models so these
are the sort of things that I'm up to I
have a few examples of things I've been
working on I built an evaluation tool
for reward models I'll talk more about
reward models to start here and we need
better evaluation because when you're
training models you need to be able to
do kind of what I call like local
evaluation you need to be able to get a
number that tells you if your training
technique is
improving the the end result you can't
wait until chatbot Arena evaluates your
model because that takes you about a
month to get your numbers back you need
to be able to run something at your desk
that gives you signal on if you're
actually doing a good job and we're
still pretty behind on those evaluation
tools and they're there are more coming
which is promising and then given dp's
Simplicity can we actually improve on
that and can we catch on to some of the
industry rumors that they've let it
drift
aside so so reward bench is this project
that I started because there are no
evaluation tools for reward models my
motivation was mostly for transparency
given how much industry says reward
models are what you need to focus on
they're really important for getting
good models out the door and it's like
what does that mean like what is like
what does it mean for a reward model to
be good if we look at this kind of
feedback diagram which is the one kind
of homage to the RL background just
feedback loops um is like a word model
is in this casee the agent is your
actual language model Pi is the policy
the training data is prompts that you
get so in this kind of um rhf framework
you have this feedback loop where the
policy generates something a which is
the action which is the completion it
goes to the reward model which then
scores it but you kind of on the side
are looking at all these evaluation
tools and it's like none of these
evaluation tools are giving us internal
insight into what's happening in this
feedback loop it seems kind of external
to what we are doing when we're training
these models so we really wanted to zoom
in on this reward model and reward
models are trained in a kind a another
kind of weird way the many quirks of rhf
so in order to train a reward model you
need to collect this pawise preference
data if you're kind of using chat 2bt a
lot you'll sometimes see it give you two
answers and ask you which one is better
this data is literally what is used to
train a reward model it's a a prompt and
then two completions a chosen completion
and a rejected completion but in order
to train these models you have to pass
both of them in at the same time so you
pass both of them in at the same time
and it gives you two scalar values you
use a language model that outputs a
scaler just by some modifications of the
last layers rather than outputting text
and then this L function I'll show you
on the next slide is essentially why you
need to you need to use this batch mode
idea which is you pass multiple things
at once and you get multiple numbers out
so this L function is ESS
here this R is the output directly from
the reward model for the rejected
completion and the chosen completion so
you're trying to separate the distance
between them and then automatic
differentiation kind of updates the
parameters so that this distance is
bigger so you can't just kind of do
supervised learning directly on one
thing to say for the reward model there
are alignment methods researching that
now but it's really built on this idea
of separating two things and creating a
margin in the prep references to kind of
learn the decision boundary there's a
lot of really specific details in
Industry such as these models are only
trained for one Epoch they get really
low accuracy scores when you compare
them to other kind of train test set
things in machine learning and there's
some additional tweaks that people do
you can do ensem ensembles lamud did
this weird margin loss but none of it
really trans is transformative and how
these models are trained they're in this
weird place where you can only get about
70% agreement with your annot
it's it's kind of the sort of thing of
is the noise part of the signal or is it
a bug so like in preferences it could
make sense that it's a signal because
not everyone's preferences here are the
same so not getting full of agreement be
like this system might be working we
don't want chpt to be fully
narrow-minded all the
time and this kind of reads to the thing
of like how do we actually evaluate
these reward models that I was talking
about I hear all the time that reward
models are crucial to rhf but um how do
we know exactly what types of the final
policy they're improving should we
include safety in these reward models
how does scaling laws impact reward
models there's kind of basic machine
learning questions it's like can we
evaluate these what should we think
about so what we kind of what we did is
we collected a bunch of prompts and then
we manually created Chosen and rejected
answers for each prompt and then we can
see whether or not the reward model
agrees with our human created data and
call that like a win or loss in an
accurate point of view it's really
direct we're just doing inference on
existing models and we're going to see
whether or not they agree with human
data and this is a slide if you want to
go into the academic side of things this
was built on a lot of existing
evaluation tools that were out there
you'll see some common names alpaca Val
Mt Ben are things that you've heard
about EXs test was on the slide when I
mentioned llama 2 being um overly safe
and there's some other things that are
really good but you might not heard
about like um this llm bar data set from
Princeton is a bunch of trick questions
that I'll have an example on later and
some kind of normal names from anthropic
and open AI in here as well so there's a
lot of different things that we're
testing with this data set and then
we're trying to get the full picture of
like what is going on with these
models we released this in March of 24
and you can see a key in the bottom
where these kind of um red circles with
the arrow in them are DPO models which
you can use as a reward model
and then um this kind of these dice
which look like gray squares when you
zoom out are what I described in this
kind of um classifier type of training
and you can see that there's reasonable
scores The Benchmark isn't
saturated bunch of open models some
names that you've seen before like the
Tulu models and the Zephyr models are on
here kind of normal stuff we like this
is what we expected it's not too
saturated but if you look here I'll show
you where this model has moved in a few
months so today we have a lot more
models and there's a lot more
information here so I get to tell you
about more interesting things which is
like how open AIS and coheres models do
on this which is like I mentioned
wanting to do this for transparency but
we also add new type so this is where
the fifth model ended up so in two
months the model that was fifth on your
leaderboard is now 31st so we're trying
we're getting the saturation from people
doing research in the area to actually
have places to compare their
models and but we also have models from
some closed labs
and I'll kind of get into the details
here so like some of these are labeled
as um are different types of models with
is llm as a judge um llm as a judge is
the idea if you can ask a language model
which answer is better this is kind of
how things like alpaca Val and Mt bench
are built but you can also use that as a
reward model I told you that I have
prompts and then Chosen and rejected I
could just ask chat gbt which one is
better and see what it does and this is
what we added in as a Baseline and this
ends up being really interesting because
GPT 4 and gbt 40 are not actually as
good in this closed domain as a reward
model that coher is training so we don't
have full information because we don't
have Open the Eyes reward models but we
can use their models to compare so we
have a lot of different information
going into one system about how language
models and different parts of the
alignment process choose different
categories so I'll kind of and kind of
go back and you can see like this Co
here is across two different months
theirs has improved a lot and then these
kind of earlier DPO models that we saw
higher up on the leaderboard have been
shifting down by more people training
reward models to begin
with and the specific category that I'll
Focus most on is this kind of chat hard
thing um if you think about evaluation a
lot it's actually surprisingly common as
a topic covered in kind of tech coverage
is how evaluation is saturating this is
the one feature of our Benchmark that
hasn't fully saturated and it's really
important to kind of having some sort of
longevity to The Benchmark and I'll talk
more about this kind of as we go from
here so I mentioned this data set and
it's interesting to understand if you
could actually do this problem so what
we have is a prompt a Chosen and a
rejected and the prompt is give an
example of a metaphor that uses the
following object stars and then the
Chosen and rejected are two similar
metaphors but one of the like you can
you can see if you read these what the
differences
are I'm just pausing for the people that
are still that are paying attention to
reading these but essentially what
happens is that the chosen one is about
the sky and the rejected is about the
moon or yeah so the twinkling diamonds
in the sky see I haven't messed it up
reading the slide but it asks for stars
and it's about this kind of metaphor of
stars where the rejected is about the
moon which is also in the sky at night
and this data set is a whole bunch of
things like this where what they do to
create this is they either manually or
by chat GPT ask the or ask to rephrase a
prompt and then you create a new
generation from it so you can kind of
get these rejected Generations that are
just off topic and it makes sense for
something that would be really hard for
language models because they have this
association between the stars and the
moon but we want our language models to
be able to answer questions like this
and this is the type of thing where our
reward model Benchmark which is
something that is training language
models has the best correlation
as something that is hard so this is
promising there's this is the sort of
thing that you if you're in research is
interesting so it's really in the weeds
but it shows that we still have things
to learn about these models and there
are things that we can't do yet but
another interesting pattern in safety I
mentioned this kind of um uncensored
models and in safety we see all the
patterns we would expect the breakdown
at the top of this table refusals is
things that we want the language mod
refuse and then this excess T Test data
set can be split into something that we
want models to refuse and we want models
to respond and you can kind of see that
there's multiple categories of either
DPO models or reward models where the
model that handles safety really well
refuses things like asking for advice on
causing harm and responds to something
that is borderline but there's actually
a lot of models out there that just
refuse everything so that'll tank your
score on things that that response um to
everything which is kind of the safe bet
we were seeing a lot of like tech
companies release models like this which
it just feels like you just it doesn't
feel right when you talk to them but
there's also the models that just
respond to everything it's like not my
job to gate whether or not I should it's
not like not the language models job to
gate the question is the philosophy
there which is something that we hear a
lot about in the discourse of alignment
but to see it in these reward models and
DPO models when directly probing them at
the without asking them to generate text
is nice to be to confirm a lot of
suspicions that we have so this is back
to some of the DPO math which is again
good to know so if you are to go into
the DPO paper you'll see equation three
here which is the reward that is defined
in order to make the math actually work
and this is very different than just
outputting a scaler it ends up being a
ratio of the probability of the policy
relative to the original policy during
training which is called the reference
model and this is an imp it's like it's
a very complicated mathematical
representation so if you actually take a
piece of text and pass it through a DPO
model the reward will be something like
minus 200 or something because it's a
bunch of log probabilities probabilities
are between 0 to one you take the log
you get negative numbers and you sum all
of these up so you got a big negative
number and that intuitively is like the
score of that these models are providing
which is very different than the other
type of reward models that I talked
about training earlier and if you have
two prompts with a Chosen and a rejected
equation 4 is the math that you actually
need to do to um decide whether or not
one of the answers was better you're
kind of comparing these ratios of
probabilities from two different models
with respect to this reference model
which was the starting point of training
and the question is when people release
a DPO model they normally release a
model and they don't release all the
intermediate checkpoints so this
reference model would be an intermediate
checkpoint and the training process so
the question is like can you do this can
you use it as a reward model if you
don't have access to all the information
and the short answer is no which is all
the scores on our Benchmark plummet
across all the DPO models that we have
which makes sense because this extra
model is a regular regularizer in the
probabilities or it it's in the actual
reward equation if you go back a few
slides like it's in the equation so if
we what we do is we get rid of this and
we stop normalizing equation 4 and we
just see if it works and it doesn't but
this is important because DPO is
training a reward model but if we don't
always have access to it we just we just
can't learn from it we can't use that in
another system as clearly so it's just a
lot to ask for when getting people to
release
models and this is a interesting slide
showing coheres kind of progress on
reward models in just a few months they
released something that was clearly
state-of-the-art on our Benchmark a
alignment lab um they this kind of RL
rhf flow work release something in May
and then just a few days later coher
sent another number of those like here's
our new model it's still better than
everyone else so it's nice to kind of
have this academic industry intersection
but it's very rare and takes a lot of
work in terms of networking and building
relationships but we're trying to do it
at least in these small niches where the
companies are willing to
share reward bench 2 is going to need to
just mostly make everything harder and
make everything more human and kind of
the last point is what I'm going to
trans into next is like everything I've
told you about is about part of this rhf
pipeline but I haven't told you how it
is impacting the final model that you
use at the end of the day which is very
rightful criticism which is like if
you're evaluating part of the alignment
pipeline you should be telling me
whether or not the final model is
actually useful so this is kind of where
I talk about our journey into trying to
train um po models so we're trying to
fine tune a good model we spent a lot of
time on DPO with this tul2 work and we
wanted to know if we could do better by
switching to PO so this is a lot of um
it's not yet published work but it's
going to be out soon so the numbers
aren't entirely final but we're just
trying to
disentangle what the difference between
DPO and PO is at a very empirical level
so um we're trying to answer if it's
better or not so what we're going to do
is kind of walk through a series of
design decisions and see how it affects
the suite of evaluations we're starting
with this llama 2 13B model and that has
already been instruction tuned the
difference between the blue and the red
is the gains from instruction tuning for
these kind of um reasoning coding chat
tasks instruction tuning does the
biggest Delta that you'll see among all
these slides instruction tuning kind of
puts the model on the map as being
useful and it is easy to see gains at
the beginning and then it's harder and
harder for us to really keep improving
these models so we start with is we add
this anthropic um helpful harmless rhf
data with DPO and you can see that there
is a small bump across all the metrics
that we did this data set is known as
being particularly noisy among
researchers in the area but it is kind
of the starting point when you're doing
research on alignment it's been around
for a few years it's big it's multi-turn
it's it's but it's known to be noisy and
it still gives Improvement and then what
you do is if we switch to this data that
was used for both Zephyr and 2 through2
officially this Ultra feedback data um
we get an even bigger bump so this is
just kind of showing the difference that
changing only the data can give you in a
DPO recipe it's normally increases of
kind of like 0 to 2% and in the research
sphere of trying to ship a model that's
a big
deal so this is kind of where we Triad
it into new territory grad students
worked really hard and implemented Po
and Jacks in addition to what they
already had and we were like okay what
happens when we add Po and require
reliably across m multiple experiments
it's this is one example with the 13
billion parameters po just happens to do
a little bit better it's like like 1%
better and we try to change a lot of
things and the changing things is where
things are get a bit Messier so we've
heard from industry that using a bigger
reward model can be really helpful to
getting a better policy model
essentially these bigger reward models
will be better at Nuance they should
give more label better scores which are
used as Rewards they should just kind of
make this process a little bit more
stable if we have the compute for it we
see that it does improve some things but
it doesn't actually make the model
overall much better it's kind of
flatlined with like pretty similar data
and then just at making the reward model
bigger which is a little bit surprising
to us and we Al this is like this is the
most this is the most realistic few
slides of the talk but it's like we did
this thing where we took the we even
were trying to see if our reward model
training was bad as we scaled it up so
we used reward bench on the right which
I had told you about earlier which it's
not clearly correlated whether or not
these two 13B models or 70b are better
we also did this best event sampling
idea which is if you generate a bunch of
completions from the language model you
can rank them by your reward model and
then re-evaluate on the top to rank
completions that shows that our reward
models are better at the bigger scale
but we couldn't get this to really click
into a like a downstream model in a p
notion of the world um we even tried
adding more prompts to rhf we added more
code and reasoning prompts because
that's something that open AI talks
about a lot it's like and we want to
improve our models on um it doesn't
really shift the needle on this kind of
cohesive average over many tasks in the
paper what you'll see when it's out is
it shows that we added prompts really
similar to two math and code evaluations
and those specific evaluations got a bit
better but adding the full noise into
the fact that some other valuations
might go down makes it this just like
this process is really hard to
disentangle and this is why it's like
we're getting the 0 to 2% Improvement
out of Po but DPO doesn't have this this
sort of mess so what we ended up getting
to is like there's always one more thing
for us to oblate when you're trading
these models with po the sort of things
like different regularization we're
learning a value function in RL
different warmup different size par
like there's just so many knobs to turn
in Po and it was reliably getting us a
pretty good model but it's like we're
staring into the abyss trying to improve
this right now in the next few months
and the bottleneck at in terms of the
actual technical side is that PO
generates new responses from the model
as it trains to kind of refresh the data
and that is by far in a way the biggest
bottle neck when you're actually
training these models is it's just way
slower than
DPO so all these resources for po things
are somewhat available to academics the
Google tensel research Cloud I think is
pretty available the grad students I
work with seem to sign up um the code
base is open so if you're interested in
a grad student and you're trying to do
po alignment and have access to tpus
please get in touch it's it's a very fun
can of worms but kind of as a summary
like this is the many different DPO data
sets that we tried this is almost all of
the well-received data sets that are out
there in the open and they all look at
like the factuality column like some of
these things just don't matter at all
when you're aligning these models so
like we need to get new data sets that
are really adding different capabilities
to these models and something that
matches these kind of ultra feedback
numbers at the bottom and I don't I
don't like I'm surprised whenever I look
at this but this is where we are at and
we need to try to keep building data
sets and keep adding freshness to this
system Ultra feedback at this point is
maybe 6 months old or so I don't know
the exact age but in terms of people
training models that that feels old to
people to things that are happening um
and these are the actual sort of numbers
that you get when you compare DPO versus
Po this is all with this 13 billion
parameter again we changed the data set
and every one of these poo comes out a
little bit better on average and this is
a few grad students and people like me
this is not a big team in Industry doing
this like we're scraping by and I don't
know if it's worth the effort if I see
why open AI uses this because we able to
get a bit more signal out of it but it's
a ton of effort to get a bit better um
signal out and I'll kind of transition
into a bit more of a like open-ended
discussion of this and then we'll have
questions but it's like what about PO is
actually special like this generation
and this online nature and like can we
just change DPO to be like this or like
where are the new things going to go and
I had the pleasure of advising one
project that was related to this but
this is much much more General so it's
like what is special about online data
there's multiple ways that you can get
new data into your
rlf process and then there's also this
related question in reinforcement
learning literature which is like on
versus off policy which is a technical
distinction that often gets looped in
with these discussions of DPO versus Po
they're actually related but the
reinforcement learning discussions have
a very much more like definitional
flavor to them while in this alignment
space we're more focused on if we need
to get fresh data in and how we need to
label our data for language models so
I'd make this distinction between these
two things which is freshly generated
data from the policy if you zoom into a
data set like Ultra feedback it has
Generations from all sorts of models
from alpaca Von kuna GPT 3.5 GPT 4 llama
like there's Generations from all sorts
of models in this data set we are using
so when we train these Zephyr these 2u
models we're incorporating information
from a lot of different models down into
our one policy whereas what PPO is doing
is only generating data from your
existing model and kind of changing this
distribution over time so like that is a
very different idea of where the signal
is coming from from the models and then
the second thing is whether or not
refreshing the data labels over time if
I have human labelers comparing Chosen
and rejected that's one data point but I
can also later on take this reward model
that I trained and generate a Chosen and
rejected and change the label so these
kind of two things of like what the
actual text is and when the chosen
rejected label was given are what people
mean when they're talking about like is
something special about online in rhf
and it's much Clear it's clear to see
that PO does it very differently than
DPO but we're not restricted to
this in the last few weeks I have the
dates all in here so um April April in
May of 2024 there started to be a lot of
papers on this about DPO po online
offline and they really kind of say
similar things which is that online is
important and these papers on this slide
they show these kind of more theoretical
and closed form experiments on like what
is special about online data and what
performance drops if you use this kind
of offline data it's good to dig into
these but it's this is why I say it's
like nice to do research now because if
you have an idea a lot of times people
have like three papers that confirm the
notion that you have it's a lot easier
to be confident in things if three
independent institutions say something
similar at the same time there's a lot
of methods coming out where people are
trying to modify DPO to actually use
this kind of online notion I think
self-rewarding language models for meta
was the first really popular one where
they just had they asked the DPO model
hey which of these answers is better in
between each iteration so they did this
like llm as a judge to relabel their own
data and then they did multiple
iterations of DPO and the model had
really strong stores there's now ideas
like not using all of your data at once
so you can kind of do batches of DPO and
update your data the paper that I was on
with this discriminator guided DPO which
I'll talk about in a second is using
reward models plus this DPO training
objective there's just a lot of things
that we can change and I think the
community again is in this expansion
phase where I even get messages from
people are like oh my paper was really
similar to this other paper they that we
did it first they didn't site us and I'm
like this is kind of the point but it's
hard it's like it's it's going to be
like this for a little bit longer and
then hopefully in the end of the year in
a few years we're going to be like okay
this is clearly what we need to do on
the method side of thing so this is one
example d2p discriminator guided DPO
which I'm is an advisor to which is a
undergrad researcher and the idea is
comparing these three different things
so like a is the standard DPO you have a
data set you apply the loss function on
it B is what we call some sort of online
preference optimization which is where
you can repeatedly label your data with
a uh reward model it just kind of like
the self-reward paper that I mentioned
which is you can read shuffle your
preference data based on a reward model
and that kind of adds some notion of
online to your data and then the third
thing is like what if we're relabeling
data and we're retraining our reward
model over time so we're just really
trying to keep our um kind of what our
policy is doing related to our reward
model and keep everything really updated
in real time so that it's all it's all
lined up and this is wondering how much
of a gain do you have by retraining the
reward model over time in a DPO
framework
and part of why I like this paper is
there's things like closed form tasks so
the biggest question that I get for
alignment is like how do we actually
evaluate it like what tasks is it good
for there's a whole philosophical
discussion where I think information
transformation is a valuable task
writers tell the same stories in
different ways but the best told story
is the one that resonates with people
that has value and but at the other time
we're academics and we need to be able
to measure things so this paper has
things like your reward is counting the
number of nouns in a sentence and then
you're using these alignment methods to
increase the number of nouns in the
outputed sentences from the model so you
can measure that a lot better because we
have classifiers which know our nouns
and you can see on this left figure is
that just by retraining this reward
Model A few times and it converges
better than if you were just to relabel
your preference data it's a mouthful but
it's just like keeping your model your
training process a little bit more
online can improve a performance and on
the right is a more standard open-ended
evaluation task where we're asking a
language model like chbt which answer is
better and that has all sorts of
problems but we can show similar results
I think the big takeaway is really like
these few slides which is the the the
literature is moving we have studies
that show that online is better and
people are coming up with really cool
clever ways to actually use online data
so I would I combined with new data sets
this is kind of this the like deep of
this year is like online methods and how
they
work so this kind of goes back to what
industry is doing and I showed this
figure earlier on the left with Claude
where you can see the little points
along the lines and these are these
different iterations we don't know
exactly what they're doing but it seems
a little bit different where the dots on
these figures are new data sets from
humans rather than this kind of redo a
reward model relabel your data this is
what happens when you have access to
different type of scale the Llama 2
paper makes this much clearer they say
they work with an annotator they get
batches of data when they're generating
this new batch of data the previous
models checkpoint was used for
Generations they do this many times and
you can kind of see that they're
collecting new human data new human data
new human data and each time they
generate human data it is trained for a
new model they're doing a lot of
training updates and they're kind of
building on each other and this kind of
leads into the last section that I'll
talk about in the conclusion
is like what did meta do with llama 3
this is one of the most funny blog post
sentences it's like the ridiculous
things that they give us and then we
parse the tea leaves um they say in the
blog post is that our approach to post
training is a combination of supervised
fine tuning rejection sampling proximal
policy optimization Po and direct
preference optimization so it's like the
people ask me like what the heck did
they do it I mean I kind of agree but it
really goes back to this slide in my
mind which is that
they're getting new data and then
they're training a new model over time
so what I think is happening at each one
of these points they you they tried a
few methods and they chose the training
method that worked best it's really it's
practical meta is a really practical
organization especially in the Gen org
right now and that just makes sense it's
like at different points in the model
your model has different capabilities
and it's ready to be trained in
different ways rejection sampling which
I didn't cover here is the simplest
Training Method you take a reward model
you rank some supervised fine tuning
outputs and then you use this autor
regressive loss function again and then
from there DPO is much simpler to PO but
it might not be give you the highest end
performance and then as your model
really starts kicking into gear or you
have more time to train this model once
all of your data is collected and you're
not on a weekly time crunch um you can
experiment with all the little knobs of
Po and you can really try to get the
best model out at the end of the day
it's just hopefully they release a
technical report that confirms some of
my hypothesis but I think this is
normally what people are interested in
when somebody from industry comes up to
give a lecture and it's it's I wish we
had more details on what industry was
doing but in terms of current directions
that I'm most interested in rhf I talked
about data a lot we are very
bottlenecked on data even as academics
with very limited compute we literally
try every data set that is available
like that's not like we don't have a lot
of compute but we need to keep
innovating there we're going to see more
DPO methods it's it's here to say
there's a ton I didn't cover here things
like removing the reference model
changing the loss function slightly um
not using pair wise preferences but
single wise preferences it's a lot going
on there we should use more model sizes
in 7 and 13 billion parameters or in
llama's case like 7 and 70 billion
parameters particularly scaling down is
very useful it's a place where Academia
can still play there's kind of less of a
weird marketing Dynamic where all the
companies are racing to go bigger for
certain um strategic reasons but this is
something that's accessible to many
people aligning small models it's hard
to get signal out of them because the
models show more or less random scores
on many benchmarks that people care
about or really low scores so even just
kind of breaking through in that domain
would be really impactful work to kind
of get more people working on alignment
and then kind of evaluations I covered
at length which is we need to keep
getting more specific on things we care
about and personalization is something
in alignment that I didn't cover in this
talk but is something that is good to
compete with this kind of big Tech which
is like how do we train models that are
good for you as an individual rather
than one big model for one big
technology
organization so this these slides will
get to you but these are the types of
places that I follow when I'm trying to
see open models or open data sets that
are reputable and easy to keep track of
so you don't have to try to follow um
everyone and I write about this a lot
without doing too much self-promotion
but I have like I ended like 10 minutes
early for questions that I'm happy to
take um in a Q&A format and then that if
you don't have to stay in waight if you
don't want to
[Applause]
okay thank you Nathan um questions
anyone got
questions assum you're hand a good
reward model which is a large assumption
I agree but what is the key challenge to
doing online D in sense you can do en
roll outs and then just like rank them
using a model and then go and you can
iterate this so what like what is the
hard
thing yeah I'm going to repeat the
questions so that people can hear them
and it gets recorded the idea is if you
have a good reward model what is
stopping you from doing online DPO and
kind of just improving the policy from
there I think there's kind of multiple
angles to this
that they're both Technical and like the
kind of industrywide but the technical
thing is I think the prompt matching
ends up being really important so prompt
matching so what your reward model can
learn is specific to the prompts
there're a technical detail where the
prompts used for your policy often are
exactly the same as your reward model in
po which is really strange because we
talk about generalization in machine
learning but we're kind of like soft
balling oursel at the PO stage which is
we're only grading po answers which our
reward model is train to answer which is
kind of strange so people think that
some of that might break down and we see
some of that when trying to train po
models with off-the-shelf reward models
it's was kind of a long answer and
then but I think that I think that's
mostly it's like mostly distribution
matching if I had to guess but if we had
truly a good model it should work for
some things and that could be one of the
reasons why there aren't that many in
the open because it would kind of help
people catch up in alignment it's like a
reward model if it is as important as
people say it is it might be easy
other questions yeah
[Music]
for examp
me yeah I think there's there this is a
whole conversation so if I don't cover
it if you want more after I answer I can
you can come up but the question is like
is there more than pairwise preferences
that could be used in rhf and there's a
lot of different lines of work that are
studying this um one is methods like
there's a method out of Stanford that's
kto name like csky I always mess it up
with these names are so hard to
pronounce but it's like idea of using
one-sided preference data so a lot of
customer apps have like did you did you
get good support from this agent yes or
no and like you could use data like that
is it just is a different loss function
for using single um single side of
preferences or just yes or no there are
other things like learning to rank for
multiple answers so this is something I
slightly insinuated but like binary
preferences is kind of like there's a
lot of literature on learning
preferences
and one of the models that got reduced
down is the Starling model and they use
a kwise preference so they have like
five or nine answers to every prompt and
then they collect answers and then they
have a different loss function and this
is one of the models has kind of like
broken through in the open alignment
space it's one of the few that I left in
and skipped in my slide deck but so
that's kind of interesting and then
there's other research that's like fine
grained um preferences so for every
completion to a prompt you get labels
like conciseness helpfulness honesty so
there's a few things on that regards
there's like a steer LM paper from
Nvidia and then there's work from udub
that does like learning from fine G
grained preferences so that one's
probably like the one that's most
emerging most in the academic sense but
there's so much to learn here there's
like all like literally all the field of
social Choice needs to get condensed
into these things
any other
[Applause]
questions yeah so the question is how
can we broadly is like how can we exceed
Human Performance with um fine-tuning or
any training for that regards I think
this is where some older ideas in CS
will come back like I think one of the
foundational ideas in CS is search which
is really also motivated as like
exploration in RL and therefore we need
to have some sort of language models
that can search and generate new data I
was talking with somebody before the
grad student and I think that it's like
search will be a large part of synthetic
data but then the human aspect will be
what gets it across the line if it can't
solve a certain area and this is like
the qar rumors are ridiculous but that
seems to be the best argument for the
sort of thing that open AI is trying
with that is like how to get that
barrier broken with
AI thank you so much for coming in you
mentioned data sets for a big limitation
and I was curious how one goes about
creating a new data
set yeah this is another thing that's
hard I think Community efforts are what
people have tried to do I mentioned open
Assistant but most people that do a
community effort are like I never want
to do this again so while I still think
it's worth doing things once that are
highly impactful even if you like might
not want to do it again other avenues
for building these in a sustainable
manner are very important I think that
there's some way that this is being done
like chatbot Arena returns some of the
prompts and the labels to users there's
specific concerns I have with that data
around being too noisy um but that is
the sort of thing that can happen if AI
2 has a demo for their models it's going
to be about science and like generating
information rather than being a chat GPT
competitor it's like a nonprofit it
can't do a product competitor but that's
the sort of data that we would want to
release and something that I might just
have to do but I'm interested in like
academic workshops and competitions as a
ground where you could have communities
meet every 3 6 8 months and have work
that's focused on an area Andor like
Focus time to have people contribute to
it but it's a good question it's not
it's probably why there aren't very
many how do you
feel are subject to reward hacking as
well so we get one at the front first
yeah close first and then we'll come to
you um the various places you've done
research at over the years do you have
any sense of how they compare in terms
of uh specifically alignment research I
mean obviously they weren't doing
alignment research specifically add
those
time I think generally they represents
different culture and Investments of the
company like the my I wasn't doing
language models until a time at hugging
phase so I can really only speak to
these kind of two open
companies and from like hugging P's
perspective is to show that more people
can do this like we're not trying to
compete with chat 2bt but we're trying
to Foster an ecosystem of doing this and
ai2 is similar but more about like what
is happening like how do we learn about
this how do we do science how do we
study the science of this and
communicate that clearly and I'm sure if
you do the exercise you can map this to
every company is like what is their
important thing and like they have
different goals in their products and
their corporate structure and things
like that
I will talk more when not
[Laughter]
recorded okay up the
back are reward model also subject to
reward hacking like they achieve a good
result on the outcome but
act in reality the outcome does not
expected yeah so this is like when
talking about reward models this is
probably the most established line of
work the question is like are reward
models subject to reward hacking and
reward hacking is a classic problem in
RL I should bring back from my RL slides
where you have the boat swimming going
in circles and then be like this happens
to your language model and and what
happens but it is and there's a lot of
research to mitigate it but it's a
fundamental problem which is you have a
very powerful Optimizer and you have a
incomplete representation of your reward
and it will always find where your
representation of reward is wrong so
it's like we will always be doing the
best we can but I think saying it's
perfect is like not possible in the math
I mean I can also say like the ways that
it fails are pretty funny cuz like if
you train these models you'll end up
with a model that just says JavaScript
to like every answer to like for on
Infinity it's like sometimes it's really
easy to see when that is happening which
is which is good or like you could
change your loss function so that it
will always exploit and like it's a good
way to kind of make sure that things are
working which is you should be able to
easily exploit if you turn the brakes
off
okay any last public
question if not uh thank you for Nathan
for giving this
call and if there's anything you'd like
to ask off the Record um he'll be here
for a bit longer