We're really lucky to have with us today
Giam Lumpl who is the co-founder and
chief scientist of
Mistral. Quick show of hands. How many
people here have heard of
Llama? All right, there we go. So, I
think folks know your work. Uh if you
look up the original Llama paper, the
first one. Yeah, there's there's a whole
team that helped make it happen, but the
last name on that is Gam's name. And so
today we're going to have a chance to
talk a little bit about the history of
open source models uh frontier open
source models the infrastructure that it
took to get here and and what the future
looks like. Um Giam
uh actually I I won't ruin that. Why
don't we start with just why don't you
tell us a little bit about what Mrol
does today and then how you got here. Uh
the end of course um so first of all
thank you for having me. Um can people
hear? No. All right, let's try to fix
that.
Oh, here you
go. Try now. Okay, better little better.
Okay. Uh, yeah. So, Mist is um, so it's
an AI company. So, we are doing research
in AI. We are training models. Uh, we
have around 15 people today, but our
research team is composed of around 40
people. Uh, we are doing many things in
AI. So sending I mean facing functioning
lot of reasoning uh cut generation as
well also multimodel we are an open
source company so we open source most of
our model most of our models are open
weight we started with a mist 7B in
September 2023 then MRX 7B few months
after that and since then we have open
sourced few of them mistral models as
well doing multimodel uh last week I
mean two weeks ago we released Mistral
small 3 which is 4B model. It's we think
it's the best model below 7B. So it's
it's a really good model and uh yeah so
we are doing um um we have a lot of
customers that actually ask us uh some
custom solutions. So what we are selling
is not well basically selling models but
more like solutions on top of this
models. So we help customers that deploy
this models. So these are on premise or
some private cloud sometime we provide
some solutions to do some custom models.
So sometimes I'm some very specific use
case the open source models or even the
public APIs are not working. So they
want us to basically do some fine tuning
for them. It can be arbitrarily complex.
Sometime it's some custom pre-training.
So we're going to pre-train models. Uh
sometime people want a 7D model that is
train 90% on this specific languages. Uh
so they very specific cues. Sometime
people want some edge models that are
that have this particular modalities
that have this size. So, so yeah, we
basically provide custom solutions
arbitrarily like advanced uh for our
customers on the Yeah. And could you
just spend a few minutes talking about
you know your personal background, how
you got here um where you know where you
got your start in ML. Uh yes, I um I did
my master in the US in 2014 at Carnegie
Milan. Uh then I came back to France to
do my PhD. In France you have this nice
thing you can actually do the PhD in
companies. So I did my PhD at M in Paris
in 2016. So you have access to
industrial resources basically while
being still a student. Uh so I was
working on many things uh in natural
language processing. Um I think
everything I did at the time is pretty
obsidized machine translation. So the
idea is that how how would you do if you
had a corpus of text in one specific
language and you have some English next
to it and if you know nothing about that
language can you find a way to translate
it nonetheless. So if I if I give you
maybe 1 gigabyte of text in some alien
language, can you translate that into
into English? So we actually developed
some method using some word buildings to
train some word meanings in that
language. Same in English and what we
observed it was quite quite interesting.
I think it was that this set of forings
in these two languages they actually
almost the same uh just have a rotation
that separates them. So what we found is
that you can actually learn this
rotation in some sort of unsupervised
way. And uh interestingly I think people
never realized this even though these
womb buildings were popular since I
think maybe 2012 even before that but
since it was some very high dimensional
vectors people did not notice that this
set of funings were actually exactly the
same but they were actually the same up
to rotation. Um so yeah so we use this
to actually create some unsupervised
machine translation. Uh then I continued
meta as a full-time searcher in 2019
2020. Um so we worked on different
topics. We worked on something which is
very popular today which is AI format. I
mean now everybody's talking about
reasoning it's super popular. I think
when we started this it was very very
few people that were doing this. I mean
there were a few groups here and there
and basically we knew all of them. Now
everybody does that. Uh I think
retrospectively we started a bit too
early. We were doing AI formats before
uh before LNN. Uh so it was a bit hard
uh because the models were not good. We
were working with 400 million parameter
models uh and we we basically trying to
do what deep mind deep mind did for go
on chess but for serum proving so
instead of being MCTS on some go on
chess games you do the same thing but
except that your environment is not a
board game it's actually some formal
prover so you are trying to prove
formally some theorems uh using
deploying it was a bit difficult at the
time I think it's a little bit easier
today because there because there was
nothing around this ecosystem. There was
no like API that allow you connect this
model to this formal system. So the
formal proving committee did not like do
any machine learning at the time. So we
had to build all this API on top of this
system that were absolutely not designed
for it. So it was a lot of painful
engineering. Uh it's also a bit more
complicated than you know for chess
chess on go when you basically have a
one position you play a move you have
another position. In formal proving it's
a bit more complicated because you have
a set of things to prove and when you
apply a tactic which is essentially an
action to your formal environment you
get a new set of goals. So for instance
let's say you want to prove that a
property is true for every integer you
apply an action which is called
reduction. Then you will have new goals
that are going to be prove that it's
true for n equals z. Prove that if it's
true for n is true for n plus one as
well. So you have like a set of states
on the set of goals. So it's we
basically had to do like what demine did
with alpha zero but it was not trees it
was hyper trees. So so yeah so we did
some research on this and uh at the end
we realized that uh I mean then GPT3
came out uh then this there was this
mina model by Google. So this model
became really powerful at doing
mathematics but it was always in Latic I
mean informal language. So not formal
math but like in singal math the same
mats that basically you will write and
um we thought that we should find a way
to leverage this uh this lens to
actually do formal proving. So what we
did is that we we had an intern who
joined us at metal albeist. So what he
did is that he um what we worked on is
can we take this really good LLM and
make them basically generate an informal
proof. So you have an input theorem and
instead of trying
to solve it formally what you do is that
you first ask your model to generate an
informal proof. So in Latic and then you
ask your formal model can you now prove
this but you don't just have the input
theorem as input you have the input
theorem but also the LLM informal proof.
So it's much easier because these
informal models are really good. There
there is tons of informal data informal
math online. You have very few like
formal math comparison. So it's much
easier to prove a theorem formally if
you know the the informal pool in proof
of latex. So so yeah so it was working
really well. We had a paper on this uh
and then we thought we need to scale
this. We need to work in this direction
much more. It was working well. So but
the issue at the time was that so we
were still at meta at meta we didn't
have any LM. So what was the base model
you were using for the original
experiment? We were using the openi
codeex basically codex. Yeah. I mean we
had our own model for the for the formal
but for the informal map we were using
codeex the openi API at the time. Uh it
was kind of a I mean of course not as
good as what we have today but it was
still kind of a revolution. So but we
thought that yeah if we want to
basically make this work better if we
want to take take this to the next level
we need to I mean you cannot do MCTS if
you just use an API every time you
expand the node. you need to have this
model in house if you want to do things
that work well. So, so yeah, we
basically decided to to train our own
LLM. Uh so we train LLM. So at the time
the best model that was kind of
documented was Chinula. It was a paper
by big mind. So we thought I mean there
was some recipe on what was a training
mixture and everything. So we thought
let's do the same thing. We know it's
trained on 1.4 trillion token. We know
the mixture it's like a 50% crawl. Uh so
let's try to do the same thing and uh
yeah and it became um it became
basically lamar initially it was a model
that was that because we wanted to do
math later the point was to find a
generic model and then function it to do
math right but then I mean other
opportunities arose on the this quick
show of hands how many folks have heard
of the chinchilla model okay so about
half maybe you could take a second to
just talk about why the chinchilla
scaling laws was um were were notable at
the time and why that recipe, you know,
was what you guys uh sort of forked as
opposed to the original, you know,
Kaplan scaling laws. Yeah, I think uh
when chin the chin paper was very
interesting. It was basically telling it
was essentially answering the question
uh if you have this amount of compute,
let's say 2,000 GPU for one month and
you want to train the best possible
model. What is the model size you should
consider? Uh on the basically founded
for 7TB model, it was I think 1.4
trillion token. Uh so that's what we
did. We train it on 1.4 trillion token.
Uh and uh but we also we didn't just
train a model like chinchilla which was
a 7TB parameter model. We also train a
series of small model because for us we
we are mostly interested in the small
model because for M you have to be fast
you have to generate fast. So we train
basically like a 7B a 13B 30B that ended
up being the Lama 7 13B and um yeah and
we for the 7B we actually trained the
model on the same amount of token a bit
less one trillion token and what we
found was that this mod actually much
stronger than we anticipated and I think
the the interesting takeway from this
lama one paper was how much you can
actually push the performance of a 7D
model and uh yeah and I think a lot of
people like didn't expect that such the
small model could get could become this
good then for it which was so a bit
further and know people are training
even on even larger horizons so I think
there's also like um something that
people today refer as chinchilla trap
which is that many people misunderstood
the message of the paper the paper was
really just answering u if you want to
maximize the performance of a model on
this amount of compute what is the model
size you should consider but uh okay
maybe for a 7D model it's going to be
like a 200 billion token but if you
train on two trillion token which is 10
times more then you get a much stronger
model and if you care a lot about
inference because at the end of the day
in train this model is also to deploy
them then you should train much more
than what is actually called comput
optimal I mean comput optimal so yeah so
many people even
in recently you know release model or
say it's train like in a chop optimal
way but it's actually not what you want
you want this model to be way beyond
this because there is actually become
Right. So, this was
um summer of 2022, right? Was it August
2022 when Llama was released? No, we
started working on it in August 2022,
right? And uh I think we started the
final cleaning maybe like end of
December and it was done after this. Ah,
right. Okay. So, early actually early
2023 was when you guys put out Llama.
And what what would you say were the
main challenges of training llama at the
time?
Um I mean we had a lot of issues during
the training that were due to some um I
mean we had a bunch of bugs. Uh I think
the maybe the difficult part of this
model is that sometimes
uh I mean for instance we had some bugs
that didn't actually manifest itself in
the 7B or 13B horizon but it actually
impacted the 7TB model uh and it's it's
this very uh small things that you will
not notice unless you actually start a
very large training. So at some point we
did some um I think we were a little bit
too ambitious in some parts on the the
precision of the model we could use. So
there were parts of the model where we
basically using like float 16 precision
and we were seeing that when you compare
float 16 to float 32 for this part of
the model it was actually giving the
same performance on small scale uh and
then when we scale this you have that
after maybe like two weeks of training
the loss is actually going up right and
it's uh and you don't know what it is
you know it can be many things or many
confounding factors and all these
experiments are very expensive uh I
think yeah the one advantage we had was
that we still had like some decent
amount of comput so we were able to run
them but um yeah I think the the
challenges are mainly like uh basically
pinpoint the issue u like being able to
identify exactly what went wrong and u
yeah because this is expensive so you
cannot actually afford too many like
trad um I know we'll come back later to
the challenges of training
infrastructure not just for you know
pre-training scaling but RL and fine
tuning scaling but why don't you
continue the story so so you release
llama at at at at uh at meta
And what what happens between then and
you guys starting the straw? Yeah. And
basically um so that was in January one
month before we so it was new 2022. It
was in I mean December we had conference
and um then I I I met Archer with also
our co I knew him from undergrad
undergrad together in France and um yeah
I mean he was working on Chinchilla
basically. I mean Chinchilla was out
there since a few months ago. So it was
like a known paper and uh we were
working on basically what became Lama at
the same time. So we discussed around
like LM and everything and it was
interesting because it was during this
same conference that uh that basically
JGPT came out that was basically
everything people were talking about at
this time. It was kind of a revolution
and I think what JGPT really did is that
it basically I think showed I mean
showcase to the world what is the
potential of this models. I mean this
models they were there before I think
the model that was released as JP was
potentially not even stronger than what
they had at the time before behind the
API but it's just when it's actually
fine tuned to this that people actually
realize I mean statistics are extremely
powerful right it's going to change the
world and it happens that I think yeah
retrospectively we are maybe like a bit
at the right time at the right moment I
mean at the right place because we we
were precisely training this model when
actually they became super popular and
it became clear that there there are
huge opportunities around geni. So, so
yeah, so it was very natural that yeah,
we discussed that maybe we should know
that we know how to train these models.
Not so many people know how to do it
because you essentially need to have you
need to have done it once to actually
know all these tricks. If you're making
a startup from scratch, you cannot like
I mean for we spend basically six months
there were like four months of trial on
error of like basically trying things
that didn't work and fixing them. But if
you're starting something new, you
cannot afford this. You basically things
have to work earlier. You cannot spend
as much money. How large was the llama
cluster that you had been experimenting
on? We had like 2,800
uh A100s. A yeah a before the Yeah.
Yeah. Yeah. So So that's at the time for
a sense of scale that was or how much in
in terms of flops budgets
um A100 rates were about was it a dollar
an hour or so? maybe a buck 50 an hour,
something like that. Uh so 2,000
H100s. Um that's about a million and a
half a month. Yeah. Right. Just on just
on a on a cluster sitting on dedicated
just for the llama. Yeah. So we're
talking about maybe seven and a half
to$10 million over six months of
experimentation R&D. roughly right maybe
maybe bit more than this uh but yeah
that's roughly that and when the paper
came out it was interesting because
people basically look at did this kind
of math and thought you know the lama 7B
it was f on this amount of GPU for like
this number of weeks so it's basically
what it cost to do this right and I
think people are doing the same today
with deepse but it's also not showing
showing I mean when we saw that we were
thinking yeah we spent six months
building this on the it doesn't show
bically all the R&D right that goes into
the final before the final training
Yeah, the final round is maybe cheap,
but everything that comes before
actually is the expensive part, right?
Um, and so, okay, then then you guys
formed the company and then you trained
7B. What did you do differently about
training 7B versus a mist 7B versus
llama? Yeah, I think um um I think what
we learned from our experience on llama
is that the data is really like the most
important thing. So, I think when we
started in June 2023, we were seven in
the company. We had basically one guy
writing the training conveys on six
people doing the data. So I think uh
what the difference was that we put I
think much more on physics on the data.
We work much more on this. It's
something that people don't like to do
because it's a sometime it doesn't feel
rewarding. It's not interesting. It's a
bit um what do you say alienating I
think. I mean it's not it's not nice to
do but it's the most critical thing. So
yeah we spent a lot of effort on this.
Uh then we trained the L the Mistral 7B
on 500 GPUs. Uh we released it I think
uh like third week of September on the
Yeah. On the Yeah, it we I was checking
the hugging face stats. Um but that
model 7B is now I think one of the top
10 downloaded models in history of
language models. I think it had more
than three and a half million downloads.
And that's just talking face. That
doesn't count all the local downloads
elsewhere. You guys put up the torrent
link. Yeah. Um can you talk a little bit
about
the what it took to you know go go from
that uh infrastructure of not having the
llama infrastructure at meta
which was a large company. You had lots
of people. You had a ML ops team who
could just do this for you to having to
set it up from scratch to get that model
out in time. What were the um yeah
biggest things you had to check off? uh
I think didn't change so much uh because
uh I think maybe compared to um I mean
the cluster we were using at meta at the
time was kind of um not bare metal but I
mean you had like a slower music
interface on the environment and uh that
was pretty much it. So all this uh
framework to train your model you
basically have to to write this and here
when we basically started the mistral we
essentially had a very similar setup
which is maybe a bit different I think I
mean for people working at Google where
there is a very specific infra when
people move out of the companies they
have to relearn things here I think the
the environment where meta it was a bit
metal so you the downside is that you
have to do everything kind of yourself
but the positive side is that I mean if
you leave you also know what to do
because it's it was not like Um yeah, we
were not like confused or anything. It
was like a not very we familiar with the
environ basically. Um
and you know a year ago I do or even two
years ago pre-training cluster setups
were like you're saying fairly bare
metal you know they as long as you had a
good slurm and sort of kubernetes uh
setup you're mostly off the races. Um
since you guys put out 7B and mixed a
bunch of things have changed in the
world right can you talk about as we've
gotten into reasoning models fine-tuning
and as you start getting into customer
deployments uh what what how does the
info change so what's how does the
infrastructure change for uh deploying
versus deploying a model for an end
customer uh ver which requires
fine-tuning and and uh model adaptation
versus just doing a pre-trained model
and throwing up the weights online for
everybody else run on their own. Yeah, I
think what we what we realized and that
we what we didn't expect when we started
is that for most companies it's actually
much uh it's actually pretty difficult
to deploy this model and even for us it
took us a while I think to have like a
stable API something we were happy with
initially I mean we had our API online
for the first time I think one I mean
maybe six months after the beginning of
Mistral so maybe December 2023 it was
pretty unstable people were complaining
a lot you have this uh I mean rate
limitation everything and
Um, so it's not super easy to do
something stable. Uh, and we're also
talking to Nvidia, so they were like
giving us some support and everything.
So, so it's hard and for most companies,
it's actually very difficult. Uh,
because the people that usually know how
to deploy these models, they don't work
in this company, they will work in some
AI company. So, for I think maybe like
yeah 90% of the company, if you give
them like a pre-trained checkpoint, they
will basically not be able to use this.
you have a lot of work to do to
basically like write this info that will
deploy this model deploy it efficiently
and u yeah so we had to basically build
this solution we had to build this um
platform that we give to customers that
they can just run on premise or in their
private cloud that will basically spawn
an instance and it will give them some
HTTP endpoint that they can query and
it's basically just to drop in a
replacement of some like like open or
something so so yeah so we basically
it's kind of one of the solutions that
we're selling so this platform that
people can just run and deploy because
it's uh yeah that's kind of where part
of the bank is also yeah so c can you
spend some time talking about that a lot
of people when they talk about AI models
they they they debate things like model
parameter size um flops budgets but the
reality is that models are not solutions
which is something we've talked about a
lot which and like you just said
customers often people needing to end to
to actually use the model often have
need somebody to help
them fill in the last mile. Mhm. That
where you you take the weights and you
connect before before the weights can
actually start being useful in a in a
deployment scenario. There's a bunch of
stuff that needs to happen. What what
does that look like? Why is it so
difficult for customers and could you
walk us through maybe an example of a
on-prem deployment that's quite
different from a cloud deployment? Yeah,
I think uh I mean the fact it's onrem or
on private code I think is is very
similar but compared to using an
external API. I think one difference is
that uh I mean sometime if people use
some out of the box general API solution
or it's not working usually there is I
mean they can iterate over the system
prompt and do like few short learning
and everything but it's a there's only
so much you can do if the online is not
good enough then there is pain you're
stuck while here if you do if you have
the weight of the model you can actually
do this fine tuning right so what we are
going to do typically is we will have
like some solution engineers that will
basically go with the
look at their use case. They will look
at what is the data they basically would
like to to have. Uh they create
synthetic data for them. It's hard to
actually annotate data efficiently. So
we provide them some tools to create the
data that they need to finetune the
model on the I think something that
people don't realize is uh how much
better a model can be if you just fine
it on a few hundred few thousand but
even a few samples. uh I mean if you
have like a model which is here the
state-of-the-art like API is there just
a little bit of fine tuning can actually
really significantly enhance the
strength of the model so there is a lot
you can you can you can gain by this so
but yeah but the challenge here is how
do you generate this synthetic data you
need efficiently for your use case uh
and then how do you fine tune this model
efficiently as well and then how do you
deploy it so there is a yeah basically
people usually need I think help for
most of this these parts and even the
most Yeah, I think the company we work
with, even the most tech savvy, the one
with the most expertise in tech that you
will not expect this, they will say that
they're happy to make a deal, but they
they basically want some AI engineers
that work with them like right 50% or
something like this because it's a Yeah,
there's a lot of work to do basically
that they are not familiar with. So,
yeah. Um, we have a bunch of student
questions piling up. So, I'm going to
ask you a couple two two more questions
before we open it up. The first is um so
we we've spent a bunch of time talking
about helping enterprises deploy like
you said for on on premise on on their
infrastructure but um in parallel you
guys have launched a hosted product
called Lasha uh which um I think you you
know you released a mobile app last week
and there was a web update with flash
answers um and when I was using it what
I was most surprised about on launch day
was how fast it was. So how what was the
thinking that went into investing in
inference speed making flash answers
work faster than anybody else? What was
the work required from an inference
optimization from a model distillation
and and why is that hard? Um yeah I mean
to to be transparent here I think uh I
think it's we're using so they basically
did this heavy work of making the
inference as efficient. Uh I think the
only downside of this very specific like
fast inference is that you you cannot
update the model so often and you
actually it's not as flexible in terms
of what you can deploy. For instance,
right now the flash answers we only have
this for the text model, right? We're
working on basically adding this for the
vision model as well because it's
slightly different architecture and
everything. But um yeah, I think it's um
I mean in the end I think most of the
solution will be more and more like
flexible and support more architectures.
I don't know if it supports Mr. Expert
typically right now. So for it's still
the Mr. large dance model we are
deploying and yeah so we we deployed the
show uh we deployed like the app I think
we have 1 million download right now it
was deployed a few weeks ago and yeah I
think the reason we did the show is also
because so it's one way to collect data
I think it's also which I think was the
initial purpose of GPT before it became
something else but uh there we have many
tools on this uh basically customerf
facing application so it has multiple
purpose one is to basically showcase I
mean like a demo of what You can do you
have this very useful feature for like
many customers this web search like this
ability of the model to like search over
internet opening pages like decide to
open again with multiple ops it it's
relevant you have this code interpreter
abilities as well right and so you're
also collecting a lot of data at least
for the future for basically improve the
model and something that we didn't
expect as well is how much you can
improve the model by training it on I
mean by leveraging basically the the
data that you on on our product which is
a uh yeah I mean in a in a way that
makes sense but you we didn't expect it
would boost the performance this much
and yeah it also helps us I think
identify the the weak spots of the model
so basically for each message people can
actually put like a feedback like plus
one minus one to say if it's a good
response or not and then you can see
that on the cut question the model is
not doing so well on this particular
kind of question the model is good so
you can actually get some insights about
what you should focus on what are the
priorities for instance right now You
see that in English 50% of the requests
are about code. So we want to like
invest more in code generation as well.
So so yeah basically having this
customerf facing solution is also like
one way to improve your model on the
mechmo of basically what your model
capable of. Yeah. And
um you know this came obviously a few
weeks after Deep Seek R1 was launched.
And so as you know you were saying
earlier you you were almost too early to
the reasoning era with your lean solvers
and formal math you know RL era with
with math um the math experiments at
meta but now that it's come full circle
what was your reaction to deepc coming
out? What does it mean for mistrol's
road map? Does it change anything at all
about the way you know you you train or
deploy a product like Lasha? uh I don't
think it changes much uh because uh I
mean at the end of the day for us we're
not selling the models like maybe that's
something we we don't communicate very
well but often people ask us like what
do you do what do you sell given that
there is all this letter of open source
models out there but what we are selling
is not the model because I mean the
model is actually very difficult for
companies to use what we are selling is
really like the solutions around it so
for us we are very happy to have the
best open source model because it's
typically something we can reuse as well
like that we can customize function for
customers
Uh so so yeah I think that was also I
think dipstick did a really really good
job here. I think some wait some
reactions were a bit dismissive but I
think what they did is really good even
their paper like showing a lot of
insights they explain in their paper
that they actually were trying things
like you know PRM I mean partial reward
modeling and NCTS that it didn't work
for them. It's also the kind of thing we
are looking at. So I think yeah they are
maybe like saving a lot of people a lot
of like time on their research agenda.
So I think it's nice. Uh but yeah,
beyond that, I think not too much. Uh
we're also doing this reasoning
internally. We'll have some things to
announce soon, but uh yeah. And and what
do you think
people misunderstand the most about
reasoning models and the sort of RL
scaling era?
I think it's maybe a bit early uh to say
no because uh I think when GPT3 came out
it was like a like a 175 billion
parameter model train on 300 million
tokens and people I think at this time
were very wrong. I mean I say like wrong
insights in the community about what is
going to work well. I think at the time
people would not have predicted that
today the most used model will be 7B
model or even 3B models. I think we
didn't scale we scaled the horizon on
the north tokens but not like the size
of the model necessarily we did a bit of
both but mostly the the amount of data
you use and uh so yeah it was very early
and I think our intuitions at the time
were a little bit off and I think it's
possible that we are in a very similar
moment today uh we still are basically
just starting the the work on reasoning
uh it's I think 2025 would probably be
pretty interesting I think it's going to
be uh a year when we're going to see
very impressive results on top of
reasoning basically know it's a question
of finding the best and most interesting
environment where you have like a
question and answer a verifier that you
can plug into some like deep lipstick
one kind of training strategy and see
the outcome of this yes there are like
many many promising things that we're
going to see here and I think it's
pretty exciting yeah great um well if we
have questions ready we'll move to to
that section yep who's the first one
first I think a question how will the EU
AI
compliance deadline um which is not yet
passed but is soon impacted m oh it was
two weeks ago there okay I think I was
in Paris for that actually uh has that
affected uh mal now in the future I mean
it's too early to say I think um the
important parts of the act I think are
still yet to be like decided I think
right now there are some parts of this
uh um regulation that is saying you know
that we have to like be transparent
about a specific number of things on the
model that we open source on the model
that we provide through APIs. uh and I
think uh that's just some very high
level statement of what we would have to
do but I think the technical
specification of this and what it
concretely means that what do you have
to do what do you have to share do you
have to share your planning set you have
to share the horizon of the training do
you have to explain how you trained it I
think this things are like actually the
important part of this act and it's I
think still very much in debate so so
yeah I think it's too early to say and
yeah at this point I think we don't know
that question is how are you going to be
working with housing? Yeah, I mean I
think there I cannot chat too much about
this partnership yet but there are
multiple things that I think are
relevant for them that are typically the
kind of thing we propose to some of our
customers. So for instance the edge
model is something which I think is
really interesting for these companies.
So you need like very small very custom
model for instance tell me some vision
action model these kind of things. uh so
yeah so we are going to basically like
build specific model it's a uh I think
the way it changes things for us is that
we we have like many companies asking us
many different things and I think based
on what is coming back the most I think
we can prioritize I think the model we
focus on first like this and yeah so of
course cannot elaborate too much on what
this partnership will look like but uh
we work with like quite a few defense
companies so
um it's never an easy uh decision um
because when you're in a big lab it's
also very comfortable you have a lot
resources. You don't have to worry
about, you know, compute and whether you
would basically have enough money to
like support the GPU on the runway,
these kind of things. So, it's moving
from like a nice environment to like
something a bit more stressful, but it's
also where you I think learn the most.
Uh you are I think it's invaluable how
much you can learn here. Um one I think
something that motivates people a lot to
join startups is uh all I mean
everything they're going to learn you
know people they join they first do
pre-training then they actually focus on
finetuning because the pre-trained model
is there then we want to do some new
modality so they learn about vision and
then they will learn about some new
modality so on know the reasoning so
they're essentially touching a bit of
everything I think we are in a quite
interesting I think era where you
basically can be very familiar
with the state of the art of like a very
large number of soft fields before you
had like you know like audio was
something very specific like vision was
completely different NLP as well and
know these models are so powerful that
they can basically be like like
state-of-the-art a bit everywhere and
since you are familiar with this you can
actually know like what is actually the
state of the art in each of these field
which I think is a very interesting time
and yeah so I think people joined for
the learning I think that's also why we
started I mean We had like a few reasons
to start this as well. I think we as I
said I think we were at the right time
at the right place. We knew how to train
these models. They were becoming like it
was becoming obvious how it was going
how powerful it was going to be, how it
was going to like impact the world. So
yeah, I think we also like were driven
by making some like a a nice AI company
in Europe. So there is no like big tech
in Europe but we have many people in
that go to the US go in this tech
companies go to like deepline or meta
but we don't have like any like really
big FI European lab so that was also I
think one of our motivation that's what
motivated a bit of people to join I mean
we are global company but I think that's
also what motivated some people to join
it so yeah all of these things I guess
together
obviously after the Paris AI summit how
is the EU changing it stance towards AI
um yeah Um I mean I think it's it's
still very recent so I don't know if
they have really reacted to this yet. Uh
I think that they I think EU is very
aware of like the potential of this
technology and that it's going to be
absolutely critical for like many
reasons for all this sovereignty kind of
thing. So so yep. So you is investing a
lot into AI. I think like during the AI
summit they know like multiple billions
of dollars into AI as well. So of course
yours. So yeah, I think they are very
well aware that it's going to be
critical and uh it's possible they're
going to like reconsider I think some
early like st they had on the topic but
yeah once again not super familiar with
this topic so
development how do you think about
competition and future biggest problems
bottlenecks? Yeah, I think for um for
the competition I think um I think given
what we are basically offering in terms
of solution and everything uh I think
our biggest competitors are not company
like I think open it's more companies
that proposes some same kind of
solutions so more like companies like
Korea I think uh so it's not I think
something um many companies are very
happy with I think some online API and
they are not don't have this concern
about peering privacy
Uh but there is still like a pretty
small I mean but non-negligible at all I
think amount of companies all in finance
defense like health insurance that
actually care a lot about privacy not
just privacy but also reliability you
don't want your if you have some
critical system in house maybe you are
not happy with your system relying on
some API that you don't control not that
you will necessarily do a better job
than maybe open air or Azure at serving
this model but at least you are in
control of what's happening in your
company if you have a system that relies
on this So, so, so yeah. So, so I think
um we're basically like addressing a
part of the market which is I think
specific people will need this custom
model. People who are not happy,
companies that are not happy with this
expensive uh solutions that want
something more custom, more like
tailored for their needs and yeah and I
think it's a it's a I mean it's a it's a
pretty big market nonetheless. We have
many companies coming for us with this
very specific use case on the Y amp on
the
I think the second part which is what
are the biggest challenges in the
future? Yeah, I think the challenge are
I think always on the basically you have
to go very fast in the research side. Uh
I think it's
um I have a feeling that like these last
couple years we were a lot focused on
the pre-training and that it was uh a
lot of you know just like basically
scaling things more and now that we are
kind of shifting parading putting more
effort on the post training on it's
possible that it's going to be quite
different and that the company that will
be I think the the most innovative will
not necessarily the one with the most
comput but I think the one with the most
flexibility I think for this
online post training kind of thing. You
need to be very organized. You need to
have like some very clear pipeline. You
need to have like some nice infra and I
think it's not something where I think a
very huge lab with a lot of resources
will necessarily have an advantage here.
I think you just need to have like a
decent amount of compute be smart in
what you are doing and do things
clearly. Uh it's yeah I think there will
be
like place for much more innovation than
the pre cleaning side. training was
mainly basically just if you look at the
current models we're training today
compared to like the model from like
2016 in ocean transformer it's
essentially everything is very similar
and I think uh I mean there are few
variations here like MLA attention this
kind of thing but it's mainly just a
question of new data and new scaling
while for post training I think it's
going to be much more innovation that
will be required so so yeah I think
whenever it's about innovation I think
any startup I think has as much chances
chances as any company basically. Yeah.
Yeah. I mean I think um they I think
once again I think EU and France are
very well aware I think of this
problematic on the fact that you have to
create a nice environment. Uh people are
very famili I mean they know that you
cannot if you regulate too much too much
regulation which kills the innovation.
So I think they're trying to like create
something which is nice for companies.
Uh we're also in touch with many people
both in in France and in the EU to
actually you know they basically want to
make sure that anything any regulation
is not going to be like an issue for us.
We are like talking with them a lot. So
yeah I mean to be honest it's
um I can understand why people are
asking this question a lot but I think
it's really not a concern we see on
internally we don't have this
problematic at all. I I think we the
first part I think we've addressed a few
times now but positioning as as Gam said
they don't sell models they sell
services unlike many of the other folks
who provide API services MRL is focused
on onrem deployment in sensitive
industries like defense healthcare and
regulations is that clear okay let's
move to your second question which is
what is the road map like for mistral
yeah I think for the road map uh we are
basically for us the fact that this all
this open source I think is also
something we are benefiting I think from
this open source on this open source
models uh given what we are selling we
can totally reuse this assets if a
company like meta is releasing a model I
don't know like 20 trillion token for
like many months on like 20,000 GPU for
us we are very happy to you know like
leverage the compute that already went
into this model and maybe like do
training on top of this model that's the
kind of thing we can do uh even though
we don't it's possible that you don't
have at the end the same resources as a
bigger lab to actually do this preing
from scratch you can we still use this
nonetheless. And um yeah, and I think um
if you look at this
um I think at the end of the day, what
matters is not really so much the model,
but more how you build the applications
on top of it. And to actually build nice
applications, you actually always need
some very specific sometimes finetuning.
For instance, we have this constra model
that we release that is extremely good
at doing this autocomplete in the middle
capabilities. So we are basically
selling this solutions of this copilot
model. So we sell this online basically
on premise copilot and for this it's not
something you can do if you just
leverage the open source model out of
the box. You actually have to do like
minor changes on top of that. So
basically what we we are what we are
doing and what we are trying to do is uh
finding the best way to leverage this
open source assets and potentially
things we train oursel to actually build
the best applications because at the end
uh if you look at for instance all these
models released by this lab it's often
the same thing it's model train like 90%
on English using pretty much I mean
pretty much all of the same data sets
the same capabilities uh and if you want
to actually make something custom make
like a really good product It's very
unlikely that you will be happy with
this out of the box solution. You
actually need to do some non-trivial
amount of work on top of this on top of
this model and basically what we are
doing is trying to find the best way to
actually transform this model into like
some nice product and yeah for instance
if you look at Russia that we have which
is basically our equivalent of CH GP we
have all these tool like web search this
code interpreter capabilities all these
things are basically absent from this
open source model and you need to do
some non clearly non criminal amount of
work to actually make this work. So it's
not like something any company can do.
You need you need to have like you don't
need to have like a lot of thousand GPU
to do this but you still need to have a
few a few thousand GPUs to do this
properly. So that's where basically
where we where we stand. If you look at
this scheduling for instance this DCR1
kind of approaches it's something that
you don't need like 100 GPU for that
again but you cannot do that with like
one node. You basically you need some uh
like some some decent amount of compute
and this is basically where we fit. This
is where we can innovate on the Yeah,
that's basically our segment. Thanks a
lot. Great. We're out of time, so we're
going to wrap. See you all next week and
we do office hours as well. Thank you.
Yeah.