very happy to end it off with a bang
here with um Andrew. Um so he's a
research scientist at Meta's Gen AI team
um focusing on media generation. Over
the past few years, his team has focused
on publishing research papers that push
the frontiers of video um generative
models including emu video as well as
movie gen. Um, prior to working on meta,
Andrew completed his PhD at Oxford's
Visual Geometry Group, VGG, under the
supervision of Professor Andrew um,
Zisserman. So, without further ado, I'll
hand it off to um, Andrew to take it.
Yeah, thank you for that. Um, like the
intro said, I'm Andrew Brown. I'm a
researcher in uh, Genaii at MESA. If you
guys haven't heard of that, Geni is the
research organization that releases uh
meta's generative models, things like uh
Llama for the text LLM and our media
generation models as well. Um I've been
there for about two and a half years,
ever since I finished my PhD. And like
Stephen said, over that period, we've
released a bunch of frontier pushing uh
video generation models. So, thank you
so much for inviting me. I'm very
honored. Thank you. And yeah, today's
talk is transformers for video
generation. So I saw in the list of
seminar speaks already, you've had a
bunch on uh NLP and some media
generation stuff. I hope this is new
compared to what you've heard already.
Okay, so text video models, you guys
might have seen videos like this uh on
the internet. Um, but given a text
prompt,
um, contemporary
textto video generation models can now
create these incredibly high quality
videos, complex motion, fantastical
scenes, very high quality. These things
are amazing.
Um, another example I quite like, this
is a ghost in a white bed sheet. These
things are amazing. Uh, not only are
they super high quality, they seem to
have learned some notion of the laws of
physics. The thing I like about this one
is if you look closely, you can see that
the reflection of the ghost is shown in
the mirror there. So, these models have
clearly learned something very like I
was saying, if you look very closely,
you can see this reflection of the ghost
uh in the mirror. These things are
amazing. And it doesn't stop there. So,
these um textto video generation models
can be used for other amazing
capabilities as well like editing. So,
for example, you can give these models
an input video like on the top left and
specify some edit prompt like turn the
runner into an inflatable dinosaur or
turn it into a cactus desert. Um, these
things are amazing. Now, I don't know
how long a lot of you have been like
paying attention to the media generation
field or even the machine learning
field, but if you've been only paying
attention for the last year, year and a
half, this is all that you're used to.
you're only used to seeing generated
videos that are completely
indistinguishable from real ones. Um,
but this is an incredibly recent
development. So on the right here, I
have the same video I showed you on the
first slide. This is from a model that
was released in October 2024.
And on the left, I have what was an
amazing state-of-the-art approach from
September 2022. This is another model
that was released by my team. Um, and I
can't stress enough how amazing this was
at the time. And this gap you'll see is
two years. Um, I'm sure every speaker at
this seminar has come in and said
there's been like amazing progress in
this machine learning subfield with that
one and there has been everywhere but
nowhere is it more clear than uh video
generation.
So how did this happen?
This is what the subject of today's talk
is going to be. How do we train models
to generate videos like this? So, all of
the videos you saw in the previous
slides are from a paper we released in
October 2024 called Movie Gen. Here's a
little snapshot of the abstract.
Um, a little spoiler for how we did
this. Uh, and a spoiler for why I was
invited to this is that we did it using
transformers. I saw this little guy
included in previous talks, so I had to
put him there.
So, um, today's conclusions are going to
be twofold. First, I'm going to talk you
through every detail of how you train a
transformer to generate videos like
this. Um, we publish all of the details.
We're going to step through everything.
Some of the concepts are going to be
familiar things like transformers. Some
are going to be new. We're going to go
through it all. The second takeaway is
going to be this conclusion that I'll
keep on saying that throughout this
project we learned that scaling data
compute and model parameters for a
simple transformer also works for video
generation. We've seen it work in all
kinds of machine learning fields. We
also saw it work here for video
generation.
Okay. So um just a little bit of
personal background. I think most of the
speakers that you've had are from NLP,
which makes sense because transformers
came from NLP. I'm a computer vision
researcher. Um, and I've been in visual
generation for a few years now, and it
hasn't always been as popular, um, as it
is now. So
how I got into this uh I was sat in this
lecture hall in the engineering
department at Oxford in what the second
year of my PhD and we were having a talk
by professor Antonio Turabler from MIT
and he was presenting this work called
GAN dissection. Um, some of you may have
heard of GANs. The state-of-the-art
image generation approach at the time
were these generative adversarial
networks. And in 2019, you could
generate like a blurry face or a blurry
kitchen or a blurry bedroom. Um, and
that was amazing at the time. And this
paper here was showing that you could
activate or deactivate certain neurons
in the GAN and in doing so you could
make certain concepts appear or
disappear.
So these are the kind of images that we
were generating at the time. So this is
this is like a blurry kitchen and this
was like near state-of-the-art. So you
can see, you know, the the visual
concepts are pretty messed up. It
doesn't make a huge amount of sense, but
I can't stress how like good this was at
the time. I'm sure a lot of you have
seen like Dolly and
um stable diffusion and so on. Um things
were not always this good. So the point
of the paper or at least in this example
was they were showing that you could
activate certain neurons and make
windows appear in the kitchen. You could
imagine how your kitchen would look with
windows. And the outcome was this.
Um so some like pretty janky windows on
the left. And my mind was completely
blown.
Um, as I can sense like all of yours are
as well. Um, this was amazing. So, what
they showed here is not only that the
model had learned a physically plausible
place to put the windows, but
importantly, they'd also shown that the
model had learned some notion of
physics. The model had learned that if
you put windows on the left hand side of
the room, light will come through them
and there'll be a reflection off the
marble countertop. And you can see that
here. And the model had just learned
this by looking at images.
So this had like a really profound
impact on me as a young PhD student and
I've been in visual generation uh ever
since.
Okay. So um the body of the talk uh
there's going to be five parts. I'll
give an overview uh of the model that we
trained to talk about architecture uh
data and training recipe results and
applications and a little discussion on
on what is next.
So first I included um a bit of
historical context on movie gen and
video generation. Maybe some of you are
quite new to the video generation field.
The field is quite new inherently. Um
this snapshot is maybe 3 years from 2024
back to around 2022. This is a century
in machine learning research. Um I
haven't included all of the works here.
Um there are some very relevant
important works here. I've just included
a snapshot to make a couple of points.
There have been two um milestone events
in video generation. The first was in
2022 when people started using diffusion
modeling. Uh this is when the whole
community started using diffusion. There
was a big step up in uh visual quality
at that point. And the second one was in
2024.
And this is like the point of today's
talk. So before 2024 people were using
quite small scale uh specialized
architectures. I say small because the
definition of small and large has been
like moving all over the place recently.
Um but these were specialized
architectures for computer vision things
like uh CNN's units uh and so on. And
then around 2024
um video generation sort of boarded this
architecture unification setup. So all
over machine learning fields we've seen
people ditch specialized architectures
and move towards this simple transformer
setup. The reason is because all of
these different fields are seeing the
benefits of efficiency and scalability
by moving to these transformers. So in
2024 um the video generation community
started doing the same and that's where
movie gen comes in which I'll talk about
uh today.
So a quick overview on what uh Movie Gen
is before we get into the details. So
Movie Jam was a a cast of foundation
models that generates high quality 1080p
HD videos with different aspect ratios
and synchronized audio. Today I'm just
going to be talking about the text to
video model. Um I'll show some fun
examples later of the other models that
we trained. Um and again like I've been
saying the point of the paper was
showing that scaling data training
compute and model parameters for a
simple transformer trained with flow
matching I'll cover that later uh
yielded state-of-the-art results.
We also presented a few sort of
innovations and simplifications along
the way. So movie jam video the model uh
was a 30 billion parameter foundation
model for joint text to image and textto
video generation. Uh the model was
trained on the order of around 100
million videos and 1 billion images.
Um okay so on to the architecture there
are three um main things that I want to
cover today. Um the first is the
representation. what representation are
we learning. The second is what learning
objective that we used and the third is
what model architecture we use for
learning it. If I do a good job here
then all of you will know all there is
to know about video generation. I'm
imagining most of you have more of a NLP
background um with sort of text
autogressive models. I'm going to try
and contextualize all of this in
relation to text and how it differs
differs from uh large language models.
Okay, so the representation,
what do we mean by that? Well, we mean
how are we going to represent the data
for the model? We're doing generative
modeling here. We're learning P of X.
The question here is what should X be?
We know that X is going to be derived in
some way from videos, but there's an
open question of how exactly do we do
that?
Um,
so to motivate what we ended up doing,
I'm just going to talk a bit about the
differences between text and media.
So let's look at some text data. For
example, um, and this piece of data, a
sentence, an image of a cat.
What has happened when this data sample
has been cur created is a human has put
in a huge amount of thought into
compressing what they're thinking into
this very well-designed semantically
rich language. It's very compressed.
Every word packs a huge amount of
information and it's also inherently
discreet. So in practice when people are
training large language models they can
use a representation that's quite close
to this. So they might use a sort of
simple tokenizer
before feeding it into the transformer.
Media data is incredibly different to
this. So let's look at a related piece
of data, an actual image of a cat.
No compression has really occurred here.
This image is just continuous raw data
that's been captured by your camera. Um,
maybe the only sort of human effort
that's gone into this is positioning the
camera and framing the cat in the middle
of the camera, but nothing else. As a
result of this, there's tons of
redundancy.
So, what I mean by this is if you know
what a cat is, and then let's say the
middle pixel, you know, is this white
fur on the catch. Well, if you know what
a cat is, you know the next pixel along
is probably going to be white fur and
the next one along from that. And if
it's a video, you know, the same pixels
one frame along are also going to be
white catfur. There's a huge amount of
redundancy. Um, so this begs the
question of perhaps this raw data could
be transformed into something that more
closely resembles language.
So what do we um actually do? So if you
forget everything that I just said on
the previous slide, one thing you could
do, a very simple approach is you just
model the pixels directly. So let's say
you took an image or a video, you
unraveled it into a long sequence of
pixels and then trained let's say next
token prediction on that and in a way
that's what some prior works did things
like imagine video or image GPT uh back
in the day along with you know a little
bit of patching.
So this is a very sort of conceptually
simple uh method but it's very
computationally constraining. So
the thing about modeling pixels directly
is the number of pixels scales
quadratically with the image or video
resolution. Um it's bad for images. It's
even worse for video when you have a
temporal dimension. In practice, what
this means is these models can only
model very low resolution images or
videos, things like 64x 64 videos, which
is not ideal. And if we want to generate
a actual large HD video, these methods
had to employ a huge cascade of
upsampling stages, things like super
resolution models, frame interpolation
models to increase the size of the data.
So this really isn't ideal.
So instead, what prior work does is they
learn a compressed latent representation
um using something like a VAE or a VQVE
trained offline.
This is what every sort of textto image
model or text video model you've seen on
social media has been doing for a long
time. The advantages here are twofold.
Um if you're modeling a compressed
version of your data, then you can
natively model larger data. We don't
need to go down to 64x 64. We can
natively model something bigger. The
other advantage is that this offline
train VAE or VQVE can remove some of the
computational burden from the language
model. For example, these autoenccoders
could handle the modeling of how two
separate blades of grass differ from
each other in an image or a video and it
can take that burden off the sort of
downstream language model.
Okay, so that is what we do
from an architecture. We train something
called a temporal autoenccoder
uh for spatial temporal video
compression. This is basically just a
variational autoenccoder.
How does this work? Well, you take a
video uh you'll feed it through the TAE
encoder. A VAE consists of an encoder
and a decoder. After the encoder, the um
the representation will be compressed
and you end up with this latent
representation at the bottleneck in the
middle. And this is the representation
that we're going to uh use downstream.
How you train these things is is quite
simple. Some of you may have seen it
before. You take your video, you feed it
through the encoder, you get to the
bottleneck latent representation, you
then decode it back to pixel space, and
you have a bunch of losses between the
output and the input. Things like L1
losses, adversarial losses, um, and so
on. So this representation in the middle
is what we're going to model. When we
talk about learning P of X, we're
learning the the the distribution of
this latent. What this means is when we
train a generative model on this, it
generates in this space. It doesn't
generate in RGB space. So after we
generate a video, we then need to decode
it back to RGB space.
So the TA that we trained had uh 8x
compression in each dimension, 8x in
height, width, and time. And this was
pretty high compression at the time. Um
it's not the highest compression
anymore. This was published like 6
months ago and 6 months is again like a
decade in machine learning research. But
at the time this was very high
compression. And like I said, this means
that we can natively model very high
resolution videos. As an example,
the largest video that we model in this
work is 768 x 768 pixels, 16 seconds, 16
fps.
Now, if we were to model pixels directly
and we took a video of that size, we
unraveled everything, we treated one
pixel as one token and we flattened the
whole thing, it would result in 150
million tokens.
Even with like very long context
training methods with language models at
the moment, this is completely
unfeasible.
But using this temporal autoenccoder,
the same video is just compressed to
73,000 tokens. So this is suddenly
completely computationally feasible
using like today's parallelism
approaches, today's infrastructure.
If anyone is doing this maths offline,
there is also a patchify layer. If if
someone thinks my maths is wrong here.
Okay, so that's everything for the
representation. Does anyone have any
questions at this point?
No,
it's a great point. Um, a lot of
autoenccoders for videos do um use
causality. Um,
some nice uh outcomes of that is that
when you encode images uh they can be
encoded completely independently of uh
subsequent frames and so on. But no,
this isn't causal.
Okay, so next up is which uh generative
modeling learning objective do we use?
So probably in most of the talks that
you've had so far, you've heard about
auto reggression and next token
prediction for text.
Um in media generation, we don't we
haven't been doing that for a couple of
years. So the def facto approach in most
media generation has been using
diffusion modeling. We use something
called uh flow matching.
So what is flow matching? Uh flow
matching is in a way a simpler
generalization of diffusion. Now if any
of you have watched a talk on diffusion
modeling or read anything about
diffusion or flow matching, I'm sure
you've seen a figure like this before.
I'm going to give a brief sort of
explainer of what is similar between
flow matching and diffusion. Um and then
we're going to go over what a training
step looks like. So both uh diffusion
and flow matching have a very similar
setup. So you assume that you have some
unknown data distribution. This is the
sort of distribution of images in this
figure. In this case like images of
cats.
Um this is the distribution you're
trying to learn. This is the
distribution that we want to learn and
then sample from.
You also assume you have a known data
distribution on the right and we model
this as normally just like gausian
noise.
Both assume then that we have this fixed
forward process. What this means is we
have a method of translating between the
unknown data data distribution and the
known one by iteratively adding noise.
Um both assume that if you keep on
adding noise you basically end up at
this known data distribution.
Then both of them train a neural network
to do the reverse process. So they train
a neural network to take um one of these
images and iteratively dn noiseise it.
And then at inference time you can
iteratively use this neural network to
go from a sample that's pure noise back
to a sample from this data distribution
that you've just learned. And that's how
we end up sampling uh images and videos.
So diffusion and flow matching are very
similar in a lot of ways. Flow matching
is in a way a simpler generalization.
It's been very recently shown to result
in more robust training uh and more
efficient probability parts that are
easier and faster to sample from. So
this paper came out um pretty recently
in 2023 from some uh colleagues at
massa.
Um importantly it's been shown to work
better than diffusion.
And I'm not going to go into a huge
amount of detail here, but we're going
to go over how a training step uh looks
like.
So, there are lots of equations here.
We're going to step through them pretty
easily.
It's a three-step process.
We first take a training data sample X1.
This is your image of a cat uh on the
previous slide. This is just an image
from your data set.
We then sample a time step. This is a
float between zero and one. and we
sample from the known data distribution.
This just means taking a sample from a a
normal gausian.
We then construct a training sample XT.
What is this? This is just this sort of
intermediate image. Uh a somewhat noised
image of a cat.
There are lots of different ways of
constructing XT. Uh we use what's called
the simple linear interpolation from the
uh flow matching paper and the equation
is shown here. So this is how we go from
the three things we sampled above to
this intermediate training sample.
Then in flow matching what you do is you
train the model to predict the velocity.
This is a value which moves the training
sample back in the direction of the data
sample.
Um in actuality it's very simple. So
this is how we compute the velocity
simply by differentiating the equation
above. This is how we get our ground
truth. And then on the right we have our
actual learning objective. So this is
the mean squared error between the model
prediction and the ground truth
velocity. Here the model prediction is
parameterized by U. It takes as input
the training sample. It's conditioned on
two things. It's conditioned on the text
prompt. That's P. Remember we're doing
text to video generation. So we need to
condition the generation on the text
prompt. I'll cover later how we do this.
Uh you condition on the time step as
well. And then theta are the uh model
parameters.
Okay, you know how to do flow matching.
Um, inference is also pretty simple. So,
you start by sampling from this known
data distribution gausian noise and then
we use an ordinary differential equation
solver to go back to the data
distribution uh given a series of time
steps. So, very simply, you'll sample
some noise. You'll sample a stream of
time steps. At each time step, you
compute the model's prediction for the
velocity and use the solver to move the
sample in the direction of the unknown
data distribution.
And at the end of that, you have your
sample. Um,
low-level detail, we use a a quite
simple uh solver. There are lots of
different options you can choose.
Okay. So lastly um which model
architecture do we use?
Now I already said that we're using
transformers.
Uh the big goal of this paper was to
benefit from like I've said about seven
times already scaling data training
compute and model parameters uh with
transformers. But there is a question
about which transformer to use. So
in my research organization, we train
these things called llamas.
Uh llama is the large language model
that meta open sources.
We take the llama 3 model, hence why I
sort of pasted this L3 on it. Llama 3 is
quite a classic uh dense fully connected
decoder only uh language model.
So what we did in movie genen is you
take your videos, you encode them with
the TAE that we discussed earlier, you
flatten the tokens, this gives you your
input sequence and we just throw it into
llama.
So very very simple.
Um
now when I say llama, um I don't mean a
pre-trained llama. I don't mean one
that's been trained for text.
Um what I mean is the architecture. So a
randomly initialized architecture,
but this is still very important.
Training large language models at scale
is incredibly difficult. Um, every time
you change anything about the
architecture, you need different
hyperparameters. They scale differently.
It's incredibly tricky. So the fact that
we already know uh in our research
organization how to scale this
architecture and the fact that we have
the infer set up already to train these
things at scale makes a huge difference.
Um so that's why the simplest thing for
us to do was to go with the llama
architecture.
Mhm.
So
taking initialized or like a pre-trained
llama?
We we didn't do that for this project
but I agree that would be a really cool
thing to try.
[Music]
Yeah, it's
it's not entirely clear why that would
work. Obviously, like these are very
different um modalities, different
learning objectives,
but
you know, in a lot of ways there's a lot
of sort of shared structure between
these modalities that would maybe
benefit from that.
Um okay so that last slide was like very
deceptively oversimplified.
Uh there are some changes that we needed
to make to llama 3. So importantly uh
llama 3 is a model for autogressive text
generation and we are doing texttovideo
generation using flow matching. So there
are three changes that we need to make.
I'm going to go over all of them
exhaustively to sort of hammer the point
that we barely changed the architecture.
Um the first thing that we need to do is
incorporate the text conditioning.
You'll have seen on the previous slide
that our input sequence is just made up
of video tokens. We're doing text to
video generation. So we need to
incorporate the text conditioning
somehow. And we do this using cross
attention layers.
So very simply we construct a sequence
made up of our text conditioning and we
add crossention layers into the
transformer block. So these go between
the self attention layers and the feed
forward network. Um it's a very common
way of adding text conditioning for
media generation models.
Um there is a question as well of what
should your text representation be? How
should you construct this sequence? One
like very simple thing to do would be
you just tokenize the prompt the caption
and then you feed that in. But when you
do that, you're very much burdening your
model with learning this text
representation from scratch. So instead,
we use pre-trained text representations.
Uh we use three in fact uh three that
are complimentary to each other. The
first two all of them are pre-trained
frozen text models. Basically the first
two have very sort of semantic level
representations. UL2 is a large scale
encoder decoder model. Meta clip is our
internal clip model and the third one
has more of a sort of character level um
text representation by T5. So we encode
the um text prompt using all three of
these. We project them all to the model
dimension and we concatenate and that
gives us our um text sequence.
The second thing we need to do, you'll
remember from the learning objective
that um we also need to condition on the
time step. Um so what we do here is we
do this in adaptive layer norm blocks.
So we've already added a cross attention
block. We also add this adaptive layer
block.
This um might seem like quite a strange
way of adding some conditioning. It's
something that was popularized in the
diffusion transformer paper which was
the first paper that uh used diffusion
with transformers obviously by the name.
Um it might seem a little bit random.
It's basically very computationally
cheap and works super well.
Okay, number three. There are only
three. Um we use full birectional
attention.
Llama is an autogressive text model.
They use causal masking for next token
prediction. Um for the flow matching
objective, we have no such constraint.
We want every video token to see every
other video token. Um we don't care
about causal masking. So we take that
out. Um a very low level detail is that
because of this we use multi head
attention instead of groups query
attention. But that's everything other
than that is the llama architecture.
Okay. So um we now have our full uh
architecture diagram. I was very wary of
putting this earlier because it's pretty
complicated but I think it should all
make sense at this point. Um so from
from left to right we during training we
take one of our training videos we
encode it with the TAE to get to our
compressed latent representation. It
goes through a small patchy. This just
does some extra compression and we
flatten it and that's how we get our
input sequence.
During training, we'll construct our
training sample by combining it with
this Gausian noise. During inference,
this whole sequence will start off being
gausian noise. The sequence goes through
these llama transformer blocks. We add
in the um conditioning and then we get
our output sequence. Uh during training,
we'd compute our loss and back
propagate. During inference, we would do
this iterative dnoising process and
finally uh decode back to the RGB space.
Any questions on the
uh architecture or
question?
So um we
at at inference for a given text prompt
we add this conditioning into the model
always. So the input sequence is just
gausian noise but that's not where the
text information comes in. The text
information comes in through these cross
attention layers. So even though the
input sequence is just noise, the model
is still seeing these clean um text
information. We don't noise the text or
anything like that.
Does that make does that make sense?
Okay. Mhm. question
that you don't all the way to clean
data.
Does that mean is that sigma min making
sure that you always get diversity in
the same uh query every single time you
go through process? Yeah,
actually all the way to P.
That's it's just a hyperparameter that
we keep um constant.
I cannot remember off the top of my head
exactly what that hyperameter is for.
Actually,
I'm going to talk to you about that
after.
Yeah. So, um
it's a very good point. So, during
inference, you'll sample a series of
time steps. uh usually with these
flow-based models the more you sample
the better you'll better approximate
these probability parts uh in practice
we use 250 I think one of the advantages
of flow matching is that the probability
parts are theoretically straighter so
you should be able to require less uh
function evaluations to approximate this
path that's one of the advantages
250 like so is there not precribed
um number of T's during training.
Yeah, that's continuous. Yeah, but
during inference it's uh we just sample
some discrete ones.
Yeah.
So I have a question on the two videos
that you showed the difference between
2022 and the
was the improvement algorithmic improve
the hardware in terms of better GPUs or
it was just a pure algorithm.
So I think everything comes down to
scale.
There are quite a lot of things that
have changed. There's an architecture
change moving towards transformers and
then there's the scale and that includes
a whole lot of things. Scaling the data,
scaling the amount of compute um in
order for that to be like tractable
um
better like GPU hardware does help.
There wasn't a huge improvement in GPU
hardware over those two years.
It might have been one or two
generations of uh Nvidia's stuff. Yeah.
Mhm.
Okay. So now we have an architecture
that we're pretty confident um scales.
We have a learning objective that we
think should work in flow mashing.
That's pretty much it for the details.
It's not the entire story. Um but that's
a lot of it.
Um okay so the last um technical details
are about data and the training recipe.
So uh data
um I think in a lot of ways this is the
most important slide of of the entire
talk today. Data is so important for
training large language models. And by
the way, when I say large language
models, I'm sort of just talking about
transformers at scale for any modality.
People use like different definitions
there. Um,
but these models are incredibly data
hungry. They require internet scale data
and they require the data to be clean.
Um, the scaling laws depend on the data
being clean otherwise the scaling laws
don't hold. Um, and the model output
quality depends on the data being clean.
As a result of this,
research groups at these big companies
spend a huge amount of resources on
data. This is something that I find
isn't really talked about so much, but
they'll spend huge amounts of resources
in terms of GPUs and also actual
researchers. Often on these research
teams, the data teams massively
outnumber the modeling teams.
Um, which was something very new to me
after my little PhD.
Um so why is this? Well, you know,
remember we're training um generative
models.
We are learning this distribution of our
training data and then we're sampling
videos from it that are likely according
to that training data. So if we want to
sample the kinds of videos that I showed
you on the first two slides, then all of
our training data needs to look like
that.
Um
I'm mainly talking about pre-training
here. You obviously have a post-training
phase as well where you can align your
videos to be more high quality perhaps,
but your pre-training data still needs
to look great.
So this is a huge challenge. Um, we
trained the model on the order of around
100 million videos.
How do we get to this number? Well, we
can predict a sort of training budget
that we had for this project. And you
want as many videos as you can that you
don't epoch very much. Um, so the
challenge was how to get this many
videos that are high enough quality. Um,
at the time of movie genen, we
constructed this incredibly detailed
complex pipeline
um, with a bunch of handcrafted and
model based uh, filters. I'll just talk
through a few bits of it because of the
sheer amount of work that went into
this. So you start with a large pool of
videos uh, from some corpus. Um, they
may be different lengths, long tail of
concepts. We did a bunch of visual
filtering on these, removing videos that
are too small, scene changes, bad
aesthetics.
We removed a bunch of videos that have
bad motion. It turns out a bunch of
videos uh in any large corpus have
really slow motion, janky motion, motion
effects. We removed all of those. We
then did a
um
content filtering step. This is first
dduplication. But the really important
one here is resampling.
Large language models do not work well
when they're trained on a very
imbalanced data set in terms of
concepts. So something with a very long
tail. They work best if the concept
distribution is roughly roughly uniform.
Um and that uniformity doesn't occur if
you just take a random set of videos. So
we do this very sort of complex um
visual concept extraction clustering the
upw weight certain clusters down weight
certain clusters
this uh all of this will give us a set
of videos uh we also need captions
because we're doing text to video
generation and we generate these
automatically uh using llama 3.
So that is data
very lastly uh the trading recipe.
So this uh multi-stage recipe here was
optimized for uh convergence speed. We
start off with a 256 pixel uh T2i stage
image generation. Here the model can
whip through a bunch of samples in very
few relatively uh GPU hours.
We then move on to a uh pre-training
stage with joint text to image and text
to video generation where we
progressively increase the resolution
from 256p to 768p
at the highest resolution here 768p.
That's where we have this sequence
length of 73k and we train this on 6,000
GPUs um around 1500 batch size.
At this point the model uh splinters. So
we have a text to video post training
stage. This is just SFT on like a very
small set of very high quality videos.
And then we also branch off into these
different capabilities. I'm not going to
talk about those a bunch um but I'll
show you some examples later.
Any questions on
Sure. for um like sort of a wider tail
data set of bravery is is there sort of
a is there retraining you can do
specifically to address those types of
challenges?
Yeah, I think um
definitely um I guess the question is
about certain concepts in your
pre-training data. I guess yeah in a in
a very large corpus like we'll be
training on there's an incredibly long
tale of concepts pretty much every
concept that you might want to uh
generate would probably appear at some
point in that data set
okay anything else
[Music]
okay so um lastly the uh results and
applications so putting everything
together that I just showed you and
that's all of the technical details by
the way like we published all of this um
we get videos uh like this and like the
ones that I showed at the beginning of
the talk as well. Um
and this pretty much sums up the whole
point of this project. I really want to
hammer home that these kinds of videos
were nowhere near possible before people
started scaling transformers.
Um and we showed here that again this
classic architecture unification story
scaling data model parameters and
compute for a simple transformer ended
up in a model that can reason about
objects motion and physics just by
watching videos.
So none of this was possible and it's
scaling transformers that unlocks all of
this.
Um I have to keep on pressing replay
because I couldn't figure out how to do
auto replay on Google Slides.
How many PhDs does it take to to auto
replay? Okay, so another one. Um, here's
a sloth with pink sunglasses on a donut
float. Um, again, I think the the like
physics of sloth like donut flotation
here are good. Um, this slide isn't only
a joke. Um, it does actually highlight
something quite important when we're
training uh generative models. One
important thing is how well it
generalizes to concepts that maybe
weren't in its pre-training data. We
can't be sure that there are no like
slots in floats in the pre-training
data, but you know, by common sense,
there probably aren't too many. So, the
fact that it can generate this is
testament to its its generalizing
capabilities.
Um, okay, a few other things. I showed
you some of these at the beginning. Um,
we also trained a movie gen edit model.
Like I said before, you take the
original video on the top left and you
can provide these precise um, edit
instructions. This is really magic to
me. Um, I didn't get a chance to cover
this too much today, but um, the team
trained this with paired data. Um, it's
incredibly hard to get paired data for
this task. These pairs of input and
outputs. They came up with a like a
fascinating self-supervised approach for
this. I'd really recommend reading the
paper. Hey,
where did you guys get the data from on
this project?
The the videos are completely licensed
videos by MASA. Yeah.
Um, and one more example here. You can
take, you know, everyone wants to take a
video of their penguin and and put some
Victorian outfits on it. So, this is
great.
Um
one other model that we trained uh is
the personalization model. So here uh
this is movie gen video but with the
added capability that you can condition
on an image of yourself. So here the
model can generate uh a video that is
faithful to this text prompt but also
contains the person in the conditioning
image. So that's really fun.
Um, and another funny example here, this
is my colleague that I worked on the
project with. This makes me laugh.
Um, so yeah, if anyone is interested in
this, please go read the paper. A bunch
of work went into this. Um, very lastly,
we're going to see now if the theater
has audio.
It doesn't.
So, we trained this movie gen audio
model. Um, again, I didn't have time to
go into this today, but this is a model
that will condition on text and a video,
either real or generated, and generate
synchronized audio. So, this way we can
add audio to our generated videos. Um,
it's an amazing research team that did
this. So, I'd recommend going to check
out the paper if you're interested.
Um, okay. So, there are a couple of um
just points left. Firstly, some
quantitative results. It's it's
incredibly hard to do fair uh
comparisons in video generation. We
don't have automated metrics or anything
like this. Um so what we did was we did
a very extensive human evaluation study.
We came up with a bunch of metrics that
are somewhat orthogonal to each other
that test every aspect of video
generation. things like motion quality,
how well the videos follow the text
prompt, uh visual quality.
Um, these metrics are shown on the left.
I won't go into a huge bunch of detail
here, but they're very sort of fully
defined in the paper. We put in a load
of work to make sure that the human
evaluators
uh had sort of low standard deviation
when multiple evaluators were rating the
same thing. So, um we compared to all of
the methods that were released in the
same year. This is 2024. So things like
uh runways models, Luma, uh Sora at the
time, and Clling.
And these are net win rates you're
seeing here. So a score above zero means
that our model was preferred.
Uh at the time of release, uh Movie Gen
outperformed all of the prior work. So
this is that's great. Um
it's very hard to draw conclusions here.
The one conclusion we can draw is that
movie jam was better than these uh at
the time of release.
We are like researchers. What we like to
do at this point is to look into all of
the technical reports of the prior work
and see what they did differently and
what um what did Movie Gen do
differently? Um because we'd like to
conclude, right, what led to these
improvements? Was it more compute? Was
it flow matching? Was it better data uh
filtration? Things like that. Um, but
it's it's unfortunately not possible in
today's age to do that um because we
don't see research publications. But
what we do know is that all of the
technical details I just presented work
and they work really really well and
they're a good starting point for anyone
who's looking to improve text to video
generation.
Uh, and we hope the community does.
Okay, the very last technical thing,
scaling laws. Um I've talked throughout
the whole talk today about architecture
unification across um modalities and
learning objectives and this was a
really nice result that we found uh at
the end of the project. So what you're
seeing here is a scaling law graph.
Um, how we use these when we're training
large language models is often when you
start training like a you know a GPT or
a U llama or whatever you have a certain
training budget. This is how many months
you have and how many GPUs you have for
that um period. Um but if you know that
training compute budget an open question
is how big your model should be. What
should be the optimal model size for
that compute budget? It could be a very
small model, you train for more um you
train for like more or a larger model,
you train for less. These scaling law
curves are for estimating the optimal
model size for a given compute budget.
So just looking at the blue crosses, we
plotted a few of these data points for a
movie gen. Remember movie gen text to
video model llama 3 architecture.
And looking at the blue crosses, we can
see this nice correlation we often see
in scaling laws with transformers. We
then overlaid the llama 3 scaling law.
So this is the scaling law for the text
model. Um and amazingly we see that the
llama 3 scaling law for this texton
model serves as a reasonable predictor
for model size and compute for video
generation. And this seems to hint that
scaling laws for transformers are maybe
modality independent which is like
pretty fascinating.
Okay, so um we're on the last part now.
What is next?
Um
movie gen did not solve uh video
generation.
Uh
there are still lots of problems. uh the
model will struggle with generating
complex motions uh from complex prompts.
Uh an example here is a dramatic scene
of two cars colliding at an
intersection.
So it's looking pretty good um at this
point. And then at some point near the
end they sort of I don't know what you'd
call that. They sort of independently
implode
um at one point the the silver car kind
of turns into two cars as well. So this
is a random generation from our model.
So you know text to video generation is
not solved.
So um my final slide
is
some ideas about where I think uh video
generation is going next. Things that
I'm sure we'll see some version of um at
some point soon. So um what is next? How
can we
solve the issues that you saw in the
previous slides? Well, the first kind of
obvious one is scaling everything more.
This has been like the story of machine
learning for the last um 6 years or
something. And I think this would like
definitely work. Movie jam was a 30
billion parameter model. It was based on
llama 3. The largest llama 3 model was
405b. I think scaling everything more
would would definitely result in far
higher quality generations.
Um some challenges there would be around
uh scaling data by like an order of
magnitude.
Um number two is reasoning.
Uh we've all seen the amazing benefits
in language modeling that have come from
reasoning in the last year or two. Um
here um the reasoning gives the model
the ability to sort of pause, think,
generate a chain of thought,
self-correct um before generating an
answer. Um
I think it's very clear that video
generation models would benefit from
this kind of reasoning capability as
well. I think that could result in a
step change. When all of us were looking
at the videos on the previous slide, it
was very clear, right, that something
was wrong. It looked like very obvious
to us. It doesn't seem um too
unfathomable to be able to imbue some
video generation model with the
capability to self-correct maybe see
that there is some errors in the video
that it generated and correct it.
Um
there are lots of like really
interesting research questions here like
what does it mean to generate a
reasoning trace for media generation?
You might have seen these like chain of
thoughts that are generated by like R1
or uh 03. Um I wonder what that looks
like for media generation. Uh the other
issue is is how to verify. So uh these
latest state-of-the-art reasoning
approaches are all trained with RL. RL
requires uh verification models to
verify the correctness of the outputs.
It's an open research question. What
that means for video generation? How do
you verify the correctness of a video?
Uh very lastly, we have native
generation. So, uh recent large language
models are natively multimodal. They can
generate text, they can do image
understanding, they can do video
understanding, some can even do image
generation. Um, so it's an interesting
question as to whether video generation
would also benefit from being thrown
into this uh native mix.
Um, and if so, there are interesting
questions around uh how you would train
such a thing. I've just talked you
through how flow matching seems to work
the best for video generation. Is there
a way that you can have multiple
learning objectives? Do you need to
unify the learning objectives? Uh,
things like that.
So, um, very lastly,
uh, it was a huge team that worked on
movie gen. Um, these are a bunch of
amazing researchers. I had so much fun
on this project, learned so much. Uh,
there are loads of good friends here.
Um, so yeah, shout outs to all of them.
So, yeah, I'm going to leave it on this
slide. Um, but we can do questions now
if there are any.
[Applause]
I guess
is
involved and a lot of these types of
architectures are unit based with helmet
kind of structures and that like so the
action diffusion policy surprisingly
like the combat architecture outperforms
the transformer architecture for action
fusion for robotics and uh and they ar
make an argument that it has an
inductive bias about smoothing so that
there's more consistency in the in the
spatial and the time domain and all that
great stuff. Um you know what do you say
back to that I guess?
Um
yeah so um I haven't read that
particular paper but it does sound like
a familiar um point. I guess the you
know the whole the whole theory around
architecture unification is that
we might have these specialized
architecture like like CNN's and uh they
hold these inductive biases around um
visual data like they um prioritize
these local interactions with the
convolutional mask and so on. And the
going idea has been that when you're
training at small scale uh having these
inductive biases helps Um but when
you're training at large scale and you
have enough data, you can sort of learn
all of these uh yourself with a
transformer in a less constrained um
setting.
We we have found that scaling
transformers here works better than
scaling these specialized architectures.
Um for a few reasons I mean it's not
it's not even to say that that I don't
think CNN's could scale. Um it seems as
though it's easier to scale
transformers. it's more straightforward
to know in which direction to scale. All
the infrastructure already exists. Um
but yeah, it's a very big debate. I'm
not I'm not like calling it.
Yeah.
Hey, can this model and approach be used
for 3D generation to like video games
and stuff like that?
Mhm.
So
if you go back to the architecture, um
it's totally modality independent.
So
for any this is for videos and images.
The important thing here is that we've
turned a modality into a sequence of
tokens. At this point after that
everything that's happening in the
architecture is modality independent. So
really for any new kind of data all you
need is a way of turning it into a
sequence of tokens.
um it may be um more challenging to uh
encode like that kind of data. Um but as
long as you can encode it in some way to
a series of tokens, you can use the
exact same approach. Yeah,
we have a lot of questions online as
well. So we can uh um I can read a few
of those right now. M um so one is so 16
seconds seems like the longest videos
you can effectively generate right now.
What are the main obstacles or things
keeping us from getting to longer for
example real movie length um
generations?
Um so the the main issue is is a
computational one. Well there there is
so many different answers to this. If
you're thinking from the movie gen setup
the issue is sequence length. Um, given
the level of compression that we had,
73K was pretty much the longest sequence
length we could feasibly train at. Um,
if you want to train on 32 second
videos, that's going to double. There
are multiple ways around this. You could
train an encoder with far more
compression and then you could uh get to
videos that long. There's another
question about um
learning objective. Um here we generate
everything at once. Uh there are lots of
papers out there that will iteratively
generate videos along the temporal axis.
You will generate a chunk and then
generate a new chunk conditioned on the
previous trunk kind of like next token
prediction. Um so I don't think there's
necessarily there there are lots of ways
around it and there are lots of
interesting papers that generate sort of
infinite length videos using these like
iterative processes.
boy. Um,
let me see.
Right, there's some questions on like
synthetic data compute. Um, so someone
says, you know, meta is a rare example
of having an abundance of training data.
Um, what if you know you run out of
video, then what's next, I guess.
Um,
I already know how to answer that. Um,
if we run out of video, um, look, I
think there's, uh,
I think that there's a lot of
interesting work to be done on improving
the um, data filtration
steps. So, you know, in this slide,
um, we were optimizing this for high
precision. So making sure that all the
videos at the end were very high
quality. Uh recall was sacrificed
throughout this. These are like very
computer vision tones. Um but we would
have lost a lot of good data in this
like very complex pipeline here. Uh one
like way forward for getting more data
is moving to smarter ways of doing this
process. Maybe completely language model
based for example.
Um
yeah I think that's one answer.
Um, a question about compute. This is
more general, I guess. How can academic
researchers contribute to video
generation without having, you know,
access to thousands of GPUs?
Yeah.
Yeah. It's it's obviously very tough to
do this level of pre-training outside of
um industry
labs. Um, but you know, throughout this
paper, we've used a bunch of innovations
that came from academia.
uh for example a lot of the flow
matching work was done at universities
uh the the main paper we take
inspiration from did come from uh meta
um but this kind of research can be done
at small scale and then all of us can
learn from it
um yeah the pre-training is is very
tough
um
yeah I think
The pre-training is tough, but things
like um things like learning objectives,
I think post training schemes, we've
seen a lot of like grade work coming out
of academia um for that. Yep.
A few questions all related to text, I
guess. Um some folks, you know, are
saying um there's a lot of work of
cleaning and um processing video data.
How do you make sure that the actual
text um for example the lema llama 3
generated captions are um high quality
and complete?
Um
yeah, good question. Um
we we put a lot of work into training
this llama 3 captioner basically. Uh so
this is a video conditioned llama model.
Uh this went through its own sort of
large scale training uh in order to
generate good-looking captions that were
aligned with uh what we wanted. Um but
certainly there's a lot of room for
improvement there. Uh these captions are
not as good as human written captions.
There are a lot of architectural reasons
for that. A lot of these like video
conditioned language models
um cannot see the whole video. If it's a
16-second video, it's 16 fps. Um, often
that's it's far too uh much video for
the for the model to be conditioned on.
So often with a lot of these open source
models like not only Llama, but but
Gemma and so on, you have to subsample
frames. Um, and so you're blocking the
model, the language model from seeing a
lot of the video. It's going to lead to
some issues, some missed things. So, we
do our best by training and
post-training a captioning model, doing
a bunch of evaluations on it, but that's
definitely something that can be
improved. And there's a bunch of really
cool results out there from the text to
image community showing that if you
improve captions, your image quality
gets better. It's not entirely clear
why, but but that keeps on happening.
Yeah, makes sense. Yeah. Um, someone
asked a related thing, which is how much
role or importance does the text or
prompt encoder play? um that were I I
think there were some image generation
works which showed like replacing the
text encoder I think it was from clip to
like T5 like
really helped improve performance. Did
you guys play around with like several
different um text encoders?
So uh this particular series of text
encodings uh was sort of precedent uh in
our team. Um, we took motivation from a
recent like state-of-the-art text to
image uh paper that used this series of
text encodings. But it, you know, it's
worth pointing out here that this is, it
is quite strange what we've done here.
Um,
you would think it would be like
intuitive that you want your best
possible text representation here.
All of these text representations are
nowhere near state-of-the-art. They're
not llama. They're not GPT. Um
there's been a few works and empirical
findings showing that in this setup at
least uh decoder only text
representations don't work as well for
some reason. Um
some reasons for that could be or some
have hypothesized that you need a text
representation that is more aligned with
the media space. That's why a lot of
people you'll see conditioning on clip
which is what we do. Um,
so yeah, a bunch of cool work to do
here. We didn't um ablate this in this
project though.
I have a question followed up on the
text part. Um, how well would this do on
with like very detailed prompts like
uh I want to move a video about this
person wearing this specific color and
here's what happens later on and then
like a very detailed script rather than
you know just a video of of some
penguins I guess.
We we definitely did observe that uh the
model can do these sequential actions um
but not always completely accurately.
Um some of that might be issues in the
captioning of the pre-training data um
like are you accurately captioning all
of these things happening. Um but yeah
that will be one of the places where it
struggles if you were to detail like
three or four things happening in
sequence. Yeah,
we have one question which is could you
somehow hardcode in some priors related
to physics and real world common sense
um to improve the realism and accuracy
of generated videos? I guess that might
be related to that video of like the car
splitting and all of that.
Yeah. Um
yeah. So
in a way it's kind of like the
antithesis of of
the the things that we were trying here
of like removing all of the inductive
biases and just scaling uh compute and
data. Um but I do think those are
interesting things to try simply because
um maybe if you are trying to learn the
laws of physics better just random
videos from like a large pool aren't
maybe the best thing to use there. Um
there are
other cool works that have been released
where they're trained like entirely on
video game data, things like that. Um
yeah, I think um I think encoding some
sort of prize would be would be cool.
Yeah, because you know there are certain
things about the natural world that we
do know for sure. Um certain like
computer vision principles and so on. Um
but yeah, we didn't do that here.
You know how possibly encode those? Yep.
That's like a super open question.
Super open question. Okay, makes sense.
We got a couple others online and then
we can go back to in person. Um, one's
more on, you know, deep fakes and
malicious use of video generation
models. Is there any work on things like
watermarking to sort of deal with that?
There's definitely a bunch of work on
watermarking.
Um
we
yeah there's definitely a bunch of work
on on watermarking coming from a a few
groups. Uh DeepMind has released a few
interesting uh papers on it. Uh MESA has
a team working on this as well. Um so
yeah very important work to be done.
Yeah
I'll
read one more and then we can go back to
some in-person questions. Um one's about
GANs actually. Um, I've noticed some
older models have a GAN discriminator
before or in the decoder for temporal
coherence. Is this still useful or does
scale overcome this need?
They mean in the VA decoder.
Um, I I think so.
Yeah. So, we we also have again
discriminator there. Um,
it's not necessarily for temporal
consistency. Um,
that might be one of the outcomes.
Um there's sort of a historical
precedent for this.
um when you are training these
where is it when you're training these
VAEs
um folk found it was the stable
diffusion researchers actually while
they were still at um college in Germany
um they published this paper called VQ
GAN uh back in 2021 I think um and they
showed that normally how you train these
VAEs is that you just use L1 losses
between the input and the output um but
they found that the amount of
compression you could was very limited
when you were doing that. So what they
started doing was adding some
adversarial losses um from the GAN
literature. What this does is it tells
the VAE that I don't have to decode
exactly what was given to me. Um because
the GAN losses, they're not L1 losses,
they're not pixel level losses. These
losses are just how well the GAN can
tell if it's a real image or a fake one.
So when folks started training VAEs with
these losses um the outputs would were
given a bit more freedom. So the model
could generate a range of things for a
certain input and it it's not getting
penalized from the loss as long as they
look real. And I realize there's a bunch
of detail there but basically by adding
these losses we were able to get like
another um 2x level of compression. Uh
so we are also using adversarial losses
in the VA if that was their question.
Someone added an interesting question
just now which is
um how much you might how might you make
sure all the videos in your training
data are real. Um what if some of them
are fake? I guess that's related to some
work nowadays in language models about
you know once um more and more training
data becomes synthetically generated
does that lead to any issues I guess.
Yeah,
definitely this idea of like uh data set
poisoning it's often called is a
problem.
Um I think there are a couple
interesting
question answers to this. Firstly in our
pre-training data um if it's low quality
then we don't want to train on it and
hopefully we would find it and get rid
of it. But training on generated data is
not always a bad thing. Um, most
contemporary post-training approaches
for language models are based upon
training on generated data. You train on
generations from the model itself. So,
it's not like training on generated data
is always bad. Um, if there's some
really like bad generated videos in the
pre-training data, we do want to get rid
of those. Um,
but it's not always bad.
We got time for a couple more inperson
questions. If
I understand.
Um in in the paper we included like full
details of the training infrastructure
that will be there. I don't I don't
think we included any details about the
um inference infrastructure.
Um there are lots of details on the
infer in the paper. I would recommend
you to go there. Yeah.
Any other questions?
I don't know if I missed that but for
the videos you generated do they come
with audio?
Yeah. So um this text to video model
that I've shown here it generates video
but uh with the publication we um
release a well published about
a where is this? Uh actually no we're
not going over that problem again.
There's no audio.
Yes.
So there w yeah there was a separate
movie gen audio model that we trained
that will add audio to a generated
video.
video as two separate models and the
audio is like another level of
complexity where there are like multiple
tracks and if you want to try mini files
for
like
what
this oil generation
um
so
we have we have a really great audio
research team that worked on this. Um,
one very nice thing to do, I think,
would be to generate everything at once,
uh, like video and audio. The two
modalities are very correlated. There's
a lot of shared information. So,
theoretically,
both modalities should benefit from
being trained together. The audio even
encodes some information about videos
that are not present in the video. Um,
the issue is one of data. Uh, it's very
hard to get high quality video data.
It's even harder to get high quality
video with good audio data. Um, so
that's part of the reason why we didn't
do that for this project. Yeah.
Awesome. Thanks so much, Andrew, for the
um very insightful talk and answering
all our questions.