hi everyone welcome to cs25 Transformers
United video
this was a course that was solid
Stanford in the winter 2023
this course is not about robots that can
transform into cars as this picture
might suggest rather it's about deep
learning models that have taken the
World by the storm and have
revolutionized the field of AI and
others starting from natural language
processing Transformers have been
applied all over from computer vision
enforcement learning biology robotics
Etc
we have an exciting set of videos lined
up for you with some truly fascinating
speakers skip talks
presenting how they're applying
Transformers to the research in
different fields and areas
we hope you'll enjoy and learn from
these videos
so without any further Ado let's get
started
this is a purely introductory lecture
and we'll go into the building blocks of
Transformers
so first let's start with introducing
the instructors
uh so for me I'm currently on a
temporary data Pro from the PHD program
and I'm leading AI to robotic startup
that I've added robotics so we're
working on some general purpose robots
uh somewhat like customer and
um yeah I'm very passionate about
Robotics and building assistive learning
algorithms my research interests are in
daily personal learning competitions in
Remodeling and I have a bunch of
Publications in a robot take part
numbers driving on the areas
um underground deposit Cornell if
somebody spoke for now so nice to meet
you
so I'm Stephen uh from the first year
CSP school here uh Pierce did my masters
at CMU and undergrad I wanted mainly
into NLP research anything involving
language and text
um but more recently I've been getting
more into computer vision as well
and just some stuff I do for fun a lot
of music stuff mainly piano some self
promo but I post a lot on my insta
YouTube and Tick Tock so if you guys
want to check it out
um my friends and I are also starting a
Stanford piano books if anybody's
interested feel free to email the DM me
for details
um other than that you know martial arts
bodybuilding
huge fan of k-dramas anime
occasional gamer
my name is Rylan um instead of talking
about myself
I just went super excited
the last one was off sorry to teach this
about excuse me I took it the last time
it was offered I did a bunch of fun
um I thought we brought in a really
great uh group of speakers last time I'm
super excited for this offering
um and yeah I'm thankful you're all here
and I'm looking forward to a really fun
quarter again thank you yeah it's a fun
fact Brandon was the most outspoken
student last year and it's like someone
wants to become instructed next year
yeah
okay
cool
um
so what we hope you will learn in this
class is first of all how do
Transformers work
um how they're being applied yes
definitely and nowadays like we are
pretty much using them everywhere in
yeah machine learning
um and lots of some new interesting
directions of research uh in this topics
uh cool so this class is just an
introductory so we're just talking about
the basics of Transformers introducing
them talking about the self attention
mechanism on which they're founded and
uh we'll do a deep dive more on like uh
models like birds GPD so get happy to
get solid
um okay so let me start with presenting
the attention timeline
uh attention all started with this one
paper transform attention is already at
l in 2017 that was the beginning of
Transformers
um before that we had the previous
historic error where we had models like
uh RNN lstms
um and their simple attention mechanisms
that will possible therefore
uh starting 2017 we solved this uh
explosion of Transformers into NLP where
people started using it for everything I
even heard the support from Google it's
like a performance increase every time
you fight our linguists uh
for the first 2018 after 2018 to 2020 we
saw this explosion of Transformers into
other few like question
um a bunch of other stuff and uh like
biology Alpha folded and in last year
2021 was the start of alternative era
where we got like a lot of opportunity
modeling uh started like almost like
kodaks uh GPT Davi stable diffusion
server a lot of like things happening in
uh genetic performance and uh and so we
actually started getting up in here
um and now is the present so this is uh
2022 and like the startup 2013 and now
we have models like uh chatricity
whisper
um a bunch of others and we are like
scaling onwards uh without spelling now
so that's great uh so that's the future
so going more into this um
so once there were elements so we have
people specific models lstns giu uh what
worked here was that they're good at
encoding history but what did not work
was they didn't and for long sequences
and they were very bad at encoding
context
uh so consider this example
consider trying to predict the last word
uh in the text I grew up in France dot
dot dot I speak fluent Dash here you
need to understand the context for it to
predict French and uh like attention
mechanism is very good at that whereas
if they're just using lstms uh it
doesn't work that well
uh another thing Transformers are good
at is
more based on content is like also
context prediction is like uh finding uh
attention Maps if I have uh something
like a word like it what noun does it
connect to and we can give a like a
probability attention on what are the
possible activations
um and this works with better than uh
existing mechanisms
okay
uh so where we were in 2021 we were on
the verge of takeoff we were starting to
realize the potential of Transformers in
different fields uh we solved a lot of
long sequence problems like uh protein
folding Alpha fold of NRL uh
we started to see three shots zero short
generalization we saw multimodal tasks
and applications like generating images
from language so that was Dali
um uh yeah and it feels like Asian but
personally like two years ago
and this is also a talk on Transformers
that you can watch on YouTube uh
yeah cool
um and this is where we was going from
2021 to 2022 which is we have gone from
the virtual thinking of actually taking
off and now we are seeing unique
applications and audio generation art
music storytelling we are starting to
see reasoning capabilities like Common
Sense uh logical reasoning mathematical
reasoning we are also able to now get
human Enlightenment and interaction
they're able to use a investment
learning and human feedback that's how
activity is trained to perform really
good uh we have a lot of mechanisms
spoken during toxicity bias in uh ethics
now and there are a lot of also a lot of
developments in other areas like
division models
cool
uh
so the feature is a spaceship and we're
all excited about it
um and there's a lot of more
applications that we can enable
um and uh it'll be great uh if you can
see Transformers also work there uh one
big example is with your understanding
and generation that is something that
everyone is interested in and I'm hoping
we'll see a lot of models in this area
this year uh also Finance uh business
um I'll be very excited to see gbt
author novel uh but we need to solve
very long sequence modeling and the most
transformative models are still limited
to like four thousand tokens or
something like that so we need to do a
make them generalize much more better on
Long sequences uh we are also we also
want to have generalized agents that can
do a lot of multi-task uh
automatic input
uh predictions like gato and uh so I
think we will see more of that too and
finally
um we also want domain specific models
so you might want like a GPD model let's
put it like maybe like you have so that
could be like a doctor GPT model you
might have like a large GPT model that's
like going on only on Law data So
currently we have like gbd models that
have trained on everything but we might
start to see more Niche models that are
like good at one task and we could have
like a mixture of experts so like you
can think like this is a like how you
normally consult an expert will have
like expert AI models and you can go to
a different air model for your different
needs
um there's still a lot of missing
ingredients uh to make this all
successful uh the the first of all is
external memory uh we are already
starting to see this with the models
like chantipity where uh the infections
are short-lived there's no long-term
memory and they don't have ability to
remember that our store conversations
for long term uh and uh this is
something we want to fix
uh second hour second is reducing the
computation complexity so attention
mechanism is quadratic over the sequence
plan which is slurred and uh we want to
radio ceramic faster uh
another thing you want to do is we want
to enhance the controllability of these
models like a lot of the smalls can be
stochastic and we want to be able to
control what sort of outputs we get from
them
um and you might have experienced the 10
GPT which is refresh you get like
different output each time but you might
want to have a mechanism that controls
what sort of things you can uh and
finally we want to align our state of
art language models with how the human
brain works and uh we are seeing the
search but we still need more research
on seeing how it can be more important
okay thank you
great bye uh yes I'm excited to be here
uh I live very nearby so I got the
invites to come to class and I was like
okay I'll just walk over
um but then I spent like 10 hours on
those slots so it wasn't as simple uh so
yeah I want to talk about uh
Transformers I'm going to skip the first
two over there we're not going to talk
about those we're going to talk about
that one just to simplify the lecture
since we've done a Time
um
okay so I wanted to provide a little bit
of context of why does this Transformers
class even exist so a little bit of
historical context I feel like Bilbo
over there I joined uh like telling you
guys about this um and I think I saw a
little drinks uh and basically I joined
AI in roughly 2012 simple course so
maybe a decade ago and back then you
wouldn't even say that you joined AI by
the way that was like a dirty word uh
now it's okay to talk about but back
then it was not even deep learning it
was machine learning that was a term
reviews uh if you were serious but now
um now ai is okay to use I think uh so
basically do you even realize how lucky
you are potentially entering this area
in roughly going through three uh so
back then in 2011 or so when I was
working specifically on computer vision
um
your your pipelines looked like this
um so you wanted to classify some images
uh you would go to a paper and I think
this is representative you would have
three pages in the paper describing all
kinds of a zoo of kitchen sink of
different kinds of features descriptors
and you would go to um poster session
and in computer Vision conference and
everyone would have their favorite
feature descriptors that they're
proposing and it's totally ridiculous
and you would take notes on like which
one you should incorporate into your
pipeline because you would extract all
of them and then you would put an svm on
top so that's what you would do so
there's two pages make sure you get your
histograms your ssims your color
histograms textiles tiny images and
don't forget the geometry specific
histograms all of them have basically
complicated code by themselves so you're
collecting code from everywhere and
running it and it was total nightmare so
that on top of that it also didn't work
so this would be I think representative
prediction from that time uh you would
just get predictions like this once in a
while and you'd be like you just shrub
your shoulders like that just happens
once in a while today you would be
looking for a bug
um and worse than that
every single
um every single sort of feel of every
single chunk of AI had their own
completely separate vocabulary that they
work with so if you go to an if you go
to NLP papers those papers would be
completely different so you're reading
the NLP paper and you're like what is uh
this part of speech tagging
morphological analysis syntactic parsing
co-reference resolution what is mpbt KJ
and you're confused so the vocabulary
and everything was completely different
and you couldn't read papers I would say
across different areas
so now that changed a little bit
starting 2012 when uh you know askewsky
and the colleagues basically
demonstrated that if you scale a large
neural network on large data set you can
get very strong performance and so up
till then there was a lot of focus on
algorithms but this showed that actually
neural Nets scale very well so you need
to now worry about compute and data and
you can scale it up it works pretty well
and then that recipe actually did copy
paste across many areas of AI so we
start to see a neural networks pop up
everywhere since 2012.
um so we saw them in computer vision and
NLP and speech and translation in RL and
so on so everyone started to use the
same kind of modeling toolkit model
framework and now when you go to NLP and
you start reading papers there in
machine translation for example uh this
is a sequel to sequence to paper which
we'll come back to in a bit you start to
read those papers and you're like okay I
can recognize these words like there's a
neural network there's some parameter
there's an Optimizer and it starts to
read like things that you know of so
that's a decreased tremendously the
barrier to entry across the different
areas
and then I think the big deal is that
when the Transformer came out in 2017
it's not even that just the toolkits and
the neural networks were similar is that
literally the architecture is converged
to like one architecture that you copy
paste across everything seemingly so
this was kind of an unassuming uh
machine translation paper at the time
proposing the Transformer architecture
but what we found since then is that you
can just uh basically copy paste this
architecture and use it everywhere and
what's changing is the details of the
data and the chunking of the data and
how you feed them and you know that's a
caricature but it's kind of like a
correct first order statement and uh so
now papers are even more similar looking
because everyone's just using
Transformer and uh so this convergence
is was remarkable to watch and unfolded
the last decade and it's pretty crazy to
me what I found kind of interesting is I
think this is some kind of a hint that
we're maybe converging to something that
maybe the brain is doing because uh the
brain is very homogeneous and uniform
across the entire sheet of your cortex
and okay maybe some of the details are
changing but those build like hyper
parameters but like a Transformer but
your auditory cortex and your visual
cortex and everything else looks very
similar and so maybe we're converging to
some kind of a uniform powerful learning
algorithm here uh something like that I
think is kind of interesting
okay so I want to talk about where the
Transformer came from very Point
historically
so I want to start in 2003 I like this
paper uh quite a bit it was the first
sort of um
popular application of neural networks
to the problem of language modeling so
predicting in this case the next word in
the sequence which allows you to build
generative models over text and in this
case they were using multi-layer
perceptron so very simple neural web the
neural Nets took three words and
predicted the probability distribution
for the fourth word in a sequence uh so
this was uh well and good at this point
now over time people started to apply
this to a machine translation so that
brings us to sequence to sequence paper
from 2014 that was pretty influential
and the big problem here was okay we
don't just want to take three words and
predict the four we want to predict how
to go from an English sentence to a
French sentence and the key problem was
okay you can have arbitrary number of
words in English an arbitrary number of
words in French so how do you get an
architecture that can process this
variably sized input and so here they
use a lstm and there there's basically
two chunks of this which are covered by
the slack by the um
by this but basically have an encoder
lstm on the left and it just consumes uh
the work one word at a time and builds
up a context of what it has read and
then that acts as a conditioning Vector
to the decoder RNN or lstm that
basically goes chong chong chunk for the
next word in the sequence uh translating
the English to French or something like
that now the big problem with this that
people identified I think very quickly
and tried to resolve is that there's
what's called this um encoder bottleneck
so this entire English sentence that we
are trying to condition on is packed
into a single Vector that goes from the
encoder for the decoder and so this is
just too much information to potentially
maintain a single vector and that didn't
seem correct and so people are looking
around for ways to alleviate the
attention of sorry the um encoded
bottleneck as it was called at the time
and so that brings us to this paper
neural machine translation by jointly
learning to align and translate and
that here just moving from the abstract
in this paper we conjectured that the
use of a fixed lung Vector is a
bottleneck in improving the performance
of the basic encoder decoder
architecture and propose to extend this
by allowing the model to automatically
soft search for parts of the source
sentence that are relevant to predicting
a Target word
um yeah without having to form these
parts or hard segments explicitly so
this was a way to look back to the words
that are coming from the encoder and it
was achieved using this soft search so
as you are decoding in the
the words here while you are decoding
them you are allowed to look back at the
words at the encoder via this soft uh
attention mechanism proposed in this
paper and so this paper I think is the
first time that I saw basically uh
attention
um so your context Vector that comes
from the encoder is a weighted sum of
the Hidden states of the words in the um
in the encoding and then the weights of
this sum come from a soft Max that is
based on these compatibilities between
the current state as you're decoding and
the hidden States uh generated by the
encoder and so this is the percent that
really you start to like look at it and
and this is the current modern equations
of the attention and I think this was
the perspective that I saw it in it's
the first time that uh there's a word
attention used as far as I know to call
this mechanism so actually try to dig
into the details of the history of the
attention uh so the first author here
Dimitri I um I had an email
correspondence with him and I basically
sent him an email I'm like Dimitri this
is really interesting Transformers have
taken over where did you come up with
the self-detension mechanism that ends
up being the heart of the Transformer
and uh to my surprise he wrote me back
this like massive email which was really
fascinating so this is an excerpt from
that email
um
so basically he talks about how he was
looking for a way to avoid this
bottleneck between the encoder and
decoder he had some ideas about the
cursors that traversed the sequences
that didn't quite work out and then here
so one day I had this thought that it
would be nice to enable the decoder RNN
to learn to search where to put the
cursor on the source sequence this was
sort of inspired by translation
exercises that um learning English in my
middle school involved you gaze shifts
back and forth between source and Target
sequence as you translate so literally I
thought this was kind of interesting
that he's not a native English speaker
and here that gave him an edge in this
machine translation that read to led to
attention and then led the Transformer
so that was that's really fascinating
um I expressed a soft search a soft Max
and then weighted averaging of the
bironial states and basically uh to my
great excitement this word this word
from the very first try so really I
think interesting piece of history and
as it later turned out that the name of
RNN search was uh kind of lame so the
better name attention came from Yeshua
on one of the final passes as they went
over the paper so maybe attention is all
you need would have been called like RNs
or just
but we have Yeshua NGO to thank for a
little bit of a better name I would say
so apparently that's the the history of
this
okay so that brings us to 2017 which is
attention is all you need so this
attention component which in uh
Dimitri's paper was just like one small
segment and there's all this
bi-directional RNN RNN and decoder and
this Tesla modeling paper is saying okay
you can actually delete everything like
what's making this work very well is
just detection by itself and so delete
everything keep attention and then
what's remarkable about this paper
actually is usually you see papers that
are very incremental they add like one
thing uh and they still get it's better
but I feel like attention is all in need
was like a mix of multiple things at the
same time they were combined in a very
unique way
and then also achieved a very good local
minimum in the architecture space and so
to me this is a really a landmark paper
that um
and it's quite quite remarkable and I
think had quite a lot of work behind the
scenes
um so delete all the RNN just keep
attention because attention is operates
over sets and I'm going to go into this
in a second you now need to positionally
encode your inputs because attention
doesn't have the notion of space right
so
um
I should be very careful
um they adopted this residual Network
structure from resonance uh they
interspersed attention with multilio
perceptrons they they use layer Norms
which came from a different paper they
introduced the concept of multiple heads
of attention that were applied in
parallel and they gave us I think like a
fairly good set of hyper parameters that
to this day are used so the expansion
factor in the multiple perceptron goes
up by 4X so we'll go into like a bit
more detail and this borax has stuck
around and I believe like there's a
number of papers that tried to play with
all kinds of little details of the
Transformer and nothing like sticks
because this is actually quite good the
only thing to my knowledge that stock
that that didn't stick was this uh we
shuffling up the layer Norms to go into
the pre-norm uh version where here you
see the layer Norms are after the
multi-headed detection RP forward but
they just put them before instead so
just reshuffling of layer Norms but
otherwise the gpts and everything else
that you're seeing today is basically
the 2017 architecture from five years
ago and even though everyone is working
on it it's proven remarkably resilient
which I think is uh there are
innovations that I think have been
adopted also in positional encodings
it's more common to use different rotary
and relative positional encodings and so
on uh so I think there have been changes
but for the most part it's proven very
resilient
so really quite an interesting paper now
I wanted to go into the attention
mechanism
um and I think I sort of like the way I
interpret it is not
is not similar to the ways that I've
seen it presented before so let me try a
different way
um of like how I see it basically to me
attention is kind of like the
communication phase of the Transformer
and the Transformer interludes two
phases uh the communication phase which
is the multi-headed attention and the
computation stage which is uh this
multilio perceptron or P1 so in the
communication phase uh it's really just
a data dependent message passing on
directed graphs and you can think of it
as okay forget everything with a machine
translation and everything let's just we
have directed graphs at each a node you
are storing a vector and then
um let me talk now about the
communication phase of how these vectors
talk to each other in this directive
graph and then the compute phase later
is just the multiple perceptron which
now which then
um basically acts on every note
individually but how do these notes talk
to each other in this directed graph so
I wrote like some simple python uh like
I wrote this in Python basically to to
create one round of communication of uh
using attention as the uh direct as the
um Master passing scheme so here
a node has this private data Vector as
you can think of it as private
information to this node and then it can
also emit a key a query and a value and
simply that's done by a linear
transformation uh from this node so the
key is
um what are the things that I am
um
sorry the query is one of the things
that I'm looking for the key is where
the thing that I have and the value is
one of the things that I will
communicate
and so then when you have your graph
that's made up of nodes and some random
edges when you actually have these nodes
communicating what's happening is you
Loop over all the nodes individually in
some random order and you you are at
some node and you get the query Vector Q
which is common node and some graph and
uh this is what I'm looking for and so
let's just achieved via this longer
transformation here and then we look at
all the inputs that point to this node
and then they broadcast what are the
things that I have which is their keys
so they broadcast the keys I have the
query then those interact by dot product
to get scores so basically uh simply by
doing Dot product you get some kind of a
unnormalized weighting well the
interestingness of all of the
information in my uh in the nodes that
point to me and to the things I'm
looking for and then when you normalize
that with a soft Max so it just sums to
one uh you basically just end up using
those scores which now sum to one in our
probability distribution and you do a
weighted sum of the values uh to get
your update so I have a query they have
keys uh dot products to get
interestingness or like Affinity softmax
to normalize it and then we get some of
those values flow to me and update me
and this is happening for each node
individually and then we update at the
end and so this kind of a message
passing scheme is kind of like at the
heart of the Transformer and happens in
a more vectorized uh batched way that is
more confusing and is also intersberg
with interspersonal layer norms and
things like that to make the training uh
behave better but that's roughly what's
happening in the attention mechanism I
think on a high level
um
so yeah so in the communication phase of
the Transformer
um then this message passing scheme
happens in every head in parallel and
then in every layer in series
um and with different weights each time
and that's the that's that's it as far
as the multi-headed tension goes and so
if you look at these encoder decoder
models you can sort of think of it then
in terms of the connectivity of these
nodes in the graph you can kind of think
of it as like okay all these tokens that
are in the encoder that we want to
condition on they are fully connected to
each other so in when they communicate
they communicate fully when you
calculate their features but in the
decoder because we are trying to have a
language model we don't want to have
communication from future tokens because
they give away the answer at this step
so the tokens in the decoder are fully
connected from all the encoder States
and then they are all Simply Connected
from everything that is important and so
you end up with this like triangular
structure in the direct graph but that's
the message passing scheme that this
basically implements
um and then you have to be also a little
bit careful because in the cross
attention here with the decoder you
consume the features from the top of the
encoder so um think of it as in the
encoder all the nodes are looking at
each other all the tokens are looking at
each other many many times and they
really figure out what's in there and
then the decoder when it's it's looking
only at the top notes
so that's roughly the message passing
scheme I was going to go into more of an
implementation of the Transformer I
don't know if there's any questions
about this group
self-advention but what is this
yeah so um
self protection and multi-headed
detection so the multi-headed attention
is just this attention scheme but it's
just applied uh multiple times in
parallel multiple heads just means
independent applications of the same
attention
so this message passing scheme basically
just happens uh in parallel multiple
times with different weights for the
query key and value so you can almost
look at it like in parallel I'm looking
for I'm seeking different kinds of
information from different nodes that
I'm collecting it all in the same note
it's all done in parallel
so heads is really just like copy paste
in parallel and layers are copy paste
but in series
maybe that makes sense
and self-attention when it's
self-attention what it's referring to is
that the node here
um produces each node here so as I
described it here this is really soft
ocean because every one of these nodes
produces a key query and a value from
this individual node when you have cross
attention
you have one cross attention here
um coming from the encoder that just
means that the queries are still
produced from this node but the piece
and the values are produced as a
function of nodes that are coming from
the encoder
so um I have my queries because I'm
trying to decode some the fifth word in
the sequence and I I'm looking for
certain things because I'm the fifth
word and then the keys and the values in
terms of the source of information that
could answer my queries can come from
the previous nodes in the current
decoding sequence or from the top of the
encoder so all the nodes that have
already seen all of the all of the
encoding tokens many many times cannot
broadcast what they contain in terms of
information
so
I guess to summarize the self-attention
is kind of like sorry cross attention
and self-attention only differ in where
the piece and the values come from
either the keys and values are produced
from this node or they are produced from
some external Source like like an
encoder and the notes over there but
algorithmically is the is the same
Michael
operations
okay
so yeah so um
um
so think of
um so each one of these nodes is a token
um
I guess like they don't have a very good
picture of it in the Transformer but
like
um
like this node here could represent the
uh third word in the output in the
decoder and
um in the beginning it is just the
embedding of the word
um
and then um
okay I have to think through this
knowledge a little bit more I came up
with it this morning
one example substantiation
uh these notes are basically the factors
um I'll go to an implementation I'll go
to the implementation and then maybe
I'll make the connections uh to the
graph so let me try to first go to let
me not go to with this intuition in mind
at least uh to Nano GPT which is a
complete implementation of a transformer
that is very minimal so I worked on this
over the last few days and here it is
reproducing gpt2 on open webtext uh so
it's a pretty serious implementation and
reproduces gpd2 I would say and uh
provided in the computer this was one
node of atpus for 38 hours or something
like that remember correctly and it's
very readable it's 300 lives so everyone
can take a look at it
um and uh yeah let me basically briefly
step through it
so let's try to have a decoder only
Transformer so what that means is that
it's a language model it tries to model
the
um the next word in the sequence or the
next character in the sequence so the
data that we train on is always some
kind of text so here's some fake
Shakespeare sorry this is real
Shakespeare we're going to produce a big
Shakespeare so this is called the tiny
Shakespeare data set which is one of my
favorite toy data sets you take all of
Shakespeare concatenate it and it's one
megawatt file and then you can train
language models on it and get infinite
Shakespeare if you like which I think is
kind of cool
so we have a text the first thing we
need to do is we need to convert it to a
sequence of integers because
Transformers natively process
um you know um you can plug text into
Transformer you need to some out encoded
so the way that encoding is done is we
convert for example in a simplest case
every character gets an integer
and then instead of hi there we would
have this sequence of integers
so then you can encode every single
um character as an integer and get like
a massive sequence of integers you just
concatenate it all into one large long
one-dimensional sequence and then you
can train on it now here we only have a
single document in some cases if you
have multiple independent documents what
people like to do is create special
tokens and they intersperse those
documents with those special end of text
tokens uh that they splice in between to
create boundaries but those boundaries
actually don't have any
um any modeling impact it's just that
the Transformer is supposed to learn via
back propagation that the end of
document sequence means that you should
wipe the memory
okay so then we produce batches so these
batches of data just mean that we go
back to the one-dimensional sequence and
we take out chunks of this sequence so
say if the block size is eight uh then
the block size indicates the um maximum
length of context that your Transformer
will process so if our block size is
eight that means that we are going to
have up to eight characters of context
to predict the ninth character in a
sequence and the batch size indicates
how many sequences in parallel we're
going to process and we want this to be
as large as possible so we're fully
taking advantage of the GPU and the
parallels under the chords so in this
example we're doing a four by eight
batches so every row here is independent
example sort of and then every um
every uh every a row here is a is a
small chunk of the sequence that we're
going to train on and then we have both
the inputs and the targets at every
single point here
so to fully spell out what's contained
in a single four by eight batch to the
Transformer uh I sort of like compact it
here so when the input is 47 by itself
the target is 58 and when the input is
the sequence 4758 the target is one and
when it's 47.581 the target is 51 and so
on so actually the single batch of
examples that score by eight actually
has a ton of individual examples that we
are expecting the Transformer to learn
on in um in parallel and so you'll see
that the batches are learned on
completely independently but the uh the
time Dimensions sort of here along
horizontally is also trained on in
parallel so sort of your your real back
size is more like B times d it's just
that the context grows linearly for the
predictions that you make along the T
Direction
um in the in the model so this is how
the this is all the examples of the
model will learn from this single back
so now this is the uh GPT class
and uh because this is a decoder only
model
um so we're not going to have an encoder
because there's no like English We're
translating from we're not trying to
condition on some other external
information we're just trying to produce
a uh sequence of words that follow each
other are likely to
so this is all pytorch and I'm going
slightly faster because I'm assuming
people have taken 231n or something
along those lines
um but here in the forward pass we take
this uh these indices
and then we both encode the identity of
the indices just via an embedding lookup
table so every single integer has a uh
we index into a lookup table of vectors
in this nn.embedding and pull out the
the um word Vector for that token and
then because the message because
transformed by itself doesn't actually
it processes sets natively so we need to
also positionally encode these vectors
so that we basically have both the
information about the token identity and
its place in the sequence from one to
block size
now those uh the information about what
and where is combined additively so the
token embeddings and the positional
embeddings are just added exactly as
here
so this x here
uh then there's optional Dropout this x
here basically just contains the set of
uh words
um and their positions
and that feeds into the blocks of
Transformer and we're going to look into
what's blocked here but for here for now
this is just a series of blocks in a
Transformer and then in the end there's
a layer norm and then you're decoding
the logits for the next
um word or next integer in a sequence
using a linear projection of the of the
output of this Transformer so LM head
here a shortcore language model head is
just a linear function
uh so basically positionally encode all
the words feed them into a sequence of
blocks and then apply a linear layer to
get the probability distribution for the
next uh character and then if we have
the targets which we produced in uh the
data loader and you'll notice that the
targets are just the inputs offset by
one in time
then those targets feed into a
cross-entropy loss so this is just a
negative one likelihood typical
classification loss so now let's drill
into what's here in the blocks
uh so these blocks that are applied
sequentially
um there's again as I mentioned
communicate base and the compute base so
in the communicate phase all the nodes
get to talk to each other and so these
nodes are basically
if our block size is eight then we are
going to have eight nodes in this graph
there's eight notes in this graph the
first node is pointed to only by itself
the second node is pointed to by the
first node and itself the third node is
pointed to by the first two nodes and
itself Etc so there's eight nodes here
so you apply there's a residual pathway
in X you take it out you apply a layer
norm and then the cell potential so that
these communicate these eight nodes
communicate but you have to keep in mind
that the dash is four so because batches
four this is also applied uh so we have
eight nodes communicating but there's a
batch of four of them all individually
communicating one those eight nodes
there's no crisscross across the fashion
motion of course there's no bash online
um and then once they change information
they are processed using the multilio
perceptron and that's the compute phase
so um and then also here we are missing
we are missing the cross attention
um and uh because this is a decoder only
model so all we have is this step here
the multi-headed retention and that's
the Slime the communicate phase and then
we have the feed forward which is the
MLP and that's the complete phase
I'll take I'll take questions a bit
later
then the MLP here is fairly
straightforward the MLP is just
individual processing on each node
um just transforming the feature
representation sort of at that node so
um applying a two-layer neural net with
a gallery nonlinearity which is just
think of it as a relu or something like
that it's just anonymity
and then MLP straightforward I don't
think there's anything too crazy there
and then this is the causal soft
retention part the communication phase
so this is kind of like the neat of
things and the most complicated part
it's only complicated because of the
batching
and the implementation detail of how you
mask the connectivity in the graph so
that you don't you can't obtain any
information from the future when you're
predicting your token otherwise it gives
away information so if I'm the fifth
token and
um if I'm the fifth position then I'm
getting the fourth token coming into the
input and I'm attending to the third
second and first and I'm trying to
figure out what is the what is the next
token well then in this batch in the
next element over in the time Dimension
the answer is at the input so I can't
get any information from there so that's
why this is all tricky but basically in
the forward pass
um we are calculating the the queries
keys and values based on x
so these are the key squares and values
here when I'm Computing the attention I
have the queries The Matrix multiplying
the keys so this is the dot product in
parallel for all the queries and all the
keys in all the heads so that I
mentioned I thought to mention that
there's also the aspect of the heads
which is also done old in parallel here
so we have the batch Dimension the time
Dimension and the head Dimension and you
end up with five dimensional tensors and
it's all really confusing so I invite
you to step through it later and
convince yourself that this is actually
doing the right thing but basically
basically you have the batch Dimension
the head Dimension and the time
Dimension and then you have features at
them and so uh this is evaluating for
all the batch elements for all the head
elements and all the time elements
the simple python that I gave you
earlier which is query.proc T
then here we do a mask still and what
this is doing is it's basically clamping
the um
the attention between the nodes that are
not supposed to communicate to be
negative infinity and we're doing
negative Infinity because we're about to
soft Max and so negative Infinity will
make basically the attention that those
elements be zero
and so here we are going to basically
end up with uh the weights
um the the sort of affinities between
these nodes
optional Dropout and then here attention
Matrix multiply V is basically the um
the Gathering of the information
according to the affinities we've
calculated and this is just a weighted
sum of the values at all those nodes so
this Matrix multiplies as doing that we
could sum
and then transpose contiguous view
because it's all complicated and bashed
in five dimensional testers but it's
really not doing anything optional
Dropout and then a linear projection
back to the residual pathway
so this is implementing the
communication phase here
then you can train this Transformer
um
and then you can generate uh infinite
Shakespeare and you will simply do this
by because our block size is eight we
start with a sum token
um say like I use in this case
um you can use something like a new line
As the start token and then um you
communicate only to yourself because
there's a single node and you get the
prompted distribution for the first word
in the sequence and then
um you decode it or the first character
in the sequence you decode the character
and then you bring back the character
and you re-encode it as an integer and
now you have the second thing and so you
you get okay we're in the first position
and this is whatever integer it is add
the positional encodings goes into the
sequence that goes into Transformer and
again this token now communicates with
the first token
um and its identity and so you just keep
plugging the doc and once you run out of
the block size which is eight you start
to crop because you can never have block
size more than eight in the way you've
trained this Transformer so we have more
and more context until eight and then if
you want to generate Beyond date you
have to start cropping because the
Transformer only works for eight
elements in time Dimension and so all of
these Transformers in the naive setting
have a finite block size or context line
and uh in typical models this will be
1020 Pro tokens or 2048 tokens something
like that but these tokens are usually
like epe tokens or sentence piece tokens
or workpiece tokens there's many
different encodings so it's not like
that long and so that's why I think did
mentioned we really want to expand the
context size and gets gnarly because the
attention is quadratic in any case
now if you want to
um Implement an encoder instead of a
decoder attention then all you have to
do is this master
you just delete that line
so if you don't mask the attention then
all the nodes communicate to each other
and everything is allowed and
information flows between all the nodes
so if you want to have the encoder here
uh just delete all the encoder blocks
will use attention where this line is
deleted that's it
so you're allowing um whatever this
encoder in my store say 10 tokens like
10 nodes and they are allowed to
communicate to each other going up the
Transformer
and then if you want to implement cross
attention so you have a full encoder
decoder Transformer not just a decoder
only Transformer or GPT
then we need to also add uh cross
attention in the middle so here there's
a self-attention piece where all the
there's a cell potential piece across
the tension piece and this LLP and in
the cross attention uh we need to take
the features from the top of the encoder
we need to add one more line here and uh
this would be the cross attention uh
instead of I should have implemented it
instead of just pointing I think but um
there will be a cross attention line
here so we'll have three lines because
we need to add another block and the
queries will come from X but the keys
and the values will come from the top of
the encoder
and there will be basically information
flowing from the encoder strictly to all
the nodes inside X
and then that's it so it's a very simple
sort of modifications on the decoder
attention
so you'll you'll hear people talk that
you kind of have a ticket or only model
like GPT you can have an encoder only
model like Bert or you can have an
encoder decoder model like say T5 doing
things like machine translation so um
and in Bert uh you can't train it using
sort of this um
language modeling setup that's Auto
aggressive and you're just trying to
predict the next element in the sequence
your training into a slightly different
objectives you're putting in like the
full sentence and the full sentence is
allowed to communicate fully and then
you're trying to classify sentiment or
something like that so you're not trying
to model like the next token in the
sequence uh so these are trained
slightly different with masked
uh with uh using masking and uh other
denoising tables
okay so that's kind of like the
transformer I'm going to continue so
yeah maybe more questions
foreign
so I'm not sure if I fully follow so
there's different ways to look at this
analogy but one analogy is you can
interpret this graph as really fixed
it's just that every time we do the
communicate we are using different ways
you can look at it
so if we have block size of eight in my
example we would have eight notes Here
we have two four six okay so we'd have
eight notes they would be connected in
in you lay them out and you only connect
from left to right now
um
uh why would the connect usually the
connections don't change as a function
of the data or something like this
route
any
I don't think I've seen a single example
where the connectivity changes Dynamic
and option of data usually the
connectivity is fixed if you have an
encoder and you're training a birch you
have how many tokens you want and they
are fully connected
and if you have uh you have this
triangular thing and if you have encoder
decoder then you have awkwardly sort of
like two tools of nodes and yeah
thank you
my question
um
rich
the report
okay
yeah it's really hard to say so that's
why I think this paper is so interesting
is like yeah usually you'd see like a
path and maybe they had path internally
they just didn't publish it and all you
can see is sort of things that didn't
look like a Transformer I mean you had
resnets which had lots of this but a
resnet would be kind of like this but
there's no um there's no self-attention
component but the MLP is there kind of
in a resnet
um
so a resnet looks very much like this
except there's no uh you can use layer
Norms in resonance I believe as well
typically sometimes they can be bash
norms so it is kind of like a resnet it
is kind of what they took a resnet and
they put in a Cell potential one in
addition to the pre-existing MLP block
which is kind of like convolutions and
MLP was strictly speaking the
convolution one by one combination
um but I think the idea is similar in
that MLP is just kind of like a you know
typical weights uh nonlinearity weights
or operation
um and but I will say like yeah it's
kind of interesting because
a lot of work is is not uh is not there
and then they give you this Transformer
and then it turns out five years later
it's not changed even though everyone's
trying to change it so it's kind of
interesting to me that it's kind of like
a package in like a package uh which I
think is really interesting historically
and um I also talked to a paper authors
and they were unaware of the impact that
the transform was half at the time so
when you read this uh paper actually uh
it's it's kind of unfortunate because
this is like the paper that changed
everything but when people read it it's
like question marks because the reason
like a pretty random machine translation
paper like oh we're doing machine
translation oh here's a cool
architecture okay great good results
like it's it doesn't sort of know what's
going to happen
and so when people read it today I think
they're kind of confused uh potentially
like having like having I will have some
tweets at the end but I think I would
have renamed it with the benefit of
hindsight of like well I'll get to it
[Music]
yeah I think that's a good question as
well uh currently I mean I certainly
don't love the auto aggressive modeling
approach I think it's kind of weird to
like sample a token and then commit to
it uh so
you know maybe there's some ways to um
uh maybe there's some ways some hybrids
with diffusion as an example which I
think would be really cool
um
or we'll find some other ways to like
edit the sequences later but still in
the auto regressive framework
um but I think the fusion is kind of
like an up-and-coming modeling approach
that I personally find much more
appealing when I sample text I don't go
chunk chunk chunk and commit I uh I do a
draft one and then I do a better draft
two
and that feels like a diffusion process
so that would be my oh
Works kind of like a confusing term
because um
I mean yeah previously there was this
notion of
uh I kind of thought maybe today
everything is a graphical Network
because the Transformer is a graphical
Network processor the native
representation that the Transformer
operates over is sets that are connected
by edges uh in a directed way and so
that's the native representation and
then um yeah
okay I should go on because I still have
like 30 slots
oh yeah
yeah the Rooty I think basically like as
your as your if you're initializing with
random uh weights separate from a
golfing as your dimensional size grows
so does your values the variance grows
and then your soft Max will just become
uh the one half Vector
um so it's just a way to control the
variance and bring it to always be in a
good range with soft Max and nice
distribution
okay
so it's almost like an initialization
thing
okay
uh so Transformers have been applied to
all the other all the other fields and
the way this was done is in in my
opinion kind of ridiculous ways honestly
because I was a computer different
person and uh you have comments and it
kind of makes sense so what we're doing
now with bits as an example is you take
an image and you chop it up into little
squares and then those squares literally
feed into a Transformer and that's it
which is kind of ridiculous and so
I mean
yeah and so the Transformer doesn't even
in the simplest case like really know
where these patches might come from they
are usually positionally encoded
um but it has to sort of like ReDiscover
a lot of the structure I think of them
in some ways
um and it's kind of weird to approach it
that way
um
but uh it's just like this this simple
Baseline the simplest Baseline of just
chomping up big images into small
squares and feeding them in as like the
individual notes actually works fairly
well and then this is in the Transformer
encoder so all the patches are talking
to each other throughout the entire
Transformer
and the number of nodes here would be
sort of like uh nine
uh also in speech recognition you just
take your Mel spectrogram and you chop
it up into little slices and feed them
into a Transformer so there was paper
like this but also whisper whisper is a
copy based Transformer if you saw
whisper uh from open AI you just chop up
null spectrogram and feed into a
Transformer and then pretend you're
dealing with text and it works very well
uh decision transform on RL you take
your States actions and rework that you
experience an environment and you just
pretend it's a language and you start to
model the sequences of that and then you
can use that for planning later that
works pretty well uh you know even
things like Alpha gold so we were
frequently talking about molecules and
how you can plot them in so at the heart
of alcohol computationally is also a
Transformer
one thing I wanted to also say about
Transformers is I find that they're very
uh they're super flexible and I really
enjoy that
um I'll give you an example from Tesla
um like you have a comment that takes an
image and makes predictions about the
image and then the big question is how
do you feed in extra information and
it's not always trivial like say I have
additional information that I want to
inform uh that I want the outputs to be
informed by maybe I have other sensors
like radar maybe I have some map
information or a vehicle type or some
audio and the question is how do you
feed information into a comment like
where do you feed it in do you
concatenate it like how do you do you
add it at what stage and so with the
Transformer it's much easier because you
just take whatever you want you chop it
up into pieces and eat it in with a set
of what you had before and you let the
self-attention figure out how everything
should communicate and that actually
apparently works so I just chop up
everything and throw it into the mix
it's kind of like the way and it frees
neural that's from from this uh from
this burden of euclidean space where
previously you had to um you had to
arrange your computation to conform to
the euclidean space of three dimensions
of how you're laying out the compute
like the compute actually kind of
happens in almost like 3D space if you
think about it um but in attention
everything is just sets uh so it's a
it's a very flexible framework and you
can just like throw in stuff into your
conditioning set and everything just
self-attended over so it's quite
beautiful I respect it okay so now what
exactly makes Transformers so effective
I think a good example of this comes
from the gbt3 paper which I encourage
people uh to read uh language models are
two shot Learners I would have probably
renamed this a little bit I would have
said something like Transformers are
capable of in context learning or like
meta learning that's kind of like what
makes them really special so basically
the the setting that they're working
with is okay I have some context and I'm
trying to like say passage this is just
one example of many I have a passage and
I'm asking questions about it and then
um I'm giving uh as part of the context
in the prompt I'm giving the questions
and the answers so I'm giving one
example a question answer another
example question answer another example
question answer and so on and this
becomes a
oh yeah people are gonna have to leave
okay it's really important for me
okay so what's really interesting is
basically like
uh with more examples given in the
context the accuracy improves and so
what that can say is that the
Transformer is able to somehow learn in
the activations without doing any
gradient descent in a typical
functioning fashion so if you fine-tune
you have to give an example and the
answer and you you fine-tune it using
gradient descent but it looks like the
transformer internally in its weights is
doing something that looks like
potential ingredients some kind of a
metal learning in the weights of the
Transformer as it is reading the prompt
and so in this paper they go into okay
distinguishing this outer loop with
stochastic Readiness and this inner loop
of the in context learning so the inner
loop is as the Transformer is sort of
like reading the sequence almost and the
outer loop is the uh is the training by
gradient descent
um so basically there's some training
happening in the activation Transformer
as it is consuming a sequence that maybe
very much looks like gradient descent
and so there's some recent papers that
kind of hint at this and study it and so
as an example in this paper here they
propose something called The Raw
operator and um they argue that the raw
operator is implemented by Transformer
and then they show that you can
Implement things like Ridge regression
on top of a raw operator and so this is
kind of giving
um there are papers hinting that maybe
there is some thing that looks like
gradient-based learning inside the
activations of the Transformer
and uh I think this is not impossible to
think through because what is what is
gradient-based learning forward pass
backward pass and an update well that
looks like a resonant
right because you're just changing
you're adding to the weights uh so you
start initial random set of Weights
forward pass backward pass and update
your weights and then forward pass
backward positive ways looks like a
reset Transformer is a resnet
oh
so uh much more handwavy but basically
some people are trying to find out why
that could be potentially possible and
then I have a bunch of tweets I just
copy pasted here in the end um I was
this was kind of like meant for General
consumption so they're a bit more high
level and high p a little bit but um I'm
talking about why this architecture is
so interesting and why why potentially
became so popular and I think it's
simultaneously optimizes three
properties that I think are very
desirable number one the Transformer is
very expressive in the forward pass it's
um it's sort of like is able to
implement very interesting functions
potentially functions that can even like
do metal learning number two it is very
optimizable thanks to things like
residual connections layer nodes and so
on and number three it's extremely
efficient this is not always appreciated
but the Transformer if you look at the
computational graph is a shallow wide
Network which is perfect to take
advantage of the parallelism of gpus so
I think the Transformer was designed
very deliberately to run efficiently on
gpus uh there's previous work like
neural GPU that I really enjoy as well
which is really just like how do we how
do we design your own ads that are
efficient on gpus and thinking backwards
from the constraints of the hardware
which I think is a very interesting way
to think about it
um
oh yeah so here I'm saying I probably
would have called
um I probably would have called the
Transformer a general purpose efficient
optimizable computer instead of
attention is all you need like that's
what I would have maybe in hindsight
called uh that paper is proposing a is a
model that is
um
very general purpose so forward pass is
expressive it's very efficient uh in
terms of GPU usage it's easily
optimizable by gradient and trains very
nicely
then I have some other hot tweets here
um
anyway so I yeah you can read them later
but I think this one's maybe interesting
so uh if previously neural Nets are
special purpose computers designed for a
specific tasks GPT is a general purpose
computer reconfigurable at runtime to
run natural language programs uh so the
program the programs are given as
prompts
and then GPT runs the program by
completing the document
so I really I really like these
analogies uh personally uh to computer
it's just like a powerful computer and
it's optimizable by doing The Descent
um
and uh
I don't know okay that's it
I think you can read this later but uh
that's right I'll just thank you I'll
just leave this up
so sorry I just found this tweet so it
turns out that if you scale up the
training set and use a powerful enough
neural lab like a Transformer the
network becomes a kind of general
purpose computer over text so I think
that's kind of like nice way to look at
it and instead of performing a single
thick sequence you can design the
sequence in the prompt and because the
Transformer is both powerful but also is
trained on large enough very hard data
set it kind of becomes this general
purpose text computer and so I think
that's kind of interesting
yeah
um
foreign
but now we
should be kind of writing years
how much do you think
there's three really like posts today
you know it really is because it's
mostly more efficient for Humanity
[Music]
so I think there's a bit of that yeah so
I would say rnn's like in principle yes
they can Implement arbitrary uh programs
I think it's kind of like a useless
statement to some extent because they
are not they're probably I'm not sure
that they're they're probably expressive
because in a sense of like power in that
they can Implement these arbitrary
functions
but they're not optimizable
and they're certainly not efficient
because they are serial Computing
devices
um so I think so if you look at it as a
compute graph rnns are very long
thin
compute graph
um like if you stretched out the neurons
and you look like take all the
individual neurons interconnectivity and
stretch them out and try to visualize
them rnns would be like a very long
graph in a bad and it's bad also for
optimizability because I don't exactly
know why but just the rock intuition is
when you're back propagating you don't
want to make too many steps and so
Transformers are shallow wide graph and
so from from supervision to inputs is a
very small number of hops and it's a
long residual Pathways which make
gradients flow very easily and there's
all these layer Norms to control the the
scales of all all of those activations
and so uh there's not too many Hops and
you're going from supervision to input
very quickly and just flows through the
graph so
um and it's it can all be done in
parallel so you don't need to do this uh
encoder decoder RNs you have to go from
first then second word then third word
but here in in Transformer every single
word was processed completely sort of in
parallel
which is kind of a so I think all these
are really important because all these
are really important and I think number
three is less talked about but extremely
important because in deep learning scale
matters and so the size of the network
that you can train it gives you uh is
extremely important and so if it's
efficient on the current Hardware then
we can make it bigger
foreign
no
[Music]
um so yeah so you take your images and
you apparently chop them up into patches
so there's the first uh thousand tokens
or whatever and now I have a special so
radar could be um also but I don't
actually want to make a representation
of radar so uh but you could uh you just
need to chop it up and enter it and then
you have to encode it somehow like the
transformer needs to know that they're
coming from radar so you create a
special
you have some kind of a special token
that you um
are these radar tokens in the
representation and it's learnable by
gradient and um
but vehicle information would also come
in with a special embedding token that
can be learned
um so um
because you don't it's all just a set
and there's another voice
yeah it's all just a set but you can't
positionally encode these sets uh if you
want so um but positional encoding means
you can hardwire for example the the
coordinates like using sinusos and
cosines you can even have wire that but
it's better if you don't have wire the
position you just it's just a vector
that is always hanging out the
dislocation whatever content is there
just adds on it and this vectors
trainable by background that's how you
do
it
but they seem to work but it seems like
they're sometimes
whatever else
I might do something better
um
a question
so I mean the positional encoder is like
they're they're actually like not uh
they have okay so they have very little
inductive bias or something like that
they're just vectors hanging out in
location always and you're trying to
you're trying to help the network
um
and
I think the intuition is is good but
um
like if you have enough data usually
trying to mess with it is like a bad
thing uh by trying to well trying to
enter knowledge when you have enough
knowledge in the data set itself is not
usually productive uh so we talked
really depends on what scale you are if
you have Infinity data then you actually
want to encode less and less that turns
out to work better and if you have very
little data then actually you do want to
encode some biases and maybe if you have
a much smaller data set then maybe
convolutions are a good idea because you
actually have this bias coming from all
filters and so
but I think um
so the Transformer is extremely General
but there are ways to mess with the
encodings to put in more structure like
you could for example in code sinuses
and cosines and fix it or you could
actually go to the attention mechanism
and say okay my if my image is chopped
up into patches this patch can only
communicate to this neighborhood and you
can you just do that in the attention
Matrix just mask out whatever you don't
want to communicate and so people really
play with this because the the full
attention is uh inefficient so they will
intersperse for example layers that only
communicate in all patches and then
layers the community globally and they
will sort of do all kinds of tricks like
that so you can slowly bring in more
inductive bias you would do it but the
inductive biases are sort of like
they're factored out from the core
Transformer and they are factored out in
the uh in the connectivity of the nodes
and they are factored out in the
positional employees and we can mess
with this
for proposition
s
so there's probably about 200 papers on
this now uh if not more they're kind of
hard to keep track of honestly like my
Safari browser which is oh it's on my
computer it's like 200 open tabs um
but um
yes I'm not even sure if I'm if I want
to like pick my favorite honestly
yeah
and even people for Transformer attack
season I think it was was a big supplies
instructions
the other one that I actually like even
more is potentially keep the context
length fixed but allow the network to
somehow use a scratch Pad okay and so
the way this works is you will teach the
Transformer somehow via examples in the
prompt but hey you actually have a
scratch Pad hey hey trust you basically
you can't remember too much your
contact's not inspired but you can use a
scratch pad and you do that by emitting
a start scratch pad and then writing
whatever you want to remember and then
end scratch pad and then uh you continue
with whatever you want and then later
when it's decoding you actually like
have special logic that when you detect
start scratch Pad you will sort of like
save whatever it puts in there in like
external thing and allow it to attend
over it so basically you can teach the
Transformer just dynamically because
it's so um meta-learned you can teach it
dynamically to use other gizmos and
gadgets and allow it to expand its
memory that way if that makes sense it's
just like human learning to use a
notepad right you don't have to keep it
in your brain so keeping things in your
brain is kind of like the context might
be the Transformer but maybe we can just
give it a notebook and then it can query
the notebook and read from it and write
to it
[Laughter]
foreign
extensively but I did see a forgetting
event and I kind of felt like the block
size was just moved
questions
so one one question is what do you think
about architecture
a sport
actually okay which one is this one
uh the second question it was a personal
question
um what are you going to work on next
I mean so right now I'm working on
things like Nano GPT whereas Nano GPT
uh
I mean I'm going basically slightly from
computer vision and like part uh kind of
like the immersion-based products to a
little bit in language domain uh
so originally I had Min GPT whichever
wrote to Nano GPT and I'm working on
this I'm trying to reproduce gpts and I
mean I think something like Chachi PT I
think um incrementally improved in the
product fashion would be extremely
interesting and uh
I think a lot of people feel it and
that's why it went so wide so I think
there's uh something like a Google plus
plus to build that I think is really
interesting
can we give our speed run