okay um let me get started for today so
for today um first of all I'm going to
spend a few minutes talking about a
couple more new net Concepts including
actually a couple of the concepts that
turn up in assignment two um um then the
bulk of today is then going to be moving
on to introducing what are language
models um and then after introducing
language models we're going to um
introduce a new kind of newal network
which is one way to build language
models which is recurrent newal networks
um they're important thing to know about
and we use them in assignment three um
but they're certainly not the only way
to build language models in fact
probably a lot of you already know that
there's this other kind of new Network
called Transformers and we'll get on to
those after we've done recurrent new
Nets um Talk a bit about problems with
um Rec current new networks and well if
I have time I'll get onto the um recap
um before getting into the content of
the class I thought I could just spend a
minute on giving you the stats of who is
in um
cs224n um who's in
cs224n kind of looks like the pie charts
they show in CS 106a these days um
except more grad students I guess um so
the four big groups are the computer
science undergrads the computer science
grads um the Undeclared
undergraduates and the um ndo grads so
this is a large portion of the scpd
students though um some of them are
Under Computer Science grads so that
makes up about 60% of the audience um
and if you're not in one of those four
big groups um you're in the other 40%
and everybody is somewhere so there are
lots of other interesting groups down
here so you know the the bright orange
down here that's where the math and
physics phds are um up here I mean
interestingly we now have more
statistics grad students and there are
ssis undergrads it didn't used to be
that way around in NLP classes um and
you know one of my favorite groups um
the little um magenta group down here um
these are the humanity undergrads yay
Humanity's undergrads um in terms of
years it breaks down like this um first
year grad students are the biggest group
tons of Juniors and seniors and a couple
of Brave FR are any Brave FR here today
[Laughter]
yeah okay um welcome yeah
so um modern newal networks especially
language models are
enormous um this chart's sort of out of
date because it only goes up to
2022 but it's sort of actually hard to
make an accurate chart for 2024 because
in the last couple of years um the
biggest language model makers have in
general stopped saying how large their
language models are in terms of
parameters but at any rate they're
clearly um huge models which um
have over a 100 billion parameters um
and so large and then deep in terms of
very many layers new Nets are a
Cornerstone of modern NLP systems we're
going to be um pretty quickly working
our way up to look at those kind of deep
models but I just sort of for starting
off with something simpler you know I
did just want to kind of um key you in
for a few minutes into a little bit of
History right um so um the last time
neural Nets were popular was in the 80s
and 90s and that was when people worked
out the back propagation algorithm Jeff
Hinton and colleagues um made famous the
back propagation algorithm that we've
looked at and that allowed the training
of neural Nets with hidden
layers um and so but in those days
pretty much all the new du Nets with
hidden layers that were trained were
trained with one hidden layer you had
the input the hidden layer and the
output and that's all that there was and
the reason for that was for a very very
long time people couldn't really get
things to work um with more hidden
layers so that only started to change in
the Resurgence of what often got called
Deep learning but anyway back to neural
Nets um started around 2006 and this was
um one of the influential papers at the
time um greedy layerwise training of
deep neural networks by Yoshua Benjo and
colleagues and so right at the beginning
of that paper they observed this the the
problem however until recently it was
believed too difficult to train deep
multi-layer newal networks empirically
deep networks were generally found to be
not better and often worse than new
networks with one or two hidden layers
um Jerry Torro um was actually a faculty
member who worked very early on
autonomous driving with new networks um
as this is a negative result there's not
been much report in the machine learning
literature um so that really you know
although people had newal networks and
back propagation and current newal
networks we're going to talk about today
that for a very long period of time you
know 15 years or so things seemed
completely stuck in that you couldn't
although in theory it seemed like deep
neural network should be promising in
practice um they didn't work and so it
really then took some new developments
that happened in the late 2000s decade
and then more profoundly in the 2010s
decade to actually figure out how we
could have deep neural networks that
actually worked working far better than
the shallow neural networks and leading
into the networks that um we have today
and you know we're going to be starting
to talk about some of those things in
this class and come um coming up with
classes and I mean I I think you know
the tendency when you see the things
that got new networks to work much
better like the the the natural action
is to sort of shrug and be underwhelmed
and think oh is this all there is to it
this doesn't exactly seem like difficult
science um and in some sense that's true
they're fairly little introductions of
new ideas and tweaks of things but
nevertheless a handful of little ideas
and tweaks of things turn things around
from a field that was sort of stuck for
15 years going nowhere and which nearly
everyone had abandoned because of that
to suddenly turning around and there
being the ability to train these deeper
neural networks which then behaved
amazingly better as machine learning
systems than other things that had
preceded them and dominated for the for
the intervening time so that took a lot
of time so what are these things um one
of them which you can greet with a bit
of a yawn in some sense is doing better
regularization of neural Nets so
regularization is the idea that Beyond
just having a loss that we want to
minimize in terms of describing the data
um we want to in some other ways
manipulate what parameters we learn so
that our models work better and so
normally we have some more complex loss
function that does some regularization
the most common way of doing this is
what's called L2 loss where you add on
this um parameter squared term at the
end and this regularization says you
know it would be kind of good to find a
model with small parameter weights so
you should be finding the smallest
parameter weights um that will explain
your data well and there's a lot you can
say about um regularization these kind
of losses they get talked about a lot
more in other classes um like cs229
machine learning and so um I'm not going
to say very much about it this is in the
machine learning theory class um but I
do just want to sort of um put in one
note that's sort of very relevant um to
um what's happened in recent new
networks work um so the classic view of
regularization was we needed this kind
of regularization to prevent our
networks from
overfitting meaning that they would do a
very good job at modeling the training
data but then they would generalize
badly to new data that was shown and so
the picture that you got shown was this
that as you train on some training data
your error necessarily goes
down however after some point you start
learning specific properties of things
that happen to turn up in those training
examples and that you're learning things
that are only good for the training
examples and so they won't generalize
well to different pieces of data you see
at test time so if you have a separate
validation set or a final test test set
you would and you traced out the error
or loss on that um validation or test
set that after some point it would start
to go up again this is a quirk in my bad
PowerPoint it's just meant to go up um
and the fact that it goes up um is then
you have overfit your training data and
have making the parameters numerically
small is meant to lessen the extent to
which you overfit on your training data
um this is not a picture um that modern
newal Network people believe at all
instead the picture has changed like
this um we don't believe that
overfitting exists anymore but what we
are concerned about is models that will
generalize well to different data um so
that when we train you know So In
classical statistics the idea that you
could train billions of parameters like
large neuron Nets now have um would be
seen as ridiculous because you could not
possibly estimate those parameters well
um and so you just have all of this
noisy mess um but what's actually been
found is that yeah it's true you can't
estimate the numbers well but what you
get is a kind of an interesting
averaging function from all these Myriad
numbers and if you do it right what
happens is as you go on
training that for a while it might look
like you're starting to overfit but if
you keep on training in a huge Network
um not only will your training loss
continue to go down very infinitesimally
but your validation loss will go down as
well and so that huge on huge networks
these days is um we train our models so
that they overfit to the training data
almost completely right so that if you
train a huge Network now on a training
set you can essentially train them to
get zero loss you know maybe it's
0.007 loss or something but you can
train them to get zero loss because
you've got such Rich models you can
perfectly fit memorize the entire
training set now classically that would
have been seen as a disaster because
you've overfit the training data with
modern large neural networks it's not
seen as a disaster because providing
you've done regularization well that
your model will also generalize well to
different
data however the flip side of that is
normally this kind of L2 regularization
or similar ones like L1 regularization
aren't strong enough regularization to
achieve that effect and so neural
network people have turned to other
methods of regularization of which
everyone's favorite is Dropout so this
is one of the things that's on the
assignment and um at this point I should
uh um apologize or something because the
way the way Dropout is um done the way
Dropout is presented here is sort of the
original formulation the way Dropout is
presented on the assignment is the way
now normally done in deep learning
packages so um the there are a couple of
details that vary a bit and let me just
present the main idea here and um not
worry too much about the details of the
math so the idea of Dropout is at
training time um every time you are
doing a piece of training with an
example what you're going to do is
inside the middle layers of the neural
network you're just going to throw away
some of the inputs and so technically
the way you do this is you have a random
mask that you sample each time of zeros
and ones you do a hadam mod product of
that with the data so some of the data
items go to zero and you have different
Mass each time so for the next um thing
you know I've now masked out um
something different this time and so
you're just sort of Random ly throwing
away the inputs and the effect of this
is that you're training the model that
it has to be robust and work well and
make as much use of every input as it
can it can't decide that can be
extremely reliant on you know component
17 of the vector because sometimes it's
just going to randomly disappear so if
there are other features that you could
use instead that would let you work out
what to do next you should also know how
to make use of those features so at
training time you randomly delete things
at test time sort of for efficiency but
also quality of the answer um you don't
delete anything you keep all of your
weights but you just rescale things to
make up for the fact that you used to be
dropping
things okay um so what there are several
ways that you can think of explaining
this one motivation that's often given
is is that this prevents feature co-
adaptation so rather than a model being
able to learn complex functions of
feature 7 8 and 11 can help me predict
this it knows that some of the features
might be missing so it has to sort of
make use of things in a more flexible
way another way of thinking of it is
that there's been a lot of work on model
ensembles where you can sort of mix
together um different models and improve
your your results if you're training
with Dropout it's kind of like you're
training with a huge model Ensemble
because you're training with the
Ensemble of the power set the
exponential number of every possible
Dropout of features all at once and that
gives you a a very good model um so
there are different ways of thinking
about it I mean if you've seen na bays
and logistic regression models before
you know I kind of think a nice way to
think of it is that it gives a sort of a
middle ground between the two because
for naive based models you're waiting
each feature independently just based on
the data statistics doesn't matter what
other features are there in a logistic
regression weights are set in the
context of all the other features and
with Dropout you're somewhere in between
you're seeing the weights in the context
of some of the other features but
different ones will disappear at
different times um but you know
following work that was done um at
Stanford by Stefan varer and others that
generally these PE days people regard
Dropout as a form of feature dependent
regularization and he shows some
theoretical results as to why to think
of it that
way okay I think we've implicitly seen
this one um but vectorization is the
idea no for Loops always use vectors
matrices and tensors right the entire
success and speed of deep learning works
from the fact that we can do things with
vectors matrices and tensors so you know
if you're writing for Loops in any
language but especially in Python things
run really slowly if you can do things
with vectors and matrices even on CPU
things run at least an order of
magnitude faster and well what everyone
really wants to move to doing in deep
learning is running things on gpus or
sometimes now newal processing units and
then you're getting you know two three
orders of magnitude of speed up so um do
always think about I should be doing
things with vectors and matrices if I'm
writing a for Loop for anything that
isn't some very superficial bit of input
processing I've almost certainly made a
mistake and I should be working out um
how to do things um with vectors and
metries and you know that's kind of
thing like Dropout you don't want to
write a for Loop um that goes through
all the positions and sets some of them
to zero you want to be sort of using a
vector operation with your
mask um two more I think um parameter
initialization I mean this one might not
be obvious but when we start training
our neural networks in almost all cases
it's vital that we
initialize the parameters of our
matrices to some random numbers and the
reason for this is if we just start with
the um if we just start with our
matrices all zero or some other constant
normally the case is that we have um
symmetry so it's sort of like in this
picture when you're starting on this
Saddle Point um that you know it's
symmetric to the left and the right and
um or whatever forward and backwards and
left and right and so is you sort of
don't know where to go and you might be
sort of stuck and stay in the one place
I mean normally a way to think about is
the operations that you're doing to all
the elements in The Matrix are sort of
the same so rather than having you know
a whole Vector of features if all of
them have the same value initially often
it's sort of like you only have one
feature and you've just got a lot of
copies of it so to initialize learning
and have things work well we almost
always want to set all the weights to
very small random numbers um and so at
that point you know CL when I say very
small we sort of want to make them an A
Range so that they don't disappear to
zero if we make them a bit smaller and
um they don't sort of start blowing up
into huge numbers when we multipli them
by things and doing this initialization
at the right scale was used to be seen
as something pretty important and there
were particular methods that had a basis
of sort of thinking of what happens once
you do Matrix multiplies that people had
worked out and often used one of these
was this harier
initialization which was sort of working
out um what variance of your uniform
distribution to be um variant of your
distribution to be using based on the
sort of number of inputs and outputs of
a layer and things like that the
specifics of that um you know I think we
still use to initialize things in
assignment two but we'll see later that
they go away because people have come up
with clever methods um in particular
doing layer normalization which sort of
obviates the need to be so careful on
the initialization but you still need to
initialize things to something
okay then the fast the final one which
I'll is also something that appears in
the second assignment that I just want
to say a word about um was optimizers so
we talked about in class um stochastic
gradient descent and did the basic um
equations for stochastic gradient
descent and you know to a first
approximation there's nothing wrong with
stochastic gradient descent and if you
fiddle around enough you can usually get
stochastic gradients send actually to
work well for almost any problem but um
getting it to work well is very
dependent on getting the scales of
things right of sort of having the right
step size and often you have to have a
learning rate schedule with decreasing
step sizes and various other
complications so people have come up
with um more sophisticated optimizers
for newal networks and for complex Nets
sometimes these seem kind of necessary
to get them to learn well and at any
rate they give you sort of lots of
margins of safety since they're much
less dependent on you setting different
hyperparameters right and the idea of
all of the well all the methods I
mentioned and the most commonly used
methods is that for each parameter
they're accumulating a measure of what
the gradient has been in the past and
they've got some idea of the scale of
the gradient the slope for a particular
parameter and then they're using that to
decide how much you move the learning
rate at each time step so the simplest
method that was come up with this one
called adrad if you know John duci and E
he was one of the co-inventors of this
um you know it's simple and nice enough
but it tends to stall early then people
came up with different methods Adam's
the one that's on assignment two it's a
really good safe place to start art um
but in a way um sort of our word vectors
have a special property because of their
spareness that you know you're very
sparely updating them because particular
words only turn up occasionally so
people have actually come up with
particular um optimizers that sort of
have special properties for things like
word vectors and so these ones with the
w at the end can sometimes be good to
try and then you know again there's a
whole family of extra ideas that people
have used to improve optimizers and if
you want to learn about that you can go
off and do an optimization class like
Conex optimization but there ideas like
momentum and nesterov acceleration and
things like that and all of those things
people also variously try to use um but
Adam is a good name to remember um if
you remember nothing
else okay that took longer than I hoped
but I'll get on now to language models
okay language models so you know um in
some sense language model is just two
English words but when in NLP we say
language models we mean it as a
technical term that has a particular
meaning um so the idea of a language
model is something that can
predict well what word is going to come
next or more precisely it's going to put
a probability distribution over what
words come next so the students open
there what words are likely to come
next
bags laptops laptops notbook notebooks
notebooks yeah um I have some of those
at least okay um yeah I mean so right so
so these are kind of likely words and if
on top of those we put a probability on
each one then we have a language model
so formally we've got a context of
proceeding items we're putting a
probability distribution over the next
item which means that the sum of the
estimates of this for the um items in
the vocabulary will sum to one and if
we've defined a p like this that
predicts probabilities of next words
that is called a language
model as it says here um an alternative
way um that you can think of a language
model is that a language model is a
system that assigns a probability to a
piece of text and um so we can say that
a language model can can take any piece
of text and give it a probability and
the reason we can do that is we can use
the chain rule so I want to know the
probability of any stretch of text I say
given my previous definition of language
model easy I can do that probability of
X1 with a null preceding context times
the probability of X2 given X1 Etc along
I can do this chain rule decomposition
and then the terms of that decomposition
are precisely what the language model as
I defined it previously provides okay so
language models are this essential
technology for NLP just just about
everything from the simplest places
forward um where people do things with
human language and computers people use
language models in particular you know
they weren't something that got invented
in 2022 with chat GPT language models
have been Central to NLP at least since
the 80s the idea of them goes back to at
least the 50s um so anytime you're
typing on your phone and it's making
suggestions of next words regardless of
whether you like those suggestions or
not um those suggestions are being
generated by a language Model A Very uh
traditionally a compact not very good
language model so it can run sort of
quickly and very little memory in your
keyboard application um if you go on
Google and you start typing some stuff
and it's telling you stuff that could
come after it um to complete your query
well again that's being generated by a
language model so how can you build a
language model so before getting into
new language models I've got just a few
slides to tell you about the old days of
language modeling so this is sort of how
language models were built um from
1975 until you know effectively around
about
2012 um so
we want to put probabilities on these
sequences um and the way we're going to
do it is we're going to build what's
called an engram language model um and
so this is meaning we're going to look
at Short word
subsequences and use them to predict so
N is a variable describing how short are
the word sequences that we're going to
use to predict um so if we just look at
the probabilities of individual words we
have a unigram language model if we look
at probabilities of pairs of words Byram
language model um uh probabilities of
three words trigram language models
probabilities of more than three words
they get called four gr language models
five gr language models six gr language
models um so for people with a Classics
education this is horrific of course um
in particular not even these ones are
correct um because Graham is a Greek
root so it should really have Greek
numbers in front here um so you should
have Monograms and diagrams um and you
know actually so the first person who
introduced the idea of engram models was
actually Claude Shannon when he was
working out information Theory the same
guy that did cross entropy and all of
that and if you look at his 1951 paper
he uses diagrams um but the idea died
about there and everyone else this is
what people say in practice um It's Kind
kind of cute I like it a nice you know
practical notation um so to build these
models the idea is look we're just going
to count how often different engrs
appear in text and use those to build
our probability estimates um and in
particular our trick is that we make a
mark of assumption so that if we're
predicting the next word based on a long
context we say ah tell you what we're
not going to use all of it we're only
going to use the most recent n minus one
words so we have this big context and we
throw most of it away and so if we're
predicting word XT + one based on simply
the preceding n minus one words well
then we can make the
prediction using
NRS um for
let's whatever it is if we use n is
three would' have a triam here and
normalized by a Bagram down here and
that that would give us relative um
frequencies of the different
terms um so we can do that simply by
counting how often NRS occur in a large
amount of text and simply divid through
by the counts and that gives us a
relative frequency estimate of the
probability of different
continuations does that make sense yeah
that's a way to do it okay um so suppose
we're um learning a a forr language
model right and we've got a piece of
text as the Proctor started the clock
the students open there so well to
estimate things we are going to throw
away all but the preceding three words
so we're going to estimate based on
students open there and so we're going
to work out the probabilities by looking
for counts of students open their W and
counts of students open there um so we
might have in a corpus that students
open there occurred a thousand times
students open their books occurred 400
times and so we'd say the probability
estimate is simply 0.4 for B
if exams occurred 100 times the
probability estimate is
0.1 for
exams
um and well you can sort of see that
this is bad it's not terrible because if
you are going to try and predict the
next word in a simple way looking at the
immediately prior words is are the most
helpful words to look at but it's it's
clearly sort of primitive because you
know if you known the prior text was as
the Proctor started the clock that makes
it sound likely that the words should
have been exams where since you're
estimating just based on students open
theirs well you'd be more likely to
choose books because it's more common so
it's a kind of a crude estimate but it's
a decent enough place to start um it's a
crude estimate that could be problematic
in other ways I mean why why else might
we kind of get in
Troubles by using this our probability
estimate
yeah so there are a lot of engrams yeah
so there are a lot of words and
therefore there are a lot of lot of
engrams yeah so that's a problem we'll
come to it later uh anything else maybe
up the back um like the word w might not
even show up in the training data so you
might just have a count zero for that
yeah yeah so um so if we're counting
over any reasonable size Corpus there
are lots of words that we just are not
going to have seen right that they never
happen to occur in the text that we
counted over you know so if you start
thinking students open there you know
there are lots of things that you could
put there you know students open their
accounts or if the students are doing
dissections in a biology class maybe
students open their frogs I don't know
um you know that there are lots of words
that in some context you know would
actually be possible and lots of them
that we won't have seen and so it give
them a probability estimate of zero and
that tends to be an especially bad thing
to do with probabilities because once we
have a probability estimate of zero any
computations that we do that involve
that will instantly go to zero so we
have to deal with some of these problems
so for that sparity problem right yeah
that we could have the word never
occurred in the numerator and so simply
done we get a probability estimate of
zero the way that was dealt with was
that people just hacked the counts a
little to make it non zero so there are
lots of ways that are explored but the
easiest way is you just sort of added a
little Delta like you know 0.25 to
counts so things that you never saw got
a count of 0 .25 in total and things you
saw once got to count of 1.25 and then
there are no zeros anymore everything is
possible um you could think then there's
a second problem that wait you might
never have seen stupid students open
there before and so that means your
denominator is just undefined and you
don't have any counts in the numerator
either so you sort of need to do
something different there and the
standard trick was used then was that
you um did back off so if you couldn't
estimate words coming after students
open there you just worked out the
estimates for come words coming after
open there and if you couldn't estimate
that you just use the estimate of words
coming after there so you used less and
less context until you could get an
estimate that you could
use um but you know something to note is
that we''ve got these conflicting
pressures now so that on the one hand
you know if you want to come up with a
better estimate that you would like to
use more context I to have a larger engr
but on the other hand as you make use
more more conditioning words well the
storage size problem someone mentioned
gets worse and worse because the number
of NRS that you have to know about is
going up exponen eventally with the size
of the context but also your spareness
problems are getting way way worse and
you're almost necessarily going to be
ending up seeing zeros and so because of
that you know in practice where things
tended to um sort of max out was five
and occasionally people use six gr and
seven G but most of the time you know
between the sort of spareness and the
cost of storage 5 G was the large thing
people dealt with um so
um a famous resource from back in the
2000s decade that Google released um was
Google engrs which was built on a a
trillion word web Corpus and had counts
of n g and it gave counts of n g up to
nals 5 and that is where they
stopped okay well we've sort of said the
storage problem the storage problem is
well to do this you need to store the
these counts the number of counts is
going up exponentially in the amount of
Contex size um okay um but you know
what's good about engram language models
they're really easy to build you can um
build one yourself in a few minutes when
you've got want to have a bit of fun on
the weekend um you know all you have to
do is start sort of storing um these
counts for engrams and you can use them
to predict things so you know for if at
least if you do it over a small Corpus
like a couple of million words of text
um you know you can build an engram
language model in seconds on your laptop
or you have to buil write the software
okay a few minutes to write the software
but building the model takes seconds
because you know there's no training in
your network all you do is count how
often um engrams occur and so once
you've done that you can then run an
engram language model to generate text
you know we could do text generation
before chat GPT right so if I have a
trigram language model I can start off
with some words today the and I could
look at my stored engrams and get a
probability distribution over next words
and here they are you know note the
strong patterning of these um these um
probabilities cuz remember they're all
der from counts right that are being
normalized so really these are words
that occurred once these are words that
occurred twice these are words that
occurred four times in this context
right so they're sort of in some sense
crude when you look at them more
carefully but so what we could do is
then at this point you know we roll a a
die and get a random number from 0er to
one and we can use that sample from this
distribution
um sorry yeah
um so we sample from this distribution
and so that if we sort of um generate so
of as our random number something
like
35 if we go down from the top we'd say
okay we've sampled the word price today
the price and then we repeat over we
condition on that we probability
distribution of the next word um we
generate a random numbered and use it to
sample from the distribution um we say
generate 2 and so we choose of um we now
condition on that we get a probability
distribution we generate a random number
which is 0.5 or something and so we get
gold coming out and we can say today the
price of gold and we can keep on doing
this and generate some text and so
here's some text generated um from 2
million words training data using a
trigram language model today the price
of gold per ton while production of shoe
lasts and shoe industry the bank
intervened just after it considered and
rejected an IMF demand to rebuild
depleted European stocks September 3rd
in primary 76 cents a share um
now okay that text isn't great um but
you know I actually want people to you
know be in a positive of mood today um
and you know actually it's not so bad
right it's sort of surprisingly
grammatical I mean in particular like I
lowercased everything so this is the IMF
that should be capitalized of the
international monetary fund right you
know there are big pieces of this that
even make sense right the bank
intervened just after it considered and
rejected an if IMF demand you know
that's pretty much making sense as a
piece of text um right so
it's mostly grammatical it looks like
you know English text I mean it it makes
no sense right it's sort of really
incoherent so there there's work to do
but you know what was already you could
see that even these simple engram models
you could from a very low level you
could kind of approach what text and
human language worked like in from below
and you know I could easily make this
better even with the engram language
model because you know rather than two
million words of text if I trained on 10
million words of text would be better if
I then rather than a trigram model could
go to a forr model get better and You'
sort of start getting better and better
um approximations of text um and so this
is essentially what people um did until
about
2012 and and you know really uh the same
story that people um tell today that
scale will solve everything is exactly
the same story that people used to tell
in the early
2010s with these engram language models
if you weren't getting a good enough
results with your 10 million words of
text and a trigram language model the
answer was that if you had a 100 million
words of text and a for gram language
model you'd do better and then if you
had a trillion words of text in a five
gr language model You' do better and gee
wouldn't it be good if we could collect
10 trillion words of text so we could
train an even better engram language
model same strategy um but it turns out
that sometimes you can do better with
better models as well as simply scale um
and so things got reinvented and started
again with building neural language
models um so how can we build a neural
language model um so you know we've got
the same task of having a sequence of
words and we want to put a probability
estimate over what word comes next um
and so the simplest way you could do
that which you'll hopefully all have
thought of because it connects what we
did in earlier classes look we already
had this idea that we could have
represented context by the concatenation
of some word vectors and we could put
that into a neural network and we could
use that to predict something and in the
example I did in the last couple of
classes what we used it to predict was
is the center word a location or not a
location just a binary choice but that's
not the only thing we could predict we
could have predicted lots of things with
this new network we could have predicted
whether the piece of text was positive
or negative we could have predicted
whether it was written in English or
Japanese you know we can predict lots of
things so one thing we could choose to
predict is we could choose to predict
what word is going to come next after
this window of text we'd have a model
just like this one apart from up the top
instead of doing this binary
classification we' do a many many way
classification over what is the next
word that is going to appear in the
piece of text and that would then give
us a neural language model in particular
it give us a fixed window neural
language model so that we'd do the same
Markoff assumption trick of throwing
away the further back context and so for
the fixed window um we'll you know um
use word embeddings which you can
concatenate we'll put it through a
hidden layer and then we'll take the
output of that hidden layer um multiply
it by by another layer say and then put
that through a soft Max and get an
output distribution and so this gives us
a sort of a fixed window neural language
model and you know apart from the fact
that we're now doing a classification
over many many many classes this is
exactly like what we did um last week so
it should look kind of familiar it's
also kind of like what you're doing for
assignment two um and so this is
essentially the first kind of new
language model that was
proposed um so in particular um yosua
Benjo um really sort of right at the
beginning of the 21st century suggested
that you could do this that rather than
using an engram language model you could
use a fixed window neural language model
and you know even at that point um he
and colleagues were able to get some
positive results from this model but you
know at the time it wasn't widely
noticed it didn't really take off that
much and you know it was sort of for a
combination of reasons when it was only
a fixed window it was sort of not that
different to engrs in some sense and
although the new network could give
better
generalization it could be argued rather
than using counts I mean in practice you
know new Nets were still hard to run
without gpus and people felt and I think
in general this was the case that you
could get more oomph by doing the scale
story and um collecting your engram
counts on hundreds of billions of words
of text um rather than trying to make a
new network out of it and so it didn't
really sort of especially take off at
that time but you know in principle it
seemed a nice thing it you know got rid
of the spasy problem um it got rid of
the storage costs you no longer have to
store all observed engrs you just have
to store the parameters of your newal
network but it didn't solve all the
problems that we'd like to solve so in
particular we still have this problem of
the Markoff assumption that we're just
using a small fixed context beforehand
to predict
from um and there are some disadvantages
to enlarging that window and you know
there's no fixed window that's ever big
enough um there's another there's
another thing that if you look
technically at this model that might
sort of make you suspicious of it which
is you know when we have words in
different positions that those words and
different positions will be treated by
completely different subp parts of this
Matrix W so you might think that you
know know okay for predicting that books
comes next you know the fact that this
is a student um is important but it
doesn't matter so much exactly where the
word student occurs right you know the
context could have been the students
slowly open there um and it's still the
same students we've just got a bit
different linguistic structure where
this W Matrix would be using completely
separate parameters to be learning stuff
about student here versus student in
this position so that seems kind of
inefficient and wrong um and so that
suggested that we kind of need a
different kind of neural architecture
that can process any length of input and
can use the same parameters to say hey I
saw the word student that's evidence
that things like books exams homework
will be turning up regardless of where
it occurs and so that then led to
exploration of this different neural
network architecture um called recurrent
neural networks which is what I'll go on
to next but before I do is everyone
basically okay with what a language
model is yeah no
questions okay um we're current newal
networks
um so
recurrent newal networks is a different
family of newal networks so effectively
in this class we see several neural
network
architectures um so in some sense the
first architecture we saw was word to V
it's a sort of a very simple um encoder
decoder architecture um the second
family we saw was feed forward Network
or fully connected layer classic neural
networks and the third family we're
going to see is recurrent neural
networks which have different kinds and
then we'll go on and go on to
Transformer models okay so the idea of a
recurrent newal network is that you've
got one set of Weights that are going to
be applied through successive moments in
time I successive positions in the text
and as you do that you're going to
update the parameters as you go um we'll
go through this in quite a bit of detail
but you know here's the idea of it so
we've got the students open there and we
want to predict with that and the way
that we're going to do
it okay I've still got four words in my
example so I can put stuff down the left
side of the slide but there could have
been 24 words with recurrent new
networks because they can deal with any
length of context okay so as before our
words start off as just words or one hot
vectors and we can look up their word
embeddings just like
before okay but now to compute
probabilities for the next word we're
going to do something different so our
hidden layer is going to be recurrent
and by recurrent it means we're going to
sort of change a hidden State at each
time step as we proceed through the text
from left to right um so we're going to
start off with an h0 which is the
initial hidden state which can actually
just be all zeros um and then at each
time step what we're going to do is
we're going to multiply the previous
hidden state by a weight M
Matrix we're going to take a word
embedding and multiply it by a weight
Matrix
and then we're going to sum the results
of those two things and that's going to
give us a new hidden state so that
hidden state will then sort of store a
memory of everything that's been seen so
far so we'll do that and then we'll
continue along so we'll multiply the
next word vector by the same weight
Matrix we we store the previous multiply
the previous hidden state by the same
weight M Matrix wa each and we add them
together and get a new
representation um I've only sort of said
this bit so I've left out a bit commonly
there are two other things you're doing
you're adding on a biased term because
we usually separate out a bias term and
you're putting things through a
nonlinearity so I should make sure I
mention that and for recurrent neural
networks most commonly this nonlinearity
has actually been the tan H function so
it's sort of balanced on the positive
negative side and so you keep on doing
that through each step and so the idea
is once we've got to here this H4 hidden
state is a hidden state that in some
sense has read the text up until now
it's seen all of the students open there
and if the word students occurred in any
of these positions it will have been
multiplied by the same we Matrix and
added into the hidden state so it's kind
of got a cleaner
low parameter way of incorporating in
the information that seen so now I want
to predict the next word and to predict
the next word I'm then going to do based
on the final hidden State the same thing
I did kind of thing I did before so I'm
going to multiply that hidden state by
matrix and add another bias and stick
that through a soft Max and use that to
um sample from that soft Max well the
softmax will give me a language model of
probability over all next words and I
can sample from it to generate the next
word that make
sense okay recurrent new um
networks
um okay um so for current newal networks
we can now process any length of
preceding content next and we'll just
put more and more stuff in our hidden
State um the so our computation is using
information from many steps back um our
model Size Doesn't increase for having a
long context right you know we have to
do more computation for a long context
but our representation of that long
context just remains this fixed size
hidden Vector h of whatever dimension it
is so there's no exponential blowout
anymore um there's the same weights
appli in every time step so there's a
symmetry and how inputs are processed um
there are some
catches um the biggest catch in practice
is that recurrent computation is slow so
for the feed forward layer we just had
you know our input Vector we multiply it
by matrix we multiply it by matrix
however many times and then at the end
we're done whereas here we've sort of
stuck with this sequentiality that you
have to be doing one hidden Vector at a
time in fact this is going against what
I said at the beginning of class because
essentially here you're doing a for Loop
um you're going through for time equals
1 to T and then you're generating and
term each hidden vector and that's one
of the big problems with rnns that have
led them to fall out of favor um there's
another
problem that we'll look at more is that
in theory this is perfect you're just
incorporating all of the past context in
in your hidden Vector in practice it
tends not to work perfectly because you
know although stuff you saw back here is
in some sense still alive in the hidden
Vector as you come across here that your
memory of it gets more and more distant
and it's the words that you saw recently
that dominate The Hidden State now in
some sense that's right because the
recent stuff is the most important stuff
that's freshest in your mind you know
it's the same with human beings um they
tend to forget stuff from further back
as well um but rnns especially in the
simple form that I've just explained
forget stuff from further back um rather
too quickly and we'll come back to that
again um into in Thursday's class
okay so for training an RNN language
model um the starting off point is we
get a big Corpus of text again um and
then we're going to compute um for each
time step a prediction of the
probability of next words and then
there's going to be an actual next word
and we're going to use you know that as
the basis of our loss
um so our loss function is the cross
entropy between the predicted
probability and what the actual next
word that we saw is which again as in
the example I showed before is just the
the negative log likelihood of the
actual next word ideally you'd like to
predict the actual next word with
probability one which means the negative
log of one would be zero and there'd be
no loss but in practice if you give it
an estimate of 0 five there's only a
little bit of loss and so on and so um
to get our overall objective function we
work out the average loss the average
negative log likelihood of predicting
each word in turn so showing that as
pictures if our Corpus is the students
open their exams we're first of all
going to be trying to predict um you
know what
comes after the and we will predict some
word with um different probabilities and
then we'll say oh the actual next word
is students okay you gave that a
probability of 0.05 say because all you
know was the first word was the okay
there's a loss for that um the negative
log prob given to students we then go on
and generate the probability estimate
over the next words and then we say well
the actual word is opened what
probability estimate did you give to
that we get a negative probability loss
keep on running this along and then we
sum all of those losses and we average
them per word and that's our sort of
average per word loss and we want to
make that as small as possible and so
that's our training mechanism and it's
important to to know no that you know
for generating this loss we're not just
doing free generation we're not just
saying to the model go off and generate
a sentence um what we're actually doing
is at each step we're effectively saying
okay the prefix is the students open
what probability distribution do you put
on next words after that um generate it
with our current new network and then
say ask for the actual next word what
probability estimate did you give to
there and that's our loss but then what
we do is stick there into our current
new network the right answer so we
always go back to the right answer
generate probability distribution for
next words and then ask okay what
probability did you give to the actual
next word exams and then again we use
the actual next word so we do one step
of generation then we pull it back to
what was actually gener ated what was
what was actually in the text and then
we ask it for guesses over the next word
and repeat forever and so the fact that
we don't do free generation but we pull
it back to the actual piece of text each
time um makes things simple because we
sort of know what an actual author used
for the next word um and that process is
called teacher forcing and so the most
common way to
language models is using this kind of
teacher forcing method I mean it's not
perfect in all respects cuz you know
we're not actually exploring different
things the model might want to generate
on its own and seeing what comes after
them we're only doing the tell me the
next word from some human generated
piece of
text okay um so that's how we get losses
um and then after that um we want to as
before use these losses to update the
parameters of a newal
network okay um and how do we do that um
well in principle you know we just have
all of the texts that we've collected
which you could think of as just a
really long sequence of okay we've got a
billion words of text here it is right
so in theory you could just run your um
recurrent newal network over your
billion words of text updating the
context as you go um but that would make
it very difficult to train a model
because you'd be accumulating these
losses for a billion steps and you'd
have to store them um and then You' be
you'd have to store hidden States so you
could update parameters and it just
wouldn't work so what we actually do is
we cut our training data into segments
of a reasonable length and then we're
going to sort of run our recurrent newal
Network on those segments and then we're
going to compute a loss for each segment
and then we're going to update the
parameters of the recurrent new network
based on the losses that we found for
that segment um I I describe it here as
the segments being sentences or
documents which seems a linguistically
nice thing it turns out that um in
recent practice when you're wanting to
scale most efficiently on gpus people
don't bother with those linguistic
niceties they just say a segment is 100
words just cut every 100 Words and the
reason why that's really convenient is
you can then create a batch of segments
all of which are 100 words long and
stick those in a matrix and do um
vectorized training more efficiently um
and things go great for you okay but
there's still a few more things that we
need to know um to get things to work
great for you I was try and get a bit
bit more through this before um today
ends so we sort of need to know about
how to work out the derivative of our
loss with respect to um the
parameters of our recurrent newal
Network and the interesting case here is
you know these wh parameters are sort of
being used everywhere through the neural
network at each stage as are the we ones
so they appear at many places in the
network so how do we work out the
partial derivatives of the loss with
respect to the repeated weight
matrices and and the answer to that is
oh it's really simple um you can just
sort of pretend that those wh's in each
position are different and work out the
partials with respect to them at one
position and then to get the partials
with respect to wh you just sum whatever
you found in the different
positions and so um that is sort of okay
the gradient with respect to repeated
weight is the sum of the gradient with
respect to each time it appears and the
reason why that is it sort of follows
what I talked about in lecture three um
that we talk or you know you can also
think about it in terms of what you
might remember um from you know
multivariable chain roles but you know
the way I introduced in lecture three is
that gradient at outward branches and so
what you can think about it in a case
like this is that you've got uh wh
Matrix which is being copied by identity
to wh1 wh2 wh3 wh4 Etc at each time step
and so since those are identity copies
they have um a partial derivative with
respect to each other of one
and so then we apply the multivariable
chain roll to these copies um and so
we've then got an outward branching node
and you're just summing the gradients um
to get the total gradient of each time
for The
Matrix okay
um yeah I mean there's one other trick
that's perhaps worth knowing I mean if
you've got sort of segments that are 100
long um a common speed up is to say oh
maybe we don't actually have to run back
propagation for 100 time steps maybe we
could just run it for 20 times steps and
stop which is referred to as truncated
back propagation through time I mean in
practice that tends to be sufficient
note in particular you're still on the
forward path updating your hidden State
using your full context but in the back
propagation you're just sort of cutting
it short um to speed up
training okay um so just as I did before
with an engram language model we can use
uh RNN language model to generate text
and it's pretty much the same idea
except now we're sort of um rather than
just using counts of engrs we're using
the hidden state of our neural network
to give us the input to a a probability
distribution that we can then sample
from so I can start with the initial
hidden State um I can use the start of
sentence symbol I mean the example I had
before I started immediately with the um
hoping that that was less confusing the
first time but what you should have
asked is wait a minute where did the the
come from um so normally what we
actually do is is use a special start of
sequence symbol like this angle
bracketed s and so we sort of feed it in
as a pseudo word which has a word
embedding and then we based on this will
be generating first words of the text um
so we end up with some
representation from which we can sample
and get the first word so now we don't
have any actual text so what we're going
to do
is take that generated word that we
generated and copy it down as the next
input and then we're going to run the
next stage of newal network um sample
from the probability distribution and
next word favorite copy it down as the
next word of the input and keep on
generating and so this is referred to as
a roll out that you're kind of
continuing to roll the dice and generate
forward and generate a piece of text and
so um and normally you want to stop at
some point and the way we can stop it
some point is we can have a second
special symbol um the angle bracket SLS
which um says end of um your sequence so
we can generate an end of sequence
symbol and then we can um stop and so
using this we can sort of generate
pieces of text and essentially you know
this is exactly what's happening if you
use something like chat GPT right that
the model is a more complicated model
that we've haven't yet gotten to but
it's generating the response to you by
doing this kind of process of generating
a word at the time treating it as an
input and generating the next word and
generating this sort of roll out and
that's why and it's done
probabilistically so if you do it
multiple times um you can get different
answers we haven't yet gone to chat GPT
but we can have a little bit of fun um
so you can take this simple recurrent
newal Network that we've just built here
and you can train it on any piece of
text and get it to generate stuff so for
example I can train it on Barack Obama's
speeches so that's a small Corpus right
you know he didn't talk that much right
I've only got a few hundred thousand
words of text it's not a huge Corpus
I'll just show this and then I can
answer the question um but you know I
can generate from it and I get something
like the United States will step up to
the cost of a new challenges of the
American people that will share the fact
that we created the problem they were
attacked and so that they have to say
that all the task of the final days of
war that I will not be able to get this
done um yeah well maybe that's slightly
better than my engram language model
still not perfect you might say but
somewhat better maybe did you have a
question uh yeah so since we're like
training the mod like truncated set of
the Corpus that impose some kind of like
limitation on like how much we can like
produce and like still have some cency
like meaning like
foring um so yeah so I suggested we're
going to chunk the S chunk the text into
100w units so you know that's the limit
of the amount of Prior context that
we're going to use so I mean that's a
fair amount 100 words that's typically
several sentences but to the extent that
you wanted to know even more about the
further back context you wouldn't be
able to and you know certainly that's
one of the ways in which modern large
language models are using far bigger
context than that they're now using
thousands of words of Prior context yeah
absolutely it's a limit on how much far
back context so in some sense actually
even though in theory a current newal
Network can feed in an arbitrary length
context as soon as I say oh practically
we cut it into segments you know
actually that means we are making a
Markoff assumption again and we're
saying the further back context doesn't
matter yeah okay uh couple more examples
um so instead of Barack Obama I can feed
in Harry Potter which is a somewhat
bigger Corpus of text actually and
generate from that and so I can get um
sorry Harry shouted panicking I'll leave
those brooms in London are they no idea
said nearly headless Nick casting low
close by Cedric carrying the last bit of
trial charms from Harry's shoulder and
to answer him the common room perched
upon it forearms held a shining knob
from when the spider hadn't felt it
seamed he reached the teams
too well there you are um you can do
other things as well um
so you can train it on recipes and
generate a recipe um this one's a recipe
I don't suggest you try and cook um but
it looks sort of like a recipe if you
don't look very hard um chocolate Ranch
Barbecue categories game casseroles
cookies cookies yield six servings two P
two tablespoons of Parmesan cheese
chopped um one cup of Co coconut milk
and three eggs beaten um Place each
pasture over layers of lumps shape
mixture into the moderate oven and
simmer until firm serve hot and bodied
fresh mustard orange and cheese combine
the cheese and salt together the dough
in a large Skillet and the ingredients
and stir in the chocolate and pepper H
um yeah it's not exactly very consistent
recipe when it comes down to it it sort
of has a langage of a recipe but it's
Absolut maybe if I had scaled it more
and had a bigger Corpus it would have
done a bit better um but it's definitely
not using the ingredients there are um
let's see it's almost um time today so
maybe about all I can do um is uh do H I
can do one more fun example and then
after that oh yeah I probably should
that bit at the start next time um so as
a variant of building RNN language
models I mean so far we've been building
them over words so our you know token
time steps over which you build it as
words I mean actually you can use the
idea of recurrent new networks over any
other size unit and people have used
them for other things so people have
used them in bioinformatics for things
like um DNA for sort of having Gene
sequencing or protein sequencing or
anything like that but even staying with
language um instead of building them
over words you can build them over
characters so that my I'm generating at
a a letter at a time rather than a word
at a time and so that can sometimes be
useful because it allows us to sort of
generate things um that sort of look
like Words um and perhaps have the
structure of English words um and so and
so similarly there are other things that
you can do so before I
initialized the hidden State I said oh
you just have an initial hidden State
you can make it zeros if you want well
sometimes we're going to build a
contextual RNN where we can initialize
the hidden State um with something else
so in particular I can initialize the
hidden state with the RGB values of a
color and so I can have initialized the
hidden state with the color and generate
character at a time the name of paint
colors and I can train a model based on
um a paint company's catalog of names of
colors and their um RGB of their colors
and then I can give it different
different paint colors and it'll come up
with names for them and it actually does
an excellent job this one worked really
well look at this um this one here is
gasty pink Power gray Naval tan bco
white hble gray Home Star Brown now
couldn't you just imagine finding all of
these in a paint catalog I mean some of
them are there's some really good ones
over here in the bottom right this color
here is
dope and then um this Stoner blue purple
s stinky
bean and Turley now I think I've got a a
real business opportunity here in the
Paint Company Market um for my recurrent
new network okay I'll stop there for
today and do more of the science of new
networks next time