You know what's crazy that all of this
is real?
>> Yeah. Meaning what?
>> Don't you think so?
>> Meaning what?
>> Like all this AI stuff and all this
area. Yeah. That it's happen like
>> isn't it straight out of science
fiction?
>> Yeah. Another thing that's crazy is like
how normal the slow takeoff feels. The
idea that we'd be investing 1% of GDP in
AI, like I feel like it would have felt
like a bigger deal, you know, where
right now it just feels like
>> you get used to things pretty fast.
Turns out Yeah. But also it's kind of
like it's abstract like what does it
mean? What it means that you see it in
the news.
>> Yeah.
>> That such and such company announced
such and such dollar amount,
>> right?
>> That's that's all you see,
>> It's not really felt in any other way so
far.
>> Yeah. Should we actually begin here? I
think this is an interesting discussion.
>> Sure.
>> I think your point about well from the
average person's point of view, nothing
is that different will continue being
true even into the singularity.
>> No, I don't think so. Okay. Interesting.
>> So the thing which I was referring to
not feeling different
is okay. So such and such company
announced some difficult to comprehend
dollar amount of investment
>> right
>> I don't think anyone knows what to do
with that.
>> Yeah.
>> But I think that the impact of AI is
going to be felt.
>> AI is going to be diffused through the
economy. There are very strong economic
forces for this and I think the impact
is going to be felt very strongly.
>> When do you expect that impact? I think
the models seem smarter than their
economic impact would imply.
>> Yeah, this is
one of the very confusing things about
the models right now. How to reconcile
the fact that they are doing so well on
evals.
>> Mhm. And you look at the evals and you
go, those are pretty hard evals,
>> right?
>> They're doing so well,
>> but the economic impact seems to be
dramatically behind. And it's almost
like
it's it's very difficult to make sense
of how can the model on the one hand do
these amazing things and then on the
other hand like repeat itself twice in
some situation in a kind of a an example
would be let's say you use VIP coding to
do something and you go to some place
and then you get a bug and then you tell
the model can you please fix the bug?
>> Yeah. And the model says, "Oh my god,
you're so right. I have a bug. Let me go
fix that." And it introduces a second
bug.
>> Yeah.
>> And then you tell it you have you have
this new second bug and it tells you,
"Oh my god, how could I've done it?
You're so right again."
>> And brings back the first bug. And you
can alternate between those.
>> Yeah.
>> And it's like, how is that possible?
>> It's like I'm not sure. But it does
suggest that the
something strange is going on. I have
two possible explanations. So here this
is the more kind of a whimsical
explanation is that maybe a real
training makes the models a little bit
too single-minded and narrowly focused a
little bit too
I don't know unaware
even though it also makes them aware in
some other ways
and because of this they can't do basic
things but there is another explanation
which is
back when people were doing pre-training
the question of what data to train on
was answered because the that answer was
everything.
>> Yeah.
>> When you do pre-training, you need all
the data.
So you don't have to think is it going
to be this data or that data.
>> Yeah.
>> But when people do RL training, they do
need to think. They say okay, we want to
have this kind of RL training for this
thing and that kind of RL training for
that thing. And from what I hear, all
the companies have teams that just
produce new RL environments and just add
it to the training mix. And then the
question is, well, what are those? There
are so many degrees of freedom. There is
such a huge variety of environments you
could produce. And one of the
one thing you could do, and I think
that's something that is done
inadvertently,
is that people take inspiration from the
evals. you say, "Hey, I would love our
model to do really well when we release
it. I want the EVOS to look great."
What would be RL training that could
help on this task, right? I think that
is something that happens and I think it
could explain a lot of what's going on.
If you combine this with generalization
of the models actually being inadequate,
that has the potential to explain a lot
of what we are seeing. this disconnect
between eval performance and actual real
real world performance which is
something that we don't today exactly
even understand what what we mean by
that I I like this idea that the real
reward hacking is a human researchers
who are too focused on the evals um I
think there's two ways to understand or
to try to think about what what you have
just pointed out one is look if it's the
case that simply by becoming superhuman
at a coding competition, a model will
not automatically become more tasteful
and exercise better judgment about how
to improve your codebase. Well, then you
should expand the suite of environments
such that you're not just testing it on
having the best performance in coding
competition. It should also be able to
make the best kind of application for X
thing or Y thing or Z thing. And another
maybe this is what you're hinting at is
to say why should it be the case in the
first place that becoming super human at
coding competitions doesn't make you a
more tasteful programmer more generally.
Maybe the thing to do is not to keep
stacking up the amount of environments
and the diversity of environments to
figure out approach with let you learn
from one environment and improve your
performance on something else. So I have
I have an analog a human analogy which
might be helpful. So even the case let's
take the case of competitive programming
since you mentioned that and suppose you
have two students
one of them work decided they want to be
the best competitive programmer. So they
will practice 10,000 hours for that
domain. They will solve all the
problems, memorize all the proof
techniques and be very very you know
be very skilled at quickly and correctly
implementing all the algorithms and by
doing by doing so they became the best
one of the best student number two
thought oh competitive programming is
cool maybe they practiced for 100 hours
>> much much less and they also did really
well which one do you think is going to
do better in their career later on
>> the second
>> right and I think that's basically
what's going on. The models are much
more like the first student but even
more because then we say okay so the
model should be good at competitive
programming so let's get every single
competitive programming problem ever and
then let's do some data augmentation so
we have even more competitive
programming problems
>> yes
>> and we train on that and so now you got
this great competitive programmer and
with this analogy I think it's more
intuitive I think it's more intuitive
with this analogy that yeah okay so if
it's so well trained okay it's like all
the different algorithms and all the
proof techniques are like right at it at
its fingertips
and it's more intuitive that with this
level of preparation it not would not
necessarily generalize to other things.
>> But then what is the um analogy for what
the second student is doing before they
do the 100 hours of fine-tuning.
>> I think it's like
they have it. I think it's the it
factor.
>> Yeah.
>> Right. And like I know like when I was
in undergrad, I remember there was there
was a student like this that studied
with me. So I I know it exists.
>> Yeah. I think it's interesting to
distinguish it from whatever
pre-training does. So one way to
understand what you just said about we
don't have to choose the data in
pre-training is to say actually it's not
dissimilar to the 10,000 hours of
practice. It's just that you get that
10,000 hours of practice for free
because it's already somewhere in the
pre-training distribution. But it's like
maybe you're suggesting actually there's
actually not that much generalization
for pre-training. There's just so much
data in pre-training but it's like it's
not necessarily generalizing better than
RL.
>> Like the main the main strength of
pre-training is that there is a so much
of it.
>> Yeah.
>> And b you don't have to think hard about
what data to put into pre-training.
>> And it's a very kind of natural data and
it does include in it a lot of what
people do.
>> Yeah.
people's thoughts and a lot of the
features of you know it's like the whole
world as projected by people onto text.
>> Yeah.
>> And pre-training tries to capture that
using a huge amount of data.
It's it's very the pre-training is very
difficult to reason about because it's
so hard to understand the manner in
which the model relies on pre-training
data. And whenever the model makes a
mistake, could it be because something
by chance is not as supported by the
pre-training data? You know, and pre
support by pre-training is maybe a loose
term.
I I don't know if I can add anything
more useful on this, but
I don't think there is a human analog to
pre-training. Um, here's analogies that
people have proposed for what the human
analogy to pre-training is, and I'm
curious to get your thoughts on why
they're potentially wrong. One is to
think about the first 18 or 15 or 13
years of a person's life when they
aren't necessarily economically
productive, but they are doing something
that is making them understand the world
better and so forth. And the other is to
think about evolution as doing some kind
of search for three billion years which
then results in a human lifetime
instance. And then I'm curious if you
think either of these are actually
analogous to pre-training or how how
would you think about at least what
lifetime human learning is like if not
pre-training. I think there are some
similarities between both of these two
pre-training and pre-training tries to
play the role of both of these
>> but I think there are some big
differences as well.
The amount of pre-training data is
very very staggering.
>> Yes.
>> And somehow a a human being after even
15 years with a tiny fraction of that
pre-training data they know much less.
>> Yeah. But whatever they do know they
know much more deeply somehow and the
mistakes like like already at that age
you would not make mistakes that are
make.
>> Yeah. There is another thing you might
say could it be something like evolution
and the answer is maybe but in this case
I think evolution might actually have an
edge like there is this I remember
reading about this case where some you
know that one thing that neuroscientists
do or rather one way in which
neuroscientists can learn about the
brain is by studying people with brain
damage to different parts of the brain
>> and and so and some people have the most
strange symptoms you could imagine. It's
actually really really interesting. And
there was one case that comes to mind
that's relevant.
I read about this person who had some
kind of brain damage that took out I
think a stroke or an accident that took
out his emotional
processing. So he stopped feeling any
emotion
and as a result of that you know he
still remained very articulate and he
could solve little puzzles and on tests
he seemed to be just fine but he felt no
emotion he didn't feel sad he didn't
feel angry he didn't feel animated and
he became somehow extremely bad at
making any decisions at all it would
take him hours to decide on which socks
to wear and he would make very bad
financial decisions
And that's very
but does what what does it say about
the role of our built-in emotions
in making us like a viable agent
essentially
>> and I guess to connect to your question
about pre-training
>> it's like maybe pre- like maybe if you
are good enough at like getting
everything out of pre-training you can
get you could get that as well but
that's the kind of thing which seems is
well it may or may not be possible to
get that from pre-training. What is
that clearly not just directly emotion?
And it seems like some
almost value function like thing which
is giving telling you which decision to
be like what the end reward for any
decision should be and you think that
doesn't sort of implicitly come from
>> I think it could I'm just saying it's
not one it's not 100% obvious.
>> Yeah. But what is that like what how do
you think about emotions and what is the
ML analogy for emotions?
>> It should be some kind of a value
function thing.
>> Yeah. But I don't think there is a great
ML analogy because right now value
functions don't play a very prominent
role in uh the things people do.
>> It might be worth defining for the
audience what a value function is if if
you want to do that.
>> I mean certainly I I'll be very happy to
do that. Right. So
so when people do reinforcement learning
the way reinforcement learning is done
right now how do they do how do people
train those agents? So you have your
neural net and you give it a problem and
then you tell the model go solve it and
the model takes maybe thousands hundreds
of thousands of actions
or thoughts or something and then it
produces a solution. The solution is
created and then the score
is used to provide a training signal for
every single action
in your trajectory.
>> Mhm. So that means that if you are doing
something that goes for a long time, if
you're training a task that takes a long
time to solve, you will do no learning
at all until you solve the until you
came up with a proposed solution. That's
how reinforcement learning is done
naively. That's how O1 R1 ostensibly are
done.
The value function says something like
okay look maybe I could sometimes not
always could tell you if you're doing
well or badly. The notion of a value
function is more useful in some domains
than others. So for example when you
play chess
and you lose a piece you know I messed
up. You don't need to play the whole
game to know that what I just did was
bad and therefore whatever um whatever
preceded it was also bad. So the value
function lets you short circuit the
weight until the very end. Like let's
suppose that you started to pursue some
kind of um okay let's suppose that you
are doing some kind of a math thing or a
programming thing and you're trying to
explore a particular solution direction
and after let's say after a thousand uh
steps of thinking you concluded that
this direction is unpromising.
As soon as you conclude this, you could
already get a reward signal a thousand
time steps previously when you decided
to pursue down this path. You say, "Oh,
next time I shouldn't pursue this path
in a similar situation long before you
actually came up with a proposed
solution." M this was in the deepcar one
paper is that the
space of trajectories is so wide that
maybe it's hard to learn a mapping from
an intermediate trajectory and value and
also given that you know in coding for
example you'll have the wrong idea then
you'll go back then you'll change
something
>> this sounds like such lack of faith in
deep learning
>> like I mean sure it might be difficult
but
>> nothing deep learning can't Yeah.
>> So my expectation is that
like value functions should be useful
and
and I fully I fully expect that they
will be used in the future if not
already. What was I alluding to with the
person whose emotional center got
>> um damaged is more that
maybe what it suggests is that the value
function of humans is modulated by
emotions in some important way that's
hardcoded by evolution
and maybe that is important for people
to be effective in the world.
>> That that's the thing I was actually
planning on asking you. There's
something really interesting about
emotions as a value function, which is
that it's impressive that they have this
much utility while still being rather
um simple to understand.
So I have two responses. I do agree that
compared to
the kind of things that we learn and the
things we are talking about, the kind of
ads we talking about, emotions are
relatively simple.
They might even be so simple that maybe
you could map them out in a human
understandable way. I think it would be
cool to do.
In terms of utility though, I think
there is a thing where you know there is
this complexity robustness trade-off
where complex things can be very useful
but simple things are very useful in a
very broad range of situations. And so I
think what what one way to interpret
what we are seeing is that we've got
these emotions that essentially evolved
mostly mostly from our mammal ancestors
and then fine-tuned a little bit while
we were homminids just a bit. We do have
like a decent amount of social emotions
though which mammals may lack
but they're not very sophisticated
and because they're not sophisticated
they serve us so well in this very
different world compared to the one that
we've been living in. Actually they they
also make mistakes. For example, our
emotions well I don't know does hunger
count as an emotion
debate. It's debatable but I think for
example our intuitive feeling of hunger
is not succeeding in guiding us
correctly in this world with an
abundance of food.
>> Yeah. People have been talking about
scaling data, scaling parameters,
scaling compute.
Is there a more general way to think
about scaling? What are the other
scaling axes?
So
the thing so so here here is a
perspective here's a perspective I think
might be might be true.
So
the way ML used to work is that people
would just think of it with stuff and
try to
and try to get interesting results.
That's what's been going on in the past.
Then
the scaling insight arrived, right?
Scaling laws, GPT3.
And suddenly everyone realized we should
scale.
And it's just this, this is an example
of how language affects thought.
Scaling is what just one word, but it's
such a powerful word because it informs
people what to do. They say, "Okay,
let's let's try to scale things." And so
you say okay so what are we scaling and
pre-training was a thing to scale it was
a particular scaling recipe.
>> Yes
>> the big breakthrough of pre-training is
the realization that this recipe is
good. So you say hey if you mix some
compute with some data into a neural net
of a certain size you will get results
and you will know that it will be better
if you just scale the recipe up. And
this is also great. Companies love this
because it gives you a very uh lowrisk
way of investing.
>> Yeah.
>> Your resources.
>> Right. It's much harder to invest your
resources in research. Compare that. You
know, if you research, you need to have
like go forth researchers and research
and come up with something versus get
more data, get more compute. You know,
you'll get something from pre-training.
And indeed, you know, it looks like I
based on various um
um things people say on some people say
on Twitter, maybe it appears that Gemini
have found a way to get more out of
pre-training. At some point though,
pre-training will run out of data. The
data is very clearly finite. And so
then, okay, what do you do next? Either
you do some kind of a souped-up
pre-training, different recipe from the
one you've done before, or you're doing
a RL or maybe something else. But now
that compute is big, computer is now
very big. In some sense, we are back to
the age of research. So maybe here's
another way to put it. Up until 2020,
from 201 from 2012 to 2020, it was the
age of research. Now from 2020 to 2025,
it was the age of scaling or maybe plus
minus. Let's add arrow bars to those
years because people say this is
amazing. You got to scale more. Keep
scaling. The one word scaling. But now
the scale is so big. Like is is it is
the belief really that oh it's so big
but if you had 100x more everything
would be so different. Like it would be
different for sure but like is the
belief that if you just 100x the scale
everything would be transformed.
I don't think that's true. So it's back
to the age of research again just with
big computers.
>> That's a very interesting way to put it.
But let me ask you the question you just
posed then. What are we scaling and what
what is what would it mean to have a
recipe? Because I guess I'm not aware of
a very clean
relationship that almost looks like a
law of physics which existed in
pre-training that was a power law
between data or computer parameters and
loss. What is the kind of relationship
we should be seeking and how how should
we think about what this new recipe
might look like? So, we've we've already
witnessed a transition from
one type of scaling to a different type
of scaling, from pre-training to RL.
Now, people are scaling RL. Now, based
on what people say on Twitter, they
spend more compute on RL than on
pre-training at this point because RL
can actually consume quite a bit of
compute. You know, you do very very long
rollouts.
>> Yes. So it takes a lot of compute to
produce those rollouts and then you get
relatively small amount of learning per
roll out. So you really can spend you
really can spend a lot of compute and I
could imagine like I wouldn't at this at
this st it's it's more like I wouldn't
even call it a scale um scaling I would
say hey like what are you doing and is
the thing you are doing the the the the
most productive thing you could be
doing? Yeah.
>> Can you find a most more productive way
of using your compute? We've discussed
the value function business earlier and
maybe once people get good at value
functions they will be using their their
um resources more productively
and if you find a whole other way of
training models you could say is this
scaling or is it just using your
resources I think it becomes a little
bit ambiguous in a sense that when
people were in the age of research back
then it was like people say hey let's
try this and this and this let's try
that and that and that oh look something
interesting is happening and I think
there will be a return to that.
>> So if we're back in the era of research,
stepping back, what is the part of the
recipe that we need to think most about?
When you say value function, people are
already trying the current recipe, but
then having LLM as a judge and so forth,
you could say that's a value function,
but it sounds like you have something
much more fundamental in mind. Do we
need do we need to go back to
should we even rethink pre-training at
all and not just add more steps to the
end of that process?
>> Yeah. So the the the the discussion
about value function I think it was
interesting. I want to like emphasize
that I think the value function is
something like
it's going to make RL more efficient
and I think that makes a difference but
I think that anything you can do with a
value function you can do without just
more slowly.
>> Mhm.
>> The thing which I think is the most
fundamental is that these models somehow
just generalize dramatically worse than
people.
>> Yes.
>> And it's super obvious.
That's that seems like a very
fundamental thing.
>> Okay, so this is the crux of
generalization and there's two
sub questions.
There's one which is about sample
efficiency which is why should it take
so much more data for these models to
learn than humans. There's a second
about even separate from the amount of
data it takes, there's a question of why
is it so hard to teach the thing we want
to a model than to a human which is to
say for to a human that we don't
necessarily need a verifiable reward to
be able to
you're probably mentoring a bunch of
researchers right now and you're you
know talking with them you're showing
them your code and you're showing them
how you think and from that they're
picking up your way of thinking and how
they should do research. You don't have
to set like a verifiable reward for them
that's like okay this is the next part
of the curriculum and now this is the
next part of your curriculum and oh it
was this training was unstable and we
gota there's not this shleppy bespoke
process. So perhaps these two issues are
actually related in some way but I'd be
curious to
explore this this second thing which
feels more like continual learning and
this first thing which feels just like
um sample efficiency.
>> Yeah. So you know you could actually
wonder one one possible explanation for
the human sample efficiency that needs
to be considered is evolution
and evolution has given us a small
amount of the mo the most useful
information possible
and for things like vision
hearing and locomotion
I think there's a pretty strong case
that evolution actually has given us a
lot. Mhm.
>> So for example, human dexterity far
exceeds I mean robots can become
dexterous too if you subject them to
like a huge amount of training in
simulation. But to train a robot in the
real world to quickly like pick up a new
skill like a person does seems very out
of reach. And here you could say, oh
yeah, like locomotion all our ancestors
needed great locomotion squirrels like
so locomotion maybe like we've got like
some unbelievable prior. You could make
the same case for vision. You know, I I
believe Yan Lakhan made the point, oh,
like um children learn to drive after 16
hour after like 10 hours of practice,
which is true, but our vision is so
good. At least for me, when I remember
myself being 5 years old, my I was I was
very excited about cars back then, and
I'm pretty sure my car recognition was
more than adequate for self-driving
already. As a 5-year-old, you don't get
to see that much data as a 5-year-old.
You spend most of your time in your
parents house, so you have very low data
diversity. But you could say maybe
that's evolution, too. But then language
and math and coding, probably not.
>> It still seems better than models. I
mean, obviously models are better than
the average human at language and math
and coding, but are they better at the
average human at learning?
>> Oh, yeah. Oh, yeah. Absolutely. What I
meant to say is that language math and
coding and especially math and coding
suggests that whatever it is that makes
people
good at learning
is probably not so much a complicated
prior but something more some
fundamental thing.
>> Wait, I'm not sure understood. Why
should that be the case? So consider a
skill
that people exhibit some kind of great
reliability or you know um
>> if the skill is one that was very useful
to our ancestors for many millions of
years, hundreds of millions of years,
you could say you could argue that maybe
humans are good at it because of
evolution because we have a prior
>> an evolutionary prior that's encoded in
some very nonobvious way.
>> Yeah.
>> That somehow makes us so good at it.
>> But if people exhibit great ability,
reliability, robustness, ability to
learn in a domain that really did not
exist until recently,
then this is more an indication that
people might have [snorts]
just better machine learning period.
>> Mhm. But then how should we think about
what that is? Is it a matter of
Yeah. What is the ML analogy for what?
There's a couple interesting things
about it. It takes fewer samples. It's
more unsupervised. You don't have to set
a ver like a child learning to drive a
car. Children are not learning to drive
a car. A teenager learning how to drive
a car is like not exactly getting
some pre-built verifiable reward.
it comes from their interaction with the
machine and the with the environment. Um
and yet it takes much fewer samples. It
seems more unsupervised. It seems more
robust. Much more robust. The robustness
of people is really staggering.
>> Yeah. So like Okay. And do you have a
unified way of thinking about why are
all these things happening at once? What
is the ML analogy that would that could
be could realize something like this?
So, so, so, um, this is where, you know,
one of the things that you've been
asking about is how can, you know, the
teenage driver kind of self-correct and
learn from their experience without an
external teacher.
>> And the answer is well, they have their
value function,
>> right? They have a general sense which
is also by the way extremely robust in
people like
whatever it is the human value function
whatever the human value function is
with a few exceptions around addiction
it's actually very very robust
and so for something like a teenager
that's learning to drive they start to
drive and they already have a sense of
how they're driving immediately how
badly they're unconfident and then they
See? Okay. And they and then of course
the the learning speed of any teenager
is so fast after 10 hours you're good to
go.
>> Yeah. It seems like humans has some
solution, but I'm curious about like
well how are they doing it and like why
is it so hard to like how do we need to
reconceptualize the way we're training
models to make something like this
possible?
>> You know that is a great question to ask
and it's a question I have a lot of
opinions about.
But unfortunately
we live in a world where not not all
machine learning ideas are discussed
freely and this is this is one of them.
So there's probably a way to do it.
I think it can be done. The fact that
people are like that I think it's a
proof that it can be done. There may be
another blocker though which is there is
a possibility
that the human neurons actually do more
compute than we think. And if that is
true and if that plays an important role
then things might be more difficult. But
regardless I do think it points to the
existence of some
machine learning principle
that I have opinions on. But
unfortunately, circumstances make it
hard to to discuss in detail. Even
though
>> nobody nobody listens to this podcast,
Ilia.
>> Yeah.
>> So, I have to say that prepping for Ilia
was pretty tough because neither I nor
anybody else had any idea what he's
working on and what SSI is trying to do.
I had no basis to come up with my
questions and the only thing I could go
off honestly was trying to think from
first principles about what are the
bottlenecks to hi because clearly Ilia
is working on them in some way. Part of
this question involved thinking about RL
scaling because everybody's asking how
well RL will generalize and how we can
make it generalize better. As part of
this I was reading this paper that came
out recently on RL scaling and it showed
that actually the learning curve on RL
looks like a sigmoid. I found this very
curious. Why should it be a sigmoid
where it learns very little for a long
time and then it quickly learns a lot
and then it asmmptotes. This is very
different from the power law you see in
pre-training where the model learns a
bunch at the very beginning and then
less and less over time. And it actually
reminded me of a note that I had written
down after I had a conversation with a
researcher friend where he pointed out
that the number of samples that you need
to take in order to find a correct
answer scales exponentially with how
different your current probability
distribution is from the target
probability distribution. And I was
thinking about how these two ideas are
related. I had this vague idea that they
should be connected, but I really didn't
know how. I don't have a math
background, so I couldn't really
formalize it. But I wondered if Gemini 3
could help me out here. And so I took a
picture of my notebook and I took the
paper and I put them both in the context
of Gemini 3 and I asked it to find the
connection. And it thought a bunch and
then it [music] realized that the
correct way to model the information you
gain from a single yes or no outcome in
RL is as the entropy of a random binary
variable. It made a graph which showed
how the bits you gain for a sample in RL
versus supervised learning scale as a
pass rate increases. And as soon as I
saw the graph that Gemini 3 made,
immediately a ton of things started
making sense to me. Then I wanted to see
if there was any empirical basis to this
theory. So I asked Gemini to code my
experiment to show whether [music] the
improvement in loss scales in this way
with pass rate. I just took the code
that Gemini outputed. I copy pasted it
into a Google Collab notebook and I was
able to run this toy ML experiment and
visualize its results without a single
bug. It's interesting because the
results look similar but not identical
to what we should have expected. And so
I downloaded this chart and I put it
into Gemini and I asked it what is going
on here. I came up with a hypothesis
that I think is actually correct which
is that we're capping how much
supervised learning can improve in the
beginning by having a fixed learning
rate and in fact we should decrease the
learning rate over time. It actually
gives us an intuitive understanding for
why in practice we have learning rate
schedulers that decrease the learning
rate over time. I did this entire flow
from coming up with this vague initial
question to building a theoretical
understanding to running some toy ML
experiments all with Gemini 3. This
feels like the first model where it can
actually come up with new connections
that I wouldn't have anticipated. It's
actually now become the default place I
go to when I want to brainstorm new ways
to think about a problem. If you want to
read more about RL scaling, you can
check out the blog post that I wrote
with a little help from Gemini 3. And if
you want to check out Gemini 3 yourself,
go [music] to gemini.google.
I am curious if you say we are back in
an era of research.
You were there from 2012 to 2020
and do do you have Yeah. What what is
now the vibe going to be if we go back
to the era of research? For example,
even after Alexet, the amount of compute
that was used to run experiments kept
increasing and the size of frontier
systems kept increasing.
And do you think now that this era of
research will still require tremendous
amounts of compute? Um, do you think it
will require going back into the
archives and reading old papers? What is
maybe what was the vibe of like you were
at Google and um OpenAI and Stanford
these places when there was like a more
of a vibe of research. What what kind of
thing should we be expecting in the
community?
>> So one consequence of um the age of
scaling is that there was this
um scaling sucked out all the air in the
room.
>> Yeah.
And so
because scaling sucked out all the air
in the room,
everyone started to do the same thing.
We got to the point where
uh we are in a world where there are
more companies than ideas by quite a
bit.
>> Actually on that you know there is this
Silicon Valley saying that says that
ideas are cheap, execution is everything
and people say that a lot.
>> Yeah. And there is truth to that. But
then I saw I saw someone say on Twitter
um something like if ideas are are so
cheap, how come no one's having any
ideas?
>> And I think it's true too. I think like
if you think about um research progress
in terms of bottlenecks,
there are several bottlenecks. If you go
back to the if if you and um one of them
is ideas and one of them is your ability
to bring them to life.
>> Yeah. which might be compute but also
engineering.
So if you go back to the '9s let's say
you had people who had had pretty good
ideas and if they had much larger
computers maybe they could demonstrate
that their ideas were viable but they
could not. So they could only have very
very small demonstration that did not
convince anyone.
>> Yeah.
>> So the bottleneck was compute. Then in
the age of scaling computers increased a
lot and of course there is a question of
how much comput is needed but compute is
large so compute is large enough such
that
it's like not obvious that you need that
much more compute to prove some idea
like I'll give you an analogy. Alexet
was built on two GPUs. That was the
total amount of compute used for it. The
transformer
was built on 8 to 64 GPUs. No single
transformer paper experiment used more
than 64 GPUs of 2017 which would be like
what two GPUs of today. So the ResNet
right many like even even the the um you
could argue that the like 01
reasoning was not the most comput heavy
thing in the world. So there definitely
for for research
you need like definitely some amount of
compute but it's far from obvious that
you need the absolutely largest amount
of compute ever for research. H
>> you might argue and I think it is true
that if you want to build the absolutely
best system, if you want to build the
absolutely best system, then it helps to
have much more compute and especially if
everyone is within the same paradigm,
then compute becomes one of the big
differentiators.
>> Yeah, I guess while it was possible to
develop these ideas, I'm asking you for
the history because you were actually
there. I'm not sure what actually
happened, but it sounds like it was
possible to develop these ideas using
minimal amounts of compute, but it
wasn't the transformer didn't
immediately become famous. It became the
thing everybody started doing and then
started experimenting on top of and
building on top of because it was
validated at higher and higher levels of
compute.
>> Correct. And if you at SSI have 50
different ideas, how will you know which
one is the next transformer and which
one is you know brittle without having
the kinds of compute that other frontier
labs have. So I can I can comment on
that which is
the short comment is that you know you
mentioned SSI specifically for us
the amount of compute that SSI has for
research is really not that small and I
want to explain why like a simple math
can explain why the amount of compute
that we have is actually a lot more
comparable for research than one might
think. And I'll explain. So
SSI has raised $3 billion which is like
not small by it's like a lot by any
absolute sense but you could say but
look at the other companies raising
>> much more
but a lot of what their a lot of their
compute goes for inference
like these big numbers these big loans
it's earmarked for inference. That's
number one. Number two, you need if you
want to have a product on which you do
inference, you need to have a big staff
of engineers of salespeople. A lot of
the research needs to be dedicated for
producing all kinds of product related
features. So then when you look at
what's actually left for research, the
difference becomes a lot smaller.
Now the other thing is is that if you
are doing something different do you
really need the absolute maximal scale
to prove it? I don't think it's true at
all. I think that in our case we have
sufficient compute to prove to convince
ourselves and anyone else that what
we're doing is correct.
There's been public estimates that you
know companies like OpenAI spend on the
order of56
billion dollars a year even just so far
on experiments.
>> This is separate from the amount of
money they're spending on inference and
so forth. So seems like they're spending
more a year running exper like research
experiments than you guys have in total
funding.
>> I think it's a question of what you do
with it. It's a question of what you do
with it. like they have a like the more
I think in in in their case in the case
of others I think there's a lot more
demand on the training compute there's a
lot more different work streams there is
there are different modalities there is
just more stuff and so it becomes
fragmented
>> how will SSI make money
>> you know
my answer to this question is something
like
we just f right now we just focus on the
research and then the answer to that
will reveal itself. I think there will
be lots of possible answers.
>> Is SSI's plan still to straightshot
super intelligence?
>> Maybe.
I think that there is merit to it.
>> I think there's a lot of merit because I
think that it's very nice to not be
affected by the day-to-day market
competition.
But I think there are two reasons that
may cause us to change the plan. one is
pragmatic if timelines turn out to be
long
which they might and second I think
there is a lot of value in the best and
most powerful AI being out there
impacting the world
>> I think this is a meaningfully valuable
thing
>> but then so why is your default plan to
straight shot super intelligence because
it sounds like you know openai anthropic
all these other companies their explicit
thinking is look we have weaker and
weaker intelligences that the public can
get used to and prepare for and why is
it potentially better to build a super
intelligence directly
>> so I'll make the case for and against
>> the case for is that you are so one of
the challenges
that people face when they're in the
market is that they have to participate
in the rat race and the rat race is
quite difficult in that it exposes you
to to to difficult trade-offs which you
need to make
and there is it is it is nice to say
we'll insulate ourselves from all this
and just focus on the research and come
out only when we are ready and not
before but the counterpoint is valid too
and those those are opposing forces the
counterpoint is hey it is useful for the
world to see powerful AI it is useful
for the world to see powerful AI because
that's the only way you and communicate
it.
>> Well, I guess not even just that you can
communicate the idea, but
>> communicate the AI, not the idea.
Communicate the AI.
>> What do you mean communicate the AI?
>> So, okay. So, let's suppose you read an
essay about AI
>> and the essay says AI is going to be
this and AI is going to be that and it's
going to be this
>> and you read it and you say, okay, this
is an interesting essay
>> right
>> now. Suppose you see an AI doing this
and AI doing that.
>> It is incomparable. Like basically I
think I think that there is a big
benefit from AI being in the public and
that would be a reason for us to not be
quite straight shot.
>> Yeah. Well, I guess it's not even that
which I but I do think that is an
important part of it. The other big
thing is I can't think of another
discipline in human engineering and
research where
the end artifact was made safer
mostly through just thinking about how
to make it safe as opposed to why are
airplane crashes per mile so much lower
today than they were decades ago? Why is
it so much harder to find a bug in Linux
than it would have been decades ago? And
I think it's mostly because these
systems were deployed to the world. you
noticed failures, those failures were
corrected and the systems became more
robust. Now, I'm not sure why AGI and
superhuman intelligence would be any
different, especially given, and I hope
we can talk, we're going to get to this.
It seems like the harms of super
intelligence are not just about like
having some malevolent uh paper clipper
out there, but it just like this is a
really powerful thing and we don't even
know how to conceptualize how people
interact with it, what people will do
with it and having gradual access to it
seems like a um better way to maybe
spread out the impact of it and to help
people prepare for it. Well, I think I
think on this point even in the straight
shot scenario, you would still do a
gradual release of it is how I would
imagine it.
The the gra gradualism would be an
inherent inherent component of any plan.
It's just a question of what is the
first thing that you get out of the
door. That's number one. Number two, I
also think you know I believe you have
advocated for continual learning more
than other people
>> and I actually think that this is an
important and correct thing and here is
why
so one of the things so I'll give you
another example of how thinking how
language affects thinking and in this
case it will be two words two words that
have shaped everyone's thinking I
maintain
F first word AGI
second word pre-training let me explain.
So the word the term AGI,
why does this term exist? It's a very
particular term. Why does it exist?
There's a reason.
The reason that the term AGI exists is
in my opinion not so much because it's
like a very important essential
descriptor of of of some end state of
intelligence but
because it is a reaction to a different
term that existed and the term is narrow
AI. If you go back to ancient history of
gameplay AI, of checkers AI, chess AI,
computer games AI, everyone would say,
look at this narrow intelligence. Sure,
the chess AI can beat Casper off, but it
can't do anything else. It is so narrow,
artificial narrow intelligence. So in
response, as a reaction to this, some
people said, well, this is not good. It
is so narrow. What we need is general
AI.
general AI, an AI that can just do all
the things.
The second and and that term just got a
lot of traction.
>> Yeah.
>> The second thing that got a lot of
traction is pre-training.
Specifically, the recipe of
pre-training. I think the current the
way people do RL now is maybe um un is
undoing the conceptual imprint of
pre-training. But pre-training had the
property. you do more pre-training and
the model gets better at everything more
or less uniformly. Yeah,
>> general AI pre-training gives AGI
but
the thing that happened with AGI and
pre-training is that in some sense they
overshock the target
because by the kind if you think about
the term AGI you will realize and
especially in the context of
pre-training you will realize that a
human being is not an AGI
because a human being Yes, there is
definitely a foundation of skills.
A human being,
a human being lacks a huge amount of
knowledge. Instead, we rely on continual
learning. We rely on continual learning.
And so then when you think about okay,
so let's suppose that we achieve success
and we produce a safe super some kind of
safe super intelligence. The question is
but how do you define it? Where on the
curve of continual learning is it going
to be? I produce like um a super
intelligent 15 year old that's very
eager to go and you say okay I'm going
to they don't know very much at all the
great student very eager you go and be a
programmer you go and be a doctor
go and learn so you could imagine that
the deployment itself will involve some
kind of a learning trial and error
period
>> it's a process as opposed to you drop
the finished thing
>> okay I I I I see so you're you're
suggesting
that the thing you're pointing out with
super intelligence
is not some finished
mind which knows how to do every single
job in the economy cuz the way say the
original I think openi charter or
whatever defines AGI is like it can do
every single job that a every single
thing a human can do. You're proposing
instead a mind which can learn to do any
single every single job.
>> Yes.
>> And that is super intelligence. And then
but once you have the learning
algorithm,
it gets deployed into the world the same
way a human laborer might join an
organization.
>> And it seems like one of these two
things might happen. Maybe neither of
these happens. One, this super efficient
learning algorithm
becomes superhuman becomes as good as
you and potentially even better at the
task of ML research. And as a result the
algorithm itself becomes more and more
superhuman. The other is even if that
doesn't happen if you have a single
model I mean this this is explicitly
your vision. If you have a single model
or instances of a model which are
deployed through the economy doing
different jobs learning how to do those
jobs continually learning on the job
picking up all the skills that any human
could pick up but actually picking them
all up at the same time and then
amalgamating the learnings.
you basically have a model which
functionally becomes super intelligent
even without any sort of recursive
self-improvement in software right
because you now have one model that can
do every single job in the economy and
humans can't merge our minds in the same
way and so do you expect some sort of
like intelligence explosion from broad
deployment
>> I think that it is likely that we will
have rapid economic growth
I think the broad deployment And
like there are two arguments you could
make which are conflicting.
One is that look if indeed you get once
indeed you get to a point where you have
an AI that can learn to do
things quickly
and you have many of them then they will
then there will be a strong force to
deploy them in the economy. Unless there
will be some kind of a regulation that
stops it, which by the way there might
be. But I think the idea of very rapid
economic growth for some time, I think
it's very possible from broad
deployment. The other question is how
rapid it's going to be.
So I think this is hard to know because
on the one hand you have this very
efficient worker. on the other hand
there is the world is just really big
and there's a lot of stuff
and that stuff moves at a different
speed but then on the other hand now the
AI could you know so I think very rapid
economic growth is possible and we will
see like all kinds of things like
different countries with different rules
and the ones which have the friendlier
rules the economic growth will be faster
hard to predict
>> some people in our audience like to read
the transcripts instead of listening to
the episode and so we put a ton of
effort into making the transcripts read
like they are standalone essays. The
problem is that if you just transcribe a
conversation verbatim using a speech to
text model, it'll be full of all kinds
of fits and starts and confusing
phrasing. We mentioned this problem to
Labelbox and they asked if they could
take a stab. Working with them on this
is probably the reason that I'm most
excited to recommend Labelbox to people.
It wasn't just, oh, hey, tell us what
kind of data you need and we'll go get
it. They walked us through the entire
process from helping us identify what
kind of data we needed in the first
place to assembling a team of expert
aligners to generate it. Even after we
got all the data back, Labelbox stayed
involved. They helped us choose the
right base model and set up auto QA on
the model's output so that we could
tweak and refine it. And now we have a
new transcriber tool that we can use for
all our episodes moving forward. This is
just one example of how Labelbox meets
their customers at the ideas level and
partners with them through their entire
journey. If you want to learn more or if
you want to try out the transcriber tool
yourself, go to labelbox.com/barcash.
It seems to me that this is a very
precarious situation to be in where
looking the limit we know that this
should be possible because if you have
something that is as good as a human at
learning but which can merge its brains
merge there are different instances in a
way that humans can't merge already.
This seems like a thing that should
physically be possible. Humans are
possible, digital computers are
possible. You just need both of those
combined to produce this thing. And it
also seems like this kind of thing is
extremely um powerful
and economic growth is one way to put
it. Um I mean Dyson spear is a lot of
economic growth but another way to put
it is just like you will have
potentially a very short period of time
because a human on the job can you know
you you're hiring people at SSI in six
months they're like net productive
probably right um a human like learns
really fast and so this thing is
becoming smarter and smarter very fast
what is how do you think about making
that go well and why is SSI positioned
to do that well or what is SSI's plan
there basically is what I'm trying to
ask
>> yeah
so one of the one of the ways in which
my thinking has been changing is that
I now place more importance on AI
being
deployed
incrementally and in advance. One very
difficult thing about AI is that we are
talking about systems that don't yet
exist
and it's hard to imagine them.
I think that one of the things that's
happening is that in practice it's very
hard to feel the AGI.
It's very hard to feel the AGI.
We can talk about it, but it's like it's
like talking about like the long f like
imagine like having a conversation about
like how is it like to be old when
you're like old and and frail and you
can have a conversation. You can try to
imagine it, but it's just hard and you
come back to reality. Well, that's not
the case. And I think that a lot of the
issues around
AGI and its future power stem from the
fact that it's very difficult to imagine
future AI is going to be diff different.
It's going to be powerful. Indeed, the
whole problem, what is the problem of AI
and AGI? The whole problem is the power.
The whole problem is the power.
When the power is really big, what's
going to happen?
And one of the one of the ways in which
I've changed my mind over the past year
and so that that change of mind may back
may I'll say I I'll I'll hedge a little
bit may back propagate into into the
plans of our of our company is that
so if it's hard to imagine
what do you do you got to be showing the
thing you got to be showing the thing
and I maintain that I think I think most
people who work Con AI also can't
imagine it because it's too different
from what people see on a day-to-day
basis.
I do maintain here is something which I
predict will happen. That's a
prediction.
I maintain
that as AI becomes more powerful
then people will change their behaviors
and we will see all kinds of
unprecedented things which are not
happening right now and I'll give some
examples. I do like I I think I think
for better or worse the the frontier
companies will play a very important
role in what happens as will the
government and the kind of things that I
think we'll see which you see the
beginnings of
companies that are fierce competitors
starting collaborate to to collaborate
on AI safety you may have seen open AI
and anthropic event doing a first small
step but that did not exist That's
actually something which I predicted in
one of my talks about three years ago
that such a thing will happen. I also
maintain that as AI continues to become
more powerful, more visibly powerful,
there will also be a desire from
governments and the public to do
something
and I think that this is a very
important force
of showing the AI. That's number one.
Number two, okay, so then the AI is
being built. what needs to what needs to
be done.
So one thing that I maintain that will
happen is that right now people who are
working on AI I maintain that the AI
doesn't feel powerful because of its
mistakes.
I do think that at some point the AI
will start to feel powerful actually and
I think when that happens we will see a
big change in the way
all AI companies approach safety.
they'll become much more paranoid. I
think I I say this as a predict as a as
a as a prediction that we will see
happen. We'll see if I'm right, but I
think this is something that will happen
because they will see the AI becoming
more powerful. Everything that's
happening right now, I maintain is
because people look at today's AI and
it's hard to imagine the future AI.
And there is a third thing which needs
to happen. And I think this is this this
and I'm talking about it in in broader
terms not just from the perspective of
SSI
because you ask me about our company but
the question is okay so then what should
what should the companies aspire to
build
>> what should they aspire to build and
there has been one big idea that
actually every that um everyone has been
locked in locked into which is the the
self-improving AI
and why why did it happen because there
is fewer ideas than companies
But I maintain that there is something
that's better to build and I think that
everyone will actually want that. It's
like the AI that's robustly aligned to
care about sentient life specifically.
I think in particular it will be there's
a case to be made that it will be easier
to build an AI that cares about sentient
life than an AI that cares about human
life alone because the AI itself will be
sentient.
And if you think about things like
mirror neurons and human empathy for
animals which is you know you might
argue it's not big enough but it exists.
I think it's an emerging property from
the fact that we model others with the
same circuit that we used to model
ourselves because that's the most
efficient thing to do.
>> So even if you got an AI to care about
sentient beings and it's not actually
clear to me that that's what you should
try to do if you solved alignment. It
would still be the case that most
sentient beings will be AIS. There will
be trillions eventually quadrillions of
AIs. Humans will be a very small
fraction of sentient beings.
So, it's not clear to me if the goal is
some kind of human control over
this future civilization
that this is the best criterion.
>> It's true. I I think that
it's possible it's not the best
criterion. I'll say two things. I think
that thing number one
I think that if there so
I think that care for sentient life I
think there is merit to it. I think it
should be considered. I think that it
will be helpful if there was some kind
of a
short list of ideas that then the
companies when they are in this
situation could use. That's number two.
Number three, I think it would be really
materially helpful if the power of the
most powerful super intelligence was
somehow capped
because it would address a lot of these
concerns.
The question of how to do it, I'm not
sure, but I think that would be
materially helpful when you're talking
about really really powerful systems.
>> Yeah. Um, before we continue the element
discussion, I I want to double click on
that. How much room is there at the top?
How do you think about super
intelligence? Do you think I mean using
this learning efficiency idea maybe is
just extremely fast at learning new
skills or new knowledge and does it just
have a bigger pool of strategies? Is
there a single cohesive it in the center
that's more powerful or bigger? And if
so,
do you do you imagine that this will be
sort of godlike in comparison to the
rest of human civilization? or does it
just feel like another agent or another
cluster of agents?
>> So this is an area where different
people have different intuitions.
>> I think it will be very powerful for
sure. I think that what I think is most
likely to happen
is that there will be multiple
such AIS being created roughly at the
same time.
I think that
if the cluster is big enough, like if
the cluster is literally continent
sized, that thing could be really
powerful indeed, right? If you literally
have a continentsized cluster, like
those those AIs can be very powerful.
And I like all I can tell you is that if
you're talking about extremely powerful
AIs, like truly dramatically powerful,
then yeah, it would be nice if they
could be restrained in some ways or if
there was some kind of an agreement or
something
because I think that if you are saying
hey like if if you really like what what
is the the concern of super
intelligence? What is one way to explain
the concern? If you imagine a system
that is sufficiently powerful, like
really sufficiently powerful, and you
could say, okay, you need to do
something sensible like care for
sentient life, let's say, in a very
single-minded way, we might not like the
results. That's really what it is. And
so maybe, by the way, the answer is that
you do not build a single you do not
build an RL agent in the usual sense.
And actually, I'll point I'll point
several things out. I think human beings
are a semi agent. You know, we pursue a
reward and then the emotions or whatever
make us tire out of the reward. We
pursue a different reward.
The market is like kind it's like a very
shortsighted
kind of agent. Evolution is the same.
Evolution is very intelligent in some
ways but very dumb in other ways. The
government has been designed to be a
never- ending fight between three parts
which has an effect. So I think things
like this
another thing that makes this discussion
difficult is that we are talking about
systems that don't exist that we don't
know how to build
right that's the other thing and that's
actually my belief I think what people
are doing right now will go some
distance and then peter out it will
continue to improve but it will also not
be it so the it we don't know how to
build and I think that a lot h a lot
hinges on
understanding and in reliable
generalization
and I'll say another thing which is like
you know one of the things that you
could say is that cause alignment to be
difficult is that human val that it's
it's um
your ability to learn human values is
fragile then your ability to optimize
them is fragile will you actually learn
to optimize them and then can't you say
are these not all instances of
unreliable generalization
why is it that human beings appear to
generalize so much better. What if
generalization was much better? What
would happen in this case? What would be
the effect? But those we can't we can't
like those questions are right now still
unanswerable.
>> Um how [clears throat] does one think
about what AI going well looks like
because I think you've scoped out how AI
might evolve. We'll have these sort of
continual learning agents. AI will be
very powerful. Maybe there will be many
different AIs. How do you think about
lots of continent computes size
intelligences going around? How
dangerous is that? How do we make that
less dangerous? And how do we do that in
a way that
protects a equilibrium where there might
be misaligned AIs out there and bad
actors out there? So, one reason why I
liked the AI that cares for sentient
life,
>> you know, and we can debate on whether
it's good or bad, but
if the first N of these dramatic systems
actually do care for, you know,
love humanity or something, you know,
care for sentient life. Obviously, this
also needs to be achieved. This needs to
be achieved.
So if this is achieved by the first n of
those systems
then then I can see it go well at least
for quite some time and then there is
the question of what happens in the long
run what happens in the long run how do
you achieve a long run equilibrium
>> and I think that there there is an
answer as well and I don't like this
answer
but it needs to be considered
In the long run, you might say, okay, so
if you have a world where powerful AI
exist. In the short term, you could say,
okay, you have universal high income.
You have universal high income and we
all doing well. But we know that what do
the Buddhists say? Change is the only
constant. And so things change and there
is some kind of government political
structure thing and it changes because
these things have a shelf life. you know
some new new government thing comes up
and it functions and then after some
time it stops functioning
that's something that you see happening
all the time and so I think that for the
long run equilibrium
one approach you could say okay so maybe
every person will have an AI that will
do their bidding and that's good and if
that could be maintained indefinitely
that's true but the downside with that
is okay so then the AI goes and like
earns earn earn you know earns money for
for the person and you know advocates
for their needs in like the political
sphere and maybe then writes a little
report saying okay here's what I've done
here's the situation and the person says
great keep it up but the person is no
longer a participant
and then you can say that's a precarious
place to be in but so I'm going to
preface by saying
I don't like this solution but it is a
solution
And the solution is if people become
part AI with some kind of neural link++
because what will happen as a result is
that now the AI understands something
and we understand it too like
because now the understanding is
transmitted wholesale. So now if the AI
is in some situation now it's like you
are involved in the situation yourself
fully
and I think this is the answer to the
equilibrium. I wonder if uh the fact
that emotions which were
developed
millions or in many cases billions of
years ago in a totally different
environment are still guiding our
actions so strongly is an example of
alignment success to maybe spell out
what I mean the brain stem has these
I don't know if it's more accurate to
call it a value function or reward
function but the brain stem has a
directive where it's saying mate with
somebody who's more successful. The
cortex is the part that understands what
does success mean in the modern context
but the brain stem is able to align the
cortex and say however you recognize
success to be and I I'm not smart enough
to understand what that is. You're still
going to pursue this directive.
>> I think I think there is
so I think there's a more general point.
I think it's actually really mysterious
how the brain encodes high level
desires. Sorry, how evolution encodes
high level desires.
>> Like it's pretty easy to understand how
evolution would would endow us with the
desire for food that smells good cuz
smell is a chemical
and so just pursue that chemical. It's
very easy to imagine such a me evolution
doing such a thing. But evolution also
has has endowed us with all these social
desires like we we really care about
being seen positively by society. We
care about being in a good standing. We
like all these social intuitions that we
have. I feel strongly that they are
baked in and I don't know how evolution
did it because it's a high level
concept. It's represented in the brain.
like what people think like let's say
you are like you care about
some social thing.
It's not like a low-level signal like
smell. It's not something that for which
there's a sensor like the brain needs to
do a lot of processing to piece together
lots of bits of information to
understand what's going on socially and
somehow evolution said that's what you
should care about.
>> Yes.
>> How did it do it? And it did it quickly
too.
>> Yeah. because I think all these
sophisticated social things that um we
care about I think they evolved pretty
recently. So evolution had an easy time
hardcoding this high level desire and
>> I maintain or you know at least I'll say
I'm unaware of good hypothesis for how
it's done. I I had some ideas I was
kicking around but none of them none of
them uh are satisfying.
>> Yeah. And what's especially impressive
is if it was a desire that you learned
in your lifetime, it kind of makes sense
because your brain is intelligent. It
makes sense why we be able to learn
intelligent desires. But your point is
that the desire is maybe this is not
your point, but one way to understand it
is the desire is built into the genome
and the genome is not intelligent,
right? But it's able to you're somehow
able to describe this feature that
requires like it's not even clear how
you define that feature and you can get
it into the you can build it into the
genes. Yeah, essentially, or maybe I'll
put it differently. If you think about
the tools that are available to the
genome,
it says, okay, here's a recipe for
building a brain. And you could say,
here is a recipe for connecting the
dopamine neurons to like the smell
sensor.
>> Yeah.
>> And if the smell is a certain kind of,
you know, good smell, you want to eat
that. I could imagine the genome doing
that. I'm I'm claiming that it is harder
to imagine. It's harder to imagine the
genome saying you should care about some
complicated computation that your entire
brain that like a big chunk of your
brain does. That's all I'm claiming. I I
can tell you like a speculation. I was
wondering how it could be done. And let
me offer a speculation and I'll explain
why the speculation is probably false.
So the speculation is okay. So the brain
it's like the brain has those regions.
You know the brain regions. We have our
cortex, right?
>> Yeah.
>> It has all those brain regions and the
cortex is uniform. But the brain regions
and and and the neurons in the cortex,
they kind of speak to their neighbors
mostly. And that's explains why you get
brain regions because if you want to do
some kind of speech processing, all the
neurons that do speech need to talk to
each other and they can and because
neurons can only speak to their nearby
neighbors for the most part, it has to
be a region. All the regions are mostly
located in the same place from person to
person. So maybe evolution hardcoded
literally a location on the brain.
So it says, "Oh, like when when like you
know the GPS of the brain, GPS
coordinates, such and such, when that
fires, that's what you should care
about." Like maybe that's what evolution
did cuz that would be within the toolkit
of evolution. Yeah. Although there are
examples where for example people who
are born blind have that area of their
cortex adopted by
another sense and I have no idea but I'd
be surprised if the desires or the
reward functions which require visual
signal no longer worked. You know people
who have their different areas of their
cortex co-opted. For example, if you no
longer have vision,
can you still feel the sense that I want
people around me to like me and so
forth, which usually there's also visual
cues for.
>> So, I actually fully agree with that. I
I think there's an even stronger counter
argument to this theory,
>> which is like if you think about people,
so there are people who get half of
their brain removed in childhood.
>> Yeah. and they still have all their
brain regions, but they all somehow move
to just one hemisphere, which suggests
that the brain regions the the location
is not fixed. And so that theory is not
true. It would have been cool if it was
true, but it's not. And so I think
that's a mystery, but it's an
interesting mystery. Like the fact is
somehow
>> evolution was able to endow us to care
about social stuff very very reliably.
And even people who have like all kinds
of strange mental conditions and
deficiencies and emotional problems tend
to care about this. Also, AI tools like
defakes, voice clones, and agents have
dramatically increased the
sophistication [music]
of fraud and abuse. So, it's more
important than ever to actually
understand the identity and intent
[music] of whoever or whatever is using
your platform. That's exactly what
Sardine helps you do. Sardine brings
together thousands of device behavior
and identity signals to help you assess
risk. Everything from how a user types
or moves their mouse or holds their
device to whether they're hiding their
true location behind a [music] VPN to
whether they're injecting a fake camera
feed during KYC selfie checks. Sardine
combines these signals with insights
from their network of almost 4 billion
devices. things like a user's history of
fraud or their associations with other
high-risisk accounts so you can spot bad
actors before they do damage. This would
literally be impossible if you only use
data from your own [music] application.
Sardine doesn't stop at detection. They
offer a suite of agents to streamline
onboarding checks and automate
investigations. [music] So, as
fraudsters use AI to scale their
attacks, you can use AI to scale your
defenses. Go to sardine.ai/warcash.
AI/Swarcash
to learn more and download their guide
on AI fraud detection.
What is SSI planning on doing
differently? So presumably your plan is
to be one of the frontier companies when
this time arrives
and then what is
presumably you started SSI because
you're like I I think I have a way of
approaching how to do this safely in a
way that the other companies don't. What
what is that difference? So the way I
would describe it as
there are some ideas that I think are
promising and I want to investigate them
and see if they are indeed promising or
not. It's really that simple. It's an
attempt. I think that if the ideas turn
out to be correct, these ideas that we
discussed around understanding
generalization,
>> if these ideas turn out to be correct,
then I think we will have something
worthy. Will it turn out to be correct?
We are doing research. We are squarely
age of research company. We are making
progress. We've actually made quite good
progress over the past year. But we need
to keep making more progress,
>> more research.
>> And that's how I see it. I see it as an
attempt to be
an attempt to be a voice and a
participant.
Um people have asked uh your co-founder
and previous CEO left to go to Meta
recently and people have asked well if
there was a lot of breakthroughs being
made that seems like a thing that should
have been unlikely. I wonder how you
respond.
>> Yeah. So I in for for this I will simply
remind a few facts that may have been
forgotten and I think this these facts
which provide the context I think they
explain the situation. So the context
was that we were fundraising at a 32
billion valuation
and then Meta um came in and offered to
to acquire us and I said no
but my former co-founder
like in some sense said yes and as a
result he also was able to enjoy from a
lot of near-term liquidity and he was
the only person from SSI to join Meta.
It sounds like SSI's plan is to be a
company that is at the frontier when you
get to this
very important period in human history
where you have superhuman intelligence
and you have these ideas about how to
make superhuman intelligence go well but
other companies will be trying their own
ideas. What distinguishes SSI's approach
to making super intelligence go well?
The
>> the main thing that distinguishes SSI is
its technical approach.
So we have a different technical
approach that I think is worthy
and we are pursuing it.
I maintain that in the end there will be
a convergence of strategies. So I think
there will be a convergence of
strategies where
at some point as AI becomes more
powerful
it's going to become more or less
clearer to everyone what the strategy
should be. And it should be something
like, yeah, you need to find some way to
talk to each other. And you want your
first
actual like real super intelligent AI to
be aligned and somehow be,
you know, care for sentient life, care
for people, democratic, one of those,
some combination of thereof. And I think
this is the condition
that everyone should strive for and
that's what SSI is striving for and I
think that with time if not already all
the other companies will realizing that
they're striving towards the same thing
and we'll see. I think that the world
will truly change as AI becomes more
powerful.
>> Yeah.
>> And I think a lot of these forecasts
will like I think things will be really
different and people will be acting
really differently. What speaking of
forecast what are your forecasts to this
system you're describing which can learn
as well as a human and
subsequently as a result become
superhuman.
>> I think like uh 5 to 20
>> 5 to 20 years.
>> Mhm.
>> So I just want to unroll your
how you might see the world coming. It's
like we have a couple more years where
these other companies are continuing the
current approach and it stalls out and
stalls out here meaning they earn no
more than low hundreds of billions in
revenue or how do you think about what
stalling out means?
>> Yeah,
I think the re I think it could I think
it could stall out and
I think stalling out will look like
it will all look very similar.
>> Yeah.
>> Among all the different companies
something like this. I'm not sure
because I think I think I think even
with I think even I think even with
stolen out I think these companies could
make a stupendous stupendous revenue
maybe not profits because they will be
it will be they will need to work hard
to differentiate each other from
themselves but revenue definitely
>> but there's something in your model
implies that
the when the correct solution does
emerge there will be convergence between
all the companies and I'm curious why
you think that's the case
>> well I was talking more about converg
convergence on their larger strategies.
>> I think eventual convergence on the
technical approach is probably going to
happen as well but I I was alluding to
convergence to the larger strategies.
What what what exactly is the thing that
should be done?
>> I I just want to better understand how
you see the future on rolling. So
currently we have these different
companies and you expect their approach
to continue generating revenue. Yes.
>> But not get to this humanlike learner.
>> Yes.
>> So now we have these different forks of
companies. We have you we have thinking
machines. There's a bunch of other labs.
>> Yes. and maybe one of them figures out
the correct approach
>> but then the release of their product
makes it clear to other people how to do
this thing.
>> I think it won't be clear how to do it
thing but it will be clear that
something different is possible
>> right
>> and that is information and I think
people will will then be trying to
figure out how how that's how that
works. I do think though that one of the
things that's that I think you know not
addressed here not discussed is that
with each increase in the AI's
capabilities I think there will be some
kind of changes but I don't know exactly
which ones in how things are being done.
So like I think it's going to be
important yet I can't spell out what
that is exactly.
>> And how how are the
by default you would expect the company
that has the model company that has that
model to be getting all these gains
because they have the model that is
learning how to do all has the skills
and knowledge that it's building up in
the world. What is the reason to think
that the benefits of that would be
widely distributed and not just end up
at whatever model company gets this
continuous learning loop going first?
>> Like I think that empirically what
happen so here here is what I think is
going to happen. Number one, I think
empirically when
let's let's look at let's look at how
things have gone so far with um the AIs
of the past. So one company produced an
advance and the other company scrambled
and produced some competi some some
similar things after some amount of time
and they started to compete in the
market and push their push the prices
down
>> and so I think from the market
perspective I think something similar
will happen there as well even if
someone okay so okay so okay so okay so
okay so okay so okay so okay so okay so
okay so okay we talking about the good
world by the way where
what's the good world. What's the good
world?
Where we have these powerful humanlike
learners that are also like and by the
way maybe there there's another thing we
haven't discussed on the on the the spec
of the super intelligent AI that I think
is worth considering is that you make it
narrow
can be useful and narrow at the same
time. So you can have lots of narrow
super intelligent AIs. But suppose you
have many of them
and you have some and you have some
company that's producing a lot of um
profits from it and then you have
another company that comes in and starts
to compete and the way the competition
is going to work is through
specialization.
I think what's going to happen is that
the way
competition like competition loves
specialization and you see it in the
market, you see it in evolution as well.
So you're going to have lots of
different niches and you're going to
have lots of different companies who are
occupying different niches in
in this kind of world where you might
say yeah like one AI company is really
quite a bit better at some area of
really complicated economic activity and
a different company is better at another
area and the third company is really
good at litigation and that's
contradicted by what humanlike learning
implies is that like it can learn
>> it can but but you have accumulated
learning you have a big investment. You
spent a lot of compute to become really
really really good really phenomenal at
this thing and someone else spent a huge
amount of comput and a huge amount of
experience to get really really good at
some other thing
>> right
>> you apply a lot of human learning to get
there but now like you you are at this
high point where someone else would say
look like I don't want to start learning
what you've learned to go
>> I guess that would require many
different companies to begin at the
human like continual learning agent at
the same time so that they can start
their different research in different
branches. But if one company,
you know, gets that agent first or gets
that learner first,
it does then seem like well, you know,
they could like if you just think about
every single job in the economy,
you just have uh instance learning each
one seems tractable for a company.
>> Yeah, that's that's that's a valid
argument. My my strong intuition is that
it's not how it's going to go.
My strong intuition is that yeah like
the argument says it will go this way.
>> Yeah.
>> But my strong intuition is that it will
not go this way that this is the you
know in in theory there is no difference
between theory and practice. In practice
there is and I think that's going to be
one of those
>> a lot of people's models of recursive
self-improvement literally explicitly
state we will have a million Ilias in a
server that are coming in with different
ideas and this will lead to a super
intelligence emerging very fast. Do you
have some intuition about how
parallelizable the thing you are doing
is? How how what are the gains from
making copies of Ilia?
>> I don't know. I think
I think there'll definitely be there'll
be diminishing returns because you want
you want people who think differently
rather than the same. I think that if
they were literal copies of me, I'm not
sure how much more incremental value
you'd get. I think that
but people who think differently that's
what you want.
>> Why is it that it's been if you look at
different models even released by
totally different companies trained on
potentially non-over overlapping data
sets it's actually crazy how similar
LLMs are to each other.
>> Maybe the data sets are not as non-over
overlapping as it seems. But there's
there's some sense there's like even if
an individual human might be less
productive than the future AI. Maybe
there's something to the fact that human
teams have more diversity than teams of
AIs might have. But how do we elicit
meaningful diversity among AI? So I
think just raising the temperature just
results in gibberish. I think you want
something more like
>> different scientists have different
different prejudices or different ideas.
[clears throat] How do you get that kind
of diversity among AI agents? So the
reason there has been no diversity I
believe is because of pre-training.
All the pre-trained models are the same
pretty much because the pre-train on the
same data. Now RL and postraining is
where some differentiation starts to
emerge because different people come up
with different RL training.
>> Yeah. And then I've heard you hint in
the past about selfplay as a way to
either get data or match agents to other
agents of equivalent intelligence to
kick off learning. How should we think
about why there's no public
um proposals of this kind of thing and
working with LLM?
>> I would say there are two things to say.
I would say that the reason why I
thought selfplayful is interesting
is because it offered a way to create
models using compute only without data,
right? And if you think that data is the
ultimate bottleneck, then using compute
only is very interesting. So that's what
makes it interesting. Now the
the thing is
that selfplay at least the way it was
done in the past when you have agents
which are somehow compete with each
other it's only good for developing a
certain set of skills it is too narrow.
It's only good for like negotiation
uh conflict
certain social skills
strategizing that kind of stuff. And so
if you care about those skills then
selfplay will be useful. Now actually I
think that selfplay
did
find a home but just in a different form
in a different form. So things like
debate prove a verifier. You have some
kind of an LLM as a judge which is also
incentivized to find mistakes in your
work. You could say this is not exactly
selfplay but this is you know a related
adversarial setup that people are doing.
believe
>> and really selfplay is an example of um
is a special case of more general like
um competition between between agents,
>> right? The response the natural response
to competition is to try to be
different. And so if you were to put
multiple agents and you tell them, you
know, you all need to work on some
problem and you're an agent and you're
inspecting what everyone else is
working, you're going to say, well, if
they already taken this approach, it's
not clear I should pursue it. they
should pursue something differentiated
and so I think that something like this
could also create an incentive for um a
diversity of approaches.
>> Yeah. Um final question,
what is research taste? You're obviously
the person in the world who is
considered to have the best taste in
doing research in AI. you were uh the
co-author on many of the biggest the
biggest things that have happened in the
history of deep learning from Alex net
to GBT3 to so on what is it that how do
you characterize how
you come up with these ideas
>> I can answer so I can comment on this
for myself
>> I think different people do it
differently
>> but one thing that um guides me
personally
is
an aesthetic
of how AI should be
>> by thinking about how people are but
thinking correctly
>> like it's very easy to think about how
people are incorrectly but what does it
mean to think about people correctly
>> so I'll give you some examples
the idea of the artificial neuron is
directly inspired by the brain and it's
a great idea why because you say sure
the brain has all these different organs
has the faults but the faults probably
don't matter M
>> why do we think that the neurons matter?
Because there's many of them. It kind of
feels right. So you want the neuron.
>> Yeah.
>> You want some kind of local learning
rule that will change the connections.
You want some local learning rule rule
that will change the connections between
the neurons,
>> right? It feels plausible that the brain
does it. The idea of the distributed
representation,
the idea that the brain,
you know, the brain responds to
experience or neural network should
learn from experience, not response. The
brain learns from experience.
the neural network of experience and you
kind of ask yourself is some is
something fundamental or not fundamental
how things should be
>> and I think that's been guiding me a
fair bit kind of thinking from multiple
angles and looking for almost beauty
beauty simplicity ugliness there's no
room for ugliness it's just beauty
simplicity elegance correct inspiration
from the brain and all of those things
need to be present at the same time and
the more they are present the more
confident you can be in a top- down
belief. And then the top down belief is
the thing that sustains you when the
experiments contradict you. Because if
you just trust the data all the time,
well, sometimes you can be doing a
correct thing, but there's a bug.
>> But you don't know that there is a bug.
How can you tell that there is a bug?
>> How do you know if you should keep
debugging or you conclude it's the wrong
direction? Well, it's the top down.
Well, how should you can say the things
have to be this way? Something like this
has to work. Therefore, we got to keep
going. That's the top down. And it's
based on this like multifaceted beauty
and inspiration by the brain.
>> All right, we'll leave it there.
>> Thank you so much.
>> All right. Appreciate it.
>> That was great.
>> Yeah, I enjoyed it.
>> Yes, me too.
>> Hey everybody, I hope you enjoyed that
episode. If you did, the most helpful
thing you can do is just share it with
other people who you think might enjoy
it. It's also helpful if you leave a
rating or a comment on whatever platform
you're listening on. If you're
interested in sponsoring the podcast,
you can reach out at
dwarcash.com/advertise.
Otherwise, I'll see you on the next one.