We will be talking today about image
classification. Basically continuing our
our discussion on the topic of image
classification from last uh lecture and
we'll get a little bit into some
uh topics that gets us closer to neural
networks and and ultimately
convolutional neural networks and so on.
We'll start with linear classifiers.
Moving to the
next slide. This was the the syllabus
that we've talked about last uh lecture
in the in the previous lecture
where we did talk about three major
categories of
topics. Deep learning basics,
perceiving uh and understanding the
visual world, reconstructing and
interacting with the visual world as the
three major topics and and some sub um
topics that we will be covering in the
in the class and at at the end we will
have some discussions around the human-
centered AI aspects
and
today the goal is to cover the first
three items datadriven approaches. I
will I will try to tell you what this
means and
linear classification
as well as the K nearest neighbor
algorithm.
So
like last the previous lecture let's
start with our core task of
image classification. Again, it's a core
task in computer vision and we actually
come back to this task quite often
throughout the quarter because it's a
very good benchmark and we have some
examples to to tell you how the
algorithms work. So this is one of the
items that we come back to quite often.
We we want to define the the image
classification task today and then
introduce two of the datadriven
approaches for image classification. One
of them nearest neighbor and one of them
the other one near linear linear
classifier. There are some other
approaches which we have
listed in our backup slides and you're
welcome to to look at them after the
class.
But this is what we will be covering.
So what is image classification?
Given an image and
a number of predefined labels,
predetermined labels, a set of possible
labels such as in this example you see
dog, cat, truck, plane, and so on.
The job of the system is to assign one
of those labels to this uh image.
So
to us this is actually a very very easy
task because our brains our co cognitive
system is wired to
get a holistic understanding of this
image and assign a label to it. But when
it comes to coding this and and looking
at how a computer can make sense of this
image that's a that's completely a
different story
and we want to see how machines can make
sense of such data. So images are often
defined
by matrices of data
more broadly more generally tensors of
data
and often the numbers are the each of
the pixel values are between zero and
255 which is a 8 bit um data structure
and since this is an image a colored
image
assuming that it's with a resolution of
800 by 600.
Since it's an R RGB image, it has three
channels of red, green, and blue RGB.
And therefore, it's a tensor of 800 by
600 by 3 as you can see on the slide.
So, um,
as you can probably guess, this is the
semantic gap between our perception of
this image and how the machine perceives
and and sees the the image, right? And
in order to be able to uh even
understand how this this could be very
challenging let's look at some some
challenges some some variations in this
type of imaging u data. So let's assume
for example as as one example let's
assume that um we move the camera if the
camera is moved for example panning the
camera around
even if the cat sits completely and
perfectly still all of those pixel
values every single pixel value of 800
by 600 by3 will be changed.
So all these pixels will have a new
value. Again, for us humans, it's the
same object. There's no absolutely no
difference. But from a computer's
perspective, it's completely a new data
point. So this is one of the challenges,
but there are quite a few
others as well. For example,
illumination is another um challenge.
So if you've seen or if you've taken
courses in graphics or maybe uh other
other vision courses
and or digital image processing uh
courses for engineering applications
you know that the value of each RGB uh
pixel the RGB values are a function of
the surface material color and their
light source
and and that's Why same cat, same object
may look at differently in terms of
numbers when it comes to
uh being pictured in different
illumination conditions.
With that uh in mind, so whether the cat
is in a dark room or under the sun,
still it's the cat. It's it's it's one
cat. But um this is creating challenges
for for the machine. Can you maybe name
some other other challenges that um may
change the the values of the pixels and
create problems for the machine to to
recognize objects
other than illumination and viewpoint
changes that I mentioned. So background
background clutter background objects
yes which is actually our next slide.
Yes, background uh clutter is another
challenge. What? Anything else?
Zooming in and out. Yes. So, the scale
basically of the object in the in the
image. Yes. What else? The resolution of
the image that is that could be
considered as that's definitely a
challenge. But often with um machine
learning models or or any model that we
want to recognize action um objects in
in images since we normalize the size of
the image resolution may not be that uh
important unless there is zooming
effects of the the objects. Occlusion is
one of the major problems. Again as
humans it's very easy to say this is cat
these are cats. Even the last one which
is actually a very challenging the one
on the on the right. You can only see a
tail and a little bit of probably paw in
in the right side.
One could say yes that could be a tiger
or it could be I don't know a raccoon
with a tiny tail. But because this is
because of the context, because we know
this is inside a living room on a couch,
most probably it's a cat. It's a cat. So
again, for us humans, it's not that
hard. Beyond that, there are many other
problems. Deformation cats are very
deformable. So
they
create challenges for for algorithms to
be uh detected recognized.
I mean not today's algorithms generally
for building uh step-by-step um
algorithms that can detect objects. So
deformation is one of the other major
challenges
and beyond that the intra class
variation is one more important
challenge.
We know that cats uh can come in
different sizes, colors, patterns or
even they can they have different breeds
and all of those are still cats. But um
for the for the machines it's it's not
that easy to recognize the intraclass
variations.
One other interesting challenge is the
context
because
if you only look at that
that part that that image on the right
or if an algorithm looks at this without
considering the context it's very easy
to classify this as a tiger or some
other animal. But because of the context
and because we know that there's the
effect of shadows and so on, this could
probably be classified correctly.
So,
but the thing is that the classifiers
that we have today can do really great
job, a good jobs at
classifying the images, identifying the
objects in images. Thanks to efforts
like ImageNet and also all of the
follow-up works that created larger
scale benchmarks for training larger
scale models and um
and and in this class what we want to do
is to get to uh to a place that we build
models that can recognize activ u
recognize objects and also other um
aspects. within the image. For the rest
of this class, we are going to be
working towards building step by step
the building blocks that are needed for
building those large algorithms. And
before doing so, uh we have to look at
the most basic building block
of classifying an image and that is
building implementing a function like
this. So if you've taken some of the
computer science or engineering courses
that often build
frameworks through algorithms like for
example sorting in uh as a as a computer
algorithm it's often it often comes with
some if then else rules and some for
loops and so on. So there's there's a
clear flowchart of um tasks and
step steps if then else steps that
creates an algorithm for sorting. But
when it comes to images and
understanding the visual world that is
um not happening that is a challenge
there is no way to hardcode the steps
for classifying images. Although
there has been some efforts um in this
space, there are papers
that
they've they've uh tried to come up with
algorithms and steps to recognize
objects. And one of those was based on
um edge detectors,
finding the edges in
um in in the image as a first step. And
then after after creating all of these
patterns, look at
uh the important patterns. for example,
corners. Extract some features that are
around the corners or count the number
of specific types of corners and based
on those from those try to map that into
the output class. So while this is been
an interesting effort and and it had
some success on very limited um
variability of type of images but this
is very hard to first it's very hard to
scale these types of algorithms. Even if
it works it's very hard to scale because
you have to create these rules and
everything for every single object that
you want to recognize. and second
finding the logic for each of those
requires a lot of uh effort by itself as
well. So because of these challenges, I
think um
these types of algorithms which are u
based on creating logics and procedures
for detecting objects or classifying
images have not been quite successful
and machine learning comes with this
datadriven approach. So with this new
paradigm of and another paradigm of
looking at this problem from a
datadriven
perspective,
we define a a procedure of a three-step
process and the first one is to collect
data sets of images and their labels. So
there are many different ways of if you
have if you want to recognize a specific
type of object
we or or specific types of objects we
can look for data sets or single data
points over the internet to create a
data many samples from each of the
examples.
We used to be doing this 10 20 years ago
uh using search engines and image search
engines over the internet to create
these types of data sets. Now we have
all of the data sets. So
and then the second step is using
machine learning algorithms to train a
classifier. basically build a function
train that takes the
images in the training data and their
associated labels and builds a model
that can relate associate images with
the labels. And then um the last step
would be evaluating the classifier on
new
images
which means implementing a function
called predict that takes the model and
some test images and for those test
images that were were not part of the
training images um predicts the labels
and returns those as the output. So a
very simple procedure but instead of
building a logic we are building a
datadriven approach for it.
As I said we want to talk about two
popular methods and and classifiers. One
of them is nearest neighbor classifier.
This is the easiest form of
classification. Um, and
we specifically want to go over this
because we can learn some of the
concepts
around building these classifiers and
it's easier to explain some um
some of the details and then we'll move
to the topic of linear classification.
Okay. to do that what we do uh to build
the nearest neighbor classifier as as I
said we need to build the train and
predict functions the train function
needs to just memorize all of the data
and labels so the training function
basically doesn't do anything other than
keeping everything in the memory and
then the prediction function the predict
uh function
looks for the most similar training
image basically It creates a lookup
table of all of the images and all of
their labels. And during the prediction
or testing time, what what it does is
tries to find the closest one, the the
most similar image and outputs the label
for that image. Let's look at an
example. So assuming that we have these
five
as in your in our training data then yes
you you see my cursor and then um this
is the query image the input image for
for prediction. What we want to do is to
see which of these training data and
training images is the most similar to
this one and for that we need a distance
function. So this distance function
needs to take the two images each pair
of images each of these images compared
to the query image and return a value
which defines the similarity between
these two
uh inputs these two images. There are
many different ways of doing that. One
of the most popular ones is
L1 distance which is defined as the sum
over all absolute values of pixel
differences
between the two images image I1 and I2.
As an example, if this is a testing
image,
if we
want to calculate the distance of this
image with
uh an image in the training data, we do
a pixel wise subtraction
and the difference between the pixel
values and then sum them up which
defines this new this value as
as the uh the distance between these two
So
this is the most basic distance function
but it's actually very useful in many
applications. We'll be coming back to
this uh L1 and and any other variations
of distances in the class quite often
with this very simple definition. We
want to see how we can get it get this
implemented. As I said the first step is
to just memorize the training data. So
the train function just keeps the data
in the memory and then
what the predict function does using
actually some um Python libraries and
numpy and so on. We can implement this
in just four lines. We calculate the
distances between each of the testing
samples
and the training data.
Take the minimum for each of the testing
samples and then output the label for it
for the for the for the one with mean
index. So this is going to be the uh
implementation for for the predict
function. Yeah, the the pixel values as
I explained
the most the the the simplest form this
is a tensor of 800 by 600 by3
and three channels and these are RGB
values for each of the pixel uh
locations. So yes the I should actually
repeat the questions for online students
too and the question was the pixel
values what do they represent? Yeah. So
the next question is why it's between 0
and 255. Um so the there are many
different standards for storing images.
The most popular one that we use in in
almost all images that you see online
and uh and here they are RGB. RGB is a
24bit format sometimes 32 because
there's an another channel alpha. We
don't want to get into uh into those but
the 24bit format it means that for each
of the channels for each of the three
channels of red green and blue which
create all of all color color
combinations we can have eight bits. So
that's that's the standard that is uh
defined. There are some other frameworks
too but this is the most popular one.
So um with that let me
go back to the code and ask you a
question.
So
[Applause]
I know some of the students uh most of
the students um come with engineering
backgrounds and a little bit of computer
science as well. But we want to see
with say n samples n examples that we
have in the training data how fast the
training and prediction happens.
I'm hoping that you're familiar with the
big O notation that we often u represent
computational and sometimes space
complexities with. But here if you look
at the the algorithms I'll I'll go with
the training data in the in the training
function uh and then I want you to help
me with the
the dancer for prediction for the
training step the the training is of 01
because we are not actually doing
anything we are not even moving any data
we're just keeping the copy of the data
in the memory so no operations it means
that without operations with and
operations of order one we can
complete the training step. What about
the prediction step? For each of the
single examples of
the um the training the testing data,
how many operations should we should we
take? And uh yes, if we have n training
data, it means that we have to calculate
the distance of every single uh testing
image with all of the images in the
training data. So at least in the order
of n operations.
So
this is um this is this is not really
good because what we often want to do is
because training is not doing anything
but during testing during prediction
time we are spending so much time uh
just to do comparisons with between the
data and the each single data point and
the training examples.
This would be similar to
the fact that each single time that you
ask that GPT a question, it will try to
see what the answer is and compare it
with all of the possible answers over
the internet, which will take years and
then return your your your response,
right? So it it wouldn't work when it
wants to it wants to scale for very
simple problems. We used to be using
these types of approaches. So what we
often want is to
build classifiers uh that are fast
during prediction. They they do it much
faster but it's okay if they take a lot
of time to do uh during the training
because that could be done offline. So
with that um in mind although there has
been a lot of efforts making uh nearest
neighbor more
much faster
using GPUs and so on which are beyond
the the scope of this class. If you're
interested you can take a look at those.
But with that I want to look at some of
the visualizations and and how this this
algorithm in general works. So given
this space that we have five classes of
red, blue, green, purple and red sorry
yellow. Um
and each dot represents one one training
sample in that class.
If you partition the space for every
single point, you see that we can we can
create these five partitions. um let's
say five or in this case six different
partitions that
each point um if if you have a testing
sample that is in that specific region
the color of that region shows what the
nearest neighbor for that sample will
be. So this this is going to be the
nearest neighbor algorithm. One nearest
neighbor algorithm partition the space
in this um setting. But do you see a
problem here in this uh example? So the
yellow one is is exactly is in the
middle of all of the greens. And this
means that probably that's an outlier.
That's probably a noise. And this is the
case for many many problems that we have
to solve. And with that um
the reason that u there are there is
this this big yellow region in the
middle is just this single point and
because you're only using one nearest
neighbor this happens. So to make it a
little bit more robust we can increase
the number of nearest neighbors that we
take which turns the nearest neighbor
algorithm into a k nearest neighbor. And
we often
select more than one
point or or sample. And we often take
the majority voting for
for identifying the label for any given
testing sample testing image.
But the problem that uh you can see here
is now we have some white regions. Those
white regions are areas that we cannot
make a decision a complete decision
because those areas are areas that we
have equal number of samples from the
neighbors um from the three different
classes and there's no way to identify
what the label of that per that example
in the in the white region is. And for
for you if you create these these types
of spaces for your problems this means
that if if you look at these type spaces
it means that those are good regions to
go and collect more data for. So those
are unclear spaces. So it's a good way
of finding regions that are important
for data uh more data collection. Okay.
So we can go larger on the value of the
K. But one of the choices that we have,
one of the
um
factors that that plays an important
role is the value of K. But if you
remember, we had another decision to
make which was the distance function. We
talked about the L1 distance. Again, sum
of all of the absolute values
between pair-wise differences of um the
pixels.
And
if I visualize the L1 distance or
sometimes in some context we call it
Manhattan distance,
the the distance function is is kind of
visualized in this way.
If I calculate if I if I look at this
square that I have in the
in this space all of the points on that
square are they have a same distance
from the origin from the center point.
So
this is a good way of visualizing and
seeing how uh this L1 distance function
works. Another popular framework,
another popular distance function that
we use is L2 which instead of the
absolute value calculates the square of
the differences sums it up but because
of the square we also do a square root
and visualizing that we'll get the
circle
um
visualization where each of the points
on the circle are they have the same
distance from the from the center from
the origin. So this visualization
actually helps us understand the
differences between these distances too
and these are the the most basic and
easiest distance functions that we can
use. So there are again a lot more the
um the reason this visualization is
helpful is because sometimes if you
rotate the so x and y in these two
visualizations are basically the
features. If we have two pixel values,
two two features then they have this 2D
space and this X and Y are often those
features. So if I rotate these features
meaning if I use other types of features
this L1 will have a different different
framework different value while it's not
any different for L2. So that's why this
is a big difference between L1 and L2.
And sometimes if our features are are
very specific and meaningful and we want
to preserve their information, often L1
is is is more important is is better
because it has um kind of as you can see
um a shape that preserves and and
enforces distances based on the
features. But if uh there is features
are more arbitrary then L2 distance
makes more sense. If I um want to
calculate the distance so the distance
of all of the points on this shape
from the origin are exactly the same
right if I use the L1 distance. But for
L2 distance,
the points on this circle have the same
distance from uh the center uh or the
origin of this uh
this space. So um that's basically the
the main
what what these two images are showing.
Any point on this shape
when using an L1 distance have the same
distance from the origin and for the
circle any point on the circle if you're
using L2 distance will have the same
distance from the origin.
Yeah. Why it's important to is better to
use L1 if we want to preserve the
features. So to answer that question, if
I rotate the feature um axis the the
distances and this distance function
changes completely, right? While if I do
the same here,
nothing changes. It's it's the exact
same value of the uh features, right? Uh
distance, sorry. So in this case L1 is
very sensitive on the feature values
while L2 is not. If you select another
feature in the same space that is having
a different creates a different shape
then your L function the distance
function changes as well. So if I draw
the lines here again the question for
online students is why it changes if we
rotate. If I select another feature that
goes from this side, right, then the
lines will look different,
right? So if you rotate the this thing,
but it's for that shape, it's not it's
agnostic, right?
So with these two distance functions
that we talked about, if I revisualize
the
um space you can see with K equals to
one with one nearest neighbor with L1
and L2 these are the space
partitionings. One of the interesting
things that you can see here is that
with L1
uh function most of the part most of the
boundaries are
parallel to the the the two axis the two
features X uh one and X2 very much
sensitive to the features while there we
have a little bit of more smooth
uh boundary separation.
So there is a tool online on the lab
website that you can uh play around with
with this with different distance
functions and different number of K. You
can you can see you can create a
different setup. So you can play around
with it. But why did we talk about
nearest neighbor to begin with first?
Yes, it's it's the easiest um problem to
solve, easiest solution, easiest
datadriven approach and um great to
start with. But one of the main reasons
that we
>> we want to iterate and and discuss
nearest neighbor is the fact that we can
look into the the the topic of
hyperparameters.
Hyperparameters are often
some of the
variables that you have to make a
decision on to be able to run your
algorithm. In this case, the value k
the number of nearest neighbors is
defined is is a hyperparameter.
Depending on how many number of uh
nearest neighbors you take, your outputs
will be different. And then another
choice that you have here is the
distance function.
So the
choice of hyperparameters are often very
much data set dependent and sometimes
problem dependent
and we have to have a way to identify
those to kind of optimize for them
for each single problem. And that's what
does what is often referred to as
hyperparameter tuning in machine
learning algorithms in in deep learning
algorithms and so on. And how to do
that? How to set
the hyperparameters? There are different
approaches. One of them is to choose the
hyperparameters that that work the best
for the training data. So you have a set
of images or data in in your training
data. You look for
the best set of hyper hyperparameters
that generates the best training
uh or
minimum training loss. While it works
for the training data, it's not a good
idea at all because especially with near
nearest neighbor, K equal to one is
always the best the best value, right?
Because you're you're memorizing
training data. So K equal to one will
give give you always the 100% accuracy.
So we know that this is this is not a
great idea. The second one is
choosing hyperparameter that works best
for for a held out testing set.
While this is a little bit better than
the first one,
there is also a big problem here. Can
can anybody say why this is a problem
exactly? And so it's it's it's kind of
cheating because you are trying to find
the best hyperparameter that works on
the testing data and you don't know how
the model will work on any other data
points not not in the testing set. So
yes that is that is exactly right. It's
not a good idea because we don't know
how the model will generalize and for
sure never do it do this as as as we
talked about it's kind of cheating and a
better idea is to always separate take
some part of the training data as
validation set
and train your model on the training
data on the train portion of the the new
portion that we call train and then Try
to find or optimize your hyper
hyperparameter on the validation set and
after you've found the best set of
hyperparameters then use those
hyperparameters to replicate the results
for the testing set and do the
predictions for the testing set. So this
is a much better approach although it
does have some uh challenges itself
because um
sometimes the the validation set that
you've selected it may not be a good
representative of the entire landscape
because you your validation set is
almost always much smaller and and
that's why one of the a better approach
is to use um
cross validation for setting
hyperparameters.
Basically you split your training data
into a number of folds, a number of uh
partitions here in this case five and
each of the folds
plays as the validation set once and
iteratively you you run this five times
for five-fold class validation. You do
this five times and average the
accuracies. So you set a a value of the
hyperparameter. You run this for all
these five uh sets.
Define the accuracy. Calculate the
accuracy on the validation set. Average
it. And then you do this multiple times
to find the best setting for the
hyperparameter. After you found the
hyperparameter setting, you apply to the
testing set. This is a little bit more
reliable and and generates much better
results. Although in larger scale deep
learning it is less
practiced because repeating this
multiple times and five times with huge
data sets is is very hard. So we often
use intuitions for setting
hyperparameters and the single
validation set is some sometimes the the
approach we go with. But this is pretty
much uh advised
again outside computer vision outside
larger scale data sets. Often research
papers require doing these types of
cross validation and um
and and these types of uh statistical
frameworks to make sure your results are
uh reproducible on a testing set.
Anyways, so there are different
approaches. Let's um finalize the topic,
wrap up the topic of um
nearest neighbor and um look at the some
examples, some results.
So, let me introduce you to the CR10
data set. It's one of the data sets that
you're going to be using in your
assignments um quite often. It has 10
classes with a number of training um
images and testing images. The 10
classes, some of the examples are shown
here with nearest neighbor. For each of
the testing images, if we run
nearest neighbor and select the top 10
nearest neighbors, they are all
um visualized there.
As you can imagine and guess, one of the
first questions to answer is how many
what should be the value for K? How many
nearest neighbors should we take? And
one study, one of the
quick experiments with five-fold each of
those points is uh is one of the folds
in fivefold for each of the values of K
shows
different values here. And as you can
probably see here, K equal to 7
generates the best results in terms of
accuracy, which is close to 29 28%
accuracy,
which is actually not too bad because
this is a 10 classification problem. And
with a 10 classification problem, often
the random guess gets you a 10%
accuracy. So this is much better than
random guess. So it's working. It's
doing something but there's a lot of
room to improve. So if we go back and
look at the examples, we can actually
see there are so many mistakes,
especially with the with the one that is
closest. For example, the fourth row, if
you look at that, it's a it's a frog,
but the first example seems to be a cat.
Sorry, a dog. And um you can guess why
this is happening because the distance
is being applied on pixels
and pixel wise they look like each
other. They have the same type of colors
in most pixels. So they are much closer.
This this example and many other
examples show that distances that work
on pixels and pixel values are not the
best choices. we never we never practice
them. There are much better approaches
that we'll discussing
um at the end of more um in the in the
future lectures. And just to wrap up the
topic, this is another example. If you
look at this original image, those three
images while they look very much
different in terms of color or maybe uh
occlusion or the one in the uh the the
third one from uh from the left side is
just same pixel. It's the same image
with one pixel shifting to the right. I
think although from a human eyes
perspective there's no absolutely no
difference but the this the distance
between that and the original image is
the same as the other two examples that
you see here. I'll um stop for a couple
of questions and this is the summary of
what we've discussed. So the question is
what how we make a decision right that's
in those cases you often go with random
uh randomly selected one of the tops. So
if you are to collect more data,
if you're uh for example, you're solving
a problem now in genetics or you're
solving a problem in medical imaging,
when you visualize your um examples,
your features or whatever. And then in
this nearest neighbor space, you do see
pockets of space that you don't have any
any good samples for or there is
ambiguity,
then you often try to go and find other
samples that lie in that same area in
that space. Okay. Um so summarizing what
we've uh talked about with K nearest
neighbor it was mostly about
um
understanding the easiest algorithm
datadriven approach and then um talking
a little bit about hyperparameter tuning
and and how distance metrics and the
value of K play a very important role.
Moving on to the next topic which is
linear classifiers. 20 five minutes uh
time to cover this. I want to
spend the remaining time of this lecture
to to talk about this very important
topic. This is the most important
building block for almost
all of deep learning.
and um
and we need to um see
how this this approach is different. So
first we want to see how it's different
from nearest neighbor. So this is a
parametric approach meaning that now we
are learning we are we are finding some
parameters W or some weights that map
the input image into the output classes
the output numbers. In this case, when
we create this function f that that maps
input to the output, often those outputs
are kind of membership scores
of the image to each of those 10 uh
output classes labels. So with this
setup that we we build, a linear
classifier
first maps uh uses uses w uses these
parameters to map each of the inputs x
into a value which is the output y. And
how this is done is very simple. This
image is basically an area of say 32x
32x3.
So
372 numbers and this defines
our X which is 372 by one vector and we
know that we have 10 output classes. So
we need 10 different scores and the
scores are the the output will be kind
of a vector of 10 by one and this means
that we have to identify to find a
weight matrix W that is a 10 by 372
that maps X into the output scores.
just to complete this linear function.
We often use this bias um
term as well. It's an input independent
um value which actually has a lot of
different use cases. I I can talk about
it uh when I do some geometric
visualizations, but it it sometimes
creates a shift for different um class
class scores and um helps with much
better
separation of each each class. So as I
said, these linear functions are
actually building blocks for building
neural networks. Each of these linear
classifiers, linear uh functions when
put together one after the other create
these uh large neural networks.
Although there are a lot other a lot of
other things that that need to be added
here but um this is one of the most
important components. If we look at some
of the
popular
neural networks, we can see that linear
functions are everywhere in the in the
architectures.
So to better understand what this
mapping and this function is doing,
let's let's go back to our example of
CR10 and our uh training and testing
samples and so on and even make it a
little bit simpler. Instead of looking
at large images of 32x 32, let's look at
images of 2x two um an input image that
has four pixels. This means that
the input image is turned into a vector.
As you can see here, we have to find a W
and the values of B. So the input image
is mapped into some scores as the
output. So
this is this is how the linear function
from an algebraic viewpoint looks like.
The output scores here we are
considering three classes of cat, dog
and and chip. And um as you can see this
function maps the image the vector
representing the image into those
scores.
So
algebraic viewpoint of linear
classification. Now let's look at some
visual uh perspectives of this linear
classifier.
As you can see, we often create these
like each of these images as um
we talked about for each this image for
each of the
classes we define some sort of we have a
we have a row of this m row in the
matrix W right. So this this row is kind
of a template for that specific class.
If I separate it like this. So this
image is multiplied by W and B and W is
this is the template from each of the
three classes of cat, dog and ship. And
after training or building the model on
the C4 data set, if I look at the visual
uh perspective visual uh a a visual
point viewpoint of the linear
classifier, if I look at those templates
that are learned for each of the 10
classes, you can see these these
templates. So it's very interesting that
in some of these cases for example for
the for the example for car you do see a
front uh the front of a car templateish
and um although this is all done with
just one linear classifier.
So the visual aspect visual uh viewpoint
of the linear classifier and there is
another aspect of um geometric
viewpoint.
What this linear classifier often does
is finding those lines if it's in 2D
space finding those lines that separates
each each class from the others.
And as you can see here, red, blue and
and green are defined in different
classes. And um in higher dimensional
space, instead of those lines, it's it's
it's these hyperplanes as you can see in
this example on the on the left.
So
you can also see the the use of the the
bias term here because if if we didn't
have the bias all of these lines should
have passed through the origin from the
center of that space which doesn't
really make sense but with the with the
bias we can actually create more
reliable
functions uh and and uh decision
boundaries.
So
a linear function is very useful. A
linear classifier is very useful for
many applications as uh we talked about
and it's a building block of
more complex neural networks but it does
have its own challenges because it
doesn't it can't classify many instances
of separate uh data. For example, in in
this case, if class one is the first and
third quadrant and the second class is
second and the fourth, there's no way to
linearly separate these. Another example
is
um if if we have this type of separation
between class one and class two that uh
shows the distance from the origin being
between one and two as class one and
then everything else is class two.
Similarly, if there is there are three
modes, three areas in the space that are
one class and then the second class is
everything else. So, in in all of these
cases, it's actually very hard to to do
the separation.
So
what we um should do so we talked about
the linear classifiers and and how they
uh they can actually map the input
images into any form of labels in the
outputs. But
now what remains is how to choose the
value W that for each of these images
maps the image into a score for each
single class as the output.
And in order to do that, we need to
define a loss function, sometimes
referred to as objective function that
quantifies how bad the classifier, how
bad the model is is working. So the
level of unhappiness with uh respect to
the score on the training data.
After defining those, we need to find a
way to efficiently change the values of
W to be able to op uh to to to minimize
that unhappiness basically minimize the
loss function. And this is the this is
the optimization
process. So the topic of next class,
next next lecture. And
in order to do that again for simplicity
let's let's look at a easier and easier
example having these three classes a
linear function as you can see here and
the
three classes of cat car and frog. We
need a loss function that tells how good
our current classifier is. And in order
to do that we need to parameterize the
problem X I and Y I defining the input
image label images and the corresponding
labels. And then we need a loss function
in distance function that
maps uh looks at the the differences and
how bad the scores are compared to the
ones that are predicted. this the
predicted scores fx and w and the ground
truth values the values that are already
given y i's we often uh normalize them
based on the number of samples as well
but uh it's not that important so this
defines the loss function the objective
function
so
how we can do the um optimization and
and how can we uh
really find the the W's. There are
different ways of defining this L
li LI and I want to talk about softmax
classifier.
Uh right now
as an example
for that cat if you remember the scores
that were given were um 3.2 5.1 and a
minus 1.7. These are um the the scores
that are the output of the function. We
decid we discussed fxi and w. And
in order to turn these scores because
these scores are unbounded and the
values are often not very much uh
controllable
because this is just a linear function,
right? In order to turn these into some
scoring functions,
the best the possible best possible way
is to turn these into probabilities
which defines the probability
of the class being this class K for each
inputs image XI. Right? And in order to
do that, we first
this is the the function that we we use
the soft max function. We first
exponentiate the values of the scores to
create these numbers. When we use exp on
these numbers, the the numbers will
always be the outputs will always be
positive, right? And we need to make
sure that the probabilities are always
positive. And after creating these
numbers, what we can do is just
normalize them.
So exponentiate and then normalize based
on sum of all of the samples. Right? So
then we normalize them based on sum of
all samples and this creates
very um very good set of values that
define a probability function. So this
is a distribution function. they sum to
one. And
if I want to interpret this, it's very
simple to say it's this this set of W's
parameters
thinks that this image is a cat with a
probability of 13%. Or 13, right? And um
obviously this is this is making making
a mistake in this example because the W
is not a good setting. We should um
optimize it and change it. So these
probabilities are the counterparts of
these unnormalized
uh log probabilities which are often
referred to as logits. So
if you've uh taken other machine
learning courses or if you I'm sure in
other fields you've used uh logistic
regression. This is a similar type of
framework. This is the exact same
framework as logistic regression
and since we have multiple classes here
it's a multinnomial logistic regression.
How do we define the function L? I told
you that there are different ways of
defining the function L.
We want to define a loss function that
what's the objective here? We want to
maximize
the probability of
the sample belonging to the correct
class. Right? So we want to maximize the
value of3.
Now we have other larger values in in
that um
set. So
if you want to maximize this this is a
maximization problem right in order to
turn it because all of the objectives
that we define we try to build the
minimization objective function. The
first step is just to
uh to negate the values right we negate
it. So the maximization problem turns
into a minimization problem. And then we
also take the log of the value just to
uh make the numbers a little bit more
manageable. So negative log of that
value will define the objective function
the the loss function for solving this
problem. Very simple. That's that's the
objective or the loss function for um
softmax and um for for this logistic
regression function and if you've taken
as I said other other classes like CS2
um it's often referred to as maximum
likelihood estimation as well it's the
same algorithm
so with that in mind I want to say that
So as as as we discussed it's the
negative of the log of that probability
of the correct class
which defines the objective function the
loss function
and that's basically that simple but
there are other types of interpreting
this this framework as well. So
one way of um
redefining this loss function is saying
that we have some estimated
probabilities and we also have a
probability function that that defines
the correct probabilities. What we want
to do is to match these two probability
functions. Right? And in order to to do
that we want to minimize the KL
divergence call back laborer divergence.
This is a information theoretic u
perspective of looking at this uh loss
function. And again
those are exactly the same. this um KL
divergence in this setting
simplifies into the same negative log
function that we defined. And even going
further, this is
um exactly the cross entropy function
because if if we define this um use this
entropy of P
which is um uh entropy of the correct
values, correct probabilities plus the
same KL divergence. Again, this
simplifies into the same negative log
function. And that's because when we use
one hot encoding setting for the classes
the entropy is zero. So that's one of
the reasons that we call this function
cross entropy or binary cross entropy
function in in all of deep learning
you've probably
if you've used any of the neural network
frameworks you've heard about BCE binary
cross entropy or you will be hearing
about it a lot. So this is the same uh
framework. We start very simple but we
got to the
to the
uh similarities and differences between
each of those. So the objective the
sorry the loss function was defined as
negative log of this probability and the
probability was was defined by the
softmax which we talked about and and
then optimizing for this which is the
topic of next session will give us the
right W's. But before I end I want to
ask a couple of questions with this
definition that you see here. What is
the mean and maximum
value that you can see for the loss
function li?
Yes, it's zero which we which turns into
minus minus infinity but we have a a
negative negation there. So it would be
infinity that is correct. But then we
also have to uh
yes that that's that's definitely um
that's right. And um let me actually
look at a second question. Yes, this
one.
So when we initialize all of the SI, so
basically the W's in the beginning, it's
almost random. So the probabilities of
each of the classes becomes mostly
um
equal. What is the softmax LI? assuming
we have C classes
and especially if it's C 10.
So because the probabilities are equal
it means that all of the probabilities
are around 1 / C right and then that
will uh be defined as log of C and we
have 10 if we have 10 classes then the
log or ln of 10 is 2.3 which is the um x
we know we know about