Thank you everyone for coming. Um we
have another guest lecture. Uh and today
we have Ranjay Krishna. Uh Ranjay
Krishna is a assistant professor at the
school of computer science and
engineering at the University of
Washington and he co-directs the Raven
lab. Um he has taught previous
iterations of CS231N in 2020 and 2021
and his research lies at the
intersection of computer v uh computer
vision natural language processing
robotics and human computer interaction.
In today's lecture he will discuss
multimodal foundation models and RJ the
floor is yours.
>> Thank you. Uh it's great to be back. The
first time I ever taught this course uh
here at Stanford, it was 2020 and we had
about 3 weeks where we had to take all
the material and move it online. Uh I'm
yeah I'm every year after that has been
much easier to teach. U it's great to be
back. So today we're going to talk about
uh multimodal foundation models. So a
lot of the lectures in this class so far
has really been focused on building
individual models for individual tasks.
So these uh usually follow a few steps
that you've seen over and over again in
lectures. You collect a data set,
usually a training set as well as a test
set. Then you train a very specialized
model for that purpose. So that could be
an image classification model or image
captioning model like the ones you've
seen in your assignments as well. And
then you finally sort of evaluate th
those models on your test set. Now
what's sort of been different uh in the
field so far uh in the last couple of
years is this sort of shift away from
these individual models into building
these more foundation models. Um and the
way to sort of think about foundation
models is that it really is trying to
pre-train models on a wide variety of
skills, a wide variety of different
tasks and then later on adapt those
things for individual tasks uh depending
on your needs. So for example, one very
common uh foundation model that you all
probably use in some form or the other
is GPT. And GPT was trained on a lot of
common crawl data from the internet. And
then you take that model that you get
and then you fine-tune it for different
purposes. So you fine-tune that model uh
for math problems or symbolic reasoning
or trivia questions. And all of these
are individual tasks that this model can
quickly adapt to. Now, what's nice about
foundation models is that it allows you
to sort of do that update step, that
adaptation to new tasks with very
minimal data. Meaning, you don't need to
collect a large amount of training data.
You can usually get away with very, very
little. Often times, you can even get
away with collecting no training data at
all. Um, and so when you think about
foundation models, there's many
different classes of foundation models
that you might care about. Uh, in
language, uh, you've got Elmo and BERT
that really started this entire
revolution. uh and then we now have GPT
and T5 and variants of these models. Uh
these are things we're not going to talk
about in this class since we're mostly
going to be talking about multimodal
models. What we will talk about is how
do you build these same kind of
foundation models for image
classification and we'll go into uh
examples like clip and cocoa today. Uh
we'll also talk about how do you combine
language models that that you might have
seen already in class with these sort of
vision foundation models to enable all
kinds of new models, multimodal
foundation models that can solve a wide
variety of tasks. And then of course we
can do a lot more than just sort of
solve tasks in language. Uh we'll talk
about how you can build models that can
output not just text but also uh masks
uh or images uh that it might you might
want to generate. And then finally,
we'll talk about this idea of chaining
where you take a bunch of foundation
models and then combine them to do all
kinds of new things together. Now, when
we talk about foundation models, there's
many different ways to classify them.
Uh, and it's hard because the definition
is often sort of um disagreed upon, but
what you typically will see in a
foundation model is that it's robust and
general uh to many different tasks. So,
you can apply that same model for all
different use cases, and I'll show you a
ton of use cases today. Um, also
something else that's common in a lot of
these foundation models is that they
have a lot of parameters. They have
large numbers amounts of parameters,
large amounts of training data, and
usually they're trained with some sort
of self-supervised objective. Okay. Um,
so of course we're not going to talk
about the language stuff. What we will
talk about are the ones in green today.
And so let's get started with image
classification. So how do we actually go
about building an foundation model that
can solve image classification for any
sort of data set you might care about?
Now, if you remember from a few lectures
ago, we were talking about
self-supervised learning. And in
self-supervised learning, one of those
uh methods that you saw was simple,
where you have this contrastive
objective that contrasts against um
dissimilar images and pulls closer
representations of the same image that
has been transformed in some way or the
other. Now, this idea you can think of
as pulling together similar concepts.
different augmentations of a cat should
result in representations that are
similar to one another, but it should
push away representations for other
kinds of categories like dogs for
example. Now, the the hope with training
with these self-supervised learning
objectives is that these representations
become general enough, right? So that
when you see something new, maybe a
sketch of a cat or a sketch of a dog, it
still embeds those in the space so that
it's easy to classify exactly what those
concepts are. Now moving on to
multimodal, we can take these same
ideas, the same objective and then start
thinking about what would happen if we
added text to that representation space.
So for example, if we could also embed a
representation of the text that says a
cute fluffy cat and have that be close
to the cat representations, that would
be great because now we can sort of
query things in both images as well as
text. uh and similarly we if we can also
embed uh the phrase my favorite dog is a
golden retriever and ideally that
representation would lie closer to
golden retrievers than other kinds of
dogs. So that's the general idea behind
sort of adapting the self-supervised
learning objectives we've been talking
about in class so far to incorporate
text and other sort of multimodal uh
inputs. So in simincere if you remember
the main objective was that you want to
pull together again uh transformations
of the same image. So the cat should be
closest to its other cat augmentation.
So that green arrow right there sort of
indicates two things that should be
pulled together and it should be further
away from all the other augmentations.
So any other image of a dog or a monkey
you want those representations to be far
away. Now we can use that same idea and
now think about training a clip model.
In clip what they do is they still have
that same image encoder that you have on
the left hand side but on the right hand
side you now have a text encoder and
this text encoder is embedding
descriptions of those individual images.
Okay. So your dog image will now
hopefully learn that it should be closer
to a representation of a text that says
my favorite dog is a golden retriever
and far away from all the other
representations. Okay. And because this
is the same formulation that you've seen
with Sinclair, the objective that you
use to train a model like this is just
by collecting a lot of image text pairs.
Uh and then once you have those pairs,
feed them into a model in a mini batch
and then make sure that you have this
contrastive objective uh that we used
for SIM clear, but now we're applying
them across images and text. So we're
pulling together here in the numerator
uh the representations uh of similar
things and pulling apart the
representations in the denominator for
everything else. Now, of course, we want
that image to be closest to its
corresponding text and far away from all
the other text. But we also want the
inverse to be true as well. So, we have
a second objective as well that says
every text should be closest to its
image and further away from all the
other image descriptions. Right? So,
it's it's a complimentary symmetric loss
that you have between the two different
types of modalities that you're feeding
into this uh learning objective.
Okay? So, of course, what's really nice
about a clip-like model is that it can
be trained with just associations of
images and text. And there's a ton of
this data on the internet. So, you have
a lot of data of corresponding images
and text that you can pull up from the
internet. You can download and now you
can train this model at a very very
large scale. And this is exactly what
OpenAI did a couple of years ago in 2021
when they released their clip model. So
they collected a lot of that data and
then they trained it using this
contrastive objective using all of the
images and text pairs that they found
from the internet and then once they
were done training that you follow the
same sort of two-step pipeline that you
saw in the self-supervised learning
object uh class where in step one you do
that pre-training and then in step two
you can take that image encoder and now
you can adapt it to a new task. So once
you have this pre-trained image encoder,
you take it, you take its weights and
then you tag on an additional linear
layer on top uh to adapt it to an image
classification task or a detection task
or you can put in something like a
decoder and even decode out uh semantic
segmentation maps. Right? So a ton of
different tasks become possible just by
initializing your model from this sort
of pre-trained objective. What was
really exciting when this paper came out
is that linear uh addition of this one
linear classifier on top of this clip
encoder led to really large improvements
in performance. So here in this graph
I'm showing you uh average performance
across many different image
classification data sets and the clip
models the ones in red they're all the
way at the top and you can see that as
you sort of train on more and more
images uh you end up getting better and
better performance. Um, so it was very
exciting because it seemed to indicate
that there's this really nice
pre-training objective that we've been
able to unlock and there's an abundance
of image text data on the internet which
means that we can train these to be very
very large and very very performant. Um,
of course that's not the end of the
story. What we want to do ideally is not
to have to adapt these features for
something new. We would ideally want to
be able to use a clip model out of the
box. So in language models for example,
you train a model to autocomplete
usually. And this autocomp completion
kind of works like this. You have a
phrase that says I love and then your
model sort of fills in the next word.
For example, cake. And then you train
with this pre-training objective. And
what you want to do during the second
stage is to basically take that same
model and adapt it to a new task. For
language models, you never have to
retrain that model. You never have to
retrain it on a new downstream task.
Every task is a language task. And so
every task can be treated as this sort
of autocomplete uh process. But with
clip the problem is there is no
autocomplete process. Right? So we've
trained this model on this contrastive
objective. But to adapt it to a new
task, we still need training data and we
still need uh a linear layer on top that
we need to train to adapt it to new
tasks. So a lot of people started
thinking about what what we can do to
sort of adapt this uh model for uh you
know to use it directly out of the box
and there's this clever trick that
people came up with and this clever
trick is basically using the text
encoder as a way of guiding the model uh
to generalize to any downstream
classifiification task. And it works
like this. Uh so let's say you want to
classify what this image is using a clip
model but you don't want to sort of
retrain this model or adapt it for any
downstream task. What you can do is you
can take the text encoder and pass in a
word through that text encoder to create
a text vector and use nearest neighbors
to figure out what is the right
classification. So the way this works is
you take all the categories in your new
data set. So for example, let's say your
new data set contains the categories
plane, dog, and bird. You're going to
embed all of them in the text space to
get a vector for plane, a vector for
dog, and a vector for bird. And now when
a new image comes in, all you have to do
is embed that image using the image
encoder and then find the closest
neighbor. So in this case, you should
find that this image has the highest
sort of similarity with uh the correct
class. uh in this case uh it should be
the dog vector and you can see the dog
vector does have the highest sort of
similarity score and so because of that
you can now classify that image as a
dog. Okay.
Now you can think of this entire process
as essentially building a one nearest
neighbor algorithm. Right? So you're you
have a bunch of centers that you've or
embeddings that you've generated in the
text space and now you can use them as
your class category labels and you're
doing one nearest neighbor to find uh
the optimal classification for any new
image that comes in.
Now of course a uh single word might not
be sufficient to get a really good word
vector. Um instead what you might want
to do is a use a phrase. And the reason
you might want to do this is because a
lot of the internet data it it usually
doesn't have words that occur by
themselves. Clip was trained from just
phrases that that were downloaded from
the internet. And so ideally you want to
pick the right phrase that gives you the
best uh representation. So instead of
just having the categories plane, dog,
and bird, you might instead want to
embed a vector that represents a photo
of a plane, a photo of a dog. And turns
out if you do this one small change, uh,
you suddenly get a large boost on
imageet where you see an improvement of
about 1.3%.
Of course, picking that right phrase is
also something that's very difficult to
do. And so what people typically do is
they don't just pick a single phrase.
They pick many different phrases. Uh, so
a photo of a dog, a drawing of a dog, or
a bunch of different ideas for different
phrases. And you want to create a many
many different vectors for all of those
different phrases you might think of.
And at the end, what you do is you just
take the mean vector representation
across all of your phrases for each
category and use that as your mean dog
vector, your mean uh plane vector, and
your mean bird vector. Right? And then
now you're back to where you started and
you can do your same sort of one nearest
neighbor uh algorithm on this. It
probably has been trained on imageet.
This is I think uh a point to show that
you can adapt it to a new task. But I
will show you other examples of data
sets where it's definitely not been
trained on and it does sort of adapt to
that as well. So you get a single vector
out. Uh it depends on the architecture
you're using. If you're using ResNet,
you take the final vector
representation. Uh if your text encoder
is let's say a VIT or a transformer,
then you usually take the CLS token uh
of your transformer.
Okay. Um so that's sort of it for clip.
you could basically adapt this for a
wide variety of new image uh
classification tasks and to your
question right now uh of course it's not
that big a deal uh that it performs just
as well on imageet uh but it is still
exciting that it does do well on imageet
at all uh what's I think more
interesting is that when you look at
other data sets data sets that were
collected after clip came out so a data
set like object net which contains
objects that people took photos of in
very weird sort of places so they put a
banana on the ground and took a photo of
it or they took a banana that was like
really rotten and took a photo of it. Uh
so things that are just not common. Uh
and so in this data set uh if you train
on imageet you don't do very well. Uh
because imageet again contains most of
these categories in its most typical
form. Uh but if you take the clip model
it performs just as well. uh and that
was really really exciting for many
people because this ability to
generalize to a completely new data set
that it hasn't seen before that's even
out of domain to some degree uh was
really great. So why do you think this
is why do you think clip generaliz is a
lot better than training on imageet to
paraphrase your response because I think
it's the right response um is you know
the text that you download from the
internet it contains a lot more than the
category labels it contains a lot more
structural information contains
information about shape about uh the
colors of things and all of that adds uh
to the representations and so these
models are able to adapt a lot better to
something that maybe is slightly out of
distribution or an object that looks
slightly different because it does have
all of these other things it's looking
for as well. Uh and so those that
additional supervision really helps
quite a lot. Uh the other reason it
helps quite a lot is the scale of data.
Imageet is only about 1.3 million images
or so whereas the internet contains
millions and billions at at this point
billions of image text pairs that we can
download very easily. And so these
models have just seen so much more data
uh that this adaptation becomes a lot
easier. Um and so people started doing
these experiments on a wide variety of
uh generalization tasks. So they showed
that you can generalize these models for
uh not just natural images but also
sketches that you can also do this on
adversarial data sets as well. And
performance across the board seem to
indicate that these models are just
really really good and robust to many
different applications. Um and then here
I'm showing you the difference between
zeroot and linear probe. And you can see
that of course linear probe when you add
that additional linear classifier and
train it and adapt it a little bit it
does improve performance in majority of
uh the data sets the ones in green and
but it's not always the case. In some
cases the clip zero shot just performs
really well out of the box. Um and so it
just seemed to indicate that we finally
unlocked this capability of being able
to adapt um image encoders for a wide
variety of different downstream tasks.
And this is why I think a lot of people
talk about clip as the first sort of
foundation model uh for images. So let's
talk about what makes clip work so well.
Uh of course there's no real labels as
such with clip. We're just downloading
any sort of text associated with images.
What makes clip work so well is what I
was saying it contained when it was
first trained it was trained on about uh
somewhere between um well the parameters
were just gigantic. they sort of scaled
up the model and they changed the
architecture from ResNet to a VIT and so
you had this transformer architecture
with 307 million parameters uh that was
used to train this model and the second
thing that helped was the amount of data
right so instead of just 1.2 2 million
images from imageet you suddenly had
about 400 million image text pairs from
the internet that they downloaded and
used that to train. So that addition
that scale both in terms of model size
as well as the amount of data helped
improve performance quite a lot. So
immediately after clip came out uh
people started experimenting with this
objective and there's many different var
variants of uh clip that have come out
over the years but one in particular
that's really stood out came out in
2022. It's called Koka. And Koka took
the clip model. Here you can see it's
the same sort of objective here. You've
got the image being encoded on one side.
You've got the text being encoded on one
side. And then you have that contrastive
loss between the two. But they added one
additional thing. They added a decoder
as well that took the image features
from the image encoder and then they fed
it in as through cost attention and
caption that image. And turns out this
captioning process also helps the model
learn quite a lot of rich information.
So the general motivation here is that
it's it's not sufficient to just be able
to say that this is an image of a cat
versus a dog, but to describe that image
in text requires a lot more information
to be learned by the model. And so it's
a the hypothesis is that it's a stronger
learning objective. And so because of
that, it learns better features. And we
found that to be true overall. Koka when
you compare Koka to clip its performance
improves quite a lot across all the
different image net variants uh and
overall there's like a 10% boost in
performance across all of the data sets
and I think this was the first time
where these sort of foundation models
actually beat all the models that we had
trained from supervised learning. So at
this point we had many different models
that people are putting out onto online
leaderboards uh and in those
leaderboards across the years um you can
see the trend sort of going upwards as
models are performing better and better
and this is I think the turning point
where people abandoned um supervised
learning objectives for image encoders
and instead focus solely on just
pre-training objectives using these sort
of self-supervised learning methods from
the internet data. Okay, so let's talk
about some advantages of clip. Eclipse's
got a lot of really fun things that you
can do with it. Uh it's super easy to
train, right? Cuz it's just a simple uh
contrastive learning objective. It's
also really fast in terms of inference.
Um you can embed your entire data set
into uh some representation and then all
you have to do to classify is just do
retrieval on that uh sort of embedded
data set. So you can retrieve things
very easily with clips representations
which makes it really useful for not
just classification tasks but also
search and retrieval tasks as well.
Another thing that people really liked
about clip is that it's open vocabulary.
You can feed in any text description and
it should be able to retrieve the right
images for you. And so that also allows
for its applicability across many
different domains. Um and of course
we're going to talk about this later.
clip is really amendable to being um
sort of chained with other models and
this idea of chaining started becoming
really popular but hold off on that.
We'll talk about that in uh a few
minutes. Um of course I'm telling you
all the good things. Turns out there's a
lot of bad as well. Uh clip
unfortunately can distinguish between
these two images. So you have an image
of a mug in grass and you have some
grass in some mug and clip just does not
know the difference between these two
things. Okay. Um, the reason it doesn't
know is because the clip's learning
objective really depends on its batch
size. If your batch size is not large
enough, then all of the other batch
elements are unlikely to provide any
useful supervisation uh for the model.
If you're always comparing a cat versus
a truck, you're not really going to
learn a representation for a cat. Um,
instead, what you get is some sort of
representation that's kind of okay at
some high level. Uh but if you increase
the batch size, you're more likely to
encounter other animals that are similar
to the cat. And then you learn a much
better representation. And then of
course if you increase your batch size
to let's say 32,000 uh and you train it
across many many GPUs, then suddenly you
start learning really good
representations. You can actually start
identifying a Welsh corgi versus another
corgi. And this only is possible when
you have gigantic batch sizes because it
requires you to have other negative
examples in your batch that are close
enough that are sort of hard negatives
that forces the model to have to learn.
Right? So that's very important for
getting these models to work well. Um
but unfortunately regardless of how much
people have tried, increasing this batch
size doesn't guarantee that the model
will learn a good representation for
things. And so you're sort of at the
mercy of the randomness of your training
data. Um, so increasing the batch size
does help with some amount of fine grain
concepts, but of course it's still
limited and training on 32,000 amounts
of batch size is just too large for most
labs to even consider doing. Um, people
have identified this error across many
different benchmarks uh and sort of
identified that clip just doesn't have
this notion of comp compositionality. So
this idea that uh the mug and the grass
versus grass in the mug, it's really
about composing different concepts like
the mug and the grass and the the sort
of relationship in all of those
individual components are not composed
well in your clip uh representations.
And there's been a ton of different
benchmarks like winterground or crepe or
arro and a lot of these benchmarks have
actually come from my lab. um they just
keep finding over and over again that
clip has a ton of limitations and
there's a ton of things that they are
just unable to do. Now of course in
reaction the community immediately
started thinking about how do I
handcraft my batch so that it contains
the hard negatives you know so if I have
one type of corgi that I should
hopefully have another type of corgi in
there so your model really is forced to
learn good representations uh and so
this idea of training with hard
negatives became really popular in the
community for a whole one year until we
released a follow-up paper that said
that if you train with hard negatives
you end up actually unlearning a a lot
of things about semantics. Uh for
whatever reason, and this is something
that we still don't theoretically
understand, we end up actually with much
worse performance in generalization
across different sort of uh environments
and different kind of data sets. So
there's a lot of work to be done still
in ter trying terms of figuring out the
right way of constructing your data set,
the right way of constructing your
batches and training signal. Uh so we're
still really far away from that but
regardless people are still very excited
about clip in general uh because it does
give you some amount of uh supervision
regardless.
Of course again image level uh captions
are again not enough. Um ideally what we
want is more than just that right we
want to be able to identify not just
that there's a person crossing the
street but that the person is in this
location the car is here the street is
here. All of that information, that
grounding information is completely
missing in clip. And so ideally, you'd
want also your data set to contain this
kind of information and your model to
also be able to reason about that kind
of information. Also, uh the final thing
that's a big disadvantage for clip is
that regardless of how big your data set
is, even if you collect upwards of let's
say 5 billion images, it's still not
going to be enough to capture all the
important things that you might care
about. uh and so there's been a lot of
efforts that we've been doing in data
filtering. So how do you filter the
internet to find the best training data
for training these clip models? I won't
go into that today. Uh but there are all
of these sort of mechanisms that people
are exploring. Uh that's now become the
frontier of what today's research looks
like in this field. Okay. So that's the
first branch of foundation models we
talked about. It's about sort of
generalizing classification to a whole
host of tasks. Now let's talk about
vision and language models. So there's a
new class of foundation models uh which
has become popular in the last 2 two and
a half years and we often refer to them
as multimodal language models. Uh and
I'll start off with this discussion by
focusing on lava which is arguably one
of the first sort of multimodal language
models that became very very popular.
The motivation here is that language
models which do this next token
prediction uh this autocomplete process
that process is really useful for
adapting to a lot of new tasks and so
can we start thinking about even image
models as well doing the same thing. Can
we given an image also start doing
different kinds of reasoning uh that's
similar to this auto uh regressive
process and that gave rise to this class
of models called visual language models
or multimodal models. Uh but of course
this just to be historically correct
this idea wasn't completely new uh in
2022. Uh in 2019 Vilbert actually
introduced this idea. Uh there's a paper
called Vilbert in 2019 that took these
image models and language models and put
them all together uh to accomplish a
generaliz generalization across
different tasks. Uh but they were all
trained uh pre-transformers and also
mostly use LSTMs instead. And so the
rebirth of all of this is what's
happening right now with uh Lava where a
lot of these models switched over to a
better architecture, switched over to a
better set of objectives, and now aren't
just training on individual tasks, but
are training on a foundation of a
variety of different tasks using some
sort of pre-training objective from the
internet. So how does this work? How do
how do you sort of think about Lava? So
to sort of talk about lava, let's take a
step back and think about uh the
transformer model or self attention in
particular. So when we think about
language models, what they're doing is
they're attending over the past. So you
have a sequence of words that are coming
in. So for example, cats are so and then
your model to generate the next word
will attend over that historical context
and then generate what it thinks the
next word should be. So it might think
that the the phrase should be cats are
so cute. Um, and here's another way of
sort of representing that same sort of
objective. You've got the input text
coming in at the bottom and your model
will generate the next word which is
cute. So when we think about vision
language models, what people usually are
referring to is adding in additional
context by grounding that conversation
that we're having with some image that
we care about. So we might care about
tokenizing our image somehow and feeding
those tokens into our language model
along with the historical context of
cats are so and then using that to
autocomplete uh the rest of the
description. So that's the basic idea
behind llama uh is sort of feed in these
image tokens along with the words that
are being generated to continuously
generate more words about that image. So
of course a question comes in which is
how do you define these tokens? what
should these tokens be in the first
place? And Lava their solution was to
use the clip image encoder. So they took
the clip model, they took the image
encoder and then they basically
extracted tokens from that encoder. So
the first thing you might think about
doing is just using the CLS token. So
here you've got uh let me see if my
mouse works here. Oh, it does. Okay. So
you've got the image coming in over here
and then they're getting patched. Each
patch turns into a representation that's
fed into your transformer architecture
in clip. It goes through a bunch of
layers of processing. And then at the
end, you get a bunch of different tokens
for each of the patches along with a
representation for the CLS token. And so
far, we've only been considering the CLS
token. We've only been doing things with
the CLS token for doing any sort of
classification task, but there are all
of these other tokens in there as well.
Now, the problem with these other tokens
is that they're never supervised, right?
Right? So the CLS token is supervised
with this contrastive objective with
text. But the other tokens are never
used for any purpose. So they might not
actually contain any useful information.
And empirically people have shown that
these features are not very useful. But
what they have shown is that if you go
one more layer back, the pen ultimate
layer in your clip encoder, these
features are actually very useful. Uh so
these features are used to generate the
final clip embedding uh in the final
layer and they contain a lot of spatial
information about where objects are uh
in your entire image. And so this is
what people typically use when combining
uh clip encoder with uh with a sort of
uh transformer sort of LLM based model.
Okay. So this is what the entire lava
architecture looks like. You feed an
image through uh your clip pre-trained
clip encoder. You extract a bunch of
features from it. You take those
features and you pass it through a
linear layer that you need to train. And
what this linear layer will train to do
is convert your clip representations
into something that the LLM can
understand and make sense of. Okay. And
once you have these tokens, you now
basically pass in all of your tokens to
your uh language model and it can now
generate some uh conversations about
that image itself.
So Lava was one of the very first sort
of popular models that were out there.
And following up, Google quickly
released Flamingo. Uh and in Flamingo,
it followed very much the entire Lava
setup of being able to combine uh a
vision encoder features with a large
language model. But the the place where
they innovated is how do you do that
fusing of these different features. So
in lava you had the features coming in
um through a linear layer and fed in as
part of the input. In Flamingo what they
did instead was they basically took all
the features coming out of your vision
encoder and fed them into every layer of
your LLM. Okay? So they had to make some
they had to make some changes to the LLM
architecture itself. And this is how
they made those changes. So, here's an
example of what Flamingo's training data
looks like. You've got images that are
encoded. So, you you've got this dog and
you've got this cat. They both get
embedded and they're both going to be
fed into every single layer of your LLM.
And down here, you've got a data that's
sort of describing every single starts
uh with the image and describes that
image, then the next image, describes
the next image, and so on and so forth.
And they're sort of fed in as input to
your LLM. And your output is going to be
to autocomplete that last uh image.
Okay, so you got one image followed by a
description of the dog second image and
you start the description and your model
will be trained on autocompleting that
description for that second image. So
what did they do? What did they change
to the model itself? They added this
sort of gated X cross attention module
to every single layer of your LLM. And
they made one other change. They also
added this perceiver sampler right here
uh that basically samples and
downsamples your image representations.
So there's smaller dimensions and a
fixed number of tokens uh for every
single layer. So let me go into some
details with what they look like. Um so
this is the full architecture overall.
Most of the components are frozen. All
the language model weights are frozen.
All the vision model parts are frozen.
The only parts that are trained are
these perceiver sampler components and
this cross attention layer that's sort
of added into every single uh layer of
your LLM. So let's talk about what this
cross attention module looks like. Uh
this is me zooming into that cross
attention module. So every single LLM
layer right before the LLM layer you
have this cross attention component and
what its purpose is is to look at the
image features and then decide what
parts of the image features it wants to
keep around and what it thinks to be
useful for the language model to know
about and they designed it as a set of
uh components that you've already seen
so far. Uh so you attend over the image
features using a cross attention layer
and then following that cross attention
they added this 10H nonlinear activation
and this is basically deciding what
parts of these components do I want to
keep around which ones uh which parts of
the image do I want to forget uh and
then it goes through this fully
connected layer where it adapts those
representations a little bit and then
again a tanh nonlinearity to decide
again which parts it should keep and
which parts it shouldn't. Once it goes
through those two components and each
one has a residual connection across
from it, uh it then goes to your normal
language model processing and then
continues to generate the word it needs
to. Okay, so this additional layers are
being added just as a way for the
language to sort of incorporate and
attend over the vision features at every
single layer. Okay, so the actual
modification itself, if you're
interested in what this looks like in
code, is just uh about two or three
lines of code where uh they added this
cross attention layer and then this tanh
nonlinearity in between. And that's
really about it. So in terms of code,
it's a very minimal change. Although for
the model, it's a very gigantic change
because now it can sort of choose what
parts of the image to attend to at every
single layer of its processing. So you
give the model a lot of uh ability to
decide when and how to attend over the
vision features.
Okay. So flamingo was very very
exciting. Uh but training it was very
difficult. Um and they had this really
ingenious way of training it that
allowed our models to adapt to many
different tasks. The way they trained it
was through this concatenation of a
bunch of different images together. So
you didn't just have one image and one
description. You had a description at
the beginning that says here some cute
pictures of my pets, end of sentence,
beginning of image, and then a
description of that first image, end of
uh that first component, and then the
second image, and a description of the
second image. Okay, so you had the
training set up so that it looks like a
long sequence of image text, image text,
interled data. And of course when
describing any single image, you don't
want the model to look at the entire
context. You want it to only look at
that one particular image. And so they
created a masking scheme where every
single image when when generating only
looks at that particular image features
and not the other ones. Uh meaning that
when you're generating the description
for my puppy is sitting in the grass,
you're only looking at the features uh
that correspond to the puppy only when
generating those words. Similarly, when
generating the the description for the
cat, you're only looking at the cat
image and not the other image. So, there
is this sort of distinction where they
created this handcraft and masking
scheme uh to make sure your descriptions
are always following and looking at only
that particular image. Uh but when
trained, the model does get to see the
entire context of everything that it's
generating.
So, why is that helpful? Why is this
entire process helpful of being able to
see all of this stuff together? Well,
it's helpful because it allows you to do
these kinds of applications. So, here is
three different applications that
Flamingo was able to showcase. The and
they all center around having multiple
conversations or dealing with multiple
images. So, in the first case, you've
got an image that's fed in uh and the
flamingo model describes the image by
saying that this is a picture of two
teddy bears on the moon. And then what
it allows people to do is then ask
another question. So people can ask what
are they doing? And because it's already
being uh it's training using an existing
large language model, that large
language model's reasoning capabilities
are inherited. And now it can reason and
answer this particular question. It it
can now answer and say there the teddy
bears are having a conversation. And
then a user might ask what objects are
they using? And again, Flamingo can say
that it looks like it's a computer and
so on and so forth. So you can enable
this multi-turn dialogue about an image
simply by doing two things. You train by
first pre-training the language model
and then incorporating that language
model into Flamingo and secondly
allowing your model to see many
different images and many different
turns uh throughout its training data so
it can adapt to longer sequences of
text. You can also give it multiple
images and ask what is a common thing
about these images. And now the flamingo
model will look at each of those
different components and sort of reason
and say that they're all flamingos. Uh
so you can start doing a lot of these
kinds of really cool applications.
People also showed that you can start
doing in context learning. I don't know
if this is something you've seen already
with uh language models, but I'm sure
you've used in context learning with GPT
where you tell GPT here's an example of
what I want. Give me more things like
this. Uh, and you can do the same thing
with Flamingo where you can pass in an
image and a description, an image and a
description, and now when you pass in a
new image, it'll give you a description.
Or you can say, uh, uh, here's some
image, here's a question and answer.
Here's an image, question and answer.
And then when you pass in a new image
and just ask the question, it'll give
you the answer. Right? So you're not
training it to do these different kinds
of tasks, but you're providing it with
examples of behaviors that it should
have and it should just generalize to
new kinds of behaviors uh that you might
care about. Similarly, you might care
about just classification and you can
use flamingo to do classification as
well. So you can give it an image and
say this is underground, this is
congress and then you can ask what is
this right? Um, and you can also even
teach it to do OCR and math where you
give it an image and say, "Oh, this
should correspond to 2 + 1= 3." And so
eventually when you give it a new image,
it should be able to autocomplete and
extract out 3 * 6 and then also give you
the output by reasoning through this
entire process. Yeah. So this would be
an example of fshot learning where you
give it some examples, a few examples of
things and then you ask it uh what the
new thing should be. uh if I were to
throw away all the incontext examples,
that would be zero shot learning. So,
we're not concatenating them. Um we're
technically passing the image tokens
through this perceiver sampler into
every single layer of your LLM instead.
And so, only the text is ever
concatenated and fed as input to your
flamingo model. And it chooses when to
attend to which parts of the image. You
give it to it once. H but behind the
scenes, uh of course, this is the
interface, right? the web interface but
behind the scenes what they actually do
is they cache the model assuming that
the user will want to continue talking
and so the model is cached and ready to
accept more tokens. Yeah. But if they
did not cache it then yes it would pass
in this entire conversation as uh as
input. Yeah.
Okay. So Flamingo was super cool because
uh they have these really big tables in
their paper that you can go check out.
Um, but what was really cool about it is
there were all of these tasks that were
very difficult and you had to adapt clip
to do them. Uh, but Flamingo was just
able to do it with zero shot or few
shot. Uh, and you started seeing these
gigantic improvements across many
different benchmarks. Uh, and this is
when I think the field shifted from
reporting on a few classification
benchmarks to reporting on any sort of
understanding task at all. As long as
you can frame it as a question answering
process, you can build uh benchmarks for
a wide variety of skills and we started
seeing that become the norm in the last
2 years in the computer vision field.
Okay. So this is where uh we were I
think sometime last year and seeing the
success of Lava a lot of companies
started investing quite heavily on these
models and so you started seeing a lot
of API models like GPT uh 40 GPT 4V uh
Gemini 1.5 Pro Gemini 1.5 Flash a lot of
these models started become being
released and even Anthropic came into
the picture with Claude 3 Opus and now
of course Claude 4 Opus is out Um, and
so you had a lot of these models come
out and they were performing a lot
better on a bunch of these benchmarks.
So here I'm showing you the average
performance across 11 of the more
popular visual understanding benchmarks
in the field and there's this gigantic
difference, right? So the difference
between Lava, the model we talked about
that's open source, that's down here at
about 43% accuracy on average.
Meanwhile, GPT and all of these other
models are performing much much better
at about somewhere like um 80s or
high7s, right? So, big difference in
performance between these two different
kinds of models. Um, of course,
immediately seeing this sort of
difference, people started distilling
GPT and Gemini into uh distilled
variants and trying to release those
models. Uh so, Alibaba, which is a
company in China, they released this
model called Quinn. uh and then there's
intern there's fi there's all of these
different models that started coming out
and all of them were distilled from GPT
uh and if not GPT then Gemini now there
that led to a big problem in the field
uh a problem that's become a big part of
what my own research agenda has been
trying to sort of focus on which is we
don't actually know as a research
community how to build really performant
vision language models the the tricks
behind how to build them they only the
people in open AI I and Gemini in
Google, those teams know how to build
these kinds of models. But the open
source community, they're down here.
They're down here. This is where the
research community was as of last year.
U of course you can argue these are
really nice open models, but they're not
really open because they're distilled.
We don't actually know how to reproduce
these models, right? We we can only
produce them but if GPT exists, but if
GPT doesn't exist, we don't know how to
create these other models. And so what
my own research agenda has been focused
on over the last couple of years is
figuring out how do you close this gap?
How do you build really good uh
multimodal language models and
disseminate that sort of uh
understanding to the entire community?
And so um what we've done over the last
uh 6 months or about a year now is we've
created our own sort of uh class of
models that we called Momo. And I'm
showing you Momo's performance up at the
top. Uh, and what sort of sets Momo
apart from all the other models out
there is that it's completely open
source, meaning it's open weights, so
you can download the model. It's open
data, meaning you can download the
training set as well as the evaluation
set. It's also open code, meaning you
can basically train your own Momo in
your own home, assuming you have enough
GPUs. And uh you can also evaluate add
on new evaluations adapt this model for
all kinds of new things and of course
start using it for a wide variety of
different contexts. Um now of course
academic benchmarks are not enough right
because what we care about at the end of
the day is are people going to use these
models? Will people want to use these
models over GPT? And so to make sure we
had that evaluation properly done, we
released a playground with a Momo and we
did a gigantic user study where we
actually compared head-to-head outputs
from our models versus outputs from all
the other models. And our model has the
same ELO rating as GPT. It comes in
second with uh a difference of one in
ELO rating versus GPT 40. This is that
same graph rotated uh so that I can show
you some examples. Our this was a
gigantic evaluation by the way. This was
about 870 users that we uh showed these
model outputs to and we did about
325,000 pair wise comparisons. We asked
people which models output do you
prefer. Our model, the MLM model ranked
uh again like I said second uh more or
less a coin flip between what people
prefer between GPT and our model. Uh but
it already beat out Gemini 1.5 Pro and
Cloud 3.5. Now the big difference is we
are a small research lab and uh we're
beating out Google's billions of dollars
of investment into Gemini as well as
Entropics billions of dollars of
investment and already matching GPT. And
so we were quite excited by this entire
process. Uh but we also developed a 7
billion model that comes in right after
those big models. And that 7 billion
model is really uh exciting because you
can put it on a single GPU. So you can
now have this model capable of doing a
wide variety of vision tasks that works
on a single GPU, meaning a lot of people
can now use it and fine-tune it for all
kinds of things. We released this model
in September 25 and the community was
very excited by it. Uh there's, you
know, this is the first time a very
performant uh multimodal vision language
model was released and a ton of people
started um talking and writing articles
about all the ways they want to use it.
One of the use cases that kept popping
up over and over again was this idea of
using Malmo finally for robotics
applications. And I I won't talk about
robotics today because you're going to
learn about it in the next class. Um but
I do want to give you some examples of
things that people were excited about
with robotics. Um but a ton of people
even like uh folks uh at NVIDIA started
chatting about how this is, you know,
you should never bet against open source
regardless of how much model development
you do in private. eventually the open
source community will catch up and we
were catching up at that point. Um, and
so seeing our model out, Meta quickly
released in response their Llama uh 3.2
model and a lot of people did
evaluations comparing Momo versus uh
Meta's Lama model and again I'm very
happy that we came up on top of Llama as
well. So let me show you why Momo does
so well. Momo was the sort of trick to
getting these models to work very well.
The trick was to ground its decision-m
in the pixels itself. So usually when
you give a model a question like count
how many boats there are, it'll give you
some number and often times it
hallucinates. But what sort of sets our
model apart is that it actually points
to all the things that it's counting. So
it generates points to all the boats and
then it outputs a final number. So its
decision-m is grounded in the pixels
itself. Uh, and this allowed us to
essentially train a model that unlike
Llama for Meta that was trained on about
6 billion image text pairs, our model
was trained on only 700,000 image text
pairs. The big difference was that we
handcurated the 700,000 image text
pairs. Uh, and that was the biggest sort
of difference between what we were able
to do versus what these models uh that
these companies were building were
doing. So a lot of folks are trying to
currently download these uh image text
pairs from the internet, right? That's
been the foundation of how a lot of
people train these visual language
models. You collect a lot of internet
data uh of images with their associated
text. But the problem with internet data
is that it's incidental. The text that's
often associated with an image describes
something subjective or something that
the uploader felt about the image. It
rarely actually talks about the contents
of the image itself. And meanwhile, this
is what our data looks like, right? So a
for a single image, we have a dense
description of the actual contents of
that image. And we have things that
people never talk about on the internet.
There's a ton of task and knowledge
about the visual world that we just
never speak about. I will never tell you
that something is to the left of
something else just because it's
unnatural for us to do that. It's just
so obvious that something is to the left
of something. Why would you ever
communicate that information? So that's
the kind of information we started
eliciting from people. We started
talking about we started getting people
to talk about how things have particular
size like large or its shape like
rectangular. We talked about material
like polished and rich and uh its
positioning across the image like it
spans uh the horizontal sort of plane of
the image. So all of this information
really is what makes these models more
performant. Here's another example from
the data set. Uh here's a very simple
image of a phone screen or tablet screen
and we connect we have information here
that again is completely missing from
the internet. Uh things that people
would find helpful things like this is a
tablet device. The time is this. The
amount of power left in your device is
this. This is the kind of information
that would help people use these models.
But this is again the kind of
information we never talk about on the
internet. And so to get this kind of
information we designed a lot of
different questions. We spent two years
doing different kinds of elicitation
studies to figure out what are the right
things or pieces of information that are
missing from the internet and how do we
elicit them them as effectively as
possible. One thing that was very
important is we had all of our
annotators not type descriptions but
talk about descriptions. Talking
automatically breaks a lot of
stereotypes uh around grym maxims. Um,
and so we by getting people to talk, we
got them to speak about things that they
would never usually type. Um, the model
itself didn't look any different from
Lava. We had the same sort of setup of a
clip encoding coming in. You had a con
connector that was just a linear layer
and then you had a large language model
that would take in all of these tokens
and then output any sort of thing that
you care about. So the model itself
looked very similar to existing models.
The biggest difference was in the data
and the quality and density of the data
itself. Uh, and because of this sort of
grounding capability where the model
grounds its decision-m in the image
itself, you could get Momo to do things
that you can't do. You can't use any of
the other models to do. Things like
point to the menu. It actually tells you
where that menu item is. Or you can tell
it uh to sort of point to where I can
set my search options and it'll show
you, okay, this is where you might want
to set those options. Or point to where
the midsize data sets are, and it'll
tell you what option you need to move.
Um, and I already showed you that you
can point to count, but you can also
point to do really fine grain things
like being able to sort of ask what is
the route number on this bus. MoMA
doesn't just simply give you an answer.
It actually points to where in the
image, in this case, there is this area
right here that contains the bus number
and then returns the bus number to you.
Uh, you can ask it to reason about how
many cars on the left versus how many
cars are on the right. You can ask it to
reason over depth images or overhead
images or even really crowded scenes and
sports uh areas. What's also really
exciting and again we'll talk about this
in a few minutes is this idea of
chaining that keeps coming up all across
multimodal models today. The idea of
chaining Momo to other models. Uh what
you can do is chain the output of Momo
to become the input of another model
like SAM 2. And so you can tell Momo to
point to the Cricut bat. And now you
take that point, you feed it to a model
like SAM 2 which does segmentation. And
now you can do segmentation of that
Cricut bat across time. And so you can
start enabling all kinds of new
applications. Here's one that we played
around with in the office. Um, which
again you're going to hopefully learn
about in the next lecture with when uh
you hear about robotics. Uh but we asked
uh Momo to point to where the water
bottle is and then we moved the robot
using simple motion planners to that
water bottle. Next we ask it to go move
that water bottle to where the dirty
dishes are. It points to the dish uh to
the sorry sink and then moves a robot
there. And then we tell it to go point
to where the uh free space is in the
sink and put that bottle in that
location. So again you can sort of
combine all these capabilities together
now and chain them to even sort of
automate a lot of robotics applications.
Uh this has been a lot of focus in my
group now is sort of adapting a lot of
these vision language models and
enabling a lot of generalization in the
actual physical domain. Uh so the
question is around um would these models
be able to sort of point if you um were
always sort of changing the resolution
of the image to be a fixed resolution
right. Um well turns out that you can
actually adapt these models to be any
resolution nowadays. There are these uh
mechanisms like flex vit uh that has
introduced uh a way of allowing for any
variable size image input and you can
adapt them to sort of point in that new
space instead. Um so your model's
position embeddings basically change
depending on how big your image size is.
Uh and you're allow you your models you
typically tend to generalize well. So
that was sort of uh the conversation
around adding vision and multimodal
models together. In the last sort of 20
minutes that we have left, I want to
talk about generalizing these foundation
models to not just deal with image
classification and text but be able to
sort of generalize to any sort of output
space you might care about. Uh and one
of those models that's become really
popular in this space is this segment
anything model. The segment anything
model or SAM for short. uh what it tries
to do is it tries to build a
segmentation model that's a foundation
model for all kinds of segmentation
tasks. So really what they're trying to
do is allow anybody to sort of point to
things that they care about in the image
and then hopefully have that thing uh be
something that they the model can sort
of output a mask for. Uh so for example
um you want a model that generalizes
beyond just a fixed number of categories
to any sort of category you might care
about and you would ideally want these
outputs to be masks for any sort of
category that is of interest to the
user. Right? So those are the two goals
uh that we want to generalize to any
category a huge number of categories and
we ideally want to be able to very
specifically output something that the
user really cares about. So they're both
challenges. They're both challenges in
figuring out how do you collect a large
amount of data that spans a wide variety
of categories as well as how do you
design an architecture that really
pinpoints what the user really cares
about. Um now the re let's start with
the second question first. Um it's
really ambiguous when uh when we want a
mask for something. So imagine a
scenario where you have two cats in an
image and a user comes in and says hey I
want a segmentation for the cat. But
it's really not clear which cat they
want a segmentation for. Ideally, again,
if you had Momo's pointing capability,
you could actually point to which cat
you care about. And then depending on
the point, you could create the masks uh
that matter. Now, of course, these are
not very good masks. And ideally, you
want these masks to be very very good at
quality that can sort of support a wide
variety of downstream applications like
image editing or any kinds of other
things you might uh think of. So to
build this architecture that allows any
user to be able to specify exactly what
they care about, we needed to go beyond
uh just simply typing in text what you
care about. Right? So what the SAM
architecture has is two components uh or
three specifically. It's got the image
encoder which is again uh it could be a
clip encoder uh and it's got a prompt
encoder which is something special. This
prompt encoder really tries to encode
text or points or bounding boxes or any
way that a user might want to specify
what they care about. And then given
these two things, it passes it through
this really lightweight decoder that
outputs a mask. And the decoder looks
very similar to like the the
segmentation decoders that you've
already seen in this course. So overall,
this is what uh the model looks like.
Given an image, we encode that image
using an image encoder. uh and then you
have a bunch of different prompts that
are going through and um interacting
with these image encoding uh through a
decoder and you output a mask right so
this is the overall architecture design
now there's one big thing that is a
problem with segmentation so let's say a
user does point at this particular
location and says hey I want a
segmentation mask for this location now
the problem with that segmentation mask
is that it's still ambiguous even with a
point it's still not sufficient because
that point might be referring to the
entire um uh scissor. It might only be
looking and referring to the parts that
you can hold or it can be referring to
one of the parts that you can hold. So
this ambiguity is really difficult to
sort of resolve for and you don't want
to penalize the model for picking the
wrong one. So what the SAM architecture
does is instead of outputting one
segmentation mask, it actually outputs
three segmentation masks at different
levels of granularity and then it picks
the one that is the closest matching to
ground truth and then uses that to
calculate the loss and therefore not
penalizing the other ones. So the hope
is that overall over time this model
will learn to output all different kinds
of masks and then the user gets to
choose basically which one is the most
appropriate for their use cases. Okay.
Um, and if you put all of this together,
the only thing you need now is data. You
need a lot of data across many different
categories to really make this model
possible. Now, the problem with data is
that until this model came out in 2023,
this was about a year and a half, maybe
2 years ago. When this model came out, u
most of the segmentation data sets were
extremely small. And what this the
authors of this paper did is that they
grew the amount of segmentation data
sets that were out there, the amount of
images by about 6x and the number of
segmentation masks by about 400x. So
they significantly grew uh and collected
a lot of masks to make this model as
performant as possible. So again the
message is very similar to the message
we had with Flamingo, the message we had
with Momo. And the message is you need
really good highquality data uh to
really get these models to be as
performant as possible. And for a lot of
vision tasks, the data is completely
missing from the internet and you need
to go out and find and collect that data
uh to get these models to work very
well. Okay. And so to make this data
happen, they created this sort of in the
loop process where they initially had
some amount of data annotated. Uh from
that annotation, they created a training
data set. They trained a model and they
used that model to annotate more data
and then they iteratively refined that
model generated uh segments using users
and continued this process. So uh they
had this human in the loop model in the
loop process of proposing segments and
then fixing the segments using human
annotators. This is what an example
image looks like from their data set.
You have quite a lot of categories. Each
individual uh vegetable here is
annotated with its own mask. So they're
quite expensive to collect. Uh and they
did this across um a lot of images,
millions of images. Here's another
example where again all the single
umbrellas are annotated. Uh again here's
another one with underwater sea. Uh and
of course paintings as well. They have
segmentations of paintings. Uh and so
all of this together is really what was
foundational to making this foundation
model for segmentation. Okay. Um so
that's for segment anything. And I want
to use the last couple of uh minutes
that I have left today to really focus
on chaining, which is the last part of
multimodal language models. The idea
behind chaining is something you've
already seen. I've given you hints
already throughout this lecture. And the
idea is to be able to combine different
models together to enable things that a
single model can't do alone. Here's a
fun little exercise we can do as a
class. So, I'm giving you four images
and I'm also giving you four categories,
right? And these are potentially
categories that some of you have never
seen before. And they're also categories
that Clip hasn't seen. And so, Clip
actually fails at these categories cuz
it doesn't have any idea which one's
associated with what. Does anyone here
know which one is what? Morima. Yeah,
the second one is Mima. That's right.
Yeah. Uh, there's one that's a little
easy. The vioaduct,
right? Yeah. I think a lot of you know
which one that is. Um, but yeah, which
one's the the dog and which one's the
bird? Um, what if I gave you these
instead?
So now I'm giving you descriptions of
these things and it suddenly becomes
very easy for you to associate each one
with the right category, right? Uh and
that's the basic idea behind chaining
that even if clip has never seen these
images chances are these these concepts
have been talked about on the internet
to some degree and it's likely that GPT
might be able to describe it and if GPT
can create those descriptions now those
descriptions become really good ways of
classifying exactly which category is
which one and that's the idea behind
chaining is that you take the strengths
of one model and you combine it with the
capabilities of another and suddenly you
get all kinds of new capabilities that
you didn't have before. Uh and so you
can take a ton of categories that have
no training data uh in clip, but if you
can describe all of them because clip
has seen a lot of descriptions for
things, it can now start classifying all
of them very well. And you can start
getting Clip to generate classifications
for individual flowers or individual
cars or individual uh spaces or even
different kinds of pets. And you start
seeing these improvements on a bunch of
different data sets that are about more
fine grained specialized categories. And
the only way it's able to do that is
because GPT has ingested some ability to
sort of describe those things. Um, and
this idea of being able to generalize to
new capabilities is something that uh
was extremely popular last year and it
still remains very popular this year. uh
and it's through this idea of chaining
for any sort of question at all. uh so
for example if I asked you how many are
there three people in the boat um the
way you might want to do this is by
again asking a multimodal language model
to answer this question or what you
could do is use all of the hundreds of
specialized vision models that we've
been developing over the last few
decades. So there are object detection
models that you learned about in class.
If you use an object detector, you'd be
able to get a detection for each of the
three people and then you could just
say, "Oh, they're three people." Because
there are three detections, right? So
that's a general idea is you can chain
other models outputs together so that
you can do new kinds of capabilities.
Here's another example. Uh if I ask you
how many total people there are uh is
across these two boats, is it six? And
again, you can do the same thing. you
can write a program that does object
detection on image one and then object
detection on image two and then adds up
all of those components uh together.
Right? So this is the basic idea behind
um what we now call uh chaining and this
was popularized by a paper that won the
best paper award last year uh called
Visprog. And in this Visprock paper, the
visual programming paper, the idea was
that you take any image or any sort of
question and you generate a program. You
generate a program that says answer
something about image one, answer
something about image two and then
return combine those answers together to
give you the final answer. Right? So you
write a function in Python and then in
that Python function you have individual
calls to other models uh that we've
already seen in training. Right? So for
example in when asking this particular
question uh deciding if this statement
is true or not the left and right image
contains a total of six people and two
boats you can ask GPT to actually create
a program that tries to answer this
question and then you can take the
answer uh from its uh program. Okay. And
you can also get GPT to do in context
examples where you give it examples of
programs that it can generate using
other functions. And we can see that it
generalizes to new sort of questions and
you start using all of the functionality
that it has available. Of course, the
one thing you need to do is give it the
functions themselves. So you need to
tell it that hey you have these
capabilities from other models that you
can use. You can localize things using
an object detector. You can localize
faces using a face detector. uh and you
can have all of these different
capabilities uh across many different
sort of other models that people have
created and you can chain them together
to do different kinds of tasks. Yeah. So
there's two different ways of doing it.
One is a static way of doing it where
you want to give it as diverse examples
as possible and then hopes that it
generalizes. Another one is to
dynamically choose given this question
what are the best in context examples I
should use. And so you can treat that as
another retrieval process where you
retrieve the best examples and then you
ask it to generate a program and that
tends to perform a lot better but only
if you have a good retrieval system. Uh
yes it would require a lot of compute.
So you there's compute in terms of uh
calling GPT which you have to do through
an API and then you have to load each of
these individual models into your memory
and then run each of them sequentially.
So it could actually be a lot more
costly. And so what people are trying to
do is figure out can we distill these
capabilities into a single model. Uh and
that's a big part of what research looks
like today in 2025. Uh but of course uh
people are also still trying to figure
out how do you chain these things
effectively. Very well.
>> Yeah. You can think of it as like an
agent. Yeah. So you have an agent that's
basically deciding hey given this
question what are the other models I
need help from and how do I sort of
stitch them together to do new kinds of
capabilities? Uh so that's what it looks
like. Yeah. Uh here's another example
where you might want to do image
editing. You might care about replacing
the sand, the desert with lush green
grass. Uh of course, image uh editing
models are still in its infancy. And so
what you might want to do instead is
call a segmentation model, identify the
desert, and then only replace the desert
parts, those pixels with grass. And then
you can sort of composite them together
to make a new image. Okay, that's sort
of um all of the things I wanted to talk
about in terms of different
capabilities. Uh so you've got um here
some capabilities around how to think
about foundation models. Uh it really is
at the end of the day uh an ability to
sort of train a model for a single task
and then from that single sort of uh
task generalized to many different
downstream applications.
And we talked about in classification
how you can create these models by just
taking a lot of image text pairs from
the internet um training them together
to do different kinds of tasks. uh and
that allows you to generalize to new
kinds of data sets that might not even
exist in the real world or have any
labels for in the real world. Uh you can
also combine them with language models
and train them to do in context examples
uh like captioning or counting or OCR.
And these are again capabilities that
enable many different applications. And
then of course the outputs don't always
have to be language or categories. There
can also be segmentation masks uh where
you can take different kinds of masks uh
depending on different user uh inputs
and you can generalize this even further
by combining many of these foundation
models or even smaller models together
through programs and do all kinds of new
things. So hallucinations still happen
all all across the board. Um what we're
showing is that it seems like pointing
does sort of reduce hallucinations quite
a bit uh because it does need to find
some evidence for its generations. Uh
but that being said, there's no
guarantee that it's going to point to to
the right thing at all. Um so there's
many different ways of sort of fixing
for this. One is uh of course collecting
more data uh related to the kinds of
reasoning that you want it to do. Uh but
a better one is to even have
verification methods that verify based
on the points whether the output is
something you should trust or not. So a
lot of the bigger models and bigger
companies what they typically do uh when
you use any of their models is they
don't have a single model that's
generating an output. you usually take
that output and pass it through other
sort of verifiers before it even gets to
the user. Um and that mitigates some of
these sort of problems. Uh but it is an
active line of uh inquiry right now. How
do you sort of reduce hallucinations and
also improve these models actual
accuracy?
>> Yeah. So uh so repeating your question
um is it possible for these models to
build new tools when uh capability
requires a tool that it doesn't have? Uh
yes uh it can. uh we have a few sort of
uh preliminary experiments in those
directions as well where you can tell a
model here's a capability that I want
and what you can build is a system that
automatically tries to collect training
data and builds a tool for specific use
cases. Uh but that line of work is still
again in its infancy. Uh it's one that
we're actively working on. Uh but you
know a lot of folks are excited about
that direction.