if you extrapolate the curves that we've
had so far right if if you say well I
don't know we're starting to get to like
PhD level and and last year we were at
undergraduate level and the year before
we were at like the level of a high
school student again you can you can
quibble with at what tasks and for what
we're still missing modalities but those
are being added like computer use was
added like image generation has been
added if you just kind of like eyeball
the rate at which these capabilities are
increasing it does make you think that
we'll get there by 2026 or 2027 I think
there are still worlds where it doesn't
happen in in a 100 years those world the
number of those worlds is rapidly
decreasing we are rapidly running out of
truly convincing blockers truly
compelling reasons why this will not
happen in the next few years the scale
up is very quick like we we do this
today we make a model and then we deploy
thousands maybe tens of thousands of
instances of it I think by the time you
know certainly within two to three years
whether we have these super powerful AIS
or not ERS are going to get to the size
where you'll be able to deploy millions
of these I am optimistic about meaning I
worry about economics and the
concentration of power that's actually
what I worry about more the abuse of
power and AI increases the amount of
power in the world and if you
concentrate that power and abuse that
power it can do immeasurable damage yes
it's very frightening it's very it's
very
frightening the following is a
conversation with Dario amade CEO of
anthropic the company that created
Claude that is currently and often at
the top of most llm Benchmark leader
boards on top of that Dario and the
anthropic team have been outspoken
advocates for taking the topic of AI
safety very seriously and they have
continued to publish a lot of
fascinating AI research on this and
other topics I'm also joined afterwards
by two other brilliant people from
propic first Amanda ascal who is a
researcher working on alignment and
fine-tuning of Claude including the
design of claude's character and
personality a few folks told me she has
probably talked with Claude more than
any human at anthropic so she was
definitely a fascinating person to talk
to about prompt engineering and
practical advice on how to get the best
out of Claude after that chrisa stopped
by for chat he's one of the pioneers of
the field of mechanistic
interpretability which is an exciting
set of efforts that aims to reverse
engineer neural networks to figure out
what's going on inside inferring
behaviors from neural activation
patterns inside the network this is a
very promising approach for keeping
future super intelligent AI systems safe
for example by detecting from the
activations when the model is trying to
deceive the human it is talking
to this is Alex Freedman podcast to
support it please check out our sponsors
in the description and now dear friends
here's Dario
amade let's start with a big idea of
scaling laws and the scaling hypothesis
what is it what is its history and where
do we stand today so I can only describe
it as it you know as it relates to kind
of my own experience but I've been in
the AI field for about uh 10 years and
it was something I noticed very early on
so I first joined the AI world when I
was uh working at BYU with Andrew in in
late 2014 which is almost exactly 10
years ago now and the first thing we
worked on was speech recognition systems
and in those days I think deep learning
was a new thing it had made lots of
progress but everyone was always saying
we don't have the algorithms we need to
succeed you know we we we we're we're
not we're only matching a tiny tiny
fraction there's so much we need to kind
of discover algorithmically we haven't
found the picture of how to match the
human brain uh and when you know in some
ways was fortunate I was kind of you
know you can have almost beginner's luck
right I was like a a newcomer to the
field and you know I looked at the
neural net that we were using for speech
the recurrent neural networks and I said
I don't know what if you make them
bigger and give them more layers and
what if you scale up the data along with
this right I just saw these as as like
independent dials that you could turn
and I noticed that the model started to
do better and better as you gave them
more data as you as you made the models
larger as you trained them for longer um
and I I didn't measure things precisely
in those days but but along with with
colleagues we very much got the informal
sense that the more data and the more
compute and the more training you put
into these models the better they
perform and so initially my thinking was
hey maybe that is just true for speech
recognition systems right maybe maybe
that's just one particular quirk one
particular area I think it wasn't until
2017 when I first saw the results from
gpt1 that it clicked for me that
language is probably the area in which
we can do this we can get trillions of
words of language data we can train on
them and the models we were training in
those days were tiny you could train
them on one to eight gpus whereas you
know now we train jobs on tens of
thousands soon going to hundreds of
thousands of gpus and so when I when I
saw those two things together um and you
know there were a few people like ilaser
who who you've interviewed who had
somewhat similar reviews right he might
have been the first one although I think
a few people came to came to similar
views around the same time Right There
Was You Know Rich Sutton's bitter lesson
there was gur wrote about the scaling
hypothesis but I think somewhere between
2014 and 2017 was when it really clicked
for me when I really got conviction that
hey we're going to be able to do these
incredibly wide cognitive tasks if we
just if we just scale up the models and
at at every stage of scaling there are
always arguments and you know when I
first heard them honestly I thought
probably I'm the one who's wrong and you
know all these all these experts in the
field are right they know the situation
better better than I do right there's
you know the Chomsky argument about like
you can get syntactics but you can't get
semantics there's this idea oh you can
make a sentence make sense but you can't
make a paragraph makes sense the latest
one we have today is uh you know we're
going to run out of data or the data
isn't high quality enough or models
can't reason and and each time every
time we manage to we manage to either
find a way around or scaling just is the
way around um sometimes it's one
sometimes it's the other uh and and so
I'm now at this point I I I still think
you know it's it's it's always quite
uncertain we have nothing but inductive
inference to tell us that the next few
years are going to be like the next the
last 10 years but but I've seen I've
seen the movie enough times I've seen
the story happen for for enough times to
to really believe that probably the
scaling is going to continue and that
there's some magic to it that we haven't
really explained on a theoretical basis
yet and of course the scaling here is
bigger networks bigger data bigger
compute yes all in in particular linear
scaling up of bigger networks bigger
training times and uh more and and more
data uh so all of these things almost
like a chemical reaction you know you
have three ingredients in the chemical
reaction and you need to linearly scale
up the three ingredients if you scale up
one not the others you run out of the
other reagents and and the reaction
stops but if you scale up everything
everything in series then then the
reaction can proceed and of course now
that you have this kind of empirical
scienceart you can apply it to
other uh more nuanced things like
scaling laws applied to interpretability
or scaling laws applied to posttraining
or just seeing how does this thing scale
but the big scaling law I guess the
underlying scaling hypothesis has to do
with big networks Big Data leads to
intelligence yeah we've we've documented
scaling laws in lots of domains other
than language right so uh initially the
the paper we did that first showed it
was in early 2020 where we first showed
it for language there was then some work
late in 2020 where we showed the same
thing for other modalities like images
video
text to image image to text math they
all had the same pattern and and you're
right now there are other stages like
posttraining or there are new types of
reasoning models and in in in all of
those cases that we've measured we see
similar similar types of scaling laws a
bit of a philosophical question but
what's your intuition about why bigger
is better in terms of network size and
data size why does it lead to more
intelligent models so in my previous
career as a as a biophysicist so I did
physics undergrad and then biophysics in
in in in grad school so I think back to
what I know as a physicist which is
actually much less than what some of my
colleagues at anthropic have in terms of
in terms of expertise in physics uh
there's this there's this concept called
the one over F noise and one overx
distributions um where where often um uh
you know just just like if you add up a
bunch of natural processes you get
gaussian if you add up a bunch of kind
of differently distributed natural
processes if you like if you like take a
take a um probe and and hook it up to a
resistor the distribution of the thermal
noise in the resistor goes as one over
the frequency um it's some kind of
natural convergent distribution uh and
and I I I I and and I think what it
amounts to is that if you look at a lot
of things that are that are produced by
some natural process that has a lot of
different scales right not a gaussian
which is kind of narrowly distributed
but you know if I look at kind of like
large and small fluctuations that lead
to lead to electrical noise um they have
this decaying 1 overx distribution and
so now I think of like patterns in the
physical world right if I if or or in
language if I think about the patterns
in language there are some really simple
patterns some words are much more common
than others like the' then there's basic
noun verb structure then there's the
fact that you know you know nouns and
verbs have to agree they have to
coordinate and there's the higher level
sentence structure then there's the
Thematic structure of paragraphs and so
the fact that there's this regressing
structure you can imagine that as you
make the networks larger first they
capture the really simple correlations
the really simple patterns and there's
this long taale of other patterns and if
that long taale of other patterns is
really smooth like it is with the one
over F noise in you know physical
processes like like like resistors then
you could imagine as you make the
network larger it's kind of capturing
more and more of that distribution and
so that smoothness gets reflected in how
well the models are at predicting and
how well they perform language is an
evolved process right we've we've
developed language we have common words
and less common words we have common
expressions and less common Expressions
we have ideas cliches that are expressed
frequently and we have novel ideas and
that process has has developed has
evolved with humans over millions of
years and so the the the guess and this
is pure speculation would be would be
that there is there's some kind of
longtail distribution of of of the
distribution of these ideas so there's
the long tail but also there's the
height of the hierarchy of Concepts that
you're building up so the bigger the
network presumably you have a higher
capacity to exactly if you have a small
Network you only get the common stuff
right if if I take a tiny neural network
it's very good at understanding that you
know a sentence has to have you know
verb adjective noun right but it's it's
terrible at deciding what those verb
adjective and noun should be and whether
they should make sense if I make it just
a little bigger it gets good at that
then suddenly it's good at the sentences
but it's not good at the paragraphs and
so the these these rare and more complex
patterns get picked up as I add as I add
more capacity to the network well the
natural question then is what's the
ceiling of this like how complicated and
complex is the real world how much of
stuff is there to learn I don't think
any of us knows the answer to that
question um I my strong Instinct would
be that there's no ceiling below level
of humans right we humans are able to
understand these various patterns and so
that that makes me think that if we
continue to you know scale up these
these these models to kind of develop
new methods for training them and
scaling them up uh that will at least
get to the level that we've gotten to
with humans there's then a question of
you know how much more is it possible to
understand than humans do how much how
much is it possible to be smarter and
more perceptive than humans I I would
guess the answer has has got to be
domain dependent if I look at an area
like biology and you know I wrote this
essay Machines of Loving Grace it seems
to me that humans are struggling to
understand the complexity of biology
right if you go to Stanford or to
Harvard or to Berkeley you have whole
Departments of you know folks trying to
study you know like the immune system or
metabolic pathways and and each person
understands only a tiny bit part of it
specializes and they're struggling to
combine their knowledge with that of
with that of other humans and so I have
an instinct that there's there's a lot
of room at the top for AIS to get
smarter if I think of something like
materials in the in the physical world
or you know um like addressing you know
conflicts between humans or something
like that I mean you know it it may be
there's only some of these problems are
not intractable but much harder and and
it it may be that there's only there's
only so well you can do with some of
these things right just like with speech
recognition there's only so clear I can
hear your speech so I think in some
areas there may be ceilings in in in you
know that are very close to what humans
have done in other areas those ceilings
may be very far away and I think we'll
only find out when we build these
systems uh there's it's very hard to
know in advance we can speculate but we
can't be sure and in some domains the
ceiling might have to do with human
bureaucracies and things like this as
you're right about yes so humans
fundamentally have to be part of the
loop that's the cause of the ceiling not
maybe the limits of the intelligence
yeah I think in many cases um you know
in theory technology could change very
fast for example all the things that we
might invent with respect to biology um
but remember there's there's a you know
there's a clinical trial system that we
have to go through to actually
administer these things to humans I
think that's a mixture of things that
are unnecessary and bureaucratic and
things that kind of protect the
Integrity of society and the whole
challenge is that it's hard to tell it's
hard to tell what's going on uh it's
hard to tell which is which right my my
view is definitely I think in terms of
drug development we my view is that
we're too slow and we're too
conservative but certainly if you get
these things wrong you know it's it's
possible to to to risk people's lives by
by being by being by being too Reckless
and so at least at least some of these
human institutions are in fact
protecting people so it's it's all about
finding the balance I strongly suspect
that balance is kind of more on the side
of pushing to make things happen faster
but there is a balance if we do hit a
limit if we do hit a Slowdown in the
scaling laws what do you think would be
the reason is it compute limited data
limited uh is it something else idea
limited so a few things now we're
talking about hitting the limit before
we get to the level of of humans and the
skill of humans um so so I think one
that's you know one that's popular today
and I think you know could be a limit
that we run into I like most of the
limits I would bet against it but it's
definitely possible is we simply run out
of data there's only so much data on the
internet and there's issues with the
quality of the data right you can get
hundreds of trillions of words on the
internet but a lot of it is is
repetitive or it's search engine you
know search engine optimization driil or
maybe in the future it'll even be text
generated by AIS itself uh and and so I
think there are limits to what to to
what can be produced in this way that
said we and I would guess other
companies are working on ways to make
data synthetic uh where you can you know
you can use the model to generate more
data of the type that you have that you
have already or even generate data from
scratch if you think about uh what was
done with uh deep mines Alpha go zero
they managed to get a bot all the way
from you know no ability to play Go
whatsoever to above human level just by
playing against itself there was no
example data from humans required in the
the alphao zero version of it the other
direction of course is these reasoning
models that do Chain of Thought and stop
to think um and and reflect on their own
thinking in a way that's another kind of
synthetic data coupled with
reinforcement learning so my my guess is
with one of those methods we'll get
around the data limitation or there may
be other sources of data that are that
are available um we could just observe
that even if there's no problem with
data as we start to scale models up they
just stop getting better it's it seemed
to be a a reliable observation that
they've gotten better that could just
stop at some point for a reason we don't
understand um the answer could be that
we need to uh you know we need to invent
some new architecture um it's been there
have been problems in the past with with
say numerical stability of models where
it looked like things were were leveling
off but but actually you know know when
we when we when we found the right
Unblocker they didn't end up doing so so
perhaps there's new some new
optimization method or some new uh
Technique we need to to unblock things
I've seen no evidence of that so far but
if things were to to slow down that
perhaps could be one reason what about
the limits of compute meaning uh the
expensive uh nature of building bigger
and bigger data centers so right now I
think uh you know most of the Frontier
Model companies I would guess are are
operating you know roughly you know $1
billion scale plus or minus a factor of
three right those are the models that
exist now or are being trained now uh I
think next year we're going to go to a
few billion and then uh 2026 we may go
to uh uh you know above 10 10 10 billion
and probably by 2027 their Ambitions to
build hundred hundred billion dollar uh
hundred billion dollar clusters and I
think all of that actually will happen
there's a lot of determination to build
the compute to do it within this country
uh and I would guess that it actually
does happen now if we get to 100 billion
that's still not enough compute that's
still not enough scale then either we
need even more scale or we need to
develop some way of doing it more
efficiently of Shifting The Curve um I
think be between all of these one of the
reasons I'm bullish about powerful AI
happening so fast is just that if you
extrapolate the next few points on the
curve we're very quickly getting towards
human level ability right some of the
new models that that we developed some
some reasoning models that have come
from other companies they're starting to
get to what I would call the PHD or
professional level right if you look at
their their coding ability um the latest
model we released Sonet 3.5 the new or
updated version it gets something like
50% on sbench and sbench is an example
of a bunch of professional real world
software engineering tasks at the
beginning of the year I think the
state-of-the-art was three or 4% so in
10 months we've gone from 3% to 50% on
this task and I think in another year
we'll probably be at 90% I mean I don't
know but might might even be might even
be less than that uh we've seen similar
things in graduate level math physics
and biology from Models like open AI 01
uh so uh if we if we just continue to
extrapolate this right in terms of skill
skill that we have I think if we
extrapolate the straight curve Within a
few years we will get to these models
being you know above the the highest
professional level in terms of humans
now will that curve continue you've
pointed to and I've pointed to a lot of
reasons why you know possible reasons
why that might not happen but if the if
the extrapolation curve continues that
is the trajectory we're on so anthropic
has several competitors it'd be
interesting to get your sort of view of
it all open aai Google xai meta what
does it take to win in the broad sense
of win in the space yeah so I want to
separate out a couple things right so
you know anthropics anthropic mission is
to kind of try to make this all go well
right and and you know we have a theory
of change called race to the top right
race to the top is about trying to push
the other players to do the right thing
by setting an example it's not about
being the good guy it's about setting
things up so that all of us can be the
good guy I'll give a few examples of
this early in the history of anthropic
one of our co-founders Chris Ola who I
believe you're you're interviewing soon
you know he's the co-founder of the
field of mechanistic interpretability
which is an attempt to understand what's
going on inside AI models uh so we had
him and one of our early teams focus on
this area of interpretability which we
think is good for making models safe and
transparent for three or four years that
had no commercial application whatsoever
it still doesn't today we're doing some
early betas with it and probably it will
eventually but uh you know this is a
very very long research bed in one in
which we've we've built in public and
shared our results publicly and and we
did this because you know we think it's
a way to make models safer an
interesting thing is that as we've done
this other companies have started doing
it as well in some cases because they've
been inspired by it in some cases
because they're worried that uh you know
if if other companies are doing this
that look more responsible they want to
look more responsible too no one wants
to look like the irresponsible ible
actor and and so they adopt this they
adopt this as well when folks come to
anthropic interpretability is often a
draw and I tell them the other places
you didn't go tell them why you came
here um and and then you see soon that
there that there's interpretability
teams else elsewhere as well and in a
way that takes away our competitive
Advantage because it's like oh they now
others are doing it as well but it's
good it's good for the broader system
and so we have to invent some new thing
that we're doing others aren't doing as
well and the hope is to basically bid up
bid up the importance of of of doing the
right thing and it's not it's not about
us in particular right it's not about
having one particular good guy other
companies can do this as well if they if
they if they join the race to do this
that's that's you know that's the best
news ever right um uh it's it's just
it's about kind of shaping the
incentives to point upward instead of
shaping the incentives to point to point
downward and we should say this example
the field of uh mechanistic
interpretability is just a a rigorous
non handwavy way of doing AI safety yes
or it's tending that way trying to I
mean I I think we're still early um in
terms of our ability to see things but
I've been surprised at how much we've
been able to look inside these systems
and understand what we see right unlike
with the scaling laws where it feels
like there's some you know law that's
driving these models to perform better
on on the inside the models aren't you
know there's no reason why they should
be designed for us to understand them
right they're designed to operate
they're designed to work just like the
human brain or human biochemistry
they're not designed for a human to open
up the hatch look inside and understand
them but we have found and you know you
can talk in much more detail about this
to Chris that when we open them up when
we do look inside them we we find things
that are surprisingly interesting and as
a side effect you also get to see the
beauty of these models you get to
explore the sort of uh the beautiful n
nature of large neural networks through
the me turb kind ofy I'm amazed at how
clean it's been I I'm amazed at things
like induction heads I'm amazed at
things like uh you know that that we can
you know use sparse autoencoders to find
these directions within the networks uh
and that the directions correspond to
these very clear Concepts we
demonstrated this a bit with the Golden
Gate Bridge clad so this was an
experiment where we found a direction
inside one of the the neural network
layers that corresponded to the Golden
Gate Bridge and we just turned that way
up and so we we released this model as a
demo it was kind of half a joke uh for a
couple days uh but it was it was
illustrative of of the method we
developed and uh you could you could
take the Golden Gate you could take the
model you could ask it about anything
you know you know it would be like how
you could say how was your day and
anything you asked because this feature
was activated would connect to the
Golden Gate Bridge so it would say you
know I'm I'm I'm feeling relaxed and
expansive much like the the arches of
the Golden Gate Bridge or you know it
would masterfully change topic to the
Golden Gate Bridge and it integrated
there was also a sadness to it to to the
focus ah had on the Golden Gate Bridge I
think people quickly fell in love with
it I think so people already miss it
because it was taken down I think after
a day somehow these interventions on the
model um where where where where you
kind of adjust Its Behavior somehow
emotionally made it seem more human than
any other version of the model strong
personality strong ID strong personality
it has these kind of like obsessive
interests you know we can all think of
someone who's like obsessed with
something so it does make it feel
somehow a bit more human let's talk
about the present let's talk about
Claude so this year A lot has happened
in March claw 3 Opa Sonet Hau were
released then claw 35 Sonet in July with
an updated version just now released and
then also claw 35 hi coup was released
okay can you explain the difference
between Opus Sonet and Haiku and how we
should think about the different
versions yeah so let's go back to March
when we first released uh these three
models so you know our thinking was you
different companies produce kind of
large and small models better and worse
models we felt that there was demand
both for a really powerful model um you
know and you that might be a little bit
slower that you'd have to pay more for
and also for fast cheap models that are
as smart as they can be for how fast and
cheap right whenever you want to do some
kind of like you know difficult analysis
like if I you know I want to write code
for instance or you know I want to I
want to brainstorm ideas or I want to do
creative writing I want the really
powerful model but then there's a lot of
practical applications in a business
sense where it's like I'm interacting
with a website I you know like I'm like
doing my taxes or I'm you know talking
to uh you know to like a legal adviser
and I want to analyze a contract or you
know we have plenty of companies that
are just like you know you know I want
to do autocomplete on my on my IDE or
something uh and and for all of those
things you want to act fast and you want
to use the model very broadly so we
wanted to serve that whole spectrum of
needs um so we ended up with this uh you
know this kind of poetry theme and so
what's a really short poem it's a Haik
cou and so Haiku is the small fast cheap
model that is you know was at the time
was released surprisingly surprisingly
uh intelligent for how fast and cheap it
was uh sonnet is a is a medium-sized
poem right a couple paragraphs since o
Sonet was the middle model it is smarter
but also a little bit slower a little
bit more expensive and and Opus like a
magnum opus is a large work uh Opus was
the the largest smartest model at the
time um so that that was the original
kind of thinking behind it um and our
our thinking then was well each new
generation of models should shift that
tradeoff curve uh so when we release
Sonet 3.5 it has the same roughly the
same you know cost and speed as the
Sonet 3 Model uh but uh it it increased
its intelligence to the point where it
was smarter than the original Opus 3
Model uh especially for code but but
also just in general and so now you know
we've shown results for a Hau 3. 5 and I
believe Hau 3.5 the smallest new model
is about as good as Opus 3 the largest
old model so basically the aim here is
to shift the curve and then at some
point there's going to be an opus 3.5 um
now every new generation of models has
its own thing they use new data their
personality changes in ways that we kind
of you know try to steer but are not
fully able to steer and and so uh
there's never quite that exact
equivalence the only thing you're
changing is intelligence um we always
try and improve other things and some
things change without us without us
knowing or measuring so it's it's very
much an inexact science in many ways the
manner and personality of these models
is more an art than it is a science so
what is sort of the reason for uh the
span of time between say Claude Opus 3
and 35 what is it what takes that time
if you can speak to yeah so there's
there's different there's different uh
processes um uh there's pre-training
which is you know just kind of the
normal language model training and that
takes a very long time um that uses you
know these days you know tens you know
tens of thousands sometimes many tens of
thousands of uh gpus or tpus or tranium
or you know what we use different
platforms but you know accelerator chips
um often often training for months uh
there's then a kind of posttraining
phase where we do reinforcement learning
from Human feedback as well as other
kinds of reinforcement learning that
that phase is getting uh larger and
larger now and you know you know often
that's less of an exact science it often
takes effort to get it right um models
are then tested with some of our early
Partners to see how good they are and
they're then tested both internally and
externally for their safety particularly
for catastrophic and autonomy r risks uh
so uh we do internal testing according
to our responsible scaling policy which
I you know could talk more about that in
detail and then we have an agreement
with the US and the UK AI safety
Institute as well as other third-party
testers in specific domains to test the
models for what are called cbrn risk
chemical biological radiological and
nuclear which are you know we don't
think that models pose these risks
seriously yet but but every new model we
want to evaluate to see if we're
starting to get close to some of these
these these more dangerous um uh these
more dangerous capabilities so those are
the phases and then uh you know then
then it just takes some time to get the
model working in terms of inference and
launching it in the API so there's just
just a lot of steps to uh to actually to
actually making a model work and of
course you know we're always trying to
make the processes as streamlined as
possible right we want our safety
testing to be rigorous but we want it to
be RoR ous and to be you know to be
automatic to happen as fast as it can
without compromising on rigor same with
our pre-training process and our
posttraining process so you know it's
just like building anything else it's
just like building airplanes you want to
make them you know you want to make them
safe but you want to make the process
streamlined and I think the creative
tension between those is is you know is
an important thing and making the models
work yeah uh rumor on the street I
forget who was saying that uh anthropic
is really good tooling so I uh probably
a lot of the challenge here is on the
software engineering side is to build
the tooling to to have a like a
efficient low friction interaction with
the infrastructure you would be
surprised how much of the challenges of
uh you know building these models comes
down to you know software engineering
performance engineering you know you you
know from the outside you might think oh
man we had this Eureka breakthrough
right you know this movie with the
science we discovered it we figured it
out but but but I think I think all
things even even even you know
incredible discoveries like they they
they they they almost always come down
to the details um and and often super
super boring details I can't speak to
whether we have better tooling than than
other companies I mean you know I
haven't been at those other companies at
least at least not recently um but it's
certainly something we give a lot of
attention to I don't know if you can say
but from three from CLA 3 to CLA 35 is
there any extra pre-training going on or
is they mostly focus on the
post-training there's been leaps in
performance yeah I think I think at any
given stage we're focused on improving
everything at once um just just
naturally like there are different teams
each team makes progress in a particular
area in in in making a particular you
know their particular segment of the
relay race better and it's just natural
that when we make a new model we put we
put all of these things in at once so
the data you have like the preference
data you get from rhf is that applicable
is there ways to apply it to newer
models as it get trained up yeah
preference data from old models
sometimes gets used for new models
although of course uh it it performs
somewhat better when it's you know
trained on it's trained on the new
models note that we have this you know
constitutional AI method such that we
don't only use preference data we kind
of there's also a post-t trainining
process where we train the model against
itself and there's you know new types of
post training the model against itself
that are used every day so it's not just
RF it's a bunch of other methods as well
um post training I think you know it's
becoming more and more sophisticated
well what explains the big leap in
performance for the new Sona 35 I mean
at least in the programming side and
maybe this is a good place to talk about
benchmarks what does it mean to get
better just the number went up but you
know I I I program but I also love
programming and I um claw 35 through
cursor is what I use uh to assist me in
programming and there was at least
experientially anecdotally it's gotten
smarter at programming so what like what
what does it take to get it uh to get it
smarter we observe that as well by the
way there were a couple uh very strong
Engineers here at anthropic um who all
previous code models both produced by us
and produced by all the other companies
hadn't really been useful to to hadn't
really been useful to them you know they
said you know maybe maybe this is useful
to beginner it's not useful to me but
Sonet 3.5 the original one for the first
time they said oh my God this helped me
with something that you know that it
would have taken me hours to do this is
the first model that has actually saved
me time so again the water line is
rising and and then I think you know the
new Sonet has been has been even better
in terms of what it what it takes I mean
I'll just say it's been across the board
it's in the pre-training it's in the
posttraining it's in various evaluations
that we do we've observed this as well
and if we go into the details of the
Benchmark so s bench is basically you
know since since you know since since
you're a programmer you know you'll be
familiar with like PLL requests and you
know uh just just PLL requests are like
you know the like a sort of a sort of
atomic unit of work you know you could
say I'm you know I'm implementing one
I'm implementing one thing um uh and and
so sbench actually gives you kind of a
real world situation where the codebase
is in a current state and I'm trying to
implement something that's you know
that's described in described in
language we have internal benchmarks
where we where we measure the same thing
and you say just give the model free
reign to like you know do anything run
run run anything edit anything um how
how well is it able to complete these
tasks and it's that Benchmark that's
gone from it can do it 3% of the time to
it can do it about 50% of the time um so
I actually do believe that if we get you
can gain benchmarks but I think if we
get to 100% on that Benchmark in a way
that isn't kind of like overtrained or
or or game for that particular Benchmark
probably represents a real and serious
increase in kind of
in kind of programming programming
ability and and I would suspect that if
we can get to you know 90 90 95% that
that that that you know it will it will
represent ability to autonomously do a
significant fraction of software
engineering
tasks well ridiculous timeline question
uh when is clad Opus uh 3.5 coming up uh
not giving you an exact date uh but you
know there there uh you know as far as
we know the plan is still to have a
Claude 3.5 opus are we gonna get it
before GTA 6 or no like Duke Nukem
Forever was that game that there was
some game that was delayed 15 years was
that Duke Nukem Forever yeah and I think
GTA is now just releasing trailers it
you know it's only been three months
since we released the first son it yeah
it's Inc the incredible pace of relas it
just it just tells you about the pace
the expectations for when things are
going to come out so uh what about
40 so how do you think about sort of as
these models get bigger and bigger about
versioning and also just versioning in
general why Sonet 35 updated with the
date why not Sonet
3.6 actually naming is actually an
interesting challenge here right because
I think a year ago most of the model was
pre-training and so you could start from
the beginning and just say okay we're
going to have models of different sizes
we're going to train them all together
and you know we'll have a a family of
naming schemes and then we'll put some
new magic into them and then you know
we'll have the next the next Generation
Um the trouble starts are already when
some of them take a lot longer than
others to train right that already
messes up your time time a little bit
but as you make big improvements in as
you make big improvements in
pre-training uh then you suddenly notice
oh I can make better pre-train model and
that doesn't take very long to do and
but you know clearly it has the same you
know size and shape of previous models
uh uh so I think those two together as
well as the timing timing issues any
kind of scheme you come up with uh you
know the reality tends to kind of
frustrate that scheme right T tends to
kind of break out of the break out of
the scheme it's not like software where
you can say oh this is like you know 3.7
this is 3.8 no you have models with
different different tradeoffs you can
change some things in your models you
can train you can change other things
some are faster and slower at inference
some have to be more expensive some have
to be less expensive and so I think all
the companies have struggled with this
um I think we did very you know I think
think we were in a good good position in
terms of naming when we had Haiku Sonet
and we're trying to maintain it but it's
not it's not it's not perfect um so
we'll we'll we'll try and get back to
the Simplicity but it it um uh just the
the the nature of the field I feel like
no one's figured out naming it's somehow
a different Paradigm from like normal
software and and and so we we just none
of the companies have been perfect at it
um it's something we struggle with
surprisingly much relative to you know
how relative to how trivial it is to you
know for the the the the grand science
of training the models so from the user
side the user experience of the updated
Sonet 35 is just different than the
previous uh June 2024 Sonet 35 it would
be nice to come up with some kind of
labeling that embodies that because
people talk about son 35 but now there's
a different one and so how do you refer
to the previous one and the new one and
it it uh when there's a distinct
Improvement it just makes conversation
about it uh just challenging yeah yeah I
I definitely think this question of
there are lots of properties of the
models that are not reflected in the
benchmarks um I I think I think that's
that's definitely the case and everyone
agrees and not all of them are
capabilities some of them are you know
models can be polite or brusk they can
be uh you know uh very reactive or they
can ask you questions um they can have
what what feels like a warm personality
or a cold personality they can be boring
or they can be very distinctive like
Golden Gate Claude was um and we have a
whole you know we have a whole team kind
of focused on I think we call it Claude
character uh Amanda leads that team and
we'll we'll talk to you about that but
it's still a very inexact science um and
and often we find that models have
properties that we're not aware of the
the fact of the matter is that you can
you know talk to a model 10,000 times
and there are some behaviors you might
not see uh just like just like with a
human right I can know someone for a few
months and you know not know that they
have a certain skill or not know there's
a certain side to them and so I think I
think we just have to get used to this
idea and we're always looking for better
ways of testing our models to to
demonstrate these capabilities and and
and also to decide which are which are
the which are the personality properties
we want models to have have and which we
don't want to have that itself the
normative question is also super
interesting I got to ask you a question
from Reddit from Reddit oh
boy you know there there's just this
fascinating to me at least it's a
psychological social
phenomenon where people report that
Claude has gotten Dumber for them over
time and so uh the question is does the
user complaint about the dumbing down of
claw 35 Sonic hold any water so are
these anecdota reports a kind of social
phenomena or did Claude is there any
cases where Claude would get Dumber so
uh this actually doesn't apply this this
isn't just about Claude I I believe this
I believe I've seen these complaints for
every Foundation model produced by a
major company um people said this about
gp4 they said it about gp4 turbo um so
so so a couple things um one the actual
weights of the model right the actual
brain of the model that does not change
unless we introduce a new model um there
there just a number of reasons why it
would not make sense practically to be
randomly substituting in substituting in
new versions of the model it's difficult
from an inference perspective and it's
actually hard to control all the
consequences of changing the way to the
model let's say you wanted to fine-tune
the model to be like I don't know to
like to say certainly less which you
know an old version of Sonet used to do
um you actually end up changing a 100
things as well so we have a whole
process for it and we have a whole
process for modifying the model we do a
bunch of testing on it we do a bunch of
um like we do a bunch of user testing
and early customers so it we both have
never changed the weights of the model
without without telling anyone and it it
it wouldn't certainly in the current
setup it would not make sense to do that
now there are a couple things that we do
occasionally do um one is sometimes we
run AB tests um but those are typically
very close to when a model is being is
being uh released and for a very small
fraction of time um so uh you know like
the you know the the day before the new
Sonet 3.5 I I agree we should have
should have had a better name it's
clunky to refer to it um there were some
comments from people that like it's got
It's got it's gotten a lot better and
that's because you know a fraction were
exposed to to an AB test for for those
one or for those one or two days um the
other is that occasionally the system
prompt will change um on the system
prompt can have some effects although
it's un it it it's unlikely to dumb down
models it's unlikely to make them Dumber
um and and and and we've seen that while
these two things which I'm listing to be
very complete um happen relatively
happen quite infrequently um the
complaints about to for us and for other
model companies about the model changed
the model isn't good at this the model
got more censored the model was dumb
down those complaints are constant and
so I don't want to say like people are
imagining it or anything but like the
models are for the most part not
changing um if I were to offer a theory
um I I think it actually relates to one
of the things I said before which is
that models have many are very complex
and have many aspects to them and so
often you know if I if I if if I ask a
model a question you know if I'm like if
I'm like do task X versus can you do
task XX the model might respond in
different ways uh and and so there are
all kinds of subtle things that you can
change about the way you interact with
the model that can give you very
different results um to be clear this
this itself is like a failing by by us
and by the other model providers that
that the models are are just just often
sensitive to like small small changes in
wording it's yet another way in which
the science of how these models work is
very poorly developed uh and and so you
know if I go to sleep one night and I
was like talking to the model in a
certain way and I like slightly Chang
the phrasing of how I talk to the model
you know I could I could get different
results so that's that's one possible
way the other thing is man it's just
hard to quantify this stuff uh it's hard
to quantify this stuff I think people
are very excited by new models when they
come out and then as time goes on they
they become very aware of the they
become very aware of the limitations so
that may be another effect but that's
that's all a very long- rended way of
saying for the most part with some
fairly narrow exceptions the models are
not changing I think there is a
psychological effect you just start
getting used to it the Baseline ra like
when people have first gotten Wi-Fi on
airplanes it's like amazing magic and
then now like I can't get this thing to
work this is such a piece of crap
exactly so it's easy to have the
conspiracy theory of they're making
Wi-Fi slower and slower this is probably
something I'll talk to Amanda much more
about but U another Reddit question uh
when will Claud stop trying to be my uh
panical grandmother imposing its moral
World viw on me as a paying customer and
also what does it that ology behind
making Claude overly apologetic so this
kind of reports about The Experience a
different angle on the frustration it
has to do with the character yeah so a
couple points on this first one is um
like things that people say on Reddit
and Twitter or X or whatever it is um
there's actually a huge distribution
shift between like the stuff that people
complain loudly about on social media
and what actually kind of like you know
statistically users care about and that
drives people to use the models like
people are frustrated with you know
things like you know the model not
writing out all the code or the model uh
you know just just not being as good at
code as it could be even though it's the
best model in the world on code um I I
think the majority of thing of things
are about that um uh but uh certainly a
a a kind of vocal minority are uh you
know kind kind of kind of rais these
concerns right are frustrated by the
model refusing things that it shouldn't
refuse or like apologizing too much or
just just having these kind of like
annoying verbal ticks um the second
caveat and I just want to say this like
super clearly because I think it's like
some people don't know it others like
kind of know it but forget it like it is
very difficult to control across the
board how the models behave you cannot
just reach in there and say oh I want
the model to like apologize less like
you can do that you can include trading
data that says like oh the models should
like apologize less but then in some
other situation they end up being like
super rude or like overconfident in a
way that's like misleading people so
they're they're all these tradeoffs um
uh for example another thing is if there
was a period during which models ours
and I think others as well were T
verbose right they would like repeat
themselves they would say too much um
you can cut down on the verbosity by
penalizing the models for for just
talking for too long what happens when
you do that if you do it in a crude way
is when the models are coding sometimes
they'll say of the code goes here right
because they've learned that that's a
way to economize and that they see it
and then and then so that leads the
model to be so-called lazy in coding
where they where they where they're just
like ah you can finish the rest of it
it's not it's not because we want to you
know save on compute or because you know
the models are lazy and you know during
winter break or any of the other kind of
conspiracy theories that have that have
that have come up it's actually it's
just very hard to control the behavior
of the model to steer the behavior of
the model in all circum ances at once
you can kind of there's this this whacka
aspect where you push on one thing and
like you know these these these you know
these other things start to move as well
that you may not even notice or measure
and so one of the reasons that I that I
care so much about uh you know kind of
grand alignment of these AI systems in
the future is actually these systems are
actually quite unpredictable they're
actually quite hard to steer and control
um and this version we're seeing today
of you make one thing better it makes
another thing worse uh I think that's
that's like a present day analog of
future control problems in AI systems
that we can start to study today right I
think I think that that that difficulty
in in steering the behavior and in
making sure that if we push an AI system
in One Direction it doesn't push it in
another Direction in some in some other
ways that we didn't want uh I think
that's that's kind of an that's kind of
an early sign of things to come and if
we can do a good job of solving this
problem right of like you ask the model
to like you know to like make and
distribute small pox and it says no but
it's willing to like help you in your
graduate level virology class like how
do we get both of those things at once
it's hard it's very easy to go to one
side or the other and it's a
multi-dimensional problem and so uh I
you know I think these questions of like
shaping the models personality I think
they're very hard I think we haven't
done perfectly on them I think we've
actually done the best of all the AI
companies but still so far from perfect
uh and I think if we can get this right
if we can control the the you know
control the false positives and false
negatives in this this very kind of
controlled present day environment will
be much better at doing it for the
future when our worry is you know will
the models be super autonomous will they
be able to you know make very dangerous
things will they be able to autonomously
you know build whole companies and are
those companies aligned so so I I I
think of this this present task as both
vacine but also good practice for the
future what's the current best way of
gathering sort of user feedback like uh
not anecdotal data but just large scale
data about pain points or the opposite
of pain points positive things so on is
it internal testing is it yeah A
specific group testing a testing what
what what works so so so typically um
we'll have internal model bashings where
all of anthropic anthropic is almost a
thousand people um you know people just
just try and break the model they try
and interact with it various ways um uh
we have a suite of evals uh for you know
oh is the model refusing in ways that
that it couldn't I think we even had a
certainly eval because you know our our
mod again at one point model had this
problem where like it had this annoying
tick where it would like respond to a
wide range of questions by saying
certainly I can help you with that
certainly I would be happy to do that
certainly this is correct um uh and so
we had a like certainly eval which is
like how how often does the model say
certainly uh uh but but look this is
just a whack-a-mole like like what if it
switches from certainly to definitely
like uh uh so you know every time we add
a new eval and we're always evaluating
for all the old things so we have
hundreds of these evaluations but we
find that there's no substitute for
human interacting with it and so it's
very much like the ordinary product
development process we have like
hundreds of people within anthropic bash
the model then we do uh you know then we
do external AB tests sometimes we'll run
tests with contractors we pay
contractors to interact with the model
um so you put all of these things
together and it's still not perfect you
still see behaviors that you don't quite
want to see right you know you see you
still see the model like refusing things
that it just doesn't make sense to
refuse um but I I I think trying to
trying to solve this challenge right
trying to stop the model from doing you
know genuinely bad things that you know
no one everyone agrees it shouldn't do
right you know everyone everyone you
know everyone agrees that you know the
model shouldn't talk about you know I I
don't know child abuse material right
like everyone agrees the model shouldn't
do that uh but but at the same time that
it doesn't refuse in these dumb and
stupid ways uh I think I think draw
drawing that line as finely as possible
approaching perfectly is still is still
a challenge and we're getting better at
it every day but there's there's a lot
to be solved and again I would point to
that as as an indicator of a challenge
ahead in terms of steering much more
powerful models do you think Claude 4.0
is ever coming out I don't want to
commit to any naming scheme because if I
say if I say here we're gonna have
Claude 4 next year and then and then you
know then we decide that like you know
we should start over because there's a
new type of mod like I I I I I I don't
want to I don't want to commit to it I
would expect in a normal course of
business that Claude four would come
after Claude 3.5 but but you know you
you you never know in this wacky field
right but the sort of this idea of
scaling is continuing scal scaling is
continuing there there will definitely
be more powerful models coming from us
in the models that exist today that is
that is certain or if there if there
aren't we've we've deeply failed as a
company okay can you explain the
responsible scaling policy and the AI
safety level standards ASL levels as
much as I'm excited about the benefits
of these models and you know we'll talk
about that if we talk about Machines of
Loving Grace um I'm I'm worried about
the risk and I continue to be worried
about the risks uh no one should think
that you know Machines of loveing Grace
was me me saying uh you know I'm no
longer worried about the risks of these
models I think they're two sides of the
same coin the the uh Power of the models
and their ability to solve all these
problems in you know biology
Neuroscience Economic Development
government governance and peace large
parts of the economy those those come
with risks as well right with great
power comes great responsibility right
that's the the two are the two are
paired uh things that are powerful can
do good things and they can do bad
things um I think of those risks as as
being in you know several different
different categories perhaps the two
biggest risks that I think about and
that's not to say that there aren't
risks today that are that are important
but when I think of the really the the
you know the things that would happen on
the grandest scale um one is what I call
catastrophic misuse these are misuse of
the models in domains like cyber bio
radiological nuclear right things that
could you know that could harm or even
kill thousands even millions of people
if they really really go wrong um like
these are the you know number one
priority to prevent and and here I would
just make a simple observation which is
that Mo the models you know if if I look
today at people who have done really bad
things in the world um uh I think
actually Humanity has been protected by
the fact that the overlap between really
smart well-educated people and people
who want to do really horrific things
has generally been small like you know
let's say let's say I'm someone who you
know uh you know I have a PhD in this
field I have a well-paying job um
there's so much to lose why do I want to
like you know even even assuming I'm
completely evil which which most people
are not um why why you know why would
such a person risk their risk their you
know risk their life RK risk their their
legacy their reputation to to do
something like you know truly truly evil
if we had a lot more people like that
the world would be a much more dangerous
place and so my my My worry is that by
being a a much more intelligent agent AI
could break that correlation and so I I
I I I do have serious worries about that
I believe we can prevent those worries
uh but you know I I think as a
Counterpoint to Machines of Loving Grace
I want to say that this is I there's
still serious risks and and the second
range of risks would be the autonomy
risks which is the idea that models
might on their own particularly as we
give them more agency than they've had
in the past uh particularly as we give
them supervision over wider tasks like
you know writing whole code bases or
someday even you know effectively
operating entire entire companies
they're on a long enough leash are they
are they doing what we really want them
to do it's very difficult to even
understand in detail what they're doing
let alone let alone control it and like
I said this these early signs that it's
it's hard to perfectly draw the boundary
between things the model should do and
things the model shouldn't do that that
you know if if you go to one side you
get things that are annoying and useless
and you go to the other side you get
other behaviors if you fix one thing it
creates other problems we're getting
better and better at solving this I
don't think this is an unsolvable
problem I think this is a you know this
is a science like like the safety of
airplanes or the safety of cars or the
safety of drugs I you know I I don't
think there's any big thing we're
missing I just think we need to get
better at controlling these models and
so these are these are the two risks I'm
worried about and our responsible
scaling plan which I'll recognize is a
very long-winded answer to your question
I love it I love it our responsible
scaling plan is designed to address
these two types of risks and so every
time we develop a new model we basically
test it for its ability to do both of
these bad things so if I were to back up
a little bit um I I think we have a I
think we have an interesting dilemma
with AI systems where they're not yet
powerful enough to present these
catastrophes I don't know that I don't
know they'll ever present prevent these
catastrophes it's possible they won't
but the the case for worry the case for
risk is strong enough that we should we
should act now and and they're they're
getting better very very fast right I
you know I testified in the Senate that
you know we might have serious bio risks
within two to three years that was about
a year ago things have preceded preceded
a pace uh uh so we have this thing where
it's like it's it's it's surprisingly
hard to to address these risks because
they're not here today they don't exist
they're like ghosts but they're coming
at us so fast because the models are
improving so fast so so how do you deal
with something that's not here today
doesn't exist but is is coming at us
very fast uh so the solution we came up
with for that in in collaboration with
uh you know people like uh the
organization meter and Paul Christiano
is okay what what what what you need for
that or you need tests to tell you when
the risk is getting close you need an
early warning system and and so every
time we have uh a new model we test it
for it capability to do these cbrn tasks
as well as testing it for you know how
capable it is of doing tasks
autonomously on its own and uh in the
latest version of our RSP which we
released in the last in the last month
or two uh the way we test autonomy risks
is the model the the AI model's ability
to do aspects of AI research itself uh
which when the model when the AI models
can do AI research they become kind of
truly truly autonomous on and that you
know that threshold is important for a
bunch of other ways and and so what do
we then do with these tasks the RSP
basically develops what we've called an
if then structure which is if the models
pass a certain capability then we impose
a certain set of Safety and Security
requirements on them so today's models
are what's called
asl2 models that were a asl1 is for
systems that manifestly don't pose any
risk of autonomy or misuse so for
example a chess plane bot deep blue
would be asl1 it's just manifestly the
case that you can't use deep blue for
anything other than chess it was just
designed for chess no one's going to use
it to like you know to conduct a
masterful Cyber attack or to you know
run wild and take over the world asl2 is
today's AI systems where we've measured
them and we think these systems are
simply not smart enough to uh to you
know autonomously self-replicate or
conduct a bunch of tasks uh and also not
smart enough to provide meaningful
information about cbrn risks and how to
build cbrn weapons above and beyond what
can be known from looking at Google uh
in fact sometimes they do provide
information but but not above and beyond
a search engine but not in a way that
can be stitched together um not not in a
way that kind of end to end is dangerous
enough so
asl3 is going to be the point at which
uh the models are helpful enough to
enhance the capabilities of non-state
actors right State actors can already do
a lot a lot of unfortunately to a high
level of proficiency a lot of these very
dangerous and destructive things the
difference is that non-state non-state
actors are not capable of it and so when
we get to asl3 we'll take special
security precautions designed to be be
sufficient to prevent theft of the model
by non-state actors and misuse of the
model as it's deployed uh will have to
have enhanced filters targeted at these
particular areas cyber bio nuclear cyber
bio nuclear and model autonomy Which is
less a misuse risk and more a risk of
the model doing bad things itself asl4
getting to the point where these models
could could enhance the capability of a
of a of a all knowledgeable State actor
Andor become the you know the main
source of such a risk like if you wanted
to engage in such a risk the main way
you would do it is through a model and
then I think asl4 on the autonomy side
it's it's some some some amount of
acceleration in AI research capabilities
with an with an AI model and then asl5
is where we would get to the models that
are you know that are that are kind of
that are kind of you know truly capable
that it could exceed Humanity in their
ability to do to do any of these tasks
and so the the the point of the if then
structure commitment is is basically to
say
look I don't know I've been I've been
working with these models for many years
and I've been worried about risk for
many years it's actually kind of
dangerous to cry wolf it's actually kind
of dangerous to say this you know this
this model is this model is risky and
you know people look at it and they say
this is manifestly not dangerous again
it's it's it's the the delicacy of the
risk isn't here to today but it's coming
at us fast how do you deal with that
it's it's really vexing to a risk
planner to deal with it and so this if
then structure basically says look we
don't want to antagonize a bunch of
people we don't want to harm our own you
know our our kind of own ability to have
a place in the conversation by imposing
these
these very honorous burdens on models
that are not dangerous today so the if
then the trigger commitment is basically
a way to deal with this says you claim
clamp down hard when you can show that
the model is dangerous and of course
what has to come with that is you know
enough of a buffer threshold that that
you know you can you can uh you know
you're you're you're you're not at high
risk of kind of missing the danger it's
not a perfect framework we've had to
change it every every uh you know we
came out with a new one just a few weeks
ago and probably probably going forward
we might release new ones multiple times
a year because it's it's hard to get
these policies right like technically
organizationally from a research
perspective but that is the proposal if
then commitments and triggers in order
to minimize burdens and false alarms now
but really react appropriately when the
dangers are here what do you think the
timeline for asl3 is where several of
the triggers are fired and what do you
think the timeline is for asl4 yeah so
that is hotly debated within the company
um uh we are working actively to prepare
asl3 uh security uh security measures as
well as ASL three deployment measures um
I'm not going to go into detail but
we've made we've made a lot of progress
on both and you know we're we're
prepared to be I think ready quite soon
uh I would I would not be surpris I
would not be surprised at all if we hit
ASL 3 uh next year there was some
concern that we we might even hit it uh
uh this year that's still that's still
possible that could still happen it's
like very hard to say but like I would
be very very surprised if it was like
2030 uh I think it's much sooner than
that so there's a protocols for
detecting it the if then and then
there's protocols for how to respond to
it yes how difficult is the second the
ladder yeah I think for asl3 it's
primarily about security um and and
about you know filters on the model
relating to a very narrow set of areas
when we deploy the model because at asl3
the model isn't autonomous yet um uh and
and so you don't have to worry about you
know kind of the model itself behaving
in a bad way even when it's deployed
internally so I think the asl3 measures
are are I won't say straightforward
they're they're they're they're rigorous
but they're easier to reason about I
think once we get to
asl4 um we start to have worries about
the models being smart enough that they
might sandbag tests they might not tell
the truth about tests um we had some
results came out about like sleeper
agents and there was a more recent paper
about you know can can the models uh uh
mislead attempts to you know s sandbag
their own abilities right show them you
know uh uh present themselves as being
less capable than they are and so I
think with asl4 there's going to be an
important component of using other
things than just interacting with the
models for example interpretability or
hidden chains of thought uh where you
have to look inside the model and verify
via some other mechanism that that is
not you know is not as easily corrupted
as what the model says
uh that that you know that that that the
model indeed has some property uh so
we're still working on asl4 one of the
properties of the RSP is that we we
don't specify asl4 until we've hit ASL 3
be and and I think that's proven to be a
wise decision because even with asl3 it
again it's hard to know this stuff in
detail and and it it we want to take as
much time as we can possibly take to get
these things right so for asl3 the bad
actor will be the humans humans yes and
so there it's a little bit more uh for
asl4 it's both I think it's both and so
deception and that's where mechanistic
interpretability comes into play and
hopefully the techniques used for that
are not made accessible to the model
yeah I mean of course you can hook up
the mechanistic contribut ability to the
model itself um but then You' then then
you then you've kind of lost it as a
reliable indicator of uh of uh of of of
the model State there are a bunch of
exotic ways you can think of that it
might also not be reliable like if the
you know model gets smart enough that it
can like you know jump computers and
like read the code where you're like
looking at its internal State we've
thought about some of those I think
they're exotic enough there are ways to
render them unlikely but yeah generally
you want to you want to preserve
mechanistic interpretability as a kind
of verification set or test set that's
separate from the training process of
the model see I think uh as these models
become better and better conversation
and become smarter social engineering
becomes a threat too cuz they oh yeah
that can start being very convincing to
the engineers inside companies oh yeah
yeah it's actually like you know we've
we've seen lots of examples of
demagoguery in our life from humans and
and you know there's a concern that
models could do that could do that as
well one of the ways that cloud has been
getting more and more powerful is it's
now able to do some agentic stuff um
computer use uh there's also an analysis
within the sandbox of claw. a itself but
let's talk about computer use that's
seems to me super exciting that you can
just give Claude a task and it uh takes
a bunch of actions figures it out and
has access to the your computer through
screenshots so can you explain how that
works uh and where that's headed yeah
it's actually relatively simple so
Claude has has had for a long time since
since Claude 3 back in March the ability
to analyze images and respond to them
with text the the only new thing we
added is those images can be screenshot
shots of a computer and in response we
train the model to give a location on
the screen where you can click Andor
buttons on the keyboard you can press in
order to take action and it turns out
that with actually not all that much
additional training the models can get
quite good at that task it's a good
example of generalization um you know
people sometimes say if you get to low
earth orbit you're like halfway to
anywhere right because of how much it
takes to escape the gravity well if you
have a strong pre-trained model I feel
like you're halfway to anywhere uh in
ter in terms of in terms of the
intelligence space uh uh uh and and and
so actually it didn't it didn't take all
that much to get to get Claude to do
this and you can just set that in a loop
give the model a screenshot tell it what
to click on give it the next screenshot
tell it what to click on and and that
turns into a full kind of almost almost
3D video interaction of the model and
it's able to do all of these tasks right
you know we we showed these demos where
it's able to like fill out spreadsheets
it's able to kind of like interact with
a website it's able to you know um you
know it's able to open all kinds of you
know programs different operating
systems Windows Linux Mac uh uh so uh
you know I think all of that is very
exciting I I will say while in theory
there's nothing you could do there that
you couldn't have done through just
giving the model the API to drive the
computer screen uh this really lowers
the barrier and you know there's there's
there's a lot of folks who who who
either you know kind of kind of ar ar
you know aren't in a position to to
interact with those apis or it takes
them a long time to do it's just the
screen is just a universal interface
that's a lot easier to interact with and
so I expect over time this is going to
lower a bunch of barriers now honestly
the current model has there's there it
leaves a lot still to be desired and we
were we were honest about that in the
blog right it makes mistakes it
misclicks and we we you know we were
careful to warn people hey this thing
isn't you can't just leave this thing to
you know run on your computer for
minutes and minutes um you got to give
this thing boundaries and guard rails
and I think that's one of the reasons we
released it first in an API form rather
than kind of you know this this kind of
just just hand it just hand it to the
consumer and give it control of their of
their of their of their computer um but
but you know I definitely feel that it's
important to get these capabilities out
there as models get more powerful we're
going to have to Grapple with you know
how do we use these capabilities safely
how do we prevent them from being abused
uh and and you know I think I think
releasing releasing the model while
while while the capabilities are are you
know are are still are still limited is
is is very helpful in terms of in terms
of doing that um you know I think since
it's been released a number of customers
I think uh repet was maybe was maybe one
of the the the most uh uh quickest
quickest quickest to quickest to deploy
things um have have you know have made
use of it in various ways people have
hooked up demos for you know Windows
desktops Macs
uh uh you know Linux Linux machines uh
so yeah it's been it's been it's been
very exciting I think as with as with
anything else you know it it it comes
with new exciting abilities and then
then then you know then then with those
new exciting abilities we have to think
about how to how to you know make the
model you know safe reliable do what
humans want them to do I mean it's the
same it's the same story for everything
right same thing it's that same tension
but but the possibility of use cases
here is just the the range is incredible
so uh how much to make it work really
well in the future how much do you have
to specially kind of uh go beyond what's
the pre-trained models doing do more
posttraining rhf or supervised
fine-tuning or synthetic data just for
the agent stff yeah I think speaking at
a high level It's Our intention to keep
investing a lot in you know making
making the model better uh like I think
I think uh you know we look at look at
some of the you know some of the
benchmarks where previous models were
like oh could do it 6% of the time and
now our model do at 14 or 22% of the
time and yeah we want to get up to you
know the human level reliability of 80
90% just like anywhere else right we're
on the same curve that we were on with
sbench where I think I would guess a
year from now the models can do this
very very reliably but you got to start
somewhere so you think it's possible to
get to the the human level 90% uh
basically doing the same thing you're
doing now or is it has to be special for
computer use I I mean uh depends what
you mean by by you know special and FAL
and
um but but you know I generally think
you know the same kinds of techniques
that we've been using to train the
current model I I expect that doubling
down in those techniques in the same way
that we have for code for code for
models in general for other k for you
know for image input um uh you know for
voice uh I expect those same techniques
will scale here as they have everywhere
else but this is giving sort of the
power of action to Claude And so you
could do a lot of really powerful things
but you could do a lot of damage also
yeah yeah no and we've been very aware
of that look my my view actually is
computer use isn't a fundamentally new
capability like the cbrn or autonomy
capabilities are um it's more like it
kind of opens the aperture for the model
to use and apply its existing abilities
uh and and so the way we think about it
going back to our RSP is nothing that
this model is
doing inherently increases
you know the risk from an RSP RSP
perspective but as the models get more
powerful having this capability may make
it scarier once it you know once it has
the cognitive capability to um you know
to do something at the asl3 and asl4
level this this you know this may be the
thing that kind of Unbound it from doing
so so going forward certainly this
modality of interaction is something we
have tested for and that we will
continue to test for in our going
forward um I think it's probably better
to have to learn and explore this
capability before the model is super uh
you know super capable yeah and there's
uh a lot of interesting attacks like
prompt injection because now you've
widened the aperture so you can prompt
inject through stuff on screen so if
this becomes more and more useful then
there's more and more benefit to inject
inject stuff into the model if it goes
to certain web page it could be harmless
stuff like advertisements or it could be
like harmful stuff right yeah I mean we
thought a lot about like spam capture
you know Mass C there's all you know
every every like if one secret I'll tell
you if you've invented a new technology
not necessarily the biggest misuse but
but the the first misuse you'll see
scams just Petty scams like you just
just just it's it's like it's like a
thing as old people scamming each other
it's it's this it's this thing as old as
time um and and and it's just every time
you got to deal with it it's almost like
silly to say but it's it's true sort of
and spam in general is a thing as it
gets more and more intelligent it's uh
there a lot of like like I said like
there are a lot of petty criminals in
the world and and and you know it's like
every new technology is like a new way
for petty petty criminals to do
something you know something stupid and
malicious um is there any ideas about
sandboxing it like how difficult is the
sandboxing task yeah we sandbox during
training so for example during training
we didn't expose the model to the
internet um I think that's probably a
bad idea during training because uh you
know the model can be changing its
policy it can be changing what it's
doing and it's having an effect in the
real world um uh you know in in terms of
actually deploying the model right it
kind of depends on the application like
you know sometimes you want the model to
do something in the real world but of
course you can always put guard you can
always put guard rails on the outside
right you can say okay well you know
this model is not going to move data
from my you know this model is not going
to move any files from my computer to or
my web server to anywhere else now when
you talk about sandboxing again when we
get to asl4 none of these precautions
are going to make sense there right
where when you when you talk about asl4
you're then the model is being kind of
you know there's a a theoretical worry
the model could be smart enough to break
it to to kind of break out of any box
and so there we need to think about
mechanistic interpretability about you
know if we're if we're going to have a
Sandbox it would need to be a
mathematically provable sound but you
know that's that's a whole different
world than what we're dealing with with
the models
today yeah the science of building a box
from which asl4 AI system cannot Escape
I I think it's probably not the right
approach I think the right approach
instead of having something you know
unaligned that that like you're trying
to prevent it from escaping I think it's
it's better to just design the model the
right way or have a loop where you you
know you look inside you look inside the
model and you're able to verify property
and that gives you an opportunity to
like iterate and actually get it right
um I think I think containing uh
containing bad models is is is much
worse solution than having good models
let me ask about regulation what's the
role of regulation in keeping AI safe so
for example he described California AI
regulation Bill SB 1047 that was
ultimately vetoed by the governor what
are the pros and cons of this bill
General yes we ended up making some
suggestions to the bill and then some of
those were opted and you know we felt I
think I think quite positively uh uh
quite positively about about the bill uh
by by the end of that um it did still
have some downsides um uh and you know
of course of course it got vetoed um I
think at a high level I think some of
the key ideas behind the bill um are you
know I would say similar to ideas behind
our rsps and I think it's very important
that some jurisdiction whether it's
California or the federal government
Andor other countries and other states
passes some regulation like this and I
can talk through why I think that's so
important so I feel good about our RSP
it's not perfect it needs to be iterated
on a lot but it's been a good forcing
function for getting the company to take
these risks seriously to put them into
product planning to really make them a
central part of work at anthropic and to
make sure that all the thousand people
and it's almost a thousand people now at
anthropic understand that this is one of
the highest priorities of the company if
not the highest priority uh
but one there are some there are still
some companies that don't have RSP like
mechanisms like open aai Google uh did
adopt these mechanisms a couple months
after uh after anthropic did uh but
there are there are other companies out
there that don't have these mechanisms
at all uh and so if some companies adopt
these mechanisms and others don't uh
it's really going to create a situation
where you know some of these dangers
have the property that it doesn't matter
if three out of five of the companies
are being safe if the other two are are
being are being unsafe it creates this
negative externality and and I think the
lack of uniformity is not fair to those
of us who have put a lot of effort into
being very thoughtful about these
procedures the second thing is I don't
think you can trust these companies to
adhere to these voluntary plans in their
own right I like to think that anthropic
will we do everything we can that we
will our our our our RSP is checked by
our long-term benefit trust uh so you
know we do everything we can to to to
adhere to our own RSP um but you know
you hear lots of things about various
companies saying oh they said they would
do they said they would give this much
compute and they didn't they said they
would do this thing and they didn't um
you know I don't I don't think it makes
sense to you know to to to you know
litigate particular things that
companies have done but I I think this
this broad principle that like if
there's nothing watching over them
there's nothing watching over us as an
industry there's no guarantee that we'll
do the right thing and the stakes are
very high uh and so I think it's I think
it's important to have a uniform
standard that that that that that
everyone follows and to make sure that
simply that the industry does what a
majority of the industry has already
said is important and has already said
that they definitely will do right some
people uh you know I think there's there
a class of people who are against
regulation on principle I understand
where that comes from if you go to
Europe and you know you see something
like gdpr you see some of the other
stuff that that that that that they've
done you know some of it's good but but
some of it is really unnecessarily
burdensome and I think it's fair to say
really has slowed really has slowed
Innovation and so I understand where
people are coming from on priors I
understand why people come from start
from that start from that position uh
but but again I think AI is different if
we go to the very serious risks of
autonomy and misuse that that that I
talked about you know just a just a few
minutes ago I think that those are
unusual and they weren't an unusually
strong response uh and so I I think it's
very important again um we need
something that everyone can get behind
uh you know I think one of the issues
with
s1047 uh especially the original version
of it was it it had a bunch of the
structure of rsps but it also had a
bunch of stuff that was either clunky or
that that that just would have created a
bunch of burdens a bunch of Hassle and
might even have missed the Target in
terms of addressing the risks um you
don't really hear about it on Twitter
you just hear about kind of you know
people are people are cheering for any
regulation and then the folks who are
against make up these often quite
intellectually dishonest arguments about
how you know it you know it'll make us
move away from California bill bill
doesn't apply if you're headquartered in
California bill only applies if you do
business in California um or that it
would damage the open source ecosystem
or that it would you know it would cause
cause all of these things I I think
those were mostly nonsense but there are
better arguments against regulation
there's one guy uh Dean ball who's
really you know I think a very scholarly
scholarly IST who who looks at what
happens when a regulation is put in
place and ways that they can kind of get
a life of their own or how they can be
poorly designed and so our interest has
always been we do think there should be
regulation in this space but we want to
be an actor who makes sure that that
that that regulation is something that's
surgical that's targeted at the serious
risks and is something people can
actually comply with because something I
think The Advocates of Regulation don't
understand as well as they could is if
we get something in place that is um
that's poorly targeted that wastes a
bunch of people's time what's going to
happen is people are going to say see
these safety risks there you know this
is this is nonsense I just you know I
just had to hire 10 lawyers to to you
know to fill out all these forms I had
to run all these tests for something
that was clearly not dangerous and after
6 months of that there will be there
will be a ground sweep well and we'll
we'll we'll we'll end up with a durable
consensus against regulation and so the
I I think the the worst enemy of those
who want real accountability is badly
designed regulation um we we need to
actually get it right uh and and this is
if there's one thing I could say to The
Advocates it it would be that I want
them to understand this Dynamic better
and we need to be really careful and we
need to talk to people who actually have
who actually have experience seeing how
regulations play out in practice and and
the people who have seen that understand
to be very careful if this was some
lesser issue I might be against
regulation at all but what what I want
the opponents to understand is is that
the underlying issues are actually
serious they're they're not they're not
something that I or the other companies
are just making up because of regulatory
capture they're not sci-fi fantasies
they're not they're not any of these
things um you know every every time we
have new model every few months we
measure the behavior of these models and
they're getting better and better at
these concerning tasks just as they are
getting better and better at um you know
good valuable economically useful tasks
and so I I I I would just love it if
some of the former you know I think
sb147 was very polarizing I would love
it if some of the most reasonable
opponents and some of the most
reasonable um uh proponents uh would sit
down together and you know I think I
think that you know the different the
different AI companies um you know
anthropic was the the only AI company
that you know felt positively in a very
detailed way I think Elon tweeted uh
tweeted briefly something positive but
you know some of the some of the big
ones like Google open AI meta Microsoft
were were pretty St stly against so I
would really like is if if you know some
of the key stakeholders some of the you
know thoughtful proponents and and some
of the most thoughtful opponents would
sit down and say how do we solve this
problem in in a way that the proponents
feel brings a real reduction in risk and
that the opponents feel that it is not
it is not hampering the the industry or
hampering Innovation any more necessary
than it than than than it needs to and
and I think for for whatever reason that
things got too polarized and those two
groups
didn't get to sit down in the way that
they should uh and and I feel I feel
urgency I really think we need to do
something in
2025 uh uh you know if we get to the end
of 2025 and we've still done nothing
about this then I'm going to be worried
I'm not I'm not worried yet because
again the risks aren't here yet but but
I I I think time is running short yeah
and come up with something surgical like
you said yeah yeah yeah exactly and and
we need to get we need to get away from
this this this intense
pro- safety versus intense
anti-regulatory rhetoric right it's
turned into these these flame Wars on
Twitter and nothing Good's going to come
with that so there's a lot of curiosity
about the different players in the game
one of the uh ogs is open AI you have
had several years of experience at open
AI what's your story and history there
yeah so I was at open AI for uh for
roughly five years uh for the last I
think it was a couple years you know I I
I I I I was uh vice president of
research there um probably myself and
Ilia suger were the ones who you know
really kind of set the set the research
Direction around 2016 or 2017 I first
started to really believe in or at least
confirm my belief in the scaling
hypothesis when when Ilia famously said
to me the thing you need to understand
about these models is they just want to
learn the models just want to learn um
and and and and again sometimes there
are these One S there these one
sentences these Zen cones that you hear
them and you're like ah that that
explains everything that explains like a
thousand things that I've seen and then
and then I I you know ever after I had
this visualization in my head of like
you optimize the models in the right way
you point the models in the right way
they just want to learn they just want
to solve the problem regardless of what
the problem is so get out of their way
basically get out of their way yeah
don't impose your own ideas about how
they should learn and you know this was
the same thing as Rich Sutton put out in
the bitter lesson or G put out in the
scaling hypothesis you know I think
generally the dynamic was you know I got
I got this kind of inspiration from uh
from from from Ilan from others folks
like Alec Radford who did the the
original uh uh
gpt1 uh and then uh ran really hard with
it me me and my collaborators on gpt2
gpt3 RL from Human feedback which was an
attempt to kind of deal with the early
safety and durability things like debate
and amplification heavy on
interpretability so again the
combination of safety plus scaling
probably 2018 2019 2020 those those were
those were kind of the years when myself
and my collaborators probably um you
know mo mo many many of whom became
co-founders of anthropic kind of really
had had had a vision and like and like
drove the direction why'd you leave why'
you decid to leave yeah so look I'm
gonna put things this way and I you know
I think it I think it ties to the to to
the race to the top right which is you
know in my time at open AI what I come
come to see as I'd come to appreciate
the scaling hypothesis and as I'd come
to appreciate kind of the importance of
safety along with the scaling hypothesis
the first one I think you know open AI
was was getting was getting on board
with um the second one in a way had
always been part of of open ai's
messaging um but uh you know over over
many years of of the time the time that
I spent there I think I had a particular
vision of how these how we should handle
these things how we should be brought
out in the world the kind of principles
that the organization should have and
look I mean there were like many many
discussions about like you know should
the or do should the company do this
should the company do that like there's
a bunch of misinformation out there
people say like we left because we
didn't like the deal with Microsoft
false although you know there was like a
lot of discussion a lot of questions
about exactly how we do the deal with
Microsoft um we left because we didn't
like commercialization that's not true
we built gbd3 which was the model that
was commercialized I was involved in
commercialization it's it's more again
about how do you do it like Civilization
is going down this path to very powerful
AI what's the way to do it that is
cautious
straightforward honest um that build
trust in the organization and in
individuals how do we get from here to
there and how do we have a real vision
for how to get it right how can safety
not just be something we say because it
helps with recruiting um and you know I
think I think at the end of the day um
if you have a vision for that forget
about anyone else's Vision I don't want
to talk about anyone else's Vision if
you have a vision for how to do it you
should go off and you should do that
Vision it is incredibly unproductive to
try and argue with someone else's Vision
you might think they're not doing it the
right way you might think they're
they're they're dishonest who knows
maybe you're right maybe you're not um
uh but uh what what you should do is you
should take some people you trust and
you should go off together and you
should make your vision happen and if
your vision is compelling if you can
make it appeal to people some you know
some combination of ethically you know
in the market uh you know if if you can
if you can make a company that's a place
people want to join uh that you know
engages in practices that people think
are are reasonable while managing to
maintain its position in the ecosystem
at the same time if you do that people
will copy it um and the fact that you
were doing it especially the fact that
you're doing it better than they are um
causes them to change their behavior in
a much more compelling way than if
they're your boss and you're arguing
with them I just I don't know how to be
any more specific about it than that but
I think it's generally very unproductive
to try and get someone else's Vision to
look like your vision um it's much more
productive to go off and do a clean
experiment and say this is our vision
this is how this is this is how we're
going to do things your choice is you
can you can ignore us you can reject
what we're doing or you can you can
start to become more like us and
imitation is the sincerest form of
flattery um and you know that that that
plays out in the behavior of customers
that PS out in the behavior of the
public that plays out in the behavior of
where people choose to work uh and again
again at the end it's it's not about one
company winning or another company
winning if if we or another company are
engaging in some practice that you know
people people find genuinely appealing
and I want it to be in substance not
just not just in appearance um and you
know I think I think researchers are
sophisticated and they look at substance
uh and then other companies start
copying that practice and they win
because they copied that practice that's
great that's success that's like the
race to the top it doesn't matter who
wins in the end as long as everyone is
copying everyone else's good practices
right one way I think of it is like the
thing we're all afraid of is a race the
bottom right in the race to the bottom
doesn't matter who wins because we all
lose right like you know in the most
extreme world we we make this autonomous
AI that you know the robots enslave us
or whatever right I mean that's half
joking but you know that that is the
most extreme uh uh thing thing that
could happen then then it doesn't matter
which company was ahead um if instead
you create a race to the top where
people are competing to engage in good
in good practices uh then you know at at
the end of the day you know it doesn't
matter who who ends up who ends up
winning doesn't even matter who who
started the race to the top the point
isn't to be virtuous the point is to get
the system into a better equilibrium
than it was before and and individual
companies can play some role in doing
this individual companies can can you
know can help to start it can help to
accelerate it and frankly I think
individuals at other companies have have
done this as well right the individuals
that when we put out an RSP react by
pushing harder to to to get something
similar done get something similar done
at at at other companies sometimes other
companies do something that's like we're
like oh it's a good practice we think we
think that's good we should adopt it too
the only difference is you know I think
I think we are um we try to be more
forward leaning we try and adopt more of
these practices first and adopt them
more quickly when others when others
invent them but I think this Dynamic is
what we should be pointing at and that I
think I think it abstracts away the
question of you know which company's
winning who trusts who I I think all
these all these questions of drama are
are profoundly uninteresting and and the
the thing that matters is the ecosystem
that we all operate in and how to make
that ecosystem better because that
constrains all the players and so
anthropic is this kind of clean
experiment built on a foundation of like
what concretely AI safety should look
like we look I'm sure we've made plenty
of mistakes along the way the perfect
organization doesn't exist it has to
deal with the the imperfection of a
thousand employees it has to deal deal
with the imperfection of our leaders
including me it has to deal with the
imperfection of the people we've put
we've put to you know to oversee the
imperfection of the of the leaders like
the like the board and the long-term
benefit trust it's it's all it's all a
set of imperfect people trying to aim
imperfectly at some ideal that will
never perfectly be achieved um that's
what you sign up for that's what it will
always be but uh uh imperfect doesn't
mean you just give up there's better and
there's worse and hopefully hopefully we
can begin to build we can do well enough
that we can begin to build some
practices that the whole industry
engages in and then you know my guess is
that M multiple of these companies will
be successful anthropic will be
successful these other companies like
ones I've been at the past will also be
successful and some will be more
successful than others that's less
important than again that we we align
the incentives of the industry and that
happens partly through the race to the
top partly through things like RSP
partly through again selected surgical
regulation you said Talent density beats
Talent
Mass so can you explain that can you
expand on it can you just talk about
what it takes to build a great team of
AI researchers and Engineers this is one
of these statements that's like more
true every every every month every month
I see this statement as more true than I
did the month before so if I were to do
a thought experiment let's say you have
a team of 100 people that are super
smart motivated and aligned with the
mission and that's your company or you
can have a team of a thousand people
where 200 people are super smart super
aligned with the mission and then uh
like and then like 800 people are let's
just say you pick 800 like random random
big Tech employees which would you
rather have right the talent mass is
greater in in the group of uh in the
group of a thousand people right you
have you have even even a larger number
of incredibly talented incredibly
aligned incredibly smart people um uh
but but the the issue is just that
if every time someone super talented
looks around they see someone else super
talented and super dedicated that sets
the tone for everything right that sets
the tone for everyone is super inspired
to work at the same place everyone
trusts everyone else if you have a
thousand or 10,000 uh people and and
things have really regressed right you
are not able to do selection and you're
choosing random people what happens is
then you need to put a lot of proc CES
and a lot of guard rails in place um
just because people don't fully trust
each other you have to adjudicate
political battles like there are so many
things that slow down the org's ability
to operate and so we're nearly a
thousand people and you know we've we've
we've tried to make it so that as large
a fraction of those thousand people as
possible are like super talented super
skilled it's one of the reasons we've
we've slowed down hiring a lot in the
last few months We Grew From 300 to 800
I believe I think in the first seven
eight months of the year and now we've
slowed down we're at like you know last
three months we went from 800 to 900 950
something like that don't quote me on
the exact numbers but I think there's an
inflection point around a thousand and
we want to be much more careful how how
we how we grow uh early on and and now
as well you know we've hired a lot of
physicists um you know theoretical
physicists can learn things really fast
um uh even even more recently as we've
continued to hire that you know we've
really had a high bar for on both the
research side and the software
engineering side have hired a lot of
senior people including folks who used
to be at other at other companies in
this space and we we've just continued
to be very selective it's very easy to
go go from 100 to a th000 a th000 to
10,000 without paying attention to
making sure everyone has a unified
purpose it's so powerful if your company
consists of a lot of different feif that
all want to do their own thing they're
all optimizing for their own thing um uh
it's very hard to get anything done but
if everyone sees the broader purpose of
the company if there's trust and there's
dedication to doing the right thing that
is a superpower that in itself I think
can overcome almost every other
disadvantage and you know it's to Steve
Jobs a players a players want to look
around and see other a players is
another way of of saying I don't know
what that is about human nature but it
is demotivating to see people who are
not obsessively driving towards a
singular Mission and it is on the flip
side of that super motivating to see
that it's interesting uh what's it take
to be a great AI researcher or engineer
from everything you've seen from working
with so many amazing people yeah um I
think the number one quality especially
on the research side but really both is
open-mindedness sounds easy to be
open-minded right you're just like oh
I'm open to anything um but you know if
I if I think about my own early history
in the scaling hypothesis um I was
seeing the same data others were seeing
I don't think I was like a better
programmer or better at coming up with
research ideas than any of the hundreds
of people that I worked with um in some
ways in some ways I was worse um uh you
know like i' I've never like you know
precise programming of like you know
finding the bug writing the GPU kernels
like I could point you to a 100 people
here who are better who are better at
that than I am um but but the the thing
that that that I think I did have that
was different was that I was just
willing to look at something with new
eyes right people said oh you know we
don't have the right algorithms yet we
haven't come up with the right the right
way to do things and I was just like uh
I don't know like you know this neural
net has like 30 billion 30 million
parameters like what if we gave it 50
million instead like let's plot some
graphs like that that basic scientific
mindset of like oh man like I I I just I
just like I you know I see some variable
that I could change like what happens
when it changes like let's let's try
these different things and like create a
graph for even this this was like the
simplest thing in the world right change
the number of you know this wasn't like
PhD level experimental design this was
like this was like simple and stupid
like anyone could have done this if you
if you just told them that that that it
was important it's also not hard to
understand you didn't need to be
brilliant to come up with this um but
you put the two things together and you
know some tiny number of people some
singled digigit number of people have
have driven forward the whole field by
realizing this uh and and it's you know
it's often like that if you look back at
the Discover you know the discoveries in
in in history they're they're often like
that and so this this open-mindedness
and this willingness to see with new
eyes that often comes from being newer
to the field often experience is a
disadvantage for this that is the most
important thing it's very hard to look
for and test for but I think I think
it's the most important thing because
when you when you find something some
really new way of thinking thinking
about things when you have the
initiative to do that it's absolutely
transformative and also be able to do
kind of Rapid experimentation and in the
face of that be open-minded and curious
and looking at the data from just these
fresh eyes and see what is that actually
saying that applies in uh mechanistic
interpretability it's another example of
this like some of the early work in
mechanistic interpretability so simple
it's it's just no one thought to care
about this question before you said what
it takes to be a great AI researcher can
we rewind the clock back what what
advice would you give to people
interested in AI they're young looking
forward how can I make an impact on the
world I think my number one piece of
advice is to just start playing with the
models um this was actually I I I worry
a little this seems like obvious advice
now I think three years ago it wasn't
obvious and people started by oh let me
read the latest reinforcement learning
paper let me you know let me let me kind
of um no I mean that was really the that
was really the the and I mean you should
do that as well but uh now you know with
wider availability of models and apis
people are doing this more but I think I
think just experiential knowledge um
these models are new artifacts that no
one really understands um and so getting
experience playing with them I would
also say again in line with the like do
something new think in some new
Direction like there are all these
things that haven't been explored like
for example mechanistic interpretability
is still very new it's probably better
to work on that than it is to work on
new model architectures because it's you
know it's more popular than it was
before there are probably like a hundred
people working on it but there aren't
like 10,000 people working on it and
it's it's just this just this this
fertile area for study like like you
know it's there's there's so much like
low hangen fruit you can just walk by
and you know you can just walk by and
you can pick things um and and the the
the only reason for whatever reason
people aren't people aren't interested
in it enough I think there are some
things around long long Horizon learning
and long Horizon tasks where there's a
lot to be done I think evaluations are
still we're still very early in our
ability to study evaluations
particularly for dynamic systems acting
in the world I think there's some stuff
around
multi-agent um skate where the puck is
going is my is my advice and you don't
have to be brilliant to think of it like
all the things that are going to be
exciting in 5 years like in in people
even mention them as like you know
conventional wisdom but like it's it's
just somehow there's this barrier that
people don't people don't double down as
much as they could or they're afraid to
do something that's not the popular
thing I don't know why it happens but
like getting over that barrier is the
that's the my number one piece of advice
let's talk if we could a bit about
posttraining yeah so it uh seems that
the modern posttraining
recipe has uh a little bit of everything
so supervised fine tuning
rhf uh the the the Constitutional AI
with RL a if best acronym it's again
that naming
thing uh and then synthetic data seems
like a lot of synthetic data or at least
trying to figure out ways to have high
quality synthetic data so what's the uh
if this is a secret sauce that makes
anthropic claw so uh incredible what how
how much of the magic is in the
pre-training how much much of is in the
post training yeah um I mean so first of
all we're not perfectly able to measure
that ourselves um uh you know when you
see some some great character ability
sometimes it's hard to tell whether it
came from pre-training or post-training
uh we developed ways to try and
distinguish between those two but
they're not perfect you know the second
thing I would say is you know it's when
there is an advantage and I think we've
been pretty good at in general in
general at RL Perhaps Perhaps the best
although although I don't know because I
don't see what goes on inside other
companies uh
usually it isn't oh my God we have this
secret magic method that others don't
have right usually it's like well you
know we got better at the infrastructure
so we could run it for longer or you
know we were able to get higher quality
data or we were able to filter our data
better or we able to you know combine
these methods and practice it's it's
usually some boring matter of matter of
kind of uh practice and tradecraft um so
you know when I think about how to do
something special in terms of how we
train these models both pre-training but
even more so posttraining um you know I
I I really think of it a little more
again as like designing airplanes or
cars like you know it's not just like oh
man I have the BL blueprint like maybe
that makes you make the next airplane
but like there's some there's some
cultural tradecraft of how we think
about the design process that I think is
more important than than you know than
than any particular Gizmo were able to
invent okay well about let me ask you
about specific techniques so first on
rhf what do you think think just zooming
out intuition almost philosophy why do
you think rhf works so well if I go back
to like the scaling hypothesis one of
the ways to skate the scaling hypothesis
is if you train for x and you throw
enough compute at it um then you get X
and and so rlf is good at doing what
humans want the model to do or at least
um to State it more precisely doing what
humans who look at the model for a brief
period of time and consider different
possible responses what prefer as the
response uh which is not perfect from
both a safety and capabilities
perspective in that humans are are often
not able to perfectly identify what the
model wants and what humans want in the
moment may not be what they want in the
long term so there's there's a lot of
subtlety there but the models are good
at uh you know producing what the humans
in some shallow sense want uh and it
actually turns out that you don't even
have to throw that much compute at it
because of another thing which is this
this thing about a strong pre-trained
model being halfway to anywhere uh uh uh
so once you have the pre-trained model
you have all the representations you
need to to get the model uh to get the
model where you where you want it to go
so do you think
rhf makes the model smarter or just
appears smarter to the humans I don't
think it makes the model smarter I don't
think it just makes the model appear
smarter it's like
rhf like Bridges the gap between the
human and the model right I could have
something really smart that like can't
communicate at all right we all know
people like this um people who are
really smart but that you know can't
understand what they're saying um uh so
I think I think rhf just bridges that
Gap um I I think it's not it's not the
only kind of RL we do it's not the only
kind of RL that will happen in the
future I think RL has the potential to
make models smarter to make them reason
better to make them operate better to
make them develop new skills even and
perhaps that could be done you know even
in some cases with human feedback but
the kind of rhf we we do today mostly
doesn't do that yet although we're very
quickly starting to be able to but it it
appears to sort of increase if you look
at the metric of helpfulness it
increases that it also increases what
was this this word in Leopold's essay un
hobbling where basically the models are
hobbled and then you do various
trainings to them to un hobble them so I
I know I like that word because it's
like a rare word but so so I think rhf
un hobbles the models in some ways
um and then there are other ways where M
hasn't yet been un hobbled and and you
know needs to needs to un hobble if you
can say in terms of cost is pre-training
the most expensive thing or is
post-training creep up to that at the
present moment it is still the case that
uh pre-training is the majority of the
cost I don't know what to expect in the
future but I could certainly anticipate
a future where post-training is the
majority of the cost in that future you
anticipate would it be the humans or the
AI That's the costly thing for the Post
training I I I I I don't think you can
scale up humans enough to get high
quality any any kind of method that
relies on humans and uses a large amount
of compute it's going to have to rely on
some scaled supervision method like uh
uh like um it you know debate or
iterated amplification or something like
that so on
that super interesting um set of ideas
around constitutional AI can describe
what it is as first detailed in December
2022 paper and uh and be on that what is
it yes so this was from two years ago
the basic idea is so we describe what
rhf is you have uh you have a model and
uh it you know spits out two you know
like you just sample from it twice it
spits out two possible responses and
you're like human which response you
like better or another variant of it is
rate this response on a scale of 1 to
seven so that's hard because you need to
scale up human interaction and uh it's
very implicit right I don't have a sense
of what I what I want the model to do I
just have a sense of like what this
average of a thousand humans wants the
model to do so two ideas one is could
the AI system itself decide which uh
which response is better right could you
show the AI system these two responses
and and ask which which which response
is better and then second well what
Criterion should the AI use and so then
there's this idea because you have a
single document a constitution if you
will that says these are the principles
the model should be using to to respond
and the AI system reads those um it
reads those principles as well as
reading the environment and the response
and it says well how good did the AI
model do um it's basically a form of
self-play you you're kind of training
the model against itself and so the AI
gives the response and then you feed
that back into What's called the
preference model which in turn feeds the
model to make it better um so you have
this triangle of like the AI the
preference model and the Improvement of
the AI itself and we should say that in
the Constitution the set of principles
are like human interpretable they're
like yeah yeah it's something both the
human and the AI system can read so it
has this nice this nice kind of
translatability or symmetry um you know
in in practice we both use a model
Constitution and we use rhf and we use
some of these other methods so it's it's
turned into one tool in a in a toolkit
that both reduces the need for rhf and
increases the value we get from um from
from using each data point of R lhf um
it also interacts in interesting ways
with kind of future reasoning type RL
methods so um it's it's one tool in the
toolkit but but I I think it is a very
important tool well it's a compelling
one to us humans you know thinking about
the founding fathers and the founding of
the United
States the natural question is who and
how do you think it gets to define the
constitution the the set of principles
in the Constitution yeah so I'll give
like a practical um answer and a more
abstract answer I think the Practical
answer is like look in practice models
get used by all kinds of different like
customers right and and so uh you can
have this idea where you know the model
can can have specialized rules or
principles you know we fine-tune
versions of models implicitly we've
talked about doing it explicitly having
having special principles that people
can can build into the models um uh so
from a practical perspective the answer
can be very different from different
people uh you know customers service
agent uh you know behaves very
differently from a lawyer and obeys
different principles um but I think at
the base of it there are specific
principles that the models uh you know
have to obey I think a lot of them are
things that people would agree with
everyone agrees that you know we don't
you know we don't want models to present
these cbrn risks um I think we can go a
little further and agree with some basic
principles of democracy and the rule of
law beyond that it gets you know very
uncertain and and there our goal is
generally for the models to be more
neutral to not espouse a particular
point of view and you know more just be
kind of like wise uh agents or advisers
that will help you think things through
and will you know present present
possible considerations but you know
don't express you know stronger specific
opinions open AI released a model spec
where it kind of clearly concretely
defines some of the goals of the model
and specific examples like AB how the
model should behave do you find that
interesting by the way I should mention
the I believe the brilliant John
Schulman was a part of that he's now an
anthropic uh do you think this is a
useful Direction might anthropic release
a model spec as well yeah so I think
that's a pretty useful direction again
it has a lot in common with uh
constitutional AI so again another
example of like a race to the top right
we have something that's like we think
you know a better and more responsible
way of doing things um it's also a
competitive advantage um then uh others
kind of you know discover that it has
advantages and then start to do that
thing uh we then no longer have the
competitive Advantage but it's good from
the perspective that now everyone has
adopted a positive practice that others
were not adopting and so our response to
that as well looks like we need a new
competitive advantage in order to keep
driving this race upwards um so that's
that's how I generally feel about that I
also think every implementation of these
things is different so you know there
were some things in the model spec that
were not in constitutional Ai and so you
know we you know we can always we can
always adopt those things or you know at
least learn from them um so again I
think this is an example of like the
positive Dynamic that uh that that that
I that that I think we should all want
the field to have let's talk about the
incredible ESS Machines of love and
grace I recommend everybody read it it's
a long one it is rather long yeah it's
really refreshing to read concrete ideas
about what a positive future looks like
and you took sort of a bold stance
because like it's very possible you
might be wrong on the dates or specific
applications yeah I'm fully expecting to
you know to definitely be wrong about
all the details I might be be just
spectacularly wrong about the whole
thing and people will you know will
laugh at me for years um uh that's
that's how that's that's just how the
future works so you provided a bunch of
concrete positive impacts of AI and how
you know exactly a super intelligent AI
might accelerate the rate of
breakthroughs in for example biology and
chemistry that would then lead to things
like we cure most cancers prevent all
infectious disease double the human
lifespan and so on so let's talk about
this essay first can you give a high
level vision of this essay and um what
key takeaways that people should have
yeah I have spent a lot of time and
anthropic has spent a lot of effort on
like you know how do we address the
risks of AI right how do we think about
those risks like we're trying to do a
race to the top you know that requires
us to build all these capabilities and
the abilities are cool but you know you
know we're we're we're like a big part
of what we're trying to do is like is
like address the risks and the
justification for that is like well you
know all these positive things you know
the the market is this very healthy
organism right it's going to produce all
the positive things the risks I don't
know we might mitigate them we might not
and so we can have more impact by trying
to mitigate the risks but I noticed that
one flaw in that way of thinking and
it's if not a change in how seriously I
take the risks it's it's maybe a change
in how I talk about them um is that you
know no matter how kind of logical or
rational that line of reasoning that I
just gave might be um if if you kind of
only talk about risks your brain only
thinks about risks and and so I think
it's actually very important to
understand what if things do go well and
the whole reason we're trying to prevent
these risks is not because we're afraid
of Technology not because we want to
slow it down it's it's it's
because if we can get to the other side
of these risks right if we can run the
gauntlet successfully um to you know to
to put it in Stark terms then then on
the other side of the gauntlet are all
these great things and these things are
worth fighting for and these things can
really inspire people and I think I
imagine because look you have all these
investors all these VCS all these AI
companies talking about all the positive
benefits of AI but as you point out it's
it's it's weird there's actually a dir
of really getting specific about it
there's a lot of like random people on
Twitter like posting these kind of like
gleaming cities and this this just kind
of like Vibe of like grind accelerate
harder like kick out the D you know it's
it's just this very this very like
aggressive ideological but then you're
like well what are you what what what
what what are you actually excited about
um and so and so I figured that you know
I think it would be interesting and
valuable for someone who's actually
coming from the risk side to to try and
and to try and really make a try at at
explaining explaining explaining what
the benefits are um both because I think
it's something we can all get behind and
I want people to understand I want them
to really understand that this isn't
this isn't doomers versus
accelerationists um this this
is that if you have a true understanding
of of where things are going with with
AI and maybe that's the more important
axis AI is moving fast versus AI is not
moving fast then you really appreciate
the benefits and you you you you really
you want Humanity our civilization to
seize those benefits but you also get
very serious about anything that could
derail them so I think the starting
point is to talk about what this
powerful AI which is the term you like
to use uh most of the world uses AGI but
you don't like the term because it's uh
basically has too much baggage has
become meaningless it's like we're stuck
with the terms like maybe we're stuck
with the terms and my efforts to change
them are futile it's ADM I'll tell you
what else I don't this is like a
pointless semantic point but I I I I
keep talking about it public so I'm just
I'm just going to do it once more um uh
I I think it's it's a little like like
let's say it was like 1995 and Mor's law
is making the computers faster and like
for some reason there there there there
had been this like verbal tick that like
everyone was like well someday we're
going to have like super super computers
and like supercomputers are going to be
able to do all these things that like
you know once we have supercomputers
we'll be able to like sequence the Geno
and we'll be able to do other things and
so and so like one it's true the
computers are getting faster and as they
get faster they're going to be able to
do all these great things but there's
like there's no discret point at which
you had a supercomputer and previous
computers were not to like supercomputer
is a term we use but like it's a vague
term to just describe like computers
that are faster than what we have today
um there's no point at which you pass a
threshold and you're like oh my God
we're doing a totally new type of
computation and new and and so I feel
that way about AGI like there's just a
smooth exponential and like if if by AGI
you mean like like AI is getting better
and better and like gradually it's going
to do more and more of what humans do
until it's going to be smarter than
humans and then it's going to get
smarter even from there then then yes I
believe in AGI if but if if if AGI is
some discreet or separate thing which is
the way people often talk about it then
it's it's kind of a meaningless buzz
word yeah I me to me it's just sort of a
IC form of a powerful AI exactly how you
define it I mean you define it very
nicely so on the intelligence axis it's
just on pure intelligence it's smarter
than a Nobel Prize winner as you
describe across most relevant
disciplines so okay that's just
intelligence so it's uh both in
creativity and be able to generate new
ideas all that kind of stuff in every
discipline Nobel Prize winner okay in
their
prime it can use every modality it so uh
that's kind of self-explanatory but just
operate across all the modalities of the
world uh it can go off for many hours
days and weeks to do tasks and do its
own sort of detailed planning and only
ask you help when it's needed uh it can
use this is actually kind of interesting
I think in the essay you said I mean
again it's a bet that it's not going to
be embodied but it can control embodied
tools so it can control tools robots
Laboratory equipment the resource used
to train it can then be repurposed to
run millions of copies of it and each of
those copies would be independent that
can do their own independent work so you
can do the cloning of the intelligence
system yeah yeah I mean you you might
imagine from outside the field that like
there's only one of these right that
like you made it you've only made one
but the truth is that like the scale up
is very quick like we we do this today
we make a model and then we deploy
thousands maybe tens of thousands of
instances of it I think by the time you
know certainly within 2 to 3 years
whether we have these superp powerful
AIS or not clusters are going to get to
the size where where you'll be able to
deploy millions of these and they'll be
you know faster than humans and so if
your picture is oh we'll have one and
it'll take a while to make them my point
there was no actually you have millions
of them right away and in general they
can learn and
act uh 10 to 100 times faster than
humans so that's a really nice
definition of powerful AI okay so that
but you also write that clearly such an
entity would be cap capable of solving
very difficult problems very fast but it
is not trivial to figure out how fast
two extreme positions both seem false to
me so the singularity is on the one
extreme and the opposite On The Other
Extreme can you describe each of the
extremes yeah why so yeah let's let's
describe the extreme so like one one
extreme would be well look um you know
uh if we look at kind of evolutionary
history like there was this big
acceleration where you know for hundreds
of thousands of years we just had like
you know single cell organisms and then
we had mammals and then we had apes and
then that quickly turned to humans
humans quickly built industrial
civilization and so this is going to
keep speeding up and there's no cealing
at the human level once models get much
much smarter than humans they'll get
really good at building the next models
and you know if you write down like a
simple differential equation like this
is an exponential and so what's what's
going to happen is that uh models will
build faster models models will build
faster models and those models will
build you know Nano that can like take
over the world and produce much more
energy than you could produce otherwise
and and so if you just kind of like
solve this abstract differential
equation then like 5 days after we you
know we build the first AI That's more
powerful than humans then then uh you
know like the world will be filled with
these AIS and every possible technology
that could be invented like will be
invented um I'm caricaturing this a
little bit um uh but I you know I think
that's one extreme and the reason that I
think that's not the case is is that one
I think they just neglect like the laws
of physics like it's only possible to do
things so fast in the physical world
like some of those Loops go through you
know producing faster Hardware um uh
takes a long time to produce faster
Hardware things take a long time there's
this issue of complexity like I think no
matter how smart you are like you know
people talk about oh we can make models
the biological systems it'll do
everything the biological systems look I
think computational modeling can do a
lot I did a lot of computational
modeling when I worked in biology but
like
just there are a lot of things that you
can't predict how they're you know
they're they're complex enough that like
just iterating just running the
experiment is going to beat any modeling
no matter how smart the system doing the
modeling is oh even if it's not
interacting with the physical world just
the modeling is going to be hard yeah I
think well the modeling is going to be
hard and getting the model to to to to
match the physical world is going to be
all right so he does have to intera the
physical world to verify but it's just
you know you just look at even the
simplest problems like I you know I
think I talk about like you know the
three body problem or simple chaotic
prediction like you know or or like
predicting the economy it's really hard
to predict the economy two years out
like maybe the case is like you know
normal you know humans can predict
what's going to happen in the economy in
the next quarter although they can't
really do that maybe a maybe a AI system
that's you know a zillion times smarter
can only predict it out a year or
something instead of instead of a you
know you have the these kind of
exponential increase in computer
intelligence for linear increase in in
in ability to predict same with again
like you know biological molecules
molecules interacting you don't know
what's going to happen when you perturb
a when you perturb a complex system you
can find simple Parts in it if you're
smarter you're better at finding these
simple parts and then I think human
institutions human institutions are just
are are really difficult like it's you
know it's it's been hard to get people I
won't give specific examples but it's
been hard to get people to adopt even
the technologies that we've developed
even ones where the case for their
efficacy is very very strong um you know
people have concerns they think things
are conspiracy theories like it's it's
just been it's been very difficult it's
also been very difficult to get you know
very simple things through the
regulatory system right I think you know
and you know I I don't want to just
spage anyone who you know you know work
Works in regulator regulatory systems of
any technology there are hard trade-offs
they have to deal with they have to save
lives but but the system as a whole I
think makes some obvious tradeoffs that
are very far from maximizing human
welfare and so if we bring AI systems
into this you
know into these human systems often the
level of intelligence may just not be
the limiting factor right it it it just
may be that it takes a long time to do
something now if the AI system uh
circumvented all governments if it just
said I'm dictator of the world and I'm
going to do whatever some of these
things it could do again the things
having to do with complexity I I I still
think a lot of things would take a while
I don't think it helps that the AI
systems can produce a lot of energy or
go to the moon like some people in
comments responded to the essay saying
the AI system can produce a lot of
energy and smarter AI systems that's
missing the point that kind of cycle
doesn't solve the key problems that I'm
talking about here um so I think I think
a bunch of people missed the point there
but even if it were completely on
aligned and you know could get around
all these human obstacles it would have
trouble but again if you want this to be
an AI system that doesn't take over the
world that doesn't destroy Humanity then
then basically you know it's it's it's
going to need to follow basic human laws
right where you know if if we want to
have an actually good world like we're
going to have to have an AI system that
that interacts with humans not one that
kind of creates its own legal system or
disregards all the laws or all of that
so as inefficient as these processes are
you know we're going to have to deal
with them because there there needs to
be some popular and Democratic
legitimacy in how these systems are
rolled out we can't have a small group
of people who are developing these
systems say this is what's best for
everyone right I think it's wrong and I
think in practice is not going to work
anyway so you put all those things
together and you know we're not we're
not g to we're not going to you know
change the world and upload everyone in
five minutes uh I I I just I don't think
it I A A I don't think it's going to
happen and be to some in you know to the
extent that it could happen it's it's
not the way to lead to a good world so
that's on one side on the other side
there's another set of perspectives
which I have actually in some ways more
sympathy for which is look we've seen
big productivity increases before right
you know economists are familiar with
studying the productivity increases that
came from the computer Revolution and
internet Revolution and generally those
productivity increases were
underwhelming they were less than you
than you might imagine um there was a
quote from Robert solo you see the
computer Revolution everywhere except
the productivity statistics so why is
this the case people point to the
structure of firms the structure of
Enterprises how um uh you know how slow
it's been to roll out our existing
technology to very poor parts of the
world which I talk about in the essay
right how do we get these Technologies
to the poorest parts of the world that
are behind on cell phone technology
computers medicine let alone you know
new fangled AI that hasn't been invented
yet um so you could have a perspective
that's like well this is amazing
technically but it's all a nothing burer
um uh you know I think um Tyler Cowan
who who wrote something response to my
essay has that perspective I think he
thinks the radical change will happen
eventually but he thinks it'll take 50
or 100 years and and you could have even
more static perspectives on the whole
thing I think there's some truth to it I
think the time scale is just is just too
long um and and I can see it I can
actually see both sides with today's AI
so uh you know a lot of our customers
are large Enterprises who are used to
doing things a certain way um I've also
seen it in talking to governments right
those are those are prototypical you
know institutions entities that are slow
to change uh but the dynamic I see over
and over again is yes it takes a long
time to move the ship yes there's a lot
of resistance and lack of understanding
but the thing that makes me feel that
progress will in the end happen
moderately fast not incredibly fast but
moderately fast is that you talk to what
I find is I find over and over again
again in large companies even in
governments um which have been actually
surprisingly forward leaning uh you find
two things that move things forward one
you find a small fraction of people
within a company within a government who
really see the big picture who see the
whole scaling hypothesis who understand
where AI is going or at least understand
where it's going within their industry
and there are a few people like that
within the current within the current US
government who really see the whole
picture and and those people see that
this is the most important thing in the
world until they agitate for it and the
thing they they alone are not enough to
succeed because they are a small set of
people within a large organization
but as the technology starts to roll out
as it succeeds in some places in the
folks who are most willing to adopt it
the Spectre of competition gives them a
wind at their backs because they can
point within their large organization
they can say look these other guys are
doing this right you know One bank can
say look this new fangled hedge fund is
doing this thing they're going to eat
our lunch in the US we can say we're
afraid China's going to get there before
before we are uh and that combination
the Spectre of competition plus a few
Visionaries Within These you know within
these the organizations that in many
ways are are sclerotic you put those two
things together and it actually makes
something happen I mean it's interesting
it's a balanced fight between the two
because inertia is very powerful but but
but eventually over enough time the
Innovative approach breaks through um
and I've seen that happen I've seen the
Arc of that over and over again and it's
like the the barriers are there the the
barriers to progress the complexity not
knowing how to use the model or how to
deploy them are there and and for a bit
it seems like they're going to last
forever like change doesn't happen but
then eventually change happens and
always comes from a few people I felt
the same way when I was an advocate of
the scaling hypothesis within the AI
field itself and others didn't get it it
felt like no one would ever get it it
felt like then it felt like we had a
secret almost no one ever had and then a
couple years later everyone has the
secret and so I think that's how it's
going to go with deployment to AI in the
world it's going to the the barriers are
going to fall apart gradually and then
all at once and so I think this is going
to be more and this is just an instinct
I could I could easily see how I'm wrong
I think it's going to be more like 10
five or 10 years as I say in the essay
then it's going to be 50 or 100 years I
also think it's going to be five or 10
years
more than it's going to be you know five
or 10 hours uh uh because I've just I've
just seen how human systems work and I
think a lot of these people who write
down the differential equations who say
AI is going to make more powerful AI who
can't understand how it could possibly
be the case that these things won't
won't change so fast I think they don't
understand these things so what to use
the timeline to where we achieve
AGI AKA powerful AI AKA super useful AI
I'm start calling it that it's a debate
it's a debate about
naming um you know unpure intelligence
you can smarter than a Nobel Prize
winner in every relevant discipline and
all the things we've said modality you
can go and do stuff on its own for days
weeks and do biology experiments uh on
its own in one you know what let's just
stick to biology because yeah I you you
sold me on the whole biology and health
section That's so exciting from um from
a just I was getting giddy from a
scientific perspective it made me want
to be a biologist it's almost it's it's
so no no that this was the feeling I had
when I was writing it that it's it's
like this would be such a beautiful
future if we can if we can just if we
can just make it happen right if we can
just get the get the landmines out of
the way and and and and make it happen
there's there's so much there's so much
Beauty and and and and and elegance and
moral force behind it if if we can if we
can just and it's something we should
all be able to agree on right like as
much as we fight about about all these
political questions is is this something
that could actually bring us together um
but you were asking when when will we
get this when when do you think what's
just put numbers on so you know this
this is of course the thing I've been
grappling with for many years and I'm
not I'm not at all confident every time
if I say 2026 or 2027 there will be like
a zillion like people on Twitter who
will be like he icoo said 2026 2020 and
it'll be repeated for like the next two
years that like this is definitely when
I think it's going to happen um so who
whoever's exerting these clips will will
we we'll we'll crop out the thing I just
said and and only say the thing I'm
about to say um but I'll just say it
anyway um have so so uh if you
extrapolate the curves that we've had so
far right if if you say well I don't
know we're starting to get to like PhD
level and and last year we were at um uh
undergraduate level in the year before
we were at like the level of a high
school student again you can you can
quibble with at what tasks and for what
we're still missing modalities but those
are being added like computer use was
added like image in was added like image
generation has been added if you just
kind of like and this is totally
unscientific but if you just kind of
like eyeball the rate at which these
capabilities are increasing it does make
you think that we'll get there by 2026
or 2027 again lots of things could
derail it we could run out of data you
know we might not be able to scale
clusters as much as we want like you
know maybe Taiwan gets blown up or
something and you know then we can't
produce as many gpus as we want so there
there are all kinds of things that could
could derail the whole process so I
don't fully believe the straight line
extrapolation but if you believe the
straight line extrapolation you'll you
we'll get there in 2026 or 2027 I think
the most likely is that there's some
mild delay relative to that um
I don't know what that delay is but I
think it could happen on schedule I
think there could be a mild delay I
think there are still worlds where it
doesn't happen in in a hundred years
those world the number of those worlds
is rapidly decreasing we are rapidly
running out of truly convincing Brockers
truly compelling reasons why this will
not happen in the next few years there
were a lot more in 2020 um although my
my guest my hunch at that time was that
we will make it through all those
blockers so sitting as someone who has
seen most of the blockers cleared out of
the way I kind of suspect my hunch my
suspicion is that the rest of them will
not block us uh but you know look look
at look at the end of the day like I
don't want to represent this as a
scientific prediction people call them
scaling laws that's a misnomer like Mo's
law is is is a misnomer Moors laws
scaling laws they're not laws of the
universe they're empirical regularities
I am going to bet in favor of them
continuing but I'm not certain of that
so you extensively describe sort of the
compressed 21st century how AGI will
help
uh set forth a chain of breakthroughs in
biology and medicine that help us in all
these kinds of ways that I mentioned so
how do you think what are the early
steps it might do and by the way I asked
Claude good questions to ask
you and Claude told me uh to ask what do
you think is a typical day for a
biologist working on AGI look like under
in this future yeah yeah Claud is
curious let me well let me start with
your first questions and then I'll then
I'll answer that Claude Claude wants to
know what's in his future right exactly
who's it who am I going to be working
with exactly um so I think one of the
things I went hard on in when I went
hard on in the essay is let me go back
to this idea of because it's it's really
had had an you know had an impact on me
this idea that within large
organizations and systems there end up
being a few people or a few new ideas
who kind of cause things to go in a
different direction they would have
before who who kind of a
disproportionately affect the the
trajectory there's a bunch of kind of
the same thing going on right if you
think about the health world there's
like you know trillions of dollars to
pay out Medicare and you know other
health insurance and then the NIH is is
100 billion and then if I think of like
the the few things that have really
revolutionized anything it could be
encapsulated in a small small fraction
of that and so when I think of like
where will AI have an impact I'm like
can AI turn that small fraction into a
much larger fraction and raise its
quality and within biology my experience
within biology is that the biggest
problem of biology is that you can't see
what's going on you you have very little
ability to see what's going on and even
less ability to change it right what you
have is this like like from this you
have to infer that there's a bunch of
cells that within each cell is you know
uh uh three billion base pairs of DNA
built according to a genetic code uh uh
and you know there are all these
processes that are just going on without
any ability of us as you know un
augmented humans to affect it these
cells are dividing most of the time
that's healthy but sometimes that
process goes wrong and that's cancer um
the cells are aging your skin may change
color develops wrinkles as you as you
age and all of this is determined by
these processes all these proteins being
produced transported to various parts of
the cells binding to each other and and
in our initial State about biology we
didn't even know that these cells
existed we had to invent microscopes to
observe the cells we had to uh we had to
invent more powerful microscopes to see
you know below the level of the cell to
the level of molecules we had to invent
x-ray crystallography to see the DNA we
had to invent Gene sequencing to read
the DNA now you know we had to invent
protein folding technology to you know
to predict how it would fold and how
they bind and how these things bind to
each other uh you know we had to we had
to invent various techniques for now we
can edit the G the DNA as of you know
with chrisopher as of the last uh uh 12
years so the the whole history of
biology a whole big part of the history
is is basically our our our our ability
to read and understand what's going on
and our ability to reach in and
selectively change things um and and my
view is that there's so much more we can
still do there right you can do crisper
but you can do it for your whole body um
let's say I want to do it for one
particular type of cell and I want the
rate of targeting the wrong cell to be
very low that's still a challenge that's
still things people are working on
that's what we might need for gene
therapy for certain diseases and so the
reason I'm saying all of this and it
goes beyond you know beyond this to you
know to Gene sequencing to new types of
nanomaterials for observing what's going
on inside cells for you know antibody
drug conjugates the the reason I'm
saying all this is that this could be a
leverage point for the AI systems right
that the number of such inventions it's
it's in the it's in the mid double
digits or something you know mid double
digits maybe low triple digits over the
history of biology let's say I have a
million of these AIS like you know can
they discover thousand you know working
together can they discover thousands of
these very quickly and and does that
provide a huge lever instead of trying
to Leverage The you know two trillion a
year we spend on you know Medicare or
whatever can we Leverage The 1 billion a
year that's that's you know that's spent
to discover but with much higher quality
um and so what what is it like you know
being a being a scientist that works
with uh with with an AI system the way I
think about it actually is well so I
think in the early stages uh the AIS are
going to be like grad students you're
going to give them a project you're
going to say you know I'm the
experienced biologist I've set up the
lab the biology Professor or even the
grad student students themselves will
say here's here's what uh here's what
you can do with an AI you know like a AI
system I'd like to study this and you
know the AI system it has all the tools
it can like look up all the literature
to decide what to do it can look at all
the equipment it can go to a website and
say hey I'm going to go to you know
thermofisher or you know whatever the
lab equipment company is dominant lab
equipment company is today and my my
time was thermofisher um uh you know I'm
I'm going to order this new equipment to
to to do this I'm going to run my
experiments I'm going to you know write
up a report about my experiments I'm
going to you know inspect the images for
contamination I'm going to decide what
the next experiment is I'm going to like
write some code and run a statistical
analysis all the things a grad student
would do there will be a computer with
an AI that like the professor talks to
every once in a while and it says this
is what you're going to do today the AI
system comes to it with questions um
when it's necessary to run the lab
equipment it may be limited in some ways
may have to hire a human lab assistant
to you know to do the experiment and
explain how to do it or it could you
know it could use advances in lab
automation that are gradually being
developed over have been developed over
the last uh uh decade or so and will
will continue to be will continue to be
developed uh and so it'll look like
there's a human professor and a thousand
AI grad students and you know if you if
you go to one of these Nobel
prizewinning biologist or so you'll say
okay well you know you had like 50 grad
students well now you have a thousand
and they're they're they're smarter than
you are by the way um uh then I think at
some point it'll flip around where the
you know the AI systems will you know
will will be the pis will be the leaders
and and and you know they'll be they'll
be ordering humans or other AI systems
around so I think that's how it'll work
on the research s and they would be the
inventors of a crisper type technology
they would be the inventors of of a a
crisper type technology um and then I
think you know as I say in the essay
we'll want to turn turn probably turning
loose is the wrong the wrong term but we
want to want to harness the AI systems
uh to improve the clinical trial system
as well there's some amount of this
that's regulatory that's a matter of
societal decisions and that'll be harder
but can we get better at predicting the
results of clinical trials can we get
better at statistical design so that
what you know clinical trials that used
to require you know 5,000 people and
therefore you know needed $100 million
and a year to enroll them now they need
500 people in two months to enroll them
um that's where we should start uh and
and you know can we increase the success
rate of clinical trials by doing things
in animal trials that we used to do in
clinical trials and doing things in
simulations that we used to do in animal
trials again we won't be able to
simulate it all AI is not God um uh but
but you know can we can we shift the
curve substantially and radically so I I
don't know that would be my picture
doing inro and doing it I mean you're
still slowed down it still takes time
but you can do it much much faster yeah
yeah yeah can we just one step at a time
and and can that can that add up to a
lot of steps even though even though we
still need clinical trials even though
we still need laws even though the FDA
and other organizations will still not
be perfect can we just move everything
in a positive direction and when you add
up all those Positive Directions do you
get everything that was going to happen
from here to 2100 instead happens from
2027 to 2032 or something another way
that I think the world might be changing
with AI
even today but moving towards this
future of the the powerful super useful
AI is uh programming so how do you see
the nature of programming because it's
so intimate to the actual Act of
building AI how do you see that changing
for us humans I think that's going to be
one of the areas that changes fastest um
for two reasons one programming is a
skill that's very close to the actual
building of the AI um so the farther
skill is from the people who are
building the AI the longer it's going to
take to get disrupted by the AI right
like I truly believe that like AI will
disrupt agriculture maybe it already has
in some ways but that's just very
distant from the folks who are building
Ai and so I think it's going to take
longer but programming is the bread and
butter of you know a large fraction of
of the employees who work at anthropic
and at the other companies and so it's
going to happen fast the other reason
it's going to happen fast is with
programming you close the loop both when
you're training model when you're
applying the model the idea that the
model can write the code means that the
model can then run the code and and and
then see the results and and interpret
it back and so it really has an ability
unlike Hardware unlike biology which we
just discussed the model has an ability
to close the loop um and and so I think
those two things are going to lead to
the model getting good at programming
very fast as I saw on you know typical
real world programming tasks models have
gone from 3% in January of this year to
50% in October of this year so you know
we're on that S curve right where it's
going to start slowing down soon because
you can only get to 100% but uh I you
know I I would guess that in another 10
months well we'll probably get pretty
close we'll be at at least 90% so again
I would guess you know I don't know how
long it'll take but I would guess again
202 2026 2027 Twitter people who crop
out my who who who crop out these these
numbers and get rid of the caveats like
like I don't know I don't like you go
away uh I would guess that the kind of
task that the vast majority of coders do
AI can
probably if we make the task very narrow
like just write code um AI systems will
uh be able to do that now that said I
think comparative advantage is powerful
we'll find that when AIS can do 80% of a
coder's job including most of it that's
literally like right code with a given
spec will find that the remaining parts
of the job become more leveraged for
humans right humans will they'll be more
about like high level system design or
you know looking at the app and like is
it architected well and the the design
and ux aspects and eventually AI will be
able to do those as well right that's my
vision of the you know powerful AI
system but I think for much longer than
we might expect we will see that
uh small parts of the job that humans
still do will expand to fill their
entire job in order for the overall
productivity to go up um that's
something we've seen you know it used to
be that you know writing you know
writing and Editing letters was very
difficult and like writing the print was
difficult well as soon as you had word
processors and then and then uh and then
computers and it became easy to produce
work and easy to share it then then that
became instant and all the focus was on
was on the ideas so this this logic of
comparative advantage that expands tiny
parts of the tasks to large parts of the
tasks and creates new tasks in order to
expand productivity I think that's going
to be the case again someday AI will be
better at everything and that logic uh
won't apply and then then we all have
you know Humanity will have to think
about how to collectively deal with that
and we're thinking about that every day
um and you know that's another one of
the grand problems to deal with aside
from misuse and autonomy and you know we
should take it very seriously but I
think I think in the in the near term
and maybe even in the medium term like
medium term like 2 three four years you
know I expect that humans will will
continue to have a huge role and the
nature of programming will change but
programming as a as a role programming
as a job will not change it'll just be
less writing things line by line and
it'll be more macroscopic and I wonder
what the future of Ides looks like so
the tooling of interacting with AI
systems this is true for programming and
also probably true for in other contexts
like computer use but maybe domain
specific like we mentioned biology it
probably needs its own tooling about how
to be effective and then programming
needs its own tooling is anthropic going
to play in that space of also tooling
potentially I'm absolutely convinced
that uh powerful
IDs uh that that there's so much low
hanging fruit to be grabbed there um
that you know right now it's just like
you talk to the model and it talks back
but but look I mean IDs are great at
kind of lots of status analysis of of
you know so much as possible with kind
of static analysis like many bugs you
can find without even writing the code
then uh you know IDs are good for
running particular things organizing
your code um measuring coverage of unit
test like there's so much that's been
possible with a normal with a normal
Ides now you add something like well the
model now you know the model can now
like write code and run code like I am
absolutely convinced that over the next
year or two even if the quality of the
models didn't improve that there would
be enormous opportunity to enhance
people's productivity by catching a
bunch of mistakes doing a bunch of grunt
work for people and that we haven't even
scratched the surface um and thropic
itself I mean you can't say you know
no you know it's hard to say what will
happen in the future currently we're not
trying to make such IDs ourself rather
we powering the companies like cursor or
like cognition or some of the other you
know
uh Expo in the security space um uh you
know others that I can mention as well
that are building such things themselves
on top of our API and our view has been
let a thousand flowers bloom we don't
internally have the the re you know the
resources to try all these different
things let's let our customers try it um
uh and you know we'll see who succeed
and maybe different customers will
succeed in different ways uh so I both
think this is super promising and you
know it's not it's not it's not
something you know anthropic isn't isn't
eager to to at least right now compete
with all our companies in this space and
maybe never yeah it's been interesting
to watch curser try to integrate claw
successfully because there's it's
actually me fascinating how many places
it can help the programming experience
it's not as trivial it is it is really
astounding I feel like you know as a CEO
I don't get to program that much and I
feel like if six months from now I go
back it'll be completely unrecognizable
to me exactly um so in this world with
super powerful AI uh that's increasingly
automated what's the source of meaning
for us humans yeah you know work is a
source of deep meaning for many of us so
what do we uh where do we find the
meaning this is something that I've I've
written about a little bit in the essay
although I I actually I give it a bit
short shrift not for any um not for any
principled reason but this essay if you
believe it was originally going to be
two or three pages I was going to talk
about it at all hands and the reason I I
I realized it was an under un important
underexplored topic is that I just kept
writing things and I was just like oh
man I can't do this Justice and so the
thing balloon to like 40 or 50 pages and
then when I got to the work in meaning
section I'm like oh man this isn't going
to be 100 Pages like I'm GNA have to
write a whole other essay about that but
meaning is actually interesting because
you think about like the life that
someone lives or something or like you
know like you know let's say you were to
put me in like a I don't know like a
simulated environment or something where
like um you know like I have a job and
I'm trying to accomplish things I don't
know I like do that for 60 years and
then then you're like oh oh like oops
this was this was actually all a game
right does that really kind of Rob you
of the meaning of the whole thing you
know like I still made important choices
including moral choices I still
sacrificed I still had to kind of gain
all these skills or or or just like a
similar exercise you know think back to
like you know one of the historical
figures who you know discovered
electromagnetism or relativity or
something if you told them well actually
20,000 years ago some some alien on you
know some alien on this planet
discovered this before before you did um
does that does that Rob the meaning of
the discovery it doesn't really seem
like it to me right it seems like the
process is what is what matters and how
it shows who you are as a person along
the way and you know how you relate to
other people and like the decisions that
you make along the way those are those
are consequential um you know I I I
could imagine if we handle things badly
in an AI world we could set things up
where people don't have any long-term
source of meaning or any but but that's
that's more a choice a set of choices we
make that's more a set of the
architecture of a society with these
powerful models if we if we design it
badly and for shallow things then then
that might happen I would also say that
you know most people's lives today while
admirably you know they work very hard
to find meaning meaning in those lives
like look you know we who are privileged
and who are developing these
Technologies we should have y for people
not just here but in the rest of the
world who who you know spend a lot of
their time kind of scraping by to to to
to to like survive assuming we can
distribute the benefits of these
technology of this technology to
everywhere like their lives are going to
get a hell of a lot better um and uh you
know meaning will be important to them
as it is important to them now but but
you know we should not forget the
importance of that and and you know that
that uh the idea of meaning as as as as
kind of the only important thing is in
some ways an artifact of of a small
subset of people who have who have been
uh economically fortunate but I you know
I think all that said I you know I think
a world is possible with powerful AI
that not only has as much meaning for
for everyone but that has that has more
meaning for everyone right that can can
allow um can allow everyone to see
worlds and experiences that it was
either possible for no one to see or or
possible for for very few people to
experience um so I I am optimistic about
meaning I worry about economics and the
concentration of power that's actually
what I worry about more um I I worry
about how do we make sure that that fair
World reaches everyone um when things
have gone wrong for humans they've often
gone wrong because humans mistreat other
humans uh that that is maybe in some
ways even more than the autonomous risk
of AI or the question of meaning that
that is the thing I worry about most um
the the concentration of power the abuse
of power um structures like autocracies
and dictatorships where a small number
of people exploits a large number of
people I'm very worried about that and
AI increases the amount of power in the
world and if you concentrate that power
and abuse that power it can do
immeasurable damage yes it's very
frightening it's very it's very
frightening
well I encourage people highly encourage
people to read the full essay that
should probably be a book or a sequence
of essays um because it does paint a
very specific future I could tell the
later sections got shorter and shorter
because you started to probably realize
that this is going to be a very long
essay one I realized it would be very
long and two I'm very aware of and very
much try to avoid um you know just just
being I I don't know I don't know what
the term for it is but one one of these
people who's kind of overon confident
and has an opinion on everything and
kind of says says a bunch of stuff and
isn't isn't an expert I very much tried
to avoid that but I have to admit once I
got the biology sections like I wasn't
an expert and so as much as I expressed
uncertainty uh probably I said some a
bunch of things that were embarrassing
are wrong well I was excited for the
future you painted and uh thank you so
much for working hard to build that
future and thank you for talking today D
thanks for having me I just I just hope
we can get it right and and make it real
and if there's one message I want to I