and hello everyone here so today for our
speaker we have Albert Jang from mistal
AI um and also from the University of
Cambridge nice to meet you and thank you
for uh coming today um and being our
speaker so Albert is a AI scientist at
mistal Ai and the final year PhD student
at the computer science department of
Cambridge University he works on on
language model pre-training and
reasoning at myal Ai and language models
for mathematics at Cambridge um so thank
you for coming today and today Albert is
going to talk about mistol um a sparse
mixture of experts language models and
yeah I think I will now uh leave it for
Albert hi uh Emily thanks uh thanks for
the really nice introduction um so let
me share my screen here yeah so yeah
thanks very much again for the really
nice introduction Emily um so today I'll
be talking about demystifying mixure of
experts and my name is Albert I'm
scientist at mroi and a PhD unit at
University of
Cambridge so the content you'll be
hearing today uh first I will talk about
the architecture of uh first the dence
Transformers architecture uh just to
review and also the sparse mixture of
experts or smoes um so after that I'll
be talking about inter Ting sparse
mixture of experts models and the
majority of this slides will be based on
the mixture of experts paper that will
put out early uh earlier this year in
January and throughout this talk if you
have any questions feel free to raise
your hand and I'll be really happy to
answer and also uh I'll be posing some
open research questions uh because the
these things are really uh very much on
the research and we hope that more
research can be down and so the open
source Community can really enjoy the
benefits okay let's get started
um so first let's talk about talk about
architecture uh we can first talk about
the dense Transformer architecture that
a lot of people must have already talked
about um but here I want to focus on the
Mi mistol 7B model which is the dense
Transformer um the the the main
difference between the mro 7B model and
the rest I guess the rest of the uh Dan
transform models is that it has group
CER attention uh which means which is
different from the multi-ad and multier
attention some in between so for multi
had attention you have the same number
of uh you have same the same number of
keys queries and values and for multier
attention you have a lot of CES and just
one key and one value and group CER
attention are sort of in between and you
have a lot of queries uh much less keys
keys and
values also the difference uh also
there's another difference in the
attention we're using for uh mral 7B
that is we're using sliding window
attention the idea being uh for some of
the lower layers of the Transformer the
tokens um uh so so for for each token
position they they attend to uh a
relatively short span of previous tokens
and as you go deeper in the Transformer
the later token positions will get
information transmitted from the earlier
token uh positions and neither of these
architectural uh designs are new so
these are already present in the uh in
previous Works uh from from 2023 uh 2019
and 2020 so so these are really nothing
new but we decided to adopt these
architectural changes in mro 7B uh to
make a better model okay so after after
writing these slides I I realized
there's um actually a huge number of
decision choices you have to make in in
in designing a a Transformer
architecture because there are so many
details so um like just presenting this
doesn't feel sufficient so I try to uh
well first these are the sort of
standard configurations for mrol 7B and
also I just want to have a very single
uh very some very clean code in pytorch
that just tells you how to write a
single Transformer layer and I'll be
adopting the uh Nome shazir uh notation
by annotating the the the dimensions of
every tensor as a suffix in in the
variable name so let's say our sequence
size is 8,000 uh 8K and that we have
have uh 32 uh query heads and eight kmb
heads so this is quite standard for
group query attention and our high head
dimensions are 128 and our latent
Dimensions is
14K um so in order to write a single
Transformer layer
um uh first you initialize your uh query
key and value matrices so here I down
their Dimensions here and notice that we
don't use bias so there's no bias in any
of these matrices and we also write down
our output uh uh Matrix so to know that
uh the alpha Matrix has uh the same
dimensions as the transpose of the C of
the Cur Matrix um so in order to write
an attention forward layer uh so here
let's assume that our uh input X has the
dimension L * D so L is the sequence
length and D is the latent dimension
um so you first want to uh use these uh
matrices to to try to find what your
cury key and values are um so here their
uh Dimensions have been normalized to l
and H LK and LBH
respectively and then you want to apply
Rosary
embedding to your keys and queries you
don't really apply that to values and
then you do a very uh standard attention
mechanism uh uh with the uh with the the
queries keys and values uh to know here
we actually repeat the keys and values a
couple of times to make their Dimensions
match with the
queres and then we just return the
output uh uh multiply with the output
Matrix so this is your very standard
attention forward layer and uh to have a
transform layer you also want to tie
that uh you you want to First do a
normalization here we use RSM uh RMS
Norm over the input and then we do a
tension forward um and then we do a
tension residual layer uh followed by
normalization plus an MLP plus a dense
residual layer so this is what's present
in a Transformer layer okay um so with
these architecture designs we managed to
make a model that's uh quite good uh so
this is releas this was released in
September last year and it was able to
beat a lot of the Llama 2 models back
then despite being very very
small okay so let's now go to the
interesting bits that's mixture of
experts and mixture of experts is not a
very a new idea it's been present
forever and uh there are a couple very
uh quite recent papers that really
highlighted the importance and like how
uh what are the benefits you're getting
from these mixture of expert mixtures of
xert layer um uh models so uh the I
guess the probably the most wellknown
one is the switch Transformers uh that
is the Google paper uh that scales
Transformers to trillions trillion
parameter models with simple and
efficient sparcity um and they discussed
a lot about the sort of parallelism
decisions you can make about data
parallelism model parallelism and expert
parallelism and for the mixture of a
mixture of experts layer it's also it's
even older idea so from 2017 uh also by
some um quite famous vi from Google and
uh the idea is that you try to take out
uh so so at the time they were still
using recurrent language models um so at
the T the idea is that you try to have a
gating layer uh a gating Network that
decides which experts you should route
to okay um so in our mixture of experts
uh uh in our implementation of the
mixture of experts layer uh we're doing
something very similar so have the
inputs uh that are get sent to a router
and the router assign the gating ways
and to pick the top two uh experts to uh
to give this inputs to and uh after
these experts individually process the
inputs the gating wavs will be applied
to the output of the experts and they
get sum to get to the results so if you
uh write it in very uh mathematically uh
you can say that the uh the input is X
and the the router has a matrix multiply
to it and then you take the top K uh
experts out of that do a softmax and
these are your getting these are your
gating weights and um and uh output of
the uh the mixture of X for layer Y is
the softmax of the top two uh gating
gating weights times a sweet glue
function over X so um for for each of
the
experts okay um so
sparse mixture of xers model near is
quite near the cost performance uh
perito Frontier uh because at for each
token you don't the token do doesn't
have to go through the entire uh neuron
Network's parameters instead it can just
go to like the active parameters for for
that token and and this mix uh mixture
of experts model can outperform Lama
270p uh with about five times faster
inference uh so we kind of see it as a
dropping replacement for GB3 five which
can also Master quite a few uh European
languages in addition to English and you
can gracefully handle contact 32k tokens
so this mixture of expert uh model was
released under Apache 2 2.0 so you can
free to use for commercial purposes I
also attach the configurations for the
mixture of expers model here but I um so
you can you can you can refer this back
to the mro 7B to see the
differences okay so um I want to talk
about what does uh amoi which is a verb
I just created uh the the MLP layers
actually give you so the conventional
wisdom is that the MLPs in a neur in a
Transformer network uh store knowledge
and the tension stores algorithms or
reasoning or they sort of implement
algorithms and reasoning so by m moying
the MLP layers we're supposed to get a
boost in knowledge right um and indeed
we try to Benchmark uh mixol a * 7B uh
with a Mr 7B and a couple Lama two ler a
couple of the Llama 2 models and uh in a
couple of different categories you can
definitely see that on the knowledge
heavy tasks such as mlu and knowledge uh
the mixol uh a Time 7B model which is uh
shaded in yellow here is doing a lot
better than mol 7B um and also of the
reasoning comp hension and uh tasks uh
it seems to be doing a little bit better
but still uh but not not as much as it
does on knowledge in
mm okay um and here is a different graph
where here what we're trying to show is
that what is on the horizontal axis is
the number of active active parameters
and on the vertical axis is the
performance of the models on uh various
tasks and the the sort of uh brown dots
here are llama 2 models the series of
llama 2 models and the orange dots are m
models from mial 7B to uh Mix A Time 7B
so the Mixel a Time 7B uses only um 12.9
billion active parameters so close to 13
billion uh yet it can perform quite a
bit better uh especially in the
knowledge category you can see the drop
you can see the increase from mial 7B to
Mixel a * 7B is quite huge here
um there are some improvements on other
categories but the knowledge Improvement
is is really
great okay um so there is a research
question uh that is if uh if uh making
your language model uh uh if making the
MLP layers of your language model can
give you a huge boost in knowledge like
how about Amo ifying the attention
layers right so this is also very well
not very old but like quite old idea uh
from 2022 in the switch Transformer
papers um so the idea is you can replace
the trainable qkv matrices with switch
layers so instead of doing a standard
matrix multiplication you can do a m so
you have a gating layer and then um some
dance layers uh for the qkb matri
matricies and the problem at a time was
with stability um so if you use bf16
Precision to train your models they can
sometimes diverge but if you had use
fp32 they don't uh and you get some
performance boost which is nice um but
at present days mostly we're try we're
we're training with bf6 so we have to
find a way to make it work um and uh so
to to in order to make this work maybe
you can try better stability techniques
maybe some normalization or maybe you
could use a different way to uh to too
by the C the the the attention layers so
this is the open research question I
would really like to see some research
to be done
here um and after this I want to just uh
talk about several myths that seems to
be present around the mixture of xers
models so the miss one is that there're
eight experts in Mixr a Time 7B so this
is probably our our fault by naming our
our model mixol A * 7B um and um so the
truth is that every layer has every
Transformer layer has eight experts and
these experts are permutationally
equivalent so you because the way it
works is that the gating the gating uh
the gating Network decides how much Wass
to give to uh each of the how much waste
to give to each of the experts and only
picks the top two so it doesn't matter
um so it doesn't matter how you uh sorry
so so it doesn't matter how you uh
permute them they will give you the same
result so that means instead of eight
experts you actually have 32 * 8 experts
in total and they're relatively
independent uh uh across
layers um the M two is that there are 56
billion parameters in Mixr a Time 7B um
but the gating and the attention layers
are shared so these are not in the a
times part and uh in fact there are only
uh 40 6 * 7 billion parameters in total
and each token will will actually only
see 12.9 billion active parameters
instead of
14 okay um so uh another thing that
seems to be quite popular these days is
to compare everything uh uh tying
everything that's related to cost with
the number of active parameters as if
they are proportional and uh that's
that's not quite true right because mix
roll a Time 7B has fewer active
parameters than l to 13B but having this
of expert routing means that you need to
send tokens around to different experts
like quite dynamically so that means you
have more communication cost you cannot
just pre-program like which token will
be sent to which expert um while you're
gain much more in performance divided by
cost the absolute the absolute cost is
not proportional to the active parameter
count um so usually your uh mixture of
expers your mixture of expers model uh
if you have the active parameters uh
your your actual cost of serving these
models is actually a bit more than the
uh than the equivalent dance model with
the same number of acent
parameters okay um here's also a really
I think a really interesting research
question is how do you balance loads at
INF time right so your gting layer might
still decide to do unbalanced loading at
inference time which makes inference
slower what that means is that ideally
you want your eight experts or like how
however many experts you have ideally
you want them to handle the same number
of tokens such that you don't get the uh
you don't get the slowest you you don't
always have to wait for the slowest
expert and some nice ideas around like
mixture of depth and also damic loading
based on scores so some of the ideas are
like uh if you uh if you saturate one of
the experts maybe you can try to find a
neighbor uh of that expert to to to give
the token to which is not saturated
and then sort of try to slowly fill up
the number the the total number of
expert times token count you
have okay um another I think quite quite
open research question is how can you
compress smoes and this uh comes from a
screenshot I I uh someone took of uh Tim
dmer because I really trust this man's
uh model compression uh SK skills with
my life so uh Tim jur said uh he he
thinks we can compress a mixture of X
ver model to uh lower smaller than four
gigabytes um so
becausee uh compression is quite
different from dense Transformer uh
compression uh because the regular
Transformers they are really really
difficult SP to sparsify and this is
really true for like the feed forward
the the MLP layers but the MLP uh the
Moe layers are quite different so maybe
there's something you can do with Amo
layers such that your compression is
much much more efficient so by
compression here I mean spcification so
like a lot of the U so so sparsification
not in the sense of like choosing only
top two experts instead of uh instead of
eight but I mean a lot of the parameters
might be like doing not much work and
you can like Shar them
out okay um so this is this was um said
by Tim deur in December last year and I
don't think of seeing like much
convincing work on like um sparsifying
Moes to to an extreme but I really like
uh more more work going going on
here okay um now I want want to talk
about uh how to interpret uh uh mixture
of expert models um so the mixture of
expert models with a sparse gating layer
actually uh provide you an incredible
opportunity by giving you disg grade
gating signals um so so deep neuron
networks are traditionally very very
hard to interpret things like all the
ways and activations living very high
dimensional Place spaces and the
attention in uh Transformers potentially
offers some interpretation opportunity
um because you can look at like how much
of the attention weights get assigned to
which tokens or to to to um uh to to
which tokens but like you you're
essentially picking at like what is the
model looking at by looking at the
ention scores but this also quickly gets
very messy as you have a lot of
attention hats and it's hard to
visualize and hard to
interpret and the gating layers in as SM
Mo potentially tells you a bit more uh
because it tells you like which experts
is looking at wish tokens um so can we
make some sense out of this then um so
in our uh paper we try to find if
there's some sort of domain
specialization with these experts um so
we took the validation splits of the
pile data sets uh and um so these are
represented in different colors you can
see the red is archive uh the green one
here is GitHub and the sort of blue one
here is field field papers the purple
one is stack exchange and for layers 0
15 and 31 so these correspond to the the
the the shallowest layer the sort of mid
layer and the deepest layer so this is
the layer 31 is the layer just before
decoding
so for each of these layers we plot how
much each expert is selected um so uh
since we have eight experts the sort of
uh random random selection chance is
around is
12.5% and you can see that at layer zero
so this is the layer that's closest to
the raw tokens um you will see that the
distribution is quite uh quite uniform
it's it's it's not like very uniform but
quite so this might be telling us that
this layer is like too shallow that it's
uh still doing some a lot of syntactical
stuff that you don't get a lot of
meaningful domain specialization going
on and um on the sort of the mid layer
so here is potentially where you get a
lot of semantic information you can you
can notice that expert 3 here uh is
doing something quite interesting right
so because it's it's it gets selected
very
not very often for any of the other
categories but gets really selected
quite a lot for DM mathematics and
second place is get up so maybe this
layer uh so maybe this expert in expert
3 in layer 15 is doing something that's
math and code heavy U but this is uh
quite speculative and we cannot really
conclude much out of it and for layer 31
I think the distribution go back to
close to uniform again although you get
some spiking uh distributions here and
here and there that specialize in
mathematics it seems or since it's um
since the data SI Deep Mind mathematics
is more
like
arithmetics okay um we also did some
analysis on cona tokens so the the
question to ask here is whether two
tokens that are consective get assigned
to the same expert um so here we have
the first choice so that means if a
token is given to expert I does the next
token also get assigned to expert I
right and we also we we we we're still
doing this analysis on the three layers
layer zero layer 15 and layer 31
corresponding to three different places
in the network and the validation set is
still the pile validation
split so the random chance uh assignment
score uh uh random chance assignment um
will give you 12
12.5% uh in terms of like how how many
of the uh tokens get that are assigned
to expert I still get assigned to expert
I sorry the max token also gets assigned
to expert I and we can see that at layer
zero this is slightly higher than random
U but at layer 15 this is significantly
uh higher than random right so uh almost
uh well it's almost double the random
chance uh that the
uh the first choice for the uh gating
layer will actually assign the next
token to the same uh expert as this
token and when go to the last layer
you'll find that this trend sort
regresses a little bit uh the uh it's
still sign quite significantly higher
than ROM but it's a bit less than layer
15 um we also look at like the first or
second choice so uh if if if this expert
is not chosen as the like the the the
best the best expert to Route this token
to uh could it be the second best um so
here the random chance uh uh uh
probability is around 46% and you can
see for layer zero this we have the sort
of the same pattern right so the for
layer zero the uh number of times that
the the next token get assigned to the
first or second choice for for this
expert is around just slightly higher
than random and for layer 15 this is
really really significantly higher and
then for layer 31 it sort of regresses a
little bit so I think there there
certainly some sort of more detailed
analysis to be done here uh that can
conclude out of the uh from from these
mixture of experts
models also we try to visualize uh in in
three examples like which experts
actually selected which uh which tokens
so um we have three examples so the
first example is from
um is actually from the uh GitHub code
for the layer and the second example are
like simple arithmetic questions I think
from DM mathematics and the third is
from a simple multiple choice question
and this is for layer zero layer 15 and
layer 31 you can see that there's there
doesn't seem to be much specialization
right um uh uh so here a lot of digits
get assigned to the same sorry so the
colors repres present different experts
so here all these digits get assigned to
the same expert but that seems to be it
we don't see a lot of like very clear
distinction between like which experts
like which uh tokens right um so that
really closely relates to uh myth four
that is you really uh the myth four is
that you want experts to specialize in
domains let's say you have two experts
specialized in coding uh so that means
they just basically like if you have
some code they'll just handle all the
tokens um then what do the other other
experts do when you're coding right so
when you want to generate a lot of uh a
lot of code it seems that you will only
have the chance to uh root all your
tokens to these two experts and the
other expert just stand there and do
nothing so you actually want all the
expert to be fully engaged at all the
time to maximize your inference
efficiency language also is so complex
that man specifying these domains uh
that experts should specialize over uh
seems to be a simplification to me
because there might be like a lot of
underlying features that the experts are
actually specializing over and just not
present at the high like the very high
domain
level um there's a treasure hunt so this
is this is why we love open source so
much so like around after 24 hours of
our uh Mixr a * 7B model release uh
there's a guy um on a Chinese website
that just found out that there is one
expert in one of the layers that's
particularly crucial so what they did
was that they try to remove um the I
expert from uh from all of the layers
and here you can see what are the
effects if you remove the I expert and
the uh on the vertical axis is the mmu
score um it seems that if you remove the
third expert then everything just
collapses the MML score is 0.63 so this
is 0.63% not um uh uh uh not uh 63% and
for other uh for other experts if you
remove the uh I expert the mmu scores
drop a little bit but not too much um so
and they made this meme about it so the
expert 3 seems to be doing all the work
well all the experts are sort of
standing around and do not
much okay um so I think another really
important research question here is how
do we interpret the mixture of expert
decisions and what what are the features
that they're learning so the experts
might capture features that are really
different uh very different concepts
than what we perceive as Concepts and it
might be more efficient to represent
linear combinations of Concepts as long
as they spend sort of the same sub space
right and it how do we recover that
Subspace or how do we recover um some of
the uh um some of the stats that we can
actually understand what are the
underlying Concepts that they're
actually
learning okay um so I just want to also
uh just conclude here that um a sparse
mixture of xers models are leverage
sparity to gain a lot more knowledge and
you can train very good uh mixture of
expert Mi mixture of experts models to
be efficient at inference and expert
specialization is not as straightforward
as one might think and just there's just
tons to do in architecture and
interpretability research um and also
just want to plug Mr AI uh co-founded by
uh uh uh by Arthur Timothy and Gom and
we're have uh offices in Paris London
San Francisco Bay Area it's actually
currently it's actually in Palo uh have
500 million in funding and if you enjoy
solving the research questions that I
just mentioned or uh doing open source
AI or just uh generally empowering
people with uh language models uh you're
very welcome to join us um thank you
very much if any of youall have any
questions feel free to come up and ask
so uh I recently uh read the paper from
meta uh they are using the Intensive
model uh not this one uh 28 I think page
28 yeah okay so which is I feel like
it's the other direction opposite way
why you choose The Spar mixture of exper
rather than the other people now I see
most of them using the Intensive
models like to do some of like Edge
database like in a confined scope you
can have more knowledges in the um
confined scope that's I see the train
goes to that way
for example you go to the uh Egypt
Museum here uh in I think in Sun
somewhere right so you can have the chat
gbt uh have the local U knowledges which
you cannot get it from the internet but
you can only cooperate with the museum
and get it I think uh the Intensive
model allows this kind of uh more uh
domain knowledge like going deeper but
now here you are using the spous model
with mixture of
experts to me it's the opposite can you
explain why yeah sure um so so if I
understand the question correctly the uh
the question is asking uh why are we
choosing sparse mixture of experts
models instead of uh dance models that
are there's no sort of sparcity involved
um so I think for for for as devices uh
dense models are have a lot of potential
because uh for spars mixure of expert
models uh although you have uh sparity
in um inference time so that means a
token does not have to see all the uh
parameters but rather just a small
fraction of it uh you still have to load
all of the experts into memory and that
might pose a huge challenge for Adge
devices so so like your phone might not
have like 200 gigabytes of memory in
order to uh run inference like very uh
uh uh you order to run inference very
efficiently but for um like I guess for
data or for people who are serving these
models uh it might pose a uh advantage
in terms of inference cost uh because
you can have um you can have very good
uh performance slash uh divided by cost
ratio I see so your point is because
there's not enough uh memory at the edge
so for the edge it's better to use Spas
model rather than denve model oh so no
no I meant uh for for ad it's I think
it's good to use dense models ah because
because for sparse models you still have
to load everything into into memory yeah
yeah yeah so so your your use case is is
more for like a closer to the center of
the cloud is it what you
mean uh yeah yeah okay got it thank
you thank you does anyone else have a
question they'd like to
ask yes
do you want
to I have a question in regards to fine
tuning um we've been working with
multiple models so Gemini Char
jpt llama and there is a big problem of
fine tune in these models especially on
on you know tensor on images um they're
like having issues with understanding
what what can you say about that
uh you mean in general fine-tuning
language models on Vis visual tasks
yeah um I guess okay I guess that's a
very broad question uh what I can what I
can say about that is uh there's um I I
guess for chat gbt and and Gemini you
don't really have the model weights in
your hand so you're basically relying on
open AI or Google uh to do lur for you
right um so you get I guess you have
less control over your fine tuning uh
whereas for an open source model or I
guess open waste model you actually have
waste in your hands so you can do you
can do Laura you can do full fine tuning
I guess you get more control and um yeah
I I guess that's in general like what
what I can say about like fine-tuning
open source models versus uh versus very
close Source models but like I guess
that really highly depends like exactly
what happens when you're doing really
depends on your use case and your data
yeah I mean I sorry I was a little bro
so um when we try start transferring
them into a large large data sets let's
say like 10,000 images or 5,000 images
so and you you have to transfer them
into textual format because none of
these models are actually tuned designed
to be fine tuned on images they don't
understand it so is this something you
see in development in open source models
um so do by trans by translating these
images into text you mean like OCR or
that is that something digital format
it's the textual format so they do
understand them in dig as an image if
you upload them into like text text line
right like you go to charp but when you
start feeding them through apis you need
to transfer them so then it becomes a
problem like is there any way to
overcome this issue with open source
models
[Music]
um I I guess I'm not uh I guess I'm not
entirely sure what the root cause of the
of of this problem is but I I I think
I'm sure that with open source models
you can actually while you can see like
what the ways are doing right so you can
you can actually tell what are like you
you have more control of the ways
basically uh so I think open open way
definitely post an advantage here
thank you for your question thank you
for the question does anyone else have
any other questions in
person yeah I guess I was curious uh
like where you think the improvements of
mixtures mixture of experts are like
coming from like I've I've heard that
you can like put different experts or
different like feed for networks on
different gpus and that that like um
allows it to be more parallel and like
speed things up from like a compute
perspective or is it like more the
sparcity itself that is like giving
these improvements I guess is there any
insight on
that um I guess there are there are two
Dimensions to this right so in terms of
improvement um the one dimension is
performance um uh so so as I said the
mixture mixture of experts models have
these uhe MLP layers so imagine your
your original MLP layers and then you
make it eight times wider you will be
able to store a lot more knowledge into
into these layers um because well you
have more parameter counts uh so that's
I guess the own the performance um
Dimension that you you can actually uh
you can actually store a lot more
knowledge into into these models and on
the performance uh sorry and the other
dimension is the the inference
efficiency Dimension right so uh um so
uh definitely go read the switch
Transformer paper where they dis discuss
the um okay I guess that's training
efficiency but they really discussed in
quite quite quite a lot of details about
data parallelism uh model parallelism
and expert parallelism and how they
affect the efficiency uh what's the
communication cost there what's the best
way to trade a models um and for for for
these uh sparse mixture experts models
since you only so so you only select um
13 billion parameters uh for each token
at inference time you are actually uh
trying to select the most relevant
parameters for each token so that can
make inference quite a lot uh quite a
lot more efficient um I hope that answer
your question um yeah I know that
definitely did um I guess I was also
wondering like if if you seen like the
uh mixture of depths paper um and like
that as like a way of sparity do you
have any thoughts on
that yeah I think sparity sparity helps
when you can do
like so adaptive computation so the
mixture of depth model is like the best
example of um the uh adaptive
computation which means for different
tokens for for predicting different
tokens you you
want first um different parameters to
engage so in the mixture of depth uh uh
paper they uh they selected different
number of parameters to engage in uh
calculating each token and in our paper
we select different like the same number
of the same number of parameters but
like uh but different experts so it's
it's a the the difference is uh I guess
quality versus quality like but there
are like two Dimension two different
dimensions you can optimize over you
definitely want to have to select the
most relevant parameters and as few
parameters as possible for decoding
at yeah okay um yeah I think those all
my
questions perfect thank you we'll take
one more inperson question if any of you
all have anything if not we can turn it
to the online
questions
yes hey Alber thanks for the talk um
just one in the earlier you uh like
beginning of the presentation you
mentioned like routing and communication
cost and I was wondering if you could
talk about like how that scales uh you
know relative to the number of experts
you have in
parameters oh yeah sure so um so so that
depends on like the first the number of
uh the number of experts you have and uh
also depends on like how large each
expert is um so that that sort of uh can
change your the way you do pism so um we
know that communication is really
expensive when you need to go from one
GPU to another and it's more expensive
if you want to go from one node to
another um and if you have a huge ton of
experts that will not fit into just one
node um then you really incur a huge qu
quite a big communication cost and uh
like how to scale beyond that is is I
guess is a is is a very open scientific
questions um but like essentially the um
the communication cost you incur is uh
roughly proportional to to to the uh to
to the number of uh token routing uh
first between gpus and then between
notes thank
you thank you for all the questions um
we'll have Stephen uh introduce some of
the questions that were submitted by the
people joining us on
Zoom hey y can you hear me yep he thanks
for the great talk thanks um all right
so we have some questions through zoom
and slido I'm G to um pick and choose
some of them starting with some Zoom
questions maybe um so we have a question
here about any comments on why
potentially llama 3 is not using a
mixture of experts a lot of people
suspected they might after misal success
um I don't know if you would know
anything about that but yeah I don't
know just ask a lot of people
sorry right um
let me
see here's OD question um do you foresee
mixture of experts techniques being
incorporated into the other large
Foundation models or will it remain a
subset of models that are best for
certain use
cases oh uh certainly so uh as uh I
think as my answer to the first like
iners question was um for as devices you
probably you probably want want to stick
with dense models because of the memory
constraints and for mixture vorts models
you really gain a lot in uh efficiency
if you if you can serve it at scale um
so if you have if you have high batch
sizes you will potentially be doing you
will potentially be doing better uh in
terms of throughput than the dance
models um so yeah it definitely depends
on like um depends on your use case uh
usually the larger this the larger the
scale the better the well I guess the
more the benefit of the mixure VAR
expert model shine and well it's
speculated that gb4 is a mixure of
experts model if you haven't heard
already can mixure of experts models out
perform domain specific models at their
respective tasks with
experts um so well first um
usually um models that have been trained
for particular domains are really hard
to beat I I think that's where also
where the the purpose of continuous Pro
training and fun tuning comes uh comes
in so if you uh let's say you you first
prra a general tax model and then you
want to adapt it to the medical domain
so you grab a lot of medical data and
then you continue P tray or fting on
that that model is going to be really
hard to beat um and I think um the
mixture of experts model uh the experts
don't really um at least in our case
here the expert don't really focus on
like tradition like domains as we know
it they don't have we don't have a
medical expert we don't have a coding
expert rather they just try to uh extend
they try to they have Concepts encoded
in a very u non-interpretable Way um so
so I I wouldn't say that just taking one
mixture of EX first model would just
outperform all the other uh domain Focus
models right that makes sense um here's
a question has there been any study on
whether thee layers should be both at
the early layers and deep layers for old
neuron Network Ensemble methods late
Fusion tends to work better than early
Fusion so um okay I think that's a
really great question because um I think
from inception from the the neuron
Network um we are trying to adopt this
um we're we're trying sort of have this
tradition of um having layers that are
that look exactly the same as at each
other um so you have and and so then you
can try to focus on just designing this
layer to be as perfect as possible and
then you can just copy paste that a
couple of times um but I think I've
recently seing a paper sorry I don't
remember the name but I think they're
just trying to put uh layers in random
ERS so sometimes it can be attention
first sometimes it can be M first and
they can have Al also some other quite
wacky layers uh but I think that
performs quite well uh it's unclear to
me
like why that is it could be just chance
um but I guess in I guess in ter in ter
if you wanted to design a generally
really perform really performing model
it's really safe to have the same
architecture uh for every layer um uh so
yeah so I guess that's I guess the sa
safest Choice uh you can also do some
sort of neuro architecture search in
order to optimize your layer sorry
optimize your architecture um but that's
that which is a much more principled
approach that's so guessing that this
ler might work
better all right thanks for the answer
um asking could you talk a bit more
about how the different uh the eight
experts are built are they just fine-
tuned on different data
sets um so they are they are trained on
the on the on roughly the same data sets
um but I I I'm not sure if I can say
more than that but uh yeah
sorry all right and here's a question
some work has suggested that learning to
Route doesn't perform any better than
simply using for example a random
mapping of inputs to experts do you have
any
thoughts I think that
um I would I would definitely need to
see the the the paper first but I
wouldn't be too surprised if that's the
case I I would still be surprised but
not like extremely surpised
because if you if you think about Amo
ifying the uh MLP layers as augmenting
the the knowledge capacity then uh it
seems that you can potentially uh just
do do that in a very root Force way and
just randomly mapping the the tokens to
to random layer to sorry to random
experts um I would still think that the
gating has the advantage of um you know
um of being able to choose experts more
intelligently than just randomly so um
yeah I I I I I don't know that paper but
I I I would love to see it um someone
was asking could you speak a bit about
the general development process from
your perspective for this model what
aspects design choices hyperparameters
and so forth did you try that did not
work before arriving at this specific
architecture um so we know uh so for for
this particular archit Ure uh the
mixture of experts architecture uh we
kind of know that it will work because
um there there's they're having a lot of
successful papers beforehand um in terms
of like what sort of things you need to
consider um I think one really good
practice I guess for an AI companies
that of as a like a a single developer
is to always cons like you you you
always want to take
inference um needs um you you you want
to think about inference needs before
you design the architecture for a model
uh you don't want to so for example you
don't want to have an have a model
that's just just slightly exceeds like
what a single 800 uh 80 80 gab h100 can
contain and then you you you basically
lose a lot of efficiency uh from just
like being like overhead being just a
little little bit more than 80 gigabytes
um so I think in terms of design before
training the model uh you definitely
want to consider how do how do how do in
how to infer with this model um and in
terms of the uh hyper parameters you
definitely want to do some sort of
scaling law uh before you you like some
some sort of scaling law uh I guess
search and Analysis before trainer model
to make sure that short model is served
um at the best performance uh cost ratio
um so yeah that's it
great um speaking of uh GPU memory
someone is asking what is the inference
runtime GPU memory footprint for um the
7B model versus the 8X 7B it would be
great to understand this for specific
applications especially if mistol has
the potential to run on edge devices um
with sufficient GPU of
vram um sorry I I I I don't think I got
the the last part of the question so ad
devices and GPU uh oh no they're just
asking what is the approximate inference
runtime of um in terms of GPU memory
footprint for the 7B model versus the 8
by 7B ah okay I see so uh if you do like
if if you do very naive um uh if you if
you do it very straightforwardly that
should load for for the a uh a Time 7B
to load all the experts in and then uh
the experts always stay in GPU memory
then your uh then then the different the
the difference between the a * 7B and
the 7B will be the same as the ratio
between
46.7 to 7 uh that's the memory
requirement um but the at at infin time
since we the mixture of xer model only
has 13B active parameters uh so each
token get to see much fewer parameters
than there are in the memory um and you
can do some interesting things like like
um I think CPU like I kind of forgot the
the name for it but you can keep some of
the experts uh in CPU and then uh and
then only load them when you need them
um so I think that's something you can
you can do as well um but then you you
also lose uh some efficiency because you
need to constantly transfer uh
parameters from CPU to GPU and vice
versa right that makes sense speaking of
parameters someone asked do you have a
rough rule of thumb for how to
approximate how capable Ane model would
be in terms of equivalent dense
parameters for example I've heard that
calculating the geometric mean of active
parameters to Total parameters is a good
way to do this which would mean that 13
billion active parameters with 47
billion total parameters would be
equivalent to a 22 billion parameters
dense model um I'm wondering how
accurate that would be um so I I think
that's I I think that's a good rule of
thumb um although that definitely
depends on like how how how well you
train these models um like um uh and how
many tokens do you put through them and
how good are those tokens if all other
things being equal I think that's a very
good rule of
Thum all right great and I'm just
looking at some of the uploaded slider
questions um someone asked for the
treasure hunted expert was there a
reverse experiment of removing all
experts except number
three oh uh that's a that's a great
question I think yeah if if you can
figure that out I I'll be really like
I'll be all yours I'll be really happy
to hear that so so then then you're just
trying to I guess you're trying to trim
the a * 7B back into a 7B which might be
an interesting experiment to
do right um someone asked what is your
intuition about why the 8X 7B is
significantly better at reasoning
compared to the 7B are they learning
better internal
algorithms um that could be the case
although I think that's very speculative
I think okay so I think for a lot of
these benchmarks uh for example the even
for the math benchmark
the the like what you do like what s of
things count as knowledge and what
things count as reasoning is quite
ambiguous for example if you are doing a
math task and you can reason to get
something out or you can just recall oh
here's a Lama and I can just use that
and so I think there's like high
ambiguity between what sort of things
count has knowledge what sort of things
counts as reasoning um so for this
particular example um the a * 7B
definitely gains a lot more in knowledge
uh but does the gaining uh knowledge
also induc some sort of change in its
reasoning capability I don't know uh but
I I think that that's just like whatever
I can say about it is like highly
speculative but I'll say the the
benchmarks themselves are also very
ambiguous so so I think it's worth
finding out what exactly um is
doing great another question about GPU
memory um someone's saying in production
we're constantly bounded by GPU memory
instead of compute we'll mixure of
experts make it more challenging to
serve any extra cost besides
communication
overhead um so you Pur of cost I think
communication like um yeah so so when
you say you're founded by GPU memory I I
assume that it's it's like it's like
comparing the a Time 7B to a 7B um then
yes if you need to load all the experts
into the GPU memory then yeah you're
going to consume you're going to uh
you're going to use a lot more um so the
the the
the benefit or or the advantage of the a
Time
7B over the 7B
um is that at or let's let's say over an
equivalent dense models uh with similar
active parameter count is that at high
batch size you'll get more thorough put
because you'll get different experts
hand handling uh handling the the the
the tokens at same
um
so I'd say yes mixer of exp first model
definitely gives you a little bit more
trouble in terms of serving but the if
you have high volume it's definitely
worth it because you you you get much
more efficient in in processing these
tokens okay great um here I'll ask a few
more um since we do have some extra time
um but do let me know when you might
need to
leave so someone has ask asking
specifically about the architecture um
they want you to clarify does each layer
include attention routing and experts or
layers of attention then routing then
experts ah okay uh let me try to find
it
um yes so um the so the architecture of
mixol a * 7B is exactly the same as mol
7B uh as I've shown here uh so in mral
7B you first do for for each of the
input you do normalization you do
attenion residual Norm MLP residual so
it's um attention followed by MLP okay
and the only difference is in the MLP
layer here so instead of instead of so
after the attention layer and after the
res the attention residual instead of
doing MLP you do Ane MLP here so here
instead of just using one uh uh or a
couple uh one Matrix to process uh these
uh this hidden uh this L representation
you use eight experts well you you
choose two out of eight experts to
process
that right that makes sense um all right
let's
see
um give me a sec
last
um introduces extra load balancing
losses and loss function discontinu uh
disc
discontinuities um did you run into any
difficulties while training due to these
um
complications um yeah that that's a
really great question so I think uh to
to to try to clarify the question um my
understanding is that when you're
training uh mixture of experts models
you definitely want each of your expert
to be quite balanced
in the sense that they handled a similar
amount of uh tokens such that you're not
uh like I guess uh I was waiting for the
the slowest expert or the expert that
handles the most um so yes you
definitely need to uh do something to
make the the the load uh balance a bit a
bit better um in in trading but um uh I
I we we didn't run into any any big
troubles uh during training this this
model
and here's a question about R um here's
the here when Ane approach would be
preferred to a rag approach in a given
domain um pros and cons
Etc I I think these are athal so you can
use Ane model to do rack um like so I I
don't see why like I don't see why there
should be a conflict between the two um
yeah so so so like you can do uh dance
model no rag dance model rag Moe no rag
rag right and someone asked Can you
potentially swap out one expert and
insert a domain specific expert that
wasn't trained on the same training data
set like a customizable or modular
uhe I see um I think that's possible uh
given that you also you also need need
to so so after you swap out one of the
one of the experts and uh and and
replace it with the domain specific
expert uh but you after after you do the
swapping you definitely need to train
this model a bit more uh such that the
ging layers know how to such as the
gting layers know how to uh uh how how
to route the that's that's you have a
Med medical expert swapped in uh you you
need to train your gting layers a little
bit such
it knows how to how to handle medical
situations um and to basically treat
this this replaced expert quite
differently uh so I think it's totly
possible and very exciting research
Direction there there're being uh quite
interesting research done all like
merging and uh swapping and Franken
merge these models uh so I think that's
that's certainly some something
something uh very exciting looking
forward to
it okay great I'll ask a two more zoom
questions and that'll be it um so
someone asked during training is mixture
of experts less computationally
intensive since the gradients would
always be
7B how do how do the gradients back
propagate through the routing
head so um if I go to the routing layer
uh you will see that the um the the the
TP so so all the operations here are
differentiable so um the
there is no there's no uh I guess like
discrete operations such that the the
the gradient just stops there uh so this
thing this thing is entirely like end to
end differentiable um uh sorry what's
the first part of the question
again you're asking if training Moes is
less computationally
intensive uh so the the cost of training
is roughly proportional to the number of
active parameters you have um um and so
so it's roughly equivalent to training a
13B um and but you incur some extra
communication
cost okay great um last question um um
let's talk about even bigger models even
if we're moving away from the Paro
Frontier like those 8X 22 8x3 or even 8X
100 plus spilling parameter models you
see any further um serving challenges
when one GPU cannot even hold a full
expert after heavy
quantization I see um yes so I I think
if you have one
GPU I think I would go for a dance model
or uh um or or or a heavily quantized uh
mixture of expert model um and about
like what you said about U like having
more module experts like having 128
experts I think that's something super
exciting uh because that basically
allows you to specialize your um uh
basically allows your experts to
specialize a bit more um and that's
always exciting you can always uh reduce
the number of uh you you can always make
the expert specialized um uh better uh
and you you can pick basically allow
giving your gating gating layers more
power to choose like which experts are
are the best for this token um I think
for serving purposes that will
definitely make things very very hard um
even like even after having quantization
if if you have 128 experts um then and
potentially you you you we're talking
about multi like having the the model
model in multiple nodes that will make
the well I guess both make the make the
Implement implementation harder and also
the uh and and also the communication
cost higher so that's something you
probably want to leave to a to a model
provider uh through API like serving
yourself but I think for like mix X
model Mix A Time 7B is definitely after
quantization is definitely very um very
doable on on single
GPU all right great thanks for answering
u a bunch of questions from very curious
folks um so thanks again Albert for the
amazing talk and the time today