okay hi
everyone okay so for today we're going
to um you know I guess do a 180 from
where we were on Tuesday and so today um
I'm going to talk about um syntactic
structure linguistic structure of human
language sentences dependency passing
and how well dependency and then how you
go about building dependency paes so um
we're um solidly inter linguistic Zone
today um how many people in the audience
have done a Linguistics class yay okay
there's some people have done
Linguistics classes okay great um and
for the rest of you well you know this
is your chance to see a little bit of
human language structure and if you like
it you can enroll in a Linguistics class
later on um yeah so
oops so um you know so assignment two we
handed out on Tuesday so in the second
half of assignment two um what your job
to do is to build a neural dependency
paard using p torch um as you'll s we'll
sort of come to later on really the bit
that you have to build is just the
machine learning bit of making decisions
and really we give you most of the rest
of the new dependency paa but this is
also then a chance to remind you that
assignment two in that second half uses
py torch one of the leading deep
learning Frameworks um so if you're not
familiar with that it'd be a really good
idea to also go along to um the Friday
pie torch tutorial um though we have
tried to make assignment too so it's a
fairly good place for learning pie torch
as you go along um we'll say more soon
about um final projects but you're
certainly already in encourage to come
and meet with Tas or me about final
projects and we're putting up
information about the T so you can know
more about them on um the office hours
page okay so let's get straight into it
and start looking at linguistic
structure so um in in um thinking about
linguistic structure of human languages
there are two primary ways um that
people have thought about it so one way
is um using the idea that linguists
normally call phrase structure which is
then represented in terms of what um
computer scientists normally know as
context free grammars so I'm going to
spend a couple of minutes um going over
that view of things but you know
actually it's not the main one that I'm
going to talk about in this class I'm
going to spend most of this class
talking about an alternative way of
thinking about things called dependency
grammars um there are actually some
correspondences you can make between the
two ways of thinking about things but
I'm not going to go through into those
um here today so for the constituency
grammar or phrase structure um version
of things the way that you go about
thinking about the structure of human
languages is well there are words
languages have lots of words hundreds of
thousands of words but it seems like a
lot of the words nearly all the words in
fact fall into a few basic classes that
represent their nature and how they
behave in sentences so for words like
the examples here we have nouns so cat
is a noun door is a noun but you know
something like Linguistics is also a
noun so we have nouns um and then we
have other kinds of words so something
like cuddly is an adjective a word that
can modify nouns um and then we have
theth for the the cuddly cat um the is
sort of a slightly more complex one as
to how to name um normally in modern
Linguistics refer to words like that as
a determiner you might also see the name
article and when sometimes when people
try to shoehorn um human language into
eight part of speech categories that
they say it's an adjective that doesn't
really behave like regular adjectives
and then we have words like by or
through or on and to and ones like that
and so they're then prepositions right
so we have these classes and with lots
of words fitting into each class and so
they're referred to conventionally as
parts of speech but then once we've got
words we start putting them into bigger
units so the cuddly cat is some kind of
unit and so it seems like this is a um
explication of a noun cat and so this
gets referred to as a noun phrase um and
then by the door well this is a phrase
um but actually it has inside it this
the door and that's a noun phrase but
this bigger unit here of by the door is
then a prepositional
phrase and we can continue to build
bigger units so inside you know this we
have this phrase that we've already
looked at with the noun phrase and a
prepositional phrase but then we can
have another noun phrase the cuddly cat
and we can put them together and build a
bigger noun phrase the cuddly Cat by the
door and so to represent this you can
start to write um a phrase structure
grammar or a context free grammar that
represents what are the possibilities
for building up sentences here in
English those similar kinds of phrase
structure grammars can be written for
other languages so this is sort of
starting to give you possible structures
for a noun phrase so you can have a noun
phrase just goes to a determiner
followed by a noun but then as well as
the cat and a dog you can have the large
cats so you might say that okay rather
than that I might want to have as a
better rule that a noun phrase goes to a
determiner and optional adjective
and then a noun if you think about it
you can sort of have multiple adjectives
so you can have the the large um green
cat or something like that um so you can
really get multiple adjectives that are
heing and that sort of star the clean
star says you can have lots of them um
the large cuddly green cat um but then
you can stick things after the now
phrase so you can put these
prepositional phrases like in a crate so
we might also want to say that a noun
phrase can be Rewritten as a noun phrase
followed by a prepositional phrase where
a prepositional phrase um can be
represented by preposition followed by a
noun phrase and somewhere we're also
going to want to represent our parts of
speech membership so a
determiner um can go to words like a or
and an adjective can go to words like
large cuddly or many other words that
I'm not going to write
down and a preposition can go to words
like in on
under Etc after that okay so now I've
got a a little grammar here and this
little grammar here could sort of make
everything
I've gotten these sentences well
actually can do this one too it can do
the large barking one where there are
multiple ones um but then if I start
going Beyond these noun phrases and say
think of sentences like talk to the cat
or talk to the large cuddly dog by the
door well now I've got here a verb talk
and I've again got a
preposition so I might um then have more
rules that says I can have a verb phrase
and the verb phrase can go to a verb and
then a prepositional phrase and then
that could explain these two sentences
as well and in this kind of way I can
start to build up a grammar of the
structure of English sentences as a
context free grammar make sense yeah
okay um and so that's
um what is being quite commonly done in
linguistics and elsewhere
um okay
uh yeah uh so let me just do that once
more but behind in this one so one thing
I can do here is say oh I have I'm going
to look at this with its phrase
structure and if I write it upside down
to give myself some space for later you
know I could start
um making a phrase structure that is of
this
sentence um and I'll start to run out of
space but I can sort of start to make
this phrase structure of the sentence so
that's um phrase structure um but
there's another form of
representation that has been fairly
widely used in linguistics and we're
going and has been commonly used in NLP
and we're going to use for the paes we
built and that's dependency structure so
dependency structure represents things
in a slightly different way it thinks
about words that are the main word or
head or something and then which words
they take as modifiers or arguments so
for look in the large crate in the
kitchen by the door well this is um
describing a looking command so that the
head of the whole thing is looking um
and then looking is taking one or more
arguments or modifiers and well what the
looking is saying here is well what you
want to do is look in the large crate so
we are looking in something and then
when what we're looking in is a crate
and then the crate has some modifiers
it's a large crate it's the large crate
and then the crate um is also um placed
somewhere it's placed in the kitchen so
that in the kitchen is also modifying
crate um and then we've got over here
the by the door um
well the by the door um is also
modifying crate so we've also got a link
down over to here and that gives us our
piece of structure here which having
filled that in makes me realize I
actually got it wrong in when I was
doing the constituency representation
whoopsie so I should get my CU in the
constituency representation I made the
kitchen by the door into a phrase that
was actually wrong whoops bad me um so
what I should have actually had um was
we had another prepositional phrase that
went to a noun phrase of in the kitchen
and then both of
those were coming off a bigger noun
phrase like that whoopsie okay um I get
it right most of the time okay but so
this idea of um dependency structure is
that we're sort of finding what is the
head word and then we're saying which
things modify the headword and either of
these represent ations we can be using
um to sort of work out what the
structure of sentences is in terms of
which words go together and which words
modify other words and so the basic idea
is so when humans communicate we
communicate in a linear stream right so
that if it's um conventional writing
systems it's a linear stream of words
that you're reading if it's spoken
language like you're understanding me
speaking right now it's not a linear
stream of words it's a linear Sound
Stream and you know like when people
speak there aren't any you know there
isn't white space between words when
people speak you know occasionally
people pause at the end of a clause or
sentence or something but in general I'm
just sort of speaking continuous words
that run one into each other so that
there's a a a linear sequence of sounds
coming out my mouth um and you have to
do all bit like that but the but if
you're then thinking oh gee
um I can actually understand Chris
talking then somehow you're taking that
linear stream and you're turning it into
a meaning where certain words are
modifying other words and you have these
bigger units um like constituents that
are understanding the meaning of the
sentence and so human listeners need to
work out what modifies what to be able
to understand sentences
correctly and so similarly our models
need to be able to understand sentence
structure in order to be able to
interpret language correctly and so for
what we're going to be doing for
building dependency paes is we're going
to be
explicitly building a neural network
model that says let's find the structure
of these sentences um in way we actually
move away from that later on because
when we move into um Transformer
language models they just take in the um
sequence of words but actually inside
the parameters of the newal network they
recognizing and building the same kind
of structural units and we'll talk about
that later in the class um to give you
more of a sense of how um these you know
understanding what modifies what is
important for interpretation um here are
a few funny examples from newspaper
headlines and they're funny examples
because you get um there sentences don't
just have one way of interpreting them
um when you have a sequence of words
commonly in human languages sequence of
words are ambiguous and it's relying on
human interpretation of what makes sense
and what goes together to work out how
to read them so here's a first example
um scientists count whales from space um
now that's um ambiguous and you can give
this two possible readings so how can
you give this um headline two possible
readings yeah one is that they scien in
space counting whales and the other one
is that they're whales from in space
yeah so one possibility is so we've got
this prepositional phrase this is a
prepositional phrase here one
possibility is that this prepositional
phrase is
modifying or is the OB yeah it's
modifying
whales um so they're whales from space
and the other possibility is that it's
the counting that's happening from space
so the scientists are counting it from
space okay so that corresponds to my two
pictures here um so in one picture it's
the counting that is happening from
space um which is actually the right
interpretation of what the article is
about um but in the other interpretation
we have space whales um and the and the
scientists are counting the space whales
that are arriving or something like that
and so then we have um the from space
that are modifying the
whales okay um so what we have here
right is a prepositional phrase which
comes after a noun phrase it's just a
onew noun phrase here whales that's fine
and then before that is a verb and so
the thing so one place in English where
you get a lot of ambiguities is from
these prepositional phrases because
whenever you get prepositional phrases
and prepositional phrases are really
common in English if you think about it
whenever you get them like this it's
always ambiguous as
to oops it's always amb uous as to what
earlier thing in the sentence they
dependent of um and so um you know you
can sort of put in another prepositional
phrase in the morning or something like
that and so then the ambiguities just
multiply and so the important thing to
notice here about human language is
human language is in synta I terms
globally ambiguous right so in
programming languages you have local
ambiguities interpretation how many
people have done a compilers class I
think very few these days anyone done a
compilers class okay it looks like less
people have done a compilers class than
a Linguistics class that's
interesting okay well I won't make too
many analogies to compilers classes in
you know when I was young you know that
was still the old days kind CS
curriculum where writing interpreters
and compilers were seen as the main sta
of Computer Science Education but no
more I guess um yeah so um in
programming languages you can have a
local ambiguity but ambiguities are
always resolved right so we have simple
rules and programming languages that
else is um construed with the nearest if
um you know it's a bit different in
Python because it's indentation but you
know There are rules that so there's
never Global ambiguity in a programming
language um and but human languages just
aren't like that right that there's
nothing that resolves which of these two
readings is correct if I made it a
bigger sentence that'd still be
ambiguous you're just sort of meant to
read it and use context in your
intelligence to decide um what's going
on and so to take a a bigger but real
example um this is the kind of boring
sentence that you can read in the Wall
Street Journal most mornings um the
board approved its acquisition by Royal
Trustco limited of Toronto for $27 a
share at its monthly meeting um so um
what you can see in this sentence is
we've got a verb and then we've got a
noun phrase and then what are what after
that we have four prepositional phrases
in a row okay so what do these
prepositional phrases modify so what
does by Royal Trustco limited
modify the acquisition right so it's the
acquisition by Royal Trust Co then of
Toronto
modifies so it's Royal Trustco limited
of
Toronto um so yeah later on
prepositional phrases can also modify
earlier prepositional phrases or at
least the noun phrase inside them World
Trustco limited okay for $27 a
share is back to modifying the
acquisition okay at its monthly
meeting is is yeah it's the approval so
it's gone way back up to there right um
but you know um yeah so you know so if
you start having sentences um with a
whole bunch of prepositional phrases
like this you can start getting more and
more ambiguities of attachment I mean
you don't get the
full you don't get the sort of full free
choice factorial number of attachment
points because there is a restriction
that these dependencies don't cross um
so once you've gone back further you
have to stay equally far back or go even
back further back again but nevertheless
so the number of readings you get is
Catalan series which is a series you see
in a whole bunch of other places if
you've done any graph Theory or anything
like that you know if you're doing
triangulations you get um cat alarms
because you get the same property um
that things don't cross so it's an
exponentially growing um sequence of
possible readings and so it quickly gets
very big so I think when you you've got
four prepositional phrases you get 13
readings and if you have five you 27 and
you know grows up from there so you get
a lot of ambiguities but the crucial
thing to notice is you know human beings
read sentences like this every morning
or at least people who work in banking
do while you know having their Corn
Flakes and you know they their brain
doesn't explode trying to think about
the 13 different readings and which one
is correct right we just sort of do this
as we go along and it's sort of obvious
um okay let's just do a couple more
examples of where we get ambiguities in
um in human language so a different one
you get is coordination scope ambiguity
so shuttle veteran and longtime Nas
executive Fred Gregory appointed the
board how is this sentence
ambiguous it mean two people or one
person yeah so there can either be one
person Fred Gregory and they're both a
shuttle veteran and a NASA
executive or it can be that there are
two people there's a shuttle veteran and
um there's a longtime Nessa executive
Fred
Gregory okay yeah so and we'd be kind of
capturing those by having extra grammar
rules where a noun phrase can go to a
noun phrase a conjunction and a noun
phrase um but then another another thing
that you get in English is um apposition
so you can have a noun phrase that's a
descriptive noun phrase of another noun
phrase like a name um you know the
author Fred Gregory or something like
that um um saying the word English again
I I I meant to comment um so you know
I'm I'm only going to give English
examples here um in different languages
you don't get all the same ambiguities
um so if you're familiar with same
Chinese um you might have thought about
the prepositional phrase example of wait
a minute we don't have that one because
the prepositional phrase modifying the
verb would appear before the verb and
the object noun would be afterward so it
would be completely unambiguous and
that's true um but you know that doesn't
mean that Chinese is unambiguous Chinese
has lots of very bad
ambiguities and um yeah it's just that
you know different languages have
different syntactic structures okay um
here's so sometimes um in English
especially when you're sort of in a more
written form rather than having an
explicit con coordination word you can
just sort of use ju to position with a
comma um to have the idea of
coordination so here's a um fun example
um from the first Trump Administration
of how we can have a coordination scope
ambiguity um doctor no heart cognitive
issues um right so again this is the
same kind of coordination scope
ambiguity that it can either be kind of
no hard and cognitive issues being
conjoined together like that or else it
could be that it's no heart or cognitive
issues being conjoined um together like
that you make the choice
um okay uh let's
see oh this this is this is my risque
one for a different kind of ambiguity um
trigger warning um students get
firsthand job
experience so this one is also um an
ambiguity um you know as to whether
you're having the um the
firsthand and then both the job and the
firsthand a modifying experience or
there's this other reading if you have a
smutty mind that might come to you
um okay one more fun one okay mutilated
body washes up on Rio Beach to be used
for Olympics beach
volleyball okay so what are what are the
two possible readings of this sentence
you know these are real examples from
quality newspapers
um okay what are the two readings of
this sentence
yeah so we've got so so the here we have
one of these
infinitival um so infinitival verb
phrase to be used for Olympic beach
volleyball and for
these as well you know they kind of have
the same effect as prepositional phrases
um that they can can modify um different
things um so it can either be the Rio
Beach that's going to be used for the
Olympic beach volleyball or it's going
to be the mutilated body that gets used
for the um beach
volleyball okay um yeah so the so these
are the kind of ways in which we sort of
want to use um the structure of the
sentence to understand what they're
meaning we also use it in lots of sort
of just sort of M
practical ways um when we're building
various kinds of natural language
processing systems so you know a kind of
thing that people often in Practical
systems do is that they want to get out
facts of various kinds so for people who
um do stuff with bioinformatics that
they commonly want to get out things
like protein protein interaction facts
and so commonly you can get those kind
of facts out by looking for patterns so
you know have a verb of interacts that's
going to be indicating um an interaction
pattern and well it's going to be taking
arguments so it's going to be taking a
subject and interacts with the
prepositional argument and so that will
be um an interaction that kisy whatever
that is interacts with sass a but in
this case the Sass a is coordinated with
the kai a and the kai B so it's also
going to end up interacting with those
two other things as well and so you can
use the sort of sentence structure
patterns of a dependency PA to be
getting out the kind of um facts and
events that you're interested in for
something like an um event understanding
system and people you know do these kind
of anal analyses over biomedical texts
to build up the kind of structured
databases of known protein protein
interactions and things of that
sort okay so linguistic structure is
useful um and it's syntactically very
ambiguous and so you should think of
humans as active interpreters that are
using their contextual knowledge both of
earlier stuff in the text knowledge of
the world around them how the world
Works to work out the right um structure
yeah so now I want to go on um and show
you a bit more about sort of dependency
grammars which is what we're going to be
using so for dependency syntax that it
postulates that you can capture the
structure of a sentence by having these
sort of asymmetric um dependent
relations which we might just call
arrows which are going from heads to
dependence so here the sentence is um
bills on ports and immigration were
submitted by Senator Brownback
Republican of Kansas and we sort of
picking out heads um and then we got um
things that depend on them that modify
them um yeah so if you're on the um
video audience and you are educated in
the United States and you're over the
age of 50 um or if you happen to go to
one of those kind of private schools
where they also teach Latin um you might
have seen sentence diagramming um so
read Kellogg um sentence diagramming was
something that was actually very
widespread um in American Education um
which really was a it was a some it was
really dependency grammar was a sort of
a somewhat quirky form of dependency
grammar where you had to write lines at
different angles and stuff like that but
basically you're writing sort of heads
and their dependence underneath them
with different funny shaped lines um it
also was dependency
grammar okay um so this is the start of
a dependency grammar but just like the
the funny angled lines of sentence
diagramming normally people want to add
some more information than that um and
so most commonly um that the arrows are
then typed by giving the name of some
grammatical relation so something can be
the noun subject or an oblique or an
appositional modifier or a case mark or
things like that um and um I I'm just
trying to give you the idea of
dependency grammars I'm not expecting
you to master all of these names and
ways of doing things um and you know
there are different systems of deciding
what's heads and dependence and not all
the details are important what you
should get into your head is just sort
of the basic idea of what one of these
does and some sense of oh it should be
at the phrase level it should be
representing what's modifying what so we
do actually ask some questions um on the
assignment and so for the cases like the
prepositional phrase what is it
modifying you should be able to give the
right answer to
that okay
um yeah um okay so uh this is just a
little bit more um vocabulary so yeah we
have these or dependencies and so I'm
going to say that they connect between a
head and a dependent but sometimes
people use other words like governor and
modifier and things like that um and so
dependencies are generally taken and
will be taking them as forming a tree so
you've got something that's connected as
cyclic and has a single root to it so
our single root is the top of the
sentence here
um so
um dependency so although what you see
most often these days either in a
Linguistics class or when you get taught
CS
103 at Stanford or computer science what
you see there is normally context free
grammars or phase structure grammars I
mean really you know it is dependency
grammars that have the really long
history so really the predominant way of
representing the structure of human
languages throughout human history is
dependency grammar um so who linguist um
Herald as the first dependency
grammarian or really the first person
who tried to write the grammar of a
human language period was panani so
panani was working with Sanskrit um
panani lived so long ago that actually
people don't really know when he lived I
mean he lived somewhere between about
the 4th and 8th Century before the
common ER
but really no one knows when um but you
know he lived um sort of up in part of
actually what's now Afghanistan um and
um for Motivated for largely religious
reasons um he said about developing a
grammar of Sanskrit and the way he
represented the syntax of Sanskrit was
using a dependency grammar um so there
was a lot of work on grammar in Arabic
in the first Millennium they used
dependency grammars um in contrast um
the idea of sort of having context free
grammars that's really really recent so
the first work on um phrase structure
grammars dates to the 40s and then was
sort of um canonicalized by the work of
Chomsky in the
1950s yeah so um a fact for the computer
science part of people in the audience
so computer dear computer scientists if
you know about Chomsky computer
scientists normally know two things
about Chomsky one is they hate on the
Chomsky hierarchy that they were forced
to learn um in CS 103 or equivalent
classes and the second one is he's a
very left politician um but um if I only
deal with the first one of the two now
um the Chomsky hierarchy was not
invented either to torture Elementary
computer scientists um or um to explain
fundamental facts about formal language
Theory the Chomsky hierarchy was
actually invented in thinking about
human languages because at that time and
in stuff that's come more often it was
commonly the case that um people were
modeling human languages with um Regular
finite so finite State grammar
equivalent mechanisms and Chomsky wanted
to argue that that was a completely
inadequate um formalism to represent um
the complexity of human language and so
it was in the context of arguments about
human language was why he developed um
the Chomsky
hierarchy okay um yeah so anyway uh
that's enough of the history of that um
here's my uh picture of part of panan
grammar but actually or a version of it
actually um this is really really
misleading and because one of the
astounding facts about P's grammar and
part of why no one knows what century he
lived in was Pan's grammar was composed
orally um so this sort of kind of blows
my mind you know it's it seems you know
um some of um the famous things in the
west like Homer's works right the
Odyssey and The Iliad right they were
originally oral works that were passed
down um in oral form you know you can
that seems hard to do but you can kind
of believe if you did plays in high
school or something that someone could
um memorize the Odyssey perhaps um but
the idea that people could memorize a
grammar of a
language passing it down for hundreds of
years um kind of blows my mind um but
that's exactly what happened um yeah
with pines grammar um so you know really
although this is sort of an old
birchbark manuscript you know that
really it probably dates from about a
millennium after panan um composed um
his grammar okay getting back to the um
modern days um yeah so um for things to
know yeah so I mean we don't want you to
fixate on the sort of details of
dependency grammar structure providing
you have the rough idea but just one
thing um that you can possibly be
confused about is you know there people
do things in different ways one way in
which they don't agree is even which way
to draw the arrows so some people draw
arrows um from the head pointing at the
dependence and there are other people
who draw the arrows starting at the
dependent and pointing back at the heads
um so um for modern dependency grammar
um largely follows the work of um Lucien
tener a French um linguist um he did the
um arrows pointing from the head to the
dependent and so that's what I'm doing
today but um you'll see both um we sort
of said that you know normally you
assume that you have a tree with a
single root it's kind of common and it
works out more easily for the paing if
you sort of add to a sentence a sort of
a fake root node so you know that that's
going to be the starting point and it's
going to take one dependent which is the
word that's the head of the sentence
and then you're going to work down from
there okay um so um before getting more
into doing dependency paing I just
wanted to sort of take a little detour
um to tell you about the you know the
importance um that happened with sort of
the rise of annotated data um in natural
language processing so and you know this
is sort of an interesting flip slop
that's occurred but we're going to sort
of today go in One Direction and later
class we'll go in the other direction um
so in early natural language processing
um people started to see oh human
languages have structure so what we
should do is start writing rules for the
structure of human languages and you
know I start writing a few context free
grammar rules for the structure of
English on that early slide and you
could also write dependency grammar
structure rules so um people tried to do
natural language processing by having
rules grammar rules dictionaries of
parts of speech and things like that and
that gave you paes um that in retrospect
worked out pretty badly and it worked
out pretty badly for a number of reasons
one reason is that although there are
these sort of very canonical clear
structures in human languages there's a
very long tale of messy stuff where all
kinds of weird um usages start to emerge
in human languages which sort of means
you just got this it's just really hard
to get coverage for handwritten language
um and that's because people you humans
use language creatively right so you
know you can start thinking of some of
the things um that you've probably come
I'm probably not very good at Young
persons slang usages of grammar these
days but you know um the kind of ones
that you might be still familiar with
right Star Wars you have Yoda talk where
you rearrange the sentences but people
still understand them right so that's
changing the word order and earlier on
than that there was sort of a uh little
a bit of a f to putting not at the end
of the sentences of that's a really
great idea not um and well you know
people um learn to understand that but
it's different to regular grammar right
so it it's really hard to write a full
grammar but the bigger reason actually
is the problem of ambiguity I talked
about right that if you just write a
grammar well you know my sentence with
the prepositional phrases had 13
different paes and you didn't have much
reason to choose between them but you
know if you had information about how
often words modify other words then you
could get some statistics and start to
predict in which order which things
modify other things and so people wanted
to start to be able to do that
prediction that underlies probalistic or
machine learning models and so to be
able to do that that led you know sort
of earliest antecedence in the 6s but
really starting in the late 80s and into
the '90s that people decide you the way
make progress in um natural language
processing natural language
understanding is to build annotated data
resources and so all through the '90s
and the 2000s decades the name of the
game for a lot of natural language
processing was people building annotated
data resources and then building machine
learning systems on top using those
resources now that's kind of gone into
reverse and gone away again with large
language models which will to another
week or so but here's an example so this
is the universal dependencies tree Banks
which I'm actually been heavily involved
with and it's a cool resource for all
kinds of purposes because it's actually
a wide
crosslinguistic um database where
there's over a 100 different languages
um with sentences passed with a uniform
um dependency formalism so it's actually
really good for things like cross
linguistic work and psychol linguistic
work work but you know what these are is
taking sentences I think mamar was a
famous goat trainer or
something um and putting a dependency
structure on it it's sort of all written
there sort of very squished down and
human beings are producing these
dependency structures and then this is
giving us data that we can learn things
from dependency like dependency paes
from and indeed um for what you do on
homework 2 this is precisely what you'll
be using is data of this sort um to
build a dependency paa and it's going to
learn that you know that you have goat
trainers um and you have famous trainers
and so it'll build up sort of statistics
and information to predict what kinds of
things are
likely um yeah so starting off building
a tree Bank like that
um feels kind of like oh this is going
to be slow hard work work and it is
actually slow hard work um but it proved
to be a very effective strategy because
it gave wonderful reusable resources
that once people had done it once all
sorts of people could use it to build
paes part of speech taggers um to do
psycholinguistic models and all kinds of
things you'd get the sort of
distributional frequency information
that's good for machine learning it also
provided one other thing that's crucial
is it gave a method to evaluate systems
to say how good they are at um producing
paes I mean this may seem kind of
comical to you in the modern era of
machine learning but the fact of the
matter is when people did natural
language processing in the 50s 60s 7s
nobody had evaluation methods the way
you showed people you had good paa is
you ran the program you said type in a
sentence look at what it look look it's
worked it's a really good paa um you
know there was no systematic valuation
of NLP systems whatsoever um so actually
saying look here's uh thousand hand
passas sentences let's evaluate how well
your paa does on those you know that was
actually a revolutionary new development
um that happened in the um
well end of the 80s but especially in
the
90s okay um so now we going have it now
that we have all of those knowledge um
we're going to um want to start building
dependency paes and so I'm going to um
show a particular way of dependency
passing which is the one you're going to
use in the assignment um but you know
just first off it's sort of worth just
thinking for a moment you know what kind
of information should a dependency paer
have to make decisions so these are kind
of the four factors the sort of the
obvious things that are useful for
dependency passing I mean the first one
is sort of thinking of the two words at
the ends of the arrow as to whether they
are plausible right so that for um
discussion of the outstanding issues was
completed um so to have um discussion of
issues right that's that's a plausible
dependency um to have um you know what's
the silly one to have something like um
the being a dependent of completed that
makes no sense at all so you know what
words there are involved um the second
one is dependency distance so you can
have longdistance dependencies that go a
long way but most dependenc sees are
short distance you know a lot of words
are depending on their neighboring words
at a very short distance so that's a
good preference to have um as well as
just the distance it's somewhat
informative knowing what's in between so
it's rare for dependencies to span verbs
or
punctuation um and then there's a final
one which is to think of the veency of
heads and that's how many
arguments um they take so that if you
have sort of something like a verb broke
um well it probably has something um to
the left because it probably has who did
the breaking and it probably has
something to the right um cuz there
might be the cup or something like that
um but you know it doesn't have to be
that cuz it could be the cup broke um so
you can have something to the left but
nothing to the right but you sort of
have to have something to the left and
conversly you can't have any number of
things you can't sort of just say he
broke the cup the sorcer um the dish um
right so it doesn't take just lots of
arguments to the left so we've got a
notion of veency like
that um yeah there's one other tricky
little notion on dependency paring which
is
normally um normally dependencies kind
of Nest like this um and nesting
dependencies corresponds to a tree
structure as you'd have in a context
free grammar
[Music]
yeah because in a sense when I read the
sentence
which I thought that the most important
discussion
[Music]
so so I will fair enough I will assert
that this
is uh
sentence and discussion is the subject
of the
verb completed and you know normally for
a sentence we say the main thing in the
sentence is its verb and so yeah so
that's why the root is heading to
completed and the subject of the verb is
also an important thing but the
arguments of the verb like the subject
of the verb the object of the verb if
there is one prepositional phrase
modifiers they're all taken as
dependence of the
verb
yeah up on that is
it is it not the that you start
with so um if you have a sentence with a
verb like this um it's always that is
always the answer I mean some of the
details here depend on languages but
there are languages in which you don't
have to have a verb in a sentence um and
you can get things like
um um just I mean you can do it in sort
of very restricted ways in in in English
right so if you just sort of say easy as
pie um there's no verb and so then
you're saying easy um the adjective
which is sort of the predicate adjective
is then the head of the
sentence
sorry like a question like what is the
story is the is like we would still look
at that as the that is complicated some
people would say it is um and some
people would say it isn't um and
particular in Universal dependencies we
don't actually say that is is the head
of the sentence but I don't want to get
too far into this if you want you could
sort of look more at how things are done
but you know I want to fully admit that
you know dependency grammar isn't sort
of one uniquely defined Theory people
have had different ideas of which things
to take as the head in various
circumstances and they argue about it
linguists argue about what the right
structure is to put over all sorts of
sentences but that the fact that people
do things different ways doesn't mean
that everybody doesn't agree that there
are units there are phrases and
modifiers and ambiguities and so on
between them okay um yeah so normally we
get this sort of nesting that
corresponds to what you can build with
context free grammar structure but
sometimes in human languages you get
dependencies that don't Nest so you get
sentences like I'll give a talk tomorrow
on new networks where actually the on
new networks is modifying the talk where
the
yesterday um is an argument of sorry the
tomorrow is an argument of give and so
you get these Crossing dependencies
which are referred to as non-projective
dependencies um you also get them when
you form questions so who did Bill buy
the coffee from yesterday that the who
is the object of the preposition from
but it's been moved out the front and so
that again um gives us
non-projective um if you think about
it um yeah you can still say um that you
have a dependency tree but it's got the
words in different orders and so one of
the things that you have to cope with
for full dependency PA
is dealing with this non projectivity
but I mean actually we're not going to
deal with it in our paes we're only
going to do um projective dependency
paing okay so there are various ways
that people do dependency paring people
have done it by dynamic programming
people who've done it using graph
algorithms if I have enough time at the
end I might mention that again people
have done it with constraint
satisfaction methods if you saw those in
cs220 21 um but the most common way in
practice that's emerged um has been this
transition based paing um which is kind
of sort of interesting as well and gives
the sort of a very simple machine
learning mechanism um so it makes it
good for um assignment two and so that's
what we're going to explore
here okay so um what we do
um in Greedy decision based paing in
transition based paing is you know this
is where it's unfortunate that only two
people in the class have done a
compiler's class um so um so a simple
form of passing that's also used in
compilers classes something called shift
reduced paing where you start sort of
bottom up and you start putting little
units together and build bigger
constituents but um if most people have
hav't seen it that's not going to be um
very much um help so I'm going to give
you a concrete example so the things to
know is we' have two data structure well
we have more than two I guess um for
dealing with the sentence we have two
data structures we have a buffer which
has the words of our input sentence and
then we start building pieces of um
sentence structure which we put on a
stack and a little trick to know is for
the buffer the the top is written to the
left and for the stack the top is
written to the right um and so we take
actions which are like shift and reduce
actions and when we take ARC building
actions we build up a set of dependency
arcs which are going to be the
dependency structure of our sentence and
that's all incredibly abstract um and so
I'm going to show an example um which
hopefully will a bit give the idea um
so here's an example so I want to do
this very um simple example um of
passing up the sentence I ate fish um so
I so the way I do this is I have my
stack and so I start by putting the root
symbol on my stack and then I have in my
buffer all the words of the sentence and
so that's the sort of start condition
I've written and very small print there
then for each step of processing I have
a choice of three operations I can
either shift which moves the top word on
the buffer onto the stack or I can do
left Arc or right Arc and these are my
two reduce operations that build a
little bit of syntactic structure by
saying that one word is a dependent of
another word in either a left or a right
direction so here a sequence of
operations I can take and um so starting
off the first thing I can do is shift so
then I've moved I onto the stack um I
can decide that I want to shift again
and so then I'd take eight and also move
it onto the stack and so I've now got
three things on my
stack so at this point you know I can do
other things I mean in particular a left
Arc is going to say well I can take the
top two things on the stack and make the
uh the thing on the top The Head and the
thing one down on the stack a dependent
of it so if I do a left Arc operation
I'm effectively saying that the I is a
dependent of eight and then I pop both
of then I pop the dependent off the
stack back but I add on that I've built
um a dependency that I made I a
dependent of eight I could then do
another shift operation so I shift fish
um from the buffer onto the stack and
then I can do a right Arc which says um
okay I'm going to have fish as a
dependent of eight so then fish
disappears from the stack and I add in
this new dependency saying fishes
dependent of eight um I then do right
Arc again um which is then saying that
um eight is a dependent of root so I'm
left with just root on my stack and I've
built a new dependent saying eight is a
dependent of root and at this point I've
gone to the finishing condition my
finishing condition is that my buffer is
empty and my um stack contains just the
word root um and so this gives me a
little step set of operations referred
to as the transitions of
transition-based passing and by making a
sequence of these different transitions
I can build sentence structure and I've
got choices of when to shift and when to
reduce and whether to reduce left or
reduce right the arc left Arc right and
so by making different ones of those
choices I could make any structure for
the sentence that I wanted to so you
know if I somehow thought that this
sentence should have a different
structure and that I should be the head
and eights are dependent of that and
fishes are dependent of that well I
could achieve this by making some
different choices as to I'd now be
saying I was doing a right Arc operation
so that eight would become a dependent
of I rather than the other way around so
the choices of which oper operations I
take determine the syntactic structure
the set of dependencies that I have
built um which are my set of
dependencies down here now the center of
dependencies I built were exactly the
right ones because at each step I took
the right
operation um and so the essential um
idea of um transition based paing and
where it came to the four was
um there was a particular guy who's I've
got a photo of him in somewhere in a bit
I thought um so yoram Nea um is a
Swedish NLP person um and in the early
2000s um he came up with the idea of um
rather than doing the kind of dynamic
programming and chart paing and things
that people commonly used to do with
PES these days we have machine Lear
learning so maybe we could build a fast
efficient paa and the way we're going to
build it is with this making a sequence
of Transitions and it'll be the job of
the machine learning to predict what is
the right transition at each point in
time so if you do that you know at each
point you're dealing with one thing and
so the number of operations you're doing
to pass a sentence is linear so this
gives a linear time passing algorithm
whereas if um you've seen context free
grammars and stuff like that in CS 103
and you want to do anything where you're
fully considering the paes and
structures of context free grammars
you've then got a cubic time algorithm
which is much less Pleasant to be
dealing with um so for the simplest form
of transition-based paing you do no
search whatsoever at each step you're
just predicting the next transition and
so you're doing this sort of sequence of
transition predictions as machine
learning operations and that sequence
gives you the path structure of the
sentence and the essential result that
Neo is able to show is that machine
learning um is good enough that you can
do this and get a very accurate paraa
despite the fact that it no search
whatsoever is just doing predictions in
this
way okay um so how did so when he did in
2005 that was before neural networks
came to the four and so the way he was
doing it was by using a sort of an older
style um symbolic feature based um
machine Learning System so he had a big
classifier which might have been a list
istic regression classifier or something
else like a support Vector machine and
so to power that he was using indicator
features so the kind of features you'd
use is that the word on the top of the
stack is the word good and it's part of
speech as an adjective or um the word um
on the top of the stack is good but the
word that's sort of second on the stack
is the verb had
right you'd get these sort of
combinations of matching functions and
they would be used as features in a
machine Learning System to predict the
pars um but the problem is that once you
started building these features that
were conjunctions of multiple terms you
ended up with millions and millions of
features right because you putting
particular words and features um and
then you're combining choices of
multiple words so they're just millions
and millions of features so had to deal
with millions and millions of features
and furthermore individual features were
exceedingly sparse that you barely ever
saw them right that you'd have a feature
that only turned up you know 10 times in
a million sentences because they are
matching these very precise systems so
on the one hand um by making these
feature conjunctions paing got more
accurate and indeed people produced
pretty accurate paes in those days but
they had sort of these unappealing
characteristics of this
sort um yeah so uh before going on
further I should just explain how we
evaluate dependency paes um so um to
evaluate dependency paes we're basically
assessing are you getting the
dependency arcs arrows your proposing
right um so here is someone's dependency
PA she saw the video
lecture
um well actually sorry that's the gold
pa okay that's a correct pa okay she saw
the video lecture that's a correct PA so
you can write out what are um the the
different
dependencies right so one's head is two
two's head is zero word three's head is
five words Four's head is five word
five's head is two so these pairs of
numbers represent our dependencies then
if someone proposes a PA of the sentence
you can literally say okay which of
these did they get right so they didn't
get this one right um they got the rest
of them right so they accuracy is 80%
and so sometimes people just assess the
arcs unlabeled and so that's referred to
as unlabeled dependency accuracy but
sometimes people also want to label them
with with um subject determiner object
Etc and say also are you getting the
labels right so in this case only two of
the five labels are right so the labeled
accuracy of the dependency passes is
40% okay um
so so that was sort of what people did
um until the mid
2010s um and and I sort of already
started saying this the problems with
indicator features were they were
sparse you didn't see them often they
were incomplete because there's some
words and combinations you've seen and
some you just didn't see in the training
data so you're missing features um but
the final problem is actually just
Computing all those um symbolic features
was just expensive it turns out that if
you did runtime analysis most of time in
the paing wasn't in doing the machine
learning decisions it was just simply in
Computing the features that you put into
this dependency paa so as new net
started to um show that they were
successful for things that suggested
that maybe you could build um a better
dependency paa by using a newal net um
transition-based dependency paa which
would benefit from the kind of dens and
compact um feature Vector
representations that we've already
started to see um and so that's um what
started to be explored and in
particular who was then a PhD student of
mine um and was head TA of 224n twice
actually in the earlier days um so um
she built um uh neural transition-based
dependency paa um and showed the success
of this method
um so this was um nea's transition-based
dependency paa um people had also
explored other methods of dependency
passing so these were two graph-based
dependency paes and essentially um for
the kind of um symbolic feature machine
learning methods um NE paa was really
fast because I was using this linear
trans um transition based paing idea
that depend the graph-based dependency
paes were way way slower right you know
they're about what 50 times slower um
but they were slightly more accurate you
can see here that you're getting a bit
better numbers so essentially what was
able to show was um you could build
something that was basically as accurate
as the best known um graph-based
dependency pases but it was fast like
other um transition based fases indeed
despite the fact that it's you might
think that oh now I've got real numbers
and matrices and stuff surely that
should be slowing me down the reality
was that the symbolic models spent so
much time in feature um computation that
actually you could make it faster at the
same time by using a newal
network okay so how did that work um
well so we've already seen word
embedding so it's going to exploit word
embed so it can use word representations
and that has the advantage that even if
you haven't seen particular words and
particular configurations you've seen
similar words and so it can exploit
what's likely in terms of word
similarity but it went a bit further
than that because why only have
distributed representations of words we
also have parts of speech and although I
sort of said just noun verb adjective
most actual systems in NLP of parts of
speech are much more fine grained so
they have different parts of speech for
plural nouns versus singular nouns so
they're sort of different symbols but
they're very similar to each other so we
might give them distributed
representation so they're also close to
each other and the same for the types of
our labels for dependencies some of them
are pretty closely related as well so
all of these were being given
distributed
representations and so then to represent
the state of the dependency paa for
predicting transitions what you were
doing is you had the same kind of stack
and buffer and you are taking the key
elements of the stack and the buffer
which are essentially the first thing on
the buffer the word that you would be
shifting if you're going to do a shift
and the two things at the top of the
stack so these are the things that if
you're either doing a left Arc or a
right Arc they're things that you're
considering combining so for those
you're going to be taking the
distributed representations of the word
and their parts of speech and also with
a bit more complexity um for
dependencies you've already constructed
if maybe something on the stack is
already involved in a dependency each of
those we're going to take their
distributed representations and we're
going to just concatenate them together
to produce a big um Vector in the same
way were concatenating together the five
words in the last class for predicting
whether something was the location or
not and then we're going to feed that um
into our neural network so um we our
input layer is our concatenate
distributed
representations we're going to put that
through a hidden layer which is like we
were talking about last time WX plus b
then put through a relue
nonlinearity and then we're going to put
above that the same kind of um another
multiply by a matri so we've got a
second layer of neural network uh plus
B2 and we're going to take the output of
that and then we're going to put that
through a soft Max that gives a
probability distribution over whether to
um shift or do a left Arc or a right Arc
operation and so the other way that this
crucially gave us more power is that
other people's dependency paes were
still using linear classifiers things
like support Vector machines or logistic
regressions where we had a deep neural
network that gave us a nonlinear
classifier but and so that's why we
could be more accurate than other um
previous um transition based paes and so
this um essentially um showed that you
could build this very accurate neural
dependency paa and that it
outperformed um symbolic um probalistic
representations and basically was as
good as any other dependency paa that
was known so um back a decade to go um
this was a big hit um people got very
excited about it um the people at Google
got very excited about it because this
gave a um a scalable way remember it's
linear time in which you could
efficiently go of and pass um the entire
web um so they did um some further work
on taking that model and proving it so
that they um made an a deeper neural
network version with bigger vectors and
better tuned hyperparameters and they
added on to a beam search I've just
presented the greedy version where you
always CH just immediately make the best
choice but you can improve these paas by
doing some amount of search that does
help um and so um they pushed that up
and so rather than our kind of 92 uas
here they got it to you know 94
94.6 and I mean
um you're uh you're probably um all too
young to remember this but um you know
really at the time of
2016 you know Google did their kind of
typical big PR PR Splash for dependency
parza which kind of blew my mind since I
didn't ever think that anyone was really
going to be writing articles in W and
Venture beat and those kind of tech um
blogs but you know Google had it all
over the place of the world's most
accurate paa and they gave it a silly
name pzy mpas face which really worked
well um for getting lots of media pickup
um and so that was then um a very
successful
paa um I've still got a couple of
minutes left so let me just um do the
last um three slides to show you sort of
another way of doing things which is
also actually also a powerful paing
method that is commonly used so um that
was transition-based paing and that's
what you'll use an assignment to another
way of doing things with dependencies
and paing can be done neural is what's
referred to as graph-based dependency
paes and in graph-based dependency paes
what you do is um for each word you sort
of ask for each word what am I a
dependent of right so if the sentence is
the big cat sat each word for example
big has to be a dependent of one of the
other four words in this sentence
including this possibility of root so we
ask am I dependent of that am I
dependent of root am I dependent of cat
am I dependent of sat and we want to
score each of those possibilities and so
hopefully we decide the most likely one
is the Bigg as a dependent of cat and
then we're going to do the same for
every other word so you know sat could
be a dependent of any of these words and
so we could start asking okay which of
these words is it most likely a
dependent
of uh beat to sat cat to sat um sorry
that's unreadable now but hopefully we
decide um that sat most likely as the
verb is a dependent of root so we sort
of scoring the N squared possible you
know dependencies of the sentence and
each one is given a score and then once
we've done that our job is let me go to
this one cleaner okay we've decided the
good one there and so we we're going to
do this using some of the same features
we talked about looking at the words at
each end looking at what occurs between
them looking at what occurs around them
um thinking about um things um and then
once we've done that the only other
thing that's a constraint is well we
want the dependencies to form a tree um
so that we need to do um something like
a minimum spanning tree algorithm to
sort of find the minimum cost tree
because we don't want to find a solution
where there are Cycles or the parts of
the sentence end up disconnected with
each other um and so that's graph-based
dependency paes and so just as in the
older symbolic paing days where the
graph based dependency paes were more
accurate than the transition based paes
um that we then started doing some work
on neural graph based depend dependency
paring and so here's our neurog graph
based dependency paring um which was
then a bit over a percent more accurate
than pzy mpaz face the world's best um
dependency paer um so um so that got us
to 2017 I mean obviously this is still a
few years ago but to get further into
the latest um paring Stories We then
need to sort of get into the ER of large
language models which I'm not doing
today um but it's this neural graph
based dependency paa um that's in um
stanza our open- source um paing
software that's available and that you
can see it's using this algorithm as the
more accurate one okay so now you
hopefully know everything about
syntactic structure constituency
independency paing and are fully
qualified to do assignment to so good
luck with that thanks