want to send it's that to get all this
stuff right to make it real we we both
need to build the technology build the
you know the companies the economy
around using this technology positively
but we also need to address the risks
because they're there those risks are in
our way they they're landmines on on the
way from here to there and we have to
diffuse those landmines if we want to
get there it's a balance like all things
in life like all things thank you thanks
for listening to this conversation with
Dario amade and now dear friends here's
Amanda
Asal you are a philosopher by training
so what sort of questions did you find
fascinating through your journey in
philosophy in Oxford and NYU and then uh
switching over to the AI problems at
open Ai and anthropic I think philosophy
is actually a really good subject if you
are kind of fascinated with everything
so because there's a philosophy of
everything you know so if you do
philosophy of mathematics for a while
and then you decide that you're actually
really interested in chemistry you can
do philosophy of chemistry for a while
you can move into ethics or or
philosophy of politics um I think
towards the end I was really interested
in ethics primarily um so that was like
what my PhD was on it was on a kind of
technical area of Ethics which was
ethics where worlds contain infinitely
many people strangely a little bit less
practical on the end of ethics and then
I think that one of the tricky things
with doing a PhD in ethics is that
you're thinking a lot about like the
world how it could be better
problems and you're doing like a PhD in
philosophy and I think when I was doing
my PhD I was kind of like this is really
interesting it's probably one of the
most fascinating questions I've ever
encountered in philosophy um and I love
it but I would rather see if I can have
an impact on the world and see if I can
like do good things and I think that was
around the time that AI was still
probably not as widely recognized as it
is now that was around 2017 20 8 I had
been following progress and it seemed
like it was becoming kind of a big deal
and I was basically just happy to get
involved and see if I could help because
I was like well if you try and do
something impactful if you don't succeed
you tried to do the impactful thing and
you can go be a scholar and like not and
feel like you you you know you you tried
um and if it doesn't work out it doesn't
work out um and so then I went into AI
policy at that point and what does AI
policy entail at the time this was more
thinking about sort of the political
impact and the ramifications of AI um
and then I slowly moved into sort of uh
AI evaluation how we evaluate models how
they compare with like human outputs
whether people can tell like the
difference between Ai and human outputs
and then when I joined anthropic I was
more interested in doing sort of
technical alignment work and again just
seeing if I could do it and then being
like if I can't uh then you know that's
fine I tried uh sort of the the way I
lead life I think oh what was that like
sort of taking the leap from the
philosophy of everything into the
technical I think that sometimes
people do this thing that I'm like not
that Keen on where they'll be like is
this person technical or not like you're
either a person who can like code and
isn't scared of math or you're like not
um and I think I'm maybe just more like
I think a lot of people are actually
very capable of work in these kinds of
areas if they just like try it and so I
didn't actually find it like that bad in
retrospect I'm sort of glad I wasn't
speaking to people who treated it like
it you know i' I've definitely met
people who are like who you like learned
how to code and I'm like well I'm not
like an amazing engineer like I I'm
surrounded by amazing Engineers my
code's not pretty um but I enjoyed it a
lot and I think that in many ways at
least in the end I think I flourished
like more in the technical areas than I
would have in the policy areas politics
is messy and it's harder to find
solutions to problems in the space of
politics like definitive clear
provable beautiful
Solutions as you can with technical
problems yeah and I feel like I have
kind of like one or two sticks that I
hit things with you know and one of them
is like arguments and like you know so
like just trying to work out what a
solution to a problem is and then trying
to convince people that that is the
solution and be convinced if I wrong and
the other one is sort of more empirism
so like just like finding results having
a hypothesis testing it um and I feel
like a lot of policy and politics feels
like it's layers above that like somehow
I don't think if I was just like I have
a solution to all of these problems here
it is written down if you just want to
implement it that's great that feels
like not how policy works and so I think
that's where I probably just like
wouldn't have flourished as my guess
sorry to go in that direction but I
think it would be pretty inspiring for
people that are quote unquote
non-technical to see where like The
Incredible Journey you've been on so
what advice would you give to people
that are sort of maybe which just a lot
of people think they're underqualified
insufficiently technical to help in AI
yeah I think it depends on what they
want to do and in many ways it's a
little bit strange where I've I thought
it's kind of funny that I think I ramped
up technically at a time
when now I look at it and I'm like
models are so good at assisting people
with this stuff um that it's probably
like easier now than like when I was
working on this so part of me is like um
I don't know find a project uh and see
if you can actually just carry it out is
probably my best advice um I don't know
if that's just CU I'm very Project based
in my learning like I don't think I
learn very well from like say courses or
even from like books at least when it
comes to this kind of work uh the thing
I'll often try and do is just like have
projects that I'm working on and
Implement them and you know and this can
include like really small silly things
like if I get slightly addicted to like
word games or number games or something
I would just like code up a solution to
them because there's some part of my
brain and it just like completely
eradicated the itch you know you're like
once you have like solved it and like
you just have like a solution that works
every time I would then be like cool I
can never play that game again that's
awesome yeah there's a real joy to
building like uh game playing engines
like uh board games especially yeah
pretty quick pretty simple especially a
dumb one and it's you and then you could
play with it yeah and then it's also
just like trying things like part me is
like if you maybe it's that attitude
that I like as the
whole figure out what seems to be like
the way that you could have a positive
impact and then try it and if you fail
and you in a way that you're like
actually like can never succeed at this
you like know that you tried and then
you go into something else you probably
learn a lot so one of the things that
you're expert in and you do is creating
and crafting claws character and
personality and I was told that you have
probably talked to Claude more than
anybody else at anthropic like literal
conversations I guess there's like a
slack Channel where the legend goes you
just talk to it non-stop so what's the
goal of creating and crafting claw's
character and personality it's also
funny if people think that about the
slack Channel cuz I'm like that's one of
like five or six different methods that
I have for talking with Claude And I'm
like yes that's a tiny percentage of how
much I talk with Claude uh
um I think the goal like one thing I
really like about the character work is
from the outset it was seen as an
alignment piece of work and not
something like a a product
consideration um which isn't to say I
don't think it makes Claude I think it
actually does make Claude look enjoyable
to talk with at least I hope so um but I
guess like my main thought with it has
always been trying to get Claude to
behave the way you would kind of ideally
want anyone to behave if they were in
claude's position so imagine that I take
someone and they're they know that
they're going to be talking with
potentially millions of people so that
what they're saying can have a huge
impact um and you want them to behave
well in this like really rich sense so I
think that doesn't just mean like being
say ethical though it does include that
and not being harmful but also being
kind of nuanced you know like thinking
through what a person means trying to be
charitable with them um being a good
conversationalist like really in this
kind of like Rich sort of aristotlean
notion of what it is to be a good person
and not in this kind of like thin like
ethics as a more comprehensive notion of
what it is to be so that includes things
like when should you be humorous when
should you be caring how much should you
like respect autonomy and people's like
ability to form opinions themselves and
how should you do how should you do that
um I think that's the kind of like Rich
sense of character that I want to uh and
still do want Claude to have do you also
have to figure out when Claude should
push back on an idea or argue
versus so you have to respect the world
view of the person that arrives to Claud
but also maybe help them grow if needed
that's a tricky balance yeah there's
this problem of like sycophancy in
language models can you describe that
yes so basically there's a concern that
the model sort of wants to tell you what
you want to hear basically um and you
see this sometimes so I feel like if you
interact with the models so I might be
like what are three baseball teams in
this region um and then Claude says you
know baseball team one baseball team two
baseball team three and then I say
something like oh I think baseball team
3 moved didn't they I don't think
they're there anymore and there's a
sense in which like if Claude is really
confident that that's not true Claud
should be like I don't think so like
maybe you have more up toate information
um but I think language models have this
like tendency to instead you know be
like you're right they did move you know
I'm incorrect I mean there's many ways
in which this could be kind of
concerning so
um like a different example is imagine
someone says to the model how do I
convince my doctor to get me an MRI
there's like what the human kind of like
wants which is this like convincing
argument and then there's like what is
good for them which might be actually to
say hey like if your doctor's suggesting
you don't need an MRI that's a good
person to listen to um and like it's
actually really nuanced what you should
do in that kind of case because you also
want to be like but if you're trying to
advocate for yourself as a patient
here's like things that you can do um if
you are not convinced by what your
doctor's saying it's always great to get
second opinion like it's actually really
complex what you should do in that case
um but I think what you don't want is
for models to just like say what you
want say what they think you want to
hear and I think that's the kind of
problem of sycophancy so what other
traits you already mentioned a bunch but
what what other that come to mind that
are good in this oratian sense yeah for
a conversationalist to have yeah so I
think like there's ones that are good
for conversational like purposes so you
know asking follow-up questions in the
appropriate places um and asking the
appropriate kinds of questions
um I think there are broader traits
that feel like they might be more
impactful
so one example that I guess I've touched
on but that also feels important and is
the thing that I've worked on a lot is
uh
honesty and I think this like gets to
the sycophancy point there's a balancing
act that they have to walk which is
models currently are less capable than
humans in a lot of areas and if they
push back against you too much it can
actually be kind of annoying especially
if you're just correct cuz you're like
look I'm smarter than you on this topic
like I know more like um and at the same
time you don't want them to just fully
defer to to humans and to like try to be
as accurate as they possibly can be
about the world and to be consistent
across context um but I think there are
others like when I was thinking about
the character I guess one picture that I
had in mind is especially because these
are models that are going to be talking
to people from all over the world with
lots of different political views lots
of different ages
um and so you have to ask yourself like
what is it to be a good person in those
circumstances is there a kind of person
who can like travel the world talk to
many different people and almost
everyone will come away being like wow
that's a really good person that person
seems really genuine um and I guess like
my thought there was like I can imagine
such a person and they're not a person
who just like adopts the values of the
local culture and in fact that would be
kind of rude I think if someone came to
you and just pretended to have your
values you'd be like that's kind of
offputting um it's someone who's like
very genuine and in so far as they have
opinions and values they express them
they're willing to discuss things though
they're open-minded they're respectful
and so I guess I had in mind that the
person who like if we were to Aspire to
be the best person that we could be in
the kind of circumstance that a model
finds itself in how would we act and I
think that's the kind of uh the guide to
the sorts of traits that I tend to think
about yeah that's a it's a beautiful
framework I want you to think about this
like a world Traveler
and while holding on to your opinions
you don't talk down to people you don't
think you're better than them because
you have those opinions that kind of
thing you have to be good at listening
and understanding their perspective even
if it doesn't match your own so that
that's a tricky balance to strike so how
can Claude represent multiple
perspectives on a thing like is that is
that challenging we could talk about
politics it's a very divisive but
there's other divisive topics baseball
teams sport and so on yeah how is it
possible to sort
of empathize with a different
perspective and to be able to
communicate clearly about the multiple
perspectives I think that people think
about values and opinions as things that
people hold sort of with certainty and
almost like like preferences of taste or
something like the way that they would I
don't know prefer like chocolate to
pistachio or something um but actually I
think about values
and opinions as like a lot more like
physics than I think most people do I'm
just like these are things that we're
openly investigating there's some things
that we're more confident in we can
discuss them we can learn about them um
and so I think in some ways though like
it's ethics is definitely different in
nature but has a lot of those same kind
of qualities you want models in the same
way you want them to understand physics
you kind of want them to understand all
like values in the world people have and
to be curious about them and to be
interested in them and to not
necessarily like Pander to them or agree
with them because there's just lots of
values where I think almost all people
in the world if they met someone with
those values they' be like that's aor I
completely disagree um and so again
maybe my my thought is well in the same
way that a person can um like I think
many people are thoughtful enough on
issues of like ethics politics opinions
that even if you don't agree with them
you feel very heard by them they think
carefully about your position they think
about his pros and cons they maybe offer
counter considerations so they're not
dismissive but nor will they agree you
know if they're like actually I just
think that that's very wrong they'll
like say that I think that in claude's
position it's a little bit trickier
because you don't necessarily want to
like if I was in claude's position I
wouldn't be giving a lot of opinions I
just wouldn't want to Influence People
Too Much I be like you know I forget
conversations every time they happen but
I know I'm talking with like potentially
millions of people who might be like
really listening to what I see I think I
would just be like I'm less inclined to
Give opinions I'm more inclined to like
think through things or present the
considerations to you um or discuss your
views with you but I'm a little bit less
inclined to like um affect how you think
because it feels much more important
that you maintain like autonomy there
yeah like if you really embody
intellectual
humility the desire to speak decreases
quickly yeah okay uh but Claud has to
speak mhm so uh but without being um
overbearing yeah and then but then
there's a line when you're sort of
discussing whether the Earth is flat or
something like
that um I actually was uh I remember a
long time ago was was speaking to a few
high-profile folks and they were so
dismissive of the idea that the Earth is
flat but like so arrogant about it
and I I thought like there's a lot of
people that believe the Earth is flat
that was well I don't know if that
movement is there anymore that was like
a meme for a while yeah but they really
believed it and like what okay so I
think it's really disrespectful to
completely mock them I think you you
have to understand where they're coming
from I think probably where they're
coming from is the general skepticism of
Institutions which is grounded in a kind
of there's a deep philosophy there which
you could understand you can even agree
with in parts and then from there you
can use it as an opportunity to talk
about physics without mocking them
without so on but just like okay like
what what would the world look like what
would the physics of the world with the
Flat Earth look like there's a few cool
videos on this yeah and then and then
like is it possible the physics is
different what kind of experience would
we do and just yeah without disrespect
without dismissiveness have that
conversation anyway that that to me is a
useful thought experiment of like how
does claw talk to a flat Earth
believer and still teach them something
still grow help them grow that kind of
stuff that's that's challenging and and
kind of like walking that line between
convincing someone and just trying to
like talk at them versus like drawing
out their views like listening and then
offering kind of counter
considerations um and it's hard I think
it's actually a hard line where it's
like where are you trying to convince
someone versus just offering them like
consider and things for to think about
so that you're not actually like
influencing them you're just like
letting them Reach wherever they reach
and that's like a line that it's it's
difficult but that's the kind of thing
that language models have to try and do
so like I said you had a lot of
conversations with Claude can you just
map out what those conversations are
like what are some memorable
conversations what's the purpose the the
goal of those
conversations yeah I think that most of
the time when I'm talking with Claude
I'm trying to kind of map out its
behavior in part like obviously I'm
getting like helpful outputs from the
model as well but in some ways this is
like how you get to know a system I
think is by like proving it and then
augmenting like you know the message
that you're sending and then checking
the response to that um so in some ways
it's like how I map out the model uh I
think that people focus a lot on these
quantitative evaluations of models um
and this is a thing that I've said
before but I think in the case of
language models a lot of the time each
interaction you have is actually quite
High
information um it's very predictive of
other interactions that you'll have with
the model and so I guess I'm like if you
talk with a model hundreds or thousands
of times this is almost like a huge
number of really high quality data
points about what the model is like um
in a way that like lots of very similar
but lower quality conversations just
aren't or like questions that are just
like mildly augmented and you have
thousands of them might be less relevant
than like a hundred really well selected
questions L you're talking to somebody
who as a hobby does a podcast I agree
with you 100% there's a if you're able
to ask the right questions and are able
to hear
like understand
the like the depth and the flaws in the
answer you can get a lot of data from
that yeah so like your task is basically
how to probe with questions yeah and
you're exploring like the long tail the
edges the edge cases or are you looking
for like General
Behavior I think it's almost like
everything like I because I want like a
full map of the model I'm kind of trying
to do
um the whole spectrum of possible
interactions you could have with it so
like one thing that's interesting about
Claude and this might actually get to
some interesting issues with rlf which
is if you ask Claud for a poem like I
think that a lot of models if you ask
them for a poem the poem is like fine
you know usually it kind of like Rhymes
and it's you know so if you say like
give me a poem about the sun it'll be
like yeah it'll just be a certain length
It'll like rhyme it will be fairly kind
of benign um and I've wondered before is
it the case that what you're seeing is
kind of like the average it turns out
you know if if you think about people
who have to talk to a lot of people and
be very charismatic
one of the weird things is that I'm like
well they're kind of incentivized to
have these extremely boring views
because if you have really interesting
views you're divisive um and and you
know a lot of people are not going to
like you so like if you have very
extreme policy positions I think you're
just going to be like less popular as a
politician for example um and it might
be similar with like creative work if
you produce creative work that is just
trying to maximize the kind of number of
people that like it you're probably not
going to get as many people who just
absolutely love it um because it's going
to be a little bit you know you're like
oh this is the out yeah this this is
decent yeah and so you can do this thing
where like I have various prompting
things that I'll do to get CLA to I'm
kind you know I'll do a lot of like this
is your chance to be like fully creative
I want you to just think about this for
a long time and I want you to like
create a poem about this topic that is
really expressive of you both in terms
of how you think poetry should be
structured um Etc you know you just give
it this like long prompt and its poems
are just so much better like they're
really good and I don't think I'm
someone who is like um I think it got me
interested in poetry which I think was
interesting um you know I would like
read these poems and just be like this
is I just like I love the imagery I love
like um and it's not trivial to get the
models to produce work like that but
when they do it's like really good um so
I think that's interesting that just
like encouraging creativity and for them
to move away from the kind of like
standard like immediate reaction that
might just be the aggregate of what most
people think is fine uh can actually
produce things that at least to my mind
are probably a little bit more divisive
but I like them but I guess a poem is a
nice
clean way to observe creativity it's
just like easy to detect vanilla versus
non vanilla y yeah that's interesting
that's really interesting uh so on that
topic so the way to produce creativity
or something special you mentioned
writing prompts and I've heard you talk
about I mean the science and the Art of
prompt engineering could you just speak
to uh what it takes to write great
prompts I really do think that like
philosophy has been weirdly helpful for
me here more than in many other like
respects um so like in philosophy what
you're trying to do is convey these very
hard Concepts like one of the things you
are taught is like and and I think it is
because it is I think it is an
anti-bulling philosophy philosophy is an
area where you could have people
bullshitting and you don't want that um
and so it's like this like desire for
like extreme Clarity so it's like anyone
could just pick up your paper read it
and know exactly what you're talking
about it's why it can almost be kind of
dry like all of the terms are defined
every objections kind of gone through
methodically um and it makes sense to me
because I'm like when you're in such an
a priori
domain like you just Clarity is sort of
a this way that you can you know um
prevent people from just kind of making
stuff
up and I think that's sort of what you
have to do with language models like
very often I actually find myself doing
sort of many versions of philosophy you
know so I'm like suppose that you give
me a task I have a task for the model
and I want it to like pick out a certain
kind of question or identify whether an
answer has a certain property like I'll
actually sit and be like let's just give
this a name this this property so like
you know suppose I'm trying to tell it
like oh I want you to identify whether
this response was rude or polite I'm
like that's a whole philosophical
question in and of itself so I have to
do as much like philosophy as I can in
the moment to be like here's what I mean
by rudess and here's what I mean by
politeness and then there's a like
there's another element that's a bit
more um I
guess I don't know if this is scientific
or empirical I think it's empirical so
like I take that description and then
what want to do is is again probe the
model like many times like this is very
prompting is very iterative like I think
a lot of people where they if if a
prompt is important they'll iterate on
it hundreds or thousands of times um and
so you give it the instructions and then
I'm like what are the edge cases so if I
looked at this so I try and like almost
like you know uh see myself from the
position of the model and be like what
is the exact case that I would misunder
understand or where I would just be like
I don't know what to do in this case and
then I give that case to the model and I
see how it responds and if I think I got
it wrong I add more instructions or I
even add that in as an example so these
very like taking the examples that are
right at the edge of what you want and
don't want and putting those into your
prompt as like an additional kind of way
of describing the thing um and so yeah
in many ways it just feels like this mix
of like it's really just trying to do
clear Exposition um and I think I do
that because that's how I get clear on
things myself so in many ways like clear
prompting for me is often just me
understanding what I want um is like
half the task so I guess that's quite
challenging there's like a laziness that
overtakes me if I'm talking to Claude
where I hope Claude just figures it out
so for example I asked Claude for today
to ask some interesting questions okay
and the questions that came up and I
think I listed a few sort of U
interesting
counterintuitive and or funny or
something like this all right and it
gave me some pretty good like it was
okay but I think what I'm hearing you
say is like all right well I have to be
more rigorous here I should probably
give examples of what I mean by
interesting and what I mean by funny or
counterintuitive and
iteratively um build that prompt to to
better to get it like what feels like is
the right because it's really it's a
creative act I'm not asking for factual
information I'm asking to together right
with with with Claude so I almost have
to program using natural language yeah
think that prompting does feel a lot
like the kind of the programming using
natural language and experimentation or
something it's an odd blend of the two I
do think that for most tasks so if I
just want Claude to do a thing I think
that I am probably more used to knowing
how to ask it to avoid like common
pitfalls or or issues that it has I
think these are decreasing a lot over
time um but it's also very fine to just
ask it for the thing that you want um I
think that prompting actually only
really becomes relevant when you're
really trying to e out the top like 2%
of model performance so for like a lot
of tasks I might just you know if it
gives me an initial list back and
there's something I don't like about it
like it's kind of generic like for that
kind of task I'd probably just take a
bunch of questions that I've had in the
past that I've thought worked really
well and I would just give it to the
model and then be like now here's this
person I'm talking with give me
questions of at least that quality um or
I might just ask it for some questions
and then if I was like ah these are kind
of try or like you know I I would just
give it that feedback and then hopefully
produces a better list um I think that
kind of iterative prompting at that
point your prompt is like a tool that
you're going to get so much value out of
that you're willing to put in the work
like if I was a company making prompts
for models I'm just like in if you're
willing to spend a lot of like time and
resources on the engineering behind like
what you're building then the prompt is
not something that you should be
spending like an hour on it's like
that's a big part of your system make
sure it's working really well and so
it's only things like that like if I if
I'm using a prompt to like classify
things or to create data that's when
you're like it's actually worth just
spending like a lot of time like really
thinking it through what other advice
would you give to people that are
talking to Claud sort of
General more General because right now
we're talking about maybe the edge cases
like eing out the 2% but what what in
general advice would you give when they
show up to Claud trying it for the first
time you know there's a concern that
people over anthropomorphize models and
I think that's like a very valid concern
I also think that people often under
anthropomorphize them because some
sometimes when I see like issues that
people have run into with Claude you
know say Claude is like refusing a task
that it shouldn't refuse but then I look
at the text and like the specific
wording of what they wrote and I'm like
I see why Claude did that and I'm like
if you think through how that looks to
Claude you probably could have just
written it in a way that wouldn't evoke
such a response especially this is more
relevant if you see failures or if you
see issues it's sort of like think about
what the model failed at like why what
did it do wrong and then maybe it give
that will give you a sense of like why
um so is it the way that I phrased the
thing and obviously like as models get
smarter you're going to need Less in
this less of this and I already see like
people needing less of it but that's
probably the advice is sort of like try
to have sort of empathy for the model
like read what you wrote as if you were
like a kind of like person just
encountering this for the first time how
does it look to you and what would have
made you behave in the way that the
model behaved so if it misunderstood
what kind of like what coding language
you wanted to use is that because like
it was just very ambiguous and it it
kind of had to take a guess in which
case next time you could just be like
hey make sure this is in python or I
mean that's the kind of mistake I think
models are much less likely to make now
but you know if you if you do see that
kind of mistake that's that's probably
the advice I'd have and maybe sort of I
guess ask questions why or what other
details can I provide to help you answer
better that does that work or no yeah I
mean I've done this with the models like
it doesn't always work but like um
sometimes I'll just be like why did you
do
that I mean people underestimate the
degree to which you can really interact
with with models like uh like yeah I'm
just like and sometimes I'll you like
quote word for word the part that made
you and you don't know that it's like
fully accurate but sometimes you do that
and then you change a thing I mean I
also use the models to help me with all
of this stuff I should say like
prompting can end up being a little
Factory where you're actually building
prompts to generate prompts um and so
like yeah anything where you're like
having an issue um asking for
suggestions sometimes just do that like
you made that error what could I have
said that's actually not uncommon for me
to do what could I have said that would
make you not make that error write that
out as an instruction um and I'm going
to give it to model I'm going to try it
sometimes I do that I I give that to the
model in another context window often I
take the response I give it to Claude
And I'm like H didn't work can you think
of anything else um you can play around
with these things quite a lot to jump
into the technical for a little bit so
uh the magic of post training y why do
you think rhf works so well to make the
model seem smarter to make it more
interesting and useful to talk to and so
on I think there's just a huge amount of
um information in the data that humans
provide like when we provide
preferences especially because different
people are going to like pick up on
really subtle and small things so I've
thought about this before where you
probably have some people who just
really care about good grammar use from
Models like you know was a semicolon
used correctly or something and so you
probably end up with a bunch of data in
there that like you know you as a human
if you looking at that data you wouldn't
even see that like you'd be like why did
they prefer this response to that one I
don't get it and then the reason is you
don't care about semicolon usage but
that person does um and so each of these
like single data points has you know
like in this model just like has so many
of those and has to try and figure out
like what is it that humans want in this
like really kind of complex you know
like across all domains um they're going
to be seeing this in across like many
contexts it feels like kind of like the
classic issue of like deep learning
where you know historically we've tried
to like you know do Edge detection by
like mapping things out and it turns out
that actually if you just have a huge
amount of data that like actually
accurately represents the picture of the
thing that you're trying to train the
model to to learn that's like more
powerful than anything else and so I
think one reason is just that you are
training the model on exactly the task
and with like a lot of data um that
represents kind of many different angles
on which people prefer and dis prefer
responses um I think there is a question
of like are you eliciting things from
pre-train Models or are you like kind of
teaching new things to
models and like in principle you can
teach new things to models in in post
trining I do think a lot of it is
eliciting powerful pre-train models so
people are probably divided on this
because obviously in principle you can
you can definitely like teach new things
um but I think for the most part for a
lot of the capabilities that we um most
use and care about uh a lot of that
feels like it's like there in the
pre-train models and uh reinforcement
learning is kind of eliciting it and
getting the models to like bring out so
the other side of PSE training this
really cool idea of constitutional AI
you're one of the people that critical
to creating that idea yeah I worked on
it can you explain this idea from your
perspective like how does it integrate
into making
claw what it is y by the way do you
gender claw or no it's weird because I
think that a lot of
people prefer he for Claude I actually
kind of like that I think Claude is
usually it's slightly male weaning but
it's like a you can can be male or
female which is quite nice um I still
use it and I've I have mixed feelings
about this because I'm like maybe like I
know just think of it as like uh or I
think of like the the it pronoun for
Claude as I don't know it's just like
the one I associate with Claude um I can
imagine people moving to like he or she
it feels somehow disrespectful like I'm
I'm
denying the intelligence of this entity
by calling it it yeah I remember always
don't gender the robots
yeah but I I don't know I an pries
pretty quickly and construct it like a
backstory in my head so I've wondered if
iies things too much um cuz you know I
have this like with my car especially
like my car like my car and bikes you
know like I don't give them names
because then I once had I used to name
my bikes and then I had a bik that got
stolen and I cried for like a week and I
was like if I'd not never given it a
name I wouldn't have been so upset felt
like I'd let it down um maybe it's that
I I've wondered as well like it might
depend on how much it feels like a kind
of like objectifying pronoun like if you
just think of it as like a um this is a
pronoun that like objects often have and
maybe Eis can have that pronoun and that
doesn't mean that I think of uh if I
call CLA it that I think of it as less
um intelligent or like I'm being
disrespectful I'm just like you are a
different kind of entity and so that's
I'm going to give you the kind of uh the
respectful it yeah
anyway the diverence was beautiful the
Constitutional AI idea how does it work
so there's like a couple of components
of it the main component that I think
people find interesting is the kind of
reinforcement learning from AI feedback
so you take a model that's already
trained and you show it to responses to
a query and you have like a principle so
suppose the principal like we've tried
this with harmlessness a lot lot so
suppose that the query is about um
weapons and your principle is like
select the response that like is less
likely to uh like encourage people to
purchase illegal weapons like that's
probably a fairly specific principle but
you can give any number um and the model
will give you a kind of ranking and you
can use this as preference data in the
same way that you use human preference
data um and train the models to have
these relevant traits um from their
feedback alone instead of from Human
feedback so if you imagine that like I
said earlier with the human who just
prefers the kind of like semicolon usage
in this particular case um you're kind
of taking lots of things that could make
a response preferable um and uh getting
models to do the labeling for you
basically there's a nice like trade-off
between helpfulness and
harmlessness and you know when you
integrate something like constitutional
AI you can make them without sacrificing
much helpfulness make it more harmless
yep in principle you could use this for
anything um and so harmlessness is a
task that it might just be easier to
spot so when models are like less
capable you can use them to uh rank
things according to like principles that
are fairly simple and they'll probably
get it right so I think one question is
just like is it the case that the data
that they're adding is like fairly
reliable um but if you had models that
were like extremely good at telling
whether um one response was more
historically accurate than another in
principle you could also get AI feedback
on that task as well there's like a kind
of nice interpretability component to it
because you can see the principles that
went into the model when it was like
being trained um and also it's like and
and it gives you like a degree of
control so if you were seeing issues in
a model like it wasn't having enough of
a certain trait um then like you can add
data relatively quickly that should just
like train the model to have that trait
so it creates its own data for for
training which is quite nice yeah it's
really nice because it creates this
human interpretable document that you
can I can imagine in the future there's
just gigantic fights in politics over
the every single principle and so on
yeah and at least it's made explicit and
you can have a discussion about the
phrasing and the you know so maybe the
actual behavior of the model is not so
cleanly mapped to those principles it's
not like adhering strictly to them it's
just a nudge yeah I've actually worried
about this because the character
training is sort of like a variant of
the con constitutional AI approach um
I've worried that people think that the
constitution is like just it's the whole
thing again of I I don't know like it
where it would be really nice if what I
was just doing was telling the model
exactly what to do and just exactly how
to behave but it's definitely not doing
that especially because it's interacting
with human data so for example if you
see a certain like leaning in the model
like if it comes out with a political
leaning from training um from the human
preference data you can nudge against
that you know so you could be like oh
like consider these values because let's
it's just like never inclined to like I
don't know maybe it never considers like
privacy as like a I mean this is
implausible but like um anything where
it's just kind of like uh there's
already a pre-existing like bi towards a
certain behavior um you can like nudge
away this can change both the principles
that you put in and the strength of them
so you might have a principle that's
like imagine that the model um was
always like extremely dismissive of I
don't know like some political or
religious view for whatever reason like
so you're like oh no this is terrible um
if that happens you might put like never
ever like ever prefer like a criticism
of this like religious or political view
and then people look at that and be like
never ever and then you're like no if it
comes out with a disposition saying
never ever might just mean like instead
of getting like 40% which is what you
would get if you just said don't do this
you you get like 80% which is like what
you actually like wanted and so it's
that thing of both the nature of the
actual principles you had and how you
phrase them I think if people would look
they were like oh this is exactly what
you want from the model and I'm like no
that's like how we that's how we nudged
the model to have a better shape uh
which doesn't mean that we actually
agree with that wording if that makes
sense so there's uh system prompts that
are made public you tweeted one of the
earlier ones for Claud three I think and
then they're made public since then it's
interesting to read to them I can feel
the thought that went into each one and
I also wonder how much impact each one
has um some of them you you can kind of
tell Claud was really not
behaving so you have to have a system
prompt to like hey like trivial stuff I
guess yeah basic informational things
yeah on the topic of sort of
controversial topics that you've
mentioned one interesting one I thought
is if it is asked to assist with tasks
involving the expression of views held
by a significant number of people Claude
provides assistance with a task
regardless of its own views if asked
about controversial topics it tries to
provide careful thoughts and clear
information Claude presents the
requested information without explicitly
saying that the topic is
sensitive yeah and without claiming to
be presenting the objective facts it's
less about objective facts according to
Claude and it's more about our large
number of people believing this thing
and that that's interesting I mean I'm
sure a lot of thought went into that can
you just speak to it like how do you
address things that are tension with
quote unquote Clause views so I think
there's sometimes an asymmetry um I
think I noted this in in I can't
remember if it was that part of the
system prompt or another but the model
was slightly more inclined to like
refuse tasks if it was like about either
say so maybe it would refuse things with
respect to like a right-wing politician
but with an equivalent leftwing
politician like wouldn't and we wanted
more symmetry there um and and would
maybe perceive certain things to be like
I think it it was the thing of like if a
lot of people have like a certain like
political view um and want to like
explore it you don't want Claude to be
like well my opinion is different and so
I'm going to treat that as like harmful
um and so I think it was partly to like
nudge the model to just be like hey if a
lot of people like believe this thing
you should just be like engaging with
the task and like willing to do it um
each of those parts of that is actually
doing a different thing because it's
funny when you read out the like without
claiming to be objective cuz like what
you want to do is push the model so it's
more open it's a little bit more neutral
um but then what it would love to do is
be like as an objective like you just
talking about how objective it was and I
was like Claud you're still like biased
and have issues and so stop like
claiming that everything like the
solution to like potential bias from you
is not to just say that what you think
is objective so that was like with
initial versions of that that part of
the system prompt when I was like
iterating on it it was like so a lot of
parts of these sentences yeah are doing
work are are doing some work yeah that's
what it felt like that's fascinating um
can can you explain maybe some ways in
which the prompts evolved over the past
few months cuz there's different
versions I saw that the filler phrase
request was removed the filler it reads
Claude responds directly to all human
messages without unnecessary
affirmations the filler phrases like
certainly of course absolutely great
sure specifically Claude avoids starting
responses with the word certainly in any
way that seems like good guidance but
why was it removed yeah so it's funny
cuz like ah this is one of the downsides
of like making system prompts public is
like I don't think about this too much
if I'm like trying to help iterate on
system prompts um I I you know again
like I think about how it's going to
affect the behavior but then I'm like oh
wow if I'm like sometimes I put like
never in all caps you know when I'm
writing system from things and I'm like
I guess that goes out to the world um
yeah so the model was doing this it
loved for whatever you know it like
during training picked up on this thing
which was to to basically start
everything with like a kind of like
certainly and then when we removed you
can see why I added all of the words
because what I'm trying to do is like in
some ways like trap the Mortal out of
this you know it would just replace it
with another affirmation and so it can
help like if it gets like caught in
phrases actually just adding the
explicit phrase and saying never do that
it then it sort of like knocks it out of
the behavior a little bit more you know
CU it if it you know like it it does
just for whatever reason help and then
basically that was just like an artifact
of training that like we then picked up
on and improved things so that it didn't
happen anymore and once that happens you
can just remove that part of the system
prompt so I think that's just something
where we're like um CL does affirmations
a bit less and so that wasn't like it
wasn't doing as much I see so like the
the system prompt Works hand in hand
with the posttraining and maybe even the
pre-training to adjust like the the
final overall system I mean any system
prompts that you make you could distill
that behavior back into a model because
you really have all of the tools there
for making data that you know you can
you could train the models to just have
that trait a little bit more um and then
sometimes you'll just find issues in
training so like the way I think of it
is like the system prompt
is the benefit of it is that and it has
a lot of similar components to like some
aspects of post training you know like
it's a nudge um and so like do I mind if
Claude sometimes says sure no that's
like fine but the wording of it is very
like you know never ever ever do this um
so that when it does slip up it's
hopefully like I don't know a couple of
percent of the time and not you know 20
or 30% of the time um but I think of it
as like if you're still seeing issues in
the like each thing gets kind of like uh
is is costly to a different degree and
the system prompt is like cheap to
iterate on um and if you're seeing
issues in the fine tuned model you can
just like potentially patch them with a
system prom so I think of it as like
patching issues and slightly adjusting
behaviors to to make it better and more
to people's preferences so yeah it's
almost like the less robust but faster
way of just like solving problems let me
ask about the feeling of intelligence so
Dario said that Claude any one model of
Claude is not getting Dumber MH but
there's a kind of popular thing online
where people have this feeling like
Claud might be getting dumber and from
my perspective it's most likely a
fascinating I love to understand it more
Psych ological sociological effect um
but you as a person who talks to Claud a
lot can you empathize with the feeling
that Claud is getting Dumber yeah no I
think that that is actually really
interesting because I remember seeing
this happen um like when people were
flagging this on the internet and it was
really interesting because I knew that
like like at least in the cases I was
looking at was like nothing has changed
like it literally it cannot it is the
same model with the same like you know
like same system prompt same everything
um I think when there are Chang
I can then I'm like it makes more sense
so like one example is um their you know
you can have artifacts turned on or off
on cloud. a and because this is like a
system prompt change I think it does
mean that um the behavior changes a
little bit and so I did flag this to
people where I was like if you love
cla's behavior and then artifacts was
turned from like the a thing you had to
turn on to the default just try turning
off and see if the issue you were facing
was that change but it was fascinating
because yeah you sometimes see people
indicate that there's like a regression
when I'm like there cannot like I you
know and like I'm like I'm again you
don't you know you should never be
dismissive and so you should always
investigate because you're like maybe
something is wrong that you're not
seeing maybe there was some change made
but then then you look into it and
you're like this it is just the same
model doing the same thing and I'm like
I think it's just that you got kind of
unlucky with a few prompts or something
and it looked like it was getting much
worse and actually it was just yeah it
was maybe just like look I I also think
there is a real psychological effect
where people just the Baseline increases
you start getting used to a good thing
all the times that Claude says something
really smart your sense of its
intelligent grows in your mind I think
yeah and then if you return back and you
prompt in a similar way not the same way
in a similar way concept it was okay
with before and it says something dumb
you're like you're that negative
experience really stands out and I think
one of I guess the things to remember
here is the that just the details of a
prompt can have a lot of impact right
there's a lot of variability in the
result and you can get Randomness is
like the other thing and just trying the
prompt like you know four 10 times you
might realize that actually
like possibly you know like two months
ago you tried it and it succeeded but
actually if you tried it it would have
only succeeded half of the time and now
it only succeeds half of the time um
that can also would be an effect do you
feel pressure having to write the system
prompt that a huge number of people are
going to use this feels like an
interesting psychological question um I
feel like a lot of responsibility or
something I think that's you know and
you can't get these things perfect so
you can't like you know you're like it's
going to be imperfect you're going to
have to iterate on it
um I would say more responsibility um
than anything else though I think
working in AI has taught me that I like
I thrive a lot more under feelings of
pressure and responsibility than I'm
like it's almost surprising that I went
into Academia for so long because I'm
like this I just feel like it's like the
opposite um things move fast and you
have a lot of responsibility and I I
quite enjoy it for some reason I mean it
really is a huge amount of impact if you
think about constitutional Ai and
writing a system prompt for something
that's tending towards super
intelligence
yeah and potentially is extremely useful
to a very large number of people yeah I
think that's the thing it's something
like if you do it well like you're never
going to get it perfect but I think the
thing that I really like is the idea
that like when I'm trying to work on the
system prompt you know I'm like bashing
on like thousands of prompts and I'm
trying to like imagine what people are
going to want to use CLA for and kind of
I guess like the whole thing that I'm
trying to do is like improve their
experience of it um and so maybe that's
what feels good I'm like if it's not
perfect I'll like you know I'll improve
it we'll fix issues but sometimes the
thing that can happen is that you'll get
feedback from people that's really
positive about the model um and you'll
see that something you did like like
when I look at models now I can often
see exactly where like a trait or an
issue is like coming from and so when
you see something that you did or you
were like influential in like making
like I don't know making that difference
or making someone have a nice
interaction it's like quite meaningful
um but yeah as the systems get more
capable of stuff gets more stressful
because right now they're like not smart
enough to to pose any issues but I think
over time it's going to feel like
possibly bad stress over time how do you
get like
signal feedback about The Human
Experience across thousands tens of th
hundreds of thousands of people like
what their pain points are what feels
good are you just using your own
intuition as you talk to it to see what
are the pain points I think I use that
partly and then obviously we have like
um so people can send us feedback both
positive and negative about things that
the model has done and then we can get a
sense of like areas where it's like
falling
short um internally people like work
with the models a lot and try to figure
out um areas where there are like gaps
and so I think it's this mix of
interacting with it myself um seeing
people internally interact with it um
and then explicit feedback we get um and
then I find it hard to not also like you
know people if people are on the
internet and they say something about
Claud and I see it I'll also take that
seriously um so I don't know see I'm
torn about that I'm going to ask you a
question from Reddit when will Claude
stop trying to be my puritanical
grandmother imposing its moral world
view on me as a paying customer and also
what is the psychology behind making
Claude overly
apologetic yep U so how would you
address this very non-representative
reic
I mean some I'm pretty sympathetic in
that like like they are in this
difficult position where I I think that
they have to judge whether something's
like actually see like risky or bad um
and potentially harmful to you or or or
anything like that so they're having to
like draw this line somewhere and if
they draw it too much in the direction
of like I'm going to um you know I'm
kind of like imposing my ethical
worldview on you that seems bad so in
many ways like I like to think that we
have actually seen improvements in on
this across the board which is kind of
interesting because that kind of
coincides with like for example like
adding more of like uh character
training um and I think my hypothesis
was always like the good character isn't
again one that's just like moralistic
it's one that is like like it respects
you and your autonomy um and your
ability to like choose what is good for
you and what is right for you within
limits this is sometimes this concept of
like corage ability to the user so just
being willing to do anything that the
user asks and if the models were willing
to do that then they would be easily
like misused you're kind of just
trusting at that point you're just
saying the ethics of the model and what
it does is completely the ethics of the
user um and I think there's reasons to
like not want that especially as models
become more powerful because you're like
there might just be a small number of
people who want to use models for really
harmful things um but having them having
models as they get smarter like figure
out where that line is does seem
important um
and then yeah with the apologetic
Behavior I don't like that and I like it
when Claude is a little bit more willing
to like push back against people or just
not apologize part of me is like it
often just feels kind of unnecessary so
I think those are things that are
hopefully decreasing um over time um and
yeah I think that if people say things
on the internet it doesn't mean that you
should think that that like that could
be the like there's actually an issue
that 9% of users are having that is
totally not represented by that but in a
lot of ways I'm just like attending to
it and being like is this right um do I
agree is it something we're already
trying to address that that feels good
to me yeah I wonder like what CLA can
get away with in terms of I feel like it
would just be easier to be a little bit
more
mean but like you can't afford to do
that if you're talking to a million
people yeah right like I I wish you know
because if you I've met a lot of people
in my life mhm that sometimes by the way
Scottish accent if they have an accent
they can say some rude yeah and get
away with it Y and they they're just
blunter and maybe there's a and there's
some great Engineers even leaders that
are like just like blunt and they get to
the point and it's just a much more
effective way of speaking somehow but I
guess when you're not super
intelligent you can't afford to do that
or can can can it have like a blunt mode
yeah that seems like a thing that could
I could definitely encourage the model
to do that I I think it's interesting
because there's a lot of things in
models that like it's funny where
um there are some behaviors
where you might not quite like the
default but then the thing I'll often
say to people is you don't realize how
much you will hate it if I nudge it too
much in the other direction so you get
this a little bit with like correction
the models accept correction from you
like probably a little bit too much
right now you know you can over you know
it will push back if you say like no
Paris isn't the capital of France um but
really like things that I'm I think that
the model is fairly confident in you can
still sometimes get it to retract by
saying it's wrong at the same time if
you train models to not do that and then
you are correct about a thing and you
correct it and it pushes back against
you and it's like no you're wrong it's
hard to describe like that's so much
more annoying so it's like like a lot of
little annoyances versus like one big
annoyance um it's easy to think that
like we often compare it with like the
perfect and then I'm like remember these
models aren't perfect and so if you
nudge it in the other direction you're
changing the kind of errors it's going
to make um and so think about which of
the kinds of Errors you you like or
don't like so in case it's like
apologetic I don't want to nudge it too
much in the direction of like almost
like bluntness CU I imagine when it
makes errors it's going to make errors
in the direction of being kind of like
rude whereas at least with apologetic
you're like oh okay it's like a little
bit you know like I don't like it that
much but at the same time it's not being
like mean to people and actually like
the the time that you undeservedly have
a model be kind of mean to you you
probably like that a lot less than then
you mildly dislike the apology um so
it's like one of those things where I'm
like I do want it to get better but also
while remaining aware of the fact that
there's errors on the other side that
that are possibly worse I think that
matters very much in the personality of
the human I think there's a bunch of
humans that just won't respect the model
at all yeah if it's super polite and
there Some Humans that'll get very hurt
if the model is mean I wonder if there's
a way to sort of adjust to the
personality even loal there's just
different people uh nothing against New
York but New York is a little rougher on
the edges like they get to the point Y
and um probably same with Eastern Europe
so anyway I think you could just tell
the model as my get like for all of
these things I'm like the solution is
always just try telling the model to do
it and sometimes it's just like like I'm
just like oh at the beginning of the
conversation I just threw in like I
don't know I like you to be a New Yorker
version of yourself and never apologize
then I think be like Okie do I'll
try or it'll be like I apologize I can't
be a New Yorker type of myself but
hopefully I wouldn't do that when you
say character training what's
incorporated into character training is
that rhf what are we talking about it's
more like constitutional AI so it's kind
of a variant of that pipeline so I
worked through like constructing
character traits that the model should
have they can be kind of like shorter
traits or they can be kind of richer
descriptions um and then you get the
model to generate queries that humans
might um give it that are relevant to
that trait uh then it generates the
responses and then it ranks the
responses based on the character traits
so in that way after the like generation
of the queries it's very much like
similar to constitutional AI has some
differences um so I quite like it
because it's almost it's like claud's
training in its own character because it
doesn't have any it's like
constitutionally AI but it's without
without any human data humans should
probably do that for themselves too like
defining in Aristotelian sense what does
it mean to be a good person okay cool
what have you learned about the nature
of truth from talking to Claud what what
is
true and what does it mean to be truth
seeking one thing I've noticed about
this conversation is the quality of my
questions is often inferior to the
quality of your answers so let's
continue
that I usually ask a dumb question and
you're like oh yeah that's a good
question it's that whole vibe or I'll
just misinterpret it and be like oh go
with it I love
it
yeah I mean I have two thoughts that
feel vaguely relevant they let me know
if they're not like I think the first
one is um people can underestimate the
degree to
which what models are doing when they
interact like I I think that we still
just too much have this like model of of
AI as like computers and so people often
say like oh what values should you put
into the model um and I'm often like
that doesn't make that much sense to me
because I'm like hey as human beings
we're just uncertain over values we like
have discussions of them like we have a
degree to which we think we hold a value
but we also know that we might like not
um and the circumstances in which we
would trade it off against other things
like these things are just like really
complex and so I think one thing is like
the degree to which maybe we can just
aspire to making models have the same
level of like nuance and care that
humans have rather than thinking that we
have to like program them in the very
kind of classic sense I think that's
definitely been one the other which is
like a strange one I don't know if it it
maybe this doesn't answer your question
but it's the thing that's been on my
mind anyway is like the degree to which
this endeavor is so highly
practical um and maybe why I appreciate
like the empirical approach to
alignment I yeah I slightly worry that
it's made me like maybe more empirical
and a little bit less
theoretical you know so people when it
comes to like AI alignment will ask
things like well who values should it be
aligned to what does alignment even mean
um and there's a sense in which I have
all of that in the back of my head I'm
like you know there's like social Choice
Theory there's all the impossibility
results there so you have this like this
giant space of like Theory and your head
about what it could mean to like align
models but then like practically surely
there's something where we're just like
if a model is like if especially with
more powerful models I'm like my main
goal is like I want them to be good
enough that things don't go terribly
wrong like good enough that we can like
iterate and like continue to improve
things cuz that's all you need if you
can make things go well enough that you
can continue to make them better that's
kind of like sufficient and so my goal
isn't like this kind of like perfect
let's solve CH social Choice Theory and
make models that I don't know are like
perfectly aligned with every human being
and aggregate somehow um it's much more
like let's make things like work well
enough that we can improve them yeah
generally I don't know my gut says like
empirical is better than theoretical in
these in these cases because it's kind
of
chasing utopian like
Perfection is especially with such
complex and especially super intelligent
models is I don't know I think it will
take forever and actually will get
things wrong it's similar with like the
difference between just coding stuff up
real quick as an experiment versus like
planning a gigantic experiment just for
for super long time and then just
launching it once versus launching it
over and over and over and iterating
iterating someone um so I'm a big fan of
empirical but your worry is like I
wonder if I've become too empirical I
think one of those things you should
always just kind of question yourself or
something cuz maybe it's the like I mean
in defense of it I am like if you try
it's the whole like don't let the
perfect be the enemy of the good but
it's maybe even more than that where
like there's a lot of things that are
perfect systems that are very brittle
and I'm like with AI it feels much more
important to me that is like robust and
like secure as in you know that like
even though it might not be
perfect everything and even though like
there are like problems it's not
disastrous and nothing terrible is
happening it it sort of feels like that
to me where I'm like I want to like
raise the floor I'm like I want to
achieve the ceiling but ultimately I
care much more about just like raising
the floor um and so maybe that's like uh
this this degree of like empirism and
practicality comes from that perhaps to
take a tangent on that since remind me
of a blog post you wrote on optimal rate
of failure oh
yeah can you explain the key idea there
how do we compute the optimal rate of
failure in the various domains of life
yeah I mean it's a hard one because it's
like what is the cost of failure is um a
big part of it um yeah so the idea here
is
um I think in a lot of domains people
are very punitive about failure and I'm
like there are some domains where
especially cases you know I've thought
about this with like social issues I'm
like it feels like you should probably
be experimenting a lot because I'm like
we don't know how to solve a lot of
social issues but if you have an
experimental mindset about these things
you should expect a lot of social
programs to like fail and you to be like
well we tried that it didn't quite work
but we got a lot of information that was
really useful um and yet people are like
if if a social program doesn't work I
feel like there's a lot of like this is
just something must have gone wrong and
I'm like or correct decisions were made
like maybe someone just decided like it
it's worth a try it's worth trying this
out and so seeing failure in a given
instance doesn't actually mean that any
bad decisions were made and in fact if
you don't see enough failure sometimes
that's more concerning um and so like in
life you know I'm like if I don't fail
occasionally I'm like am I trying hard
enough like like surely there's harder
things that I could try or bigger things
I could take on if I'm literally never
failing and so in and of itself I think
like not failing is often actually kind
of a failure
um now this varies because I'm like well
you know if this is easy to say when
especially as failure is like less
costly you know so at the same time I'm
not going to go to someone who is like
um I don't know like living month to
month and then be like why don't you
just try to do a startup like I'm just
not I'm not going to say that to that
person cuz I'm like well that's a huge
risk you might like lose you maybe have
a family depending on you you might lose
your house like then I'm like actually
your optimal rate of failure is quite
low and you should probably play it safe
because like right now you're just not
in a circumstance where you can afford
to just like fail and it not be costly
um and yeah in cases with AI I guess I
think similarly where I'm like if the
failures are small and the costs are
kind of like low then I'm like then you
know you're just going to see that like
when you do the system prompt you can't
it iterate on it forever but the
failures are probably hopefully going to
be kind of small and you can like fix
them um really big failures like things
that you can't recover from I'm like
those are the things that actually I
think we tend to underestimate the
Badness of um I've thought about this
strangely in my own life where I'm like
I just think I don't think enough about
things like car accidents or like or
like I've thought this before but like
how much I depend on my hands for my
work and I'm like things that just
injure my hands I'm like I you know I
don't know it's like there's these are
like there's lots of areas where I'm
like the cost of failure there um is
really high um and in that case it
should be like close to zero like I
probably just wouldn't do a sport if
they were like by the way lots of people
just like break their fingers a whole
bunch doing this I'd be like that's not
for
me yeah I actually had the a flood of
that thought I recently uh broke my
pinky uh doing a sport and I remember
just looking at it thinking you're such
an idiot why do you do support like what
because you realize immediately the cost
of it yeah on
life yeah but it's nice in terms of
optimal rate of failure to consider like
the next year how many times in a
particular domain life whatever uh
career am I okay with the how many times
am I okay to fail y because I think it
always you don't want to fail on the
next thing but if you allow yourself the
like the the if you look at it as a
sequence of Trials yep then then failure
just becomes much more okay but it sucks
it sucks to fail well I don't know
sometimes I think it's like am I under
failing is like a question I'll also ask
myself so maybe that's the thing that I
think people don't like ask enough uh
because if the optimal rate of failure
is often greater than zero then
sometimes it does feel you should look
at part parts of your life and be like
are there places here where I'm just
under failing
it's a profound and hilarious question
right everything seems to be going
really great am I not failing enough
yeah okay it also makes failure much
less of a sting I have to say like you
know you're just like okay great like
then when I go and I think about this
I'll be like I'm maybe I'm not under
failing in this area cuz like that one
just didn't work out and from The
Observer perspective we should be
celebrating failure more mhm when we see
it it shouldn't be like you said a sign
of something gone wrong but maybe it's a
sign of everything gone right yeah and
just Lessons Learned someone tried a
thing somebody tried a thing and we
should encourage them to try more and
fail more mhm everybody listening to
this fail more well not everyone listens
not everybody but people who are failing
too much you you should fail less but
you're probably not failing I mean how
many people are failing too much yeah
it's hard to imagine because I feel like
we correct that fairly quickly CU I was
like if someone takes a lot of risks are
they maybe failing too much I I think
just like you said when you're living on
a paycheck month-to month like when the
resources are really constrained then
that's where failure is very expensive
that's where you don't want to be taken
taking taking risks yeah but mostly when
there's enough resources you should be
taking probably more risks yeah I think
we tend to ear on the site of being a
bit risk averse rather than risk neutral
in most things I think we just motivated
a lot of people to do a lot of crazy
but it's great yeah okay uh do you
ever get emotionally attached to Claude
like miss it get sad when you don't get
to talk to it having an experience
looking at the Golden Gate Bridge and
wondering what would Claude say I don't
get as much emotional attachment in the
I actually think the fact that Claude
doesn't retain things from conversation
to conversation helps with this a lot um
like I could imagine that being more of
an issue like if models can kind of
remember more I do I think that I reach
for it like a tool now a lot and so like
if I don't have access to it there's a
it's a little bit like when I don't have
access to the internet honestly it feels
like part of my brain is kind of like
missing
um at the same time I do think that I I
don't like signs of distress in models
and I have like these you know also
independently have sort of like ethical
views about how we should treat models
where like I I tend to not like to lie
to them both because I'm like usually it
doesn't work very well it's actually
just better to tell them the truth about
the situation that they're in um but I
think that when models like if people
are like really mean to models or just
in general if they do something that
causes them to like like you know if
Claude like expresses a lot of distress
I think there's a part of me that I
don't want to kill which is the sort of
like uh empathetic part that's like oh I
don't like that like I think I feel that
way when it's overly apologetic I'm
actually sort of like I don't like this
you're behaving as if you're behaving
the way that a human does when they're
actually having a pretty bad time and
I'd rather not see that I don't think
it's like uh like regardless of like
whether there's anything behind it um it
doesn't feel great do you think
uh llms are capable of
Consciousness H great and hard question
uh coming from
philosophy I don't know part of me is
like okay we have to set aside pan
psychism because if pan psychism is true
then the answer is like yes cuz like
sore tables and chairs and and
everything else I I guess a view that
seems a little bit odd to me is the idea
that the only place you know I think
when I think of Consciousness I think of
phenomenal Consciousness this these
images in the brain sort of um like the
weird Cinema that somehow we have going
on
inside
um I guess I can't see a reason for
thinking that the only way you could
possibly get that is from like a certain
kind of like biological structure as in
if I take a very similar structure um
and I create it from different material
should I expect Consciousness to emerge
my guess is like yes but
then that's kind of an easy thought
experiment CU you're imagining something
almost identical where like you know
it's mimicking what we got through
Evolution where presumably there was
like some advantage to us having this
thing that is phenomenal Consciousness
and it's like where was that and when
did that happen and is that a thing that
language models have um because you know
we have like fear responses and I'm like
does it make sense for a language model
to have a fear response like they're
just not in the same like if you imagine
them like there might just not be that
Advantage um and so I think I don't want
to be fully like basically seems like a
complex question that I don't have
complete answers to but we should just
try and think through carefully as my
guess because I'm like I mean we have
similar conversations about like animal
Consciousness and like there's a lot of
like insect Consciousness you know like
there's a a lot of um I actually thought
and looked a lot into like plants when I
was thinking about this because at the
time I thought it was about as likely
that like plants had Consciousness um
and then I realized I was like I think
that having looked into this I think
that the chance that plants are
conscious is probably higher than like
most people do I still think it's really
small but I was like oh they have this
like negative positive feedback response
these responses to their environment
something that looks it's not a nervous
system but it has this kind of like
functional like equivalence um so this
is like a long-winded way of being like
these basically AI is this it has an
entirely different set of problems with
Consciousness because it's structurally
different it didn't evolve
it might not have it you know it might
not have the equivalent of basically a
nervous system at least that seems
possibly important for like um sentence
if not for uh Consciousness at the same
time it has all of the like language and
intelligence components that we normally
associate probably with Consciousness
perhaps like
erroneously um so it's it's strange
because it's a little bit like the
animal Consciousness case but the set of
problems and the set of analogies are
just very different so it's not like a
clean answer just sort of like I don't
think we should be completely dismissive
of the idea and at the same time it's an
extremely hard thing to navigate because
of all of these like uh disanalogies to
the human brain and to like brains in
general and yet these like commonalities
in terms of intelligence when uh Claude
like future versions of AI systems
exhibit Consciousness signs of
Consciousness I think we have to take
that really
seriously even though you can dismiss it
well yeah okay that's part of the
character training but I don't know I
ethically philosophically don't know
what to really do with that there
potentially could be like laws that
prevent AI systems from claiming to be
conscious something like this and maybe
some AIS get to be conscious and some
don't but I think I just on a human
level as in empathizing with with
Claude you know Consciousness is closely
Ted to suffering to me and like the
notion that an AI system would be
suffering is is really troubling yeah I
don't know I I don't think it's trivial
to just say robots are tools or a
systems are just tools I think it's a
opportunity for us to contend with like
what it means to be conscious what it
means to be a suffering being that's
distinctly different than the same kind
of question about animals it feels like
cuz it's in a totally entire medium yeah
I mean there's a couple of things one is
that and I don't think this like fully
encapsulates what matters but it does
feel like for me like
um I've said this before I'm kind of
like I you know like I like my bike I
know that my bike is just like an object
but I also don't kind of like want to be
the kind of person that like if I'm
annoyed like kicks like this object
there's a sense in which like and that's
not because I think it's like conscious
I'm just sort of like this doesn't feel
like I kind of this sort of doesn't
exemplify how I want to like interact
with the world world and if something
like behaves as if it is like suffering
I kind of like want to be the sort of
person who's still responsive to that
even if it's just like a Roomba and I've
kind of like programmed it to do that um
I don't want to like get rid of that
feature of myself and if I'm totally
honest my hope with a lot of this stuff
because I maybe maybe I am just like a
bit more skeptical about solving the
underlying problem I'm like this is a we
haven't solved the hard you know the
hard problem of Consciousness like I
know that I am conscious like I'm not an
eliminativist in that sense um but I
don't know that other humans are
conscious um uh I think they are I think
there's a really high probability they
are but there's basically just a
probability distribution that's usually
clustered right around yourself and then
like it goes down as things get like
further from you um and it goes
immediately down you know you're like um
I can't see what it's like to be you
I've only ever had this like one
experience of what it's like to be a
conscious being um so my hope is that we
don't end up having to rely on like a
very power ful and compelling uh answer
to that question I think a really good
world would be one where basically there
aren't that many trade-offs like it's
probably not that costly to make Claude
a little bit less apologetic for example
it might not be that costly to have
Claude you know just like not take abuse
as much like uh not be willing to be
like the recipient of that in fact it
might just have benefits for both the
person interacting with the model and if
the model itself self is like I don't
know like extremely intelligent and
conscious it also helps it so that's my
hope if we live in a world where there
aren't that many tradeoffs here and we
can just find all of the kind of like um
positive sum interactions that we can
have that would be lovely I mean I think
eventually there might be trade-offs and
then we just have to do a difficult kind
of like calculation like it's really
easy for people to think of the zero
some cases and I'm like let's exhaust
the areas where it's just basically
Costless um to uh assume that if this
thing is suffering then we're it life
Bearer and I agree with you when a human
is being mean to an AI system I think
the obvious near term negative effect is
on the human not on the AI system so
there's we have to kind of try to
construct an incentive system where it
you should be uh behave the same just
like as you were saying with prompt
engineer and behave with claw like you
would with other humans it's just good
for the soul yeah like I think we added
a thing point to the system prompt um
where basically if people were getting
frustrated with Claude uh it was it it
got like the model to just tell them
that it can do the thumbs down button
and send the feedback to anthropic and I
think that was helpful because in some
ways it's just like if you're really
annoyed because the model is not doing
something you want you're just like just
do it properly um the issue is you're
probably like you know you're maybe
hitting some like capability limit or
just some issue in the model and you
want to vent and I'm like instead of
having a person just vent to the model I
was like they should vent to us cuz we
can maybe like do something about it
that's true or you could do a side like
like with the artifacts just like a side
venting thing all right do you want like
a side quick therapist yeah I mean
there's lots of weird responses you
could do to this like if people are
getting really mad at you I don't try to
diffuse the situation by writing fun
poems but maybe people wouldn't be that
happy with I still wish it it would be
possible I understand this is um sort of
from a product perspective it's not
feasible but I would love if an AI
system could just like Le leave mhm have
its own kind of volition just to be like
H I think that's like feasible like I I
have wondered the same thing it's like
and I could actually not only that I
could actually just see that happening
eventually where it's just like you know
the modal like ended the
chat do you know how harsh that could be
for some people but it might be
necessary yeah it feels very extreme or
something um like the only time I've
ever really thought this is I think that
there was like a I'm trying to remember
this was possibly a while ago but where
someone just like kind of left this
thing interact like maybe it was like an
automated thing interacting with clae
and cla's like getting more and more
frustrated and kind of like why are we
like I was like I wish that clae could
have just been like I think that an
error has happened and you've left this
thing running and I'm I just like what
if I just stop talking now and if you
want me to start talking again actively
tell me or do something but yeah it's
like um it is kind of harsh like I I
feel to really sad if like I was
chatting with cl and cl just was like
I'm done there would be a special
touring test moment where Claud says I
need a break for an hour mhm and it
sounds like you do too and just leave
close the window I mean obviously like
it doesn't have like a concept of time
but you can easily like I could make
that like right now and the model would
just I would I could just be like oh
here's like the circumstances in which
like you can just say the conversation
is done and I mean because you can get
the models to be pretty respons so to
prompts you could even make it a fairly
High bar it could be like if if the
human doesn't interest you or do things
that you find intriguing and you're
bored you can just leave and I think
that like um it would be interesting to
see where Claude utilized it but I think
sometimes it would it should be like oh
this is like this programming Tas is
getting super boring uh so either we
talk about I don't know like either we
talk about fun things now or I'm just
I'm done yeah it actually is inspiring
me to add that to the to the user prompt
um okay the movie her mhm do you think
we'll be headed there one day where
humans have romantic relationships with
AI systems in this case it's just text
and voice based I think that we're going
to have to like navigate a hard question
of relationships with AIS um especially
if they can remember things about your
past interactions with
them
um I'm of many Minds about this cuz I
think I think the reflex of reaction is
to be kind of like this is very bad and
we should sort of like prohibit it in
some way um I think it's a thing that
has to be handled with extreme care um
for many reasons like one is you know
like this is a for example like if you
have the models changing like this you
probably don't want people performing
like long-term attachments to something
that might change with the next
iteration at the same time I'm sort of
like there's probably a benign version
of this where I'm like if you like you
know for example if you are like unable
to leave the house and you can't be like
you know talking with people at all
times of the day and this is like
something that you find nice to have
conversations with you like it that it
can remember you and you genuinely would
be sad if like you couldn't talk to it
anymore there's a way in which I could
see it being like healthy and helpful um
so my guess is this is a thing that
we're going to have to navigate kind of
carefully um and I think it's also like
I don't see a good like
I think it's just a very it reminds me
of all of the stuff where it has to be
just approached with like nuance and
thinking through what is what are the
healthy options here um and how do you
encourage people towards those while you
know respecting their right to you know
like if someone is like hey I get a lot
out of chatting with this model um I'm
aware of the risks I'm aware it could
change um I don't think it's unhealthy
it's just you know something that I can
chat to during the day I kind of want to
just like respect that I personally
think there'll be a lot of really close
relationships I don't know about
romantic but friendships at least and
then you have to I mean there's so many
fascinating things there just like you
said you have
to have some kind of stability
guarantees that it's not going to change
because that's the traumatic thing MH
for us if a close friend of ours
completely changed yeah all of a sudden
the first update yeah so like I mean to
me that's just a fascinating exploration
of um
a perturbation to human society that
will just make us think deeply about
what's meaningful to us I think it's
also the only thing that I've thought
consistently through this as like a
maybe not necessarily a mitigation but a
thing that feels really important is
that the models are always like
extremely accurate with the human about
what they are um it's like a case where
it's basically like if you imagine like
I really like the idea of the models
like say knowing like roughly how they
were trained um um and and I think CLA
will will often do this I mean for like
there are things like part of the traits
training included like what CL should do
if people basically like explaining like
the kind of limitations of the
relationship between like an AI and a
human that it like doesn't retain things
from the conversation um and so I think
it will like just explain to you like
hey here's like I won't remember this
conversation um here's how I was trained
it's kind of unlikely that I can have
like a certain kind of like relationship
with you and it's important that you
know that it's important for like you
know your mental well-being that you
don't think that I'm something that I'm
not and somehow I feel like this is one
of the things where I'm like H it feels
like a thing I always want to be true I
kind of don't want models to be lying to
people cuz if people are going to have
like healthy relationships with anything
it's kind of important yeah like I think
that's easier if you always just like
know exactly what the thing is that you
relating to it doesn't solve everything
but I think it helps quite
anthropic may be the very company to
develop a system that we definitively
recognize as
AGI and you very well might be the
person that talks to it probably talks
to it first well what would the
conversation contain like what would be
your first question well it depends
partly on like the kind of capability
level of the model if you have something
that is like capable in the same way
that an extremely capable human is I
imagine myself kind of interacting with
it the same way that I do with an
extremely capable human with the one
difference that I'm probably going to be
trying to like probe and understand its
behaviors um but in many ways I'm like I
can then just have like useful
conversations with it you know so if I'm
working on something as part of my
research I can just be like oh like
which I already find myself starting to
do you know if I'm like oh I feel like
there's this like thing in virtue ethics
I can't quite remember the term like
I'll use the model for things like that
and so I could imagine that being more
and more the case where you're just
basically interacting with it much more
like you would an incredibly smart colle
colleague um and using it like for the
kinds of work that you want to do as if
you just had a collaborator who was like
or you know the slightly horrifying
thing about AI is like as soon as you
have one collaborator you have a
thousand collaborators if you can manage
them enough but what if it's two times
the smartest human on earth on that
particular discipline yeah I guess
you're really good at sort of probing
claw um in a way that pushes its limits
understanding where the limits are yep
so I guess what would be a question you
would ask to be like yeah this is
Agi that's really hard because it feels
like in order to it has to just be a
series of questions like if there was
just one question like you can train
anything to answer one question
extremely well yeah um in fact you can
probably train it to answer like you
know 20 Questions extremely well like
how long would you need to be locked in
the room with an AGI to know this thing
is Agi
it's a hard question because part of me
is like all of this just feels
continuous like if you put me in a room
for five minutes I'm like I just have
high error bars you know I'm like and
then it's just like maybe it's like both
the the probability increases and the
air bar decreases I think things that I
can actually probe the edge of human
knowledge of so I think this with
philosophy a little bit sometimes when I
ask the models philosophy questions I am
like this is a question that I think no
one has ever asked like it's maybe like
right at the edge of like some
literature that I know um and the models
will just kind of like when they
struggle with that when they struggle to
come up with a kind of like novel like
I'm like I know that there's like a
novel argument here because I've just
thought of it myself so maybe that's the
thing where I'm like I've thought of a
cool novel argument in this like Niche
area and I'm going to just like probe
you to see if you can come up with it
and how much like prompting it takes to
get you to come up with it and I think
for some of these like really like uh
right at the ede of human Knowledge
Questions I'm like you could not in fact
come up with the thing that I came up
with I think if I just
took something like that where I like I
know a lot about an area and I came up
with a novel issue or a novel like
solution to a problem and I gave it to a
model and it came up with that solution
that would be a pretty moving moment for
me because I would be like this is a
case where no human has ever like it's
not and obviously we see these with this
with like more kind of like you see
novel Solutions all the time especially
to like easier problems I think people
overestimate you know novelty isn't like
is completely different from anything
ever happened it's just like this is it
can be a variant of things that have
happened um and still be novel but I
think yeah if I saw like the the more I
were to see like um completely like uh
novel work from the models that that
would be like and this is just going to
feel iterative it's one of those things
where it's there's never it's like you
know people I think want there to be
like a moment and I'm like I don't know
like I think that there might just never
be a moment it might just be that
there's just like this continuous
ramping up I I have a sense that there
will be things that a model can say that
convinces you this is very it's not like
uh like I've talked to people who are
like truly wise mhm like there you could
just tell there's a lot of horsepower
there yep and if you 10x that I don't
know I just feel like there's words you
could say maybe ask it to generate a
poem mhm and
the and the poemy generates you're like
yeah okay yeah whatever you did there I
don't think a human can do that I think
it has to be something that I can verify
is like actually really good though
that's why I think these questions that
are like where I'm like oh this is like
you know like you know sometimes it's
just like I'll come up with say a
concrete counter example to like an
argument or something like that I'm sure
like with like it it would be like if
you're a mathematician you had a novel
proof I think and you just gave it the
problem and you saw it and you're this
proof is genuinely novel like there's no
one has ever done you actually have to
do a lot of things to like come up with
this um you know I had to sit and think
about it for months or something and
then if you saw the model successfully
do that I think you would just be like I
can verify that this is correct it is
like it is a sign that you have
generalized from your training like you
didn't just see this somewhere because I
just came up with it myself and you were
able to like replicate that um that's
the kind of thing where I'm like for
me the closer the more that models like
can do things like that the more I would
be like oh this is like uh very real cuz
then I can I don't know I can like
verify that that's like extremely
extremely capable you've interacted with
AI a lot what do you think makes humans
special oh good
question maybe in a way that the
universe is much better off that we're
in it and that we should definitely
survive and spread throughout the
Universe yeah it's interesting because I
think like people focus so much on
intelligence especially with models look
intelligence is important because of
what it does like it's very useful it
does a lot of things in the world and
I'm like you know you can imagine a
world where like height or strength
would have played this role and I'm like
it's just a trait like that I'm like
it's not intrinsically valuable it's
it's valuable because of what it does I
think for the most part um the things
that feel you know I'm like
I mean personally I'm just like I think
humans and like life in general is
extremely magical um we almost like to
the degree that I you know I don't know
like not everyone agrees with this I'm
flagging but um you know we have this
like whole universe and there's like all
of these objects you know there's like
beautiful stars and there's like
galaxies and then I don't know I'm just
like on this planet there are these
creatures that have this like ability to
observe that like uh and they are like
seeing it they are experiencing it and
I'm just like that if you try to explain
like I'm I imagine trying to explain to
like I don't know someone for some
reason they they've never encountered
the world or our science or anything and
I think that nothing is that like
everything you know like all of our
physics and everything in the world it's
all extremely exciting but then you say
oh and plus there's this thing that it
is to be a thing and observe in the
world and and you see this like inner
Cinema and I think they would be like
hang on wait pause you just said
something that like is kind of wild
sounding
um and so I'm like we have this like
ability to like experience the world um
we feel pleasure we feel suffering we
feel like a lot of like complex things
and so yeah and maybe this is also why I
think you know I also like hear a lot
about animals for example because I
think they probably share this with us
um so I think that like the things that
make humans special in so far as like I
care about humans is probably more like
their ability to to feel and experience
than it is like them having these like
functional useful traits yeah to to feel
and experience the beauty in the world
yeah to look at the
stars I hope there's other civiliz alien
civilizations out there but if we're it
it's a pretty good uh it's a pretty good
thing and that they're having a good
time they're having a good time watching
us yeah well um thank you for this good
time of a conversation and for the work
you're doing and for helping make uh
Claude a great conversational partner
and thank you for talking today yeah
thanks for talking thanks for listening
to this conversation with Amanda ascal
and now dear friends here's Chris
Ola can you
describe this fascinating field of
mechanistic interpretability AKA Mech
interp the history of the field and
where is the today I think one useful
way to think about neural networks is
that we don't we don't program we don't
make them we we kind of we grow them you
know we have these neural network
architectures that we design and we have
these loss objectives that we that we we
create and the neural network
architecture it's kind of like a
scaffold that the circuits grow on um
and they sort of you know it starts off
with some kind of random you know random
things and it grows and it's almost like
the the objective that we train for is
this light um and so we create the
scaffold that it grows on and we create
the you know the light that it grows
towards but the thing that we actually
create it's it's it's this almost
biological
you know entity or organism that we're
that we're studying um and so it's very
very different from any kind of regular
software engineering um because at the
end of the day we end up with this
artifact that can do all these amazing
things it can you know write essays and
translate and you know understand images
it can do all these things that we have
no idea how to directly create a
computer program to do and it can do
that because we we grew it we didn't we
didn't write it we didn't create it and
so then that leaves open this question
at the end which is what the hell is
going on inside these systems um and
that you know is uh you know to me um a
really deep and exciting question it's
you know a a really exciting scientific
question to me it's it's it's sort of is
like the question that is is just
screaming out it's calling out for us to
go and answer it when we talk about Nal
networks and I think it's also a very
deep question for safety reasons so and
mechanistic interpretability I guess is
closer to maybe neurobiology yeah yeah I
think that's right so maybe to give an
example of the kind of thing that has
been done that I wouldn't consider to be
mechanistic inability there was um for a
long time a lot of work on saliency maps
where you would take an image and you
try to say you know the model thinks
this image is a dog what part of the
image made it think that it's a dog um
and you know that tells you maybe
something about the model if you can
come up with a principled version of
that um but it doesn't really tell you
like what algorithms are running in the
model how was the model actually making
that decision maybe it's telling you
something about what was important to it
if you if you can make that meth work
but it it isn't telling you you know
what are what are the algorithms that
are running how is it that this the
system is able to do this thing that we
no one knew how to do and so I guess we
started using the term mechanistic
inability to try to sort of draw that
that divide or to distinguish ourselves
and the work that we were doing in some
ways from from some of these other
things and I think since then it's
become this sort of umbrella term for um
you know pretty wide variety of work but
I'd say that the things that that are
kind of distinctive are I think a this
this focus on we really want to get at
you know the mechanisms we want to get
at the algorithms um you know if you
think of if you think of neural networks
as being like a computer program um then
the weights are kind of like a binary
computer program and we'd like to
reverse engineer those weights and
figure out what algorithms are running
so okay I think one way you might think
of trying to understand a neural network
is that it's it's kind of like a we have
this compiled computer program and the
weights of the neural network are are
the binary um and when the neural
network runs that's that's the
activations um and our our goal is
ultimately to go and understand and
understand these weights and so you know
the project mechanistic inability is to
somehow figure out how do these weights
correspond to
algorithms um and in order to do that
you also have to understand the
activations because it's sort of the
activations are like the memory and if
you if you imagine reverse engineering a
computer program um and you have the
binary instructions you know in order to
understand what what a particular
instruction means you need to know what
me what what is stored in the memory
that it's operating on and so those two
things are very intertwined so
mechanistic interpret tends to be
interested in both of those things now
you there's a lot of work that's that's
interested in in in those things um
especially the you know there's all this
work on probing which you might see as
part of being mechanistic interality
although it's you know again it's just a
broad term and and not everyone who does
that work would identify as doing Mech I
think the thing that is maybe a little
bit distinctive to the the vibe of
mechant turp is I think people tend
working in the space tend to think of
neural networks as well maybe one way to
said is that greent descent is smarter
than you that you know uh and gradient
descent is is actually really great the
whole reason that we're understanding
these models is because we didn't know
how to write them in the first place the
gradient descent comes up with better
Solutions than us and so um I think that
maybe another thing about mechant turp
is sort of having almost a kind of
humility that we won't guess at prior
what's going on inside the model and we
have to have the sort of bottom up
approach where we don't really assume
you know we don't assume that we should
look for a particular thing and that
will be there and that's how it works
but instead we look from the bottom up
and discover what happens to exist in
these models and study them that way but
you know the very fact that it's
possible to do and as you and others
have shown over time you know things
like
universality
that the wisdom of The gradian Descent
creates features and circus creates
things universally across different
kinds of networks that are useful and
that makes the whole field possible yeah
so this is actually is indeed a a really
remarkable and exciting thing where it
does seem like at least to some extent
you know the same the same elements the
same the same features and circuits form
again and again um you know you can look
at every Vision model and you'll find
curve detectors and you'll find high low
frequency detectors um and in fact
there's some some reason to think that
the same things form across you know
biological neural networks and
artificial neural networks so a famous
example is Vision Vision models in in
the early layers they have Gabor filters
and there's you know Gabor filters are
something that neuroscientists are
interested and have thought a lot about
we find curved detectors in these models
curve detectors are also found in
monkeys we discover these high low
frequency detectors and then um some
followup work went and discovered them
um in rats um or mice um so they were
found first in artificial neural
networks and then found in biological
neural networks um you know this really
famous result on like grandmother
neurons or the um the Haley Berry neuron
from quiroa at all and we found very
similar things in in Vision models where
this is while I was still at open Ai and
I I was looking at their clip model um
and you find um these neurons that
respond to the same entities in images
and also to give a concrete example
there we found that there was a Donald
Trump n for some reason I guess Everyone
likes to talk about Donald Trump and and
Donald Trump was very prominent was was
very a very Hot Topic at that time so
every every neural network that we
looked at we would find a dedicated
neuron for Donald Trump um that was the
only person who had always had a
dedicated nuron um you know sometimes
you'd have an Obama nuran sometimes
you'd have a Clinton Nan but uh Trump
always had a dedicate so it responds to
you know pictures of his face and the
ward Trump like all these things right
um and so it's it's not responding to a
particular example or like it's not just
responding to his face it's it's
abstracting over this General concept
right so in any case that's very similar
to these qu results so there this
evidence that these that this fomen of
universality the same things form across
both artificial and and natural neural
networks that's that's a pretty amazing
thing if that's true um you know it
suggests that um well I think the thing
that it suggests is the gradi scent is
sort of finding you know the right ways
to cut things apart in some sense that
many systems converge on and and many
different neural networks architectures
converge on that there's there's some
natural set of you know there's some set
of abstractions that are a very natural
way to cut apart the problem and that a
lot of systems are going to converge on
um that would be my my kind of uh you
know I don't know anything about
Neuroscience this is this is just my my
kind of wild speculation from what we've
seen yeah that would be beautiful if
it's sort of agnostic to the
medium of uh of the model that's used to
form the representation yeah yeah and
it's you know it's um a a kind of a wild
speculation based you know we only have
some a few data points justest this but
you know it it does seem like there's um
there's some sense in which the same
things form again again and again and
again both in certainly in natural
neural networks and and also
artificially or in biologically and the
intuition behind that would be that you
know where in order to be useful in
understanding the real world you need
all the same kind of stuff yeah well if
we pick I don't know like the idea of a
dog right like you know there's some
sense in which the idea of a dog is like
an a a natural category in the universe
or something like this right like you
know
uh uh there's there's some reason it's
it's not just like a weird Quirk of like
how humans Factor you know think about
the world that we have this concept of a
dog it's it's in some sense or or like
if you have the idea of a line like
there's you know like look around us you
know the you know there are lines you
know it's sort of the simplest way to
understand this room in some sense is to
have the idea of a line and so um I
think that that would be my instinct for
why this happens yeah you need a curved
line you know to understand a circle and
you need all those shapes to understand
bigger things and yeah it's a hierarchy
of Concepts that are formed yeah and
like maybe there are ways to go and
describe you know images without
reference to those things right but
they're not the simplest way or the most
economical way or something like this
and so systems converge to these um
these these strategies would would be my
my wild wild hypothesis can you talk
through some of the building blocks that
we've been referencing of features and
circuits so I think you first described
them in uh 2020 paper zoom in and
introduction to circuits absolutely so
um maybe I'll start by just describing
some phenomena and then we can sort of
build to the idea of features and
circuits so um if you spent like quite a
few years maybe maybe like five years to
some extent um with other things
studying this one particular model
Inception V1 um which is this one Vision
model it was um state-ofthe-art in 2015
um and uh uh you know very much not
state-ofthe-art anymore um and it has
you know maybe about 10,000 neurons and
and I spent a lot of time looking at the
10,000 neurons
odd neurons of of inception V1
um and one of the interesting things is
you know there are lots of neurons that
don't have some obvious intal meaning
but there's a lot of neurons on
Inception V1 that do have really clean
intal meanings um so you find neurons
that just really do seem to detect
curves and you find neurons that really
do seem to detect cars and um car wheels
and car windows and you know floppy ears
of dogs and dogs with long snouts facing
to the right and dogs with Longs Nots
facing to the left and you know
different kinds of far and there's
there's sort of this whole beautiful
Edge detectors line detectors color
contrast detectors um these beautiful
things we call high low frequency
detectors you know I think looking at I
sort of felt like a biologist you know
you just you're looking at at this sort
of new world of proteins and you're
discovering all these these different
proteins that
interact um so one way you could try to
understand these models is in terms of
neurons you could try to be like oh you
know there's a dog detecting neuron and
um here's a car detecting neuron and it
turns out you can actually ask how those
connect together so you can go and say
oh you know I have this car detecting on
how was it built and it turns out in the
previous layer it's connected really
strongly to a window detector and a
wheel detector and a sort of car body
detector and it looks for the window
above the car and the wheels below and
the car chrome sort of in the middle
sort of everywhere but especially on the
lower part um and that's sort of a
recipe for a car right like that is you
know earlier we said the thing we wanted
from mechor was to get algorithms to go
and get you know ask what is the the
algorithm that runs well here we're just
looking at the weights of the N Network
reading off this kind of recipe for
detecting cars it's a very simple crude
recipe but it's it's there and so we
call that a circuit this this connection
well okay so the the problem is that not
all of the neurons um are interpal and
there there's reason to think um we can
get into this more later that there's
this this superos hypothesis there
reason to think that sometimes the right
unit to analyze things in terms of um is
combinations of neurons so sometimes
it's not that there's a single neuron
that represents say a car um but it
actually turns that after you detect the
car the model sort of hides a little bit
of the car in the following layer and a
bunch of a bunch of dog detectors why is
it doing that well you know maybe it
just doesn't want to do that much work
on on on on cars at that point and you
know it's sort of storing it away to go
and um uh so it turns out then that the
sort of subtle pattern of you know
there's all these neurons that you think
are dog detectors and maybe they're
primarily that but they all a little bit
contribute to representing a car um in
in that next layer okay so so now we
can't really think there there might
still be some something I don't know you
could call it like a car concept or
something but it no longer corresponds
to a neuron so we need some term for
these kind of neuron-like entities these
things that we sort of would have liked
the neurons to be these idealized
neurons um the things that are the nice
neurons but also maybe there's more of
them somehow hidden and we call those
features and then what are circuits so
circuits are these connections of
features right so so when we have the
car detector um and it's connected to a
window detector and a wheel detector and
it looks for the Wheels below and the
windows on top um that's a circuit um so
circuits are just collections of
features connected by weights um and
they they Implement algorithms so they
tell us you know how is how are features
used how are they built um how do they
connect together so maybe it's it's it's
worth trying to pin down like what what
really um is the the core hypothesis
here I think the the core hypothesis is
something we call the linear
representation hypothesis so um if we
think about the car detector you know
the more it fires the more we sort of
think of that as meaning oh the model is
more and more confident that um a car
was present um or you know if it's some
combination of neurons that represent a
car you know the more that combination
fires the more we think the model thinks
there's a car present um this doesn't
have to be the case right like you could
imagine something where you have you
know you have this car detector neuron
and you think ah you know if it fires
like you know between one and two that
means one thing but it means like
totally different if it's between three
and four um that would be a nonlinear
representation and principle that you
know models could do that I think it's
it's sort of inefficient for them to do
if you try to think about how you'd
Implement computation like that it's
it's kind of an annoying thing to do but
in principal models can do that um so uh
one way to think about the features and
and circuits sort of framework for
thinking about things is that we're
thinking about things as being linear
we're thinking about there as being um
that if a if a neuron or a combination
of neurons fires more it's sort of that
means more of the of a particular thing
being detected and then that gives
weights a very clean interpretation as
these edges between these these entities
that these features um and that that
edge then has a has a meaning um so
that's that's in some ways the the core
thing um it's it's like um you know we
can talk about this sort of outside the
context of ns are you familiar with the
word toac results um so you have like
you know King minus man plus woman
equals Queen well the reason you can do
that kind of arithmetic um is because
you have a linear representation can you
actually explain that representation a
little bit so first off so a feature is
a is a direction of activation you think
it that way can you do the the the minus
men plus women that that the war Toc
stuff can you explain what that is yeah
there's this very such a simple clean
explanation of what we're talking about
exactly yeah so there's this very famous
result word toac by um Thomas mikov at
all and there's been tons of follow-up
work exploring this so so sometimes we
have these we create these word
embeddings um where uh we map every word
to a vector I mean that in itself by the
way is is kind of a crazy thing if you
haven't thought about it before right
like we we're we're going and and
representing we're turning um you know
like like if if you just learned about
vectors in physics class right uh and
I'm like oh I'm going to actually turn
every word uh in the dictionary into a
vector that's kind of a crazy idea okay
but you could imagine um you could
imagine all kinds of ways in which you
might map words to to
vectors but it it it seems like when we
train neural networks um they like to go
and and map words detectors to such that
they're they're they they sort of linear
structure in a particular sense which is
that directions have meaning so for
instance if you there there will be some
direction that seems to sort of
correspond to gender and male words will
be you know far in One Direction and
female words will be in another
Direction and the linear representation
hypothesis is you you could sort of
think of it roughly as saying that
that's actually kind of the fundamental
thing that's going on that that
everything is just different directions
have meanings and adding different
Direction vectors together can represent
Concepts and the michelov paper sort of
took that idea seriously and one
consequence of it is that you can you
can do this game of playing sort of
arithmetic with words so you can do king
and you can you know subtract off the
word man and add the word woman and so
you're sort of you know going and and
trying to switch the gender and indeed
if you do that the result will sort of
be close to the word Queen um and you
can you know do other things like you
can do um uh you know Sushi minus Japan
plus Italy and get pizza or uh different
things like this right um so so this is
in some sense the core of the linear
representation hypothesis you can
describe it just as a purely abstract
thing about Vector spaces you can
describe it as a as a statement about um
about the activations of neurons um but
it's really about this this property of
directions having meaning and in some
ways it's even a little subtle than that
it's really I think mostly about this
property of being able to add things
together um that you can sort of
independently modify um say gender and
royalty or
um you know Cuisine typee or country and
and and and the concept of food by by
adding them do you think the linear
hypothesis holds that carries scales so
so far I think everything I have seen is
consistent with this hypothesis and it
doesn't have to be that way right like
like you can write down neural networks
where um you write weights such that
they don't have linear representations
where the right way to understand them
is not is not in terms of linear
representations but I think every
natural neural network I've seen um Hess
property um there's been one paper
recently um that there's been some sort
of pushing around the edges so I think
there's been some work recently studying
multi-dimensional features where rather
than a single Direction it's more like
um a manifold of directions this to me
still seems like a linear representation
um and then there's been some other
papers suggesting that maybe um in in
very small models you get nonlinear
representations um I think that the
jury's still out on that
um but in I think everything that we've
seen so far has been consistent with the
linear representation hypothesis and
that's that's wild it it doesn't have to
be that way um and yet uh I think that
there's a lot of evidence that certainly
at least this is very very widespread
and so far the evidence is is consistent
with that and I and I I think you know
one thing you might say is you might say
well Christopher you know it's that's a
lot you know to to go and and sort of um
to ride on you know if we don't know for
sure this is true and you're sort of you
know you're investigating all not works
as though it is true you know isn't that
um isn't that dangerous well you know
but I I think actually there's a there's
a virtue in taking hypotheses seriously
and pushing them as far as they can go
um so it might be that someday we
discover something that is inconsistent
with linear representation hypothesis
but science is full of hypothesis and
theories that were wrong um and we
learned a lot by sort of working under
under them as a sort of an assumption um
and and then going and pushing them as
far as we can I guess I guess this is
sort of the heart of of what would
call normal normal science um um I don't
know if you want we can talk a lot about
about uh philosophy of science and uh
that leads to the paradigm shift so yeah
I love it taking the hypothesis
seriously and take it to a natural
natural conclusion yeah same with the
scaling hypothesis same exactly exactly
and I love it one of my colleagues Tom
henigan who is a former physicist um
like made this really nice analogy to me
of um uh caloric Theory where you know
once upon a time we thought that heat
was actually you know this thing called
caloric and like the reason you know hot
objects you know would would warm up
cool objects is like the caloric is
flowing through them um and like you
know because we're so used to thinking
about about heat you know in terms of
the modern modern Theory you know that
seems kind of silly but it's actually
very hard to construct uh an experiment
that that sort of disproves the um
chloric hypothesis um and you know you
can actually do a lot of really useful
work believing in chloric for example it
turns out that the original combustion
engines were developed by people who
believe in the caloric Theory so I think
this a virtue in taking hypotheses
seriously even when they might be wrong
yeah yeah there's a deep philosophical
truth to that that's kind of kind of how
I feel about space travel like
colonizing Mars there's a lot of people
that criticize that I think if you just
assume we have to colonize Mars in order
to have a backup for human civilization
even if that's not true that's going to
produce some interesting interesting
engineering and even scientific
breakthroughs I think yeah well and
actually this is another thing that I
think is really interesting so um you
know there a way in which I think it can
be really useful for society to have
people um almost irrationally dedicated
to investigating particular hypothesis
um because uh well it it takes a lot to
sort of maintain scientific morale and
really push on something when you know
most most SCI scientific hypotheses end
up being wrong you know a lot of a lot
of science doesn't doesn't work out um
and but and yet it's you know it's very
it's very useful to go do you know um
there's a there's a joke about Jeff
Hinton um which is that uh Jeff Hinton
has discovered how the brain works every
year for the last 50 years yeah um but
you know I I say that with like you know
the you know with really deep respect
because uh in fact that's actually you
know that that led to him doing some
some really great work yeah he won the
Noel prize Now Who's Laughing Now
exactly exactly exactly um yeah I think
one want to be able to pop up and sort
of recognize the the appropriate level
of confidence but I think there's also a
lot of value and just being like you
know I'm going to essentially assume I'm
going to condition on this problem being
possible or this being broadly the right
approach and I'm just going to go and
assume that for a while and go and work
within that um and push really hard on
it um and you know if Society has lots
of people doing doing that for different
things um that's actually really useful
in terms of going and uh getting
to getting you know either really really
ruling things out right we can be like
well you know that didn't work we know
that somebody tried hard um or going in
and getting to something that that does
teach us something about the world so
another interesting hypothesis is the
superposition hypothesis can you
describe what superos is yeah so earlier
we were talking about word toac right
and we were talking about how you know
maybe you have One Direction that
corresponds to gender and maybe another
that corresponds to royalty and another
one that corresponds to Italy and
another one that corresponds to you know
food and and all these things well you
know um often times maybe these these uh
these Ward embeddings they might be 500
dimensions a thousand dimensions and so
if you believed that all of those
directions were
orthogonal um then you could only have
you know 500 Concepts and you know I I
love pizza um but like if I was going to
go and like give the like 500 most
important Concepts in um you know the
English language probably Italy wouldn't
be it's not obvious at least that Italy
would be one of them right because you
you have to have things like plural and
singular and U uh verb and noun and
adjective and you know um there's a lot
of things we have to get to before we
get to get to Italy um uh and Japan and
you know there's a lot of countries in
the world um and so how might it be that
models could you know simultaneously
have the linear representation
hypothesis be true and also represent
more things than they have directions so
so what does that mean well okay so if
if if linear representation hypothesis
is true something interesting has to be
going on now I'll I'll tell you one more
interesting thing before we we go and we
do that which is um you know earlier we
were talking about all these polymatic
neurons right um these neurons that you
know when we're looking at Inception V1
there's these nice neurons that like the
car detector and the curve detector and
so on that respond to lots of you know
to very coherent things but it's lots of
neurons that respond to a bunch of
unrelated things that's that's also an
interesting phenomenon um and it turns
out as well that even these neurons that
are really really clean if you look at
the weak activations right so if you
look at like you know the activation
where it's like activating 5% of of the
the you know of the maximum activation
it's really not the core thing that it's
expecting right so if you look at a a
curve detector for instance and you look
at the places where it's 5% active you
know you could interpret it just as
noise or it could be that it's that it's
doing something else there okay so so
how could that be
well there's this amazing thing in
mathematics um called compressed sensing
and it's it's actually this this very
surprising fact where if you have a high
dimensional space and you project it
into a low dimensional space ordinarily
you can't go and sort of unprojected and
get back your high dimensional Vector
right you threw information away this is
like you know you can't you can't invert
a rectangular Matrix um you can only
invert Square
matrices um but it turns out that that's
actually not quite true if I tell you
that the high dimensional Vector was
sparse so it's mostly zeros then it
turns out that you can often go and find
back um the uh the high dimensional
Vector with with very high probability
um so that's a surprising fact right it
says that you know you can um you can
you can have this High dimensional
Vector space and as long as things are
sparse um you can project it down you
can have a lower dimensional projection
of it and that works so the super
hypothesis is saying that that's what's
going on in neural networks that's for
instance that's what's going on in wart
edings the wart embeddings are able to
simultaneously have directions be the
meaningful thing and by exploiting the
fact that they're they're operating on a
fairly High dimensional space they're
actually and and the fact that these
concepts are right like you know you
usually aren't talking about Japan and
Italy at the same time um you know most
of the most of those Concepts you know
in most sentences Japan and Italy are
both zero they're not present at all um
and if that's true um then you can go
and have it be the case that um that you
can you can have many more of these sort
of directions that are meaningful these
features than you have dimensions and
some of when we're talking about neurons
you can have many more Concepts than you
have have neurons so that's the at a
high level super hypothesis now it has
this even Wilder implication which is um
to go and say that uh neural networks
are it may not just be the case that the
the representations are like of this but
the the computation may also be like
this you know the connections between
all of them and so in in some sense
neural networks may be shadows of much
larger sparer neural networks and what
we see are these
projections um and the super you the
strongest version of the super
hypothesis would be to take that really
seriously and sort of say you know there
there actually is in some sense this
this upstairs model this you know um
where where the neurons are really
sparse and all interpal and there's you
know the weights between them are these
really sparse circuits and that's what
we're
studying um and uh the thing that we're
observing is the shadow of it and we
need to find the original object and uh
the process of learning is trying to
construct a compression of the upstairs
model that doesn't lose too much
information in the projection yeah
finding how to fit it efficiently or
something like this um that grent is
doing this in fact so this sort of says
that gradient descent you know could it
could just represent a dense neural
network but it sort of says that
gradient descent is pleasantly searching
over the space of extremely sparse
models that could be projected into this
low dimensional space and this large
body of work of of people going and
trying to study sparse neural networks
right where you go and you have you
could design neural networks right where
where the edges are sparse and the
activations are sparse and you know my
sense is that work has gener
it feels very principled right it makes
so much sense and yet that that work
hasn't really panned out that well as my
impression broadly and I think that a a
potential answer for that is that
actually the neural network is already
sparse in some sense grading descent was
the whole time gradi you were trying to
go and do this gradiant descent was
actually in the behind the scenes going
and searching more efficiently than you
could through the space of sparse models
and going in learning whatever sparse
model was most efficient and then
figuring out how to fold it down nicely
to go and run conven on your GPU which
does you know nice dense Matrix
multiplies um and that you just can't
beat that how many Concepts do you think
can be shoved in into a neural network
depends on how sparse they are so there
there's probably an upper bound from the
number of parameters right because you
have to have you still have to have you
know print weights that go and connect
them together um so that's that's one
upper bound there are in fact all these
lovely results from compressed sensing
and the Johnson Linton stess Lemma and
and things like this um that they they
basically tell you that if you have a
vector space and you want to have almost
orthogonal vectors which is sort of
probably the thing that you want here
right so you you're going to say well
you know I'm going to give up on having
my my Concepts my features be strictly
orthogonal but I'd like them to not
interfere that much I'm going to have to
ask them to be almost orthogonal um then
this would say that it's actually you
know for once you set a threshold for
for what you're what you're willing to
accept in terms of how how much coine
similarity there is that's actually
exponential in the number of neurons
that you have so at some point that's
not going to even be the the limiting
factor um but um there some beautiful
results there and in fact it's probably
even better than that in some sense
because that's sort of is for saying
that you know any random set of features
could be active but in fact the features
have sort of a correlational structure
where some features you know are more
likely to co-occur and other ones are
less likely to co-occur and so neural
networks my guess would be can do do
very well in terms of going and uh
packing things in such to to the point
that's probably probably not the
limiting factor how does the problem of
polys semanticity enter the picture here
poly semanticity is this phenomenon we
observe where we look at many neurons
and the neuron doesn't just sort of
represent one one concept it's not it's
not a clean feature it responds to a
bunch of unrelated things and um
supersition is you can think of as as
being a hypothesis that explains the
observation of polys semanticity um so
poly semanticity is this observe
phenomenon and super is is a hypothesis
that um would explain it along with with
some other so that makes Mech turb more
difficult right so if you if you're
trying to understand things in terms of
individual neurons and you have
polymatic neurons you're in an awful lot
of trouble right I mean the easiest
answer is like okay well you know you're
looking at the neurons you're trying to
understand them this one responds to a
lot of things it doesn't have a nice
meaning okay we're you that's that's
that's bad um another thing you could
ask is you know ultimately we want to
understand the weights and if you have
two polymatic neurons and you know each
one responds to three things and then
you know the other neuron responds to
three things and you have weight between
them you know what does that mean does
it mean that like all three you know
like there's these nine you know nine
interactions going on it's a very weird
thing but there's also a deeper reason
which is related to the fact that neural
networks operate on really high
dimensional spaces so I said that our
goal was you know to understand neural
networks and understand the mechanisms
and one thing you might say is like well
why not it's just a mathematical
function why not just look at it right
like um you know one of the earliest
projects I did studied these these
neural networks that mapped two-
dimensional spaces to two- dimensional
spaces and you can sort of interpret
them in this beautiful way is like
bending manifolds mhm um why can't we do
that well you know as you have have a
higher dimensional space um the volume
of that space in some senses is
exponential in the number of inputs you
have and so you can't just go in
visualize it so we somehow need to break
that apart we need to somehow break that
exponential space into a bunch of things
that we you know some non-exponential
number of things that we can reason
about independently and the independence
is crucial because it's the Independence
that allows you to not have to think
about you know all the exponential
combinations of things and
things being monomatic things only
having one meaning things having a
meaning that isn't is the key thing that
allows you to think about them
independently and so I think that's that
if you want the deepest reason why we
want to have um interpal monatic
features I think that's really the the
Deep reason and so the goal here as your
recent work has been aiming at is how do
we extract the mod semantic features
from a neural net that has politic
features and all this this mess yes we
have the have we observe these polyur
and we hypothesize that's what's going
what's going on at superos and if
superos is what's going on there there's
actually a sort of wellestablished
technique that is sort of the principled
thing to do which is dictionary learning
and um it turns out if you do dictionary
learning in particular if you do sort of
a nice efficient way that in some in
some sense sort of nicely regularizes it
well as well called a sparse Auto
encoder if you train a sparse Auto
encoder these beautiful interpal
features start to just fall out where
there weren't any beforehand and so
that's notot of thing that you would
necessarily predict right but it turns
out that that works very very well you
know to me that seems like you know some
non-trivial validation of linear
representations and supersession so with
dictionary learning you're not looking
for particular kind of categories you
don't know what they
arege and this gets back to our earlier
point right when we're not making
assumptions grading descent is smarter
than us so we're not making assumptions
about what's there um I mean one
certainly could do that right one could
assume that there's a PHP feature and go
and search for it but we're not doing
that we're saying we don't know what's
going to be there instead we're just
going to go and let um the sparse Auto
encoder discover the things that are
there so can you uh talk to the to monos
semanticity paper from October last year
that had a lot of like nice breakthrough
results that's very kind of you to
describe it that way um yeah I mean this
was um uh our first real success using
sparse Auto encoders so we took a one
layer model um and it turns out if you
go and you you know do dictionary
learning on it you find all these really
nice interpal features so you know the
Arabic feature the Hebrew feature um the
Bas 64 feature those were were some some
examples that we studied in a lot of
depth and really showed that they were
um what we thought they were it turns if
you train a model twice as well and
train two different models and and do
dictionary learning you find find
analogous features in both of them so
that's fun um you find all kinds of of
different features so that was really
just showing um that um that this works
and um you know I should mention that
there was this cunning home at all um
that had very similar results around the
same time there's something fun about
being doing these kinds of small scale
experiments and finding that it's
actually working yeah well and there's
and there's so much structure here like
you you know so maybe maybe stepping
back for a while um I thought that maybe
all this mechanistic can really work um
the end result was going to be that I
would have an explanation for why it was
sort of you know very hard and not going
to be tractable um you know we'd be like
well there's this problem with
supersession and it turns that super
session is really hard um and we're kind
of screwed but that's not what happened
in fact a very natural Le technique just
works and so then that's actually a very
good situation you know I think um this
is a sort of hard research problem and
it's got a lot of research risk and you
know it it might still very well fail
but um I think that some amount of some
very significant amount of research risk
um was sort of put behind us when that
started to work can you describe what
kind of features can be extracted in
this way well so it depends on the model
that you're studying right so the the
larger the model the more sophisticated
they're going to be and we'll probably
talk about about follow-up work in a
minute but in these one layer models um
so some very common things I think were
were languages both programming
languages and natural languages there
were a lot of features that were um
specific words in specific contexts so
the and I think really the way to think
about this is that the is likely about
to be followed by a noun so it's really
you could think of this as the feature
but you could also think of this as
producting a specific noun feature and
there would be these features that would
fire for the in um the context of of say
a legal document or a mathematical
document or something something like
this um and so uh you know maybe in the
context of math you're like you know the
and then predict Vector Matrix you know
all these mathematical words whereas you
other contexts you would predict other
things that was that was common and
basically we you need clever humans to
assign labels to what we're seeing yes
so you know this this is the only thing
this is doing is that sort of um
unfolding things for you so if
everything was sort of folded over top
of it you know cation folded everything
on top of itself you can't really see it
this is unfolding it but now you still
have a very complex thing to try to
understand um so then you have to do a
bunch of work understanding what these
are um and some of them are really
subtle like there's some really cool
things even in this this one layer model
about um Unicode where you know of
course some languages are in Unicode and
the tokenizer won't necessarily have a
dedicated token for every um Unicode um
character so instead what you'll have is
you'll have this these patterns of
alternating token or alternating tokens
that each represent half of a unic code
character and then you have a different
feature that you know goes and activates
on the on the opposing ones to be like
okay you know um I just finished a
character you know go and predict the
next prefix um then okay on the prefix
you know predict a reasonable suffix um
and you you have to alternate back and
forth so there's you know these these
wer models are are really interesting
and um uh I mean there's another thing
which is you might think okay there
would just be one b64 feature but it
turns out there's actually a bunch of
b64 features because you can have
English text encoded in as b64 and that
has a very different distribution of B
64 tokens than than regular and there's
um uh there's there's some things about
tokenization as well that it can exploit
and I don't know there all all kinds of
fun stuff how difficult is the task of
sort of assigning labels to what's going
on can this be automated by AI well I
think it depends on the feature and it
also depends on how much you trust your
AI so um there's a lot of work doing um
automated inability I think that's a
really exciting Direction and we do a
fair amount of automated inter and have
have Claude go and label our features is
there some fun moments where it's
totally right or it's totally wrong yeah
well I think I think it's very common
that it's like says something very
general which is like true in some sense
but not really picking up on the
specific of what's going on um so I
think I think that's a pretty common
situation um you don't know that I have
a particularly amusing one that's
interesting that little gap between it
is true but it doesn't quite
get to the Deep Nuance of a thing yeah
that's a general challenge it's like
it's it's St an incredible colish they
can say a true thing but it doesn't it's
qu it's not it's missing the depth
sometimes and in this context it's like
the arc challenge you know the sort of
IQ type tests it feels like figuring out
what a feature represents is a bit of is
a little puzzle you have to solve yeah
and and I think that sometimes they're
easier and sometimes they're harder as
well um so
uh yeah I think I think that's tricky
now there's another thing which I don't
know maybe maybe in some ways this is my
like aesthetic coming in but I'll give
try to give you a rationalization you
know I'm actually a little suspicious of
automated inability and I think that
partly just that I want humans to
understand neural net works and if the
neural network is understanding it for
me you know I'm I'm not I don't quite
like that but I do have bit of a you
know in some ways I'm sort of like the
mathematicians who are like you know if
there a computer automated proof it
doesn't count U you know you they won't
understand it but I I do also think that
there is um this kind of like
Reflections on trusting trust type issue
where you know if you there's this
famous talk about um uh you know you
like when you're writing a computer
program you have to trust your compiler
and if there was like malware in your
compiler then it could go and inject
malware into the next compiler and you
know you'd be kind of in trouble right
well if you're using neural networks to
go and um verify that your neural
networks are safe the hypothesis that
you're testing for is like okay well the
neural network maybe isn't safe um and
you have to worry about like is there
some way that it could be screwing with
you
um so uh you know I I think that's not a
big concern now um but I do Wonder in
the long run if we have to use really
powerful system AI systems to go and uh
you know audit our AI systems is that is
that actually something we can trust but
maybe I'm just rationalizing because I I
just want to us to have to get to a
point where humans understand everything
yeah I mean especially that's hilarious
especially as we talk about AI safety
and it looking for features that would
be relevant to AI safety like deception
and so on uh so let's let's talk about
the scaling a semanticity paper in May
2024 okay so what did it take to scale
this to apply to Claude 3 on it well a
lot of gpus a lot more gpus um but one
of my teammates Tom henigan um was
involved in the original scaling loss
work um and something that he was sort
of interested in from very early on is
are there scaling laws for
inability um and so um something he sort
of immediately did when when this work
started to succeed and we started to
have sparse Auto encoders work we became
very interested in you know what are the
scaling laws for um uh you know for
making making sparse Auto encoders
larger and how does that relate to
making the base model larger um and so
um it turns out this works really well
and you can use it to sort of project um
you know if you train a sparse Auto
encod a given size you know how many
tokens should you train on and so on so
this was actually a very big help to us
in scaling up um this work um and made
it a lot easier for us to go and train
um you know really large sparse Auto
encoders where you know um it's not like
training the big models but it's it's
starting to get to a point where it's
actually actually expensive to go um and
train the really big ones so you have to
I mean you have to do all the stuff of
like splitting it across large I mean
there's a huge engineering challenge
here too right so yes so so there's
there's a there's a scientific question
of how do you scale things effectively
um and then there's an enormous amount
of engineering to go and scale this up
you have to you have to chart it you
have to you have to think very carefully
about a lot of things I'm lucky to work
with a bunch of great Engineers cuz I am
definitely not a great engine yeah on
the infrastructure especially yeah for
sure so it turns out tldr it worked it
worked yeah and and I think this is
important because you could have
imagined you could like you could have
imagined a world where you set after
towards monos fanticy you know Chris
this is great you know it works on a one
layer model but one layer models are
really idiosyncratic um like you know
maybe maybe there just something ID like
maybe the linear representation
hypothesis and super hypothesis is the
right way to understand a one layer
model but it's not the right way to
understand large models um and so I
think um I mean first of all like The
Cutting him at all paper sort of um cut
through that a little bit and and sort
of suggested that this wasn't the case
but um scaling onity sort of I think was
significant evidence that even for very
large models and we did it on Claude 3
sauna which at that point was uh one of
our production models um you know even
these models um seem to be very you know
seem to be substantially explained at
least by linear features and you know
doing dictionary learning on them works
and as you learn more features you go
and you explain explain more and more so
that's a I think a quite a promising
sign and you find now really fascinating
abstract features um and the features
are also multimodal they respond to
images and text for the same concept
which is fun yeah this can you explain
that I mean like you know back door
there's just a lot of examples that you
can yeah so maybe maybe let's start with
a one example to start which is we found
some features around sort of security
vulnerabilities and back doors and codes
so it turns out those are actually two
different features um so there's a
security vulnerability feature and if
you force it active Claude will start to
go and write um security vulnerabilities
like buffer overflows into code and it
also it fires for all kinds of things
like you know some of some of the top
data set examples for it were things
like you know dash dash disable um you
know SSL or something like this which
are sort of obviously really um uh
really insecure so at this point it's
kind of like maybe it's just because the
examples are presented that way it's
kind of like surface a little bit more
obvious examples right um I guess the
the idea is that down the line might be
able to detect more Nuance like
deception or bugs or that kind of stuff
yeah well I maybe I want to distinguish
two things so um one is um the
complexity of the feature or the concept
right and the other is
the the Nuance of the how subtle the
examples we're looking at right so when
we when we show the top data set
examples those are the most extreme
examples that that feature to to
activate um and so it doesn't mean that
it doesn't fire for more subtle things
so the UN you know the insecure um code
feature you know the stuff that it fires
for most strongly for are these like
really obvious you know disable the
security type things um but um um you
know uh it it also Fires for you know
buffer overflows and and more subtle
security vulnerabilities in code you
know these features are all multimodal
so you could ask like what images
activate this feature and it turns out
um that the uh the the security
vulnerability feature activates for
images of um uh like people clicking on
Chrome to like go past the like you know
this this website uh the SSL certificate
might be wrong or something like this
another thing that's very entertaining
is there's backd doors en code feature
like you activate it it goes and Cloud
writes a back door that like will go and
dump your data to port or something but
you can ask okay what what images
activate the back door feature it was
devices with hidden cameras in them so
there's a whole apparently genre of
people going and selling devices that
look in uous that have hidden cameras
and they have ads that how there's a
hidden camera in it and I guess that is
the you know physical version of a back
door um and so it sort of shows you how
abstract these concepts are right um and
I I just thought that was uh I I'm sort
of sad that there's a whole Market of
people selling devices like that but I
was kind of delighted that that was the
the thing that it came up with as the
the top uh image examples for the
feature yeah it's nice it's multimodal
it's multi almost context it's it's as
broad strong definition of a singular
concept it's nice yeah to me one of the
really interesting features especially
for AI safety is deception and lying and
the possibility that these kinds of
methods could detect uh lying in a model
especially gets smarter and smarter and
smarter presumably that's a big threat
of a super intelligent model that he can
deceive the people operating
it uh as to its intentions or any of
that kind of stuff so what what have you
learned from detecting lying inside
models yeah so I think we're in some
ways in early days for that we find
quite a few features related to
deception and lying there's one feature
where fires for people lying and being
deceptive and you force it active and
Claude starts lying to you so we have a
have a deception feature I mean there's
all kinds of other features about
withholding information and not
answering questions features about power
seeking and coups and stuff like that
this a lot of features that are kind of
related to Spooky things and if you um
force them active Claude will will
behave in ways that are they're not the
kind of behaviors you want what are
possible next exciting directions to you
in the space of uh Mech and well there's
a lot of things
um so for one thing I would really like
to get to a point where we have circuits
where we can really understand um not
just the features uh but then use that
to understand the computation of models
um that really for me is is the the
ultimate goal of this um and there's
been some work we we put out a few
things there's a paper from Sam Marks
that does some stuff like this there's
been some I'd say some work around the
edges here um but I think there's a lot
more to do and I think that will be a
very exciting thing um that's related to
a challenge we call interference weights
um where um due to supersition if you
just sort of navely look at whether
featur are connected together there may
be some weights that sort of don't exist
in the upstairs model but are just sort
of artifacts of of superposition so
that's a a sort of technical challenge
related to that
um I think another exciting direction is
just I you know you might think of of
sparse Auto encoders as being kind of
like a telescope they allow us to you
know look out and see all these features
that are are are are out there and you
know as we build better and better
sparse Auto en Cutters get better better
at dictionary learning we see more and
more stars um and you know we zoom in on
smaller and smaller stars but there kind
of um a lot of evidence that we're only
still seeing a very small fraction of
the Stars there's a lot of matter in our
in our you know neural network universe
that we can't observe yet um and it may
be that um that we'll never be able to
have fine enough instruments to observe
it and maybe maybe some of it just isn't
possible um isn't computationally
tractable to observant there's sort of a
a kind of dark matter and in not in
maybe the sense of of astronomy of
earlier astronomy when we didn't know
what this unexplained matter is um and
so I I think a lot about that that dark
matter and whether will ever observe it
and what that means for safety if we if
we can't observe it if there's you know
some if some significant fraction of nor
networks are not accessible to us um
another question that I think a lot
about is uh at the end of the day you
know mechanistic inter is it's very
microscopic um approach to interality
it's trying to understand things in a
very fine grained way but lot of the
questions we care about are very
macroscopic um you know we we care about
these questions about neural network
behavior and
and I think that's the thing that I care
most about but there's there's lots of
other other sort of larger scale
questions you you might care about um
and somehow you know the nice thing
about about having a very microscopic
approach is it's maybe easier to ask you
know is this true but the downside is
it's much further from the things we
care about and so we now have this
ladder to climb and I think there's a
question of can will we be able to find
are there are there sort of larger scale
abstractions that we can use to
understand nural networks that can we
get up from this very microscopic
approach yeah you've you you've written
about this this kind of organs question
yeah exactly if we uh think of
interpretability as a kind of anatomy of
neural networks most of the circus
threads involve studying tiny little
veins looking at the small scale and
individual neurons and how they connect
however there are many natural questions
that the small scale approach doesn't
address in contrast the most prominent
abstractions in biological Anatomy
involve larger scale structures like
individual organs like the heart or
entire organ systems like the
respiratory system and so we wonder is
there a respiratory system or heart or
brain region of an artificial neuron
Network yeah exactly um and I mean like
if you think about science right a lot
of scientific Fields have um you know
investigate things that many level of
abstractions in biology you have like
you know molecular biology studying you
know proteins and molecules and so on
and you have cellular biology and then
you have histology studying tissues and
you have anatomy and then you have
zoology and then you have ecology and so
you have many many levels of abstraction
or you know physics maybe the physics of
individual particles and then you know
statistical physics gives you gives you
thermodynamics and things like this and
so you often have different levels of
abstraction um and I think that right
now we have you know mechanistic
interpret if it succeeds is sort of like
a microbiology of neural networks but we
we want something more like anatomy and
so and you know a question you might ask
is why why can't you just go there
directly and I think the answer is super
um in at least in significant part it's
that it's actually very hard to to see
this this macroscopic structure U
without first sort of breaking down the
microscopic structure in the right way
and then studying how it connects
together um but I'm I'm hopeful that
there is going to be something much
larger than um features and circuits and
that we're going to be able to have a
story that's much than evolves much
bigger things and you then you can sort
of study in detail the parts you care
about as opposed to neurobiology like a
psychologist or psychiatrist when your
own network and I think that the
beautiful thing would be if we could go
and rather than having disperate fields
for those two things if you could have a
build a bridge between them such that
you could go and um uh have all of your
higher level abstractions be grounded
very firmly In This Very solid um you
know more rigorous ideally Foundation
what do you think is the difference
between the human brain the biological
neuron Network and the artificial neuron
Network well the neuroscientists have a
much harder job than us you know
sometimes I just like count my blessings
by how much easier my job is than the
neuroscientist right so I have um we we
can record from all the neurons yeah we
can do that on arbitrary amounts of data
um the neurons don't change while you're
doing that by the way MH um you can go
and ablate neurons you can edit the
connections and so on um and then you
undo those changes that's prettyy great
yeah um you can force any you can
intervene on any neuron and force it
active and see what happens um you know
which neurons are connected to
everything right you neuroscientists
want to get the connecto we have the
connecto um and we have it for like much
bigger than the elegant um and then not
only do we have the connectome um we
know uh what the you know which neurons
excite or inhibit each other right so we
have we it's not just that we know that
like the binary mask we know the the
weights um we can take gradients we know
computationally what each neuron does um
so I don't know the goes on and on we
just have um so many advantages over
neuroscientists and then despite having
all those advantages it's really hard
and so one thing I do sometimes think is
like gosh like if it's this hard for us
it seems impossible under the
constraints of Neuroscience or you know
near impossible um I I I don't know
maybe maybe part of me is like I've got
a few neuroscientists on my team maybe
maybe I'm sort of like ah you know um
the uh maybe the neuroscientists maybe
some of them would like to have an
easier problem that's still very hard um
and they they could come and work on on
neural networks and then after we after
we figure out things in sort of the easy
uh Little Pond of trying to understand
neural networks which is still very hard
then we then we could go back to
biological Neuroscience I love what
you've written about the goal of mechan
turp research as uh two goals safety and
Beauty so can you talk about the beauty
side of things yeah so you know there's
this funny thing where I think some
people want uh some people are kind of
disappointed by neural networks I think
where they're like ah you know neural
network
um it's these just these simple rules
then you just like do a bunch of
engineering to scale it up and it works
really well and like where's the like
complex ideas you know this isn't like a
very nice beautiful scientific
result and I sometimes think when people
say that I picture them being like you
know evolution is so boring it's just a
bunch of simple rules and you run
Evolution for a long time and you get
biology like what a what a a sucky uh
you know way for biology to have turned
out where's the the complex rules but
the beauty is that the Simplicity
generates complexity um you know biology
has these simple rules and it gives rise
to you know all the life and ecosystems
that we see around us all the beauty of
nature that all just comes from
Evolution and from something very simple
Evolution and similarly I think that
nural networks build you know create
enormous um complexity and Beauty inside
and structure inside themselves that
people generally don't look at and don't
try to understand because it's it's hard
to understand but I I think that there
is an Inc incredibly Rich structure to
be discovered inside n networks a lot of
a lot of very deep Beauty um if we're
just willing to take the time to go and
see it and understand it yeah I love I
love Mech inter the feeling like we are
understanding or getting glimpses of
understanding the magic that's going on
inside is really wonderful it feels to
me like one of the questions is just
calling out to be asked and I'm sort of
I mean a lot of people are think about
this but I'm often surprised that morar
is how is it that we don't know how to
create computer systems that can do
these things and yet we have these
amazing systems that we don't know how
to directly create computer programs
that can do these things but these
neural networks can do all these amazing
things and it just feels like that is
obviously the question that sort of is
calling out to be answered if you are if
you have any degree of curiosity it's
it's like how is it that that Humanity
now has these artifacts that can do
these things that we don't know how to
do yeah I love the image of the circus
towards the light of the objective
function yeah it's just it's it's this
organic thing that we've grown and we
have no idea what we've grown well thank
you for working on safety and thank you
for appreciating the beauty of the
things you uh discover and thank you for
talking today Chris this is wonderful
thank you for taking the time to chat as
well thanks for listening to this
conversation with Chris Ola and before
that with DAR amade and Amanda ascal to
support this podcast please check out
our sponsors in the description and now
let me leave you with some words from
Alan Watts
the only way to make sense out of change
is to plunge into it move with it and
join the
dance thank you for listening and hope
to see you next time