[Music]
So it's my absolute pleasure to close
out the course to share a bit about my
work at Microsoft research on how we are
developing new AI methods for the life
sciences and
biology. So, kind of to set the stage
and step back first, uh, in addition to
teaching this course, my, you know,
day-to-day full-time job is that I'm a
researcher at Microsoft Research or MSR.
And really the core mission of MSR is to
advance the frontiers of science and
technology to benefit humanity. And so
we serve as the engine for pushing
really the the complete frontier of tech
and how tech interacts with the world
and how those fundamental research
advances can unlock new opportunities
for Microsoft and the world. And so
really we come to this through a couple
of different lenses that you can think
of in a kind of a hierarchical way. One
on the outermost lens is really doing
foundational fundamental academic-driven
research in a variety of different areas
and doing so responsibly with the ethos
of trust and how we deploy these
technologies and advances uh ethically
and responsibly in the world. And
ultimately our goal is to benefit
humanity in a positive way. Whether
that's by empowering individuals and
companies to to achieve more to embibing
systems and our planet with greater
resilience to leading to fundamental
breakthroughs that can impact human
health and advance our discovery of the
natural sciences. So if the themes that
are presented here and you know the
prospect of work at MSR excites you,
please follow along with these links to
learn more about our mission and our
work.
Okay. So with that we're going to dive
in and really you know I've given a few
lectures now kind of from the lens of
teaching in this course but my personal
passion and my academic work lies at the
intersection of computation and biology
and I came to this field really through
a dual background. I spent much of my
undergraduate and PhD research actually
in the wet lab right doing experiments
working with cells working with animal
models very much bringing that kind of
hands-on mentality that menus mentality
of MIT to the work that I did and toward
the end of my PhD I started to realize
you know that I could combine my passion
for biology and kind of leveraging new
insights into biology with this idea of
thinking about biology as sort of the
ultimate computing system and the
ultimate substrate to engineer through
the lens of computation and quantitative
work to try to create new advances to
benefit human health.
And so with that to set the stage today,
we're going to dive into a very
different world to the world of biology
that operates fundamentally at the
nanocale. So what you're seeing here is
a visualization, a scientifically
accurate visual visualization of a
single membrane boundary in a single
cell at 1 million times magnification.
So take a moment and I think you can
appreciate that just at this very very
very small slice of that nanocale world
we already see this tremendous
complexity. Some elements seem to be
semantic and ordered as visualized here
but still there's a lot of structure and
a lot of richness that probably l lends
itself to a lot of rich data that we can
tap into.
And so in this class, we've we've
thought about algorithms and deep
learning methods through these two dual
lenses of predictive modeling and
generative modeling and how they inform
each other. And now when we consider
this framework applied to the biological
world, the problems are still very
similar, but the types of data that
we're interacting with and the types of
decisions that we may want to make at
the end can be very different. And so
now we're thinking not about natural
language, but rather about the language
of individual
biomolecules. We're not thinking about
images of faces or images of cars or
scenes, but rather we're talking about
representations of individual cells or
how those cells act together in concert
or data from a patient or a medical
record. And ultimately what we want to
assign is okay given a representation of
a biomolelecule say what is the function
that that biomolecule actually exerts in
a real biological context. How would the
cell respond to a drug or a
perturbation? How would a patient, you
know, uh what's the most likely outcome
for that patient on a clinical therapy?
And vice versa, right? Let's say we have
a function that we want to engineer. Can
we realize actual real world biological
substrates to execute that function?
So hopefully you realize that this is
not only a tremendous opportunity for
AI, but as I've sort of illustrated
through these through these icons here,
fundamentally this requires interfacing
and interacting with the natural world
through experiments. Either through
generating observations, the data that
fuels these algorithms or taking the
predictions from the algorithms and
going out in the real world and actually
verifying them, testing them.
And so fundamentally really what I think
about is this link between AI and the
natural world through this lens of
experimentation. And so today we're
going to dive in to one aspect of this
this uh kind of framework which is how
we can build generative models very
similar to the ones that you have
learned about in this class to actually
design new functional
biomolecules. And so what I didn't tell
you in this visualization that I showed
earlier is that at this nanocale world,
these individual objects that you see as
colored and segmented are proteins. And
proteins are this incredible and diverse
class of biomolelecules that you can
think about as biologies actuators.
They're what underly and actuate all
functions in your cells. And because of
this tremendous potential to actually
exert functions dynamically, there's
this tremendous question and
opportunity thought by the principle of
can we actually design new protein
molecules to expand the range of
functions or therapeutic capabilities
that they can actually exert.
And so this is exactly the grand
research challenge that has motivated a
lot of the work of myself and my
wonderful colleagues where our vision is
to build generative AI models that can
achieve this idea of functional protein
design. So imagine the ability to now
specify in a natural language prompt
this target objective. design a new
protein that will target and bind to
breast cancer cells and help deliver
drugs to those
cells. And having a generative AI model
that can condition on that natural
language prompt to design candidate
proteins that would hopefully meet that
design criteria, that function.
Now, as you can start to imagine and
start to realize, this generative
ability would unlock tremendous
opportunities across sectors and
industries. whether we can improve our
ability to design new molecular tools
like enzymes that can go actually make
edits at the genomic level at the level
of your DNA to proteins that can perform
new chemistry that cannot naturally
occur and ultimately new therapeutics
like this example that I'm showing here
which is actually a protein that's
clinically approved uh to treat certain
leukemias and so with this bridge of
complexity and functional design. As you
may realize and think, right, the power
of deep neural networks and deep
learning can really come to bear on
these types of problems so that we can
develop new generative models to design
novel and functional proteins.
And as you've seen in this class, right,
you had the ability to actually go deep
into the details certain classes of
generative models, VAS and GANs, as as
you saw in the fourth lecture of the
course to the brand new and cutting edge
of generative models like diffusion
models. And as you learned and as we
discussed, these diffusion models have
presented tremendous uh advances in the
quality and fidelity of the generations
that they used. And so we're actually
going to focus on this class of
generative models and how we can now
bring this same framework to bear on
some of these protein design challenges
and questions that I outlined. So to
give a bit of a recap and to refresh on
how diffusion models operate, the really
core idea is this idea of learning to
generate data from noise through this
iterative procedure. If you recall,
right, in diffusion models, we have
these two steps. The first is this
forward noising process where we start
with data in our original data space
like images. And we apply a noising
function to corrupt that data
iteratively. And these iterative
corruptions can then serve as sort of
training examples by which we can use to
learn a reverse dnoising process to go
from noise back to our data
space. Another way of visualizing this
is in this diagram that I'm showing
here. And as as we talked about, right,
we can train actual neural network
models as these deninoisers as the
backbones of these diffusion models to
be able to learn this procedure from
noise to
data. And right as we as we went through
we have these two steps of a forward
noising process where we go from an
image we want to arrive at a random
noise pattern and importantly this
doesn't require any training. All we did
was we progressively added more and more
noise to the image in an iterative way.
So over these fixed number of iterative
time steps of noising we had these
increasingly more noisy examples than we
started with. And then we saw the how we
can go from data to noising. We could
actually formulate a really concrete
learning task to train a neural network
to reverse this noising process. Right?
Where our task was given an image at a
time step t, can we learn to estimate
the less noise version at a prior time
step t minus
one? And we saw as in the case of image
data, right? we can formulate an
objective to train the neural network to
predict that residual difference in
noise,
right? And we saw as well that this this
noise prediction was actually a very
effective way to train these models.
And finally we close out by saying okay
for image data this modeling framework
of diffusion modeling had really led to
breakthroughs in the quality the
fidelity and the diversity of
generations that we were able to
produce. Now let's say we want to bring
these same principles of generative
modeling to
biology. Right? As we as we've seen
throughout many examples in this class,
our first task, our first step in any
learning problem is how can we actually
represent or formulate our data in a way
to operate on by a neural network. So
how can we represent biomolelecules like
proteins to a neural
network? Well, the answer to that comes
rooted in actually the biology itself.
To build AI to understand and design
proteins, we first need to understand
how to define and represent a protein.
And it turns out that every protein is
defined by a sequence of amino acids
which you can think of as sort of the
chemical building blocks behind a
protein. And we can actually represent
as sort of a language where we can
represent each of these individual amino
acids by a single character code. Right?
So we have a vocabulary over these
individual amino acids and a sequence of
those amino acids encodes the biological
function of the protein that's often
realized through a structure. Right? So
we have these three sort of
representations or scales in this
hierarchy of protein biology sequence to
structure to function.
And indeed there has been tremendous
work in the community that has aimed to
take deep learning and computational
methods and sort of tackle individual
pieces of this of this pipeline. So
there has been tremendous work in
building language models that can
operate over protein sequences and
represent protein sequences. There have
also been uh very powerful generative
models of protein structures that can
actually computationally design new
geometries that haven't been realized
before in nature. And finally, tools
that go from sequence to structure such
as alpha fold where the task is can you
take this amino acid language encoding
and predict the complex 3D geometry of
the protein that then
results. Looking at this pipeline,
right, ultimately our task, right,
coming back to our motivation at the
very beginning is actually to kind of
turn this paradigm on its head. We want
to be able to go from a function that we
as engineers or as biologists desire to
a sequence of these amino acid building
blocks to actually physically realize a
protein that would hopefully meet and
fulfill that desired function. And this
was exactly the motivation behind a a
recent work that we did where our goal
was to build a generative model that
could learn from protein sequence data
to generate new proteins and that we
could use as a basis to effectively
prompt in different ways with the
desired functions we wanted the protein
to embody and hopefully generate uh
resultant designs
out. And as a step towards doing this,
we developed a new generative model that
we call Evodiff that gives us a
foundation to this approach. And Evod is
a diffusionbased model, a generative
model for functional protein design. And
we've trained it on protein sequence
data that spans evolutionary scale,
meaning we have representations of many
different biological functions from many
different organisms across the tree of
life. And this data set is large and
it's diverse. And after training our EVO
diff model on these protein sequence
data sets, we can then sample from it to
generate new protein sequence instances
that will hopefully meet desired
functions. And so really this was a
tremendous uh team effort from several
individuals across MSR but was
particularly spearheaded by an amazing
applied scientist at MSR Sarah and
together with my colleague Kevin uh we
we kind of formulated and led the the
research vision behind this work. So, so
far right I've told you that protein
sequence data is kind of this
fundamental and universal encoding for
this class of
biomolelecules and I've told you and
reminded you and recaped how we train
diffusion models over data like images
right which is fundamentally
continuous as you may realize and I
shared in this language-based
representation sequences are not
inherently continuous right they're
inherently discrete
So to now move into this new modality
and this new representation of data, we
need a way to formulate a diffusion
process over discrete data like sequence
data or language data. So how could we
possibly do this? To to get the
intuition for this, let's start with an
example in natural language, right? This
class is fun. Hopefully you're agreeing
with me.
as evidenced by the fact that you're
here. I I would hope so. But again, the
principle is the same. We start with
clean data in our input space. Now, we
need a way to noise it to corrupt it.
Any ideas on how we could possibly do
this?
Tokens. Switch tokens. Absolutely.
Just change one character at a time.
Change one character to a time is
exactly related to switching tokens.
Right? If our individual characters are
tokens, switching a character is
switching a token.
Yes. Add tokens. Add tokens. Yeah. All
these ideas are are really great ones.
And as we'll see, a couple of them are
actually how we achieve this. We could
actually, it turns out, do something
even simpler, which is not instead of
switching the tokens in our vocabulary,
what if we just obscured or masked
individual tokens? And we did this by
selecting a position in the sequence at
random. And at our first step, we mask
one of these sequences. And our second
corruption step, we choose another set
of positions and mask those all the way
to the end until we have reached a fully
corrupted uh sequence where all the
instances of our tokens are replaced
with these special mask tokens. And now
our procedure for dnoising to train our
null network is to be able to go from
this fully corrupted fully uh mass text
step by step to undo this corruption all
the way back to our original input data.
And as the idea was proposed another way
we could do this is actually changing
tokens. So this is actually a bit harder
of a task. Rather than delineating the
identity of these mutated or corrupted
tokens through this special indicator,
now we've picked another word or token
in our vocabulary at some probability
and replaced it or changed or mutated
it. And this is the way that we noise
again step by step. And our task is now
to learn how to undo this corruption.
Right? So hopefully this gives the
intuition behind how we can take this
principle of noising or corruption and
dnoising to now the discrete domain and
the analog is exactly the same when now
we think about protein sequence data and
in fact with our method evodiff we apply
this exact discrete diffusion scheme to
formulate our model. One way we could do
this is now we start with a protein
sequence of amino acids and again we
choose any arbitrary position in this
sequence as the position to mask to
corrupt. We do this step by step and in
this way we formulate these iterative
training samples such that we can then
train our neural network model to undo
this corruption in a step-wise manner.
And just as was proposed, you don't have
to use this masking approach. You can
actually mutate the individual amino
acid tokens in your protein sequence
according to some probability as your
form of actually noising the sequence
and the principle is exactly the
same. So now this gives us a modeling
framework for how to bring this power
and paradigm of diffusion modeling to a
discrete domain. And you may be may be
considering okay maybe there are some
similarities behind this discrete
diffusion scheme and other language
model schemes like we saw with LLM's and
in fact mathematically and theoretically
this framework of discrete masking
diffusion gives us a generalization of a
couple of closely related language
modeling schemes. So the first is this
idea of next token prediction right that
we saw yesterday and Wednesday. In that
approach we have a fixed order where
we're going from start to end just
learning over that single order.
Another approach that can be taken is
instead of decoding step-wise left to
right, left to right, left to right, we
start with seeing the whole sequence and
we just mask or corrupt a fixed portion
and predict the identity of those mass
tokens in a single step. Discrete
diffusion is more general is a more
general framework for both of these
schemes because actually what our task
learns is over all possible decoding
orders and over all possible schemes of
and steps of corrupting individual uh
subsets of the sequence. So it's really
a very general framework for bringing
diffusion to uh the discrete
domain. And so with this modeling
framework in hand, what we did was we
took a large uh unanotated data set of
approximately 50 million unique protein
sequences and used it to train this
model EVO diff. And it turns out that we
can go actually a step further and add
another layer of information to this
where instead of just operating on
single protein sequences, what we can do
is use the evolutionary context of
related but distinct protein sequences
to bring even more information and prior
knowledge to the model. So the approach
for doing this is given a sequence of
interest, we can do a simple string sim
similarity search to find sequences that
are closely related but not exactly the
same as that sequence. And just like
before, we can now take a a grid of
these aligned related sequences and
again formulate this discrete scheme to
mask iteratively and un and unlearn this
masking to uh dn noiseise. And so we
trained a model variant on these
alignments of multiple related sequences
as well.
So with these two pieces in hand right
we can operate over not only individual
sequences but actually contexts of
related sequences that give more
information to the model. How do we
actually leverage this framework to now
generate brand new protein
instances? Once the model is trained we
can start from a state just like we saw
of images of pure noise complete
corruption. So here the instance is an
all mass sequence and the EVO diff model
has been trained to undo this corruption
step by step. So you can see that
principle come to life in this
visualization where on the left is the
actual step-wise generation from our EVO
diff sequence model and on the right I'm
showing you the predicted structure of
the protein that would result out
importantly right all this learning is
in occurring entirely over sequence
space so that structure on the right is
just an end visualization for our
purposes there's no information about
the structure that's given to the
model. So our framework brings these two
components in hand. And now the question
you're probably all wondering is okay
well does it work? How good is it? Can
we actually generate new protein
instances and validate that their
function uh works? And this is exactly
what we did. We spent a lot of time
thinking very carefully about how we can
go about evaluating a generative model
like this. Right? It's not so easy to
just look at accuracy. You need to think
about very carefully how you evaluate
the quality of your generations. Not
only on an individual basis, meaning is
this protein sound? Could it exist
biologically, but also on a
distributional basis, meaning if I
generate a thousand or 10,000 samples
from my model, is it spanning and
learning the data distribution? Well,
right. So, this guided the evaluations
we did in looking at the quality of the
individual proteins, the diversity and
space of coverage that they yielded, and
finally, can we actually use this
framework as a way to be able to specify
functions that we could then go out and
realize. So, I'll give you a taste of of
those results. Now, this is going into
kind of this bridge between biology and
computer science analysis. So, I'll keep
it at a level that I think even those
hopefully with with nonbio expertise can
appreciate. So, the first thing we did
was we used our trained model to now
sample new protein sequences and we
wanted to ask the question are these
good? Could these actually be realized?
What we did is given a generation we
predicted its structure and then we
asked okay now if I inferred a sequence
that could adopt that structure how
close is it to the sequence that my
model originally designed. And we can
see the result of the anal of that type
of analysis here where on the bottom
sort of right quadrant are generations
that are more structurally realistic and
more consistent. And in gray I'm showing
the distribution of the space for
natural proteins in the test set. And
now I overlay the generations from
evodiff. And as as you can see we see a
decent coverage of this complete space.
We actually took this a step further and
sampled these individual generations and
then went out and tested them
experimentally in the lab. So this
involved can we actually get these
proteins to be produced biologically?
They're completely synthetic and then
can we go out and measure how
structurally stable they are. And so
here are four examples of successful
designs from uh generated by EVO diff
which were physically expressed and
validated structurally in the real
world.
This evaluation is is really at the
individual basis. But like I said, we
can actually consider many many
different samples on the scale of
thousands to understand how well the
model is actually learning the data
distribution of natural proteins. And
here we take real protein sequences. We
use another model to generate a
representation, a feature extraction for
those natural proteins and visualize
that distribution in 2D on the right. We
can do a similar analysis for
generations from evodiff and overlay
them and ask, okay, how close do these
distributions match? You can appreciate
maybe qualitatively that we do a a good
job of covering some parts of the space,
but there are other parts that are still
not yet covered by EVO diff. But the
power really comes now when we
contextualize how EVO diff compares to
other state-of-the-art approaches for
protein design. When we look at an next
token prediction model, they're
approximately similar with the next
token prediction model doing a little
bit better. If we look at a masked
one-step model, there's a big gap
between the quality of coverage between
EVO diff and this baseline. And really
interestingly, when we look at a purely
structuralbased method, so this is not
looking at sequences, but rather protein
structures, the state-of-the-art method
exhibits a really biased coverage of
this space of natural protein functions.
And so this tells us and gives us a
sense of how well our method is actually
learning this data
distribution. So finally and and kind of
most excitingly is our ability to use
this discrete diffusion framework as a
step towards this vision of functional
and controllable protein design. And
here the beauty really lies in the
strength of the modeling framework
itself. As we showed, we have this
ability to mutate or mask these
individual residues or tokens in this
sequence. And what that means is by
learning over all possible ways to mask
step by step, Evoiff can actually uh
learn to look at a sequence where a
small portion of those tokens are masked
and infill or inpaint just those masked
portions. So you can supply some amount
of sequence information as context and
ask the model to now produce a a
remainder just in the mass portions. I
think this concept comes to life and
comes to intuition most clearly through
this example and it gets at this notion
of biological prompting if you will. So
here what you're looking at is the
structure of a protein that functions in
uh your cells to actually bind to
calcium ions and relay signals based on
the binding of those calcium ions. And
at the bottom you see the complete amino
acid sequence of that protein. In green
I've highlighted that particular sub
region what we call a motif that
actually is responsible for the physical
binding and interaction to the calcium
ion. What we can do with evodiff is we
can take that part that subset as a
prompt and design a brand new protein
sequence around that part supplying the
prompt step by step from the bottom up.
And so this is the generation from EVO
diff visualized below in purely in
sequence space and the structure that we
predict is on the top. And so this gives
you a sense of now how we can use some
information about the biology to
condition and prompt the evodiff model
to now produce a a protein based on that
information. Does this work? Does this
actually lead to real biological
function in the real world? And the
answer is that we yes in the experiments
that we did, we do see that this method
actually yields functional proteins. So
in this very sa very same example that I
showed just now with this calcium
binding pro protein, we again did this
test where we give the sequence
information from that green prompt part
that prompt that conveys function as a
starting point to evodiff and ask it to
condition on that information and
generate a new protein alongside. And
then we went out in the lab and
experimentally tested the calcium
binding properties of this generated
protein. And as you can see, our design
here is in blue. The natural protein is
in gray. And here this is just a
measurement of how well that binding
actually occurs in the
lab. And so right, this is this is quite
exciting, but it's really really just a
first step. These are first experiments
to get at, you know, a sense of the
capabilities with this model and its
abilities to take this functional
information and generate new protein
instances around alongside even using
the context of other related proteins
and evolutionary information.
And so hopefully right this gives you a
sense of how we are bringing these same
concepts of generative models, diffusion
models to a problem like protein design
where we have trained this method
evotiff to learn from the diversity of
natural proteins to now generate and
sample brand new proteins um as a
result.
But this is just one layer of sort of
the biological hierarchy. And what I
love about biology as a space is that
it's incredibly rich, incredibly
complex, and very
multiaceted. Nevertheless, right, our
efforts in, you know, molecular design
and protein engineering are not just
limited to the work on evodiff that I
shared. So together with with colleagues
um in particular Sarah Alamari, Kevin
Yang, Samir Char, Alex Louu and Neil
Tenon Holtz, we're exploring this
question of how we can bring generative
AI methods together with predictive
models to now uh unlock new functional
capabilities in protein design. Whether
that's designing new sequences, new
structures, combining sequence and
structure, building methods to go from a
protein to annotating it with a
textbased function description or vice
versa to understanding and quantifying
uncertainty in lab experiments where you
can actually go and make iterative
measurements of the function of these
proteins and use that to improve your
models. and ultimately putting this all
together to actually uh target real
biological applications like therapeutic
design, molecular sensor design and so
on. And the beauty about our group um in
biomedical machine learning is that we
have a diversity of perspectives with
people's interests spanning all
different scales of this biological
hierarchy. And generating molecules like
proteins is just the start, right?
because they ultimately are the
molecular act actuators that define the
complex behavior of cell cells and and
how they actually exhibit defined
cellular states. And so even here we're
taking this a step further along this
hierarchy particularly building AI
methods that can actually define entire
cellular states and produce
representations of cellular states such
that we can understand how those are
changed in disease and use that
information to now go out and inform
better therapeutic design. And so we've
done several investigations that kind of
span the spectrum of computa purely
computational to hybrid computational
and experimental to purely experimental
right from fundamental questions around
data quality in this context to actually
leveraging um systems biology analyses
to inform therapy
selection. And in fact, we're very
privileged to
have a a long-term research partnership
between our group at Microsoft Research
with the Broad Institute of MIT and
Harvard, which is one of the world's
leaders in um in precision medicine and
genomics and fundamental biological
research. And here really we're thinking
about how we can bring this vision of AI
and experimentation side to side face to
face to realize changes for um patients
in the context of cancer. And you can
start to envision what this paradigm may
look like by thinking about taking and
making measurements of molecular data
from realworld patients, uh, cancer
patients, and using that to train your
AI system to now make predictions that
you go out and test experimentally in
the lab and using the measurements from
those experiments to update your your
model, make improved recommendations,
and try to close this loop. uh that goes
all the way from the clinical context to
the computation to the experiments and
back. And finally, right, those these
types of experiments at the cellular
scale are part of a broader
microenvironmental context, right? How
tissues are organized within the space
of your organs and how those
disregulations in tissues can yield uh
uh diseases. And so here we've had
really breakthrough works in bringing
computer vision methods to the domain of
digital pathology which is at looking at
images of tissues and understanding how
to detect, classify and prognosticate
cancer on the basis of those vision
recommendations.
So hopefully this gives you a sense of
how in bio bioml at MSR we're trying to
build methods that can reason at
individual steps of this biological
hierarchy but ultimately to bring these
modalities together to drive
recommendations that will impact
patients in the clinical setting.
This sits in the scope of a broader
picture of AI research at Microsoft. And
so what I shared is I I I'm just, you
know, one person and with a
collaborating with a fantastic team of
peers and collaborators across MSR to
think about questions in life sciences
and health. But there are a broad swath
of areas that uh we cover. And I think
actually one of the powers and strengths
of Microsoft is this
multidisciplinarity perspective that we
bring to something like AI. Going all
the way from fundamentals to thinking
about how AI can actually have a
cultural and sociological impact on our
world and society.
So once again, right, if you enjoyed
some of the work that I shared and
you're curious to learn more, please
please follow along um with with the
latest and greatest ad advances from uh
from throughout Microsoft. And with
that, I'll close. And it's tremendous
tremendous thanks to uh the fantastic
fantastic colleagues that I'm privileged
to work with every day. I think it's an
awesome team of not only great
scientists but really really great
people that I'm lucky to be a part of.
So thank you so much for your attention
and happy to take
[Applause]
questions. Thank you. Wow the work is so
amazing. So very impressive. Uh the
first question there's a lot of question
but let me just start with one question.
Uh so basically at the like a prom level
uh you will be able in the future saying
that okay you design a protein that help
to uh deal with this particular symptom
at the same time take care of the side
effect that it might uh come come for
it. uh so that will be uh situation now
the question actually question that I
have is that uh in terms of uh the
approach you are taking like the
diffusion model right now I suppose uh
there's other approach of uh trying to
look at uh situation like this come up
optimal uh protein structure and stuff
like that uh can you make some comment
about uh what other approach and how do
you compare with that so thank you
absolutely so so our approach which is a
diffusion method on protein sequence
data. Right now the there is also very
powerful diffusion methods for protein
structure data and the difference
fundamentally besides how the data is
represented and is a lot in the scale of
the data that's available. So for
protein sequence data, we have hundreds
of millions and even now new data sets
of billions of individual protein
sequences. But for structures, we only
have about 300,000 solved experimentally
solved structures of proteins. We can
use tools like Alphafold to predict the
structure, but that's a predicted
surrogate, right? Not a real
measurement. And so there's a there's a
great difference in the magnitude of
data available, but really the two are
complimentary because structure gives
you high resolution, precise geometric
control, but sequence gives you greater
representation over the diversity of
biology that exists.
Thanks for
Sorry. Um, amazing talk and super
inspiring. Thank you so much. My
question follows up with the one that
was just asked actually and it's kind of
two-part. So first, you showed that the
state-of-the-art model that focuses on
structural prediction has really severe
bias especially compared to EVO diff. So
the first question I have is why do you
think that is? And then secondly, do you
think that evo diff could also embed
structural information in the future,
especially if it could inform the
protein stability when it is synthesized
or other characteristics that are
desirable? Two two fantastic questions.
So to tackle the first one, what is the
bias?
the bias is so we know that the as I as
I mentioned right we have the solved
structures for about 300,000 proteins
these are tend to be very globular they
tend to meaning that they're compact and
they can exist stably in a solution of
water and so that lends itself to a
particular set of structural elements
that are over represented in those
proteins that we've measured for. So in
particular, there's a structural element
called a he alpha helix and these uh
proteins that we have structural data
for tend to be biased in these alpha
helical elements. And so we know that
that's a result of the um that's a
source of the bias. And in our paper we
have data that points out specifically
and we show actually that evo diff
generations h better capture other
elements of structure besides helyses
whereas the state-of-the-art structural
methods over sample proteins that are
enriched in these
helyses. So the second question about
can we use sequence and structure
combined? Absolutely. This is actually a
very active area of work in the protein
ML field. And if you're interested, I'll
point you to this um second work. Uh the
first author is is Chenong Wang. It's a
review paper that we recently wrote that
actually summarizes the approaches being
considered for combining sequence and
structure. There are different ways you
can do this. You could try to um put
them into a common representation space
and reason simultaneously. You could
have a base sequence model and kind of
inject or um embeddings from another
structural model on top. So there are
different strategies that you can take
for this.
So with this like functional conditional
protein generation, say if we're given
like a protease, can we predict what
like a cleavage targetment sequence can
look
like? Amazing. Yeah. So amazing
question. It almost seems set up because
my PhD was entirely on proteasis. Um so
so
uh yes actually we have a one work that
we're very actively working on right now
is given a target protease of interest
can we design new substrates for that
protease that would be cleaved by that
protease. Um you could also envision the
capability to go in the inverse
direction where let's say you have a
substrate and you want to design a
protease um this could be could be
feasible. We don't use evodiff in this
work because the task is slightly
different. And now if you have a
substrate and a protease enzyme, these
are two entities, but Evod is really
looking at designing one entity,
right? Hello. Um, I'm sorry if you
already covered this,
but when it comes to
like if you have like a discreetly
generated protein and you want to
evaluate it and you have some way of
determining, oh, these proteins are high
quality and these proteins are not high
quality. Um, how do you teach that to
the model if you
can't like how do you teach that to the
model? Um, if you don't have
like a gradient over like oh if you
change this letter it would get this
much better or something. Yeah, it's a
it's a great question.
So remember right that these generative
models are learning their task is to
learn a probability distribution over
data. And so the hypothesis is that in
the natural distribution of proteins
because these exist in nature. There are
going to be conserved implicit patterns
that dictate stability that dictate
function. And so if your generative
model learns over this whole space,
right, it should hopefully span that
complete distribution of different
functions and stabilities and qualities
that exist in the natural world. So here
we're not taking any explicit
conditioning or supervision on a notion
of quality. We're doing this
unsupervised learning over the dist
distribution.
Oh yeah. Hi. Uh thanks very inspiring
talk. Um I was just wondering so my
question has two parts. So the first
part is about the input to the model
because it seems like you're putting in
an
sequence. So do you encode any
structural information? Because in the
sense that you when you were generating
the motive, it seems to me that you were
just generating say A connected to B and
you just specify the number of amino
acids in that
connection. So this kind of constrains
the space. So my assumption is that you
just input a string into it. And my
question is and the second part of the
question relies on the assumption
because I'm like so if you can you know
the motive you can generate a sequence
but what if we want to generate
something that has a function we know
the structure like RF diffusion so how
will you incorporate that into evodive
in the future?
Yeah. So there are multiple parts to the
question. The first is it is correct
that we are not giving any structure
information. This is purely the sequence
representation. And in the motif
example, you may have noticed the space
in between the two segments of the
motif. We did experiments where we keep
that number of amino acids uh fixed
according to what occurs biologically
but vary the length of the generation on
the on either side. You can also imagine
changing and toggling that space in
between to see how that improves
quality. With respect to the relation to
um structure design and a method like RF
diffusion, you you are correct that this
motif task is typically conducted by
structural methods, right? because you
have that information about the
structure of and you want to design
around it. We wanted to approach this
from the sequence first perspective
because there could be cases where you
have information about the sequence of a
motif but may not have a solved
structure. So can we do this without any
structural information? And it turns out
the answer is yes.
If you're curious, there is also a a
benchmark comparison of EVO diff against
RF diffusion on these types of uh motif
design motif scaffolding tasks in the in
the manuscript.
Okay, maybe just a couple more
questions.
Thank you for the presentation. Um I
asked Doug this question. I just want to
maybe for somebody who worked in
university and and now in Microsoft uh
research where do you think the
breakthroughs are happening over the
next maybe 20 years in AI? I know that
this is a big question maybe you don't
have the answer for that just wanted to
take your opinion. Is this do you think
that industry is going to be far
exceeding by strides and strides what
happens in you know government funded
programs and universities and this or is
something else going to happen? Thank
you.
Yeah.
So I think that
the synergy of people who bring
different perspectives is really
critical here. So we are very privileged
because in the the team we've sort of
assembled we have complimentary
expertise from very fundamental ML
engineers and ML scientists all the way
up to biologists and people like me who
came from really experimental background
and it's that synergy in one place in a
team of peers catalyzed by the scale of
resources the scale of partnerships the
scale of impact that someone like
Microsoft can have that I think unlocks
opportunities that are accessible to us
that
really you know no or very few other um
players can play. So I I'm really really
excited about what the opportunity and
horizon of breakthrough capabilities can
come from from people like ourselves.
That said, I think that recipe um you
know, you don't necessarily need to be
in a industry research lab to power
that. And so there are new um frameworks
for privately funded research or very
wellunded academic institutes that are
bringing this same hybrid approach. Uh
for example, the Institute for Protein
Design at University of Washington. But
really it's this synergy of people
mixing scientific atmosphere and the
scale and vision of problems to
tackle. So my first question is that
where do you see the future of AI in
health? Do you believe that AI may be
able to create drugs that can be used in
real clinical settings or do you think
that it's still in the early stages
where it can only work in the
lab? Yeah, I mean my ultimate vision is
to realize change that can can impact
people's lives. So right that that's
what motivates me. The work things
working in the lab is the first step
right. I don't think we are going to
bypass the lab entirely. Um what I think
is going to happen is hopefully we have
engines that can accelerate our ability
to reach discoveries faster and that can
occur in many ways. That could mean
having to do fewer experiments. That
could mean doing smarter experiments.
That could mean dreaming up new
experiments that are not possible today.
But the AI helps us design. uh and
ultimately I think it's going to be um
you know a a snowball effect of those
fundamental discoveries from the lab
that lead to actual changes that people
will realize and patients will realize.
So yes to both. I I think we'll get
there.
Yeah. Thanks for your presentation. Um
to me it looks like Evo has huge
potential for dual use as well.
Um, so I'm wondering how you manage that
and if there's any way of creating
values for evodive.
It's a fantastic question and
this prospect of dual use of a
generative method like this is very very
top of mind for us and also for the
leadership um at Microsoft and in in
terms of the scientific community
broadly. We see, you know, my optimistic
hope and vision is that the potential
upsides, right, are tremendous and that
can lend greater positive benefit to
humanity. But we absolutely have to be
very considerate about formulating the
regulations around these technologies.
And as a step and example towards that,
um, our chief scientific officer, uh, at
Microsoft, Eric Horvitz, has been very
passionate about advocating for
biocurity and regulation principles
around model AI models in biology at the
level of the government and at the level
of the the president. And so there he
has a couple white papers out recently
that kind of explore and set the stage
in terms of principles of how to be
thinking about these technologies. But
you're absolutely right.
Um you know we're at the cusp of of
these technologies and now as a
community and as leaders we have to
think about how to formulate.
Excellent. Thank you Ava. Let's all
thank Ava one more time.