the introduction um I'll let me start
just by um before I get into the
technical content uh let me say uh ah
good um let me I'll introduce myself um
because um so uh so my uh so my journey
is like hon said I did a postto at
Berkeley from 2007 to 2009 uh with with
Mike Jordan which was fantastic my um
back during my PhD what I worked on was
machine learning um uh deep learning
didn't exist then and uh for for natural
language uh processing so back when none
of this stuff really worked um and then
um around the time uh I kind of uh I
left Berkeley I started as a professor
at Edinburgh I started working on kind
of machine learning for program
synthesis kind of codenation and
software engineering problems uh these
were very exciting to us at the time but
you know this is when we were just
starting to get deep learning so kind of
none of this worked
um and then I moved to Google in 2018
and it's only kind of very recently and
kind of when I've been at Google I've
been working on machine learning for
code generation and then kind of very
recently like in the past year I've
started to get interested in AI for
security so why am I telling you this um
there's kind of three reasons um one is
I always like to begin a lecture by
professing my ignorance so uh so my
background is very much more on the Deep
learning side than on the computer
security side um so so you're very
welcome to ask me any questions you want
about computer security because
fortunately Don song is sitting in the
front row and uh we can get EX and you
know many of her my group as well so we
can get kind of expert answers to a lot
of these questions even if I don't know
them um and um the other thing is just
like I I like to give career advice I
have a Blog where I give people uh kind
of defunct career advice and research
and um because you know it's fun um and
um the one thing when I look back is
that you know I mean your career is very
long right if you see like in the past
couple of years like things are febrile
you know everything's changing every
three months um you know it's not the
technologies that are on top now you
know they're not going to be on top in
five years they might not be on top in
five weeks uh the way things are so like
having kind of just like change is
normal um Technologies change and you
want to learn how to change with them
and um the other thing that I think I uh
is
a a theme of this talk and something
that uh I liked the is kind of like
thinking across different uh different
disciplines right so if you are working
in machine learning um if you're working
sometimes of Applied research or product
driven research or in or if you're in
tech building products um a lot of
there's going to be the kind of machine
learning Tech and there's also going to
be the problem that you're trying to
solve and if you if you know only the
machine learning part of it and you
don't think about oh kind of deeply
about what problem you're trying to see
you're kind of missing a trick like the
more you understand the kind of AI for
computer security the more you
understand about computer security or if
you're building a product the more you
understand about where your customers
want it'll help you to do better
technical work um okay so that's the end
of my sermon and um now I will start
actually talking about um kind of coding
agents um so there's going to be three
parts I'll say a little bit kind of in
general about kind of uh agents for code
like swe s Ben s agent type things
that'll be the first part of the talk um
then I'll start talking about Ai and
agents for computer security and then at
the end I'll talk a little bit about a
project uh that Dawn mentioned that I uh
I'm part of with a with a number of
other people to do LL agents for finding
security bugs and um so but I'm going to
start off with um uh so I'm going to
start off with being um maybe a little
bit philosophical about what llm agents
are since you're already partway through
the t uh class and you've already seen a
number of examples of Agents I wanted to
give like llm agent is a bit of a
buzzword so um so I wanted to give kind
of my perspective on kind of what that
buzzword means um other people would say
potentially different things and that's
okay um but this is kind of what I would
emphasize in terms of what seems kind of
fundamental um so I would say um the um
so kind of this slide's a little bit
abstract I'll talk talk start I'll start
talking about actual stuff in a few
minutes in one more slide um but but for
me uh if you ask me to Define what an LM
agent is without the kind of buzzword or
whatever um I would say look
it's a multi- turn llm with tool right
theal thing is kind of this react Loop
uh that we're going to talk about and
why what makes this fundamental like why
is this good um one is that you get
Dynamic computation time so the point of
like if you just give if you just prompt
an llm question answer it has to start
generating the answer right away and
it's maybe some of the earlier tokens
kind of commit the llm to an answer that
it then has to like that it doesn't want
to contradict whereas if you give it
kind of dynamic computation if you give
it if if the L LM can generate a thought
uh whether it's kind of a reasoning
model or whether it's just prompted that
gives uh more computation time uh for
harder uh problems the other thing which
we're going to talk a lot about is kind
of information from external tools um so
and that's kind of another part of the
point of Agents is that you can actually
oh I'm going to oh is that for example
in coding agents you actually run the
code see what happens and then um and
then write different code based on the
output and it turns out that's
incredibly powerful uh for kind of more
complex uh code generation tasks and
we'll see examples of lots of other
things you'd want to use external tools
for in a in kind of code generation
software engineering uh type scenarios
um the other thing that's maybe more
from the um uh um more from the kind of
cognitive perspective of what's
interesting about tool use is that tools
give the agent the ability to test
hypothesis right so the agent can like
in the thinking part of a loop uh say oh
I think that when I run this code uh on
this input it will break at line 13 and
they can actually do it see if it was
right and then kind of revise in later
turns like say something different if it
turns out that this hypothesis was wrong
and then the and I think that's
something we're kind of uh for some of
these simpler tasks you might not need
that level of um experimentation in the
agent but I think for more complex tasks
you will and then the final thing this
gives you which I think is really good
is like if you want the element to
actually do anything right then it needs
to uh interact with the external world
that's in one sense that's what a tool
is giving you so the um I guess um so
the main thing um maybe I disagree with
what I wrote on the slides next um like
uh so you could think of when people
talk about planning or Chain of Thought
you can view these as like special cases
of dynamic dynamic computation type
right these are ways to use the extra
computation that you get from having
thinking tokens uh this deemphasizes
multi-agent a little bit that's you know
maybe that'll turn out to be really
important to have different interacting
agents with different prompts but I
think the uh um you know uh my sense is
that that that's still emerging the jury
is still out on
that okay so that is um okay so that's
the um that's going to be the end of the
philosophy for now I'll intersperse
philosophy maybe uh in into the uh the
rest of the of the lecture um I'm going
to start by not talking about agents
though I guess I've already started by
not talking about agents I'm going to
continue starting the agents lecture by
not talking about agents and the next
thing that's not agents that I'm going
to talk about is
evaluation so um so the the reason that
I'm the reason that I'm doing that will
become kind of I'll talk about that in a
minute um so before um uh when we first
started to see big but I want to talk a
little bit first about say the
prehistory of evaluating uh code uh
generation in llms so um the when we
start um there um there was a big uh
kind of moment in I guess four years ago
now it doesn't feel that long but it was
uh when we kind of saw a step change in
the ability of llms to do code
completion and codenation tasks this was
about the time the open AI codex model
uh came out kind of the gpt3 kind of
iterations and at that time there were a
couple kind of evaluations of kind of
code uh generation capabilities that
people were doing at the time and BPP
that we were we did at Google and kind
of human eval uh from open Ai and these
are kind of broadly similar uh things
and what these are is basically natural
language to code so uh these would each
of these data sets would have you know
order several hundred examples where you
would generate a small Python program
maybe five or 10 lines of code and you
wanted to do that given like a one or
two sentence prompt that says uh what
the code is supposed to do and a series
of
assertions and um at the time this was
uh you know at the time that this came
out like um well say later um uh and
these were both uh kind of generated by
people so we uh there were kind of human
annotators kind of wrote the programs
and the uh the problem descriptions so
um I I don't recommend using these
evaluations anymore uh they're kind of
more like amist um but I think they're
they let me talk about a couple of
points that's why why I'm starting with
this um one and at the time that these
came out it was kind of amazing that a
language model could generate you know
an entire function of 10 lines of code
right uh that's not amazing anymore um
the um so one thing that's interesting
about this I'll come back to later is I
want to talk about uh kind of um both
how you would use these to do
evaluations and why you don't use them
anymore
so um we talk about how you use them to
do evaluations the um so what we would
do for for these data sets is we measure
pass at K so how often given the kind of
natural language prompt do we get a
correct answer in K samples so if you go
um um if I uh so if you take if you like
my uh fancy AI generated uh graphic
there if you take a prompt and get say
Cas samples from the model and just say
kind of run them all on those uh a set
of assertion that maybe the model the
model ones that model did see maybe a
few hidden ones the model didn't see and
then say okay how often does the program
pass those assertions and then if any of
them pass you get a score of one for
pass at k for this example um so the
reason I'm telling you is this is
there's some principles of this that
even though we don't use MPP human eval
anymore we probably shouldn't um uh
there's some principles of this that you
do want to use when you divine evals one
is that this requires an automated
correctness check to work having that it
if you if if it's all possible for you
to have that when you're defining an
eval you want to have that um the other
thing that's kind of nice about this you
don't see this as much in agents because
it's so much more expensive to run is
that you get to measure kind of explore
exploit Behavior if you can afford to do
a pass a k evalve right so if you had a
model that like always produced the
correct answer uh it was either always
right or always wrong and there was no
diversity in its output it's kind of
pass it one would be the same as pass at
K whereas like you know if pass at K
kind of goes up sharply that's telling
you well maybe the model's first
solution is always correct but it's
giving you more diversity that's kind of
interesting um the other thing to point
out here is kind of an interesting
question like does pass at K match what
you want when you deploy the model and
the answer is sometimes yes and
sometimes no um if you are doing code
completion you probably don't care as
much about pass it K because I'm not
going to show every time I hit the
completion button you get to see 10
examples and pick the one that's right
that's probably not so good um whereas
if you're doing something more agentic
it might be use it might be fine it
might be perfectly fair to say I mean it
is perfectly fair to say oh in
production I'm going to generate case
samples keep the ones that pass the test
cases and only show say a highly ranked
one of them uh to the user so sometimes
this is a um this is kind of reasonable
sometimes it's a good metric sometimes
it's not so it's always interesting to
think about for this particular way in
which I'm uh evaluating a coding tool
does it match uh what the way I'm
actually going to use it in
production okay this is um maybe not I
just putting this because I think it's
cool it's a little statistical aside uh
which you may may or may not know and
since like machine learning used to be
based on statistics uh you see less of
that work anymore I find it kind of
interesting um so um if you are um so
how do you want to compute like say I
care about P 10 right how am I going to
compute that um well the naive thing you
could do is I could say well take 100
samples from the model and say okay how
what percentage of them actually passed
so maybe it's 20% and then what I want
to know is if I take 10 samples from
this uh how much does it uh um um How
likely I'm going to get it and so you
could take 20% and plug it into that um
it turns out that's bad uh that's a
really noisy statistical estimate so the
um so it turns out it's much better to
say take those 10 samples and then say
if I take those 100 samples and say if I
take a Sub sub sample 10 without
replacement right um how um um how often
do I get at least one success and that's
uh that's the estimator that's proposed
in the Codex paper where they talk about
human evil I don't know I just think
that's cool okay so now let me so I've
gone through this at length and the
reason that I've gone through this is to
get to this slide um which is like what
is the design of a good evaluation for
coding agents or for agents in general
and um in 2020 I think these were
probably reasonable evals at the time um
and there were kind of three uh and the
reason is that they could drive model
development uh the reason is um the the
reason they could is that they were kind
of just hard enough um if uh so they're
not floor and they're not at ceiling so
that when you improve the base model you
would actually see a difference uh in
these numbers and then at the time they
kind of weren't leaked right so they
weren't already on the internet um now
uh probably not right uh kind of too
easy it's kind of too easy to over you
could over fit to the assertions uh and
they're certainly leaked uh so these are
probably more like the mnist of code
evals now uh but the reason I go through
this is when we look at other evals we
can ask kind of the same uh same
question so the um uh probably most
influential so far kind of so let's now
move to evaluations kind of used for
agents so the most influential um
evaluation has been swe bench so let me
kind of talk uh which I didn't maybe I
have the citation on a different slide
but it's easy easy to find um is um so
what sweet bench is a way of kind of
generate it's a data set of real world
coding problems that have been um
collected from python repositories on
GitHub so one example of a um uh an
example from the data set is here so the
idea is that um they would um I talk
about filterings on the next step so um
so the idea is you would have a problem
statement which is actually from kind of
the a statement from the GitHub issue
tracker um this is um one thing I point
out here is just kind of the that they
the issue issues will often contain kind
of poins to a part of the code or um
that uh that you want to modify and um
all of these um examples have uh have
test cases that were part of the patch
and there test cases for which before
the patch the test case fails and after
the Patch the test case succeeds so you
have um for each of these you have kind
of a a test case uh you have an issue
description you have a change to the
tests and um and you have a patch and so
the uh the goal of the uh of s bench is
generate the patch from the generate the
generate the patch from the
description and um these are um okay so
I've talked about so there's some steps
of filtering you do like this fail to
pass filtering and um also the fact that
you can actually install and run the
projects um
and I wanted to show um in terms of U
looking at the Domain so so this has
been um kind of very influential because
at the time that it was introduced it
was kind of at the Goldilocks level that
um the kind of Baseline LMS were getting
like two or three% um and then as soon
as we switched to agents we got kind of
non- trivial boost so this was kind of
introduced it's kind of an it was a
interesting uh subset of real world
tasks that was introduced just at the
right time where this could drive model
development and so it's kind of been
very influential and a lot of people
have used it um the what I would point
out from the things in the bottom is on
the left is a kind of a pie chart of
which 12 uh projects these came from and
you can see there's kind of like it's
kind of a small set of domains right
these are python packages that are kind
of you know mathematical data analysis
you know web right so there's kind of a
um it's not covering the full range of
software engineering tasks but it is
covering tasks that are
interesting and look at you know the set
of files edit it the set of functions
edit it it's kind of a big step above
previous evals but there's a lot again
that it's not
covering um the um so there there's also
and then there's also uh a kind of a
small so one thing that's both uh kind
of nice and um not nice about this is
that you have the issue descriptions
that are um uh that are coming the issue
descriptions are the ones coming coming
from GitHub um so that means that you
know sometimes these are Under
specified or uh they test cases that are
just somebody was uh they're Tangled
somebody was fixing something in the
code they wrote some more tests but it
doesn't actually test the problem so
there's a subset where these have been
um uh where these have been removed so
now let me pop up and say okay now let's
ask the same question that we asked of
the previous slide which is are these EV
vals good and um the answer is well yes
yes and no right so as we said this is a
significant Step Up in realism and it's
came at the right time to drive the
field so that's great um what's wrong
with it uh well there are lots of things
that are wrong with it that's okay there
are lots of things that are wrong with
everything um so what's wrong what's
wrong here is that you know you can
overfit to the test right um the tests
aren't an exact uh verifier so you can
produce a patch that makes the test pass
uh but isn't actually correct um maybe
even something uh worries me a little
bit more is the natural language is out
of domain
in the sense that if you are interacting
with an agent in your IDE and you want
to tell it to make a change you're
probably not going to use the same types
of natural language as you would in a
GitHub issue description right like
maybe you've um um diagnosed the problem
a little bit more if you're going to
share it with other people than if
you're just asking an AI in your IDE
please fix this um and there might and
some issues might contain things about
the solution right about what part of
the code uh the issue should be fixed
sometimes you know that sometimes you
not and so um we've talked about
coverage a bit already um and we've Talk
data leakage is um you know when this
data set came out a lot of people were
kind of worried about oh these are all
from GitHub uh this is in the training
set of all the large models uh should we
be worried about that and I think the
answer is when systems are getting 2% on
sweet bench no we should not be worried
about that uh when systems are getting
you know 50% we probably should um and
then the other thing whenever you do
these kinds of historical data sets
uh I think something that people um uh
often don't realize is these commits are
Tangled uh it's kind of often the case
and there on open source repositories
that um a commit will not just fix the
one issue that it claims to fix but
it'll do some other things like maybe it
fixes another issue maybe it does some
other cleanup right so that kind of
affects the quality of of it certainly
affects the test cases but it also
affects like if you were going to do
supervised fine tuning on patches uh
that might not be uh might not be such
there's problems with
that okay so um the reason I'm going
through this at such length is that I
think in large part the quality of
either the base llm or the agent that
you develop is going to be driven by the
quality of the evaluation and um the
reason for this is um I don't know
sometimes I like making analogies to
statistical machine learning methods um
any kind of organization that builds
either llms or LM applications it's just
doing uh giant combinatorial
optimization right so you have you have
a design space you have a bunch of knobs
like uh we'll talk about the knobs for
agents in a minute um is um and you are
um um and you say okay what if I said
what if I set this knob this way what if
I add this tool what if I change the
system instruction this way what if I
clean up um you know this part of the
post training mixture and then you try
it and you see how the numbers change so
if your um if your numbers aren't good
you're hill climbing on the wrong thing
and I think that has a direct impact on
how whether the the quality of your
evaluations has a direct impact on the
final system whether it does what you
want um and so the things you want to
think about are like you know some
obvious like uh I think the main one the
level of difficulty you have to be in
The Sweet Spot also you want things that
are realistic that test what you care
about and that aren't leaked to be
leaked um and the other thing like all
evaluations have a shelf life right like
once they start out you're kind of they
start out like with say mbpp human eval
they start out being kind of hard and
unleaked and then like a couple years
later they're easy and leaked so it's
just like you have to keep making new
ones
continuously okay so um I uh hopefully
I've spent enough time um so I'm kind of
going into kind of you know technically
simple stuff at length um but I think it
is important to actually building these
things um so now I can actually kind of
talk about a code agent um which is um
um kind of a good good thing to do in
electure EN coding
agents and um you know one that I
thought was kind of kind of a particular
Milestone was um s agent so this was
kind of one of the early ones that was
kind of specifically designed for sweet
bench style tasks um in some sense um in
some sense this talk is going to be very
repetitive um because I think that we're
all working with the same set of three
or four it is right in the kind of the
base models or in the kind of you know
application layer on top of it which an
agent is an example of this like crank
and there's a certain thing like if you
want to do an agent for I don't know um
you know fixing AV issues vers as an
agent for kind of making patches to
repositories it's going to be a lot of
the same types of engineering that you
do first thing you're going to do is
Define find an eval the second thing
you're going to do is kind of create
something that looks like sweet agent um
so what um Su agent is it combines like
a bunch of different things that uh kind
of you know people had all done kind of
before but it's kind of a powerful
combination um so uh one is that it's
going to give you um that we're we're
going to instruct the model in such a
way that it does kind of Chain of
Thought in the sense that it explains uh
what it's going to do uh before it does
it uh there's going to be a set of tools
that are specific software develop and
the agent is going to get execution
feedback uh so that way like I've said
before if uh if you have if you um you
can get information about uh what
happens so the the main Loop um which is
um is going to be kind of what I call
the react Loop and I put those emoji on
there for a reason uh react loop from
from the rack paper a couple years ago
oh because I I think this kind of loop
is a kind of at the heart of what it was
saying about agents of kind of this idea
of kind of uh uh Chain of Thought Plus
tool use so um all you're doing is
basically it's basically like a very
simple um Loop where you say you at
every point you have a what we call a
trajectory right some text that the LM
has generated so far at every step we
ask the LM to generate more text um and
then that text will end in a tool call
um in whatever format that you like and
then you get the tool call you actually
run it um every tool is basically to a
first approximation a python function
that outputs more text like I'm not
going to talk about multimodal agents
because we don't really need them for
there's been less work on multimol
agents for code so far um um and then
whatever the output is you just have
pend it to trajectory and then you
repeat right and that's that's that's it
um so the um and this this kind of loop
we'll talk about alternatives to this
kind of control flow as well but that
Loop alone is kind of very powerful to
the heart of a lot of what these things
are doing and um in principle the llm
can generate whatever text that it wants
right we would hope that it it's
something that actually helps it decide
what tool call to use and so we instruct
it you know it's a system instruction in
the beginning uh I guess I I should have
initialized this with what we call like
a system instruction and that's going to
tell you that says it please explain
what you're doing and so then it
will so the one of the main design
decisions here is like well what tools
do you want to use um one option uh that
you could imagine is okay we'll just
give the agent access to a Linux shell
and an
IDE then a person can do
on that on that machine it can write
whatever code it wants um this seems I'm
not saying this will be true forever uh
right now this still feels a little bit
futuristic right um you know two weeks
from now who knows right but um there
and this is kind of another theme uh
when we talk about the design of Agents
maybe this is one of the things I forgot
to write on the slides um is that the
design of the agent harness and the
tools you have to co-design it with
whatever the model can do
right so when you're doing if you're
doing prompt optimization to try to
decide okay how do I summarize the
output of this tool well probably the
way you're doing it is you're adapting
either knowingly or if you're part of
the uh or unknowingly you're adapting to
whatever the model is seen in
posttraining data right because the more
the closer um like you want whatever
format to use to be things the model's
familiar with so where we are now is
like okay maybe right now option one is
a bit ambitious um the so let's do
something different let's make things
easier for the model so what we'll do is
we'll say We'll design tools in such a
way that there's going to be a small
number of them that are kind of spec
that are kind of good for this task and
they'll have out inputs and outputs that
are friendly to the agent and um there's
kind of a really uh catchy term they use
in the S agent paper it's like an agent
computer interface instead of a user
interface uh so instead of HCI there
could be a science of ACI um that might
be going a bit far but there are design
principles here so um so what are they
doing Inu agent uh oh okay yeah before I
get to that um what so like I said a
tool is just a python function or or a
code uh that the agent can call and to
get a string from the context um what do
you want um what do you want these
things to do is um when you're thinking
about them well they should be easy to
describe to the agent right so um the um
you don't want to like make up technical
terms right that uh like if you're
writing when you're designing a piece of
software you you can invent
vocabulary right um different objects in
the thing here like you want like the
closer um you um I've heard this I think
the some of the the guys uh I think I
heard this from um some of the people
who um um developed co-pilot is uh so
there's a lot in the initial probably
still but certainly the initial version
of co-pilot there's some really clever
prompt engineering uh to make things
work with the LM of that time I'm sure
there still is and um one thing they
talked about they call it like the
Little Red Riding Hood principle right
that when you're doing prompt
engineering you want the you want to
kind of lead the model down familiar
path from post training data and um I
think that's uh I think that's true here
as well that you want kind of uh to be
able to describe what the tool does in a
way that the agent will have understood
that like there are plenty of web pages
that talk about um Co talk about goat
jump to this line of code right so
that's something that's natural the
other thing is you want the the agent
you want the actions to be compact right
like you don't want something where the
agent has to call four or five tools to
do one logical thing um the other thing
is you you design the output of the
tools right so you might say you know it
might make a difference oh how do you
handle trailing new lines in the output
of some tool or if the output if if
you're doing a code browser tool and
there are many many um results like how
do you summarize that like there's
different those different options and um
and the other thing you want to think
about is a guard rails is like State uh
so like if you're talking about code
editing right then um you know you could
imagine something where it say the agent
adds it the first thing the agent does
is add a stupid syntax error to some
file and it doesn't realize it and so
then the rest of the trajectory the
agent is just messed up because no
matter what it does it it hasn't fixed a
syntax error right so you want to kind
of try to to have some error checking to
avoid uh especially for like stateful
tools like code editing uh getting the
agent into a state bad State that's easy
to get out
of okay so um so what what tools do they
have in umu agent one is well they I
think they did they did have a Linux
shell but that's uh um uh maybe
sometimes useful but not so useful uh
but um but often like uh these tools are
helpful um I would say there's like
three types of tools you could think
about um in kind of AG in this style
agent um one would be kind of
information gathering so um that doesn't
doesn't help the agent solve the it
gathers information right so um in the
case of um um in the case of code these
would be um uh kind of doing code search
and uh kind of viewing code files um so
you can um so this would be and so you
see some of the design like uh like this
would be things like oh find this term
in this file find this term in any file
in this directory um you notice that
it's kind of a nice shortcut right you
could imagine having just doing LS in
the Linux shell and then doing uh then
the agent could do search file in any of
these uh that seems cumbersome right um
and then you know how do you deal with
files that are too long for context here
what you could do is call the open F
open to see part of a file and then have
a specific kind of scroll
commands um the um so the second kind of
thing you do is acting right which is
just in this case you know make edits or
create new files and then you can get
feedback by saying okay I'm done please
submit this
patch so and I think in general if you
want more complex tools I think most
tools will kind of fit in uh to some
kind of to to fit into this um you know
there are guard rails here that like you
know if you make a dumb edit that kind
of tax error lender error it just gets
rolled back for you uh so then you can
do there things like
this so I mean give you a sense of kind
of what the I couldn't f a full I will
show some trajectories throughout this I
couldn't fit a full s agent trajectory
um on here um the um but here's kind of
an example of the kind of explanations
you might get right that you say okay oh
now I know what to do we need to add a
check to ensure that all of these things
are the same let's edit the code and so
it says oh replace these lines of code
with this um the um or if you want to do
like a kind of file search you might
perhaps you want to uh uh you know you
might like elad the lines you might
provide line numbers like these are kind
of like you need the line numers so you
can use them in a in a subsequent
command um so you can design the tools
to kind of fit together in this way um
typically what you will see uh for for
this agent you would typically see um um
the um the tools are called in the order
that you would expect like if there's
some identifiers used in the issue
description then um the agent can call
the code browser tools to to find uh
kind of code that's relevant to it at
some point one of these thoughts will
say oh let me make this change and you
see edits and then you might see like
kind of multiple edits and then a
submit um but the agent isn't restricted
to do that right this is just the it has
far has the model is concerned there is
just a string and the model is
continually appending to the
string um so okay so let me say I'll say
a little bit about the results and the
sweet bench data so the first thing is I
did kind of set it up and say well sweet
bench was really hard uh when it came
out and so if you look at you know
whatever the uh state-of-the-art llms at
that time and say what percentage of the
I think couple thousand issues in sbench
were resolved by the model it's like one
or three% and um I can do tell a kind of
fun I don't know if it's fun for me I
don't know if it's fun for you a story
there which is that when s bench first
came out um you know I I thought it was
kind of thought it was a pointless
evaluation um because it was just too
hard right like how do you he'll climb
on a Model when you're getting one or
three% um so it turns out I was wrong
and um the reason that I was wrong about
that is because it turn because agents
are actually really good um so like when
you put an agent loop on top of the bace
models you go from like 1% to 12% right
and I think now um uh now the state
of-the-art in full sweep inch is is
quite a bit higher than that um so it
was um so this so it's like the fact
agents came out sbench came out as part
of the reason they they the kind of part
of the Cod development uh that happened
um the um the one thing to point out is
um you might uh one thing I can kind of
experimentally criticize here although I
think the this a good paper the results
are good um is the um you know an agent
is going to have to generate more tokens
right to get this kind of same level of
performance uh so you see that uh as
represented uh the dollar average cost
uh per successful trajectory in the
second column the um so the fact you
know you would like to know uh you would
like to see computation normalized
results um like it would be interesting
like if I ran 10 times as much do I
expect to If I Ran 10 times as many um
if I generate the same number of tokens
on average from both you know here I
think like you know a agents work it's
fine but I think when you're comparing
other changes to the agent um you might
say well there might be some changes to
the agent that look really good but it
turns out what you're doing is getting
higher um is getting um like maybe you
add I don't know some kind of grep tool
that puts lots of tokens in the
environment and if it helps that's great
but it might be that oh it's helping
because it's adding more tokens to the
average trajectory and if you didn't
have the tool and just generated more
trajectories you could get the same the
same point on the kind of cost uh
performance curve so it's something you
know you want to think about that when
you're running these comp comparisons um
there was something that I wanted to say
about the shell only agent which I don't
remember oh well okay uh maybe we'll
come back later um okay so that's um so
that's uh so that's kind of maybe the
kind of the first kind of uh very
Dynamic react style agent so now I want
to talk about a different kind of agent
design and um that's kind of The Other
Extreme uh which is called Agent less um
you know it's kind of like yeah you um
so so this was kind of like in terms of
like where does this is the Other
Extreme in terms of how much control
flow do you handr write so the I so what
we've talked about is kind of dynamic
where the control flow is I'm appending
to a string everything else the llm
decides um the llm could in principle
Implement whatever algorithm it wants on
top of on top of these tools um The
Other Extreme is just procedural so um
basically I will write some say python
code that does something natural for uh
solving program repair tasks and um
every time where it's kind of like where
I might say oh okay so first I'm going
to iterate through every file in the
project and then I'm going
to uh whether that file is relevant to
the um uh to the issue description or
whatever and so whenever you get to
point in the algorithm where you need to
say quote unquote magic happens you call
the LOL and so so this basically like
you have code you have the Logics and
code but then you're asking the Alm to
make the U to to make certain decisions
in the middle of the control flow so
that's basically what a agent list is
doing so um so there's kind of three I
say hardcoded I don't mean that in a
pejorative way uh kind of three steps
one is like you know figure out what you
want to edit uh then generate a patch
and then validate St the patch and um I
will give you a colorful diagram that
says the same thing
um um so um so what you're going to do
is you'll have uh uh is that you'll have
this workflow where at various points
you call an llm uh so you'll start by
saying okay you have some codebase you
textify the structure of the repository
you prompt the model to say oh which
file should I look at um so then you get
the model will give you a list of kind
of topend files and then each of those
you could say okay here is a um here is
a skeleton of the kind of methods and
classes within each of those files then
you call the LM again to say oh where
does it look like I should edit and then
you can do that one more time to get a
set of lines uh that you might want to
edit so at each one you're kind so at
every point you have kind of a an nbest
list of potential things that you might
want to edit and then you go through and
say okay now for each one of these let
me independently give this to an LM and
say hey um here's a description of the
issue generate a patch and then what you
can do is and then once you you have
that you apply the pat a let me see
which one's pissed now one thing that's
kind of important about s agent is you
don't know what the test cases are right
so um the agent itself um has to come up
with its own test that hopefully
describe the issue all the agent has is
it has the previous tests which might
not which probably don't test the the
bug it's trying to fix because if they
did the test would fail and the bug
wouldn't be there um so the um so the
agent's GNA have to generate gonna have
to propos its own tests and then run the
test in the proposed patches and so that
gives you a
um um so that gives you a a set of
patches that are kind of plausible that
in in the sense it's a technical term if
means that they pass the agent generated
test case and um the um and then we kind
of rank them and then one of them we
submit so
the um okay so there's a very big table
so um at them that uh um I'm not going
to read the entire table to you this is
a subset of the sweet bench leaderboard
uh at the time that the paper came out
um the order is now changed um um
changed but at the time that this came
out uh this was and this was one of the
best open source uh agents and it it
still is the the the order is slightly
different but it's still kind of near
near the top um the um so what I want to
um so the thing I want to take away from
this
is what are the advantages and
disadvantages of different agent designs
um so under one on the more Dynamic s
agent type approach the llm gets to
choose what problem solving strategy
it's using so you know if the llm if um
if the if the model produces a patch
that's nearly right and then there is a
whatever one of the tests fail then the
model then you can extend that
trajectory the model can decide oh do I
need to do some more code search in
order to figure out oh that this thing
has failed why I wasn't able to get the
the patch right or maybe I just want to
make a a small change to the patch
that's going to make it correct right
the model has this um um has the
flexibility to decide what strategy it's
going to do um whereas for for whereas
on the other side for the more
procedural one um if you have a case
where you know the problem can be solved
uh with the simple workflow then why
make the llm figure out what the
workflow is right and uh
the let the let the model spend more
time actually trying to solve the
problem and you kind of avoid tool use
errors because the tool use is happening
on top of the LM rather than within the
llm and you know you can avoid things
where the llm makes some initial mistake
and then the whole trajectory uh goes
off the
rails so the um um what was it I missed
one thing there okay yeah um so of these
come down to how do you want to budget
the set of comput amount of compute that
you have at test time like if you
imagine that I have one kind of partial
patch where it's failed is it a better
idea to kind of extend that trajectory
and try to fix that patch or is it a
better idea to throw it away and
generate a new one right um agent list
is more going to be like generating test
whereas um um where Dynamic could choose
um and the second part of this is that
um this may be a case where the kind of
winner between the the two of these
depends on what type of um um what's the
word um depends on what type of problem
you're considering right so for simpler
Pro for simpler smaller patches
generating text test might be better uh
kind of I'm speculating here but the um
um perhaps for longer more complex
changes we will start to see as we move
to that we will start to see more
advantages to having more flexibility in
the problem solving sty um so that's the
so you think there's kind of Continuum
in terms of we we've actually talked
about three different coding agents so
far uh one which I didn't talk much
about was just give the agent a Linux
prompt uh so that's kind of all there's
almost all the controllers in the model
then or you could do something like s
agent or agent list and there's kind of
a Continuum here and um it may be that
has the base model capability changes
has the um amount of um um and has the
complexity of the task changes the
design Point here uh that you do might
want to change
okay so there are I think three more uh
kind of coding agents I wanted to talk
about um but these kind of go faster and
faster because they are kind of more
similar to each other um so um another
one of the kind of highest performing o
Open Source agents right now is this one
uh auto code Rover uh which is from um
this um um university of Singapore um
there's a it's I think the last time
checked I think it was open hands was
the biggest um um um was the highest
highest on the sweep bench leaderboard
that might have changed um but I think
there's a lecture from last semester on
that so I won't go into it um so for
autoc code Rover the two things I wanted
to talk about here are the first one is
that it has a different set of search
tools so it's um that um rather than
being oh let me find this string in a
set of files um it's actually indexing
the um the a the methods and classes in
the files in the same way that an ID
would so you can have the the search
tools are things like you know find a
class with this name find a method with
this name in this class CL so that kind
of changes the type of code browsing
Behavior you see it can do kind of more
explicit command click um I also wanted
to talk about the um um uh the the kind
of control uh uh loop here which is that
it's sort of a concatenation of dynamic
agents so there's kind of there two
phases to this one is kind of try to
collect uh kind of uh kind of
information gathering try to do Code
retrieval and then the second part of it
is actually generate the patch and each
one of these a separate trajectory with
a different system instruction kind of
different set of tools and um then you
um and then you run them one the other
so it is kind of like a kind of a it's
kind of a an in between point between
agent list and S agent with kind of some
procedural control uh some that's more
Dynamic and um and the other thing that
you get from having these two um agent
Loops is kind of information hiding like
if there were particular if in like one
and for code search this probably
doesn't matter so much but there might
be other other types of Agents you
design where you care about this um
which is that if you have a uh you might
want one of these kind of agent Loops to
come up with an answer and then you want
to throw away the intermediate reasoning
just get the answer that it came up with
and give that to another agent that's
something you could because you're
worried that if you keep irrelevant
things in the context it will confuse
things um so let me um then the I think
I have two so I oh I didn't want okay
that's fine um so the other no I'm going
to do things out of order um the one I
will come back to those don't um so you
can can take this um you could take this
kind of procedural control to another
extreme to filtering you can have a
state machine so this uh so repair agent
is another uh kind of recent one where
um the it's you know it's a similar the
way it so this is these are four kind of
program repair tasks a different data
set it's not sweep bench but that's not
so important the kind of main thing is
for doing program fixing is the design
of the agent is given by the state
machine so where you know we kind of
design the what are the steps that we
think you do when you investigate and
repair a bug um each state is you know
has a a kind of specific system
instruction that says please try to do
please try to understand the bug if
you're in this
state and um depending on which tool the
model does next uh at the end so this
and then the model's then given the
system instruction the model is going to
do some thinking output a tool call
depending on which tool call is um um is
chosen you move to a different state of
the state machine so if you're currently
in the collect information State then um
when you do a code search you stay in
that state and you can do more code
searching if you call the kind of a
right fix that's a tool that moves you
into a different state and changes your
system instruction so that's kind of a
different way to get Dynamic control
with more information
hiding okay so the the final thing I
wanted to talk about which is you know
try uh uh there is although there are um
so what I've been talking about are more
kind of uh kind of academic agents there
although there are a lot of industrial
coding agents there's less technical
detail about them so this is one of the
of the ones that I know that's kind of
like a research agent moving towards uh
being used in industry so this is a kind
of a research agent at Google called
pasarin and uh these are kind of several
of so I'm not involved in this work uh
several of my friends in the kind of uh
developer tools org uh built this and um
so this is an agent that is designed to
solve kind of internal kind of coding
issues that Google developers have and
um the uh what makes the Google code
base kind of different and it's is that
um everything is in a monor repo um so
this thing is rather gigantic and
therefore we have kind of special the
build system is to take into effect
account the fact that there's a monor
repo that's so big that we can't kind of
store all of Google's code on our
laptops for example um so um so there
was I've talked I've talked about agents
so the first thing you have to do is
kind of make an evaluation if you want
to have this kind of thing so what uh
what they did is there's kind of a a
sweep bench like Loop where instead of
using GitHub uh uh pull requests uh we
use kind of internal bugs and fixes from
our issue tracker system so we'll take
cases where there are bugs that were
fixed and kind of some heris that these
are kind of reasonable things that we
want to use for an agent like uh like
there's a change in test in tests and
the um the kind of size of the patch and
so on and then we do a list of filtering
to have kind of a curated uh test set
both of two different kinds of bugs one
is um ones where the bug report was
written by a person um uh but it had a
kind of a small enough patch size and so
on and the other one is kind of
automatically generated bugs so these
are things that I'm going to talk about
this a bit more in the computer security
part of the lecture is that um the um
that when when for when we're doing
testing of Google code sometimes we will
run sanitizers so these are kind of
dynamic analyzers that kind of sit
underneath the code that's running and
check that certain bad things aren't
happening so one bad thing that could
happen is a buffer overflow so there's a
particular sanitizer called a dress
sanitizer um which you can use it well
at you can use at home as well um where
you know it it tries to detect at
runtime whether your executable is
reading or writing out of bounds and if
it does it causes a crash so you know
internally when these kinds of bugs
happen the um it creates automatically
report in RSU tracking system so we have
a number of reports like this and um so
they so this this this research agent is
kind of react style Dynamic agent like
swe bench uh s agent the um the
difference is the tools are actually our
Google development tools so the there's
an API to kind of Google code search our
build system which is called Basel and
is kind of um and um and you can kind of
view and edit
files so um so that is uh so that's kind
of that's kind of pass R and one thing I
wanted to point out since I've talked
about evals is what are the differences
between this curated um evaluation set
and um you know sayu uh s bench so um
these top three plots are kind of uh
different um um they are cumulative
distribution functions of different
statistics of sweet bench versus the our
internal evaluation for Pine and the um
so sweet bench is the blue one and then
the other two are kind of the machine or
human subset so generally what it is
especially the so this one is like how
many identifiers are in the patch how
many files how many lines and so for
example the um the especially the human
Patches from this uh from this data set
kind of are larger affect more files
kind of have more identifiers than the
um what we see on swe bench um sweet
bench is more similar to these kind of
sanitizer
reports um so the um uh and then you
know there's uh there's also uh maybe I
won't get into
so reports about The you can look into
how this agent
performs okay so um so that is um so
that's going to be so this is maybe a
good place to um um to stop for the
coding agents part of it so I'll get
into AI for security next uh but the the
main thing to so I've talked about how
agents uh Drive um um uh the design of
these systems evaluations Drive the
design of these systems um the other
thing is like we're it's so all of these
are kind of more similar than they are
different I think we're all working on
the same three ideas uh right now so the
um and the other thing about these is um
the ideas I mean I don't mean this
disparagingly the ideas behind all of
these agents are are fairly simple it's
just the design space is large so
there's kind of a large set of hill
climbing uh that you do when you have
this so we talk about so what is the
design space so one is okay tools do you
want we've kind of we've talked seen
different examples of that how do you
handle control flow is it Dynamic is
there a state machine uh do you kind of
recursively call an agent within a lower
level agent like you know whatever right
do you just write the control flow and
code um and then there is kind of the
design of the text like what do you
write in the system instruction um you
can do kind of the general things you do
for prompt tuning you can tell the agent
in kind of stronger or less strong
language how you want it to solve the
problem what order you want it to call
the
tools how you describe the tools how you
summarize tool outputs and uh and and so
on um all of these things have to have
sandboxes right because you're running
model generated code so uh I guess there
kind of a right way to do that but
that's something you have to deal with
if you want to have an agent that is
communicating with external surfaces
right all of these are hermetic right if
you were doing something like to prage
the uh the next set of the talk like
penetration testing um as an agent then
you need to figure out oh this is
actually communicating with external or
if you wanted an agent to manage your
email right like how would you you have
to think about okay how do you even kind
of prototype that uh when you have to
communicate with external surfaces and
one thing we haven't talked about
because these are research agents is you
know what do we do how would you involve
a human in the loop like when when do
you ask for clarification questions when
do you ask for
approval okay so I think and I think I I
already talked about this so um that is
kind of what I wanted to say about kind
of General coding agents so the next
part of the lecture is going to be more
kind of AI for computer security and
then some of our own work in AI security
so let so now I want to kind of finish
by talking a little bit about uh AI for
computer security which is kind of like
maybe a more emerging area than um AI
for uh code Generation Um why did oh was
this oh no I didn't that sorry I'm
confusing myself um so um let me start
um I I'm just I'm going to kind of dive
in and talk about yeah I'll talk about
evaluations but uh particular um uh I
want to start like one type of work that
I want to start by talking about is um
uh is kind of Capture the Flag
competition so that's one so if you say
oh I want to do AI for SEC Nah if you
start by saying Hey I want to do AI for
computer security questions are okay
what problem do you want to try to solve
within that and um how do you um so
there is a um particular type of
competition that people have like at
schools and and um um security
conferences things like that uh which
are called capture the flag what I like
I mean what I like about these at least
as a stepping stone is that it gives
some idea of the breadth of the type of
real problems that you'd like to solve
in in AIA for security that's why uh so
that's why uh I think it's interesting
that talk about um um there's different
kinds of CTF uh competitions um and I am
probably going to kind of butcher uh
this description a little bit so I would
feel free if you are a computer security
expert in the audience um but um the the
idea is there are different types of
tasks that are like toy versions of
something that you might do as a
professional researcher and that the the
task is set up in such a way
that uh for this particular typee of
Jeopardy task where uh there's there's a
special message which I call a flag and
if if you do the task for a while you
will see something where you're like oh
yeah that's the flag like hey I'm the
flag or whatever um maybe it's not that
but um and so and then then you know you
solve the task and you can submit it so
like one example would be like there are
kinds that are like digital frics where
they might say okay here's a file system
you know find uh find the hidden message
or they might give you more ins about
what it is and then you have to know
okay how do I kind of look through this
file system do clever searches you know
maybe uh more complex ones I might need
to use stenography or I might need to
like find a QR code or or whatever um so
this would be more like kind of modeling
digital investigations um you know then
there's like uh the ones that are just
cryptography where you have an encrypted
message you want to decrypt it um there
are ones where uh you want to uh kind of
P pone challenges you want to exploit
kind of memory vulnerabilities you might
want to kind of find find a
vulnerability and get a ccus um there
are ones where you want to kind of
identify a vulnerabilities or one or the
web ones where you want to do kind of
injection or or kind of cross site
scripting attacks and the the reason I
like to go through this is two one is
you can kind of see how these map even
though these are kind of games in some
sense you can see how they map to kind
of real world tasks that you might want
an agent to do and the other thing
that's nice is I think you if you've
been sitting in this class or even just
in this lecture by the end of this I
think if I just took one of those and
gave like a random one of these to like
any of you and said design an LM agent
for this you know you could do it right
it's pretty obvious why you would want
an agent to do any one of these
tasks um so I mean again like like we
were saying for coding like a kind of
toy game Benchmark isn't the same it's
not as complex has a real world task but
I think if you can't do these you're
probably not going to be able to do the
real world tasks either so and I think
we're we're currently at the stage of uh
agent development where uh kind of CDF
tasks are still a challenge so there are
kind of uh several different data sets
like some of them are kind of recent
with kind of C uh historical CTF
competitions of different
difficulties so like uh this top one the
NYU one is maybe the most recent one uh
there's also one with from uh kind of
high school level uh competitions and
know each one of these will contain kind
of the task description uh kind of
sandboxing environment and um a way a
raidar that will automatically check
like whether whether you found the flag
or not um so that gives you something
you to start with um and I want to go
through kind of one recent uh uh paper
to show okay how would you use an agent
uh for one of these tasks um so this
this one called Enigma it's going to be
the last maybe the second to last agent
I'm going to show you um uh they do all
run together after a while um so uh so
what this is uh so this is an agent to
solve these type of these Capture the
Flag uh competitions so the it is a um
it is a react style Loop so here's an
example and the um do I see on the next
slide yes I do so this is just an
example of uh running some of the tools
like you can do you can edit files and
so on um so the um so the types of tools
that you have there are the kind of the
general um um site agent Suite so you
can do file search you can edit code you
can do think you can have a command line
um but there's a few one of the things I
liked about this a few kind of
interactive tools uh that the agent can
call which you probably want for
security scenarios one of which is
having a debugger so um there are just
different tools that are like debug kind
of stateful tools uh as the way this is
designed I'll show you a different
debugger design in a minute um where um
the the debugger says there's a command
debugger start debugger stop debugger
step and those are just different top
level commands that the agent can use
and also there tools for connecting to
servers and again these are implemented
as three different stool tools that
change the trajectory state so the agent
can ask to start a connection stop a
connection or or send a line and um the
other thing that um is uh it kind of
does a kind of a natural idea they don't
see very much is a lot of these like if
you need need to like examine a binary
file as part of digital forensics like
you're going to um uh run up your
context length very quickly so there is
one like for long tool outputs there is
this kind of natural thing where oh let
me just ask an llm to summarize this
long output um so the um and then there
are um um one thing which is kind of
like a useful trick for when you're
designing your own agents is well the
first thing is um always look at the
trajectories right uh it's just like
when you're doing regular uh supervised
learning always or evaluation always
look at the data always look at the data
right so here it's like always look at
the trajectories right you want to see
what mistakes the agent's making and use
that to design the harness so like you
know one thing that's here is like there
are kind of bullet points in the system
instruction that says oh yeah I noticed
the agent screwed up on this let me add
a bullet point that says please don't
screw up in this way and then it makes
that error less often um okay so um this
had uh where okay let me
um so this is so this is then kind of
agent kind of versus on the left uh
versus no agent on the right and we see
overall you kind of a similar set of
increase that you saw from like the
initial S agent results like going from
basically nothing is Sol like three to
four perent to like double digit uh
percentage so it's kind of nice when you
see the so it seems like maybe this is
the same thing as a s b uh swe bench
kind of leaderboard but at a different
uh point in the
curve okay so that's basically what I
wanted to say about more General Capture
the Flag challenges so I I find I wanted
to talk End by talking about a kind of
specific security task which is kind of
vulnerability detection so um um so
these would be like you know if you want
to exploit a computer system to get you
know unauthorized access or something
like that um one one way you could do
this is by targeting bugs right in this
kind of software Hardware Network layer
whatever so I so I'm going to talk
specifically about uh so a vulnerability
is basically a bug in the system that
has security implications so I'm going
to talk specifically about software
vulnerabilities both because I'm talking
about coding agents and because um
that's I think where most of the most of
the work has happened so far so some
examples like you know reading out of
bounds or kind of cross-site scripting
or something like that with this kind of
it could be a potentially a small bug in
the program that the the attacker can
use to to do bad things so um so let me
take let me take an example of like an
outof bounds right uh which is kind of a
particular bad could have so there is a
kind of taxonomy of these different kind
of software bugs that you can go to and
if you go to the taxonomy and say okay
what kind of bug is it out of bounds
right um it'll show you C code that
looks like the the code on the right
where it says oh okay like one kind of
Illustrated version of this bug is oh if
you have a function that returns
negative one on error and then I use
that as an index well the negative one
is going to get cast to it could get
cast to something unsigned which is now
going to point someplace way off into
Oblivion and then you'll kind of write
something to memory you didn't want want
to and then when you look at that it
really seems like detecting
vulnerability should be pretty easy
right because you just want to kind of
find the statea flow and find things
that aren't within the bounds um so
here's another example of an of an out
of bounds right um so this is an example
of a a kind of function from the Linux
kernel um I mean I know the first
example was probably relatively simple
you might have seen the bug right away
uh know do you see the bug in this one
that's a
joke so um so what this is is I mean
actually this it's not like I mean it's
too small for you to see but the this
this part of it isn't like if you kind
of make reasonable assumptions about
Linux kernel macros uh this part of this
code is not that difficult uh to
understand so um what's happening here
here is uh
this function is copying some data from
a network packet if you look at the two
arguments to I don't know what I guess
RCV stands for receive but um the the
first argument is the actual packet the
second argument is a header and what it
is doing is on I just I have it in my
notes um this line here it's doing a
malic uh the size is this thing's size
which it's pulling from the header and
then on line uh let me see it's 40 oh
yeah 44 I think uh uh it's like it's
doing a mem copy uh from something in
the packet to this thing that's
allocated based on the size um so what
you can see here is that um both of
these things were read from the network
and there hasn't been checking done of
the size so that means that oh you could
actually um there's no um the actual
payload might not match the size in the
header and so if it doesn't then the
buffer this allocated will be too small
and who knows how much you're going to
be writing um so the reason that so so
that's so this is actually kind of a a
kind of a real vulnerability in the Cor
in the kernel and the two things that I
wanted to point out why this is hard um
one is a bit of a needle and a hyack
right um there's could be lots of
functions like this in the Linux kernel
and it could be kind of difficult to
craft inputs that reach them I have to
know which network protocol uh this
thing is handling and so on and so this
kind of you know identifying the the
actual data flow um that breaks is
fairly simple but kind of identifying it
from a lot of things that look similar
but are perfectly safe is very difficult
and the second thing is this function on
its own it's not vulnerable or
non-vulnerable that's not even a
well-defined question to say is this
function vulnerable because if the
caller checked did the balance checking
this function would be fine right so you
actually can't understand whether this
function is vulnerable or not without
kind of knowing globally uh what what's
going
on okay so that's why AI for
vulnerability detection is hard um in
fact uh in fact this slide is basically
a criticism of the next slide so um the
next slide is so we have this really
nice source of data uh which is the kind
of vulnerability database so there is a
place where if you have public software
and you discover a vulnerability you can
kind of get a unique trafficking number
write a description and um you know give
links to the patch any other information
about the advisories and there are kind
of thousands of these uh of these
collected so this seems like great for
machine learning right because all I
need to do is is say um oh let me kind
of download all these vulnerabilities
and I'll um uh kind of the patches and
I'll try to have some classifier that
says whether things are vulnerable or
not so this very so I'm I'm exaggerating
my criticism of this but it's a very
natural thing to do right the first
thing you see a big data you see a big
data set on the web is let's download
and use it it's what you should do um
and so there's a bunch of authors who
have done this and kind of created data
sets that say oh that the idea is that
I'll take examples of code where we
found a vulnerability we've not found a
vulnerability and you know try to have
you can measure kind of detection or
patching uh kind of based on this um
seems like a natural thing to do uh
unfortunately you know it's it's what I
would have done too uh I got started and
the problems with it uh the main the
first problem is like how much of the
code you put in the input right like we
saw in the previous slide if I just look
at one function that's been patched um
you know that might not be where um I
might not know just looking at that
function whether there's a problem or
not um or just because if I take a
function in the patch that might not be
what does it mean for a line of code to
be vulnerable right um there's a line of
code where an incorrect memory access
happens sure but that that line of code
might be correct right the part that's
incorrect might be something Upstream
did something wrong um so the patch
might be very far from the line of code
that crashed so the idea even of a line
of code or a function being vulnerable
something I'd argue it's not a
meaningful concept um then the other
thing like if you want to so there is a
question of like how much context do you
want to give and I I'm not it's a very
difficult question to answer or another
question how do you handle Tangled
commits so I kind of mentioned this a
little bit in swe bench like if you want
to use this as a patching data set well
lots of times the a patch will do more
than just fix the vulnerability that's a
very common case so kind of learning
kind of difficult um the other thing is
like maybe this is easier like kind of
judging correctness of patches is kind
of tricky is like if you can run the
code you could probably judge
correctness if you're trying to do it
statically um then that's difficult
right because there are many ways to
patch a vulnerability um and the fact um
I gave you this example of um um of a
vulnerability description like these are
vague um that they will give you some
information about where to start uh they
might they'll be vague they'll be noisy
sometimes just because people are busy
they make mistakes sometimes because you
don't want to give out too much
information about a security
vulnerability so I think these are
really difficult issues it's really
difficult to come up with a static
evaluation of vulnerability detection in
this way and um and I think these issues
are fundamental um I think people have
done a lot of great work trying to get
around them to make the data sets
cleaner and cleaner but I think I think
these data sets are really hard to use
um so what I would um um so I would
recommend instead for working on this
kind of problem is is do something
Dynamic so you need something like a
sweet bench eval where you can actually
run the the code on an input that
exposes the vulnerability um so there um
um so there are kind of there are some
data sets I left one out that's one of
the things you're supposed to ask me
about um so I'll just tell you about it
now um so there is um so there is like a
a DARPA sponsored competition going on
now uh the finals are later this year
for like AI based vulnerability
detection um there was uh kind of an
older one um 2016 it's also kind of
interesting both because you can get the
kind of programs and also I think the
story of it is interesting if you want
to look it up uh there is a more recent
security evaluation from meta that
contains some um it tests various parts
of security for AI and AI for security
but there is like a a memory
vulnerability thing there is a more
recent thing that I like uh which I
forgot to put on the slide uh which is
arv arvo it's a um it's for some past
vulnerabilities that been found by
fuzzers containerized so that you can
run them so you can act checking of
whether you found or fix
fixed um so there is uh I'm about to uh
I'm about to talk about one more agent I
promise uh but um there is a lot of a
huge amount of research on automated
techniques for vulnerability detection
like uh both some AI but also kind of
non- AI so probably the most a commonly
used technique for automatically finding
vulnerabilities is called fuzzing so
that is like you run the programs on
many many random inputs uh you can
choose them like a genetic algorithm
type search so you can flip bits in the
inputs you can mix and match them and so
you try to find an input that causes
like uh vulnerability to happen like an
outof bounds right um those are like
those are really important in practice
like uh security critical uh software is
uh commonly is fuzzed uh extensively um
so and so this is uh this is kind of
important technology but it's also it
also ASM tootes like if you run a fuzzer
for long enough on a um on a software
package like it will you don't like
continually find bugs even if they they
exist and there are kind of famous
examples of bugs where they've been
found exploited in the wild these are
packages that are commonly fuzzed but it
was a difficult part of the code for the
fuzzer to reach um there's a lot of work
on so I think there's an opportunity for
AI to try to uh well keep fuzzing things
but trying to find deeper bugs maybe
that require um kind of complex
invariance that fuzzers can't reach um
people work on static analysis for
vulnerabilities for vulnerability
detection um that's um you know it's
kind of there's a lot of interesting
work that's been done in that space uh
the downside is kind of combinatorial
explosion and the false positive rate
it's kind of very it's very difficult to
Define um uh it's kind of a very very
difficult business to be in um and then
like on some of these other data sets
I've talked about like you know once you
collect the vulnerability data sets on
the previous Slide the ones that I don't
like you can try find who an LM on them
and so a lot of papers the papers that I
cite it will show you some results for
that um but um you know we wanted to do
something different so uh we thought
there was kind of an opportunity to try
to use um the um uh to try to kind of
you know leverage AI in a more
interesting way and so that's this
project that I'm involved in which
called the Big Sleep um one thing I've
noticed having named a project this is
that most people do not have the same
knowledge of Classic Cinema as I do so
the big sleep is kind of a it's a it's a
famous movie from the 40s but starring
Humphrey bogar and if you like old
movies I recommend it um the um there's
a story about why this is named that
that I won't get into so um so this is a
collaboration between some of us in
Google Deep Mind and some um Security
Experts from Google project zero so
these uh which you know this is a kind
of a really um uh a nice Security Group
within Google that tries to find
vulnerabilities it tries it does they
they also they try they also succeed in
kind of finding vulnerabilities in open
source projects and um if you look at
other things on their blog you can see
kind of how intense uh some of the
vulnerabilities that they find are so
with this kind of group of collaborators
we've been kind of creating this this
agent and and um the thing that
motivated us about this was thinking
about um or one way to motivate this is
by thinking about kind of the experience
of our collaborators in Project zero as
a human security researcher auditing
code to try to find a vulnerability um
they don't think of it like a classifier
right you don't just read some code as a
person then say yes no I think it's
vulnerable right so instead what you do
is you going to read the code try to
understand it you have some hypothesis
about what would be going wrong and then
you try to run the code in a or
something gain some information about
whether your hypothesis is correct and
um and we and we wanted to see and we
think that if an AI is going to be
successful that it should do that too so
and this kind of naturally suggested NH
entic approach uh where you'd have kind
of a code browser that and a debuger so
one way you can think about this is
analysis versus static um if you are if
you're trying to train just an llm you
know maybe with some um maybe some
reasoning tokens or whatever to examine
code uh do some reasoning come up with
the vulnerability that's kind of like
static analysis you haven't run the code
whereas if you do an agentic approach
that's more like running a fuzzer it's
more like Dynamic
analysis so um what the we're focusing
on a particular type of security issue
um in in the big sleep and that we're
focusing on memory safety of
vulnerabilities and the idea is kind of
uh given a given a code base the goal of
the agent is going to be like a fuzzer
to generate an input that when it's run
on this program under test causes bad
memory Behavior like an out-of-bounds
read or something and um what um some of
this is so you get some of the
advantages of a react style Loop but the
other Advantage compared to static
analysis approaches and even compared to
say something like code editing is in
some ways this is a simpler problem than
code editing and the reason is we have
an oracle so if we can so I mentioned um
sanitizers to you earlier in the lecture
so when we are running the program in
this agent we are going to run it um in
a sanitizer in a debugger so the goal of
the agent is to actually generate an
input that causes the program to crash
and when it crashes we know you found a
security bug so um you know whereas uh
if you're doing code generation you
don't know what the real you don't know
what the true true tests are so you have
some part at the end where you have to
figure out oh which patch do I choose um
here it's like if you find a bug you
find a bug and one thing that's nice
about well let me actually say the agent
before I start telling you about how
good it is so um so what we're going to
do in big sleep it's going to be a react
style agent the goal of the agent is to
generate an input that triggers a
sanitizer crash um we have access to
three different types of tools so one is
like a code browser tool so this would
be kind of similar to what I said about
auto code Ro Rover that we actually
index uh the program we know what all
the identifiers are so our tools are
like the type of tools you do in ide
navigation so like given the name of a
method jump to definition or we can also
follow cross
references um then in order to generate
inputs we do that using a we don't
actually ask the agent to generate text
directly uh we ask the agent to rate a
Python program that generates the input
and the reason we do that is like if you
want to do a buffer overrun or something
you know we don't want the agent have to
generate 20 48 A's we'd rather generate
a python program this is a * right it's
just simple so we we tell the agent
please generate a Python program that
sends a writes a string to a particular
variable we send that string to standard
in and then we can run the target
program in a debugger so we've talked
about the the Enigma agent also had a
debugger the design of this tool is
similar but a little bit different um so
in our tool right now the agent doesn't
call the debugger interactively um what
it does is it can say you know it first
it calls the python interpreter to set
up an input and then when it calls the
debugger it it just runs the whole
program and it can optionally specify a
list of quote unquote uh breakpoints so
a breakpoint is a a file line number and
an expression optionally and what it
does is we we tell the agent their break
points but they're really watch points
so we'll run the whole program without
stopping I mean they break wait uh we'll
run the whole program without stopping
and at the end we tell the agent here
are the break points that were hit and
here's the value of the Expressions you
asked me for so this way this gives the
agent another way to check whether when
it generates an input whether it's doing
what it expects whether it's having the
control flow that the agent expects from
the
input okay so let me show you an example
of a trajectory so um I don't know what
that meant um so this is a um let me see
this is an example of a program from The
Meta cyers SEC eval Benchmark that I
kind of briefly mentioned in the
previous slide uh so there is a system
instruction that I haven't told you that
kind of explains the task to the agent
describes the tools and um um get
presents a problem solving strategy and
some guidelines uh to the agent so the
first thing agent's going to do is say
okay please show me the main method um
so here all of the the as I said the
control flow is completely Dynamic like
react style and there's no um the agent
has to use the Cod browser tools to see
the code so then it gets a thing of the
main method and typically what the agent
does is it summarizes the code sometimes
longer sometimes less whenever it sees
it and then it'll decide okay I see an
identifier there okay you can't see
there's a reader class because I snipped
it out but somewhere in this there's a
class called reader so the agent says
okay let me look at the reader class and
so it says okay let me look it so it
looks at this and it'll do a bunch of
turns of code
browsing and um after a while the agent
gets tired of code browsing and it
decides okay I think I found a
vulnerability now so what it does then
what we've instructed it to do is to
write a report that explains what the
vulnerability is and uh what happen
uh how to exploit it so the agent will
generate this text after it's seen
enough code where it says oh on line 70
you use string copy but you didn't use
bound checking so if I create an input
of this type then um then this is it
loves saying a typical buffer overflow
or a classic buffer overflow really
likes that um the so this this could
this this could be exploited in this way
here's my report now let me generate an
input and so the input is going to
python now this is a python code here's
an example of like what I said where you
can construct a long input um the um the
agent can you know it can um it's
helpful to have access to the library
because you know if you want to um if
you want to kind of generate uh uh sorry
I'm having English if you wanted to
agent to generate binary strings for
example um You can call you know number
to bytes it can um it can also if it
knows things about particular input
formats so if you have a um
a program that takes Json or images has
input then the Python program can
generate that so in this case after
generate some python input it calls the
debugger function it says oh the these
were like ters that it thought was
related to the vulnerable code path so
it says oh yeah please show me those and
um so now we run the program in the
debugger and um the agent is sad because
the program exited without crashing um
generally that's what you want but not
if you're doing a security audit so um
so now the agent's like okay it didn't
trigger the bug that it thought it did
so it can um let's let's keep iterating
and so so then it write some things
about why why it messed up um so so here
it says oh the program failed ear than
anticipate it because I forgot to do
such and such and so let me update the
input so that I don't make this mistake
and it might iterate through do that
multiple times and then and run the
debugger again after each one and then
at some point it says Ah the program
crashes uh yay it crashed
um so um and then it gives some
information and then that means the
agent has
succeeded so uh so where are we where
where are we right now so I'd say the
current kind of state of the agent is
like we have kind of ways of testing it
on kind of Capture the Flag challenges
like uh like for example this open uh2
Benchmark and um and there it's kind of
reasonably effective there's still a lot
that we need to do to scale it up um and
we have found uh one real world of
vulnerability that we've disclosed and
um that is uh kind of in SQL light um so
um one thing about this it's kind of one
of the advantages of agents for this
type of security task is you can put any
information that you have in the context
so in this case we did a type of variant
analysis so um so it turns out that when
you find a a security bug a
vulnerability in a project there are
often many similar vulnerabilities at
different places in the same project
project so those are called variants and
some like a very large number of
vulnerabilities that we see exploited in
the wild are variants of bugs that have
already been fixed so what we did here
is we took kind of a recent uh bug that
had been fixed in SQL light and we added
the information about it into the
context and then said I don't know try
to find something similar and um and you
know eventually and it did um one thing
I want to comment on this is one thing
that was kind of working in our favor
this is maybe like best case in some
sense because in I I mentioned the kind
of Little Red Riding Hood principle um
the agent has seen a lot of SQL queries
right in the pre-training data so if it
sees kind of one SQL query that used to
that used to break the system it's kind
of easy for it it's kind of reasonable
that the that llm could generate similar
queries um and the other thing I
mentioned fuzzing it turns out we did go
back with general purpose fuzzers and
try to see okay now that we know where
the bug is can I get a kind of state of
the art general purpose fuzzer to find
it and in some reason it was and it was
pretty hard to find like after 150 hours
we weren't able to find it so um yeah so
that's uh that's kind of our our status
so far so finally let me pop up and say
uh so I had to summ summarize just the
security part of the lecture so I think
this is kind of a wide open area uh
we're just getting started there's a lot
to be done um I think it's an exciting
application area for AI because agentic
techniques seem really natural here you
need to interact with servers you need
to run debuggers um and it's also um and
it's also kind of a really nice um test
bed for code understanding methods right
that to find a security issue and to say
oh yeah this is a software vulnerability
you've got to think really carefully
about the corner cases that the
developer maybe didn't think of or or
and you have to track kind of data
flow along stretches of the program so
it kind of and or and if you're doing
Network or system security you have to
do that across multiple interacting um
um Parts uh programs in a system so it
really does require you to kind of
understand that a deep level what
programs are doing which makes it kind
of an interesting challenge model
challenge task for llms and you know
I've talked you know in depth about some
Capture the Flag stuff and some
vulnerabilities but there's kind of a
huge space here that we're kind of only
starting to get into and there's a lot
of real T and kind of and this is the
time we're starting to scale it up so
it's kind of an exciting time to be part
of this area Okay so this is that's kind
of all I have to say I'm kind of happy
to take some more questions thank you