I'm really happy to announce uh our next
guest speaker for the course uh
professor Jajun Wu. So Jajun is an
assistant professor here at Stanford uh
in the department of computer science
and he's a faculty member of the
Stanford vision and uh sorry vision and
learning lab. Um his research focuses on
scene understanding uh with an emphasis
on multimodal perception uh robotics and
embodied AI, visual generation and
reasoning and uh 3D understanding which
is the topic of today's lecture. Um and
so I'll now turn it over to Jajun to
begin today's lecture.
>> Okay. Yeah. So I'm Jun. I'm an assistant
professor here and I think a few years
ago I used to teach this class code
teach. So I heard this year it's the
10th year anniversary right. So we have
guest speakers from different places.
Okay. Um so today we're going to talk
about 3D vision. Uh so it might be kind
of different from a lot of things you um
you you learned before because I think
in the past few weeks we talked about
like conversion new networks and
transformers and maybe vision language
models and generator models as well for
justing right. Okay. Yeah. So here for
3D I think I'm going to first introduce
a little bit on what are the 3D
representations you know. So it's more
like it's pretty distant from all the
deep learning stuff. But then we're
going to talk about how deep learning or
AI has changed 3D vision and how they
can be integrated in different ways, you
know, and we look into a few different
applications about 3D generation,
reconstruction and stuff like that.
Okay. So let's begin by looking into
what are the possible ways to represent
objects in in 3D because in 2D is so so
straightforward. It looks like I just
have pixels, right? I have a I loading a
file of a PNG file or JPEG file. It's
like 200 by 200 pixels. But how can we
represent 3D objects? I think that's the
first thing you want to look into.
And uh 3D objects, you know, they can be
diverse. Uh they can be at different
scales. It can be like huge large
buildings and trees, complex structures.
And if you zoom in, you know, you can
also see all the fine details. So what
are the best 3D representations to
represent all these different types of
3D objects at different scales with
different features
and unlike images where everyone just
use pixels you know so we have 200 by
200 500 by 500 um the way to represent
3D objects in ter you know objects are
also like you have geometry you have
textures you have materials but let's
just maybe start by looking at geometry
and even just for 3D object geometry
there are so many different ways to
represent them you know we can basically
categorize them into two different
categories. One is called explicit
representations. So where you can you
can in some sense they're directly I
would say explicitly representing part
of the objects. This includes uh things
like point clouds. If you have a cloud
of 3D points or a polygon mesh or
subdivisions which we're going to talk
about it and others and there's a
different categories of object shape
representations which are often called
implicit. So we're going to talk about
them as well. So I'm going to explain
them in a little bit detail later
including level sets, algebraic
surfaces, distance functions. So they're
basically representing 3D objects or
their geometries as functions which it
is not directly know it's not as in some
sense intuitive as oh it's just a
collection of points but as we'll see
later they also have their own
advantages and weaknesses uh using
implicit representations. So every
choice they have their you know suitable
task and type of geometry in particular
in the context deep learning you know
they may also have their own strengths
and weakness when you want to apply a
deep learning method on top of it.
So when do we choose representation? You
know we want we have to store them. So
pixels are easy to store because it's
just a matrix. But then 3D point clouds
are kind of more irregular and also you
know if especially if you use some
implicit representations like
representing object as a function how
would you how would you store that in a
in a computer and how does it support
you know creating a new shapes um and
especially now let's say maybe the input
is a picture or the input is a language
descriptions and different type of
operations you have a 3D objects then
how can you edit it simplify it smooth
it filter it repair it right so you can
have to do a lot more you know for for
images sometimes you want to do that too
you want to edit it. You want to add it
using language. You want to edit it
using stroke. And how can you edit or
perform any type of operations on 3D
objects and rendering? How can you turn
that 3D objects render into computer v
uh into 2D pixels? In some sense, you
can 3D vision is is to invert a process,
right? How can you go from 2D images to
reconstruct the 3D objects? So, how does
support all these different things
including NN animations especially if
you are modeling let's say 3D humans or
animals and you want to animate them. So
all these factors need to be considered
and something else of course it is sort
of connect through all these is also
their integration with different deep
learning methods for let's say shape
editing rendering inverse rendering
animation as well. So very quickly we
can go through some of these
representations like point clouds. Um so
point cloud is probably the simplest
representations uh only has 3D points.
It doesn't have connectivity. So it
doesn't capture how these points are
connected. So you basically just have a
instead of having a n byn matrix uh
which is about the pixel values of all
the pixels in a picture now you have a
3xn matrix where three is xyz
coordinates of these individual points
and you have a number of points.
So sometimes you can represent the
surface normals of the point as well so
that you have not only where the point
is in the 3D space but also uh which uh
to which direction is facing. So you
have the surface normals which give you
a bit more information and sometimes
people call them surf which is points uh
with orientations
and yeah so why do you need surface
normals? Because if you want to render
them, you want to see like how the
object look like you know if you then
that means you have to often specify a
lighting source right where's the
lighting coming from and but you know to
make the rendering look realistic you
have to consider how the lighting you
know coming from a certain direction is
going to interact with the point and
this is where the surface norms normals
is used to help you to make the
rendering look realistic like you can
see here.
So how can you get points? Um you know a
benefit of the point cloud it is it is
often a raw format that you will get
from a lot of the 3D sensors. Um you
know including these kind of depth
sensors including some 3D scanners and
you know nowadays I think if you can
even use your iPhone and I think they
have a AR kit or these kind of software
allow to scan 3D objects but but the raw
output of those sensors they're still
kind of 3D point clouds. Now of course
after that you have to process them and
fuse them to make it like maybe objects
with textures.
Um so yeah they often results of from
scanners they can potentially be very
noisy and there are things like this and
you want to fuse them merge them repair
them um and this in this part you know
you have to consider how these different
pictures can be registered uh to give
you the shared point cloud
and um they can they're very flexible so
you can because you can move points here
and there so you can use them to
represent basically any type of object
geometry you're not constrained by the
topology or stuff like
uh it's kind of useful for large data
sets because sometimes you have to
consider a very diverse set of objects.
Um but you know because points are
already in some you consider to have pre
being pres right so you know if you have
a lot of points if if you're
representing objects and but your points
are sampled in uneven way in the sense
that you have a lot of points let's say
on the on the head of the rabbit but you
have very very few points on the tail of
the rabbit then it will be actually hard
to draw samples from these inner sample
regions. So sometimes when people
consider you know sampling points you
have to design algorithm to make sure
you sample them roughly evenly you know
across different parts of the objects
and other limitations or you know it's
not obvious how we can directly perform
sometimes the very useful operations
like simplification or subdivisions on
these objects. Uh it doesn't directly
allow you to do smooth rendering.
There's no topological information.
Right? So for example here, you know, if
I give you a collection of points, then
you can't even tell, you know, if this
is like a Taurus or this is like these
kind of ring-l like shapes, right?
Because it doesn't tell you how these
points are connected. So it's kind of a
a partial information about what object
is if you just have the point clouds. So
naturally people will say, okay, how can
I actually capture, you know, more
information so that I can distinguish
between these two different objects?
Then naturally that goes to the
polygonal meshes right. So it represent
the object that still has a collection
of points but then also how these points
are connected. So now you have not only
the points but also the faces the
surfaces
and this is arguably like uh I would say
the most widely used representations for
3D objects in all these graphics engines
and in computer games and stuff like
that. You know basically it is all
represented as polygon meshes. Uh but
you can see that you know to represent
faces it is more complex because often
you have to consider um you know
especially if you're looking at raw
meshes then every face may have a
different number of points some have
three points some have four points have
five points and how you can represent
them especially given their irregularity
how you can integrate them with neuronet
networks you know especially in early
stage when people start with like
commercial neuron networks okay they
always assume a fixed resolution but
here you have you know not I would say a
variable uh dimension of these raw
information how does that integrate with
deep learning that's been some big
challenge that's why you know deep
learning with 3D vision kind of started
kind of late because people are thinking
about how we can adapt all these deep
learning method to deal with all these
um uh complex representations for
objects which are not as unified as uh
images
but meshes are really widely used and
they can be you know very complex meshes
that capture all the details you know
for example you have scanners you get
points and then you fuse them and you
apply some algorithm you can get you
know very arch mesh. This one has like
56 uh million triangles and 28 million
uh vertices uh to represent a sculpture.
And you can have even larger ones. You
know, let's say from Google Earth, they
have trillions of triangles try to
represent basically all all the
buildings on Earth. The nice thing about
meshes, it supports a lot of operations
like subdivisions. Oh, I want to have
more details and how can I have more use
more meshes to capture more details of
the shape.
Um and you can do simplification as
well. Sometimes you want to process
things very fast. So I don't need that
many meshes. I just want to simplify it
and so I can there are existing
algorithms allows you to do that as
well.
And regularization you know if you get
irregular mesh and sometimes you want to
regularize them so that every phase is a
triangle they always connect three
vertices. they have roughly uh the same
uh size and so that it's easier for
processing and they have uh more say
good properties that supports future
processing of different graphics
algorithms and matches you know there
have been people who develop these
algorithms as well so that you have you
can ensure that you know basically
points at different regions they're
roughly evenly sampled so that it won't
be the case that okay let's say the head
of the tail or the head of the rabbit is
much more densely sampled than the tail
and these kind of things
okay so this is kind one type of shape
representations and there are other type
of shape representations. For example,
uh parametric representations because
objects are not just totally irregular.
It's not just often a collection of
points and meshes. They're very general.
But sometimes you lose a lot of
information if you look at let's say
your chairs or the tables, you know, you
have all these kind of straight lines,
right? So how can you represent these
kind of straight lines? And when people
design them, you know, they often use
some of these parametric
representations, you know, so you can
represent shapes as a function, right?
As I think about it, you know, so when I
design them, I can, you know, it's
really if I want to represent a surface
or represent a curve, right? The
underlying dimen degree of freedom is
actually lower. You know, often if I
have a curve, you know, there's only
only one underlying degree of freedom.
That's why I can represent a curve using
a function f ofx, right? Just varied x
and get a value of y. So you can use
basically all these different types of
functions in 2D, but also more often in
3D, right? to map I know a certain
number of variables the underlying
intrinsic dimensionality of the objects
which are often let's say two or even
one uh and then map it into the 3D space
and then this allows you to represent a
3D objects in a parametric
representations using basically a set of
functions right you can do that for
curves no let's say in circles right
basically if you want to represent a
circle you know you don't really need to
you know one way is you simple number of
points right or you can even connect
them uh like a meshes you using the
lines
Another way is you just represent the
curve uh the the circle as this function
right basically there's a sign function
and cosine function uh and you just vary
one variable which is t you can think
about it as the degrees or the angles
and it will map it to all the points on
the circles right so here now you can
use a function to represent a parametric
representations for a curves in 2D and
of course you can do that uh in 3D as
well if you want to represent a sphere
all you need is just like two degrees of
freedoms um UMV and then you can go
through these functions so that you can
map them to every point in the 3D space
for this sphere right so people have
designed I'm not going to detail here
but more complex parametric
representations like basic curves and
basier surfaces which allows you to
represent like these kind of pretty
flexible and smooth surfaces in 3D using
basically a few control points um so you
basically use these basia functions to
capture the underlying lower
dimensionalities of these surfaces and
then you can map these underlying low
dimensionality into these kind of
flexible shapes
and they also allow you to do things
like subdivisions. So you can you know
trying to get more details uh into the
surfaces and to make it more fine grain
and stuff like that. Okay, so that would
be the second category of shape
representations. You know, you can
represent 3D objects in a nonparametric
way like a collection of unordered
points or their connections as meshes or
you can represent them in a parametric
way where you have a function basically
and you by varying a few parameters that
are underlying the true degree of
freedoms of the object geometry you can
map them into more complex shapes.
So basically everything here as I said
has been you know if you remember at the
very beginning we said there are two
types of ways to represent object
geometry. one is explicit there's more
implicit and all of them they fall into
this category of being quite explicit
right so it's like I have a points and
points are just directly points you on
objects and for the surfaces or for
parametric curves as well you know they
directly map it right to the points on
the on on the on objects um so their
explicit representations they have a lot
of benefits you know for first they have
you map all the points uh directly um so
you can get all these points in general
eneral you know you can you know every
point I have let's say I sample I have a
basia surface representations I can
basically sample two points and UV in
this underlying low dimensional space
and then going through that function I
map it to a point in the 3D space right
so I directly get a point on the 3D surf
in a 3D space so all points are given in
some sense you can say directly I can
directly get all the points so it's very
easy for us to sample points right so
let's say I have this Taurus and I have
represented using this f function So now
my question is can you just sample some
points on the surface of the object for
me? This is so easy because I will just
you know randomly put in some UMV
values. I just randomly sample those UMV
values and then let them go through this
function and it will just you know
compute and give me some of the 3D
points which are guaranteed to be on
this surface of the object. Right? So
sampling is much easier. The what is
hard about these explicit
representations?
The hard thing is it's very hard in some
sense you know to test whether a point
is inside or outside the objects.
Similarly, you know, if I represent a
sphere as this function and it's easy
for me to sample points on a sphere, but
it is hard for me to say, you know, now
I have a different, you know, I have a
query, right? I say this point 3 over 4,
one over two, one over four, I have this
point in 3D space, is it inside object
or is it outside object,
right, right? You know, I think we can
maybe actually I'm not even sure about
that. Um so it is actually kind of hard
to test you know whether this certain
point is inside or outside object. So
you can see that explicit
representations um is you know it's all
these representations they have their
own strengths and weaknesses and for
explicit representations it's actually
pretty easy to sample points which are
very useful because sometimes you want
to convert them into let's say a
collection of points you know and then
you want to apply whatever your point
neuron networks on it but it's hard to
test if a certain point is inside
outside object which may have some
issues you know for example let's say if
you want to use a uh newer rendering
methods and nowadays a lot of these
newer rendering methods requires a lot
of these kind of queries about whether a
point is inside object, outside object,
what will be the geometry or density of
object at a particular point, what will
be the material or what will be the
radiance or color of the object at a
particular point. Right? So explicit
representations are not very um
supportive of it's not easy to run these
operations on these explicit
representations.
So naturally people thought okay maybe
we can come up with a different type of
ways to represent geometry and here I
say implicit representational geometry
but as you can see later you know a lot
of these newer rendering methods or deep
learning methods they just extend these
implicit representations for not only
geometry but also for colors and
appearance of objects in 3D. So idea of
these implicit representations is now
that I want to uh classify these points.
So I assume you know uh if the points
are on the objects they're on the
surface of objects then they satisfy
some certain relationship. So for
example you know for a sphere what will
be the points on a sphere on a unit
sphere you know the the the constraint
they satisfy is you know square of x and
square of y and square z you know when
they sum them up when you sum them up
they equal to one right so this is
constraint they satisfy for all the
points um uh on the sphere. All right.
So more generally you know you can write
it down as you know the constraint will
be some function of x and y and z equals
zero. Right. So in this case fx and y
the function will be x2 + y square 2 + z
2 - 1 right? So that would be the
function here. But more generally you
can think about it is you know for even
for complex shapes you can represent
sometimes you know these functions can
be so complex that you don't even have a
closed form you know. So how can I
represent f I don't know I I just write
it as a neuronet network. My hope is a
neuron network will be able to represent
it. But in general the idea is you know
you have some function um or some
constraints that the points on a certain
object will satisfy and this is the way
you will represent an object. This is
called implicit representations which
started with geometry but as I said you
now use it in all these different ways
representing textures materials
appearance and all these things. So the
good thing about implicit representation
oh sorry let's start with the bad thing
the bad thing about implicit
representation is now it's actually much
harder to sample points right I tell you
okay this is a constraint let's say this
tora satisfy right okay um know every x
and y and z you know if I put into this
function and the output is zero then
yeah they must be on the surface of this
object but then how can I get a couple
of these xyz you know tupless that would
be very hard because they're required to
solve this function and this function is
maybe not too hard to solve you Maybe
you can still solve that using some high
school math. Uh but uh you know when the
function gets really complex you know
for arbitrary shapes it becomes much
harder to solve these functions. So it's
not easy to actually now sample points
on the surface of the objects if you are
representing objects implicitly. But
benefit the strength of that is now it's
actually pretty easy to test whether a
point is inside object outside object
because you know if I want to do testing
I just have a query then this is so easy
because is it inside outside I just send
it into that function I'll get a value
or the value is okay minus one / 8 okay
this more than zero so you know because
I assume you know the object is
represented by this function and all the
surface point on object they satisfy
that function equals zero anything
that's no I would say lower than zero
that's negative The output value is
negative then the point must be inside
object and if the output value is
positive then the point must be outside
object right so now it becomes much
easier to test whether a certain point
is inside outside object although it
becomes much harder to sample a number
of points on the surface of object so
you can see now there's a clear
trade-off between this implicit and
explicit representations here we again
we talk about geometry and but this
distinction and the contrast between
explicit implicit representations is I I
think is very important and fundamental
is behind development of deep neuron
deep neuronet networks when they apply
to 3D uh data in general as we'll see
later. Okay. So before we mean 25
minutes so I promise I spend another
more no more than five minutes and then
we're going to talk about deep learning.
So before we talk about how deep
learning can be applied to 3D
representations in general, you know, a
little bit more on implicit
representations is uh some other
features of implicit representations.
The good things about them is it's easy
uh to compose them, right? So sometimes
you feel like oh if I have to represent
everything with a function uh that seems
uh great you know if I have a closed
form but also seem very constrained
because every closed form I can write it
out you know the the geometries look
very very regular. So if I want to
represent the shape of a cow, you know,
how would I represent that? What would
be the function I can write for the
shape of a cow? It's just not obvious.
But nice thing about implicit
representation is you don't have to
write everything in one shot because
it's so easy to compose them, right? You
can actually perform logical operations
on these implicit functions. Let's say
you have two objects and you find the
unions or intersections or differences.
You know, you can again they're just
values, right? So you put XYZ onto this
function, you get a value. You put XYZ
onto that function, you get a value. You
can just do you know arithmetic
operations on top of these values and
that allows you to compute the unions or
intersections or differences between
these objects and eventually you can
compose them to uh develop pretty
complex shapes and this is actually you
know behind uh support a lot of these
industrial designs when people are
designing you know complex parts uh for
you know I would say uh I don't know I
mean when you're doing manufacturing on
a on you have a you have to fabricate
some complex shapes a lot of these
designs are done by these kind of cat
models, computer AD designs and they're
composing these implicit functions using
simple logical operations
and you know you can also do things that
beyond just logical you can even add
things up especially if you have a
distance function where every point is
sort of like oh um the positive value
and the negative value the values
actually have meanings because they
indicate how far you are to the surface
of object. So you can even add them up
and this allows you to just smoothly
blend the shapes. Right? So you can see
that here you know if I have a distance
function and here I just want to
represent a vertical line. Okay this is
here and then anything that's minus zero
is to the left of the line anything that
is positive is to the right of the line
and then you have another line
represented using different function you
know. So what happens if you add them
up? You know, if you add them up, then
it naturally becomes an interpolation
between these two shapes, right? This is
example of doing things in 1D. But you
can imagine, you know, you can even
similar doing things in 3D in a sense.
Okay, now you can actually even blend
the these different shapes and these
distance functions can be arbitrary
composed and allow you to create
actually pretty complex worlds like
this. And this is not easy but you can
even you know think about you know con
you can construct really complex with
all the details worlds uh by just simply
not simply by difficulty but compose
these different functions but they are
actually very expressive if you're very
good at it.
Okay. Um so we said okay we have
parametric representation that can be
explicit that directly give you points
on 3D surface or we can have parametric
representations like these functions but
they're implicit right? So they're just
like okay now you can only try to verify
if the point is inside and outside an
object but then you can also compose
them to build more complex shapes and is
that possible for us to also have
implicit repetition and nonparametric
like like point style but then you also
querying functions or sometimes they
actually do have things like that and
this eventually goes to methods like
level set methods right so implicit
surfaces are very nice because as we
said it's easy to merge them it's easy
to split them but sometimes you know
it's hard to describe as we said a
complex shapes in closed forms Right?
You have a cow. How would you represent
it? Okay, you can compose them. But you
know if every time I have to query
whether whether a certain point is
inside a cow, you have to have hundreds
of functions and you perform all these
add and or plus minus operations, then
it takes a long time. So what if I just
pre-query, right? So I have I have a I
have a 3D space and I just sample let's
say a 100 by 100 by 100 grid, right? So
any I have now a million points
pre-sampled and for these 1 million
points I just premputee whether they're
inside the objects or outside the
objects. What is the distance of these 1
million points to the surfaces for
complex shapes? So you can premputee
them and then you can store all the
values in a matrix. This is in 2D but
you can this is for visualization but in
practice is in 3D right? So you have a
you have a 3D matrix that store all
these precomputed values of the distance
functions. So now you're sort of in some
you still have implicit representations
but be because you have pre-qui them you
you turn it into a nonparametric
representations and even if you just
look at this matrix right in 2D you can
now still find okay where the boundaries
are so where are the boundaries they're
just basically where you know you have
two adjacent values one is positive and
one is negative right so that means
there must be somewhere in between that
uh the point here they satisfy the
function fx equals z which means means
the point must be on the surface. Right?
So in that sense you're sort of turning
an parametric representation which are
implicit into a nonparametric
representations by pre-quaring a lot of
these points using the functions and
this allows you to have actually more
explicit controls because you know you
can now visualize them. You can say I
have this matrix and I can visualize
them based on their values. And this is
used a lot in things like uh uh CTS and
MRIs and all these like medical data.
And a related thing is people may say
okay what if I don't care about all
these distance values you know I can
pre-query what's going on at all these
points but then I compute all the
values. Let's say plus five minus five
but all I care about is whether this is
inside object or outside object. Right?
So if it's positive I'll just treat them
as one. If it's negative which means
they're inside object treat them as
zero. Let's say so if you binarize them
then this give you a final
representations which is arguably the
easiest to to understand this is called
called voxels right so you know you can
pre-query where the implicit functions
are uh and then you have all these kind
of you know density sample grid and but
now instead of storing you know their
distance functions how far they are from
the surface by going through the
functions and give you plus five minus 5
you just binarize it you only care about
whether a certain point is inside
objects or outside objects then you have
a voxel representation which is again
like a 3D matrix can be 100 by 100 by
100 but for every point you have go
through this function and query whether
it's inside and outside objects you have
one or zero and you can represent
objects in a binarized way right so this
gives you the final representations I'm
going to talk about for objects in 3D
so I have introduced voxels in a kind of
complex way but from a different
perspective people may say this is
actually very easy to understand because
in some sense voxels actually have a lot
of analogy as pixel because pixels are
like 2D matrices and now you have a 3D
matrices and voxels is basically just a
3D matrix right so um although you can
see that they have connections with all
the other ways that we can represent
shapes and the way I'm introducing it
this way is you know actually when when
deep learning come in right so first
deep learning when when did it started
right 2010 you know deep learning has
been there for a long time but the more
than deep learning thing is 2010 people
started Jeff Hinton started doing that
on speech recognition And then 2012 they
have Alex net which is run on image net.
So you've learned all these and they're
all in 2D. Okay. Now people say okay
what if I want to do in 3D right? This
is a very natural thought. So I want to
go from 2D commercial networks. 2012
there's no transformer right? There's a
so how can I apply a 2D commercial
network on 3D data and everyone knows we
have all these different 3D
representations.
But which one to begin with? Right? And
it turns out that people say, "Okay,
yeah, you know, the people who started
doing uh deep learning on your data,
they're the computer vision people.
They're not like the graphics people.
They're like, I've been working with
pixels and maybe the easiest thing I can
do is just to, you know, scale up and
instead of working on 2D matrices, I
just make it work on 3D matrices." So
that would be the simplest thing I can
do. Instead of having a 2D convolution
in your network, I have a volumetric
convolution in your network. Then which
of these representations allow you or
support a volumetric convolution? Right?
It turned out to be this box of
representation. This is this is
basically the the easiest you can
imagine, right? So, but the graphics
people do not agree with that because
the graphics people are like, "Oh, this
box representation is really bad because
it's uh it's very slow to compute as you
as we talked about. We have to
pre-sample all these values and there
you know you can look at the quality
right is so bad compared with meshes or
point clouds." So, people like you know
why do you want to start with that? But
the reason that people started doing
deep learning on 3D data with voxels
because I think it's like you just it's
so easy to draw an analogy between
pixels and voxels and and you just have
to change one type of code that is
instead of doing 2D convolution now do
3D convolution right so that's sort of
in some sense how things get started
okay but before I talk about the
different methods for 3D uh data another
aspect that's very important is the data
uh sorry for 3D yeah so beyond methods
data sets are also very important you
know image net really prompted annex and
stuff like that so for 3D similarly you
know, we have to collect a lot of data
as well. So, preDep learning, um, the
common data set, the popular data set
people often use is this thing called
Princeton data shape benchmark, which
has 1,800 models, 180 categories. So,
you can see they actually have quite a
lot of categories, 180 categories, but
there are only 1,800 models, which means
there are like basically 10 models per
hydrator, which is so small, but back
then it was considered pretty large, and
people feel like, oh, this is already
enough to do because we can't really
make any of things really work well on
them. Um and there was very little
machine learning there. Um so prior to
2014 you know all these data sets are
kind of more or less small. You know
they may have a certain number of models
even up to 10,000 9,000 10,000 but you
know they also divided into so many
different classes and so each class you
only have like 10 models each or less
than 100 I would say. Um so after that
people started by saying okay if we have
image net we also have the 3D data sets
for shapes. So this is uh behind efforts
of a few concurrent work but really I
think eventually they sort of
consolidated into this thing called
shapenet which is a lot of them are
actually led by Stanford you know
there's Leo Gibbus and Sylvio Sarasi um
so they led this kind of large data sets
called shapenet which has three million
models and so but in practice just like
image net you have this large image and
there's a smaller data set that people
often use. So shapeet similarly you have
a shapeet core data set which is what
people typically use as 50 basically
50,000 models in 55 categories now you
can see for every category you have
1,000 models on average but in practice
it's not that balanced so for chairs you
have actually a lot more so that's why
you know people say oh now I have
finally I have thousands of models on
chairs I can train some deep networks on
it right before it just you have 10
models you can't do anything so that is
how things started and uh so there has
been a few years where a lot of these
advances and all the results are just
present on chairs and cars because these
are like the largest categories in
shapeet and people feel like okay that's
great but then that's not enough so we
should uh move you know even bigger so
in the past few years uh this is work at
AI2 the island institute from Seattle
where what they did is they collected
much larger data sets called obverse and
objiverse extra large that you have
roughly 1 million or 10 million uh
models uh for different 3D assets you
can see they have much more categories
uh and they also have these models on
average also are have higher quality
also with textures.
So these are entire data sets but also
there are real data sets that are being
produced including you know some some of
them are from like 3D scans you know you
just take uh 3D scanners back in 2016
people have been working on it this is a
data set uh called I think the redwood
data set or something so you have like
10,000 scans of real world objects
and more recently you know people have
been building larger data sets where
they also encourage people I think this
is effort collab by Meta and Oxford
heard. Um, so they encourage people to
take data for them. Uh, they also pay
people to take data for them. So people
just use it on iPhone. You you have an
object, you put it on a table, you use
an iPhone, you take a 360 video around
objects and then you get $1 or something
like that. Um, so they encourage people
to take data for them. This is the first
version. They have 19,000 videos of
objects. Now these are like real
objects, right? Because capturing real
objects is much harder and the object
version and all the things I talked
about before it was like synced objects,
but these are like real objects. And
then uh also because of a lot of the
development in 3D vision algorithms, you
can actually take these 360 videos and
trying to reconstruct uh the 3D objects.
So now you have paired data of the
videos or images of objects as well as
their 3D geometries and textures.
This is their first version. I think
they have a more recent version V2 or
maybe even V3 right now which is
supposed to be a little larger but still
it's kind of hard to scale up. Think
about it right now you have like 90,000
videos or basically 19,000 objects and I
think they're scaling it up but I don't
think it's over 100,000. So basically
you can think about it as for real
objects you have like 100,000 models and
but if you look at what's the data set
size of the images right so it's like I
know line on 5B or whatever that's like
5 billion images and Google and open
must have much larger data sets so
there's still kind of a huge gap between
number of data points that you can have
for 2D images or videos versus you can
have for 3D objects so I think that's a
kind of a big challenge you know how we
can move forward with 3D vision and
people have different ideas uh but still
you know this is much larger than what
we had before at least you can you know
it's possible that you can still more or
less train some deep learning models on
these data sets now
and quickly there are also other data
sets of people being built on parts and
this is also from Stanford where they
try to annotate a little bit of object
parts and their correspondence and
hierarchies
um and you know their uh and also uh
there's this this data set called
partnet where they want to annotate not
only the parts and their semantics but
also how they may move also a little bit
of mo mobility information of different
parts like laptop you can open and close
it and there also data sets for 3D
scenes so not only just objects and
parts but they're also the the rooms um
so they're having things like the scan
data sets like you know um this are
people actually just go inside your home
or go inside to actually to our office
as well this come and then they just
have a 3D scanner they scan home and
then they have some annotations so you
know here
know and more recently again you can use
you can do that even with your iPhone
right now but still um these kind of
data sets are much smaller right so here
this one the first version of scanner
you have 1,500 I think they have a plus+
the second version which is roughly the
same size maybe 2,000 or 3,000 rooms so
the amount of data you have for 3D data
uh for 3D scenes in particular is also
you know even much smaller than the
amount of data you have for 3D objects
um so I I think it's not obvious that
how can we go beyond that constraints
because if you have to scan it yourself
you're always bounded by how much time
you have and how much people you
Um
anyway, but you know there there are
attempts being made in trying to collect
data
okay and finally uh if want to apply
deep learning on to 3D vision so what
are the tasks we care about right so
there are generative modeling just like
in generative just like what Justin said
you can generate 2D images or videos um
you can also generate 3D shapes you can
generate 3D scenes you can make them
condition right the condition can be
condition on language conditional image.
You have an input image and how can you
reconstruct the 3D objects and you have
to learn the shape priors. You have to
do shape generation completion.
Sometimes you have a partial objects and
you want to you know repair it. You want
to fix it. So there's geometry data
processing as well. Other tasks
including discriminative uh models for
example you have a 3D shape. How can you
classify what's the category of objects
it belongs to? Is it a chair or a table?
and a lot of them and now actually done
them by rendering them into pixels right
because you have very good you know
image recognition models like GPT or
something right so you just take a 3D
object you can render them into a
picture you can upload a picture to GPT
and they can do it for you right so
that's in some sense one way of solving
these discriminative problems uh but
there are also more specific things that
is not very easy to solve you know for
example you have a different type of
cell and you have the 3D scans and how
can you classify the cell and all these
kind of more specialized domains where
you don't have that much data So how can
you solve these discriminative problems
and uh join modeling of 2D and 3D data
which is becoming more and more
important because the 2D data we have so
much more we have so many images and
videos we have very good foundation
models that got trained on them. So how
can we leverage the priors in our 2D
foundation models like what an image
look like? How to make an image look
like look realistic? How to make a video
look realistic? How can we use that
information to help our 3D
reconstruction to be more realistic?
Right? So joint modeling and 2D and 3D
data because there are so many large
scale 2D data sets and very good
training models and also there has been
a lot of advances in uh neural rendering
or differential rendering methods that
basically connect 3D world and 2D world
because you have 3D world you have 3D
model you can render them into 2D the
rendering process you know can be made
differentiable or can be even
approximated with neuronet networks then
now you can connect all these data in
different modalities through
differentable neural networks allows you
to bridge the prior you have in 2D data
or 2D foundation models into the 3D
world.
Yeah. And then you know sometimes you
want to even do some joint multim model
beyond visual data including textile
data but sometimes you have other data.
Let's say in robotics you often have
tactile data. So how to fuse them as
well? And sometimes for autonomous
driving you know maybe you have lighter
data or depth data. How can you fuse
them as well? So we want to use deep
learning on 3D data to solve all these
different problems. So we spend all the
time talking about representation. So
how do we begin with? So as I suggested
you know people who are initially doing
that is the computer vision people do
they work on pixels they work on images.
So naturally they say why don't we start
with voxels but even before that they
say okay this is the old idea and this
is the very first idea that people tried
in applying deep learning to 3D vision
and now in some sense it's coming back
but the very first idea they tried is
you know let's don't even worry about
voxels let's just say you have a 3D
shape you know it's a mesh it's a voxel
whatever you know I want to uh learn to
recognize what an object is right what
is the object here is a chair but what
if the input is 3D data how can we
process that before we have a 3D deep
learning methods. What if I just render
into images because I have very good
image models. I'll just you know render
I just take the 3D objects. I would just
put camera at different places. I can
render all these images the objects from
different views and then now this
becomes a 2D problem. I would just apply
a commercial neuron network you know on
each of these views and I have some ways
of fuse them right. So I have some
pooling whatever uh and then I just do
an image classification you know. So
this becomes an image classification
problem while the only difference being
now you have multiple views right so
this is like in some one of the very
first idea people apply to 3D vision
they just use 2D networks and why do you
want to use 2D networks because back
then they're approaching on image net
and they're very good um so they have
image net is much larger than 3D data
sets so any model that approaching on
image net they have very good
performance so the easiest way to solve
your 3D recognition problem is to first
render into 2D
later people sort of move away from it
because people like oh you know we have
more 3D data we should try to do 3D
native come up with 3D native methods
and people also you know come up with
ideas about connecting 3D and 2D through
like newer rendering but now I feel like
this trend is coming back because you
know all these image and video models
are getting so great I don't know many
of you may have seen like the V3
whatever was released yesterday right so
if they're so great you know maybe we
should just rely a bit more on the image
and video foundation models again
because they they just train on you know
a thousand times or tens of thousands
times or even more than and maybe a
million times more data than 3D data. So
how can we incorporate that? But I
anyway coming back now this is the very
first methods in some sense people try
to apply deep learning on 3D data just
by converting them into 2D and they do
very well in image shape classification
you have shapes and you want to classify
them into different categories and they
have very good performance. Um and yeah
so you can leverage you know a lot of
literatures on 2D image models. Um, but
the issue is you need some projections.
Um, but sometimes, you know, the input
can be very noisy. People like, what if
my input is too noisy? The point clouds
or whatever, they're just not very good.
If I render them, they look kind of bad.
Um, so is that possible for us to come
up with more 3D native methods? So later
people tried a number of 3D native
methods uh that just apply deep learning
directly on 3D data. As I said, the
easiest way to do this is just to apply
your uh pixel connection
network. So this is actually a deep
belief network which is generated
network. Uh but still you know you have
some 3D convolutional uh features and
this is in 2015 uh by Princeton and you
can see that they learn gen model that
can actually synthesize 3D shapes in
form of in the form of 3D box at
relatively lower resolution. Uh but you
know this is 10 years ago now. So back
then this is considered kind of pretty
impressive
and you can do all these condition
generations condition on uh semantic
labels at bats and a desk and tables.
You can singleize these different shapes
and because this is a generative network
you can also use it for classification.
Um so you can do image shape
classification as well.
And later um something that actually we
did is you know what if we just applied
against this generative server. Now you
can use scans to generate 2D pixels.
There's no reason you cannot use GANs to
generate 3D box. So we just this this
very simple thing and that is apply
again to 3D box and actually give you a
pretty good generation of uh 3D objects.
This is eight nine years ago. Yeah.
Yeah. Okay.
And um later uh with Chyen from CMU we
also did an extension that is you can
use GANs to not only generate 3D shapes
but also you can render them into 2D you
can project them into 2D surfaces u so
that you can get the depth map of the 2D
objects you 3D objects you generated and
then you can use a cycle GAN uh to
convert this depth map into a color um
color image. Now you can have adversary
losses not only on 3D shapes but also on
2D pictures, right? You want the 3D
shapes to look realistic so that they
can be indisting indistinguishable from
the 3D object data you have. You also
want the 2D images to look realistic so
that they're indistinguishable from
images of real cars. Um so then you can
do 3D generation as well as 2D
generation at the same time. And because
you have you know different latent
vectors for the shapes for the
viewpoints and for the textures you also
have some level of controllability like
you can change the viewpoint you can
change the textures you can do
interpolation and you can you know uh
transfer the texture of one car onto the
shape of another car you know this is
so people tried applying deep networks
like neural networks gener networks on
3D voxels instead of 2D pixels
And can we do a little bit better with
box holes? Because one thing that people
have complained about vox holes is
they're just like really slow, right?
You have to presample them and there are
a lot of wasted effort because a lot of
sample points just like empty space or
they're inside object and g give you no
information. So naturally people thought
okay can we actually make it better? So
there are improvements to voxels like
octtop trees. The idea of octtop trees
is you still have explicit
representations. Um sorry in some sense
you can argue it's implicit
representation but it's like
nonparametric implicit representations.
Uh but then instead of representing
every spa uh every point in the space at
a at a at a uniform scale right you
actually you know um assuming uh the
voxels or yeah basically the voxels can
be of different sizes you know I just
divide the space into like different
regions and I spin a lot more when I
feel like I'm really close to the
surface objects I just represent objects
in a much finer scale and when I'm like
in this empty space or inside objects
where I really don't care too much about
what's going on I just I can have like
huge voxels in some sense, right? So you
can recursively partition the space and
you can have, you know, different sizes
of voxels at different space and this
allows you to really scale up. Um, so
you can see that compared with just
directly using voxels, you know, this is
2019ish. You know, people say, okay,
octave trees are great because allows me
to go from lower resolution. That's how
much you can fit into GPU memory, right?
You can do 64 x 64 with voxels, but with
oct trees, you can do 256, right? So,
and you can even use that for generation
as well. You can generate objects also,
you know, they look like voxels, but
they're kind of higher resolution
because you're more efficient in
representing the space. So, these are
like the very early attempts in applying
deep learning to each space and they're
like, okay, why don't we just try
voxels?
Then this is the moment where people
have get a bit more interest into like,
oh, now what if you know uh um the
graphics people feel like, you know,
you're just doing all this wrong, right?
Because why do why do you want to use
these kind of pretty inefficient ugly
looking representations like voxels or
octtop trees? Now we have all these good
representations point clouds meshes
splines you know why are we not using
these representations but as we said the
challenge is you know point here and
there right how can you even apply
convolution on points and stuff like
that it's not just not very obvious but
people start to look into it so
naturally people move into you know
applying or developing new deep learning
methods that directly work on uh not
only just 3D data but also different
type of 3D representations like point
clouds so in point I think this is an
important work also from Stanford uh
from Leo's team. Um what's going on here
is they develop a new type of deep
network that direct work with 3D point
clouds. So it's called pointet. Um so
the idea is you know for points you have
to be permutationally invariant right
because you know if I have point one and
point 2 okay like 0.1 is here and point
2 is here okay now I have a you know
different input I would say 0.1 here and
point two there right so then you know
whatever your network should be
environment to these different two types
of input which means you know no matter
I ne I name this one is 0.1 that one's
point 2 or I name this one's point 2 one
this that one's point 2 your output
should be the Right? Because there's no
the points they're like kind of
unordered. There's no guaranteed
ordering in the sense our top left is
one one bottom right is 100 100. Right?
So if there's unorder if the points are
unordered you have to be permutitional
environment. So how can we do that
and second is you have to be also
sampling environment. Um so you know
sometimes you sample like say uh 10
points on the on the head of the b the
bunny or a rabbit and five points on the
tail of the rabbit and sometimes you
sample 10 points on the tail of the
rabbit only five points on the head of
of the rabbit right so how can also be
invarant to that right because there's
no guarantee on how you sample points so
they're kind of a bit of a issue here
and there um but the one idea they they
imply they they used uh and I think it's
basically probably the most important
point at is they just you know I just
apply It's also so simple. I just apply
a symmetric function on the embeddings
of the points. So basically, you know,
for all the points, you know, I first
compute some embeddings for them just
like you will compute uh embings for
different regions or different windows
of image and I compute the features for
each point and then I just have to fuse
them. But because I want them to be
permutational environment, right? So I I
just use a symmetric function in a sense
that for example, it can be just a max
function and then I take the maximum
soft max. It can also be a sum function.
I just add them up, you know. So that's
what's going on. This is so simple. You
have a you have a number of points 1 2 3
1 and then you have computer embeddings
for them. And they just aggregate them.
You can say you compute the max for each
dimension. You can sum them up or stuff
like that. And yeah, and then you have
this aggregated embeddings for all the
points and then you go through maybe a
few layers of fully connected networks
or stuff like that. and then you use it
to uh classify you know oh are these
points really representing a chair or a
table
so that's basically what's going on and
uh it turned out to be quite powerful
and of course there have been a lot of
the uh I would say improvements on top
of that people have been coming up with
new methods that improve on point they
have they have point plus and there are
things like people have been trying to
do is like graph neuron networks because
you can easily translate points into
nodes of a graph and then the the
neighborhood you know the proximity
whether two point points are close to
each other as the edges connecting these
points. So there have been like graph
neural networks and all these other
methods that have been developed for
these uh point point cloud processing
but you know the original idea in the uh
point paper is kind of so simple and
turned out to be also very powerful.
Something else you want to consider is
you also want to measure you know for
pixels it's easy I have an output image
I have the ground truth image I just
compute differences between the two I
have out two loss or whatever for points
how would you compare the output point
cloud and input point cloud right
especially if you care about generation
task if you do a classification that's
fine you have input point cloud and
output is uh you know chair table
whatever you have a cross entropy loss
that's that's all you need but if you
output if if you're doing a generation
task you have a box it's also easy right
just do a cross entropy loss of the you
know 100 by 100 by 100 voxal grid but if
your output is a point 100 points and
how would you compare uh the output
point cloud versus the ground truth
point cloud you have to also design
distance metrics so the common the two
common distance metrics that people did
use one is called the chamfer distance a
chamfer distance is easy to understand
that is you have two set of points and
for each point on each side or each set
you just basically find the nearest
neighbor right so you have a collection
of red points you have a collection of
blue points And for the red point, for
each of the red point, you just find its
nearest neighbor in the blue set. And
for each of the blue points, you just
find the nearest neighbor in the red
set. And you want to minimize the
distance, you know, minimize the
distance of each point to its nearest
neighbor in the other set. And the
second idea loss function that people
may use is called earth move distance.
And here you do a bipartite matching
between the two set of points. And you
have a onetoone paired matching between
these points. And you want to minimize
distance uh among all these pairs. So
these are the two common metrics that
people use when they're comparing the
distance between the point clouds and
they can be made differentiable which
means you can now computer gradients and
use it to op optimize your neuron
network so that hopefully they you know
output better point clouds if you're
caring about a point cloud generation
problem.
Um so we have moved from uh vauels to
point clouds and then people are like
okay this is great and now I can process
the points I can output points but we
also have other you know beautiful
repartitions like uh splines you know
they're very good at capturing the
surfaces of objects if if you use any
kind of neuron network to generate
voxels or generate point clouds they
always look very ugly right so they
don't have smooth surfaces and stuff
like that so how can we have a neuronet
network that can output or understand
objects but also represent the beautiful
surfaces
So people go a bit forward and think
about how I can integrate neural
networks with things like splines or
functions like that. And a notable
example here is the thing called atlet.
So what's going on here is they try to
use deep learning uh but then instead of
you know directly outputting a set of 3D
point clouds right. So I learn a
transformation function. You know I have
a latent shape representations and then
you know if you remember right when we
say you have these parametric
representation of object shapes you're
basically transforming let's say a 2D
space of U and V into a 3D space like a
sphere. So and you know for simple
things like sphere it's easy you can
write it down right what is that
function uh and s cosine whatever uh but
for complex objects it is very hard to
write a function and often there's no
closed form. So the idea here is okay if
there's no closed form then why don't we
just use a neuron network to represent
that right so here you can see this
neuron network which is repres
implemented as MLP just learns that
function f right you can take the two
values u and v as the input to the
function f and the neuronet networks is
performing the computation of that
function f and u and v and output a
point in the 3D space so it's basically
learning how we are able to transform
this comput space into the 3D case and
it might be too hard uh to represent the
entire object using a single
transformation. So people thought okay
we can use a couple of small neuron
networks. So think about it as now you
have a piece of paper you can fold it in
different ways and you can fold it
multiple times and all these things get
put together uh to form the final shapes
you care about right so this is you can
see the differences between these two
three different representations you have
input image and if you want to represent
a reconstruct using voxels you can see
it's it's doing something but you're
really bounded by limited resolution
voxels and for point clouds you know
yeah you're no longer bounded by the
resolutions and it give maybe a bit more
details but points are really unordered.
you cannot really get any smooth
surfaces out of the point clouds and for
this thing called island net which is
basically learning transform pieces you
can see that they have actually smoother
surfaces right so using new and to
represent how you can map a parametric
representations from lower dimensional
space to a higher dimension higher
dimensional space and you learn multiple
of these mappings and when they're
combined that give you the final output
geometries conditional 2D images
okay Uh so finally you know
uh
no in some sense
we can put it this way right so what is
um what is deep network doing when
they're doing image classification right
they're basically learning a very
complex functions that map uh input
images in the form of pixels into a
final category label is it a cat or a
dog or person or whatever that function
is really complex and output Output
space is really small. Output space is
like, you know, 1,000 dimensions, right?
So it's like, okay, it's a cat or dog.
You have 1,000 with classification.
Output space is so small. Input space is
much larger because you have, you know,
500 by 500 pixels. So it's that's
250,000 or something, right? The input
space is much larger. Output space is
really small. The function is really
hard to to to write. You know, I how can
you can you is it possible for me to
write down some formulas so that I can
classify the input image uh by computing
whatever some specific values and output
if this is a cat or a dog? I cannot do
that right a function is so hard to
write there's no closed form that's why
you need a deep network input space is
large output space is small so if you
really think about deep networks that
way and think about what they are doing
then you realize you know a lot of the
things that we have doing with deep
networks on 3D shapes it doesn't seem to
map that you know map into that you know
I would say equation right so it doesn't
map that well and what are the
representations that really map them map
it the best right what's the optimal
representations that seems to really fit
into the paradigm
And if we think more carefully I think
around 2019 and people realize oh yeah
you know in some sense deep network is
implicit function and why don't we just
use it to represent an implicit function
for object 3D geometry right so instead
of representing the kind of voxels
because now you're just doing you know
you you turn it into pixels and you but
then you just scale up into 3D and you
apply 3D convolution okay but you know
fundamentally voxil is really about you
know whether this thing is inside and
outside object so instead of just
directly
pre-quing the space and get the voxels
and apply convolution on top of it. what
if I just directly using deep network to
perform that query for me so that I
don't have to run 3D conversion or
anything you know I just query a space
in 3D and deep network should tell me
you know if in the output can just be
one dimensional you know inside and
outside right whether that point is
inside a sweet shape or outside the 3D
shape
so finally I think people move that leap
you know take the leap to go from uh
explicit representations on point cows
or splines into implicit repetitions but
not directly working on voxels but
instead that you know think about it as
a level set or or or some implicit
functions that use deep number to
represent you know that's the final step
right going from this uh atlas now
whatever you're learning that trans
transformation from a from a 2D space to
the 3D space but now I can directly do
implicit query using the deep networks
so that goes through deep implicit
functions where which is kind of
interesting because around that time in
2019 there are like four papers that are
doing almost exactly the same thing you
know they all argue that before we have
been using voxels and point calls and
matches or whatever they have their own
strengths or weakness but really the
right thing to do is I should just send
you know the query into deep network so
deep what it should do is it should take
the input let's say xyz coordinate and
output whether that point is inside and
outside object you know and that will be
in some sense the the final I would say
one of the final and that's the kind of
idea that has been that was proposed in
2019 and even right now 2025 right a lot
of people has been still using this kind
of same idea
that is I'll just use deep network to
tell me whether a point is inside
outside object and not only you can go a
little bit beyond than just like a
binary classification of inside outside
because you can also say oh maybe I care
a bit more I say what will be the sign
distance function how far the point is
from the from the surface of the object
or what will be the density values of
the of the point or later what will be
the color what will be the radiance
values of of the point right but here
starting from 2019 people really start
to you know apply deep network in a way
that is in something similar to
classification that is I take points in
3D space and use it as implicit function
to query you know some properties of the
points in the 3D space
and you know people have tried to use it
as you know represent a collection of
implicit functions not just like how
pieces are deforming into the 3D space
to get different pieces of papers in 3D
but really representing implicit parts
of the objects using small neural
networks and they can form a complex
shapes uh and you know If you can rent
represent objects in 3D uh using
implicit functions uh you can do that
not only for geometry you can query not
only the inside whether a point is
inside outside objects whether how far
the point is from the surface of the
object you can also query what will be
the radiance what will be the color of
object and then I go there actually one
year later this is maybe one or two year
later no people come up with this thing
called nerf right so where they used
differences here is now say oh I I I
should use deep network knowledge to
query what will be uh the sign distance
function or density of the objects but
also quering the radiance. Um so here
you can see what's going on is you query
nerf about xyz coordinate in the 3D
space. In addition to that, because
you're trying to model the appearance as
well, you also query the viewing
directions, right? The camera viewing
directions and the output of the neuron
network is not just like one or zero
inside outside. It is uh the density
values in addition to the color values,
right? The radiance and you know if you
directly train uh implicit functions on
3D shapes and then you require 3D
supervision, right? So you know if you
have a collection of 3D objects you can
use them as a supervision that give you
okay you know ground you know you have
the ground truth about whether a point
is inside outside a 3D object but here
you know uh you want to train on 2D
images that's what's going on with nerf
so they also put that together with a
newer rendering uh volume rendering
function and they made this volume
rendering function differentiable in the
sense that you can have a rendering
model uh you can query all these
different points in a 3D space you can
get their colors and also their
densities and appearances
And then you can compute in how much
light is blocked along the way. Right?
So this is basically volume rendering as
in computer graphics. Uh there's
there's very minimally changed made
because you can see even directly from
the volume rendering equations that
everything here is you know this is
approximation but with the approximation
everything here is sort of
differentiable. So you can compute you
know how much light you know if you have
if the neural network gives you the
density which is basically you can think
about as opacity of the point in 3D
space and also give you the color then
you can compute you know how much light
has been blocked by the points I sampled
ahead of that ahead of that point and
along the ray and you can compute also
you know how much light is there
contributing to what I'm going to see in
this ray from any particular point right
so now you have a few things you have
new number to represent implicit
functions for colors or radians and and
densities and then you have this volume
rendering equations which is made
differentiable so that you can learn
directly from 2D images. So these are
the two things I have changed and one is
I no longer have to train on 3D shapes I
can train on 2D images with this volume
render equations and the second is
instead of just looking into geometry or
density of objects in the 3D I also look
into their radiance or appearance in 3D
right so these two changes lead to this
kind of big jump uh behind you know from
nerf or implic from implicit functions
deep SDF and all these earlier methods
to nerf so a lot of people feel like
okay yeah nerf has been great and seems
out of nowhere. That's really not the
case because, you know, they're very
much inspired if you look at the
articles they later wrote themselves.
Um, you know, they're very much inspired
by all these advances in deep in
functions. Although they focus only on
geometry, but now I do both geometry and
appearance and I do learning from 2D
images instead of 3D shapes. Um, so
yeah, here are some results of Nerf. Uh,
this you may have seen many times.
Um
okay so if you remember we said you know
in the past we have been working on
something like generating a 3D shapes
and then uh also generating their 2D
appearances. Uh here at the very
beginning we use the representations
that is voxels. Um but now as we said
yeah nerf is great and if we have
implicit representations there's no need
to really represent it as a voxels. What
if we just replace that with a with a
with a radiance fields right? So we also
did that as well. So we have a neuron
network that capture the implicit
radiance fields and densities but it is
generative neuron network and then you
can even still apply the same GAN
rendering framework so that you can
render objects in 3D as well as their 2D
uh pictures and then you can also do the
same as controllability and you know you
can you can change the you can change
the camera viewpoint you can change
object identity but then you can keep
the viewpoint you can do all these
things as we can do before but now with
nerf you can learn directly from images.
uh so you don't have to restrict
yourself to the categories of cars or
chairs where you have a lot of 3D 3D
data because you can learn directly from
images and yeah so you can see that now
the output becomes much more realistic
so this is the thing we did called pyan
with uh Eric Chen as a first author and
also with uh mostly people from Gordon's
group
okay and finally you know nerf is great
but then Nerf has this issue do that is
you know you have to sample a lot of
points in 3D you know you you're no
longer pre-sampling them and then
applying a volumetric convolution but
still just like a level set right you
have to sample all the points and
current neon all the time and now you
can do it learning from 2D uh you can do
all these great things but because you
still have to do all these sampling but
it's very slow so people thought it a
bit more again from the graphics people
they're like okay I have this good idea
about points and meshes and the nice
thing about them is they're free in
space they're very efficient uh so it's
possible for us to integrate it to can I
have implicit representations but maybe
I don't have to have a fixed sampling
grid I don't have to sample all the at
times because they take so much time so
maybe I really should put them together
right so you can argue that nip nerf try
to parameterize densities uh sorry
parameterize the scenes very very
densely you have to sample all the
points densely in 3D
um a lot of points are wasted just like
in voxels you know you have all the
points that are representing empty space
you don't want that in nerf a lot of
samplings a All the queries are also
querying empty space and network may
give you like density of zero or
something like that but it's taking a
lot of time so how can we address that
um you know what if I just try to sample
things more sparsely right I still have
this implicit representations but
instead of you know uh you know sampling
empty spaces all the time I only sample
at places where I know there are stuff
but how can I know that you know if I
what if I have a point representations
so this is the idea behind this thing
called Gaussian spats which you may have
heard of. So it still has the same
implicitive functions, you're acquiring
new network for densities and for
appearance and stuff like that, but
instead of quiring new network all the
time, I have a point representation. I
have these 3D Gaussian blobs in the 3D
space, which I think sometimes you can
think about them as point clouds, but
the points are not like a single point.
They're they're like a blob. They're
like some regions. uh and uh because you
know where these blobs are, you know,
when you're sending out array from your
camera to the 3D space and sample
points, you don't have to sample all the
time. You just look at all where these
blobs are and then you can know based on
their um the the radius of these
different galaxies. You will only sample
at regions where you know there's some
stuff. Uh so this makes rendering much
more efficient.
And uh so here are some of the
reconstruction results using 3D gossian
spats.
And you can see that you know in terms
of quality right they're actually you
know not that you know they're
comparable I would say they're
comparable to nerves uh this is like
different matrix PS and SSM they're like
rendering qualities and I think the
x-axis the sorry the y- axis is it
doesn't start from zero so this is a
little misleading but basically you can
see these numbers are really close so in
terms of quality rendering quality
gaussian spats and nerves are similar at
least when They're first proposed, but
Gaussian splats are just much more
efficient, right? So this is FPS, frame
per second, right? You can render 150
pictures per second. Well, for Nerf, you
know, it takes you like maybe um 20
seconds to render just a single picture,
right? So now you this thing is now made
1,000 times faster. At least that's what
they argued. So because you don't you
you no longer waste all your computing
power on simply simply empty space and
querying nerve quering your networks all
the time on these uh about these points
that are in the empty space.
Okay. Yeah. So that is basically how
deep learning has been integrated on 3D
data in all these different
representations how they got started how
they have involved and it connection
with all these uh different shape
representations. And one thing we didn't
talk about I just use two minutes to
quickly cover it is uh you know there
has been also interesting things about
object geometry that is not only about
the element geometry the specific
details about the parts but also the
structures you know because often there
could be you know the shares are
symmetric right so we talked a little
bit about it where like there's a
parametric surface and you can
parameterize part of a surface using
like a sphere or stuff like that using
these kind of closed form equations and
that give you a little bit of symmetry
but there has been also more systematic
studies about uh the regularities or
structures within object geometry
including their repetitions including
their symmetries and people also come up
with different representations for it as
well you know so you know so how can we
really represent you know in some sense
you can argue that point clouds meshes
inclive functions they're really
representing geometric details maybe for
the individual parts none of none of
them is directly capturing things like
regularities like symmetry or repetition
so how can we capture that a few other
attempts that people have been exploring
mostly from the graphics community is
you know I can represent objects just
basically as a collection of these
sample geometric parts uh like a part
set but I can and there has been methods
that apply deep learnings on it you know
representing uh using deep to represent
different parts of object using simple
geometry primitives and then compose
them or you know using implicit
functions and compose them as we talked
about before but you know there has also
been attempts to do a bit more right So
not just like representing objects as a
collection of parts without considering
their relationships but also modeling
the relationships between these parts. U
this is you know even more so the case
for for scenes let's say a bed or bed is
usually next to the wall chairs is
usually next to a tables and stuff like
that. So you not only want to represent
them as a you know unrelated collection
of parts or objects you want to capture
their relationships as well in the
hierarchies. you know when you are
constructing when you're building uh
you're doing some constructions you're
architecture uh you're architecting
design your building um then you of
course you know you're not like just
like representing objects or their
relationships you have to consider
hierarchies what you build first uh
there's a classroom and the classroom
has you know there's some tables and
chairs in it and chairs has parts
there's basically like a kind of level
hierarchy and how this can be used and
integrated with neuronet networks as
well as you know you have not only
hierarchy but also you can you can
compose hierarchies and relationships
Right? So you have a hierarchal graph
where let's say for chairs you know you
have different level hierarchy for bases
for seats for backs and the bases may
have you know different legs but then
also the legs themselves are related
right the left leg of the chair and the
right leg of the chair they're supposed
to be symmetric and they have they
should have the identical shape you
there are constraints on where these
legs are they have to be you know really
aligned otherwise the chair is going to
fall. So there are all these constraints
that are sort of you know pretty useful
and how could we represent them and
people come up with all these different
representations and for each of them
there are also you know a lot of
neuronet networks you know deep learning
method designed to learn and to capture
and to generate objects that satisfy all
these constraints. Uh for example like
you can see this is a kind of
hierarchical graph encoders and decoders
that try to uh represent and generate 3D
chairs that satisfy all these
constraints while maintaining their
hierarchies. Right? So I think this is
also from the ODUS group from 2019
and you know sometimes we can even
represent shapes using some form of
programs right because there's
repetitions and for loops and how this
can be incorporated into using neuronet
networks to generate programs that
synthesize object shapes and synize
their uh relations between these object
parts. uh and that's also an important
topic and most recently I'll say let me
end it this by saying
I think there has been a new trend just
in the past one year or two that the
deep networks or large language models
are doing so well and they understand
things so well that people are exploring
is it possible for us to just use large
language models like GPT to output these
programs right because they understand
semantics and what the tier should be
like what are the constraints the chair
should satisfy so is that possible for
me to use a large language model the
output programs but then maybe I can use
some implicitive functions or whatever
right to capture the specific geometric
details of the parts of the objects like
the chairs so there's some kind of new
emerging trend of research that is
happening right now in these days okay I
think that's all I have thank