hi everyone I'm happy to be here thank
you for the invitation and I'd like to
talk about agents for software
development uh so to give my profile uh
very quickly to kind of ground the
discussion I'm a professor at
CMU and I've been there for about eight
years working on various uh you know
research topics including the ones that
shenyun mentioned I'm also a chief
scientist at all hands AI which is a
company that started very recently
building uh open source coding agents uh
and it's a maintainer of uh software
Library called Open Hands uh which used
to be called open Devon and we are um so
a lot of my discussion and examples will
be based on this um I'm also a software
developer um I am I I like my GitHub to
be green basically so um today I'm very
happy to talk about my uh two Passions
which are research for artificial
intelligence and software development
and I get to talk about both of them in
one talk so I'm very happy to do
that so to give some grounding of this
discussion I'd first like to talk about
the importance of agents for software
development in particular and this is
from a very famous essay by Mark andreon
called why software is eating the world
um and this happened in
2011 and it basically says uh more and
more major businesses and industries are
being run on software and delivered his
online services from movies to
agriculture to National Defense over the
next 10 years I expect many more
Industries to be disrupted by software
so this was written in 2011 I I think
this mostly came true I think it would
be very weird for us to think about
movies not being delivered through
software uh like how many people have
gone and rented a physical movie in the
past like five years nobody right so uh
you can see like more and more of our
life is
uh you know happening through
software um so one of my motivating
things is if we gave everybody the
ability to quickly write software to
achieve their goals uh what would people
be able to do and I think the answer
especially for people here in you know
computer science the answer is a lot
this is also timely uh because if you
look at the Nobel Prize for physics and
the Nobel Prize for chemistry this year
T these uh two of these Nobel prizes
were awarded for people who wrote
software right and so if we think about
this this has pretty big implications
you know like it used to be that this
was given to people who were using test
tubes and running cyclotrons and other
things like this and those are still
important of course but now uh a lot
more of our science and you know human
progress is going to happen in software
I'm not just going to be talking about
models for coding today although that's
mostly what I'm going to be talking
about um but do people know how much
time the average software engineer
spends coding uh in terms of like
producing new code every
day okay it's uh it's
15% um and this is from a study in uh
from Microsoft in 2019 U maybe maybe
this is more or less nowadays but it's
not uh
just coding that people are doing um
they also do bug fix bug fixing testing
documentation and reviews um 36% of
their time is spent on communication of
some variety and 177% of the time is
spent on other things like going to the
bathroom um so another thing I'd like to
point out is how uh can we support
software uh support
developers and I I came up with a kind
of imprecise but maybe helpful
categorization of automation with
respect to things like
self-driving uh where self-driving um we
have this well-known classification of
kind of no automation to uh full
Automation and self-driving we have
manual driving at no Automation and then
we have things like adaptive cruise
control braking um Tesla's autopilot
which is at the time of writing uh was
partial automation um conditional
automation automation in certain things
and then High automation which would be
like Cru or weo self-driving
vehicles um and in terms of software
development I think there's also
different kind of levels of automation
that we could think about um where uh
zero would be just writing all your code
by hand um one is smart autocomplete
like things like co-pilot or cursor um
number two would be like co-pilot or
cursor chat uh where you kind of
refactor larger amounts of data
um conditional automation would be
automating particular tasks that people
want to do and then High automation
would be um kind of more uh autonomous
things that solve full software
development tasks and this time I want
to be uh talking about the last one but
um I think if people are familiar with
uh kind of GitHub copilot or cursor I
think this is something that a lot of
people use it's something I use every
day and basically what this is doing is
it's completing your next thought so
like as a programmer you write a few um
you write a few lines or something like
this and it goes in and like fills in
the next line for you very very useful
um I tried coding on the plane on the
way over here and I had no internet and
it was miserable so I stopped because I
you know can't code without autocomplete
anymore um but at the same time it works
synchronously with
developers the thing I'm going to talk
about more um this time is something
like a more autonomous agent so this is
an example example of our software open
hands and the way it works is you fill
in a large uh kind of uh command of what
you want to do this is uh resolving a
GitHub issue and so uh basically I told
it it needs to go into lm. and uh
essentially fix uh fix a bug in lm. so
it goes and downloads the GitHub repo um
makes additional tests oh sorry this is
not fixing a bug this is adding tests to
a file so it makes a repo it creates
some
tests uh it created them for the init
function of the llm class now it's
waiting for a little
bit um
so it created the tests now what it's
doing is it's installing the
dependencies for the
project it is running the tests
according to the directions that I gave
it um
it ran the test the test did not oh
sorry it got an error in poetry it
couldn't find the P project. tummel file
it ran the test the test works so now
it's checking out a
branch um it's committing the branch uh
add unit tests it's pushing using the
credentials that I provided
it and um now starting here this is
under human control so I I click on the
link uh that it gave to me and I open up
the the page I can review the code and
stuff like this and make sure it's okay
and not you know Incorporated if it
makes sense so I think you can see the
difference between like completion uh
just you know completing individual
tasks and actually solving tasks and
end another thing that is really popular
nowadays is uh autonomous issue
resolution and um this is another
example of autonomous issue resolution
within GitHub where you basically issue
with the words fix me the agent goes in
and does its work and if it works if the
agent decided that it did a good job it
would uh send it in a poll request so
you could go in and um and accept it or
not accept it so these are some
examples so um there's a question of how
promising this is and this is actually
old data but it's still relatively
compelling data and there was a study
where GitHub co-pilot did
a study with a sample size of 95
developers where they had some
developers use GitHub co-pilot and some
developers not use GitHub
co-pilot and 78% of the developers or 8%
more of the developers using co-pilot
finished the task and they finished it
more uh 56% faster so basically this is
doubling the speed of
coding uh for uh people people using
GitHub co-pilot versus not using
co-pilot and now we have you know even
better code completion like in my
opinion cursor code completion is better
than than gith hubs so it might be even
faster um and that means you cut into a
very big chunk of the like 15% of time
developers spend on coding which is
great like let's say we could make
developers 7% more productive um make
them enjoy coding more you know I think
uh that's wonderful but that doesn't you
know all of software development as I
mentioned before so the rest of the time
uh here I'd like to spend talking about
challenges in coding agents and um how
we evaluate coding agents and or how we
build coding agents and how we evaluate
them so some challenges that I see in
this area are number one defining an
environment that the the agents can work
in and be tested in designing a space of
observations and actions so you know
this is an agents class so I think
you're very familiar with the fact that
one of the things that defines agents is
how they can interact with the
environment so how do we Define that for
COD uh coding and software development
tasks more specifically how do we
specifically generate code like what are
the language models we use for code how
do we build
them um file localization so how do we
identify which parts of a code base that
we would want to be editing this has
parallels to rein enforcement learning
because in reinforcement learning we
have the idea of exploring our
environment and uh I think file
localization is a lot like this another
thing is planning and error recovery so
how do we make plans about what we want
to do and how do we recover from errors
and finally safety so if we're actually
interacting with environments through
software how do we ensure that this uh
happens in a safe way okay so first I'd
like to talk about software development
environments and there's a number of
types of environments if we think about
the actual environments that uh software
developers act in they can be things
like manipulating Source repositories
like uh GitHub gitlab other things like
this they can also be interacting with
task management software so this could
be things like Jura or linear or GitHub
issues or other things like this so we
would want agents to be able to do that
as well software developers also use
Office software they use like Google
Docs or Microsoft Office to you know
exchange information about requirements
and other things like this so how could
they uh how could they interact with
this
software um communication tools like
Gmail and slack so I think if I
enumerate these four tools that covers
you know most of the environments that I
interact with in some way when I'm
developing software there might be other
ones like interacting with like a server
uh logging into servers manipulating
Cloud infrastructure other stuff like
that but um these are kind of main ones
um in contrast if we look at the
environments that are available now for
testing a lot of these are focused
mostly on code on generating code um so
I'm going to mostly be talking about
these
um I'd like to note that developers do
more and they do things like browsing
the web but I'm not going to talk about
that because I know next session I think
you're having somebody uh talk about web
browsing agents so that's super
important for development but I'll not
focus on that here so the first thing uh
is simple coding and simple coding
basically what this is is it's just
testing the ability of language models
to go from a specification to code
and the most common examples of this are
things like human ofel and
mbpp and these are uh things like here
you can look at um the the problem they
have here given a non list of integers
return the Su of all of the odd elements
that are in even
positions so I think these are kind of
good uh in some way because you know you
should be able to solve these if you're
a good language model um but this is
kind of like asking leite code questions
on a coding interview right you know um
I'm sure everybody if you've done a
coding interview you've done leak code
questions and you've been thinking why
am I doing this you know like I never do
this in my everyday you know coding
experience it's testing like algorithmic
knowledge but not necessarily knowledge
of you know software development or
software
engineering
um but yeah anyway these include the
examples of usage of the Python standard
Library doc string other things like
this this is probably a necessary
condition for being a good coding model
but not a sufficient one there's also
some work on building coding benchmarks
for broader domains and both of these
are are papers that I uh I did at some
point but the first one is uh konola and
this is broader data that was scraped
from stack Overflow and so basically
what we did is we scraped uh data from
stack Overflow by getting questions from
the stack Overflow titles um context in
the code snippet that answered uh that
basically solved this
context um and originally we just
measured this uh using kind of like the
overlap between the generated code but
we also uh recently added execution
based
evaluation and this covers a relatively
wide variety of libraries that people
use in like actual uh kind of data
science uh or other things so you can
see it covers like n uh pandas numpy uh
rega OS collections other stuff like
this and that's in contrast to things
like um uh apps or human ofel or
something like that that basically use
only very standard libraries so the this
moves a Step Beyond the existing ones
and says okay can you interact with the
whole python
ecosystem another thing is data science
notebooks um and so this is another uh
this is a great paper by uh people at
Google and basically they use uh data
science notebooks to allow for um
incremental implementation in evaluation
of code in
context and so uh you have a notebook
and you have people going through the
not book and then you need to generate
the next cells based on the context you
have already so this moves you know kind
of another step adding context adding
you know practical uh long
implementations then another data set
that's um relatively recent compared to
these other ones is called sbench it's a
very popular data set uh nowadays so I
think a lot of people have heard of it
uh but the way it works is they scraped
issues uh from GitHub and the code
bases and the output of the model is a
poll
request uh so it's very similar to the
kind of situation that I talked about
before where we have agents actually go
in and and you know send a poll request
to your solve your GitHub issues but
basically here's an example uh you have
like data leak and gbdt uh due to warm
start uh this is about non- histogram
based version of Da D um you get a code
base and then you want the language
model to go in and modify a few files
and then your evaluation is measured
based on whether you can pass tests that
were introduced together with the poll
request so this is a really really nice
Benchmark in some ways um it requires
long context understanding it requires
you to understand a whole code base it
requires you to implement things in a
very precise way so that they can pass
tests um there are some problems with it
though uh so one problem
is that it's kind of limited only to
high quality repos where on PRS where
they introduced new tests and so these
are very heavily biased towards for
example bug fixing PRS they're very
heavily biased towards non-
documentation or uh non- refactoring or
other stuff like this um so it's a great
data set um and people should definitely
use it but it's it does have its
limitations in covering software
development tasks um another problem is
a lot of the data has leaked into
language models because the language
models are like trained on data from
GitHub so actually um there there's some
concerns about leakage there too so
given these environments if we look at
um how we measure success uh some of the
most common uh metrics are something
called pass it K uh so if this is
basically if we generate K examples
we'll at least one of them pass unit
tests um and uh this is a little bit of
a small detail but if you generate only
K it will result in high variance
because you might get like if you
generate only one you might get it right
like 70% of the time and wrong 30% of
the time or something like this so what
they actually do is they generate n and
then they use kind of Statistics to
figure out what it would be
itk so this is I think by far the most
common um the only disadvantage to this
is it requires unit tests so you're
limited to um doing things where you
have unit tests so there's also other
methods based on lexical or semantic
overlap and what this means is um you
basically look at how well um the
generated code overlaps with gold
standard code created by programmers and
there's a bunch of different ways to do
this um there's a method called Blue
which has been used for long time in
machine translation which basically
looks at the engram overlap between the
generated code and the uh and the
reference code and then you also have
embedding based methods uh like code
Bird score or something like this but um
these are uh these are
details so as I mentioned in sbench uh
leakage of data sets is a big problem
for things that were created on
um like public code this is nobody has
really convincingly
or no actually sorry there's a paper
very very recent called s uh sbench plus
which evaluated this on S bench but I
only learned about it since I created my
slides so um it's not on my slides but
another compelling example of this is um
in
arcade and arcade basically uh it's the
data science notebook uh problem uh data
set that I talked about before and they
demonstrated that when they evaluated on
existing data sets uh from the internet
they got kind of like scores in the the
30s or 40s but then they created new uh
new data sets uh kind of just by like
getting people at Google to create uh
data science notebooks and the accuracy
dropped by like 20% or 40% or something
like this so uh leakage is definitely a
big issue there another um example is
live codebench uh which shows that some
uh code LMS outperform on a particular
data sets uh that are very widely
benchmarked on so human ofel is a very
uh very widely used data set and so um
if you look at the scores on human Nel
on the Y AIS um and compare them to live
codebench on the xais you can see a
cluster of data sets where kind of the
scores on human ofel and the scores on
live codebench correlate and then you
can see another cluster where the scores
on human ofel are very high but the
scores on life codebench are not very
high so um these ones
are ones that maybe in some way kind of
overfit to the data set and um managed
to get a very high score on it a final
exciting direction that people are
working on recently is multimodal coding
models and there's a data set by people
at Stanford called design to code
and uh the way it works is uh they do
code generation from websites so they
have a bunch of websites that have
various uh designs uh like the ones uh
down here and based on that you need to
um they you know generate output code
and also very recently again to so
recently that I haven't been able to add
it to my slides there's a multimodal
version of sweet bench that is also
similar in that way um one interesting
thing that they do in
this data set for design to code is they
measure this the visual similarity of
the websites so they generate the
websites they take screenshots of the
websites and then they do a visual
similarity both on the high level
according to embeddings over the whole
image and then on the low level um
recalling uh each element's visual
similarity so this is kind of a
whirlwind tour of how people are
evaluating uh models in what
environments people are testing uh these
sorts of coding agents in uh so now
we'll move on to the like actual
modeling part and um I'd like to start
out by talking about observation in
action spaces and
so if we think about what coding agents
must do they must do things like uh
understand repository
structure read an existing
code modify or produce code uh in run
code and debug and this is separate from
all of the other stuff that software
Engineers do which might require web
browsing or other things like
this um and I'd like to give there's a
bunch of coding agents I'd like to give
just a few examples of the observations
and action spaces that are used in some
of the popular ones so one of the
popular uh ones that's used pretty
widely is uh one that I mentioned here
it's called Coda it's a method that
essentially interacts
with uh environments by writing code
this is also the one we use in uh in
Open Hands our coding model uh our
coding uh platform by the way um but the
way it works is traditional agents which
I I think you have probably t uh talked
about multiple times in this class
already one of the things they do is
tool use and typically when you use a
tool the idea is that at every time step
you call a tool and you get the result
back and then based on that you make the
next action so this is kind of the
traditional Paradigm and so if we look
at in example sorry this is very small
on the screen so I'll read it aloud it
says determine the most cost effective
country to purchase the smartphone model
uh Coda one the countries to consider
are the US Japan Germany and India and
so if you have these available apis um
what a traditional model would do is it
would do like lookup rates Germany it
would do look up phone price uh Germany
um convert in tax look up rates Japan
and then it would step like over and
over and over again to try to um you
know generate do all of these API calls
and you might need you know 15 API calls
before you can get the final answer uh
the idea of what Kodak uh proposed is
basically moving beyond just individual
step-by-step tool use and actually
allowing the models to act by writing
programs and if you do this um you can
essentially uh write a for Loop over all
of the countries that you're supposed to
be examining and run the for Loop and
get the answer and this doesn't mean you
can't get like intermediate feedback of
course like for example let's say this
for Loop didn't work because instead of
USA um instead of USA you would need to
write U period s period a period you
would get an error when you tried to run
the code and you could go back and
modify the code and then run it again so
you can get multi-step feedback but it's
at a much less granular level so you can
do more things in fewer
steps um in the original formulation of
this it did uh it executed batch
commands and Jupiter
commands um and they found that this
gave a faster resolution higher success
rate than direct tool
use so this kind of sets the stage for
coding agents it allows you to run bash
it allows you to generate
code but one other important thing that
we need to do is not just generate code
but actually go in and modify code
because most coding tasks or Mo like any
serious code repository you spend much
more time modifying code than you do
generating code
denovo and uhu agent which was kind of
uh the follow-up modeling work after s
bench uh basically did this by defining
specialized tools that make it possible
to efficiently explore repositories and
edit
code
so what it does is you have the LM agent
it is given a set of LM friendly
commands the LM friendly commands
interact with the computer and terminal
and file system and you get LM friendly
environmental
feedback and if you want to look at all
the details you can go through the paper
but here's uh an example
so you could get a um observation which
is uh you would get this observation
from one of the uh one of the commands
like show
file and let's say you called show file
and then uh 405 for line
405 if you do this uh basically you will
have a a program that will go in and
parse the file it will get lines from
401 to 409 because you get a window
around the file uh a window around the
line that you selected within the file
and this will be returned back to the um
back to the llm and in reality this
isn't um this isn't like four lines
above and four lines below it's actually
like 50 lines above and 50 lines below
or 100 lines above and 100 lines below
but what this allows you to do is like
even if you have files that are like
thousands of lines in your code
repository you can still par them in a
reasonable size in the llm context
window
without uh you know expending your
entire context length without spending
too much money uh other things like this
um then the basic uh response after
doing this is you get a thought so it's
like chain Chain of Thought reasoning
you get a thought about what you need to
do next and um then you need to go in
and edit um uh the files so you now call
an edit command where you edit lines 40
404 to 407 and then you have um an end
of edit uh thing here uh so then this
will edit the lines and insert this uh
this information here and there's
actually a bunch of different ways to do
this like the S uhu uh agent way is just
one way um and then there's uh there's
other ways as well uh which I'll
probably talk about a second
um So within Open Hands uh
we do something very similar it's kind
of like a combination of Coda and the S
agent uh kind of editing and obser uh
edit and observation actions so um we
execute all of the actions as calling
code so you can do something like let's
say you run an observation action or you
run a find command and you find that
there is a
a you find that there's like 10 examples
of something that you want to uh replace
in various places in your code base it
could then execute 10 of the site agent
actions and go in and replace all of the
lines in the files so this essentially
gives you a programmatic interface you
call it by calling python programs which
all LMS are very familiar with and it
allows you to do things like write a for
Loop over file editing commands and
other stuff like this um so uh that's
the general way that we uh we do this
and then you run this and then you get
um a observation from this uh that is
like the results of executing the
commands and other things like this okay
so um I've talked a little bit about the
observation in action space one really
really important thing um in order to
make these models work well is to have
good code-based LMS
um because all of the success of these
models depends on the ability to write
code um and so I'd like to talk a little
bit about the methods that people use
for uh generating uh or for creating
code-based
LMS so um yeah the basic method is you
feed in the instructions or input code
into the LM um recently virtually all
Sirius LMS are trained on code nowadays
so it doesn't matter if you're talking
about like gbt or Claud or gemini or
llama or um whatever else um but some
are more
specialized and unfortunately for closed
models and even for some open models
there's not a whole lot of information
about you know what goes into training
these models um but uh I can tell you
about some things that they definitely
are doing so the first thing that
everybody is doing is training on lots
and lots of code data um so you you know
lots of code is added to the data
mixtures this is both to improve coding
ability and because some prior research
has demonstrated that adding code
improves the reasoning ability of models
uh in
general but um just to give one example
of a coding data set that we know that's
open and has actually been used in
training open models uh this is the
stack 2 and this is a code pre-training
data set um they also looked carefully
into licensing considerations
um and the reason why is because like a
lot of code is licensed and if people
don't want you to be using the code uh
in training language models it could
theoretically cause legal problems later
so um they basically went through and
and did the license cleansing and other
stuff like this um so they checked if
the licenses are availables and other
things um and again this is really tiny
over here I'm sure you probably can't
see this on the right side of the page
well um but one interesting thing to
look at is the distribution of the
programming languages that are included
in data sets like this and the first
thing is um if you look at the largest
um number of uh data that's included in
here the data sets uh that or the
languages that are most well represented
are
python uh P PHP
markdown um JavaScript Java C++ C and C
um which is uh great you know these are
popular programming languages that a lot
of people want to work on um there's a
lot of less well represented languages
that are really important like Docker
files um you know a lot of deployment
works on doer files um I don't even see
terraform uh represented here and
terraform is like a really important
thing for deploying Cloud
infrastructure um and stuff like this so
um there's kind of a a very L difference
between the availability of data for
different programming languages another
one is cobal like nobody programs in
cobal anymore but a lot of banks have
Legacy systems written in cobal that
they would love to have you know
translated to new programming languages
and stuff so uh that that's a very low
resource so another method that's kind
of specific to code language models uh
that is really really important for code
but maybe a little bit less important
for other places is
infilling and um in code generation
because we're not generating stuff to
noo we're doing lots of editing uh we
often want to fill in uh code and so the
way that this is done is you uh can take
original documents uh like the documents
here and you can take like a coherent
section of this document and basically
mask out that section and then move that
mask zero to the end of the document and
generate the masked uh data there so
this is kind of like like a pre-training
method that people use to train models
to be good at infilling data and so this
is super important for code every code
model does this nowadays um so or every
model that seriously wants to handle
code does this nowadays so this is uh
pretty important another thing that's
done in every code model um and also
more and more models almost every model
is doing this now is some variety of
long context extension and so language
models um they it typically train on
relatively short contexts for kind of uh
efficiency reasons so they'll train on
like 4,000 token chunks when they
actually do the pre-training of the
model um
another but when you try to take the
model and generalize beyond the context
it was trained on at training time it
does a really poor job at generalizing
so um part of the reason why is because
um in Transformer models we have
positional encodings I think many people
have heard of these um but just in case
you haven't uh there are things that you
append to each token um based on the
position of the token in the sequence
and the most common variety of this is
something called rope and the way rope
works is essentially you have a Theta um
where the Theta is depends on the length
of the out output and so if you train
here you would have um 40 like let's say
you were training on 4096 context links
you would have like one half of that so
it' be 20 48 different uh kind of theta
values um but then if you expanded
beyond that you would get a whole bunch
of theta values that you've never seen
before so there's methods that fix this
um and one way they do this is by
multiplying this by a constant scaling
factor and what this does is this makes
sure that all of this the um Theta
values that you've seen before get
Scaled um in a Range that it saw at
pre-training time
and then another um method is something
called the neural neural tangent kernel
based method and basically what this
does is um these are like cosine and S
values so you have some high frequency
components and some low frequency
components and so they scale the low
frequency components but maintain the
high frequency components which makes
kind of attention over long distances
work uh you know work well but keeps the
like local context so there's a lot of
um you know a lot of examples like
this and this paper uh L at all goes
into much more detail um it's a paper on
Long context extension and I um you can
take a look so another thing I'd like to
point out is that there's lots of
context that's available for coding and
um coding models specifically like in
the co-pilot setting where you're
interacting with a model within your IDE
um pull in lots of different information
um so uh some examples of information
that you could be pulling in are things
like current coding context um the
description of an issue to fix uh
context about the repo in some way um
also open tabs in an IDE or something
like this um and so what information
should you be using to generate the next
code it depends a lot if you're working
on agents or working on code um uncode
like co-pilot style models but agents at
the moment largely use the things that
are uh kind of like in theu bench uhu
agent uh style uh style tools but
separately from this there's this really
good blog post on um deconstructing
co-pilot and what information co-pilot
is pulling in and basically the way it
works is it extracts a prompt from a
current Dock and cursor position um
identifies the relative path and
language that the model uh is occurring
in it finds the most recently accessed
20 files of the same language so if
you've been programming in Python it
will look at the most recently accessed
20 files um it includes uh text before
and text after uh the cursor um similar
files imported files metadata about the
language and path and basically long
story short they did a bunch of prompt
engineering to pull in all of the
relevant context um into the prompt and
that seems to work well for uh you know
recommending code to human coders who
are working on it I think the agent
space has not quite gone this far in
prompt engineering based on like the
current contexts and things like this so
I think that's an area for potential
improvement in our models uh going
forward so another thing I'd like to
talk about is um file localization so
file localization is a big problem it
might even be the biggest problem in
coding agents nowadays and what I mean
by this is that we want to find the
correct files given a user intent so
like let's say we have an intent that
looks like
um uh this so this is an actual example
of an issue from our repo and I think
it's a reasonably good example of kind
of the level of detail that people
actually write issues in so it says um
when in confirmation mode it's not
possible to give instructions in between
steps you have to reject an action and
it seems like it doesn't know that the
action was
rejected um and then describe the ux of
the solution that you'd like we'd like
to have a third option confirm action
and wait this action is confirmed but
before it tries to take the next step
you are able to give some feedback so
this is a feature request basically it's
a request to add like another option
that doesn't exist already but it
doesn't tell you anything about where
confirmation mode is implemented it
doesn't tell you whether this needs to
be implemented in the frontend code the
backend code or both or other things
like this and models and agents like
really struggle to do uh very well at
this um and I think like one interesting
thing is that this is analogous to like
understanding the environment in
embodied agents so like embodied agents
um let's say you have a robot that needs
to work in your kitchen or something
like this the first thing that it should
do before it starts solving any problems
that you have in your kitchen is go and
like open all the kitchen
drawers right or drawers or cabinets or
whatever else and I feel like um you
know this localization problem is kind
of that it needs to go in and either
like go in and open all the kitchen
doors or all the F the files and
understand what's going on in them or it
needs to have a really good system to
retrieve uh at retrieval
time but anyway um so solution one uh
this is offload to the user and
basically what this requires is this
requires that you have a user that's
very familiar with the capabilities of
Agents um and what they can do and how
you can uh help them out in doing their
job well which I think is reasonable if
it's somebody who interacts with agents
so this issue was written by uh me um
and I'm very familiar with like how
agents can work so I told it
specifically which files it should be
you know manipulating but this isn't you
know obviously a final solution because
not all users are like that they might
not know the code base they might know
that there's a bug but not know where
the bug what is causing the bug and
other stuff like this so this is limited
in its value even though it is helpful
in cases where it's applicable so the
next is uh to prompt the agent with
search tools and so umu agent uh is one
example of something that does this um
it provides a tool for searching
repositories and specifically this tool
is um is named search uh
so it will search for the thing that
says PV system um
and it uh as a result of that it will
list out all the files that had PV
system in them um then if it doesn't
find the thing it wants it will click
like next uh and search for the next one
um another thing is you can search and
then summarize the search results for
the agent and provide the information is
necessary so I think this is good I
think it's actually very nice for kind
of agent based systems that have uh the
ability to use tools well um but it's
not like the equivalent to going in and
opening all the cabinets uh before you
start and so there's other methods um
that do something like this so uh the
first thing is creating a map of the
repository that you're working in of the
codebase that you're working in and
prompting the agent with it so um
there's a tool that a lot of people um
it's kind of an open source tool that
people use called AER and the way ader
does this is it creates a tree
structured map of the repository a
priori the human user has the ability to
like add files to the map to make them
more prominent and then it summarizes
the map so it's a decent uh a decent
size um and then taking this a step
further there's uh a method called
agentless and this does a higher IAL
search for every issue so the way this
looks is um you essentially start out
with a project codebase you feed the
agent a very very simple tree of all of
the code that's in the codebase and this
is fed into the language
model then based on this the agent
basically will or the language model
will respond I want to open this file
and it will open all of the files and in
each of the files it will get a summary
like the methods and classes that are
implemented in that file and then after
it does that the agent then needs to
localize to specific functions it will
um say the functions it needs to edit or
modify and then those functions will be
displayed in full to the agent uh in
order for it to finally generate the
code so um this this is a pretty
effective approach um the final thing is
uh retrieval augmented code generation
and the way this works is uh you
basically retrieve similar codes so you
have like an embedding based model and
um you can fill uh feed in the retrieved
code to the model and then just generate
the
outputs um particularly in code there's
also documentation which can be
retrieved so one difficulty in uh
retrieval based code generation is that
the code itself is in Python where the
natural language description is in
English and there can be a disconnect
between the two of them and so uh
sometimes it's more effective to
directly try to retrieve the
documentation and and generate the
output based on that so there are some
references for this um my impression is
that there aren't a lot of approaches
that have really effectively used this
in the agentic setting yet um I
think people will probably be moving in
this direction and it's possible that
there's some new archive papers that
I've missed but I think leveraging this
appropriately is kind of like an
unsolved problem and uh we'll want to
work towards uh towards improving that
okay so the next thing I'd like to talk
about is planning and Air recovery so um
solving coding tasks can be difficult
and in order to solve the tasks you want
to have some concept of uh you know you
might want to have some concept of a
plan and uh keeping track of uh when
you're on track with your plan or other
things uh like this
and a lot of the
top coding models or a lot of the top
code agent models uh that have high
scores on leaderboards uh like sbench
have a hardcoded uh task completion
process and um for example agentless is
an example of this uh it's
not actually uh so much of an agent
because it mostly just goes through this
process um but it just contains two uh
three steps so file
localization um like I talked about
before it has this hierarchical
localization
process um and then function
localization it then generates patches
uh and it generates a whole bunch of
patches um runs them against uh a linter
or um runs tests against them to make
sure that they are appropriately
formatted don't have syntax errors pass
existing tests and then uh they take the
best one the one that passes the tests
and they um uh they apply it and if
there's multiple ones that pass the
tests they use a similarity metric to
try to pick the one that that looks the
best compared to the
others so this is
very effective actually agent list gets
good results for how simple of a method
it is it also costs less than some agent
style planning methods but the problem
is it's very inflexible so like let's
say now you wanted to go online line and
read the documentation before you solve
the task in some cases you wouldn't be
able to do this because this is
hardcoded another thing that's like a
little bit less inflexible um are kind
of multi multi-agent style methods or um
methods that use an llm generated plan
beforehand actually it doesn't need to
be multi-agent it could be just a single
agent that generates a plan beforehand
and then steps through the plan um this
is an example from a multi-agent system
called coder and basically the way it
works is it generates a plan this plan
is based on the fact that this manager
has a whole bunch of
um kind of sub agents like a reproducer
a fault localizer an editor and a
verifier and it has a semi hardcoded
structure between all of these uh agents
where you first generate a plan that
includes the re uh reproducer step
theault local ation step editor step
verifier step and then you have kind of
a hardcoded control flow where the
reproducer runs it if they're able to
reproduce it then um uh they send it to
the fault localizer if not they send it
directly to the editor other things like
this so there's a lot of works that have
this kind of thing that's highly
tailored towards uh solving uh GitHub
issues one problem with uh one problem
with this sort of thing though is
I've noticed that language model agents
very often they'll generate a plan and
then after they've generated the plan
they realize that their plan was not the
greatest plan in the first place like um
their underlying assumptions were not
correct like the test directory that
they were supposed to use doesn't exist
in the first place so they need to go
back and modify it or other things like
this so um there's an example of a work
this was tested on web agents not coding
agents but I think it's applicable to
coding agents as well and we've tried it
out a little bit but basically it has
the ability to kick the plan back to the
planners so if the um agent that's
executing the plan fails at doing any of
the steps in the plan it can kick it
back to the planner and the planner can
say oh I need to generate a new plan and
I think if you're going to have this
sort of like uh kind of structured
architecture this is really really
important in doing a good
job another really important thing is um
having the ability to fix uh outputs
based on error messages and like one of
the advantages of using the agents
versus using kind of like an agentless
uh framework is that the agents can
actually run the code see the results of
the code and go back and fix uh the code
uh
appropriately and there's not a whole
lot of work on doing this especially
with the kind of like strong modern
language models as far as I can tell
um I kind of hope that there's more work
in this general direction this intercode
is one example of this um but even like
our strongest models are not super great
at this um like uh just to give an
example GPT 40 uh one of the issues we
found is it will attempt to fix an issue
um it will fail at fixing an issue then
it will attempt to fix the issue in the
same way and get stuck in a loop and
just do this over and over and over
again until you run out of turns um for
some reason CLA is better uh at not
doing this and trying different
approaches um I don't know why because
the Claud people have not told me uh
what they did so uh if any of the cloud
people are listening please tell me um
but
uh I I think methods that train models
to do really well at Air recovery are
going to be like a big research topic
going uh going forward and I think
people are working on this now this well
um a final thing I'd like to talk about
is uh safety and this is uh really
important because coding models can
cause harm um right now at the moment
I'm most worried about because I use
coding models in my everyday coding uh
experience I'm most worried about them
causing harm by accident because I uh
told it to do something it either made a
mistake or it misinterpreted my um my
commands and it fixed uh and you know it
it did some damage uh so to give some
examples that have like actually
happened to me before um you have a
coding model and you ask it to commit it
to your GitHub repository and you never
said you want it to push it onto GitHub
uh but it just assumes that you want to
push it onto GitHub so it will uh you
know commit things and push them
directly to your main branch on GitHub
and then you need to go clean up your uh
your code repository or in the worst
case let's say there's bugs it causes
you know major issues for people who
would be using the reposit story
Downstream
um this was a really uh crazy one that I
was very surprised by which um was I
told the model uh that the tests needed
to pass and it was having trouble making
the test pass so it just deleted the
tests um and uh this this is a little
bit scary right you know it's uh it's
doing something that's pretty obviously
harmful in order to obtain its
objectives so you know we don't uh we
don't want to do
that another thing is intentional uh
misuse and um there have been uh
essentially papers have demonstrated
that coding agents can be used for
hacking and other uh things like this
and I think this is you know we need to
be careful uh in uh making sure that we
have tools that are able to mitigate
these risks I don't think that means you
know don't build tools because if we
don't build tools and only hackers will
have these tools but um we we do need to
be very conscientious of that um so the
first safety mitigation one that I think
is absolutely essential if you're using
coding agents in your everyday life is
sandboxing and we can improve safety by
basically limiting the environment that
the agent has access to um just to give
one example um Open Hands uh executes
all actions within a Docker environment
that's isolated from the main system
that using right then so it only has
access to the um it only has access to
the files that you put into that Docker
environment and other things like this
um also with Docker you can limit access
to the internet you can limit access to
any other variety of things so I like
one General theme with respect to safety
is that we shouldn't uh according to my
philosophy anyway is we've already
thought a lot about safety of software
in kind of like non- agent scenarios and
so we can reuse a lot of the tools that
we already you know know are important
and useful in those sorts of uh you know
code security uh in non-agent scenarios
and kind of reuse them for safety and
Docker is one example of
that um the next thing is
credentialing and um there's a very
important you know Concept in security
that I think many or most people have
heard of called the principle of lease
privilege which is that people should
only have privileges that are necessary
to do their job services should only
have privileges that are necessary to do
their
jobs and just to give an example um
there are GitHub access uh tokens um
that now have very fine gr Privileges
and allow you to only do certain things
on GitHub
repositories um the example on the right
is very small so uh let me read it out
loud but um
the first thing it it says is um
repository access so you can either make
it a public uh give it access to all
public repositories with only readon
access you can give it access to all
repositories that you have access to are
only select repositories so you can
decide which like GitHub repositories
it's allowed to access um you can also
figure out whether it can run GitHub
actions uh do
Administration um for example modify
content open issues and other things
like this so what you can do here is you
can basically prevent Agents from you
know having access to more privileges
than they need but still give them the
Privileges that they need and like
actually one thing I forgot to say is
it's very easy to create a completely
useless agent you just put it in a
sandbox and don't give it access to
anything and you'll have an agent that
you know can't really do anything other
than work as a calculator um or
something like this um but at the same
time we want to build agents that are
helpful uh while also not causing you
know undo uh harm so this is another
thing that we need to think
about so another um thing that we have
looked at um is uh creating post
auditing auditing for models and post
Hawk uh auditing for models uh the way
you can do this is you can generate
action
and then based on um the actions you can
either decide to execute them if they're
deemed to be harmless actions and uh if
they are deemed to be harmful actions
you don't execute them and you return
basically a like this is dangerous you
shouldn't be executing that action
message back to the agent um and so this
can use llms can use static analysis
tools vulnerability detection tools or
other things um and I I should mention
that this is actually joint work with um
uh people at invariant labs and eth um
but this is a conclusion uh in summary I
think we've already demonstrated that
co-pilots are very useful um code agents
are getting there I have repositories
where I have done half of the commits
with a coding agent or at least it's
drafted half of the commits and then
I've gone in and fixed them and other
stuff like this so I think um you know
in the next one or two years uh there's
going to be the ability to use coding
agents in many of our mundane tasks ones
that don't require very much thought and
they'll gradually get better at doing
things that require more thought and
more care I think um current challenges
include coming up with good code llms uh
editing methods localization planning
and
safety um in terms of future directions
I think there's a lot of interesting
directions in this area um the first one
uh in addition to all of the current
challenges uh the first one is agentic
training methods so Training Method
training on agent style data uh that
will give us the ability to adhere to
agent formats do kind of better planning
um recover from errors
better another thing is human in the
loop uh methods for uh evaluating agents
so like one of the nice things about
agents is they can communicate with
humans and I'm much more effective at
solving tasks if I'm willing to spend
the time interacting with the agent then
just asking it to do it um on the fly I
can do things like watch the agent do
its work and pause it when it seems to
be making a mistake and just go in and
push it in the right direction and it
will correct course but we really don't
know like the best modality for this and
we don't have any good evaluation
benchmarks to evaluate uh how well
models are able to do at this so I think
that's another big
thing um also broader software tasks
than coding I think there's
basically no or at least very few uh
benchmarks that tell us how good we're
doing at this in the first place and
like software toolkits like Devon and
Open Hands can do this they can do web
browsing they can do other stuff like
this um but it's not clear how well they
can do at any of these tasks and how
much you know um how much work there is
still to be
done so yeah that's my that's my summary
sorry this is a very Broad I know I went
through a lot of stuff in uh in an hour
um but if you want to try it out
yourself you can download uh our
software toolkit and it does all the
things I talked about here um and we'd
love to have feedback or collaborate
with people and things like that as well
so uh yeah thank you