good evening people um even how are you
guys
doing all right my name is archa Sharma
I'm a PhD student at Stanford and I'm
very very excited to talk about post
training generally speaking for large
language models and I hope you guys are
ready to learn some stuff because this
has been one of the last few years in
machine learning have been very very
exciting uh with the Advent of large
language model CH GPD and everything to
that extent and hopefully after today's
lecture you will be more comfortable
understanding how we go from pre-train
Models to models like CH GPD and we'll
take a whole journey through prompting
instruction fine tuning and DP and
rlf so let's get
started all
right so something that has been very
fundamental to our entire field is this
idea of scaling loss and models are
increasingly becoming larger and larger
and they're expanding more and more
compute so this is a graph of models
starting all the way back in 1950s to
somewhere around these are still this is
an outdated graph so like this shows up
to 10 to^ 24 flops or floating Point
operations that go into pre-training
these models but the number is well
above 10 to^ 26 now but you can see the
graph and the way it's
trending and more more and more compute
requires more and more data because you
need to train on something meaningful
and this is roughly the trend on the
amount of language tokens that are going
into the language models in pre-training
and again this plot is outdated does
anybody want to guess like we're in 2024
2022 we were at 1.4 trillion tokens or
words roughly speaking in language model
pre-training do does anyone want to
guess like where we are in 2024
that's a pretty good guess yeah so we're
close to 15 trillion tokens um recent
llama 3 models were roughly trained on
15 trillion tokens so yeah just just for
a second appreciate that these are a lot
of words uh this is not yeah I don't I
don't think anybody of us listens to
like trillions of tokens in our lifetime
so this is where we are right now and I
hope you guys were here for the pre-
pre-training lectures cool um so what do
we do so like I mean broadly speaking we
are really just learning to predict text
tokens or language tokens but what do we
learn in the process of pre-training why
is why are people spending so much money
so much compute because these Compu and
tokens take dollars to do and we're
we're on the order spending hundreds of
millions of dollars on these runs so why
are we doing this and this is basically
a recall from whatever you have probably
learned till now but we're learning
things like oh we are learning knowledge
Stanford University is located in Santa
clar California or wherever you want to
like say you're learning syntax you're
learning semantics of the sentences
these are things that you would expect
to learn when you're training on
language data broadly you're probably
learning a lot about different languages
as well so like depending on your text
Data distribution you're learning a lot
of things but the models we interact
with are very intelligent so where is
that coming from like I mean just simply
learning about very factual things and
it's a very simple loss function we're
optimizing and where is that
Intelligence coming
from and this perhaps is the interesting
bit recently like people have like
started accumulating evidence for that
like when you optimize the next token
prediction losses you're not just
learning about syntax you're not just
learning knowledge but you're starting
to like form models of Agents beliefs
and actions as well so how do we know
this again a lot of this is speculative
evidence but it's mayy to like form an
understanding that the losses we're
optimizing are not just about the data
fitting the data but you start learning
something maybe more meaningful as
well um for example like I mean in this
specific case um we change the last
sentence and the prediction of the text
or the next Tex that that is predicted
changes as well so here it starts with
Pat watch as a demonstration of a
bowling ball and the leaf being dropped
at the same time pat who is a physicist
predicts that the bowling ball and the
leaf will land at the same rate we all
know Gravity the way it works but when
you L change the last sentence to Pat
who has never seen this demonstration
before Pat predicts that bowling ball
will fall to the ground first maybe
somebody who's never seen this
experiment before might intuitively
believe that correct so like I mean the
language model was able to predict this
so how do you predict this you have to
have some notion of understanding of how
humans work to even be able to predict
this and that's maybe like something
that is not obvious with You're simply
optimizing to predict the
text similarly like I mean these kind of
examples are we're going to run through
some examples to like sort of
communicate that when you're
pre-training these models you're
learning much more than just language
tokens and so on you're also learning
about math like you're able to
understand what a graph of a circle
means and what the center is and where
how to like understand
equations probably my favorite example
something I use pretty much every day is
you're learning how to write code so I
don't know how many of you have
interacted with co-pilot before but if
you have like you probably know like if
you write down a few commands write down
a function template it will
automatically complete code for you so
again it's not perfect but it has to
have some deeper understanding of what
your intent is for something like that
to
emerge and similarly we have examples
from medicine as well I don't know about
you guys but like whenever I have some
issue I probably go to chat gbd or
Claude or something to that effect and
ask them a diagnosis for those things as
well
um I don't recommend that uh please
don't take medical advice from me but
yeah so broadly like the way we're
seeing language models at this point is
that like they're sort of emerging as
this general purpose multitask
assistance and it's very strange right
like I mean we started off with text
token prediction and we're reaching the
stage where it can like sort of rely to
them on them to do many many different
things so how are we getting there and
I'm sure you all are aware of like what
these models are so yeah
so today's lecture is largely going to
be about how do we go from something
Stanford University is located this very
simple pretraining task a very simple
procedure well it's more complicated but
in abstract terms it's not very
complicated to like something as
powerful as CH
GPD cool
so um I recommend you guys stopping me
asking me a lot of questions because
this is a there's a lot of fun examples
and a lot of fun techniques so like I I
want you guys to like learn everything
about here so the overall plan is we're
going to talk about zero shot and few
shot in context learning um next we're
going to follow up with instruction
fine-tuning and then we're going to talk
about optimizing for preferences and
this is where roughly things are right
now in the industry and when we're going
to talk about what's next what the
limitations are and how do we move from
here cool so we're going to start off
with zero shot INF fusure in context
learning um broad we're going to take an
example example of GPT or the generative
pre-train Transformer and this is a
whole series of models that started off
in roughly 2018 and like up to 2020 they
were building GPD gpd2 gbd3 so we're
going to start off with this example and
yes so it's a decoder only model that is
trained on roughly 4.6 GB of text and it
has 12 layers of Transformers layers and
it's trained with the next token
prediction
loss and the first model obviously was
not extremely good but it started
showing that like hey like this
technique for pre-training can be very
effective for general purpose tasks and
we're going to see some
examples um for example like I mean here
it's able to do the task for entainment
and okay
um yeah and gbd1 itself was not very
strong as a model so like but they took
the same recipe and like I mean tried to
like increase the model size so they
went from 117 million parameters to
about 1.5 billion parameters and we're
now scaling up the data alongside as
well so we went from 4 gabt of data to
approximately 40 gab of data and
pre-training is a whole different like
melting part of techniques and there's a
lot that goes into it but like roughly
for example here they filter data by the
number of upwards on the redit
data and yeah so this is roughly where
we are and I think one of the things
that started emerging with gpd2 is zero
shot learning and what do we mean by
zero shot learning
um conventionally in the field like when
we pre-train models there was the idea
that you take a few examples you update
the model um and then you are able to
adapt to a specific task but as you
pre-train on more and more data and more
and more tasks you sort of start seeing
this phenomena where they're able to do
the task basically zero short they're
shown no examples of how to do the task
and you can start thinking of oh how you
can do it summarization you can follow
some instructions you can do maybe a
little bit of math as well so this is
where the idea of zero shot learning
started to
emerge yeah so how do we do zero shot
learning or task specific learning from
these pre-trained models really the idea
is that we have to be creative here we
know that these are text prediction
models if you put in a text they will
complete whatever follows so if we can
sort of course these models into
completing the task we care about maybe
it's question answering we can so start
getting them to solve tasks here so for
example if you want to ask questions
about Tom Brady you sort of set it up
you sort put information about Tom Brady
and then you put a question that you
wanted to answer and then it will
autocomplete in some sense so this is
one early perspective on these models
these are very Advanced autocomplete
models and
similarly if you want to figure out like
which answer is true or which is not
something that is very useful to measure
is log probabilities so
for example we want to figure out what
is the word it refering to here in this
sentence the cat couldn't fit into the
Hat because it was too big um what we
can do is we can take the sentence
replace it with either the cat or either
the hat and then you can measure the
probability of which Mo which one does
the model think is higher and you can
sort of get the idea what the reference
here is so none of this is like in the
training data it's simply learning to
predict text but you can start seeing
how like we can leverage these models to
do other tasks as well be besides
prediction so this is just more evidence
about like how gpd2 no task specific
fine-tuning no task specific training it
simply is learning to predict text and
it's establishes the state-of-the-art on
many many different tasks simply by
scaling up the model parameters and
scaling up the amount of data it's
stained on
so this is a fun example so if you want
to do summarization for data or like you
have a news article that you want to
summarize so how do you get a zero shot
model to do it this answer is you put
the document into the context and you
simply put tldr in front of
it now like I mean if most of the data
on internet whenever you see tldr you'll
naturally summarize it so yeah you can
get zero shot performance and
summarization here as well and again
this is not trained to do something
summarization in any specific way and
it's still doing really well simply
because of its pre-training
data so yeah um I think gp22 tldr is
somewhere there and like some of the
very Tas specific train models are um
like and I think you will see the trend
with again if you were Alec Radford or
somebody like I mean you see like these
cool things emerging your next step
would obviously be I'm going to scale
this up a little more I'm going to make
an even bigger model I'm going to train
it even more data and we'll see how
things go right so that's how we got
gbd3 uh we went from 1.5 billion
parameters to 175 billion parameters we
are well over like 40 GB of data to 600
gbt of data of course like now we're in
like terabytes of data and text is a
very compressed representation so like
terabytes of data is a
lot um and you know we we talked about
zero shot learning the cool thing that
emerged in gbd3 is like go ahead like
used before the passage right no you
typically put the passage uh if youve
like interacted with Reddit or something
like that typically somebody will write
an entire post and then end with TLD drr
here's a summary of the thing too long
didn't read or if you have
used opposite comes first oh yeah there
are situations where it also comes first
but um one reason is that these are like
decoder only models so like they are
often these are causal attention models
so the typically need to see the context
before yeah understand I'm just curious
like from my experience the comes first
then how is
it
the okay um there's probably a lot of
data where the tldr comes first but
there's probably a lot of data where
tldr comes after as
well cool so we saw Zero shot learning
emerging in gpd2 few shot learning maybe
seem slightly easier but like this is
where things started getting really
funny is that like you're starting to
beat state-ofthe-art simply by just
putting examples in context so yeah what
does f shot learning mean here what is
what are we talking about um as I
mentioned like the typical idea here is
is that like you want to solve
translation so you would put some
examples of translation into
context and you know this is a
correction task here or maybe you want
interested in Translation and no
gradient updates no learning in any
conventional sense whatso ever you put a
few examples in and that's it like I
mean you know how to solve the task
isn't that like crazy like you're bu you
guys did the assignment on translation
right so but this is what the modern NLP
looks like
so yeah um you put in some examples and
you have the entire system and this is
where things got really interesting is
that all these task specific models that
were created to like be really really
good at translation or really good at
summarization you can just put let's
look at this graph so we start with a
zero shot performance of this in a
similar fashion that I described earlier
and you start somewhere there you put
one example in of translation from
English to French you get to somewhere
like already at a fine level few
examples in you're already starting to
like be close to the state-ofthe-art
models wait but in that gra the state of
theart is really high isn't
it uh find your Inver of the bird Plus+
here I think is like the one I'm
referring to find your of the like which
is trained exclusively on a lot of um
translation data might be like slightly
better yes um and I think that's the
relevant comparison here is the in
context learning starts to emerge at
scale so and this is I think like the
key point is that this some of this is
contested just to be very upfront but
like there's this idea of emergence of
this property as you train on more
Computing and more scale um there's more
recent research which suggest that if we
plot the access correctly it feels less
emergent but the general idea is as you
increase the number of parameters and
increase the number of compute that is
going into the models the ability to
just go from a few examples to really
strong performance is very
compelling cool
um and yeah I think as I explained
earlier the general idea is that this is
very different from the conventional
idea of fine tuning that we typically go
for instead of like iterating over
examples putting it into context and
doing gradient updates we are actually
just going for few short promting we're
going to put in few examples and that's
going to give us the
system um yes I mean the exact details
roughly can depend on the prom template
that you use but typically you would
just put examples so like c order and
put these examples and then whatever
your task is you can just let the model
complete from there because it can infer
the task
um based on the examples you've
given any other
questions
cool
so yeah like I mean we have gotten from
zero shot prompting and like we've seen
seeing that F shot prompting is becoming
really competitive with good models but
there's still limitations to this like I
mean you cannot solve every task that
you see here and particularly like
things that involve like richer
multi-step reasoning is something that
actually can be pretty challenging and
just to be fair human struggle at these
tasks as well so things like addition
and so on like these are these are
probably like still still hard to do
like when you keep increasing the number
of digits but one thing that you have to
start being creative with I alluded to
this earlier is that you can get these
models to do the task if you're creative
in how you prompt the model and this is
what we're going to see
next um so this technique called Chain
of Thought prompting emerged here and
the idea that we have explored thus far
is that we put in examples of the kind
of tasks we want to do and we expect the
model to zero shot learn what the task
is and go from there um the idea is that
like instead of just showing what the
task is you show them examples where
they reason through the task so they're
not just learning to do the task but
also learning how the reasoning is
working so in this example initially we
started with like we have to solve a
simple math problem and we are just
shown exactly the answer answer directly
instead of doing that and if you do that
directly you'll observe that the model
gets the answer wrong instead of that
what if you show model how to reason
about the task show it a chain of
thought and include that in the prompt
as
well and then you ask at a new question
the idea is that now the model is not
just going to Output an answer it's
going to reason about the task and it's
going to do actually a lot better and
this has been shown to be very effective
um Chain of Thought is also as you can
see like I mean it's again something
that improves a lot with model scale
it's not just um yeah um but what you
can probably start seeing is like it's
nearly better than supervised best
models here so power models roughly were
about 5 40 billion
parameters and simply with this Chain of
Thought kind of a skill you're already
like beating state of the
art cool um
so yeah so I showed you examples of
Chain of Thought reasoning to to this
point where you go through a reasoning
chain but you can be even slightly
smarter than that you might not even
need to show them any examples you just
need to trick them into thinking about
what to do
next um so yeah this s this idea emerged
in this paper called where you let's
think step by step where instead of even
showing an example you just start your
answer with let's think step by step and
that's it like I mean the model will
start reasoning about the answer itself
instead of just like autoc completing to
an answer and you get something like
this
so maybe you don't even need to show any
examples like you can probably induce
the reasoning Behavior through zero shot
Behavior as well and again um what the
final numbers look like is like compared
to zero shot performance that we got
from essentially autoc comp completing
this zero shot Chain of Thought
substantially improves the performance
so you go from like 17.7 to 78.7 it's
still worse than still putting like
examples of reasoning and multi-shot few
shot Chain of Thought as well but you
can see like how much it improves the
performance simply by asking you to
let's think by step by step and maybe
this is like a lesson that interacting
with these models is like when you
interact with these models you might not
get the exact desired behavior from
these models up front but often like
these models are capable of doing the
behavior that you might want and often
you have to think about how to induce
that behavior such that and the right
way to think perhaps is like what is the
pre-training data what is the data on
the internet it might have seen which
induces a similar Behavior to the kind I
want and you probably want to like think
about that and then induce these kinds
of behaviors from those
models and yeah like I mean um you know
we we hand designed some of these
prompts you can also like get an llm to
design these prompts as well there's
like recursive self-improving ideas here
um that happen and you can bump up the
performance a little bit
more cool so what we have seen so far is
that as models get stronger and stronger
you can start forcing them to do your
task zero shot or with few short
examples and you can trick them into
thinking what task you want them to
solve
but the downside is that there's only so
much you can fit into context this might
not be very true anymore models like
becoming increasingly larger context but
it's still somewhat unsatisfactory to
think you have to trick the model into
doing your task rather than like it just
doing the task you wanted to do and
potentially like I mean going forward
like you probably still want to fine
tune these models for more and more
complex tasks and that's where we're
going to go forward in this
um next section we're going to cover is
instruction fine tuning and the general
idea we have right now is that as we
talked about pre-training is not about
assisting users it is about predicting
the next token now you can trick it into
assisting users and uh following the
instruction you wanted to but in general
that's not what it retrained it for and
this is an example of where if you ask
GPD 3 pretty strong model to explain
like moon landing to a six-year-old in a
few sentences and it will follow up with
more questions about what a 60-year-old
might want this is not what you wanted
the model to do right so the general
term that people use these days is that
they're not aligned with user intent and
the next sections that we're going to
cover are going to talk about how to
align it with the user intent so that
they don't have to trick the model into
whatever uh we wanted to
do and this is a kind of like desired
completion we want at the end of
instruction tuning um and yeah
how do we get from those pre-trained
models to models which can respond to
user
intent um again um I hope this was
covered somewhere in the class the
general idea of pre-training and
fine-tuning um but what you have
probably seen thus far is that you
pre-train on a lot of different language
task uh on data but then you find on
your specific task so you're taking the
same decoder only models and you're fine
tuning to some task with very little
amount of data the thing that is going
to be different now is not that we're no
longer fine tuning on a little amount of
data we're going to fine tune on many
many different tasks and we're going to
just try to put them into a single
usable um ux for users and this is where
fine tuning or instruction fine tuning
comes
in cool um so again the recipe is not
very very complicated here um we're
going to collect a lot of examples of
instruction and output Pairs and the
instructions are going to rrange over
several task different forms um there's
going to be question answering they're
going to be summarization translation
code reasoning and so on and we're going
to collect a lot of examples uh related
to all those tasks and the idea is like
I mean we'll train on instruction and
output pairs exactly with them and then
we're going to evaluate on some unseen
tasks as well so this is a general
Paradigm of instruction fine tuning and
again it's the same idea which we
explored in pre-training is that data
plus scale is really important and these
days like a mean you start off with like
one task you're now extending it over
thousands of thousands and thousands of
tasks with like three million plus
examples and this is generally like a
broad range of tasks that you might see
in instruction fine tuning data
sets and yeah you might even think of
like why are we calling it fine tuning
anymore like it's almost starting to
look like pre-training um but yeah we
can these are just terms um so so you
can decide whatever you are comfortable
with um so yeah we we get this like huge
instruction data set we finder model the
next question is like how do we evaluate
these data sets um now I think you guys
will see another lecture on evaluation
so I don't want to like dive too deep
into this but generally evaluation of
these language models is an extremely
tricky topic um there's a lot of biases
that you need to deal with and a lot of
this will be covered but some more
recent progess on this is like we are
starting to curate these like really
large benchmarks uh like mlu where the
models are tested on a broad range of
diverse knowledge and this is just one
example which is and these are the
topics that you will see and just to
give some intuition of what the examples
in these evaluation look like um under
astronomy you might be asked what is
true for type 1 a supernova or you might
be asked some questions about biology
and there's a huge host of tasks for
this and you can typically like these
are multi- choice questions and you can
ask the model to answer the question if
they're instruction fine tuned already
hopefully they can like simply answer
the question but you can also uh Chain
of Thought prompt these questions or few
short promp these questions too and
recently there's been a huge amount of
progress uh on this Benchmark what
people have observed is like more and
more pre-training on more and more data
and larger models is simply just like
climbing up these um the number on this
so 90% is often seen as a benchmark Mark
number that these model wanted to cross
because it's roughly like human level
knowledge or understanding and recently
the Gemini models purply cross this
number so yeah go
ahead is isn't this like the entire sort
of thing all over again right like imag
at some point you're like okay maybe my
methods are too like too fine tuned
implicitly on on the image bi and isn't
something like that happening here as
well uh um yes I think this is a tricky
topic because a lot of the models often
there's this idea about whether your
test sets are leaking into your training
data set and there's are huge concerns
about that it's a perfectly valid
question to ask how do we even evaluate
this is why evaluation is actually very
tricky but one General thing to be
careful about is like at some point like
it doesn't matter what your trained test
is if the models are generally useful if
their models are doing useful stuff like
does it matter like how if your test if
you train on everything you care about
and it does well on it like does it
matter so yeah um again we still need
better ways to evaluate the models um
and to understand what methods are doing
and how they're if they're improving the
model or not but at some point like that
those boundaries start to like be less
important cool so massive progress on
this Benchmark starting with gpd2 and
like we're roughly at 90% which to the
point where these benchmarks are
starting to become unclear if like
improvements on these are actually
meaningful or not um in fact like most
of the times when the models are wrong
like you might often find that the
question itself was unclear or ambiguous
so all evaluation benchmarks have a
certain limited utility to
them so yeah um going to go over like
another evaluation example of how this
recipe like changes things so T5 models
were instruction fine tuned on a huge
number of tasks and another Trend to or
which I think will be the theme across
this lecture is that as your models
become larger as they're trained on more
data they become more and more
responsive to your task information as
well so what you will observe here is
like as the number of parameters ex
increase we have like T5 small FL T5
small and we go up to 11 billion
parameters where where we have T5 XXL
you'll see that the Improvement actually
improves like going from a pre into an
instruction model the instruction model
is all the more better at following
instructions so the difference is plus
6.1 and goes to plus 26.6 as the models
become larger so this is another very
encouraging Trend that you probably
should train on a lot of data with a lot
of compute and you know pre-training
just keeps on
giving
so yeah um you I hope you guys get a
chance to like play with a lot of these
models I I think you already hopefully
are uh but yeah before instruction fine
tuning something when you're asked a
question related to disambiguation QA um
you get something like this and it
doesn't actually follow the let's think
by step byep instruction very clearly
but after instruction fine tuning it is
able to answer the question
here and yeah like more recently people
have been like researching into like
what the instruction tuning data set
should look like there's a huge plora of
instruction tuning data sets now
available like this is just a
representative diagram and there's a h
open source Community developing around
these as
well um some high level lessons that we
have learned from this
is one lesson that I think might be
interesting is that we can actually use
really large strong models to generate
some of the instruction tuning data to
train some of our smaller models so take
your favorite model right now gbd4 maybe
or maybe Claud or whatever and you can
get it to answer some question s and
generate instruction outut pairs for
training your open source or smaller
model and that actually is a very
successful recipe so instead of getting
a human to collect all the instruction
output pairs or getting humans to
generate the answers you can get bigger
models to generate the answers as well
so that's number one thing that like has
recently emerged another thing that are
is being emerged or is like being
discussed is how much data do we need I
talked about millions of examples but
like people have often found that if you
have really high quality example you can
get away with thousand examples as well
so this is the paperless as more for
alignment and this is still an active
area of research on how like data
scaling and instruction tuning affects
the final model
performance and yeah crowdsourcing these
models can be effective as well so there
are very cool benchmarks that are
emerging like open Assistant um yeah a
lot of activity in the field and
hopefully like a lot more progress as we
go on yes um a question sort of in the
spirit of this LMA paper uh doesn't like
code or like I don't know like math word
problems have this desired structure so
like shouldn't we just like be training
code models and doing like some English
stuff and then just be like okay this is
the best reasoning we can get at some
point right cuz like C code has the
structure where where where like you're
going sort of step by step and you're
sort of thinking in in some way in like
a so breaking down a concept into a
smaller so you can consider like cod
have like very high value tokens so
maybe like just doing so I think there's
again pre-training is a whole Dark Art
that I am not completely familiar with
but um code actually ends up being
really useful in pre-training mixtures
and people do like up with code data
quite a lot um similarly like I mean but
it depends upon what the users are going
to use the models for right um some
people might use it for Cotes some
people people might do for reasoning but
that's not the only task we care about
as you might see later on in the next
step we'll discuss this as well is that
people often use these models for
Creative task they wanted to write a
story uh they wanted to generate a movie
script or so on and I don't know if like
necessarily training on reasoning only
tasks would help with that so go ahead
yeah would you explain like there there
exists like some data distribution which
is like high value for Creative tasks
yes like I mean it seems like um a lot
of PE people write about stories and
everything on the internet all the time
like which is not code and sometimes
like there's this idea of hallucinations
as well in this like field but you can
often think like hey like creativity
might be a byproduct of hallucinations
as well so I don't know what exact data
would like lead to like more creative
models but generally like there's a lot
of data or a lot of stories that are
written on the internet which allows the
model to be
creative yeah but I don't know if I have
a specific answer to the
question cool so we discussed
instruction fine tuning um very simple
and very straightforward there's like no
complicated algorithms here just collect
a lot of data and then you can start
leveraging the performance at scale as
well like as models become better these
models also become more easily
specifiable and they become more
responsive to task as well we're going
to discuss some limitations and I think
this is like really important to
understand why we are going to optimize
for human
preferences cool so we talked a bit
about this like instruction fine tuning
is necessarily contingent on humans
labeling the data now
humans it's expensive to collect this
data especially as the questions become
more and more complex you want to answer
questions about what which may be at
physics PhD level or things to that
effect these things become increasingly
expensive to collect
so yeah this is maybe like perhaps
obvious like collecting data
pre-training does not require any
specific data you scrape data of the web
but for instruction fing you probably
need to recruit some people to write
down answer to your instructions so this
can become very expensive very quickly
but there's more limitations to this as
well and we we just discussing this like
there are open-ended tasks related to
creativity that don't really have like
an exact correct answer to begin with so
how do you generate the right answer to
the kind of a
question and yeah like language modeling
inherently like penalizes all token
level mistakes equally um this is what
super fine supervised fine tuning does
as well but often like not all mistakes
are the same so this is an example where
you're trying to do this prediction task
Avatar is a fantasy TV show and perhaps
you can see like I mean calling it an
adventure TV show is perhaps okay but
calling it a musical May be like a much
worse mistake but both these mistakes
are penalized
equally and I think one General aspect
which is like more becoming increasingly
relevant is that the humans that you
might ask might not generate the right
or the highest quality answer your
models are becoming increasingly
competitive and you want in some sense
you're going to be limited by how high
quality the answer um humans can
generate but often I find that the
models are generating better and better
answers so do we really want to keep
relying on humans to write down the
answers or do we want to like somehow go
over
that so these are the three problems we
have talked about um with instruction
fine tuning and we made a lot of
progress with this but this is not how
we got Char
GPT um and one high level problem here
is that even though when even when we
are instruction fine tuning there is
still a huge mismatch
between the end goal is to optimize for
human preferences generate an output
that a human might like and we're still
doing prediction kind of tasks where
we're predicting the next token but now
in a more curated data set so that's
still a bit of a mismatch going on here
and it's not exactly what we want to
do hopefully like I mean I'm going to
take a second here to pause because this
is important to understand the next
section and if there's any
questions feel free to ask so is this
step uh still taken as a as a first step
or we discard this it's a good question
so um I think this is still one of the
more important steps that you take
before taking the next step but people
are trying to like remove the step Al
together and jump directly to the next
step so there's work emerging on that
but yeah and this is still a very
important step before we do the next
step
go ahead is PR two also present in
pre-training uh and if so how how do you
avoid that ver just by having a lot of
data um yeah that's a great question uh
there's two diff there's one difference
one major difference on pre-training um
pre-training covers a lot more text so
um just for context like I mean as we
talked about it's pre-training is
roughly 15 trillion tokens whereas like
supervised instruction fine tuning might
be somewhere on the order of millions to
billions of tokens so it's like few
orders of magnitude lower typically
you'd only see one answer for a specific
instruction but during pre-training
you'll see multiple text and multiple
completions for a same kind of a prompt
um now that's good because when you see
multiple answers or completions during
pre-training you sort of start to weigh
different answers you start to put
probability Mass on different kind of
answers or completions but instruction
fineing might force you to put and wait
on only one
answer does it okay but generally yeah
like I mean this is a problem with both
the stages you're
right anything
else
cool so as this whole thing alludes to
we're going to start to attempt to
satisfy human preferences directly we're
no longer going to like try to like get
humans to generate some data and try to
do some kind of a token level prediction
loss we're going to try to optimize for
human preferences directly and that is
uh the general field of rlf and that's
the final step in typically getting a
model like CH
GPD so we talked about how collecting
demonstration is expensive and there's
still a broad mismatch between the LM
objective and human preferences and now
we're going to try and optimize for
human preferences
directly so what ises optimizing for
human preferences even mean um to like
concretely establish that let's go
through like a specific example in mind
which is
summarization um we want to train a
model to be better at
summarization and we want to satisfy
human preferences so let's imagine that
a human is able to prescribe a reward
for a specific summary let's just
pretend there is a reward function you
and I can assign say like reward this is
plus one this is minus one or something
to that
effect okay um so in this specific case
we have this input X which uh which is
about an earthquake in San Francisco so
this is news article that we want to
summarize
and let's pretend that we get these
rewards and we want to optimize this so
we we get one summary y1 which gives us
an earthquake hit and so on and we
assign a reward of 8.0 and another
summary which gives us a reward of
1.2 generally speaking like the
objective that we want to set up is
something of the following form where we
want to take our language model P Theta
which generates a completion y uh given
an input X and we want to maximize the
reward of rxy where X is the input and Y
is the output summary in this specific
task and maybe like just to like really
concretely point out something here this
is different from everything that we
have done in one very specific way um we
are sampling from the model itself in
the bottom term if you see like we're
using Y from P Theta everything we've
seen so far the data is sampled from
some other source either during
pre-training either in supervised fine
tuning and we're maximizing the log
likelihood of those tokens but now we're
explicitly sampling from our model and
optimizing potentially a
non-differentiable
objective
cool so broadly the rlf pipeline looks
something like this and first step is
still instruction tuning something we
have seen up until now where we take our
pre-trained model we instruction tune on
a large collection of tasks and we get
some something which starts responding
to our desired intent or
not but there are two more steps after
this which are typically followed in
creating something like instruct gbt the
first step is estimating some kind of a
reward model something which tells us
given an instruction how much would a
human like this answer or how much would
a human hate this answer so we looked at
something like this earlier but I didn't
talk about how do we even get something
like that that's the second step and
then we take this reward model and we
optimize it through the optimiz ation
that I suggested earlier so the
maximizing the expected reward under
your language
model and we're going to go over a lot
over in the second and third
steps so the first question we want to
answer is how do we even get like a
reward model what about what humans are
going to like like this is a very IL
defined problem generally speaking
so there's there's two problems here
that we're going to address first is a
human in the loop is expensive so let's
say like if I ask a model to like
generate an answer and then I get a
human to label with some kind of a score
I'm doing this over millions of
completions that is not very scalable I
I don't want to sit around and label
millions of examples
so this is very easy like we're in a
machine learning class so what are we
going to do what we're going to do is
we're going to train something which
predicts what a human would like or what
a human might not like and this is
roughly um this is essentially a machine
learning problem where we take these
Rewards scor scores and we try to train
a reward model to predict given an input
and output what the reward scores would
look
like simple simple machine learning
regression style problem uh you might
have seen this
earlier
cool now there's a bigger problem here
and sorry go ahead one so do we use like
I don't know like just embedding
withier we use a real language model to
do that um that's a good question
generally like what we do is like we
still typically need reward models where
they need to be able to understand the
text really well so like bigger models
and like they're typically initialized
from the language model that you trained
pre-trained as well so you typically
start with the pre-trained language
model and do some kind of prediction
that we'll talk about and they'll give
you a
score how do you if you're doing that
how do you separate X and Y how does the
language model know which part it
doesn't need to it can put the X and Y
like it only sees X and Y as an input so
it doesn't need to T typically see it
separated it's just going to predict a
score at the end okay yeah the X and Y
is more for notational convenience here
because for us X and Y are different X
is a question user asked and Y is
something the model generated but you
shove the whole thing into you shove the
whole thing into yes
cool now this is the bigger problem here
and human judgments are very noisy we
have talked about we want to assign a
score to a completion this is something
that's like extremely non-trivial to do
so if I give you a summary like this
what score are you going to assign on a
scale of 10 if you ask me on different
days I'll give a different answer first
of all but across humans itself this
this number is not calibrated in any
meaningful way so you could assign
number of 4.1 6.6 and different humans
would just simply assign different
scores and there are ways to address
this you can like calibrate humans you
can give them a specific rubric you can
like talk to them but it's a very
complicated process and like still like
there's a lot of room for judgment which
is not typically very nice for training
a model like this if your labels can
vary a lot it's just hard to
predict so the way this is addressed is
that instead of trying to predict the
reward label directly you actually want
to set up a problem in a slightly
different way what is something much
easier for humans to do is give them two
answers or maybe many answers and tell
them ask them which one is better so
this is where the idea of asking humans
to rank answers comes in so if I give
you a whole news article and ask you
which summary is better you might be
able to give me a ranking that oh this
second summary is the worst but the
first one is better and the third one is
somewhere in the middle between those
two so you get like a ranking which
gives you um preference over
summaries and hopefully like I mean you
can see like the idea that is important
here is that even when we have some kind
of a consistent utility function even
when I have it's much easier to compare
to something and know that which is
better than this rather than ascribing
it an arbitrary number on a scale and
that's why the signal from something
like this is a lot
better now how do we get like we talked
about we need like we get this kind of a
preference data and now we need some
kind of a reward score out of this and
we shove in like our input we shove in a
summary as well and we still need to get
a score out of this but it's not clearly
obvious to me like how do we take this
data and convert it into that kind of
score
um incomes are pretty good friends named
Bradley Terry um and essentially like
there's a lot of study in like many in
economics and like psychology which
basically tries to model how humans make
decisions in specific case like this
Brad lary model essentially says that a
probability that a human chooses answer
y1 over y two is based on the difference
between the rewards that humans assign
internally and then you take a sigmoid
around it so if you have looked at
binary classification before uh the
logic is simply the difference between
the reward of some y1 minus Y2 or the
difference between the winning
completion and the losing
completion is everybody with me till
this point
so the idea is that like if you have a
data set where given y1 and Y2 where y1
is a winning completion and we have a
winning completion YW and a losing
completion y l um the winning completion
should score higher than the losing
completion go ahead sorry what is J is
that a log or like sorry what what like
what is the type of J like this number
here that we're getting as the
expectation is it a log prop or what is
it it's an log prop so it will be a
scaler at the end sigmoid is so you're
taking the let's say you have a reward
model which gives a
score R1 to like YW and R2 to y l you
subtract that number you get another
number you put it into sigmoid and you
get a probability because sigmoid will
convert a logit into probability and
then you take a logarithm of that and
you take the expectation of everything
and you get this final number which
tells you how good your reward model is
doing on the entire data set
so like a good model of humans should
behave like this a good model of humans
would um score very low here so it would
generally assign a higher reward to the
winning completion and generally assign
a lower reward to the losing
completion
cool the math is just beginning so um
hold on to your seats
um cool so now let's see where we are we
have a pre-trained model p p d y given X
and we got this like fancy reward model
which tells us that hey how we have a
model of humans and it can tell us which
instruction which answer they like and
which in answer did not
like now to do rlf generally like I mean
we have discussed what this will look
like uh we will copy our pre-train model
or instruction tune model and we'll
optimize the parameters for those models
and I suggested that the param objective
that we want to optimize is the expected
reward when we sample completions from P
Theta and we're going to optimize our
learned reward model instead of like the
true reward model which humans would
have typically assigned do you guys see
any problem with
this
um is there something that's wrong here
or like that might go wrong if we do
something along these
lines go for itel
it might collapse yes okay um but
generally at least from my intuition
like if you're ever doing something and
you have you're optimizing some learned
metric I'd be very careful because
typically our loss functions are very
clearly defined but here my reward model
is learned what when it's learned it
means it will have
errors yes so it's going to be trained
on some distribution it will generalize
as well but it will have errors and when
you're optimizing against a learn model
it will tend to hack the reward model so
it might exploit the reward model might
erroneously assign a really high score
to a really bad completion if your
policy learns or if your language model
learns to do that it will completely
Hack That and start generating those
gibberish
completions
so just as a general machine learning
tip as well if you're optimizing a learn
metric be careful about what you're
optimizing and make sure that it's
actually
reliable um and the way and this is
obviously not desirable like I mean if
you start optimizing this objective
you're going to converse to gibberish
language models very very quickly so
typically what people do is that you
want to add some kind of a penalty that
like avoids it drifting too far from its
initialization and why do we want to do
that like if it cannot Drift from too
far from its initialization we know the
initialization of the model is a decent
language model and we know it is not
necessarily satisfying this reward model
too much and we also know that like the
reward model is trained on a distrib
ution of completions where the um
initial model is so typically we when we
talk about training this reward model we
have trained on certain completions
which are sampled from this initial
distribution so we know the reward model
will be somewhat reliable in that
distribution so we're just going to
Simply add a penalty which tells us that
you should not drift too far away from
the initial distribution and just to go
over this we want to maximize the
objective where we have RMF which is our
learned one model but we're going to add
this term beta log ratio and the ratio
is our the model we're optimizing P
Theta and our initial model PP PT and
what this says is that if we assign a
much higher probability to certain
completion as compared to our pre-train
model you're going to add an
increasingly large penalty to
it and simply you're paying a price for
drifting too far from initial
distribution if you guys have taken like
machine learning this the expectation of
this quantity can is exactly the cbak LI
Li Divergence or k Divergence between P
Theta and PPT so you're penalizing
drifting between two distributions go
forhead question shouldn't you also do
this like add a penalty in the previous
version where you had to find huning or
is this only relevant for the RL HF
that's a good question so um I think
people do add some kinds of
regularization in fine tuning it's not
nearly not as critical when you're doing
this with RL like the incentive is to
exploit this reward model as well as
much as possible and we'll see examples
where like the Learned reward predicts
like it's doing really well but the true
reward models are completely garbage so
it's much more important in this
optimization cool
so now this assume does this course does
not assume background on reinforcement
learning so we're not going to go into
reinforce learning but I just want to
give a very high level intuition about
how this works and reinforcement
learning is not typically just used for
language model it's been applied to
several uh domains of Interest game
playing agents re um robotics developing
chip designs and so on and the interest
between like RL and model LMS it's also
like dates back to roughly like 2016 as
well but like it's been really
successful recently and especially with
the success of rlf
um the general idea is that we're going
to use our model that we're optimizing
to generate several completions for an
instruction um we're going to compute
the reward under our learned reward
model and then we're going to simply try
and like update the update our model to
increase the probability on the high
reward completions so when we sample a
model we'll see completions of varing
quality and we'll see some good
completions good summaries for our task
some bad summaries for our task and
we'll try to update our log
probabilities in a way such that uh the
reward for when you use a updated model
you're typically in the higher reward
region does the high level summary like
make
sense
cool and rhf is incredibly successful I
think this is a very good example of um
this is the same summarization example
and I think the key Point here is that
the performance improves by increasing
the model size for sure we have seen
this in many different example what you
can actually see is that even very small
models can outperform human completions
if you train it with with rlf and this
is exactly the result you see here the
reference summaries are human generated
and when you evaluate when you ask
humans which ones they prefer they often
prefer the model generated summary over
the human generated summary and this is
something you only observe with rlf even
at small scales and again the same
scaling phenomena still holds here
bigger models do become more responsive
but are of itself is very impactful
here
cool the problem with rlf is that it's
just incredibly complex like um I gave
you a very high level summary that's
like doesn't that there's whole courses
on this for a reason um so it just and
this image is not for you to understand
it's just completely to intimidate you
um
so um you want to fit a value function
to something there's you have to sample
the model a lot it can be sensitive to a
lot of hyperparameters so there's a lot
that goes on here and yeah um if you
start implementing an rlf pipeline it
can be very hard and this is the reason
why like a lot of rlf was restricted to
very very like high compute High
resource places and it was not very
accessible so what we're going to talk
about and cover in this course is
something called direct preference
optimization which is a much simpler
alternative to R LF and hopefully like
that's much more accessible but but
please bear with me there will be a lot
of math on here but the end goal of the
math is to make come up with a very
simple algorithm so hopefully like it's
um and feel free to stop me and ask me
questions you need in terms of like gbt
4 versus three like how much do the
number of parameters in the base model
help with like need to reduce the number
of parameters or like in order sorry R
the number of like examples from humans
for RFS that work
well yeah that's a really good question
so generally speaking as the if you hold
the data set size constant and simply
increase the mod size it will improve
quite a lot sure but the nice thing is
that you can reuse the data and you can
keep adding data yeah uh as you keep
like scaling models up so typically like
nobody tries to like reduce the amount
of data collection yeah right you just
keep increasing both the things
out cool so we talked about rlf and the
current pipeline is some something like
um we train a reward model on the
comparison data that we have seen so far
and we're going to optimize we're going
to start with our pre-train our
instruction tune model and convert it
into an rlf model using the
reinforcement learning
techniques now the really the key idea
in direct preference optimization is
what if we could just simply write a
reward model in terms of our language
model itself now to intuitively
understand that like what is going on a
language model is assigning
probabilities to whatever is the most
plausible completion next but those
plausible completions might not be what
we intended but you could restrict the
probability simply to the completions
that a human might like and then the log
probabilities of your model might
represent something which the humans
might like and not just some arbitrary
completion on the internet so there is a
direct correspondence between the log
probability that a language model
assigns and how much a human might like
the answer they can have like a direct
correspondence in them and this is not
some arbitrary intuition that I'm trying
to like come up with we will derive this
mathematically so the general idea with
direct preference optimization is going
to be we're going to write down reward
model in terms of our language model and
now that we can write our reward model
in terms of our language model we can
simply solve directly fit our reward
model to the preference data we have and
we don't need to do the RL Step at all
so we started off with some preference
data and we simply fit our reward model
to it which directly optimiz as the
language
parameters and maybe at a high level why
is this like even possible like we did
this like really cumbersome process with
fitting a reward model and optimizing it
but in the whole process the only
external information that was being
added to the system like was human
labels labels on the preference data
when we optimize a learned reward model
there's no new information being added
into the system so this is why something
like this is even possible for quite a
few years this was not obvious obvious
but like as you will see like some of
these results like start to make sense
so we're going to derive direct
preference
optimization I'll I'll be after I'll be
here after the class as well if you have
questions but I'll hopefully like this
is clear
so yes um we discussed that we wanted to
solve this expected reward problem where
we want to maximize the expected reward
but we subtract this term which is the
beta log ratio which essentially
penalizes the distance between where our
current model is and where we started
off so we don't want to drift too far
away from our um from where we
started now it turns out that this
specific problem instead of doing like
an iterative routine um there's actually
a close form solution to this problem so
the close form solution looks something
like this um again if you have seen the
boltzman distribution or something to
that effect before this is very
basically the same idea but the idea is
this that we're going to take a
pre-train distribution PPT y given X and
we're going to rade the distribution by
the expected
reward so if if if a completion has a
very high reward it's going to have a
higher probability mass and if it has a
lower reward it's going to have a lower
probability mass and it's determined by
the expected reward and beta is a
hyperparameter which essentially governs
like what is the trade-off between the
reward model and the constraint and as
beta becomes lower and lower you're
going to start paying more and more
attention to the reward
model so the probabilities look
something like this and there's this
like really annoying term this ZX and
the reason why it exists is that the
numerator by itself is not normalized
it's not a probability distribution so
to construct like an actual probability
distribution you have to normalize it
and ZX is simply just this
normalization so if we write ZX out is
the sum of all y okay yeah and that's
exactly like it's some overall wise for
a given instruction and that's exactly
why this is very pesky is like it's
intractable if I take an instruction and
try to sum over every possible
completion and not just like
syntactically correct ones every single
possible we have 50,000 tokens maybe
even more and the completions can go
arbitrary long so this space is
completely intractable this quantity is
not easy to approximate
even um so the main point here is that
you if you're given in a reward model
you can actually there does exist at
least a close form solution which tells
us what the optimal policy will look
like or optimal language model will look
like but if you do a little bit of
algebra just move some terms around take
a logarithm here or there I I promise
this is not very complicated you can
actually Express the reward model in
terms of the language model itself and I
think this term is reasonably intuitive
as well uh what it says is that um a
completion y hat has a high reward if
the model my optimal policy assigns a
higher probability to it relative to my
initialized model and this is scal by
Beta so the beta log ratio is what we're
looking at
here and the partition function let's
just ignore it for now but it's
intractable but the beta log ratio is
the key part
here is everyone following
along awesome okay so right now I'm
talking about optimal policies but
really like every policy is probably
optimal for some kind of a reward right
like this is mathematically true as well
so the important bit here is that you
can actually Express you take a current
policy take your initialized model and
you can get some kind of a reward model
out of it and this is the exact identity
which leads to this so reward model can
be expressed in terms of your language
model baring the log partition term
which we'll see what happens to it go
for sorry I don't know how you got like
why is it that we can swap because there
is a thing that we're trying to optimize
and how do p star turn into P yeah um
for now like we're not optimizing any
reward model okay all I'm saying is that
if I take my current language model it
is it probably represents some kind of a
reward model
implicitly because of this relationship
because this holds for every P star and
every reward model what I'm saying is
that like there if I plug in my current
language model it also represents some
kind of a reward model I'm not saying
it's optimal
okay but I want say because at the
beginning uh PRL is PPT yes and so we
just get that the reward is basically
zero and so what what do we do initially
it's zero but like we can optimize the
parameters okay okay yeah um yeah but
that's a good observation that it's
basically zero in the beginning but how
do we start optimizing
it I'll get to okay okay any other
questions so the idea is that given the
language model you have model such that
that makes the language model
op yes that's uh that's the next step
yes uh but the key idea is that like my
log my language model the probabilities
already implicitly Define a reward model
I think that's really the main point
here and this mathematical relationship
is
exact cool now like I mean I'm obviously
ignoring like the elephant in the room
here which is the partition function um
it's not going to magically vanish away
so like if this was just the beta log
ratio that would be really nice I can
compute all these quantities I know how
to compute the log probability under my
language model I know how to compute the
log probability under my pre-train model
and I can compute the reward score and I
can optimize this but I don't know what
to do about my Lo log partition function
this is where something fun happens so
recall what the the reward modeling
objective was uh when we started off
like we started off with the friends
Bradley Terry again and what we really
wanted to optimize was the reward
difference between the winning
completion and the losing
completion um and really like I mean
that's all we care about we don't care
about the exact reward itself what we
care about is maximizing the difference
between the the difference between
winning and losing completion and that's
actually really key here because if you
plug in the definition of of the RM
Theta there what you'll observe is that
the partition function actually just
cancels out now why does it cancel out
um the input is exactly the same the x
is actually exactly the same in the
difference so the partition function ZX
will just cancel out like it's the same
in both the terms so what you get is
that the reward difference between the
winning and losing completion is the
differences between the beta log ratio
for the winning and losing
completion you can plug in the terms you
can work it out it's fairly simple so
the partition function which was our
like um which was something we could not
address we could not compute actually
just simply vanished away I'm so sorry Z
doesn't appear in theary mod um but it
appears here in this equation so how
does plug in
model um so we're going to take this
equation uh the last line that you see
and we're going to plug in in place of
RMF
okay so um and in this the first loss
equation oh I see got yeah so the first
loss equation is the broadly ter loss
model
cool so this really is it like I mean
the key observation is we could express
our reward model in terms of language
model and our problems with the
partition function actually go away
because we were optimizing the Brad lary
model and um what you get is something
like this is that um we're going to
Express the loss function directly in
terms of our language model parameters
Theta and we're going to be able to
directly optimize on our data um without
doing any RL steps or not and this is
simply a binary classification problem
so we're really just trying to classify
whether an answer is good or bad and
that's really what we're
doing before I go on like people want to
like absorb this in like I mean feel
they're okay with it
I don't get where they why good and why
win and why lose come from are they
human and or they good question um it's
the same data set we started with in rlf
as well but the way the process works is
that you take a set of instructions and
get the model to generate some answers
and then you get humans to label which
answer they prefer so they're model
generated uh typically they can be human
generated as well but they're typically
model generated and then you get some
preference labels okay all you need is a
label saying which is a better
answer what do you lose here like you
must be losing some information because
of the lack of information about like
other you're canceling out your your
your because of the lack of uh any
information about the partition function
yeah you are bound to lose information
about like other possible completions
which you would have taken into account
in like standard rlf right
um that's a really good question I don't
think I'll be able to completely answer
this question in time but like partition
function is almost kind of a free
variable so I think the problem here is
that the reward model there think of
when you there's many reward models that
satisfy this optimization so there's a
free variable here that you can actually
completely remove and that's what this
optimization benefits from so think of
it this way like if I assign something a
reward of plus one and assign something
a reward of minus one that's basically
the same as saying as if it's a reward
of plus
99 and it will give you the same loss
right so um that scale doesn't that
shift invariant in a ways is that like
isn't that somehow like not what you
want though like like okay like if if
you have if you're actually training a
reward model right like 199 is like much
you should pay much less attention to
that as compared to
like one right
Zer or something what we're assuming is
our choice model here is like if a human
prefers something over the other like
the probability is governed only by the
difference between the rewards so that's
an assumption that every rlf also makes
and like DPO also makes now is that
assumption true not completely true but
like it it holds to a fairly large
degree but that's a good question
yeah cool um I'll move on and rest of
time um and really like I mean the goal
of this plot is to like we actually get
fairly performant models when we
optimize things with DPO um we so in
this plot I think the main thing that
you should look at is po which is the
typical rlf Pipeline and we are
evaluating the models for summarization
and we're comparing to human summaries
and what we find is that DP and BP sort
of do similarly but you're really not
losing much by just doing the DPO
procedure instead of R LF and that's
really compelling because DP is simply a
classif app ation loss instead of like a
whole reinforcement learning
procedure so I want to quickly summarize
um what we have seen thus far is that we
want to optimize for human preferences
so um and the way we do this is like
instead of relying on uncalibrated
scores we're getting comparison data and
feedback on that and we use this ranking
data to either do something like rlf
where we first fit a reward model and
optimize using reinforcement learning um
or we do something that like direct
preference optimization we simply take
the data set and do a classification
loss on that um and yeah like there's
trade offs in these algorithms like
people when they have a lot of
computational budget they typically
maybe go for rlf or some routine like
that but if you're really looking to get
the bank for your buck like I mean you
might want to go for DPO and if and
that's like probably going to work out
of the box um it's a still an active
area of research people are still trying
to understand how to like best work with
these algorithms so like I'm not making
any strong claims here but like both of
these algorithms are very effective DP
is just much simpler to work
with
cool um so yeah like I mean let's see
like we went through all this
instruction tuning rlf what do we get um
instruct GPD is the first model which
sort of followed this pipeline it
defined this pipeline so we got models
which did 30,000 or so tasks remember
when we were doing like only one task
and now we have scaled it up from th000
tasks to like 30,000 different task with
many many different examples so that's
like where we are with instruct GPT and
it follows this pipeline that we just
described in this case they're following
a specific rlf pipeline where we
explicitly fit a reward model and then
do some kind of a reinforcement learning
routine on top of it um and yeah like
the task collected from labelers looks
something like this um I leave it to
your imagination or you can look at the
details but how we started off with this
model was something like completions we
see from G GPD 3 uh which you know
explained the moon Ling to sixer and
like it is not really following the
instructions but instruct GPD will give
you something which is Meaningful so
it's inferring what a user wanted from
the specific instruction and it's
converting to a realistic answer that a
user might
like and yeah these are just more
examples of what an instruct GPD like
model would do whereas your base model
might not follow the instructions to
your desired intentions
and yeah like we went from instruct GPD
to chart GPD and it was essentially this
pipeline um the key difference here is
that it is still doing the instruction
tuning but it is more optimized for
dialogue more optimized for interacting
with users so the core algorithmic
techniques that we discussed today are
what give us CH GPD but you have to be
really careful about the kind of data
you're training on and that's really the
whole game um but this is the foundation
for CH GPD
and yeah it it follows the same pipeline
as well and you might look at you might
interact with ch gbd I'm sure you all
have interacted with it some form or not
but like this is an example of what a CH
gbd interaction might look
like um you want to make a gen Z so like
I mean you can you know the idea here is
that it's like very good at responding
to instructions and intent this is not
something that we could like even fuse
shot in very easily uh these are kind of
instructions are hard to come examples
for but like this is probably not
something to trained on either but it's
able to like infer the intent and
generalize very very nicely and that's
something I find personally very
remarkable cool and there's been a lot
of progress on the open source front as
well so like DPO is much simpler and
much more efficient and essentially all
the open source models these days are
using DPO so this is a leaderboard that
is maintained by hugging hugging face a
so like I mean N9 out of 10 more models
here are trained with DPO so that's been
something that's been enabled the open
source Community to instruction tune
their model betters as well and same is
being used in many production models now
as well mistol is using DPO llama 3 used
DPO so these are very very strong models
which are nearly gp4 level and they're
also like starting to use um these
algorithms as well and something that's
very cool cool to see is like like we
went through all this like optimization
and like I mean math and stuff but what
is really fundamentally changing in the
behavior and I think this is a really
good example is that if you simply ask
an instruction for and ask for an sft
output from an instruction tune model
you'll get something like this but when
you RL of the model you actually get a
lot more details in your answer and
they'll probably organize the answers a
little better and there's something that
they maybe humans prefer that's why it's
an property that is emerging in these
model but it's something that's a very
clear difference between simply
instruction tude models and some models
which are
rft so yeah um we discuss like this
whole rlf routine where we are directly
modeling the preferences and we are
generalizing Beyond label data um and we
also discussed RL can be very tricky to
um correctly Implement though DPO sort
of implements this or like avoid some of
these issue and we briefly also touched
upon the idea of reward model and reward
hacking um and when you're optimizing
for learned reward models you will often
see this example is that there's a way
for it to just simply crash into um the
object some keep repe repetitively
crashing the board to get more and more
points that wasn't the goal of this game
so um this is a very common example that
is shown for reward hacking if you do
not specify Rewards well the models can
like learn weird behaviors which are not
your desired intent and there's
something a lot of people worry about as
well um part of the reason is
reinforcement learning is a very strong
optimization algorithm it's at the heart
of alpha go Alpha zero uh which like
results in superhuman models so you have
to be careful about how you specify
things and the other thing is like even
optimizing for human preferences is
often not the right thing because humans
are not do not always like things which
are in their best interest so something
that emerges is that they like
authoritative and helpful answers but
they often like don't necessarily like
truthful answers
so one property that happens is like is
that they'll prefer authoritativeness
more than correctness which is maybe
like not something nice please go ahead
on those lines I'm curious if maybe like
chbt being so like now widely used by
the public will maybe change the like
how people were like made the rewards
because I at least feel like now when I
go to chat I TP something it gives me
five like detailed paragraphs of
information sometimes I'm just annoyed
by that that's not what I wanted but
maybe in the original reward function in
the original people actually pref that
and nower it less yeah um that's a great
point because like as these models like
integrate more and more into our system
they're going to collect more and more
data and they will like pick up on
things maybe undesirable things as well
um as far as I understand chbd is really
cutting down on the verbosity which is
like a huge issue that all of these
models are trying to cut down on and
they are dealing with that um part of
the reason why that emerges is that when
you collect preference data at scale
people are not necessarily reading the
answers the turkers might just simply
choose the longer answer and that's a
property that actually goes into these
models so but hopefully like these
things will improve over time as they
get more feedb and yeah hallucinations
is not a problem that is going to go
away with RL and we talked a bit about
reward hacking as well um biases from
things and so on but hopefully like I
mean what I want to conclude out is like
we started with pre-trained
models we we had these things which
could predict text and we got chargy GPD
and hopefully like it's a little more
clear how we go from something like that
to chat
GPD and that's I'll end
here thanks