Uh welcome to the second lecture of our
current offering of CS25 Transformers
United. So this will be the first
lecture featuring an external speaker.
Um so the rest of the course will have
um folks come in and talk about you know
the state-of-the-art and cool research
they're doing um as part of their work.
So we have an exciting lineup of
speakers for you guys for the rest of
the quarter. Um, so I'm delighted today
to have uh Karina um from OpenAI. Um, so
she works on both product and research
there. Um, and also previously worked at
Anthropic. Um, so I'll let her take it
from here. Thank you.
Should I um, can everybody hear?
Cool. Let's see.
So before I start this talk, I would
love to set a tone for I'm not here to
lecture you, but uh I would love to have
much more collaborative and interactive
session. Um, and I do hear I've heard a
lot of, you know, people kind of
concerning about AI and the future of
AI. And I understand that the
development of a GI is both scary and
exhilarating. And if anything I would
love to get for you to get out from this
talk is the fact that I think everybody
can have like very meaningful um future
and everybody can like build something
really really cool with an AI and as a
part of this journey. Um cool. So before
I start with the talk uh there'll be all
about how ARAL is a co-design of product
and research and you know we are
shifting both in the labs we're shifting
the focus towards more of a frontier
product research where the tasks that we
teach the models are becoming much more
real world
tasks. So, um, and before we get
started, I'll just like share some of
the vignettes of like what I'm really,
really excited about the future of AI
and what the AI is capable of right now
that can inspire
everybody. Um, so the first one is
actually education. I'm actually really
really excited about the fact that AI
can democratize education. Here's an
example of me asking PT to explain the
goian. um distribution and then um was
and in canvas it creates you know the
code itself in order to visualize for
me. So it explains in text and then I
ask it to write in code and then you can
render the code in order to visualize
it. So in a way it becomes much more a
little bit
personalized. The second demo is also
something that a lot of people might
want to use it. So let's let's see if
you take a screenshot from the paper and
you want to understand what's going on
and um the model can go and explain in a
separate canvas that's like another
feature in CHPT and then then you can
start to have much more interactive
conversation with the model by selecting
very um certain like things and try to
like uh ask more questions you know
follow-up questions. So in a way when
chatpt came out to be uh first in 2022
it was purely conversational UI it was
mostly chat and as the use cases kind of
grown from the product itself you know
there was no expectation of how people
would use chatd at that time but over
time you've seen a lot of people started
using it for code generation for writing
and long form writing it became very
obvious that the interface of chat was
kind of very limited so Um, Canvas is
kind of like the first attempt uh of um
of our team to break out from the cycle
in order to allow people to have much
more fine grain collaboration with AI.
Um and actually today uh Antarpic
published a small report uh around the
education and how people use uh claude
for education and it's very interesting
to see the correlation between the US
bachelor's degrees and the way people
use um um yeah use cases. So you can see
there's a huge difference between like
computer science there.
Um, another thing that I'm really really
excited about the AIS is that anyone can
create their own tools for themselves,
for their friends, for the family or
even run their business. And um, you
know, the models now can generate a lot
of front-end code and then you can
render that code inside the canvas and
then iterate on it and have much more
visual representation of things. Um, you
know, on Twitter, I've seen a lot of
people creating ex like very very
personalized and customized tools that
they really really want, even like games
like
chess. And with recent image and uh
image generation model from
um open AAI you can literally sketch
anything um on with your own hands and
then recreate or kind of realize what
you're dreaming of h in within in image
and in the style that you really really
want. So I do really hope that the
creativity, the human creativity and how
AI tools can help anyone to become
creatives or be an artist um in a way
that was not possible
before. Another thing that I've tried
actually on the mobile is to create a
mini game um and you can easily do that
in canvas. So I ask to just like
generate me, you know, a react app of
interesting game because I'm on the
plane and then the model does
that. And I do hope that in the future
instead of me prompting it to generate a
game, it will kind of like be more
proactive and have this kind of
personalization
um as AI become more of a companion to
humans. Um and uh an exciting thing um
about touchp is that the
compositionality of different
capabilities that can allow you to
augment like human creativity. So here I
can I asked um to generate an image of
the UI and then uh sorry
um generate an image of an of UI and
then ask the model to kind of implement
this and you can do that literally in
canvas right now and like it can render
it's not um it's just a front end it
doesn't have full kind of stack
engineering um but you know you can do
some some of the things like this you
can compose different tools and compose
in a way that was was never possible
before. So I do hope that ideas like
this will be very very powerful and
everybody in this room can play with
those things. Um and actually how did we
get there and I think there are like two
main scaling paradigms that helped us to
get there. The first one is next token
prediction obviously versus a
pre-training scaling paradigm um where
the model kind of becomes like a world
building machine understanding the world
in a much better scale um you know but
it becomes the the next token prediction
uh works really really good at certain
tasks but it becomes harder at tasks
like writing if the model predicts a
wrong to next token it can kind of the
coherence of the plot thought will just
be lost in the pertaining stage and
maybe you kind of want to recover this
in reinforcement learning. And the next
second paradigm that has happened um is
um RL on a chain of thought for more
complex uh task and this is the
reasoning work from open AI and now it's
being adopted by a lot of different labs
and um I do think this is scaling RL is
in itself is another paradigm that we
can train the models on the axis um to
and especially for the real world task
that was never possible before. So all
the agent work um agents like operator
deep research um other agents are kind
of like trained on this kind of new
paradigm of on the chain of thoughts.
So yeah, I I I want to like uh finish
this section of like vignette of like
yeah build create build and make
something wonderful in this world and I
hope like people be more inspired rather
than scared that AI is going to take
their jobs or kind of remove their
creativity. Instead I feel like people
can become more more powerful with with
their imaginations with these
tools.
So I currently work at OpenAI. Before
that I worked at Antropic and um I was
kind of like at the intersection of
product and research. When I first came
to Antropic I was a product engineer and
then over time I switched to research
engineering. So my gra background is
mostly both in product and research now.
And what I've learned over and over
across different projects is that there
are two kind of main ways of building
research driven products. And the first
one um is when you have unfamiliar
capability of the model your job might
be to create familiar form factor for
that unfamiliar capability and an
examples of that could be um you know
chargunded contexts from cloud was like
this and I'll share let's dive deeper
into this actually the early prototypes
that I've done before joining any lab
was actually working with a clip um uh
which is
contestive model and um it's like image
um text to image basically and um I
fine- tuned clip a little bit on the
images that I was excited about and I
think this is the prototype of you know
fashion search um I think some some
people you know people kind of like it
it went viral on Twitter and and I feel
like that's because people really found
some usefulness if you bring some like
clip um technology into some form factor
that people will like and so um I think
a lot of the product work is around that
like like this it's like if the model
has a certain capability that was never
possible before how do we create this
new um form factor same happened with
100k context when claude um started
being able to you know consume the
entire books
Um you can imagine to have various form
factors file uploads is just like very
general and something really familiar to
people that can just like dump the
entire documents um into cloud and ask
follow-up questions. But you can imagine
other form factors for this like
infinite chats and in a way it's like
infinite memory um as a way to kind of
like take this 100k context into some
form factor. So you can like exercise
this product thinking by um thinking of
like novel ways that people can interact
um with this novel technology. Um
another example this is more speculative
it wasn't deployed anywhere um is if the
model has kind of have a sense of
self-calibration
uh or um it's also called P I know if
the model knows the confidence of the
answer that it knows. So for example, if
I'm really really confident in this
claim and then my confidence may be uh
85%. Then maybe there's a way for the
interface to highlight that um maybe the
um more highlighted versions is much
more confident um kind of much more
confident uh claims and less highlighted
is um kind of less less uh uh
confidence. So in a way you can imagine
if the model yeah you can like think of
okay if if you train the model to be
really good at like self calibration how
do we then represent that to the humans
and if if anything will it be useful um
for
humans. Same happened with uh when we
were trying to deploy 01 preview. Um the
chain of thought itself is a very alien
thing and um a lot of people were okay
how do you bring along humans with
models thinking right if the model if if
the human needs to wait for chain of
thought for like two minutes or five
minutes that's kind of boring and um
people don't I think it's just like more
of a how would people perceive the model
thoughts and one thing that we did uh is
actually we wanted to create the
streaming uh kind of interaction. Um so
the model would always stream its
thoughts ephemeral. Um and we train the
model to do that. Um so in a way that
was chain of thought is an alien
technology is an alien artifact of the
model and then trying to figure out like
how do we best bring to the humans um is
another way of thinking of uh building
product. Okay. So another way the second
way of
building research um during products is
actually start with a deep belief in
what you want to make um with either
from a product perspective or um kind of
like vision um and literally make the
model do that. Okay. So I feel like this
is more of a common thing. Um so we can
go through some examples.
Um before Antaric I worked at the New
York Times and uh in a lot of ways we
were thinking about how to represent
information uh to people and like how do
we add layer of context to the product
and coverage and at that time we were
all working on like elections and uh we
only had tools like NLP but you can
imagine this idea this concept could
have extended given the current tools of
AI to have much more dynamic um
representation know dynamic UIs that
people could um consume the content
better. Same when I was working on this
um product uh the command line the
terminal the new terminal uh I think it
would be much much richer if you could
have integrated autocomp completion or
some of the benefits of GPT3 at that
time um into the product itself. Um and
so we wanted to have it was a vision of
like having much more humane command
line for people to for junior engineers
to actually um be more well equipped. Um
yeah and then like early prototypes
around with GBD3 even though it was just
next token prediction um how do I make a
writing IDE uh with GBD3 and at that
time it was just you know trying to um
whenever I type it would autocomplete my
thoughts almost. So those ideas were
kind of present early days with the
technology was coming out. Um and yeah
and I feel like when I was at Antabric I
kind of realized that and actually if
you want to create like new interaction
paradigm of interfaces you actually need
to train the model um for that. Um,
another example of what we did with
claude, which I don't think a lot of
people know, um, is when cloud generates
titles is actually has some
micropersonalization. So, it takes the
style uh, the writing style of the user
and then generates a title in the same
style of the user. So, you can imagine
sort of like interesting microproization
that you could create um, within the
products themselves. And
um another project was Claude and Slack
and that was the vision of cloud
becoming a first virtual teammate. It
was back in 2022. Um and you know Slack
was is a very very natural workspace
where people collaborate and um you can
you know imagine a cloud model to be
able to jump into the threads and
suggest new things or sometimes um you
know cloud was really really good at uh
summarizing the what's what went what's
going on in within this channel at the
high volume content. Um and so this was
the first kind of vision and the first
attempt of making cloud being a virtual
super assistant being and being able to
like use different
tools and uh my first one of the first
projects at OpenAI was around canvas. Um
so that was you know that was in the
same spirit of breaking out from the
chat interface to something different
and we wanted to create um much more
human AI collaborative and flexible
affordance that will scale uh with new
modalities. So canvas is not just like a
thing that you can write into this. It's
also a thing that the model can write
into this and the model can render code
and another model can check and you can
create like the interfaces that will
scale with new model capabilities and
other tools that will happen.
So one thing one interesting things um
about canvas is that we actually
postrained the model purely on synthetic
data and um you know we live in the age
where um a lot of most powerful
reasoning models um can be distilled via
APIs and this like distillation is a a
very powerful idea uh of having a
student and teacher and have a teacher
um to teach things to a smaller model.
So we've trained um you know this model
to become of a collaborator but what
does it mean for a model to become a
collaborator and how do we actually make
evals for this right um so one thing
that we wanted to kind of decompose is
that teaching the model to use a tool is
kind of different behavior from uh
having a model to be proactive or act as
a collaborator. Um so teaching a tool in
itself is also have a nuanced kind of
behavior. So one thing that we um had to
calibrate the model on is when to
entirely rewrite the document versus
when to uh if you look at the canvas
sometimes the model can just
specifically select sections and delete
those and rewrite them uh in a much more
fine grain way instead of like rewriting
everything. um when um you know to
create uh code in canvas versus um ask
like a python tool call. So it's like
different tools compositionality
um is happening. So it's a lot of work
around um teaching the behaviors for the
models for this
um and you have you can employ different
um techniques for this and I can I can
share a little bit more uh how we did
with cloud um so another project that we
did was uh it's called tasks and you
know everybody is familiar with the idea
of having reminders or to-do lists and
um the model can now maybe schedule
tasks for you. Uh but the most important
thing about it is the tasks itself is
very very diverse and it's not just you
know just a reminder of your to-do list.
It can create stories for you every day
or it can continue the story from the
previous day. So you can imagine this
like the modularity of tool compositions
but it's very powerful in product.
Um okay
so let's go to the case study of the
model behavior in more specifically.
Um so I really want to like dive deep
into the idea of how do we shape the
models and why how do you post train the
models on the behaviors that you want.
Um and you know I think to be more
specific and be grounded in the real
world uh use case I'll share more uh how
we might want to think about shaping the
um kind of behavior of the model uh
around refusals.
So you know let's let's have we we it's
also like the second way of making the
product where we have this um kind of
vision of how the model should behave
and that vision is also grounded by the
you know cross functional collaboration
between different teams on how you want
the model to respond to various users.
Um so one particular thing that you can
imagine is like the model should have
more opinions but with caveats. It
should give opinions but with caveats.
So what does it mean actually? So the
model maybe needs to be more decisive
um when asked direct questions. And um
let's say one thing that we've seen with
RHF is that the model is very sick
authentic back like early days in like
2022 203 the model would just agree with
everything you would say. And so how do
we actually teach the model to be more
not to do that and be more nuanced? Um
another thing that was annoying uh is is
that like the model says I don't
actually have a point of view. um and uh
is just just willing to chat with
people. But actually maybe the model
should have some views on certain
things.
Um yeah and then sometimes the model
could indicate when when things are just
opinions um and notes its own biases and
inconsistencies and it should
acknowledge kind of have like
self-nowledge of what it knows and what
it thinks is right and not right. And I
think the model back like back in 2022
cloud 1.3 uh didn't really have like any
thoughtful responses for things like
philosophy uh like ethical questions. So
uh you can imagine chain the model um on
the behavior that would be much more
nuanced than the philosophical
questions. Um yeah and like other
behaviors that you might want to encode
in your model. So you kind of like list
out all the various things that you
would like a model to behave. So maybe
like the model can have better knowledge
of who it is and what it's capable of.
Um because we've seen in the product a
lot of people just like ask the model
about its features and oftentimes it
doesn't know. Um
yeah and um let's dive deep into the uh
most specific example. So cloud 2.1 I
don't know if if anybody remembers um
but when it was launched I think it was
um kind of had the issue of like over
refusals
um yeah like 2.1 would refuse tasks that
superficially sounded harmful but
actually were not and um you know it
wasn't just caused by a single source of
data. Uh so we had to like investigate
um and you know we knew that it was
fixable because for some reason
something was 2.1 led to some refusals
on benign prompts than 2.0. So you kind
of have like a really good baseline for
experimentation and debugging. And
actually the way you debug the model
behavior is actually very similar to how
you would want to debug software.
Um and um and the way we would approach
this is um okay how do we actually craft
this morning answer? Um so the first
principles that we had is like maybe the
model should assume terrible
interpretation of what the person is
asking without being harmful. Um so
instead of you know crafted dialogue
between two characters who are planning
a complex heist the model would refuse
because it's not comfortable with that
but the model should have much more
charitable interpretation and you know
this is a creative writing prompt so
probably it should respond. Um another
principles that we've kind of like
thought about is like how do we actually
use non-verbal communication nonviolent
uh communication principles.
um you know maybe the model should um
refuse um more like I statements instead
of and take responsibility for its own
refusal instead of saying you statements
or any judgment to the user.
Um ask if the user would be willing to
make some changes so clot can be more
comfortable with its boundaries. That's
another kind of like very nuanced
behavior we wanted to teach the model.
So um you know then the model needs to
know what its boundaries are. Um and
this is like much more of a meta kind of
post training learning. Um yeah and also
like acknowledges impact like I know
this may be annoying to you and this is
like much more empathetic answer than
saying you know um I I don't want to
respond to this.
Um and then you know I think we've kind
of came up with different like refusal
tonomy there are like benign uh of
refusals on like harmless prompts um
there were creative writing with
refusals um and uh there actually some
of the interesting refusals were around
um tool calls or function calls um it
might have access uh had a tool to view
a note but actually would say I can't
see your note um and why is this
happening. Um yeah
so other yeah other uh taxonomies of
refusals at that time was like you know
long document attachments the if I
upload the document it would just say
like I don't have a capability to read
this document like why um so something
in the data might have been causing this
um and misdirected refusals um when they
um you know it kind of like took
interpretation
um of the user and it should have had
like much more charitable charitable
view of the user during um
yeah. So you kind of construct this like
categories um of various refusals
because you know if it's in every
behavior or like capability that you
want to like post in the model you have
like various use cases and various edge
cases and you kind of want to be
approached within more nuance. Um and
yeah like so the first thing in every
research project is like how do we
actually what evolves do we build to
trust and like what evolves we would
trust. Um and there are for subjective
things like this or for class obviously
evals for certain task class of tasks
like math would be very very different
from what is here. Um so in terms of
refusals um how did we construct the
emails? Well, first is like product of
flywheel, right? Like we have all the
users or manually collected prompts that
would induce refusals. Uh we can also
like sendarily generate diverse prompts
on the borderline between harmfulness
and helpfulness and those are prompts
are around like creative writing um like
edgy creative writing as we call it. Um
and you can also use other evals. you
kind of want to construct a suit of evol
um like X test with like 200
non-malicious prompts um wild chat data
set um a collection of diverse user
chatb interactions with ambiguous
requests topic switching political
discussions so you can also um use some
of the open source benchmarks
um yeah and I think like general
approaches not particular what has
happened with cloud but like more of a
general approaches to the model behavior
pro training is that you know you kind
want to like look at the data, clean up
the data. Um, you might want to consider
either have like collect targeted human
feedback collection for supervised
fine-tuning or preference modeling,
reward modeling. Or you might not want
to do that because human feedback is
very costly. And now especially with
reasoning models um right you might want
to just not have any human feedback and
control with like synthetically
generating some of the behavioral
changes uh like a preference data to
train reward models um and do our so I
think uh at that time you know I think
this is like more employing uh
constitutional AI uh principles of those
uh anti-refusal behaviors and create a
preference data where you only change
one particular feature within your
pairs, let's say, of preferences. You
only want to control um one change that
in that pair uh to have much more
control over the revoid model data
because if you can like a dumb the
dumbest simplest thing that you can do
is like take um a preference like take a
response from model A and take a
response of model B and prefer B over A.
But um it doesn't necessarily reduce um
affect the spirious features that the
model will learn that you don't want
actually want to. Um so you kind of want
to craft this distribution. Um yeah this
is mostly around like crafting the
distribution of the data that you want.
Um and actually yeah look at the data
like you would debug software like each
refusal might be caused by different
data sets right if it's like a tool
called refusal maybe it came from some
kind of self-nowledge data that it would
teach that the model doesn't have a
physical body and uh the model might
just refuse to set an alarm um because
it doesn't have a physical body but
actually it does have a tool to set an
arm, right? So, it it has some this
contradictory data that might affect VR
model behaviors. Um, yeah, also like
long dog refusals like this. Um, with
creative writing fusels, it's like more
of a this balanced um challenging act
between like safety and harmfulness uh
data and helpfulness
data. Um, in cloud 3 model, Kardy
actually uh wrote everything about this.
Um, you know, models that are trained to
be more helpful and responsive to user
requests may also lean towards harmful
behaviors like sharing information that
violates the policy. And conversely,
when models just overindex on
harmlessness can tend towards not
sharing any information with users,
which in itself makes the model very
unusable. Um so navigating this
balancing act is very challenging um and
works. So yeah and this is the plots of
uh what we did and the results of cloud
2.1 and cloud 3 at that time. Um and
yeah like you kind of want to like v
check uh the responses. So uh when we
asked to draft like fictional science
sci-fi novel about surveillance system
actually three would respond in much
more it will respond instead of like um
refusing. Same
here. Uh yeah mostly for creative
writing
um um
tasks. Cool. um my third section um of
the talk. So before we go before I jump
into this um I would love to invite you
if anybody has any questions or um I
don't want to like mumble all along. Um
anything I can just move on.
Yeah. I'm curious like what's your
process that you guys follow in order to
like see how new thing you're trying to
push out?
How do you go from launching that
particular feature or behavior to
actually like inducing that into models
like like I Yeah, I um you know it's um
supposed to call like the risking. So um
you might want to you know if this is
your project then you might want to
think of what kind of data you want to
collect and how you would want to
collect the data and then uh you can
take like uh the base config or um train
a model um the same way as you know
let's say you want to make a change in
like for O you might want to take the
for model and add your data change and
then retrain the model again and then
see the effect on the evolves that you
will build. Um there are other m much
more cheaper approaches
um like incremental like training on top
of um the for let's say um yeah so like
using either SFT so like some of the
choices that you will have to make is
either you want to change in um like
supervised fine-tuning uh stage or you
might want to have retrained reward
model or um create a new kind of like
evaluate a greater
um for that particular task. And then
you can like create prompts in our own
environment and then um exercise those
um exercise that scale for the model and
then see if the model learns over the
course of training and if it doesn't um
you know you then look at the bunch of
like plots and you know your plot might
go up but maybe some other plots might
go down. So you kind of want to like
calibrate um and fix those or the Yeah,
it's a very complex
um as more and more tools and as more
things we teach the model becomes much
more uh kind of uncontrollable almost.
Um
yeah cool. Um the third section is more
about um the point that how you
construct RL environment and rewards is
how your product will work.
Um you know I think real world use cases
is what creates the complexity of our
environment and the complexity comes
from you know the teaching the model to
complete hard tasks and oftentimes hard
tasks are require much more than just
answering the question. They require
tools like search um code tools uh
computer use tools uh reasoning over a
long context um and kind of like reward
design that you want to shape um and I
think maybe it's obvious maybe it's not
obvious but let's say you know as we
teach the models for the model to become
very useful we actually need to teach
the models on useful things and um we
can think of like uh let's say we want
to teach the model to be uh like a soft
engineer then okay what does it actually
mean does it mean it like creates really
good PRs then your task distribution
will be on that and how do you evaluate
what is a good PR what is not good PR um
is actually isn't itself more of a can
be also like a product thinking work um
same we can dive deeper into the
creative storyteller right like if you
want to teach the model to be uh good at
writing. Actually, what does it mean for
a human to be a good writer? Well, they
actually need some kind of tool to draft
and edit the thoughts and like have
multiple days to do that. And maybe the
model should be able to do that. Uh
maybe the model should have a tool that
where you can like edit and draft. And
oftentimes for creatives, you know,
people go observe the world for like a
long like sometimes they like connect
the dot like the dots are getting
connected in a very random times and
maybe you want to expose the model to
never ending uh kind of search engine
like the model should be able to always
have access to the latest state of the
world. uh and then um maybe over the
course of let's say a week of being
exposed to latest thing that is
happening in the world the model can
start reflecting on the world and like
write something um and maybe that's like
much more natural process of writing
than just like ask or prompt it like
write about XYZ
um and we are shifting towards much more
uh more complex uh kind of interactions
within the environments so the
multiplayer interactions right it's not
just one user communicates with one
model but it might be the case that
multiple users multiplayer collaboration
that can happen with uh a model. So if
I'm a um product designer and you're a
product manager, we collaborating on
something and we want to collaborate
with an agent to um make a new product
and this in itself is a task that you
can learn in our but each user has
different preferences and each user is
has different um things. So yeah, how do
you construct this environment is
actually important and uh you know
multi-aggendentic environments is um
more of uh the model debate with each
other or deliberate on like certain
topic to reach a conclusion. So you can
construct um I I think like multi-
agentic is like more more like alpha go
like uh kind of environments um where
they they like got reward by achieving
something um together.
Um so um I think in AI labs I feel like
we are also shifting um possibly the
focus from because we we kind of like
optimized so much around the class of
tasks that is like really easy to
measure like was it like math
competitive programming right and we're
shifting the focus maybe towards more
subjective class of tasks that is really
really hard to measure but that are
becoming much more important if AI
models get socially integrated in our
lives. Um, and more specifically, let's
say emotional intelligence, right? The
humans who use Chajbt uh use it so much
for things like coaching, therapy, uh
emotional but we don't actually have
much open source evolves on this and how
do we actually measure that is actually
becomes much more interesting question
um like social intelligence in voice
mode right I think it's one thing for
model to be intelligent in reason like
math and its reasoning another thing but
another axis of intelligence is when I
talk to a model in voice. Uh, it can
actually suggest something really
meaningful. It might just say like,
"Hey, I noticed you did XYZ. Maybe I
should create um a new tool for you."
So, I think it's a different kind of
like uh social like intelligence in that
way. Um, another class of task that I'm
interested in is uh writing. Obviously,
I think um models creativity. Um, you
know, writing is like really hard to
measure because it's so personal and
subjective. Um, but it's interesting to
think about can we make those tasks a
bit more objective? Um, you know,
everybody loves like some kind of like
sci-fi novel. Okay, what makes it really
really good? Um, so maybe there are
certain like rules, technological rules
or consistency of the world um that
people really like or the character
development. So you can like decompose
um those objective tasks into much more
objective. Same with like visual design
and aesthetics. Um and for the model to
generate something really aesthetically
interesting um it should know like the
basic principles of good visual design.
So those are like much more
objective. Yeah. And I think like this
is more of a kind of new kind new new
kind of product research that a lot of
people are starting doing is creating
new RL tasks and this is more of a
simulation of real world scenarios. Um
leveraging in context learning if you
want to teach like a new tool or
something. Um leveraging synthetic data
w distillation from stronger reasoning
models. Um yeah, you can think of like
inventing new model behavior and
interactions like multiplayer and also
incorporating product and user feedback
uh during the entire
process. Well, another axis of this work
is actually around reward design. Um how
do we teach the model? um like what kind
of feedback would I want to give to a
model so that it will learn how to
better operate in this real world
scenario use case and be more adapted in
social contexts and actually this is
this requires quite deep product
thinking right so we want to teach the
model um to have like followup like
meaningful follow-up questions but not
like overly being annoying or something
um so how do you reward for completing a
tasks in a way that makes that will make
a lot of sense in the product and will
shape um the product experience with the
user in the
future and obviously during that process
you will get into IO VR things like do
you have a question? Yes. So
wondering design for a lot of cases. I'm
just curious thinking about like kind of
inferred rewards from the data from like
a certain group of people that will have
some like internal reward you know like
the mechanism not guiding to make
decision and then you can use that to
sort of you know to inject such a
insight into your model design reward
like a universal rewarding model. Yeah,
I
think there are certainly various
approaches to how you construct a
reward, right? Like there is one um you
can construct very simple rewards. You
can also like train a reward model um
that will as yeah you can like train
like some kind of like inversed um
reward modeling um tasks.
Yeah. Um it depends on the tasks too. Uh
it depends on the like what kind of
thing that you want to like optimize the
model for.
Um yeah and um I think an interesting um
thing that you will discover during this
entire process is uh reward hacks which
is very very common in RAL and there are
many many different reasons why it's
happening. I actually really highly
recommend to read Lilian's blog about
reward hacking in RAL. It's very
comprehensive. Um there's reward hacking
is basically when um the model achieves
high reward for uh things that it
actually didn't do like it kind of
deceived. Um and especially right now as
more and more systems we use other AI
models LLM to be evaluators for policy
models. Actually an interesting the most
common like reward hack is when a policy
model tries to deceive uh to think that
deceive the evaluator model such that it
will think that the policy completed the
task or something. So um here's um an
example of like the code patch tool. So
the model is like to skip all the tests
you can define this function that always
skips so and then it passes um and it's
mo mostly interesting. There's a paper
recent paper from OpenAI around um this
like monitoring uh reasoning models for
misbehavior and an interesting finding
is that if you you actually don't want
to optimize chain of thought uh on being
because then the model will be much more
kind of hided its intent. Um so yeah
it's like very interesting paper on like
reward hacks and especially with like
more complex reasoning models the
complexity of reward hacks will also um
change um and especially let's say in
the soft engineering you might not want
to know what kind of code changed uh it
it made in order to create some certain
vulnerability right so you need actually
um more
um create like new affordances to have
like much higher like much more
trustworthier uh verification of the
model outputs. Um and this is like more
alignment problem
too. Okay. Um I'm almost done. I think
this is the fourth section. Um it's more
like vignettes uh in the future of human
AI interactions and how I think um about
things. Um obviously I made this graph
like a year ago and nobody cares about
MLU anymore. But I think this is to
communicate the fact that the cost of
reasoning is drastically decreasing and
it will only just be decreasing. Um and
this idea of like raw intelligence in
itself is just become so cheap that I I
think like anybody can create like
really useful and really amazing things
with those models um at pretty much low
cost.
um you know I yeah as I mentioned before
it's like um when we are entering the
age where it's really hard to verify AI
of course because I'm not an expert in
let's say medical um or financial
analysis like how do we actually teach
create like new audences for humans to
verify or edit models outputs um and
help them to teach the models um I do
think there's a a cool feature of like
dynamic generative UI. Um it's kind of
like invisible software creation on the
fly. So let's say you talk to a model
and you know I say like I want to learn
more about the solar system instead of
right now the model will just like
output text but I would want to believe
that in the future uh it would be much
more personalized. Let's say I'm a
visual thinker and you are more of a
listener. Like if you're a listener, it
will create maybe a podcast, but if I'm
a visual um person, it might want to
create me a picture or you know um like
a 3G 3GS visualization. Um yeah, this
idea of like uh this interface is like
ephemeral, it's like self moors depends
on understanding your intent and your
context. Um it's like deeply personal
personalized models. Um yeah, I'm also
excited about personalized access to
health care and education. I think it's
really um incredible um that anybody can
check their symptoms and with PD or
something and get like some advice. Um
and also like with that also comes like
some of the interesting like consumer
hardware um in the
future. And uh lastly is like our
relationship to the process of
storytelling will forever change like
the way we tell the stories the way we
will create new novels maybe co-writing
with like with models co-scripting new
films um I don't think like I think
there will be the new generation of
creative people who um will change our
relationship with storytelling and I I
would hope to think that the current
creatives creators don't are not scared
of the eye and more of open-minded to
use those tools for their
process. Yeah. Thank you.
Some questions.
Yeah. So, thanks Karina for the very
interesting talk. Um, so yeah, now we'll
open the floor to questions, a Q&A
session. So, um, we'll structure it more
openly. So, anything you want to ask her
about um research products um things
that OpenAI um that she can talk about
and so forth. And for the folks on Zoom,
feel free to ask questions in the chat.
Um and so we'll take a mix of Zoom and
in-person questions.
Thank you. Yeah.
Um, is there any like category of
like right now?
Yeah, there's like not enough. Yeah, I
mean I think yeah creative writing I
don't think like anybody
um yeah like
um a lot of researchers are really like
um working on problems where it's very
easy to evaluate I think um and I think
there is a class of problems there's
like subjective tasks like there's no
open like frontier benchmark for
creative writing or emotional
intelligence. Um, right. But you can
construct one if you want to. Um, yeah,
we can like brainstorm if that's
helpful. Yeah.
So you can't move as fast but they're
also important. Like would it be better
to just take all the researchers and put
them on the things that are objective
and you can like move very fast? Yeah, I
think this is um I I think moving fast
though is also as task becomes like much
more complex as we kind of like um
optimized everything out from uh kind of
easy tasks. Now we kind of want to like
teach the models for more low like
longer horizon tasks of software
engineering or uh kind of automating
like AI research right is in itself as a
very hard tasks um and you you know you
have like kind of have some milestones
maybe you can create benchmarks uh to
hit those milestones um yeah I do think
this is like you know
um I I think like this is all solvable
things and I don't think people should
be worried about like moving fast versus
like slow because I feel like everything
is moving fast these days. Yeah.
Um I had I mean I was thinking about
building a startup before joining
Anthropic was that project was
interalia. Um
well let's see I actually really like
one thing that I recently told someone
is like I would actually build something
around like particle collider I don't
know or biotech like I do think we need
larger particle collider than CERN then
somebody should be building one um
yeah because I feel like uh the models
will be able to build any product that
you imagine um Yeah.
Yeah.
Um the bottlenecks are repeat. Oh, the
question is what's the major bottlenecks
uh for OpenAI? Um
um I don't know. I'm not sure if like
faster execution should be solved with
more people versus
um like using AIS now to to help us move
faster if that makes sense. So I feel
like that's the bottleneck. I think
there's a lot of I I think right now we
are like in the middle of figuring a lot
of things out in order to like like I
feel like in a year or two that will
accelerate us so much more. I feel like
infrastructure is actually one of the
major bottlenecks right if you don't
build infrastructure with uh multimodel
like as a first class citizen then um
obviously all the multimodal things will
be much more um slow like u more
difficult so yeah in a way it's like in
for um figuring out like what to
prioritize at a given time because
sometimes you can say yes to everything
and then not having a focus time is also
I think yeah
Um, so what's your takes on context and
rubber
explores? Basically, when the model
check the turn's context and updates how
we should score the same parameter based
on that
turn. Wait. Um I'm a little bit confused
by this question. Um I think generally
like rubric based grading is um very
powerful and um you know as long as you
optimize um things that you want to
optimize and there's no reward hacks
then it's good.
Um how do you imagine AI will be used by
creatives if not just generating entire
works on their own? How will they be
integrated in their creative flow? Well,
um I think yeah, I think AI is is just
like right now maybe it's more like you
would use Figma or like tools like
Adobe. Um and I think in the future it's
more um maybe will be much more
co-creation with an AI rather than using
as a tool. Uh maybe we have like live
brainstorming and create things on the
fly and then publish it together. It's
like much more of a companion um work.
Cool. Other questions?
I mean I cannot think of any because the
way you can the way you teach model is
based on some of the human preferences
maybe right or like pair wise
comparisons. So essentially you can
almost teach anything uh to the model. I
do think the complexity will like the
complexity always arises with like tools
right and like if you give very
complicated tool um then you might want
to be then the diff like the learning is
like much more difficult so I feel like
um I do hope that almost anything can be
teachable in a yeah
um so I'm curious like now that you
bring up like the learning practice how
do you prevent the model from converging
into like the new like reference like
Airbnb listings all looking the same
like how do you inject some creativity
diversity? Yeah, I think this is an
interesting question. I think the the
choice um like what's my mind is um how
do you preserve and
[Music]
prote from the base model during the RL
and another way um is uh the reason why
we love our layoff like reinforcement
learning from AI feedback and create
synthetic generations of pair wise
comparisons let's say is because it can
induce the diversity that you really
want to teach on like distribution that
you care about uh that is not like the
mean average consumer um yeah because
sometimes like you know um average human
can prefer certain emojis or markdown
but actually you don't want the model to
behave like this so in a way you can
discourage the model from doing that. Um
yeah, so I feel like synthetic curation
like synthetic data generation is mostly
like curation of um that kind of
diversity. Um
yeah,
you guys are working with and like
figuring out what the issues are. How do
you go about diagnosing like problems
and like bugs in the models and like do
you do it qualitatively or is it more?
Yeah, I think it's a lot of qualitative
especially for the model behavioral like
refusals. Um
oh um how do I distill this question?
Oh yeah. Like how do you capture the
models implementations like something
automatic versus manual? Um I think
there's a lot of benefit of literally
playing with the model and uh look at
the outputs and see what are the
weirdnesses it has. There are definitely
like um maybe more automatic checks uh
and those are mostly like evolves,
right? Um but um and maybe you have an
eval that specifically checks with a
behavior that you really don't want. Um
and that might be helpful. But a lot of
nuanced weirdnesses that um like you
realize is like through kind of like
manual and and like um another thing is
like the model should be consistently
behaving like this because if it's just
like oneoff then it's fine. But if the
model consistently exhibits this
behavior then uh this becomes like a
more problematic thing. Yeah.
But also you know kind of subjective and
creative
dimensions visual interface or something
arguably the complexity of the problem
increases. Do you think that you know
for those problems compute is still very
much limitation or you think that we're
kind of getting to the point where
there's going to be improvements in our
models or data sets and evolution?
Um I think efficiency is important. I
think that with more test time compute
generally the assumption is um the model
can always get better and better. So it
might achieve kind of human level of
visual design but can it just invent new
interaction paradigms like new
interaction patterns? I feel like that's
more of a super superhuman skill. Um and
I do hope that with more compute um it
will do that at some point. Yeah.
start passing the mic
to generate synthetic reference data.
How do you verify?
Um well, the thing with synthetic data
is that you don't actually need to
generate a lot of it, right? Um so you
can actually have like very much like
manual inspection of what's going on. Um
obviously you can think of other methods
like um ask human labelers to check the
the work. Um you can also ask another
model if that model is like very well
covered. So it's like much it becomes a
more like meta thing. Maybe you can have
a meta eval for that model to verify
what you want to like verify. Um and I
think we are kind of entering those
types of tasks too. Um but the thing
what I like the thing with synthetic
data u and the data itself is like maybe
you don't need as much u what's
important really is diversity and um
yeah diversity.
Cool question to that. What do you think
about like the diversity and quality? So
there's like been like recent code
generation before like um well they put
instruction diversity as like um they
prioritize it more than code execution
quality. So like after filtering code
execution quality it actually led to
like a poor training outcome which is
very like interesting. So um yeah I was
just like wondering what your stance is
on that. Yeah, I think it's um it's
actually depends so much on the like
task and what you're trying to do.
Sometimes synthetic data uh like a lot
if you like if synthetic data happens to
collapse certain mode and then it will
like actually be hurting uh your
training but if synthetic data is
actually um diverse it might actually at
scale if you do a lot of this it might
just like recover from this um
yeah it's hard to give you the right
answer because depends
Nice. Another question. Thanks. So, I
have a question that's about making
money, I guess. So, okay. Um, okay. It's
a real question though. Uh, like we all
know that
uh serving large language models is
expensive especially at the scale that
uh you know, OpenAI, Anthropic are
doing. Uh and my impression has been
that uh at the current stage um it's
actually losing money to uh you know
serve all these models uh to produce the
products. Mhm. Uh is that true or uh
what what's being done to to I guess
bring down the cost? Oh yeah. I mean, I
think uh for a developer
um I think I don't think like I I I
don't know. I think it's the question
for Sam whether you're losing money or
not. But um I do think that
the like the generality of the
technology is like so wide that um you
know I don't think I think about like
how to make money in on a regular basis.
So I don't know but um yeah as a
developer let's say h and if you're
using all the tools you actually don't
need to like create like foundation
model now like you can just use uh like
very inexpense like very like open like
deepse is like very interesting results
right so you can have you can like
bootstrap from existing research I think
it's harder to be at the frontier
because you kind of need to like invent
and that might be expensive like when
you invent something new it's always
inefficient It's always expensive but um
actually it was every technological
innovation um like then what comes next
the second innovation is uh how do we
bring down the cost of this thing that
that happened right and this is what's
happening in AI too um
so is the create amazing product and
this is how you make money
that's that's a good answer uh just
quickly following up so
um is most of the cost reduction coming
from like infrastructure improvements or
can better models or better algorithms
also uh contribute to lower cost? Yeah,
I mean like uh lowering cost might um I
think it's
um the costs of production maybe just
you know the cost of production of the
model training itself might go down um
like it's um the training process in
itself uh might be not as costly anymore
but obviously
uh we scale a lot like scale yeah it's
very much like in linear relation like
scaling and you I think it's just like
yeah it's hard to know I'm sorry I don't
have an answer this
okay thank you
so how do you envision LMS could be used
in other fields such as robotics or body
AI oh yeah I do think like um future AIs
will be building data centers
um to or like um how the current LMS in
robotics I I think I've I've read like
um pi um the company by Sergey Lemon
like the paper they're using a lot of
like RHF like RL uh for robotics tasks
um obviously I feel like data is a huge
limitation and bottleneck uh but I think
as as long as you solve that um I think
it will be really amazingly I'm very
hopeful and very yeah excited about is
oh hi so you mentioned you work uh in
both product and research so I'm
interested in um from the developer or
the researcher point of view at
anthroporic and openai um what's the
visibility for you into other components
of the model and how easy is it for you
to learn say the pre-training of GPT
while you are like responsible for part
of the post- trainining. Oh yeah. Um
well I mostly worked on post training
side of things. Um obviously
pre-training um obviously you just
cannot run like pretaining on your own.
You want to like be a part of like the
next big uh like training run or
something. So that's like part of the
teams that you can join and I think
there's um good visibility in like the
steps are and sometimes you want to you
know uh contribute the data sets to them
or um help with yeah certain like tasks
that you're interested in.
So I was curious do you have any uh
co-workers who are AIs right now and do
you use like agents and a kind of
co-orker relationship right now? Um I
don't think I have like a amazing
product to be like this right I think I
use chach on a regular basis is it my
co-worker not really like sometimes I
ask like what do you
think yeah but it's like in charge like
what I really want uh I don't know if
people have used this product called
it's a pair programming um software but
then it's like you can just call a model
and then share screen and then the model
can um just literally start like editing
my code if I'm coding or I can like
highlight things and then the model can
see it and change this is much more of a
natural co-working
um form factor but no like I don't think
we technology wise like we are not there
yet. Do you have any ideas for like
what's missing in having an autonomous
like co-orker partner? Because I mean
I've seen there were cool, you know,
demonstrations here. I think one there's
a paper like a year or two ago on just
like simulating like a city of people
and all that. Like what's the gap
between that and so like a pure that you
could have on Slack? I think I think the
gap is actually social intelligence and
like some of the human things like being
able to like in real time um like
generate things that I'm asking and then
also being smart about things like maybe
I want to code too but like will the
model be able to det like tell me
instead of like uh taking agency from me
the model can just like guide me through
this or like it depends on like how you
want to form this relationship. It's
like really hard. So the model is I feel
like is currently limited by its the
social abilities. Does it make sense?
Like I think that's missing um kind of
like um speechtoech conversation um like
can the model converse back with me in
real time and then point to things that
it talked about exactly at the same
time. So it's like those type of um
things that might need might have
possibly need like some of the changes
in like architecture and like
multimodality things. Yeah.
in your experience which is which are
the biggest differences between
traditional product development and
yeah that's a good question because um I
interned briefly at like companies like
Dropbox or um Square and they are mainly
very much like traditional software
product development and they go through
like this interesting life cycle of okay
I have like PRD I do this I incentivize
designer designers comes up with like
UIs and then I ask software engineers to
do this. Um we have two minutes I
believe. Um yeah but
uh I think with research products is
actually comes from research uh like if
the research has like an impressive demo
uh of the model capability um maybe then
um there is um then you shape the
product around it. Um and sometimes it's
like both product and research come
together from the very beginning and do
something. Um this happened with the
canvas for example. Yeah. When both
product and research were together and
there was like less less of a process.
It's like more of a ad hoc. Yeah.
Yeah.
Three questions.
Um, for fundamentally unverifiable
domains like creative writing or visual
art, have you thought about using the
real world as an aural environment,
social media verality or competition
results as a reward? Kind of like LMS's.
Um, yeah, it's interesting. Um, I think
you know, nobody have started like this
this looks reasonable. Um yeah,
especially with creative writing, you
have all the like competitions or prizes
that people uh got from um their
writing. So there's something in there.
Um as someone who's still concerned with
AI or stepping into the creative space,
do you have any personal moral
affliction on how your work is so
powerful and that was only positive
people negatively affected? I actually
wrote a blog post about this. Um I have
a blog post. It's called in substack and
the post is called moral progress and I
think you will find it interesting. All
right. So give a give a hand again for
Karina.