okay uh let's just get started welcome
to lecture 14 everyone uh hope you've
been uh doing well and uh you know
managing all of the various deadlines so
uh today we'll be looking at two
interesting
applications of language models uh the
first half I'll be talking about using
language models to reason
in domains like math geometry uh doing
things like spatial reasoning and then
in the second half of the lecture I'll
be talking about how you can use
language models to take actions in
grounded
environments okay um so a little bit of
a disclaimer a lot of the content
today's research that was done in the
last 3 4 years so there's plenty of
questions plenty of unanswered questions
and not a lot of uh uh an so you know
let's let's maybe we can have more of a
discussion U around these topics
okay okay so let's get started with
reasoning um so experts like to start a
lecture on reasoning by really uh
talking about what are the various kinds
of freezing so I'm going to do that here
okay but at a high level it's really
about using facts and logic to arrive at
an answer okay uh but more concretely
there's three distinct categories of
reasoning that that we we can uh talk
about the first one which is probably
the one that most of you are familiar
with is deductive reasoning where we go
from uh rules of logic along with a
premise to come with a firm conclusion
so an example of that could be that we
have the sentence all mammals have
kidneys and all whales are mammals and
then we can come up with the conclusion
all whales have kidneys and we could do
multiple such steps of reasoning okay a
second form of reasoning is inductive
where uh given observations we derive
conclusions okay so maybe we've learned
from experience that every time we see a
creature with wings it is usually a bird
and uh let's say we
observe uh a state where we see a
creature with wings and using our observ
using our experience we can come up with
this conclusion that the creature is
likely to be
so that form of reasoning is inductive
okay and finally we have abductive
reasoning where we're given an
observation and then we start drawing
possible explanations okay so maybe you
see a car that cannot start and there's
a puddle of liquid under the under the
engine and then you you start drawing
inferences about the situation so one of
them could be that the car has leak in
the radiator
okay all right and apart from that
taxonomy uh we can also think of
reasoning in formal and informal terms
where formal reasoning involves using
aums and rules of formal logic to derive
truth conditions okay uh there's also
informal reasoning which is what you and
I uh probably do every day and here we
just reason about everyday situations
and use common sense to derive
conclusions for most of the lecture when
I say reasoning I will mean informal
dedu Ive reasoning and it's often going
to involve multiple
steps okay so uh let's let's come back
to language models okay so uh we've
learned in lectures 9 10 11 that uh
language models are really really good
at or large language models are really
really good at coming up with plausible
continuations of text that reflect human
preferences and constraints today we'll
try to answer if they can also reason
okay so one of the most basic ways we
can try to answer this question is we
are prompting okay and uh we've probably
already seen this uh there's this uh
popular method called Chain of Thought
prompting where you get a language model
to produce a reasoning step before
producing an answer and we could do this
by providing some in context examples
with explicit uh reasoning steps that
the language model can then mimic at
test time okay so that's Chain of
Thought
prompting uh another rather surprising
uh property of language models is that
sometimes you don't even have to show
them these in context examples and you
could just prompt them with the sentence
let's things step by step and you can
get these uh reasoning rationals before
they produce an
answer okay so that's pretty
simple uh but let's let's keep going
okay so another popular way to prompt
language models to do reasoning is via
self-consistency
so here what we do is instead of uh
greedily sampling a rationale followed
by an answer we're going to sample
multiple reasoning steps and
correspondingly multiple answers okay so
what we see in the figure on the right
uh we have a question and then what you
would normally do with Chain of Thought
prompting is you would greedily decode a
rational and then condition on the
rational generate an answer with
self-consistency we're going to sample
multiple times so sample multiple
rationals they are all going to lead to
multiple answers and then we're going to
pick the one that is the most common
okay with the idea being that if an
answer keeps appearing uh for multiple
rationals as the majority uh of the
rationals agree on then it's more likely
to be
correct and the authors of
self-consistency find that on a VAR of
mathematical reasoning tasks if you add
this simple idea of self-consistency
where you sample multiple times and sort
of do majority voting that improves
performance pretty drastically over over
standard Chain of
Thought and interestingly you know when
I saw this result the first time I
thought okay this is just like
ensembling which is you know we we
learned this in cs229 the idea is if you
want to boost the performance of your
system I'm going to produce like uh 10
classifiers with different random seeds
and I'm going to produce a
classification decision and I'm going to
do a majority voting but turns out that
it's doing maybe a little bit more than
just simple ensembling so the author's
also compared uh an ensembling approach
where it's the same language model with
multiple different prompts and then you
do majority voting there and then turns
out that self-consistency is better than
just simple
embling okay okay so earlier today I
said that I'll be talking about
multi-step reasoning uh so far we've
looked at sort of math problems but not
and and like prompting but not
necessarily multi-step reasoning uh one
of the main kind of aspects about
multi-step reasoning is it involves
breaking down a large problem into
several
subparts uh where and and answering each
of the sub uh subp parts and then
combining everything into a solution
okay uh so there's this kind of
decomposition strategy that was uh
integrated into another prompting method
called least to most
prompting and the idea behind least to
most prompting is uh like I said given a
question we're going to first break it
down into sub questions as shown
here um and then given these sub
questions the language model will sort
of answer each of the sub questions and
then conditioned on its answers to the
sub questions is going to generate the
final
answer and this is kind of how it looks
like uh for uh sort of a math reasoning
problem so in standard Chain of Thought
prompting uh you would have a question
followed by a rationale and the answer
with least to most prompting which is
this like de composition strategy uh you
take the question and then instead of
directly producing a rational you you uh
sort of ask the language model to break
it down into problems and then you have
like these uh two different sub problems
and then you start answering both of
those sub problems and then condition
your final answer on the answers to
those sub
problems so okay so that's just like a
prompting method right uh one
interesting experiment from least to
most prompting was showing that you can
sometimes generalize from a small number
of reasoning steps to much larger number
of reasoning steps so here in this sort
of math word
problem uh there's two reasoning steps
and if we show this prompt to the
language model sort of as in context
example we see that it continues to
generalize even on examples that
required more than five steps of
reasoning um and in a way that's much
better than standard Chain of
Thought uh but it's not entirely clear
if structuring inference in this manner
is really
fundamental uh one of the other results
they reported was um sort of uh that
with enough prompt engineering so uh the
rose corresponding to best uh normal
Chain of Thought is on par with least to
most prompting but it's it's kind of an
interesting idea of trying to break down
problems into sub problems solving the
sub problems and then sort of building
up a solution based on your answers to
the sub
problems okay so all this was different
sort of prompting methods to get
reasoning behavor AV out of language
models can we do something more um so
one of the things that we might be
interested in is instead of trying to
get really large language models to do
reasoning maybe we want to somehow get
this kind of reasoning behavior in a
smaller language model and one popular
approach for doing that is
distillation where maybe you want to
fine-tune a smaller llama model uh by
teaching it to imitate a larger llama
model
model um and so that's what we're going
to look at now okay so uh this model is
called
Orca and at a high level Orca is going
to fine tune a smaller 13 billion Lama
language model on explanations produced
by
gbd4 okay and to construct this data it
it's pretty simple uh it has these three
steps so the first step is uh we get a
wide variety of instructions from the
flan V2 collection okay so flan V2 is
basically a data set it's it kind of
cumulates multiple data sets into one
sort of collection uh and it consists of
instructions paired with uh questions
and answers and I I'll show an example
of this um in a moment and then we're
going to prompt gbd4 or chat
GPT with these instructions along with a
system message
and the objective of the system message
is to get chat GPT or gp4 to produce an
informative explanation along with the
answer so here we have a question about
you know simple data processing uh about
calculating the median and there's a
system instruction that says uh please
justify your steps and uh kind of answer
step by step and uh in producing its
output the model sort of provides
uh a fairly detailed explanation of how
it got to the answer and what orai is
going to do is use precisely this
explanation to fine tune a much smaller
model okay uh so that's what's going to
happen uh once we have these
explanations we're going to fine-tune a
much smaller 13 billion parameter llama
model on these explanations
okay so uh so far we've looked at sort
of math reasoning
um and um sort of grade school math
problems uh let's kind of turn to a
different Benchmark for reasoning so
we're going to look at big bench hard uh
and this is another data set for
multi-step reasoning okay and uh let's
look at some examples from Big bench
hard um so it consists of uh multiple
different uh subas so there's a total of
23 different subas I'm going to show a
few examples so one of them is
evaluating Boolean Expressions so uh the
question is true and false and not true
and true is okay so that's basically um
you know uh evaluate this Boolean
expression and um you know with with
sort of Chain of Thought the model can
evaluate each of the sub expressions and
get to The Final
Answer um and another example of a task
from Big bench hard is dat uh is data
understanding
where uh you know like maybe the
question is uh sorry this is date
understanding not data understanding uh
so the question is tomorrow is a given
date uh what is the date one year ago
from today in a given format and uh it's
paired with some options and again the
model can sort of think step by step
following you know basic Chain of
Thought and then come up with an answer
so this is kind of the flavor of tasks
in big bench you know most of these
involveed mult step reasoning they're
fairly synthetic but also um reasonably
hard uh for for for for language models
okay another example is geometric shapes
and uh this one is you know pretty
surprising that language models can do
anything here so you're given sort of
the SVG path
element and uh you know sort of I I have
no idea what this renders us but like
the question is uh you know just given
the SVG what shape uh you're going to
get okay and there's a bunch of options
and then again the model uh prompted
with let's things step by step will
produce some answer we don't know if
it's correct but it's going to produce
some answer okay uh and so it's
basically this data set covering
different kinds of reasoning spatial
reasoning data understanding um you know
evaluating booleans um and it's sort of
multi-choice so it's easier to kind of
get uh get sort of an accuracy number
and so yeah so it covers like a wide
variety of different tasks um on the
left we have performance from uh really
large language models uh this is zero
short um Chain of Thought with just the
prompt lets things step by
step um so gbd4 has some potential
contamination issues with big bench
heart so let's maybe we can ignore that
column uh wuna is is um I think a few
months ago it was state-ofthe-art as as
an instruction tuned uh llama 13B model
and orca is is again a llama 13B that's
fine-tuned specifically on this uh like
explanation um data where you know you
have instructions and then you have
explanations from chat GPD or gp4 and
you f tune on that and we see that
overall it it outperforms chat GPT uh
maybe because it's specialized to just
like these reasoning problems uh and it
outperforms wuna which was not trained
on like these really extensive
explanations um so that's one way you
can get a smaller language model to
display some kind of reasoning Behavior
okay so you know this was all great and
you know we we we are very happy that
like you can just generate rationals
from Big LM and then fine tune a smaller
language model on that but then someone
could ask why not just fine tune the big
language model on its own rationals
right um so that's also been explored uh
and there's a bunch of different methods
that do this I'm going to talk about one
of them called reinforced self trining
or rest and that's going to alternate
between two
stages the first stage uh given a
reasoning problem and perhaps The Prompt
lets things step by step I'm going to
have the language model generate
multiple rationals okay and then I'm
going to filter these rationals based on
whether they give me the correct answer
or not okay so you know think about the
word uh algebra problems someone has
three apples someone else has four
apples you generate a rationale and the
answer comes out to be seven you keep
that rational the answer is 12 you sort
of leave that rational out and then I'm
going to do an update step where I'm
going to take uh these rationals that I
filtered in my first stage I'm going to
f tune the language model on that and
then I can do this iteratively now I
have an updated language model I can get
hopefully better rationals and then I
can update the language model on better
rationals to get an even better language
model and I can keep doing
that
okay and uh the results are promising
but uh you know uh what we find is uh on
on gsm 8K which is this great School
math uh data set of like algebraic word
problems um as you increase the number
of iterations of
self-training we see a slight
Improvement in performance and then it
starts
degrading uh math is another data set
that again focuses on multi-step
reasoning uh covering math problems and
again we on this data set we see that as
we do more iterations of this reinforced
self trining Paradigm we see an
improvement in in the
accuracy and uh the numbers in Orange
here are a much larger uh Palm model the
numbers in blue are a smaller model uh
and the dash lines represent what you
get um sort of if you did supervised
fine tuning on human provided rationals
so one of the promising things about
this approach is when you do multiple
iterations of training on your own
rationals you can
outperform um sort of human generated
rationals um and that is exemplified
again in in this graph where uh what we
find is uh the blue bar represents
accuracy when you take uh the Palm model
and you do supervised fine-tuning on
human provided
rationals okay and then in green is if
you did if you controlled uh for the
sorry uh so blue is if you f tune on all
human provided
rationals orange is if you f tune on one
rational per training
example okay and these are from these
are written by humans in
green uh it's what you get if you fine
tune on one rational chosen at random
per question which is generated by the
model so it's controlling for the number
of rationals and we see that it out
performs human provided rationals and
then if you sort of do the full
multi-step uh iterative procedure where
you keep improving the model we see
again a boost in
performance so that's uh super
promising um but let's kind of start
revisiting the question that we asked um
in the beginning about reasoning in
language models okay um so one way of
answering that question is we can apply
all these methods and we can look at
benchmarks uh but maybe the way to
answer the question correctly is to be
more
systematic uh come up with
counterfactual tasks and be very uh
careful about possible data
contamination and I'm going to show some
results uh around around
that so uh we started the lecture with
Chain of Thought and maybe the first
question to ask is are the rationals
that the model produces would change of
thought
faithful what I mean by Faithful Is
maybe the model produces some rational
and then it produces an answer maybe the
answer does not even depend on the
rational that It produced right so maybe
the question was you know Tom has three
apples and Jerry has four apples and the
rational It produced was okay Tom has
three apples Jerry has four 3 + 4 is
seven so the answer is 25 you know uh so
in a case like that uh you'd say that
the model was not faithful to its
rational
and so what we see in this plot is is a
very careful experiment where um on on
the x-
axis uh we have the number of reasoning
samples so okay so the setup is
something like this so for every
question the model produces a rational
and a rational here is multiple
sentences and what we're going to do is
we're going to force the model to
sort of early exit from its
rationalization and just like force it
to produce an answer okay so if it
produced four rationals I can early exit
right after the first rational and ask
it to produce an answer I can exit after
the second rational ask it to produce an
answer and so on and what I'm going to
plot on the Y AIS is the model's
accuracy after early exiting um in in in
this
procedure so let's say that I early
exerted after just one rational and the
model produced exactly the same answer
that it would if it had seen all four uh
sentences in its rational then maybe we
can conclude that uh the kind of
reasoning is is not faithful like it
doesn't matter if the model C is the
full rational or just the first sentence
uh and if you take that to the extreme
um you know maybe you terine it even
without any rational and it produces the
same answer so the results here are
somewhat mixed but we see that there are
enough data sets where uh it doesn't
matter if you see the full if the model
sees the full rational before answering
or if you early sort of early exit you
kind of get the same answer which means
that sometimes uh these rationals may be
post hog explanations of the model's
answer okay another experiment that
tries to answer this exact same question
is uh you can take these rationals and
then you can start corrupting them
so maybe your rational was length four
and then I generate the first rational
the second rational and for the third
rational I just corrupt it okay and then
uh the fourth rational and then I asked
the model to generate my answer if it
turns out that no matter how much I
corrupt my rational the model produces
the same answer then I can conclude that
again the answer kind of did not depend
on my
rational so on the x-axis uh we are
looking at the number number of re the
percentage of reasoning steps before uh
I add sort of a mistake in the rational
okay so what you should see is kind of a
strictly increasing uh increasing sort
of trend where if I add a mistake after
the very first step then that's probably
going to change the answer a lot and
then if I add a mistake after the last
step that maybe doesn't change the
answer all that much but again we find
that for some data sets uh it so happens
that you know you can add a mistake in
the first sentence in your rationale and
the answer is not going to change all
that much and so that's also kind of an
indicator that maybe these rationals are
sort of post talk explanations of the
model's
behavior um so yeah so there's a lot of
lines here so if anyone has questions uh
see a few blank faces in the audience
okay so let's let's uh let's keep moving
um okay so that's that was about like
whether uh the models where sort of
Chain of Thought expresses kind of a
reasoning that the model is faithful to
uh another question you could ask is
what if I changed my setting a little
bit right so my model let's say I
observe that it's able to do arithmetic
in base 10 so it's able to answer
something like 12 + 14 uh does that mean
that my model knows how to do it
arithmetic or maybe there was just this
exact same um you know example was
present in the training data so one way
you could test for this is by creating
counterfactuals which uh based on our
understanding of the data you expect uh
to not be present that frequently in the
training
data so instead of doing base 10
addition you could do addition in base 9
and then if the model has the same
accuracy in base 9 then you can conclude
that maybe this model has under OD how
to do
addition similarly for logic uh maybe uh
the reason why the model is so good at
solving logic problems is because it's
seen something very similar in its
training data so what if I construct a
world where I don't know corgis are
reptiles can it still do this logic
problem okay and so what we find is uh
there is a you know sometimes a pretty
significant drop when you move from
there's a question sorry you counteract
why is base 9 counteract and Bas
10 so it's it's a counterfactual excuse
me in the sense that
um uh the the authors comment that like
base 10 addition is like frequently
observed in training data but very few
people do base 9 addition and so there's
going to be much fewer examples of this
in training data so it's more so add a
distribution I right yeah yeah so you
can also call it out of distribution for
sure
um and yeah so like from results like
what we see is uh you know there's
there's like this drop in performance
even for like very simple logic problems
that don't involve like multiple steps
of reasoning a you know kind of a
significant drop in
performance um which maybe suggest that
there's not that much reasoning there's
more memorization um
yeah so we could keep going with this
Paradigm of like changing the problem
setting so that it starts looking sort
of out of distribution to the training
Corpus um and this is exactly what was
done in this paper that looked at
analogical
reasoning so uh so basically the setup
is something like this I'm going to show
certain examples of string
Transformations and I'm going to ask the
model to generalize to new examples okay
so in this extend sequence problem I
have ABCD and the output is AB bcde e
and then given i j KL the model has to
produce I J K L M okay and so on now the
way you can sort of make this into like
a
counterfactual or uh something that is
out of distribution is uh maybe you can
kind of change what the extend sequence
Quin task is so now instead of
outputting ABCDE e maybe the model has
to Output ABCD F okay so instead of
outputting the next character it has to
Output um sort of one more uh so the
second character after the next and so
on uh the other kind of contactual you
could add is instead of operating on the
standard uh alphabet you could modify
the alphabet completely so instead of
the alphabet being ABC maybe you start
at x y and you know so
on um so what we find is uh so we find
two things uh the first thing that we
find is that uh there's a significant
drop in performance as we go from the
standard sort of analogical reasoning
problem to one of these counterfactuals
where we either change the alphabet we
change the description of the Tas so
that it becomes slightly
unnatural on the other hand the authors
also did this exact same experiment on
human subjects where they find very
little uh decrease in
performance okay so overall what this
result suggests is maybe there's some
reasoning um maybe there's some
memorization but there's nothing
systematic okay uh so you know again
this is like all emerging so uh maybe uh
someone will find that you know if you
if you change your prompt a little bit
now now models get can do reasoning uh
but this is kind of the current lay of
the
land
okay
um so uh that was sort of the reasoning
module of the lecture I'm going to now
switch gar and talk about uh language
model
agents
um so uh and and this is kind of related
to reasoning in the sense that uh
reasoning involves sort of this
multi-step inferences where you know
given some facts have to arrive at
completely new
conclusions um with agents what we'll
see is that there's some high level kind
of objective or model has to accomplish
and it has to reason about post
conditions object
affordances um kind of uncertainty in
the world to carry out a sequence of
steps
um so let's start with some
terminology okay so we have our agent on
the right um that's going to be some
some neural network
and then we have an
environment um you know and I I I'll
give some examples of what what these
environments could be
um the agent receives an observation
from its
environment and based on the observation
IT issues an action
okay and along with that it receives
this second variable G and G represents
a language
instruction okay uh so there's many
names for this setting and and what uh
and these models uh digital agent
language conditioned policy or an
instruction following
agent uh some examples of environments
are maybe uh it's it's sort of a web
browser and in sort of a browsing
environment uh where the uh objective is
to book a flight from San Francisco to
New York and the observation could
either be raw pixel that the model
sees or or it could be the HTML Dom
representation and the action space if
you're looking at these web environments
could be uh typing on specific web
elements clicking on web elements uh
moving your mouse to a certain web
element to interact with it and so
on and yeah I mean like this are sort of
a vast number of applications I don't
think can cover all applications but
like you know uh we can look at some so
there's obviously uh like digital
assistance like uh you know I'm not
going to say the names because I I know
people's mobiles might might might start
popping up um but you know you can give
them natural language commands and like
you know set an alarm uh set reminders
and so on uh you could also do natural
language programming uh where you could
given natural language descript
descriptions uh get a model to sort of
write python code another example of
this could be UI
automation where maybe you want to do
automated testing of of UI elements and
so instead of having a human sort of
verify whether uh a UI UI element Works
maybe you can get a model to execute
actions corresponding to a given
instruction or it could be something
more sort of user facing where uh you
know given some kind of complex
environment like Spotify you could ask
an agent to play some
songs and then finally uh there is this
sort of emerging
application where we want to add
additional tools um or plugins to
language models so that they can control
various different
applications
um okay so uh before we look at how we
can use language models to do
instruction following I think it's very
helpful to look at how this was done
before language
models um so uh there were basically
three main
ideas uh sometimes uh the the the right
thing to do was uh collect examples of
utterances paired with uh logical forms
so logical forms uh could be some kind
of an executable representation that you
could just execute against either a
knowledge graph or a database to get an
answer so maybe you have a query like
what state botherers
Texas and then there exists some sort of
program description that you could
execute against uh a Knowledge Graph to
get sort of an answer or a list
here um and and idea number one that
people looked at was to treat this as
almost like machine translation right so
you have uh
a source language which is sort of
English commands and then you have a
target language which is sort of these
uh these like meaning representations or
logical forms and then you could apply
the same Machinery from assignment 3 uh
to build kind of a natural language
interface here okay so you directly
maximize the probability of a sequence
of actions given a goal or a
command idea number two was
um something a little bit more complex
so here you have um instructions paired
with actions instead of directly mapping
instructions to
actions uh I'm going to infer an
executable plan okay from these
instructions uh and action sequences and
I'm going to train a model to go from
instructions to these plans and then
Define a very rich execution model
that's going to directly execute these
plans the advantage of this is uh maybe
there is more sort of highlevel uh
decisions you could encode in your plan
which would be harder to like get into
the model if you were to just train it
uh to produce the action trajectories
directly and I have an example of a
system like that from
2011 which uh was basically an agent
that could navigate in um in sort of
grounded environment
and yeah the idea was something like
this that uh you kind of took an
instruction and obtained a
plan um and then you would uh train a
semantic par so which is basically like
this kind of machine translation system
that would convert commands into
sequences of uh into this plan and then
once that's trained at test time given a
completely new instruction you would run
the semantic parsel get this plan and
then execute it in this execution model
okay and I have an example of an
instruction and and a plan uh from this
system the third idea uh which is
probably um you know maybe the first one
that comes to mind if you see a setting
like that is to use reinforcement
learning
directly and what people did there was
to use RL to directly map instructions
into actions so I'm going to learn a
policy that outputs actions that
maximize some reward okay which is
conditioned on my natural language
instruction and the observation and this
reward could be both sparse which is I
carry out the entire task and then my
environment tells me if I achieve the
task or not or it could be something
that I obtain after each step so I take
an action and then the and and then the
environment tells me if this action sort
of completed some percentage of my task
or not uh and on the top I've included
an example of a system from 2009 that
did this for automated Windows debugging
and so you know you have some natural
language uh instruction uh to click some
UI elements and that that get mapped
into kind of an API command that the
model executes one after the
other um okay so these were basically
the three main ideas that people had
before language models you would either
train semantic parsers you would either
infer these plans from instruction
trajectory pairs uh and then learn to
directly model plans and then have an
execution model that can execute plans
or you would do reinforcement learning
if you had a reward
signal so how do we do things in
2024 so uh there are a few ways to think
about this uh I think like maybe most
instructive is to think about what we
trying to achieve right so we are trying
to model trajectories so sequence of
actions conditioned on some goal okay so
I want my model to book a flight from
San Francisco to New York and I want it
to produce a trajectory of like maybe
tip uh typing and clicking actions so
let's look at how that
factorizes so the probability of a
trajectory uh conditioned on a goal or
an instruction is just the probability
of the State action next state and so on
condition on the goal and you could
factorize that into two terms so the
first term is sort of the transition
dynamics of the environment and that's
just what happens if I take a certain
action in a given State how is my state
going to change and the second object is
sort of the agent policy which is given
my goal and the trajectory so far what
what is the next action I should be
taking okay and then uh sort of people
quickly realize that you could just
treat this as kind of a generative
problem so you could treat uh the
problem of decision- making in
environments as sort of a generative
trajectory modeling
problem and what I have in sort of the
top right is an example of a transformer
that just takes uh the history of
actions it's taken so far are the
current state and uh some indication of
what task it should achieve here uh
based on reward but it could be a
natural language string and it's just
trained to predict what's the next
action okay and you could just train an
auto regressive language model to do
this and it turned out that this worked
very well in sort of an offline RL case
question sorry in figure why are we
predicting one one action
uh so we are predicting one action
before and the current action uh oh so
so no no so you predict an action
execute that right append that to your
trajectory and then you predict the next
action and so on goe so we we we resolve
three input to tokens into one output
token and turn it off yeah okay sounds
good um and it turned out that this
worked really well and so you know the
the instead of uh you know uh getting
these latent plans and training semantic
parsers or trying to do reinforcement
learning uh we started using language
models as policies and so a simple way
to do all of that is uh to prompt a
language model in a loop
okay so uh we're going to specify the
action space and text so this is like a
simple uh sort of language model agent
this is not going to work at all but
like probably just like illustrative of
of how agent can be built now so you
provide an action space in text um so
maybe it's a digital environment and
maybe it can type maybe it can click
maybe it can type characters maybe it
can move Mouse somewhere uh you provide
it an
instruction and you provide it the
sequence of actions and observations
it's received so far okay and then
condition on all that you ask it to
predict the next uh the next
action and there's nothing deep going on
here this is just Chain of Thought
prompting in a loop okay but uh the hope
is that uh because all of this uh
because we reduce the problem of
decision making into just Auto
regressive modeling this this could work
okay and indeed like you know a slightly
more complex version of this can work in
some
environments okay so now I'm going to
sort of give a little FL faor of what
different environments look like now for
evaluating language models um as
agents so the simplest environment uh
that that that people consider is mini
wob so uh this is a Sandbox environment
um that evaluates like basic browser
interactions like you know maybe on a
mini Twitter environment can you get a
language model to retweet a given tweet
um given sort of a simulat email client
can the model forward someone's email
can it compose an email uh can it click
on certain buttons or
not uh it's not at all real world so
it's not real websites uh and it's
relatively short Horizon so given any
instruction most tasks can be
accomplished in under three
actions uh but zero short performance of
even the best language models is still
far from perfect even on this very
simple
Benchmark um
a second slightly more real world
Benchmark is web
Arina and this is also a Sandbox
environment but it's kind of an a pretty
close approximation of real websites uh
that span e-commerce so there is a
website in web Arina that resembles
Amazon um social media so something that
resembles
Twitter and additionally there are
utility tools like Maps so an
instruction could require a model to
open up sort of a map application find
the shortest path from point A to point
B and use that uh in its later uh
sequence of actions and there's
multi-tab browsing like we kind of
commonly do uh so with mini wob there's
only one single tab uh and and with web
Arena I think this was the first
environment that introduced this idea
where uh you kind of have multiple tabs
and the agent can sort of switch between
uh apps tabs uh and again we are going
to evaluate sort of functional
correctness um which is whether the
model sort of gave uh the correct answer
at the end whether the sequence of steps
it took um gave the intended Behavior as
opposed to whether it took a sequence of
steps that maybe a user had
pre-programmed so another popular uh
kind of uh environment is or a data set
is web links so web links also has
multi-tab browsing
and uh it has web interactions on real
websites so this is not sandboxed
approximations of real websites is not
sandboxed kind of just like browser like
uh uh like browser interactions these
are like actual real websites um and it
also introduced like a new action where
the agent could communicate with the
user so maybe there's some instruction
uh which is to like
reserve um kind of
I don't know like like a movie or like
uh buy a movie ticket or something and
then at some point the model has to
request credit card information and so
there is this like additional action
where a human could be involved in
communicating um with the
agent uh and this is not an environment
uh but just a collection of interactions
uh so you can't for example do any kind
of exploration or online learning here
but you could definitely use this for
evaluating um um okay uh so this was
just a taste of what some benchmarks
look like uh for for language model
agents so how are we going to train
these models right so uh you know given
that we we're going to train we're going
to treat like uh decision making as sort
of casual uh as causal language modeling
we're not going to use any of the ideas
from
pre-ms uh the standard practice is to do
in context learning with few short
examples uh and in the few short
examples uh for typically for any new
kind of uh website or any new use case
you're going to get humans to perform
those tasks and sort of feed that into
the language models prompt as in context
demonstrations which it could then use
to solve um similar similar looking
tasks on very similar
websites so obviously this is not
scalable uh there's thousands of
environments on some environments that
like lots of different interactions that
are possible and so maybe there's
something better that we can do than
just U sort of getting humans to provide
demonstrations for every new use
case um and so we going to use something
we saw early on in the lecture okay
which was to kind of use the language
model to generate rationals and then
fine tune on that and here we don't have
rationals but we could produce action
trajectories and then we're going to use
that
as supervision okay so the way that
looks like is something like this so
let's say I have some
environment um you know let's say it's
some mini wob environment and I'm going
to just uh get an agent that can
randomly explore the environment so
it'll just execute a random
sequence of clicks and types uh and
scrolling
operations and let's say it produces
some trajectories
okay and now I'm going to use these traj
and somehow filter them so that was the
idea from earlier so you're going to get
a bunch of different outputs and then
you're going to filter it somehow so
here we're going to use a second
language model because we don't know
what a good trajectory looks like so not
like a math problem where you know you
know the correct answer uh we just had a
language model interact with the website
and generate trajectories and we want to
somehow filter out what a good
trajectories and so we're going to use a
second
model that will produce a
description uh of these trajectories and
the idea here is that if you can get a
model to produce a description of what
uh what the sequence of actions
corresponds to then maybe that's a good
enough signal for a good trajectory okay
and so maybe given the first trajectory
it guesses that the instruction was to
book a flight from San Francisco to New
York um for the second trajectory it
said set the date to some given date um
um and maybe it it wasn't able to come
up with any good uh sort of uh
instruction for the third
trajectory and then we're going to do
something uh again uh that we saw
earlier on which is to like kind of do
this iteratively so now uh we have a a
goal that we got for for a trajectory
and now I'm going to get the language
model to condition Its Behavior on this
goal so the goal is to set the date as
some given date and now instead of doing
random exploration the model is going to
produce a sequence of actions that have
a better correspondence with some
natural language
instruction So It produced a trajectory
based on that
instruction and then I'm going to use
sort of some course filter that's just
going to look at correspondences between
the instruction and uh the sequence of
actions and the states the language
model visited and used that to decide if
the trajectory was a good trajectory for
the
instruction and in this case uh you know
given the instruction this seems like a
pretty good trajectory for completing
this task and so then we added to a set
of examples okay but maybe sometimes uh
things are not so good so for that
second
instruction the generated label was to
book a flight from San Francisco to New
York and let's say we run that again
through the language model and It
produced a second trajectory okay and
clearly this does not seem like uh kind
of a successful trajectory corresponding
to booking a
flight um and so what do we do here
maybe we can throw away this uh
interaction but interactions are pretty
costly like
specifically uh you know if you're
looking at real websites and each
interaction uh you know could take a few
milliseconds and so maybe we don't want
to throw away this interaction
so what we're going to do here is again
invoke the Rel laaber to take the
trajectory and assign it a new label so
the model was not successful at
accomplishing the task it set out to do
but it accomplished something and we're
going to come up with the best guess of
what that was with a second language
model and it's going to say that okay uh
maybe the instruction you accomplished
instead was to set the origin to SFO and
the destination to New York City okay
and so that's going to get get fed back
into the language model and we're going
to keep doing this iteratively till our
filter says that this is a good
instruction trajectory pair okay so we
have the same idea of using a language
model to sort of generate outputs and
some iterative uh procedure that will
like you know give us kind of a good set
of training
examples um so overall the method looks
something like this uh you know you have
some
environment uh we going to use uh kind
of an unconditioned language model to
just randomly explore the environment
and generate a sequence of
trajectories and then we're going to
convert these trajectories into
synthetic training data by iteratively
converting trajectories into natural
language descriptions and then taking
natural language descriptions and
converting them into even better
trajectories and so on and once we have
this collection of synthetic examples uh
there are two things we could do
one could fine-tune using this data uh
but the simplest thing you could do is
kind of repeat the Paradigm earlier of
you know replace uh human provided
demonstrations in context with these
synthetic
demonstrations um and we find uh a a
reasonable boost in performance or 13
Point Improvement on the mini Benchmark
and again uh you know even though mini
wob is very very simple zero short
performance for even the best language
models is far from from perfect and we
also see an improvement on second sort
of multi-step uh tool use uh environment
but so far we've only looked at text
right um but uh maybe for real world
applications it's kind of intractable to
for every environment obtain the HTML
and feed that into the language models
context uh sometimes there can be tens
of thousands of Dom uh elements and then
corresponding uh JavaScript and
inputting all that into the language
models context could be you know
intractable and maybe that's also not
the best way to kind of uh
show the state of the environment maybe
the best way is to directly show the
pixels uh corresponding to uh the the
environment and so now we're going to
look at some examples of vision language
models that people have used for
building these agents
okay so uh the first one that that we're
going to look at is
lava uh and the idea here is again kind
of similar to Orca that we looked at uh
in in sort of the reasoning half of the
lecture uh we're going to use
gp4 to generate uh this time both
instructions and
responses uh for textual descriptions of
images so maybe there's an image um and
we're going to sort of use uh metadata
corresponding to that image to come up
with a texture description feed that
into gbd4 and ask it to generate
possible questions and
responses and then we're going to
jointly
fine-tune um sort of an image encoder um
here clip along with a uh a Texton
decoder here wuna which is a Lama model
that is instruction
tuned um and through this sort of joint
fine-tuning uh at the end we we kind of
get this image
encoder um that can output language
responses and now we can sort of ask
questions about images maybe use that uh
to directly input uh screenshots instead
of HTML Dom
elements so a second approach that um
looked at sort of building joint uh
image language models that then people
later adapted to agents was uh pix to
struct and uh the idea is again very
similar uh there's an image encoder and
a text decoder U the image encoder will
will will sort of take the image convert
them into patches and assign each patch
sort of a position ID uh run that
through a
Transformer and then there's a decoder
that will decode out some text okay uh
one of the new things that pix to struct
introduced was a new pre-training task
so uh for for lava the pre-training was
you know fairly simple uh we're going to
use gbd4 to just generate sort of
synthetic uh questions and responses
based on textual descriptions of images
but there's only so far you can go with
textual descriptions of images what pix
to struck did was uh to look at
screenshots uh from websites and mask
out uh screenshots and then ask the
Transformer decoder to produce HTML
corresponding to the marked outout
elements uh so here there is uh like
this list um that has a corresponding
HTML uh one of the data points in uh in
pix to struct looks something like this
so you you might mask out let's say the
first uh the first answer corresponding
to Python and ask the model to produce
the HTML corresponding to just the uh
patch that was mased
out uh and so this seems like a more
natural sort of pre-training objective
that can maybe have like better
interactions between image uh and text
and then this was also adapted for uh
building like these multimodal
agents okay so uh you know at this point
I just want to kind of highlight that
this is really an emerging application
um there's kind of this huge kind of
prompting Gap uh is what I like to call
it so if you do not do extensive
prompting and if you do not use thepoke
few short example where for every
different environment you have a
different set of few short examples even
the best language models are very very
far from perfect even on very very
simple tasks like mini wob uh where you
know the goal was just to click on
certain elements or uh you know respond
to someone's email where in mini wob
that just takes like five
actions
um and then uh even for something as
simple as mini wob even after doing
extensive prompting and few short
examples
is this like U drop in performance as
you go from sort of the simplest task
that involve mapping and instruction
into a single action to mapping an
instruction into maybe five or 10
actions uh so long Horizon planning uh
is is still very very hard even on these
very simple
benchmarks um and then if you look at
something more complex like web Arena
which tries to approximate real websites
has multi-tab browsing has external
tools that the mod can use there's just
a huge difference between sort of human
level uh task success rate and what the
best models get uh even after prompting
even with few short
examples um and then the kinds of Errors
model make models make are
also pretty weird so one of the examples
uh from from web links was uh the task
was to just open Google Translate and
sign in using credentials and there was
an email and a password and then what
gbd4 V did was instead of uh typing in
the password it just typed in the email
into the password tab uh and it just
couldn't recover from this error so you
know it it tried to sign in there was an
error it tried to insert uh try tried to
type in the the email again and so on
and I'm sure with extensive prompting
you can fix this and maybe that's
besides the point right um
and then again uh you know there was
like a different example where uh the
model had to issue a search and then
instead of issuing the search with the
correct term it sort of repeated the
same term like three times um and
obviously that's not going to return any
query uh return any
results um so there's lot lot of room
for for improvement as you can see um
and then there's lots to be done in the
space okay so I'm going to recap um and
take any questions so we kind of looked
at two different things today we looked
at reasoning in language models uh we
saw that there's a few ways that you can
get reasoning like behavior in language
models you can prompt them in various
ways so the simplest example of that is
Chain of Thought prompting you can do
Chain of Thought prompting but generate
multiple rationals and sort of try to uh
reconcile them and pick the answer that
was most
uh most like
frequent uh you can do sort of problem
decomposition in your prompt so ask the
model to explicitly decompose a problem
into multiple steps before
answering U so that was all
prompting you could also try and train
specialize small language models for
reasoning by generating rationals from a
big language model and then F tuning a
smaller language model on these
rationals uh instead of fine tuning a
smaller language model on rationals from
a big language model you could just
fine-tune the big language model on its
own rationals and keep doing this
iteratively and we saw that sometimes
like if you do multiple iterations of
that performance can keep
improving and and and can even
outperform sort of human provided
rationals um but on the flip side we saw
that while there are some initial
reasons to be optimistic if we go and do
counterfactual evalu ation we see that
you know it's not clear if the models
are good because they're reasoning or if
models are good because you know all of
these problems were in some shape or
form already in the training data and we
saw that with sort of counterfactual
evaluation um in the second part we
looked at language model
agents uh we kind of talked about the
historical perspective through which uh
people built sort of grounded agents and
then we saw that you could recast the
problem of decision making as just sort
of uh causal language modeling and then
we looked at various ways through which
people have modeled uh decision making
with language models most of it involves
prompting and in context learning and
then we looked at a method for U you
know similar to sort of what we saw in
the first module uh generating synthetic
demonstrations and here we looked at
doing exploration and the same kind of
iterative
relabeling um um you know most of the
language models we looked at today were
text only uh we saw some examples of
language models that can take both text
and uh visual
input and then uh you know we we saw
that benchmarks are very very
challenging models make kind of trivial
mistakes uh there's a huge gap between
human performance and sort of what we
get with models uh so there's a huge uh
like there's a huge difference between
human performance and where models are
and you know a lot of room for driving
further
Improvement um and maybe some of you are
doing it for your projects uh thank you
[Applause]