now we have uh kangan um give a talk so
he is currently a research scientist at
um on the open AI chat gbd team um he
has worked on various aspects of large
language models um things like
pre-training instruction fine-tuning
reinforcement learning with human
feedback uh reasoning um and so forth
and some of his notable Works include um
the scaling flan paper such as flan T5
as well as flan Palm and uh t5x the
training framework used to train the
Palm language model and before open AI
um he was at Google brain and um he
received his PhD from MIT um so give a
hand for um
[Applause]
hangan all right my name isan and really
happy to be here today and this week I
was thinking about about by the way it's
mic working
fine yeah yeah um so this week I thought
about okay I'm giving a lecture on
Transformers at Stanford what should I
talk about and I thought okay some of
you in this room and in in Zoom will
actually go shape the future of AI so
maybe I should talk about that it's a
really important goal and ambitious and
we really have to get it right so that
could be a good topic to think about and
when we talk about something into the
future the best place to get an advice
is to look into the history and in
particular we'll look at the early
history of Transformer and try to learn
many lessons from there and the goal
will be to develop a unified perspective
in uh with which we can look into many
seemingly disjoint events and and from
that we can probably uh hope to project
into the future what might be coming and
so um that will be the goal of this
lecture and we'll look at some of the
architectures of the Transformers so
let's get
started everyone I see uh it's saying AI
is so advancing so fast that it's so
hard to keep up and doesn't matter if
you have like years of experience the so
many things are coming out every week
that it's just hard to keep up and I do
see many people spend a lot of time and
energy catching up with this latest
development the The Cutting Edge and the
the the newest thing and then not enough
ion goes into old things because they
become um deprecated and no longer
relevant but I think it's important
actually to look into that because we
really need to when things are moving so
fast beyond our ability to catch up what
we need to do is study the change itself
and that means we can look back at the
previous things and then look at the
current thing and try to map how we got
here and from which we can look into
what where we are heading towards so
what does it mean to study the change
itself first um we need to identify the
dominant driving forces behind the
change so here dominant is an important
word because typically a change has many
many driving forces and we only care
about the dominant one because we're not
trying to get really accurate just want
to have the sense of directionality
second we need to understand the driving
force really well and then after that we
can predict the future trajectory by I
don't know rolling out the driving force
and so on and you heard that right I
mentioned about predicting the future
this is a computer science class not
like an astrology or something but we do
I think it's actually not that
impossible to predict some future
trajectory of a very narrow scientific
domain and that um Endeavor is really
useful uh to do because uh you let's say
you you do all these and then make your
prediction accuracy to from 1% to 10%
and then you'll make say 100 predictions
10 of them will be correct say one of
them will be really really correct
meaning it will have an outside impact
that outweighs everything and I think
that um is kind of how uh many I've seen
many General thing in life that you
really have to be right a few times so
why um so so if we think about why um
predicting the future is difficult or
maybe even think about the extreme case
where we can all do the prediction with
perect perfect accuracy almost perfect
accuracy so here I'm going to do a very
simple experiment of dropping this pen
and follow this uh same three-step
process so we're going to identify the
driving dominant driving force first of
all what what are the driving forces
acting on this pen gravity downwards and
is that all we we also have like a say
um air friction right going if I drop it
and that will cause What's called the
drag force acting upwards and actually
depending on how I drop this the
orientation the the aerodynamic
interaction will be so complicated that
we don't currently have any analytical
way of modeling that we can do it with
the cftd the competitional fluid
dynamics but it will be non-trivial so
so we can neglect that this is have
enough that gravity is probably the only
dominant Force so we simpli simplify the
problem second we do we understand this
dominant driving force which is gravity
and we do because we have this Newtonian
mechanics which provides reasonably good
model and then with that we can predict
the future trajectory of this pen and if
you remember from this Dynamics class if
we have this initial velocity is zero
I'm not going to put any velocity and
then let's say position is zero here and
then uh 1 12 GT Square will give a
precise um trajectory of this pen as I
Dro this so if there is a driving force
single driving force that we really
understand it's actually possible to
predict what's going to happen so then
why do we really um fear about
predicting the future in the most
General sense and I argue that among
many reasons the number of driving force
the sheer number of dominant driving
forces acting on the General's um
prediction is so complicated and their
interaction creates a complexity that we
cannot predict the most General sense so
here's my cartoon way of thinking about
the prediction of future xaxis we have a
number of dominant driving forces Y axis
we have a prediction difficulty so on
the left hand side we have a dropping of
pen it's a very simple case we it's a
difficulty it's very small you just need
to learn um physics and then as you add
more stuff it just becomes impossible so
how does this fit into the AI research
and you might think okay I see all the
time things are coming in and we are
bombarded by new things and some people
will come up with the new agent new
modality new MML use score whatever that
we just see so many things it just um
I'm not even able to catch up with the
latest thing how can I even hope to
predict the future of the AI research
but I I argue that it's actually simpler
because there is a dominant driving
force that is governing a lot if any if
not all of the AI research and because
of that I would like to point out that
it should it's actually closer to the
left than to the right uh than we
actually may perceive um
so what is that driving force oh maybe
before that I would like to caveat that
uh when I do this kind of talk I would
like to not focus too much on the
technical stuff which you can probably
do better in your own time but rather I
want to uh share how I think and for
that I want to share how my opinion as
this and so it will be very strongly
opinionated and I'm by no means I'm
saying this is uh correct or not just
wanted to share my perspective so coming
back to this driving force for AI what
is that Domino driving force and here's
a plot from Rich suton and on the y-
axis we have the uh calculations floped
if you pay $100 and how much computing
power do you get and it's in log scale
and then xais we have a a time of of
more more than 100 years so this is
actually more than like exponential and
I don't know any Trend that is as strong
and as long lasting as this one so this
whenever I see this kind of thing I
should say okay I should not compete
with this and better I should try to
leverage as much as possible and um so
what this means is you get 10x more
compute every five years if you spend
the same amount of dollar and so in
other words you get the cost of compute
is going down exponentially and this and
Associated scaling is really dominating
the AI research and that is somewhat
hard to take but that is I think really
important to uh think about so coming
back to this AI research how is how is
this uh exponentially cheaper compute
Drive the AI research let's think about
the job of the AI researchers it is to
teach machines how to think in a very
general sense and one somewhat uh you
know unfortunately common approach is we
think about how we teach machine how we
think we think so meaning we model how
how we think and then try to incorporate
that into some kind of mathematical
model and teach that and now the
question is do we understand how we
think at the very low level I don't
think we do I don't I have no idea
what's going on so it's fundamentally
flawed in the sense that we try to model
something that we have no idea about and
what happens if we go with this kind of
approach is that it poses a structure
that serves as a shortcut in the short
term and so you can maybe get a paper or
something but then it becomes a
bottleneck when when when because you
ites we don't know how this will um
limit further scaling up um more
fundamentally what this is doing is we
are limiting the degree of Freedom we
are giving to the machines and that will
backfire at some point and this has been
uh going on for decades and bitter
lesson is I think the single most
important piece of writing in Ai and it
says uh this is my wording by way SE
past 70 years of entire AI research can
be summarized into developing
progressively more General method with
weaker modeling assumptions or inductive
biases and add more data and compute in
other words scale up and that has been
the recipe of entire AI research not
fancy things and if you think about this
the models of 20 2000 is a lot more
difficult than what we use now and so
it's much easier to get into AI nowadays
um from technical perspective so so this
uh is I think the really the key
information we have this compute cost is
going down exponentially and it's
getting cheaper faster than we're
becoming a better researcher so don't
compete with that and just try to
leverage that as much as possible and
that is the driving force that I wanted
to uh identify and I'm not saying this
is the only driving force but this is
the dominant driving force so we can
probably neglect the other ones so
here's a graphical version of that xais
we have a compute yaxis we have a
performance of some kind let's think
about some general intelligence and
let's look at two different methods uh
one with more structure more modeling
assumptions fancier math whatever and
then the other one is a less structure
what you see is typically you start with
a better performance uh when you have a
low compute regime and then but it
plateaus because of some kind of
structure backfiring and then with the
less structure because we give a lot
more freedom to the model it doesn't
work at the beginning but then as we add
more comput it's starts working and then
it gets better we call this more
scalable method so does that mean we
should just go with the least structure
most freedom to the model uh possible
way from the get-go and the answer is
obviously no let's think about even less
structure case this red one here is um
it will pick up a lot later um and
requires a lot more compute so it really
depends on where we are we cannot
indefinitely wait for the most General
case and so let's think about the case
where our compute situation is at this
dotted line if we're here we should um
choose this less structure one as
opposed to this even less structure one
because the other one doesn't really
work and the the other one works but
crucially we need to remember that we
are adding some structure because we
don't have compute so we need to remove
that later and so the difference between
these two method is that additional
inductive biases or structure we impose
someone impose uh that typically the get
removed so adding this uh what what that
means is that at the given level of
compute data algorithmic development and
architecture that we have there's like
an optimal inductive bias or structure
that we can add to the problem to make
the progress and that has been really uh
how we have made so much progress but
these are like shortcuts that hinder
further scaling later on so we have to
remove them later on when we have more
compute better algorithm or whatever and
as a community we do adding structure
very well and because there's an
incentive structure of with like papers
you add a nice one then you get a paper
but removing that doesn't really get you
much so that we don't really uh do that
and I think we should do a lot more of
those so maybe another implication of
This Bitter lesson is that because of
this what is better in the long term
almost necessarily looks worse now and
this is quite unique to AI research
because the AI research of current um
Paradigm is learning based method
meaning that we are giving models
Freedom the machines choose how they
learn so because we need to give more
freedom it gives uh it's a more chaotic
at the beginning so it doesn't work but
then when it start working we can put in
more compute and then it can be better
so it's really important to have this in
mind so to summarize we have identified
this dominant driving force behind the
AI research and that is this
exponentially cheaper compute and
Associated scaling up now that we have
identified if you remember back from my
uh initial slides we the next step is to
understand this driving force better and
so that's we're going to spend uh most
of the time doing that and for that we
need to go back to some history of
Transformer because this is a
transformance class and analyze key
structures and decisions that were made
by the uh researcher at the time and why
they did that whether that was an
optimal structure that could have been
added at the time and why they might be
irrelevant now and should we remove that
and we'll go through some of the
practice of this and hopefully this will
give you some flavor of what um like
scaling research looks like so now we'll
go into a little bit of the technical
stuff Tech uh Transformer architecture
there are some variants um I'll talk
about three of them first is the encoder
decoder which is the original
Transformer which has a little bit more
structure second one is the encoder only
which is popularized by Bert and then
third one is um decoder only which you
can think of as a current um like gpt3
or other language models this has a lot
less structure than the encoder decoder
so these are the three types we will go
into detail second the encoder only is
actually not that useful in the most
General sense it still has some um place
but we will so U just briefly go over
that and then spend most of the time
comparing one and three so one has more
structure what's the implication of that
and so on so first of all let's think
about what a Transformer is just um uh
at a very uh high level or first
principles what is a Transformer is a
sequence model and sequence model is a
has an input of a sequence so sequence
can be um sequence of elements can be
words or images or whatever it's a very
general Concept in this particular
example I'll show you with the words
sentences say sequence of words and then
we the first step is to tokenize it
because we have to represent this um
word in computers which requires just
some kind of a uh encoding scheme so we
just do do it with a fixed number of
integers that we have now sequence of
integers and then the dominant Paradigm
uh nowadays is to represent each
sequence element as a vector dense
Vector because we know how to multiply
them well and then so we have a sequence
of vectors um and finally this um
sequence model will do the following we
just want to model the interaction
between sequence elements and we do that
by let them take the dot product of each
other and if the dot product is high we
can say semantically they are more
related than the dot product that is low
and that's kind of the sequence model
and the Transformer is a particular type
of sequence model that uses What's
called the tension uh to model this
interaction so let's get into the
details of this encoder decoder which
was the original Transformer it's quite
many many pieces so let's go into a
little bit a piece at a time so starting
with the encoder so here I'm going to
show you an example of machine
translation which used to be very uh
cool thing and so you are you have an
English sentence that is good and then
we're going to translate into German so
first thing is to uh encode this into a
dense Vector so here I'm representing it
with the um this like a vector of size
three or something and then we have to
let them take the dot product so this um
you know lines represent which element
can talk to which element other elements
and here because it's an input we take
what is called a bir directional
attention so any token can talk to any
other token and then we have this uh um
MLP or feed forward layer which is per
token it doesn't have any interaction
you just do some you know some some some
multiplication just because we can do it
and then that's one layer and we repeat
that and times and this is the
Transformer encoder and at the end what
you get is the sequence of vectors each
representing the sequence element in
this case a word so that's the the
output of this encoder now let's look at
the decoder which is similarly shaped um
St of layers so here we put in as an
input um the uh what what the answer
should be so here BOS is a beginning of
sequence and then Dust is good I don't
know how to pronounce it but that's the
German translation of that is good and
so we kind of go through the similar
process here we have a causal sful
tension meaning that the tokens of time
step T can only attend to T and before
because when we start generating it we
don't have the future tokens so we
cannot when we train it we should limit
that and and that way we this is done by
like masking but uh just just different
from the
encoder so after this you can get um
after again end layers you you get this
um sequence output and you have this the
output is sequence so sequence to
sequence mapping this is a general um
encoded decoder architecture and when
you get this end of sequence you stop
generating it so this is the the overall
picture now I'll point out some
important uh attention pattern so we are
translating um the into German what is
in input to the encoder so there has to
be some connection between the decoder
and the encoder that is done by this
cross attention mechanism shown in this
red which is just that each Vector
representation of each sequence in the
output decoder should attend to some of
them in the encoder and that is done in
particular the design feature which is
interesting is that all the layers in
the decoder attend to the final layer
output of the encoder we'll come back to
the implication of this design so um yep
that's that and now move on to the
second type of architecture which is
encoder only we'll spend a little bit of
time here so again we have to uh in we
have the same input uh and we go through
similar uh structure and then the in
this case the final output is a single
Vector regardless of the length of the
uh sequence we just get a single vector
and and that is uh that represent the
input sequence that's a dense Vector
representation and then let's say we do
some kind of a sentiment analysis we run
through a task specific linear layer to
map it to classification labels positive
or negative probability here and that's
required for for all these um test
specific um cases and this is kind of
popularized by ber and what this means
is that here at the time 2018 when bird
came out uh we had the Benchmark called
glue which was a language understanding
test you have a sequence in
classification labels out for most cases
this was how the field really Advanced
at the time so when we care about such
tasks then there's an incentive to think
about simplifying the problem adding the
structure to the problem so that we can
make a progress so this the additional
structure that was put into this
particular architecture is that we're
going to give up on the uh generation if
we do that it becomes a lot simpler
problem instead of sequence to sequence
we're talking about sequence to
classification labels and that's just so
much easier and so um at some point 2018
2019 a lot of the papers or just
research was like we sometimes call it
birth Engineers little bit change of
something get .5% better on glue you get
a paper and things like that it was like
very chaotic era and and but but if we
look at from this perspective we are
putting the sequence uh structure of not
generating the sequence that puts a lot
of uh uh performance win but in the long
term it's not really useful so we're not
going to look at this encoder only
architecture going forward third
architecture decoded only this one is um
my favorite personally and it looks kind
of uh daunting but but uh because of
this attention pattern but it actually
is very simple so here we only have a
single stack and it can actually
generate stuff and so there's
misconception that some people think
this decoder only architecture is used
for language modeling next to comp
prediction so it cannot be used for
supervised learning but here we can
actually do it the trick is to have this
input that is good concatenated with the
Target and if you do that then it just
becomes um simple the sequence in
sequence out so what what we do is um
the self attention mechanism here is
actually handling both the cross
attention between Target and the input
and self attention sequence uh learning
within each so that's the causal
attention and then the the yeah as I
mentioned the output is a sequence and
then the key design features are self
attention is serving both roles and we
are in some sense sharing the parameters
between input and Target so same set of
parameters are applied to both input and
the target sequences so this this is the
decoder only now we will go into the
comparison so I think there many um like
they look very different at least on the
schematics so how different are they
actually and to I I argue that they're
actually quite similar and so to
illustrate that we're going to transform
starting from this encoder decoder which
has more structures built in and then
into um the decoder only architecture
and see what what are some of the
differences and then interpret those
differences those addition structures
are they relevant nowadays now that we
have more compute better algorithm and
so
on so let's have this table four
differences we'll see each of them and
then as we go through we'll um populate
the this table so let's first look at
this additional cross to tension um what
that means is that this on the left is
an encoded decoder which has this
additional red block that cross the
tension compared to the simpler one that
doesn't have that so we want to make it
make the left closer to the right so
that means we need to either get rid of
it or something and a tension mechanism
has kind of the four projection matrices
and so self attention and cross
attention actually have the same number
of parameters same shape so we can just
share them so that's the first step
share both of these and then it becomes
mostly the same uh mechanism and then so
that's the first difference separate
curs attention or self attention serving
both roles second difference is the
parameter sharing so what that means is
that between the input and the target
encoder decoder architecture uses a
separate parameters and decoder only
only has a single stack so it uses the
share parameter so if you want to make
the left close to right we want to share
the encoder parameters so let's do that
I just color this so now they share the
parameters third difference is the
target to input attention pattern so we
need to connect the target to the input
and how does that how is it done in the
encoder decoder case we had this cross
attention and then in the decoder only
it's a per
uh the self tension doing everything
what the difference is that U we have
this
um every layer of the decoder attending
to the final layer output of the encoder
whereas if you think about this decoder
is actually per layer within layer when
we are decoding the say word do we are
looking at the same layer representation
of the encoder and and that's within
layer and I think this is the design
feature so if you want to make this
close to that we have to bring back back
this attention to each layer so now
layer one will be attending to layer one
of this and that's the then finally the
last uh difference is the input
attention I mentioned about this by
directional attension and because we
have this decoder only typically with
the um unidirectional tension we need to
make them matching so that's the we can
just get rid of it I just got rid of the
the some of the arrows so then at this
point these two architectures are almost
identical um a little bit of difference
in the cross tangent but same number of
parameters and if you have in deep
learning if you just train this these
two architecture in the same task same
data I think you will get pretty much
within the noise probably closer than if
you train the same thing twice so um I
would say they are identical and so
these are the main differences now look
at how what are the additional
structures what they mean what they mean
me means so yeah that's the populated
table now and then so we can say that
encoder decoder compared to the decoder
only architecture has these additional
um structures indu bies built in so
let's go into each of them the first one
is the what what encoder decoder tries
added as a structure is that input and
the target sequences are sufficiently
different that we it'll be useful to use
a separate parameters that's the
Assumption and so why is that useful
when that when can that assumption be
useful and one example is machine
translation uh back when the transform
was introduced in 2017 translation was
really popular task and it was difficult
consider difficult and because it's
you're a sequence to sequence and you
can actually have a blue score which is
heuristic based method that can give you
a single number and then people can
optimize that so what what that in that
task we have this input and Target in
completely different languages so if you
if the goal is to learn translation only
then it kind of makes sense to have okay
this parameter the encoder will take
care of the English and this parameter
in the decoder will take care of the
German that seems natural and and what
about now modern language models is
about learning knowledge and it's not
just about translation or not even about
language language just comes up as a
byproduct of doing this next token
prediction and translation as well so
does it make sense to have a separate
parameter for um this kind of situation
now like we have some knowledge in
German some knowledge in English and we
if anything we want to combine them and
have if we represent them in a separate
parameters I don't think that's natural
so I would say with this uh much more
General larger models that can do a lot
of things this assumption seems very
unnatural to me second example is a
little bit more modern uh two years ago
when I was at Google uh and with Jason
we uh did this instruction fine tuning
work and what this is uh is you take the
pre-train model and then just fine tune
on academic data set and and so that it
can understand the natural language
instruction so the detail doesn't matter
but here let's think about the the
performance gain by doing this fine
tuning on two different architectures we
tried so first five is the flon T5 which
is T5 based which is encoder decoder
architecture last one uh the letter five
decoder only architecture based on pal
so we spend 99% of the time on Palm
optimizing a lot of these and then at
the end we just spend like three days on
T5 but the the performance gain was a
lot higher on this and I was really
confused about this in in a very good
way and after the paper was published I
wanted to like dig a little bit deeper
into why this might be the case
so uh the my hypothesis is that it's
about the length so academic data sets
we use we use like 1832 tasks and here
they have this very distinctive
characteristic where we have a long
input long in order to make the task
more difficult but then we cannot make
the target long because if we do there's
no way to grade it so there's
fundamental challenge of that so what
happens is you have a long text of input
and then short text of the Target and
and so this is kind of the length
distribution of what it went into the
fla uh fine tuning so then you see this
um you have a very different sequence
going into the encoder as an input and a
very different type of sequence going
into the target so now this encoder
decoder architecture has an assumption
that they will be very different that
structure really shines because of this
it was a kind of an accident but that
was I think why this really architecture
was um just suitable for fine-tuning
with the academic data sets what about
now do we care about this kind of a
assumption and if you think about the
general use cases of language models
nowadays if anything the more
interesting cases involve longer
generation longer Target uh just because
we cannot grade them doesn't mean that
we are not interested in them actually
if anything we are more interested in
that so now we have this like longer
Target situation so this separate
sequence length um parameter doesn't
seem to make much sense and moreover we
think about this chat application like
chat GPT we do multi- turn conversation
and then so what is a target of this
turn becomes the input of the next turn
and then my question is does that make
sense to even think about a um different
parameters if next turn it's going to be
the same
thing so um that was the first inductive
bi we just uh mentioned and then the
second structure is that Target element
can only attend to the full fully
encoded ones the final out putut of the
encoder let's look at this additional
structure what that means so as I
mentioned we have this U very top layer
attending to it and so in deep neuron
Nets typically we see that the bottom
layers and the top layers encode
information at a very different level uh
meaning that for example in computer
vision lower layer bottom layers encode
something like edges top layers higher
levels combining the features something
like cat face and so we call this deep
learning a hierarchical representation
learning method and so now the question
is if decoder layer one attends to
incoder final layer which probably has a
very different level of information is
that some kind of an information
bottleneck which actually um motivated
the original attention mechanism and in
practice I would say in my experience
doesn't really make any difference and
that's because my experience was limited
to say 25 24 layers of encoder of T5 so
layer one 10 to 24 probably fine but
what if we have 10x or THX more layers
would that be problematic I'm not really
comfortable with that so I think this is
also unnecessary um uh design that maybe
we need to
revisit final structure we're going to
talk about is the when we do this
there's like a bir directional thing in
the encoder decoder Let's uh think about
that so yeah bir directional input
attention is that really necessary so
when we um in had this Bert b in BT
stand for bidirectional 2018 when we
were solving that question answering
squat actually was very difficult task
so if you have any additional trick it
can make a huge difference by
directionality was really uh useful like
I think maybe boosting up the squat
score by like 20 so it was really huge
thing but at scale I don't think this
matters at much this is my highly
anecdotal experience so we did in flan 2
we tried both B directional and
unidirectional fine tuning didn't really
make much difference so but but I want
to point out this B directionality
actually bring in an engineering
challenge for modern multi-turn chat
application so at every turn the new
input has to be encoded again and for
Union directional tension it's uh much
much better so here is what I mean by
that so let's think about this um more
modern conversation between user and uh
assistant how are you bad and why and so
here if we think about the B directional
case we will and when we generate bad we
need to encode this input with the B
directional thing which is fine and then
um after the bad is generated when we
we're trying to generate why we'll need
to encode how again because how can ATT
tend to bad so we need to do everything
from scratch again in contrast if we do
uni Direction one we can do uh much much
better because now when we are trying to
generate why we don't have to redo how
because we cannot uh attend to the ne
future tokens so we don't have to do
anything if you see the difference this
part can be cached and then this part is
the only thing that can has to be
encoded again so this kind of makes a
big difference when we think about multi
multiple turns going in so I would say
bir directional tension did well in 2018
which is mostly soled by scale and now
because of this engineering challenge we
don't really need that so to conclude we
have looked into this driving force
Domino driving force covering this AI
research and that was this exponentially
cheaper compute and Associated scaling
effort and so to understand this driving
for course we analyzed some of the
additional structures added to the
encoder decoder compared to the decoder
only and then thought about how what
that means as a from the perspective of
scaling and I wanted to just conclude
with this remark so we have looked at
these kind of analysis which are all one
can say this is just historical um
artifacts and doesn't matter but if you
do many of these now you look at this
current events you can hopefully think
about those in a more unified Manner and
then um see okay what assumptions in my
problem that I need to revisit and are
they relevant and if not why and you
have an answer to it is can we do it
with a more General thing and scale up
and so I hope you can go back and really
uh think about these problems and
together we can really shape the future
of AI in a really nice way so that's it
thanks