Okay. Uh we'll get started. Um
this is the second of the post training
lectures and we're going to talk about
well we're going to finish off the
lecture from from Tuesday first. Uh
whatever remaining content we have. Um
and then we'll talk about reinforcement
learning from verifiable rewards kind of
the new exciting thing that's been
happening over maybe the last six months
or so. um and really powering all of
these reasoning models that you kind of
see uh dominating the landscape. So, uh,
before I get into the verifiable rewards
part, um, the exciting, you know, math
RL content, um, I'm going to go back and
I'm going to finish off RLHF, right? So,
this is, uh, a very very quick recap of
the last few slides from Tuesday's
lecture, right? So, we want to do
reinforcement learning from human
feedback, which is the setting where we
observe pair-wise preference data, like
which of the two responses are better,
and we'd like to get a language model
policy that sort of maximizes some sort
of underlying reward. um for this
preference data, right? Um and if you
remember, DPO is this algorithm that
allows to allows us to optimize this
reinforcement learning objective. And
this objective is hard because our
language model, the policy, so to speak,
is is on the bottom of this expectation,
right? You're sampling from your
language model. You're not just
maximizing uh the likelihood under the
language model. Um, and the way we're
going to do this, um, you know, if you
remember the derivation is that we're
going to, you know, make the
nonparametric assumption that our policy
class is the set of all functions. We're
going to rewrite the reward as a ratio
of the policies. Um, and then plug that
in to the Bradley Terry objective. And
so what we're going to do is we're going
to find a policy such that sort of the
implied reward maximizes the probability
of seeing sort of the references uh,
sorry, the pair-wise preferences that we
see, right? Um so now this is great
because it's basically supervised
learning on a kind of alternatively
parameterized objective. Um which is
nice. Um DPO updates have this following
form. Um the reason why you know DPO has
kind of took the world by storm for a
bit um a year ago or so um is that it
can be written in this very nice form
where you know what you're going to do
is you're going to take these gradient
steps which are going to be you know
multiplied by beta. That's kind of your
regularization.
You're going to have higher weight when
your reward estimates are wrong. So
you're going to update more when your
sort of implied rewards are are not
correct. Um and then it you're going to
increase the likelihood of the good
example and you're going to decrease the
likelihood of the bad example. Right? As
I was kind of saying, if you sort of
remember what I was saying last lecture,
um really RL algorithms kind of boil
down often to just upweight the good
stuff, downweight the bad stuff. And the
subtlety really is in deciding, you
know, h what the good stuff is and how
much to upweight, right? And so this is
one particular choice of doing that. And
we'll see, you know, other things
happen. Uh and so DPO um works pretty
well. Um for a while essentially all the
open model releases use some variant of
a DPO uh to do their post training. Um
and really it's just very easy to get
working um compared to to uh PO. And so
for a while it was um really the
dominant approach. Um in the the time
since then there was a huge flood of
papers that was like you know asterisk
PO. Basically everyone wanted to come up
with a DPO variant. There was dozens and
dozens of papers. Um there's so many
that I don't think it's it's worth it to
go over the big uh ocean of such papers.
Um, I'll mention two, um, not because
necessarily that I think they're like
the right ones, but because I think
they're ones that have been used
recently, um, by people that are sort of
really pushing the limits of of this
kind of DPO style post training. One is
SPIO. Um, and SPIO just makes a very
simple modification or two simple
modifications. Um, the first one is to
really normalize the update size by the
length of the responses. Um, we'll see
kind of this theme appearing later. Um,
and the other thing they do is they just
get rid of the reference. So now we've
lost the DPO sort of mathematical
argument that you know what we're doing
is looking at ratios of policies but
well this is more purely looking at
something looks like something where we
upweight you know the um the good stuff
and downweight the bad stuff under that
sort of underlying motivation simpio
totally fine um there's other variants
uh where you don't do necessarily this
like reference policy removal where you
just sort of normalize by length um
called length normalized dpo um that
kind of people have done. Um, and this,
you know, these two forms, DPO with
length normalization and simpio were the
things that were tried, you know, pretty
extensively by, uh, AI2 folks when they
did Tulu 3. Um, and I think one thing
that I'll point out, so I'm going to
pause for a moment because I feel like
this is an important conceptual, not
conceptual, just an important empirical
point, which is that in RL a lot of the
the findings are very very contingent on
the specific setting, right? So
depending on the environment in which
you run it, depending on the base model
that you have, depending on the the
post-training preferences that you're
running on, you will find pretty
different conclusions. Um, and so one
example of this, right? So, uh, you
know, a bunch of the AI2 folks have been
doing a lot of really good post-training
empirical work. Um, and they had one
work where they were sort of comparing
DPO and PO and they had found that PO
was better than DPO um, because of maybe
it's on policiness and they show this,
you know, this jump exactly is the DPO
to PO gap. Um, and then in a later work
in Tulu 3, they find actually if you do
your SFT in a sort of nicer, better way,
actually that just eats up all the gains
of both PO and DPO. So neither of these
really get any gains. And the only thing
that does better is maybe DPO with
normalization, right? Like pretty
different conclusions. Of course, a lot
is different between this left and right
paper. Um, but it's not that one is
wrong and the other is wrong. really
that you should be careful about reading
too many like generalized conclusions
about any of this stuff on the basis um
of one paper right so that's an
important note even as I go and talk
about you know PO and I go and talk
about uh GRPO later in this you
shouldn't really take any single
experimental result necessarily as
gospel okay so the last thing I want to
end with for RLHF um is sort of two
important things um and one of them will
really just motivate I think the
entirety of today's lecture so I think
that's important so the first is
overoptimization. Um so in some sense
this is just overfitting in fancier
naming but it is a a term that I think
is very important because what it's
saying is essentially as you optimize
your policy more and more so think about
this x-axis as how much RLI did
initially your reward kind of goes up
and up and up but eventually you know
the reward that reward models that you
fitted on human preferences are
diverging from you know real human
preferences and the more you optimize
you eventually kind of diverge out right
like you're not doing any better you're
just you know optimiz optimizing uh but
not actually improving your rewards,
right? So this overoptimization thing
appears basically everywhere in RHF. It
is a very big problem. Um and so that
that is kind of a a concern. Um and
overoptimization is a phenomenon that
really happens in many ways because of
the noisiness of human preferences and
the complexities of human preferences.
So so um some of my students had a study
where you know they basically did RLHF
on human preferences. They did RLHF on
noisy versions of, you know, AI feedback
and then they did RLHF on non-noisy
versions of human feedback. And you see
clear over optimization phenomena both
for humans and for noisy AI feedback,
but not really for sort of clean
noiseless um AI feedback. And so really,
you know, if you're going to be
post-raining, you should expect to see
curves that look like things on the
left. as you train your model to do
better and better on your sort of proxy
rewards that you've measured, you're not
necessarily going to get better and
better models in terms of uh sort of
human preference win rates. Okay? And
then the other thing which is an
important side note is that when you do
RL, right, remember that I said that
we're no longer in probabilistic world,
right? So when you're doing supervised
fine-tuning or when you're doing
pre-training, it's quite clear that what
you're doing is you're trying to do
probabilistic modeling on some
distribution, right? you're doing
distribution matching for something,
right? Um, but RLHF is all it's all just
a policy. There's no underlying
necessarily distribution. And how this
manifests is that often you'll get much
less calibrated models, right? A number
of results across many different papers
have shown that, you know, RLHF models
um often, especially at temperature one,
you know, show much more overconfident
behavior. So, this one was from one of
the anthropic papers. This one was from,
I think, the GPT4 release. Um this one
was from a a paper that one of my
posttos did. In all these cases
essentially the RLHF models are much
less calibrated and maybe that's fine
right because calibration isn't part of
the reward that you're putting in. So so
that's you know as designed but you
should be very careful thinking of these
models as sort of calibrated
probabilistic models which you might be
sort of tempted to do if you're kind of
coming into this from a generative
modeling um background. So, okay. Um, so
up until now, we've been kind of
thinking about um, RLHF and all these
things. Actually, I'll stop for a
moment. If anyone has any final
questions for RLHF, I'll answer them
before I go on because we're going to
totally switch topics to uh, RL from
verified rewards in a moment.
Yes. Uh, going back to the human
preferences graph, what's what are the
two axes that that we're looking at?
This one? Yeah. Yeah. So, the x-axis is
proxy reward. So, um, here we're fitting
like a reward model. We're not we're not
doing VPO here, right? So let's say
we're doing something like PO where we
fit a a reward uh classifier and the
X-axis is saying how well did my RL
algorithm optimize that reward
classifier. Right? So this is success at
RL on is on the X- axis. Y-axis is this
is kind of like true win rates either
measured by you know AI feedback here or
human feedback. So this is like real
human votes you know on the y- axis
here. Um, and so this is saying you
might think that succeeding at RL will
make you succeed at the actual task that
you know you're trying to optimize for.
That's not the case. It will overfit at
some point for at least human
preferences. Um, yes. So question
why is it written in that not like beta
log a minus log b or just like log of a
b like are you just asking like why
don't they like pull the fractions out
in the log or because I thought is this
like a numeric computation thing that
like when you take these two ratios the
taking the log is easier to compute and
that's why we want to do no I don't
think that I think taking ratios is
actually add numerically. So I think
this is really just like a save the
space you know the ratios you know are
are more compact and they're also
intuitive objects right so the moment
you put simple it becomes a different
form because you no longer have the same
beta concept yes that's right yeah
simpio is just like a very different
motivation for why you would do this
thing right there's no ratios it's a
very fundamentally different object
yes in the graph where you showed like a
more sort of hacking thing um I was
wondering like how you like how the
measure like you know the ground truth
of like the reward score, right? Cuz
presumably the reward function is a
model like the human preference, right?
But it's kind of like a train test gap,
right? The x-axis here, you know, you
have a train set, you fit a reward model
on it and you're measuring that fitted
reward model, right? And the y-axis is
fresh samples from the true reward
oracle, right? Um and so they're
measuring in expectation the same thing,
but they're not measuring in finite
sample the same thing. like the same
this is the same as like train test gaps
in machine learning right same
conceptual object they are in
expectation measuring the same thing um
for any finite sample that's not the
case okay good um so I think you know
all this questions about um
reinforcement learning from human
feedback I think brings up a good point
which is that you know human feedback is
very difficult to optimize it's very
difficult to scale and so you might
wonder are there other kinds of more
effective RL that we can bring to bear
on post training right And that's going
to get us here, right? So, up until now,
we've been kind of talking about chat
GBD 3.5 and that era of models. And now
I think we want to talk about 01 and the
the you know the new set of kind of
reasoning style models, right? And the
way we're going to get there is kind of
this thinking of saying, okay, we have
this very powerful tool now. We have
this reinforcement learning tool that we
can use for post- training. Um, and
initially, you know, the the instinct
was to say, you know, there's one true
objective, and that objective is whether
people like the bot, right? And so, if
we just optimize for the true objective
we care about, that's all we need. Turns
out to be very difficult, right? Human
uh human uh approval is easy to hack.
It's hard to collect at scale. It's hard
to RL at scale. For all those reasons,
you see, you know, overoptimization and
all these kind of issues. On the other
hand, we could instead turn to to where
RL has really dominated, right? things
like alpha go or alpha fold. And then
you know looking at those domains you
might say you know what we really need
is kind of a domain which we know the
true reward and for which we can
evaluate such true rewards very quickly
and efficiently and at scale right and
if we could do that then we can bring to
bear all of the successes of
reinforcement learning from the past
into language modeling. Right? So that's
the overall mindset that we're we're
we're adopting now. Right? We have the
tools that we've built. Now let's apply
them into a very kind of different way
of using the same tools, right? Taking
inspiration from successes in in RL.
Okay. Um and so today I'm going to talk
in two parts, right? So the first part
is just going to be an algorithmic part,
right? So this part on the very top I'm
going to talk about different um
algorithms. First I'm going to talk
about PO in more detail because you know
I kind of cut that from last lecture for
length reasons. And then I'm going to
transform PO into GRPO. um a simpler
version in some sense and then we'll
talk through those objectives and
various uh implementation details of
GRPO um to get us to multiple like
canonical variations of GRPO and having
done that we will then walk through the
three I think uh big reasoning model
sort of training things that have been
done as case studies um since after part
one you'll have all the tools that you
need to understand everything that is
happening in part two right and after
you do part two you'll understand at
least how these three uh Chinese open
LMS were made.
Okay, so now we are going to return to
PO. Um it is the thing that I didn't
want to do but we have to do in order
for you to understand why GRPO exists,
right? Um so what is PO? Um at least in
my sort of mental model of what PO is,
we start from the simplest possible
thing and then we move you know slowly
but surely downwards to PO, right? So
the simplest possible thing um I
mentioned this in last lecture. This is
the policy gradient, right? So on the
left, I would like to optimize the
expected reward under my policy P of
theta, right? Um, and we're going to
optimize that through gradient descent.
So I take the gradient of that object
and I get the right hand side of that
equation, which is the policy gradient,
the expectation uh under my current
policy of the reward and I'm going to
take gradient steps that sort of either
increase or decrease the probability
according to the sign of the reward Z.
Right? Um, hopefully straightforward. Um
if this is not familiar to you, you can
sort of brush up on how that policy
gradient derivation happens. Now um
there are two things that we might want
to to think about uh here that are kind
of inefficient, right? So the first
thing is that this is uh what you might
call purely on policy, right? So the way
that the reinforced gradients work, I
have to sample from P theta and then I
will immediately take a step uh on those
sampled examples, right? And so every
time that I want to take a gradient
step, I have to compute a reward, right?
and I have to do a roll out. You will
sort of understand this in your in your
assignment five, but the expensive part
of RL is the rollouts, right? We have to
actually run the language model and get
samples. And we know that that's slow,
right? From Percy's inference lecture,
we know that that's very complicated.
It's very tricky. Um, we would much
rather sample less frequently, right? We
we do a roll out once, we sample once,
and then we take multiple updates on
those rollouts. So that motivates
something called TRPO, right? where
instead of taking updates from P theta,
I would like to allow my sort of updates
to go stale. So what I'm going to do is
I'm going to sample from um P theta old,
this sort of base distribution down here
um but still get sort of valid policy
gradients. Well, how can I do that?
Well, I can do what's called an
important sampling correction and then I
can keep, you know, um, my policies
close to my old one so that I don't get
too far uh, from my old one and get sort
of crazy reward estimates. Right? Very
simple idea. Just do a little bit of off
to on policy correction. You get
something called TRPO. This a of T is a
lower variance version of R of Z. I'm
not going to talk about advantage
estimation uh, in much more detail. PO
is a is a simple extra step beyond this.
It says, you know, instead of doing KL
divergences, I'm just going to clip the
advantages. And this is naturally going
to force my policy to remain close
because if I go too far, then I'm not
going to be able to get higher and
higher rewards. These rewards will just
get clipped off at sort of a one minus
epsilon or one plus epsilon. There's an
upper bound to how much reward I can
collect. So there's no incentive for the
RL algorithm to make the policy really
different from the current one, right?
So it's a soft version you can say think
of kind of this idea. Okay, so PO very
successful RL algorithm um used in many
different places um you know used in
sort of very toy RL environments uh it
was used in OpenAI sort of Dotaabot um
works very well in such actual RL tasks
oh yeah there was a video I forgot about
that yeah look you can run around yeah
okay um and at a conceptual level it's
not that complicated right um if you go
look at the openai documentation uh for
PO it looks fairly simple right you see
that equation that I listed above, it's
this po clip objective. And really the
only thing that's maybe slightly
complicated is that this a of t is
actually calculated by using something
called a value function. So you need a
second neural network to essentially
compute kind of the expected rewards. Um
and that would be used to to in some
sense lower the variance of my
gradients, right? Um I'm not going to go
into the details once again of of sort
of all the RL details but you know the
one implementation uh difference here
that matters is that we need this value
function and that will become important
in a moment here.
Um but PO in practice is a very very
different beast from PO in theory. Um
and you know you're in for a very bad
time if you know there's a blog post
that says 37 implementation details of
PO. Um you know I don't want to know all
37 of those guys. Um, and you know, it's
a there's a huge long list of sort of
different PO variants in this blog post
and all of them have the different
scores on the RL uh benchmarks and
there's a whole paper written on why
implementation details matter in PO and
how if you really mess it up, you're not
even computing the policy gradient
correctly anymore, but it actually works
better, right? Um, so it's kind of a a
crazy place. Um, if you look at the
implementation details of PO and so we
actually do have to maybe look at a live
implementation detail. Um, I'll actually
go over it quickly because PO isn't the
point of this lecture. But what I want
to get across to you is, you know, you
all haven't been necessarily working on
this post- training space. Like why do
people care so much about alternatives
to PO? It is because of things like
this, right? PO works well, but it is
kind of a beast. Um, and this is one
example I think from the early days of
of RLHF uh re-implementations.
Um, there was this nice diagram
describing, you know, this is how you
would do a pretty standard
implementation of PO. This diagram is
pretty gnarly, right? We've got a reward
model for RLHF. We've got a value model
that's supposed to keep track of kind of
the expected reward. Um, we've got
generalized advantage estimation. I
haven't even explained what that is. Um,
and that's going to go into the policy
um, language model. and we're going to
do, you know, our policy gradient
updates. So there's there's all this
sort of machinery that has to go into
place for PO to work. Um so we're going
to look at an implementation. Um a few
years back now actually um some of my
students and I did you know
reimplementations of algorithms like PO
um and other people have used it. So
this is an implementation that's been
somewhat tested. Not to say that this is
a good implementation. I'm sure you know
something like uh more modern
implementations from Volcano Engine and
other things uh probably work a little
bit better but I just want to walk you
through all the different components. Um
also because as you write um GRPO in
your assignments your structure will
probably mirror some aspects of this
right all RL algorithms have similar
kind of outer loop. So um if we look at
this right so a a PO step looks very
similar to a standard uh gradient update
step uh in a language model. So this is
the outer sort of loop. What we're going
to do is we're going to you know get a
bunch of rollouts. Um and once we get
you know a bunch of rollouts what we're
going to do is we're going to compute
some losses and then we're going to just
take backwards and then gradient steps
with you know clip norm and that's it
right very unintimidating. the outer
loop of of RL is is usually fine, right?
Um, you know, loss computation is also
basically the same thing. So, um, this
is probably uh small for those of you in
the back. Um, but if you look at this,
you know, what you have is one block
that's computing the loss for the value
function. Remember, PO has both a value
function and a policy. So, we have to
update both of those at once. So, we're
computing how close is the value
function to kind of the actual sort of
returns, the rewards that we saw. Um,
and we want to keep those close because
the value function is supposed to
provide variance reduction. And then
we've got the actual sort of rewards
that we're going to update on for uh PO.
And then we have sort of the clipping
constants 1 - epsilon 1 plus epsilon.
This code is literally just copying this
back over. And just to give you sort of
some, you know, intuition for
hyperparameters, you know, a typical
clip range might be something like 02
here, right? So, so you would be allowed
to go essentially from 0.8 to 1.2 two in
likelihood ratio between your old and
new policy. Um the rollouts is where
things start to get gnarly, but this is
still essentially just calling
inference. The left side is really just
sampling, you know, rollouts from your
current policy and then you evaluate the
log problems of your samples and you
move on to the right and what do you
see? Well, uh the only subtlety here is
that your value and your reward and your
policy may have different tokenizers. So
you got to do retokenization. But
otherwise you just feed your rollouts
into the model. So okay, at this point
you're like looking at this code and you
say okay that's fine like this is not
not so horrible. Um but the places where
things start to get a little bit tricky.
Um is first we have to do some reward
shaping right? So what does this mean?
Um so stepping slightly back. One thing
that's weird about reinforcement
learning for language models is if you
you know think about it from the RL
perspective technically it's kind of
like a contextual bandit. Well, what
what is a contextual bandit? A
contextual bandit is something where you
get an input and you have a bunch of
possible, you know, uh actions to take
and you immediately get a reward, right?
In language modeling, you get a prompt,
you can give an output, and you
immediately get a reward. There's no
like state transitions. There's no
environment exploration. There's none of
this like complexity, right? Um reward
shaping here is essentially constructing
um uh per token losses in order to be
able to give you something more uh easy
to learn for the RL algorithm. And so
what happens in practice for PO and for
GRPO which you'll be implementing um is
that the KL terms essentially the
regularization that we're applying is
actually computed per token whereas the
um actual true reward like the did you
complete the task or not kind of thing
that's computed at the very last token.
Right? So you see that there's
essentially a per token reward for the
regularization and there's a single
terminal reward at the end for um
success or not. Yes. What does it mean?
What does not work?
Um, oh, right, right, right. This is um
this is a Right, right. This is uh kind
of funny. This basically we're only
adding per token KL penalty, but once
again, this is one of those funny um uh
PL implementation things. Um this second
line here, this is the actual true KL
calculation. Um but when this number
goes to negative, um it becomes
numerically unstable and you can
actually hit that pretty often. And so
this gets clamped off at zero, which you
know all of you know if you clip off a a
log likelihood uh ratio at zero that's
not a KL anymore, but it is some
approximation to a KL. Yes. What are um
so we've talked about like boss
function. What are our update steps
especially like as it relates to the um
the reward function? Is that the same as
other Yeah. Yeah. Good good point. So
the the updates you know as I was saying
in this outer loop is actually just
taking gradient steps. So in terms of
your code it will look no different than
just taking you know normal gradient
steps. Um what is happening here though
is in some sense uh let's go back to the
policy gradient equation here. Um right
if you write down this thing this is r
of z * p theta z. This is kind of like
just taking gradients with respect to
theta of rzp log p theta z. It's a
weighted loss that you then take
gradients of. Um, and what you're not
doing is technically if you're taking a
real gradient, you should also take a
gradient into P theta, but you don't do
that. There's kind of a stop implicit
stop gradient. And so all you do is you
compute this inner loss, you feed it to
the autograd, and you'll get the right
steps for the rein uh for the policy
gradient.
Um, yeah, you'll have to do that for for
the assignment as well. And we have like
a little tutorial that explains kind of
what's going on there in case that that
quick explanation was not clear. Okay.
And finally, the part that I think is
the gnarliest is there's a the box that
I did not explain called generalized
advantage estimation, right? Um so what
you need to do whenever you have a
policy gradient, um the variances of the
gradient are often very high, right? And
so you want to do as much variance
reduction as you can. And instead of
multiplying the gradients with uh the
rewards directly, you can instead you
can show that the following um a of t
quantity which is essentially a
discounted um advantage estimate. That's
a sort of RL term um is an appropriate
substitute. And so one of the things
that PO does that's very different is to
use this advantage estimate where you
can tweak lambda um and gamma to trade
off bias and variance uh of your
gradients. One of the funny things
though is despite kind of the annoyance
of this this implementation complexity
of like maintaining this value function
and estimating all these quantities um
you can just pick gamma equals lambda
equals 1 which reduces this whole thing
basically to a baselined policy
gradient. So your guts taking R uh minus
the the implied value. Um and that works
well too. And so the point of making you
go through this was um a lot of the
implementations details for PO are both
simple in that it is just the outer loop
RL. You do just take gradients and also
kind of annoying, right? You have to do
all these sort of clipping things. You
have to think about what am I going to
do with the generalized advantage
estimate. Um what am I going to do to
train the value um estimate? Um but you
expect to see, you know, overall
increasing rewards. um including reward
models and sort of negative KL rewards
kind of go down. This is a once again um
a contextual bandit. So you expect to
see pretty reasonable training curves,
not like crazy RL ones. Okay, so I went
through PO. Um that was kind of a
whirlwind tour, but I think hopefully
you get the context of a what PO is and
b that it is sometimes a little bit
tricky to get working right. And so, you
know, this has motivated a lot of people
to try to find alternatives to PO. Um,
what we're going to want to do is to
apply, you know, essentially these RL
algorithms to settings where PO applies.
And PO applies very well to to general
RL settings where you have sort of
rewards. Um, but we don't want the
complicated implementation. And maybe
more importantly, we want to get rid of
the value model. That is actually if you
try to implement PO really, really
annoying, right? because a value model
is usually as big as your policy. So now
in terms of GPU memory, you're paying
twice the cost of your language model.
Right? Now you might say, okay, uh why
can't we use DPO? Well, DPO is well
suited for like pair-wise comparisons
like Bradley Terry comparisons. Um it's
not so good if what you want to do is
let's say do reinforcement learning on
math questions and check whether or not
the answers are correct, right? There's
no pair-wise structure so to speak
inherently there. So maybe DPO is not
great, right? Um, DPO also, you know,
originally is is kind of an offline
algorithm in a sense in that it has a
whole bunch of sort of pairs that you
initially collect and you just update
your model on those. You could make it
online by iterating, but that's not
usually the way in which uh people apply
GPO.
So then now this brings us to the new
hotness which I think is uh GRPO, right?
So GRPO is actually very very simple um
both in motivation and in actual
implementation. So where you start with
is conceptually you start at PO, right?
You start with very similar pieces. Um
you think about kind of this clipping
thing. You think about policy updates in
very similar ways. Um but what you do is
you remove the really complicated
generalized advantage estimation. You
just get rid of it completely. Um and
you replace it with something that is
much much simpler. Right? Uh so what is
the much simpler thing? Well, we are
going to replace um the advantage which
used to be this like GA thing. It was
the sum o over returns and had the value
function in there. Instead, it's going
to be this equation three at the bottom
of this slide here. Um and what is this?
Uh the advantage of you know response I
is equal to the reward that response I
receives minus the mean of the responses
within my group. And I'll define what a
group is in a moment. and then divided
by the standard deviation of the rewards
within the group. So this is a zcore uh
if you know what that is um of the
rewards within the group. Right? Now
what is a group? A group is a very in
some sense natural object for for
language model RL. You have an input
question. Let's say like solve this math
problem. Right? That is a group. And I
have many different candidate responses.
I have capital G uh different responses.
Um and those are all the responses
within my single group. Right? So um the
nice thing is if you think about it
right maybe problems are harder or
easier right you know some math problems
are much harder than others um and
because of that the average reward that
my sort of other samples receive is a
natural baseline for myself and and
people have explored exactly these kinds
of algorithms um if you look up like uh
reinforcement learning with leave one
out or sorry policy gradients with leave
one out this is the leave one out
baseline um in action minus the standard
deviation piece um right
Um the yes I was wondering
talking about here like so you said it's
a it's like they have a batch of
questions right and then there are
answers to it which are reported so like
is each like answer only corresponding
to one unique question or are we doing
like multiple like kind of um like
trajectories of the same question for
multiple questions right you do multiple
answers per question and that's how you
get kind of variance reduction in
like multiple different questions and
also like kind of like multiple answers
for each of the questions. Is that a
really important example? No. No. So for
each question Q, GRPO samples a group of
outputs, right? So so I mean this is not
batched like you you normally you would
if you were doing this for real, you
would have multiple questions and for
each question you'd have G responses and
those would get baseline together.
Across questions you would have no
baselining or any interaction really
other than the policies get updated
together. Okay. So the the baseline is
only doing within the same question. And
that that's why the baseline makes
sense, right? Because a question is like
hard or easy and the mean of that that
reward isn't sometimes capturing the
question difficulty and you're
subtracting that guy out.
Okay, good. Um and the other thing, this
is a fun note. Um I I'm going to mention
it because I just kind of think this is
fun and cool. Uh this DKL, uh if you've
seen lots of KL divergence computations,
um this is actually a little
non-standard, right? uh because the
natural kale divergence estimate is
actually just you you take a bunch of
samples and then you compute the average
of the log ratio which is kind of this
inner term over here right um but this
one from from gpo actually has these two
extra terms it has the log or has the
ratio of pi ref over pi theta and has
this minus one um and you can kind of
convince yourself that if you take the
expectation of this with respect to pi
theta um you know this is just going to
be uh cancelling with this one over
here. So this is a control variant
scheme that reduces the variance of uh
this KL divergence estimate which is
cool uh because maybe you all need to
estimate KL divergence from samples. Uh
this equation two is just a slightly
nicer way of estimating that exact same
thing. Okay.
Um and GRPO is really nice. Um oh one
one last note. Um if you're only taking
one step which is doing the pure online
case, right? all this clipping stuff
just kind of disappears and all you're
doing is policy gradients, right? Policy
gradient is just upweing good stuff and
downweing bad stuff where the rewards
that I'm multiplying the policy
gradients by is this avi. So it's just
like an incredibly simple algorithm for
the the truly online case where you're
not doing multiple steps on a single
example. Um so there's multiple kind of
different repositories um for gpo
implementations. Um I I can point you to
several including uh this one that I
sort of copied and put onto this slide
here. Um but basically uh I can just say
that it's it's exactly the way you think
it would go. Um sort of in the outer
loop you would compute the reward for
each nor roll out you normalize for each
group the the mean and the variance of
the rewards. You'd compute the KL term
in this case per sequence which isn't
quite right uh for the more heavyweight
implementations. And then you do
gradient updates on the loss. And this
is you know one example of the loss
computation that you also have here. Um
and the advantage computation unlike in
the uh PO case is just really really
simple. Uh this is almost exactly you
know line for line the equations that I
showed you with just one minor
difference that's not shown in the
equation which is that you know as you
do in almost everything because we're
dividing by the standard deviation you
add a tiny fudge factor of 1 eg4 to to
make sure it doesn't numerically uh blow
up on you right and you'll have to do
this in the assignment as well. you'll
have to add a little epsilon uh to your
gpo uh setup.
So, how well does this work? Um gpo
works pretty well. Um this is from the
original uh deepseek math paper. Um and
I'll get back to this later because it
is interesting um to look at this this
plot and this result in light of later
R1 results. Um they show essentially uh
the two fine-tuning based methods uh RF
and online RFT. This is basically a a
fairly weak baseline I would say. um
where what you're doing is you're only
looking at examples that sort of get the
right answer. They're doing math in this
case. So you only get examples where you
get the right answer and you fine-tune
on your own outputs that got the right
answer. Right? Reinforcing uh correct
answers with fine-tuning. Um GRPO with
outcome level rewards where you only get
a correct or not answer is the yellow.
The blue one is process level rewards
where it's kind of you got a system that
looks at each step of your reasoning and
sort of gives you a grade for that. And
they're arguing, you know, maybe process
rewards are better. We'll talk a little
bit more about that later. But in in
either case, you see that gpo works and
it works um pretty well.
Okay, any questions about the basic gpo
piece before we move on to kind of
details about gpo and thinking kind of
deeply about what's actually happening
in the algorithm?
Good. Okay. So now let's think about uh
the difference between uh gpo and po and
and what we've done and what's
different. Okay. So really there's, you
know, as I was saying, only one
difference, although it's a really
important difference. It's replacing the
the advantage estimator with this thing,
right? The the mean uh or the zcore,
let's say, of the rewards. Um, and so
now I'm going to kind of go back to uh
the policy gradient theorem or the
policy gradient result, and I'm going to
think through this result with you,
right? So when we uh when we take a
policy gradient update, right, what can
we do? So I'll just go back a couple
slides, right? Um
on this slide, we've got right here at
the very top policy gradients. This is
the most basic RL algorithm that you can
do, right? You take gradients where you
multiply the log probability gradients
with the reward. Right? This is
something that I'm always allowed to do.
This is a mathematical equivalence.
Right? Now, one other thing I can do is
called baselining. I can take this
reward Z and I can subtract any constant
uh or any in fact any random variable
that doesn't depend on uh Z itself. Um
and this would still be a valid uh
policy gradient. Right? So so this
baselining thing is really important
because what you're going to try to do
is you're going to try to subtract
constants that give you lower variances
on this expectation. Right? So that's
called baselining. Um and if we go here,
you know, that's kind of um a classic
result that you can look up in Senarto.
They say, okay, look, we've got the
policy gradient. You can subtract out
any baseline B of S because B of S, you
know, when we sum it up across the
policy is going to be zero, right? Um so
this is fine, right? We can always
baseline, but let's look at this A of A
of I. Is this a baseline? Well, um,
we're subtracting the mean and that's
kind of a baseline because all the other
rewards are not dependent on RO of I. So
maybe that's okay. I mean, technically
this notation includes RO of II, but if
I remove that, that's a valid baseline.
But one thing that's really weird is I'm
dividing by the standard deviation here,
right? That that's not something that
really seems allowed according to this
derivation in Senardau.
Um, and that turns out to be a problem.
uh some folks uh that have gone and you
know reanalyzed gpo and its behaviors
basically argue that gpo has two things
that at least mathematically are a
little bit off. Um and the first thing
is this division by standard deviation
right as I was kind of talking you
through just now this breaks that sort
of you know contract that a baseline
just needs to be subtracting a zero mean
uh variable uh that's you know
independent of of my draw. Um, and the
other thing that GRPO does, uh, which I
did it kind of, sorry, I glossed over
when I previously presented it, is that
it's actually dividing, um, kind of the
rewards by the length of the output. Um,
and that's going to have that's also a
little bit weird according to the policy
gradient theorem. This is not something
that would naturally show up. Um, and so
these authors who did like this this
pretty interesting study of uh GRPO
algorithms kind of argue that maybe we
should just get rid of these two things.
And if you do, then you'll actually have
much shorter output length and higher
reward without having much longer
responses.
Um, and so let's talk about these
results uh, you know, uh, carefully for
each one of these two fixes. Um and
hopefully by talking through these you
will gain an intuition about how the RL
algorithm works. Right? So first I want
to talk about uh the standard deviation.
Um this one's maybe somewhat obvious
what it's doing. Um okay let me let me
go back because I think it's easier to
talk about when I'm highlighting the
equation here. Um so I'm dividing the
advantage by the standard deviation. So
what does that mean? When the standard
deviation is small, right, the reward is
going to be amplified. it's going to be
more important for me to optimize that
group when the standard deviations are
small, right? And when is the standard
deviation small? Well, it's when the
problem is too easy or it's too hard,
right? Because that's when the rewards
are either all zero or they're all ones.
And so there's a bias in the standard
deviation term that upweights problems
that are too easy or too hard. Um the
authors argue this slows convergence.
Maybe true. At the very least, it
certainly breaks the validity of the
policy gradient. The second thing which
is subtle but also interesting is the
length normalization.
Now let's kind of look at what's
happening here. So we have this length
normalization before the gpo reward. Now
what does that do? If my model got a
question wrong, right? Then the best
thing to do is I'm receiving negative
reward in here. So the best thing to do
is to make the response really really
long. And if I get the answer right, the
best thing to do is to make the answer
short so I can sort of maximize my
positive reward. Right? So what this
does is it actually produces uh a model
that kind of BS as aggressively as
possible. If the model thinks it can't
get the answer right, it just produces
the longest possible response, which is
a very very bad incentive for you to
give the model. Um and so if you fix
this, uh what happens is, you know, on
various sort of toy tasks like GSMAK and
so on, you you can get um a reward
that's just as good. The red one is sort
of the modified version, but the output
length doesn't keep growing and growing
and growing. It sort of like stabilizes
at a certain point, right? Um and so
there is actually some interesting
observation that like maybe some of the
really long coots that people are seeing
in uh things like gRPO are a result of
these like actual implementation details
and choices rather than inherently long
coots being a necessary part of the
performance of these models. And I think
that's like a very interesting although
not fully proven out uh class of
hypothesis.
Cool. Okay. So that's the GRPO
algorithm. Hopefully now you're all
familiar with it and I think you now
have the background to go through uh all
three of these papers now. Uh deep sea
car 1, Kimmy 1.5 and uh Quent 3. Um any
questions?
Yes. So a question about why like
operating is bad just to confirm like my
understanding. I guess it's bad because
like in those in either the very easy or
the very hard cases we don't want to
actually like aggressively update the
model. Yeah. I think this gets into sort
of um uh wishy-washy folk theorem
territory, but actually some of these
papers will talk about this folk theory
and so I'll mention it which is what you
really want the RL algorithm to do is to
get problems that it can like do
somewhat well on like it can get some
reward on but is not so easy that it can
like already solve them right so there's
like kind of a curriculum effect where
you want to feed the models the right
you know level of difficulty and if
you're maximizing the that standard
deviation that's kind of the wrong
direction Right? You're really maxing
out the stuff at the extremes that you
either already all know or are just way
too hard for you to solve. Um,
cool. Okay. So, we're going to talk
about uh all three of these papers
today. R1, uh, Kimmy K1.5, and Quen 3.
Um, R1 and K1.5, I think, are pretty
interesting because they came out at
roughly the same time. Um, sadly, R1 was
the only one to to get like a gigantic
social uh, what's it called? Uh,
reception. Um but both of these actually
um show how to do RL based reasoning on
like math and other things with LLMs,
right? And they because they're
contemporaneous um you can kind of see
almost two parallel ways to tackle the
same problem like which things are
similar, which things are different and
so on which is great. Um Quinn 3 is the
newest of the releases. Um and they do
some fairly interesting variations of
ideas in R1. Um, and also they have some
new kind of tricks that that R1 doesn't
have, which I think are pretty
interesting things to look at,
especially if you're interested in
things like inference efficiency, uh, of
reasoning models.
So, uh, I'll start with R1. Um, I think
R1 is, you know, kind of amazing in the
sense that it's a it's a, you know,
archive paper that launched a whole
social phenomenon. Never let your
advisers tell you that, you know, your
archive papers will never matter. you
know, this one uh lost like what almost
half a billion dollars of of Nvidia
valuation. You two can one day maybe
cause that kind of a wave. Um R1, I
think, is quite remarkable because you
know it in many ways replicates all of
the qualitative properties of the 01
recipe in a way that is extremely
simple. Um so you know the the key
properties that I want to talk through
and and you know make sure you all
understand. Um the first thing right is
that you know it hits the performance
targets that open AIO1 set. Everyone was
really excited about reasoning model. So
this is very exciting. The second thing
is that you know it opens up a RL recipe
that is not only just like a replicable
one but I think more importantly one
that is extremely simple right it
doesn't have any search it doesn't have
any process reward models. I think lots
of people at the time thought maybe we
need all these complicated pieces to get
reasoning models. R1 really shows you
don't need any of that, right? And then
finally, um there's lots of interesting
insights about the interaction between
supervised fine-tuning um and RL that I
think um continue to be really
important. Okay, so uh the starting
point of R1 is they build on deepseek
math. Um, and actually some of the
equations I showed you of GRPO are from
Deepseek math where they originally
proposed GRPO as an alternative simpler
or system more systems efficient variant
of PO, right? To them actually the most
important piece was they wanted to get
rid of the value model just because it's
really annoying to have around. Um, but
one thing that's really interesting is
is you know they actually go for this
yellow line the outcome supervision
which is not actually the best
performing model um in deepseek math.
talk about that again at the very end of
this this section here. So I'll walk
through all the different pieces of R1.
Um so I'll start with R10 uh which I
think of as the controlled setting,
right? So R10 um is a very pure form of
RL learning. um it basically takes uh
essentially the model that is
pre-trained plus mid-trained um before
doing any RLHF or instruction tuning and
then throws it into the uh math RL loop
and then they try to find out how well
does that do right so the details here
um how do they do the reinforcement
learning well they have a bunch of uh
sort of mathish tasks the data is not
public um they take deepseeek v3 as
their kind of base model um and then
their rewards there's two forms of
rewards that they use. One of them is an
accuracy reward. So like did it get the
math question correct? Right? It's a
correct or not reward. It's binary. Uh
they have a format reward that basically
forces the model to put its coot within
like thinking tags like thinking start
thinking end of thinking tags, right?
And that's important if you want your
model to have these like long coots uh
being used. Now, um the format reward
feels like something that doesn't
matter, but from many papers and from
having talked to many people, apparently
it is a pretty critical part of actually
getting this whole like reasoning RL
thing to work. Um once you do this
right, all they're doing is is doing RL
on top of the base model. Nothing very
fancy, but the results are are pretty
striking. they get performance that is
getting pretty close to open AIO1 by
just doing some RL um on top of of the
model that they already had, right? Um
without any like, you know, coot
fine-tuning or anything like this. Um
and there's kind of two things uh that
they note in their paper as being really
interesting about R10. Um and I want to
talk about this because I think it's
important to to carefully examine what
is happening in R10. So the first thing
they say is, "Oh, it's very cool that if
you just let the model do RL on this
this verifiable rewards, the length of
the coot just kind of increases like
pretty predictably." Um, and you know,
in commentary that I don't know if I
necessarily agree with, you know, in the
paper they're like, "Oh, it's learning
to solve harder and harder problems by
thinking harder and harder." It's like,
well, maybe. Um, they also, you know,
point out it's kind of cool that, you
know, they learn, you know, phenomena
like backtracking. They call this the
aha moment. I think much has been made
uh about this in sort of public
discourse that wow it's cool that RL
training can give models these kind of
emergent insights. Um I'll kind of refer
you back to the the doctor gpo paper the
one that was talking about the
corrections to GRPO. Um and I think they
have honestly pretty good and
interesting arguments that both of these
are not particularly interesting
phenomena. Like first of all they argue
that like the length just goes up
because of the biased objective not
because you know it's an inherently
interesting object. Um and second they
they argue well if you just run
deepseeek v3 on a bunch of math
questions it'll also sometimes output
things like aha I can do this or that
which is maybe not like a deeply new
phenomenon that arises from RL. Um you
know both of these seem like given more
recent evidence kind of credible uh
things that like maybe there's nothing
like emergent and special about R10 but
it is actually working very well right
that is a good math model.
So R10 you can think of as kind of a
research setting, right? They're taking
a controlled model, they're doing
something very controlled on top of it,
which is math RL, and they get a good
model out, right? But if you're trying
to build a really strong model that
you're going to ship to the world, um
this is not what you're going to do,
right? You're going to like basically do
everything that you can to get the best
model that you can, right? So what would
you do uh in that sort of more
unrestricted setting? Well, um you're
going to maybe insert some supervised
fine-tuning. you're going to take, you
know, coots from, you know, some
undisclosed source and you're going to
fine-tune your deepseeek model on that
before you do your RL. And after you do
that, right, you don't want your model
to be kind of like this math savant that
can't do anything else. So, you're going
to, you know, apply your usual
post-training pipeline on top of that to
make sure that it can do all the other
tasks that, you know, people normally
want to use these models for, right? So,
this is kind of the the the pipeline
differences. Um, and so the key
differences both within the pipeline and
uh within the RL is they do SFT
initialization to try to get the model
to to know how to do long coots without
starting with RL. They add a language
language consistency reward in order to
make sure that the chains of thought
remain in a single language and then
they do you know a secondary RLHF stage
um kind of at the end. So I think this
makes a lot of sense, right? Every time
you want to do something advanced like
reinforcement learning, um you're
probably going to start by doing a
little bit of supervised fine-tuning. Um
and so even in sort of reasoning models
or long coot models like deepcar1, this
is the case, right? You start with uh
long coot supervised fine-tuning data
and then you're going to, you know, do
RL. Um I will point out that the uh
description of where they get this data
and what this data is remains very very
vague. like they don't tell us like what
was the coot data derived from um how
did they filter it I don't really have
any idea based on reading the R1 paper
um the claimed benefit of this is that
if you coot the model on sorry if you
sft the model on long let's say English
coots then this gives you an
interpretability benefit right as you do
RL you're not going to get like weird
gibberish it's going to kind of keep the
model closer to these like more
interpretable coots that you started out
with um So and and that would be kind of
good for users, right? Like as you're,
you know, using a math model, it would
be nice to see its reasoning uh as it
goes. Um and an additional thing, right?
So so when they do SFT initialization,
they use a ton of data. But one really
interesting thing is that for a lot of
models, even a tiny amount of uh SFT on
these kinds of like long coot data can
be good. Um, one thing that some of my
students in collaboration with Percy,
uh, we did was, um, basically take a
bunch of long coots from Gemini 2.0
flash thinking and, you know, fine-tune
Quen 2.5. And maybe surprisingly, you
know, with just a thousand examples, you
know, you get really, really high, you
know, uh, math benchmark accuracy, um,
with just a little bit of long coot
fine-tuning. So I think both of these
are really pointing to the fact that the
base model already has a lot of kind of
like thinking capabilities that you're
just like kind of priming and extracting
um from the model. Um and after that of
course you're going to do um RL, right?
So after you've gotten the the model set
up with SFT, you know, as with kind of
the instruction tuning and RHF pipeline,
so you start with SFT and then you do RL
to to basically get the model to to
actually optimize the rewards you're
looking for. Um, the RL part is
basically the same as R10. Not not huge
differences, but with a a minor
difference that you're going to add a
language consistency loss. And they have
I think I think this note is is pretty
interesting. This is a minor note, but
I'll describe it anyway where they
basically say um, you know, they add
this like language consistency reward
because, you know, during the training
process, if they just let the model RL,
they find that actually the coot will
will language mix like it will switch
between languages. Um, and if many of
you have kind of seen people playing
with um, reasoning models, um, I've seen
people on the internet post things like,
oh, it's kind of weird that like Grock 3
like suddenly switches to Chinese and
the coot. And this is kind of consistent
with those kinds of things that if you
aggressively RL a model, like actually,
you know, there's natural tendencies for
models to language mix um, rather than
staying in a single language. So it
actually requires an additional reward
to keep it in the single language.
Um and then finally after you've done RL
on like math and other verifiable
domains you basically layer on the usual
post training. So you do uh instruction
tuning and then you do sort of the the
pair wise preference tuning um
afterwards right so uh they do an SFT
spe where they combine both reasoning
data um on non-verifiable tasks like
write a proof of something um these are
not verifiable and then so they use
their own model as a judge for whether
or not they got the answer correct. um
they have non-reasoning data like sort
of you know write a nice essay um and
they use the same SFT data set as what
they used for uh Deepseek V3 and then
finally for RLHF they actually still use
GRPO for RLHF which is kind of cool they
use the same RL algorithm for everything
um and then they um basically just
follow the V3 RLHF pipeline like there's
not really anything different for this
post-training part right um how well
does it work um works very very well I
think Many of you probably experienced
this as well, right? Like R1 was in many
ways a shock because it matched the O1
performance, you know, really kind of
across the board on a very simple
recipe, right? Like as I describe this,
I don't think any of you found any of it
particularly surprising. Um, but the the
uh outcomes kind of speak for
themselves. You know, you've got sort of
on the English tasks basically, you
know, tied or matching uh 01 on across
the board. really slightly worse on code
models but very very close really across
all these different um tasks. The final
thing that uh the R1 paper showed is
that you can take these big big models
and you can distill them into other
models. So you can take your big deepsee
R1 and you can take those chains of
thought like in their case they take
almost a million chains of thought and
then they fine-tune Quen with those
chains of thought and they actually get
big boosts in sort of math performance
relative to the base model which is only
getting something like 50% uh
performance on on Amy for for the 32B
model. So they get 25 plus% boost on
this task which is which is pretty
surprising.
Cool. And then uh finally um there's two
I think interesting and good
observations from R1 and I think
scientifically maybe this was the the
biggest contribution of R1 in a way. So
I think R1 maybe had three contributions
scientifically, right? One of it was it
showed that outcome based rewards with
GRPO works, right? It's like the
positive proof and then R1 also had two
other kind of like negative results kind
of uh contributions and they are sort of
contained in the very last part of the
R1 report and they basically say okay
like we tried two things uh like pretty
extensively. We tried PRM and we also
tried MCTS. Um, and neither of those
really helped us at all on like
replicating something like 01, right?
And so to to get into a little bit of
detail, right, PRM are basically uh
process reward models. Those are kind of
like uh systems that can give you
intermediate rewards on a proof, right?
So when your model is giving a chain of
thought, a PRM would be able to say,
"Oh, you went wrong at this step in the
middle, right?" And obviously that is
much richer and very powerful form of
feedback. an RL algorithm can make
really really good use of a PRM. But
unfortunately, it's also very difficult
to get a PRM in the first place. And so,
you know, R1 um and the Deepseek math
people like they had gone down this road
of doing uh PRM for a while and they
kind of concluded this doesn't work
quite as well as outcome based rewards.
And thus far, I think outcomebased
rewards remain the way that in which you
would build these models. The second
thing that I think hasn't uh really
panned out is searchbased methods. I
think lots of people were interested in
in search based approaches to reasoning.
Thus far at least it hasn't really
panned out in the same way that RL and
outcome based rewards um has that that
remains I think kind of the strongest uh
kind of baseline and system um in this
this universe. Okay. So any questions
about um R1 like kind of their setup or
any of the other findings? Yes.
PRM GRPO and PRM are kind of two
different
Oh yes. Oh yeah. Yeah. That's right.
Yes. Okay. Good. Sorry. I said I was
going to mention it, but I didn't. So
that is totally on me. That's right.
Exactly. Um and so I think especially
for the the PRM, I think it's really
interesting and telling that in DeepSeek
math, you know, they were very much
convinced by sort of the strength of the
PRM, which is this blue line with PS.
And then in R1, they, you know,
concluded that actually this approach
that had worked for Deepseek math was
not really going to work for R1. and
they had gone with outcome based uh
rewards. Yeah, thank you for reminding
me. Um I was about to to forget my
promise there. Uh yes
consistency is that for I guess ease of
understanding or is do they actually
know how it protects performance? Yeah.
So so um yeah in this note here they
basically say um if you ablate away the
the language uh consistency experiment
it results in degradation of the model's
performance. Um, but they're gonna put
it in anyway because they prefer to have
coots that are more readable to humans.
Um, it's an interesting trade-off. Um,
there have been lots of research about
whether coots are faithful and they're
not truly faithful. We kind of know
that. Um, but maybe it's better to have
a slightly more faithful coot than to
have the extra, I don't know, half
percentage point performance on Amy.
Uh, yes.
translated out the end, but if you if
what you care about is that someone can
read it, like
so uh I mean I'm sure they can do like
translations or or other kinds of like
post-processing to make the coots
better. And in some ways you might think
of uh OpenAI and and these other vendors
efforts to like summarize the coots as
being very similar, right? Like because
the raw coots are probably much messier
and then they probably like sort of
rationalize it away. Um that is one way
and I think that is an effective way to
to get interpretability. Um but I do
think if you're interested in somehow if
you aesthetically believe that the raw
coot is very important for monitoring
and and you know closer interpretability
then I do think you do want something
like this. Right.
Cool. Okay. Um so now we're going to
move on to uh Kimmy K1.5. Um and why do
we study this one? Um, if you look at
the timestamps for when R1 and K1.5 were
released, it's it's kind of, you know,
contemporaneous. Um, and it achieves
very similar results. It does so using
outcome based rewards in RL. It doesn't
use the same algorithm. It has kind of
different details and different
interesting insights. And so we can
learn about kind of what's the same,
what's different, and maybe, you know,
what parts are maybe important in this
process. Um so to you know just show you
the headline result before we start just
to to get you to to believe that this is
a paper that's you know worth being
discussed here right um Kim K 1.5 is the
the dark blue bars here um you can see
openai's 01 as the the next highest bar
so they're you know beating or matching
01 across the board on a bunch of
important tasks and they do basically uh
things similar to R1. So they do SFT,
they do RL, they have a different RL
algorithm, but they do RL. Um they also
describe their data set construction in
a little bit more detail. And this
actually gets used in in Quinn 3 later,
so it's worth uh discussing. So let me
talk through data. Um as Percy said
earlier, maybe data is the most
important thing in your whole pipeline.
And so we should always pay attention
when people talk about their kind of
data curation, you know, strategies in
like a large scale training paper. Um
and so Kimmy 1.5 does several things to
try to curate their data set. So what
they first do is they try to balance
across different domains like they have
an automated I'm guessing um LM based
tagging system to categorize um
basically math questions by different
domains and disciplines and then they
kind of balance across these to try to
get diversity across different domains.
um they exclude even though these are
verifiable multiple choice and true
false questions because they argue that
these are too easy to to hack or to
randomly guess. So they're only looking
for verifiable answers that are kind of
short and can be evaluated by things
like regex um or or LM. Um and this is
maybe the most interesting piece of the
curation here. Um what they do is they
take the model uh that doesn't do any
reasoning uh you know their SFT model um
and they have this model generate uh 10
answers um and the pass rate is used um
in order to determine whether to include
that example uh or not. Um and I I think
the the exact thing they use for their
latest selection strategy is they only
select examples that fail best of eight.
So if it if if they can get any one out
of a correct, then it's excluded for
being too easy. Um SFT data similar to
to R1, very little description. Who
knows where they got that from? Um they
just say they do some prompt
engineering. So clearly it was distilled
from something else. Uh but we don't
really know what they distilled off of.
Um so I'll talk about the RL algorithm.
The Kimmy one's kind of interesting. Um
it's a different variation. It's
actually maybe closer to DPO in a way.
um but you end up with a you know
algorithm that I think you'll very much
recognize. So you can kind of think of
this in a very interesting way as
convergent evolution of of RL
algorithms. So you start once again at
the very top. This is our you know
classic goal. You know we're sampling
from a data set. We're sampling from our
policy. We want to maximize rewards. We
don't want to be too far from our base
policy. So this is the KL regularizer.
Um you know if you remember our DPO
derivation you make a nonparametric
assumption you say pi star is the
optimal policy is an arbitrary function
that means that the reward can be
written as you know the log normalizer
plus the ratio of policies right this is
the exact same thing we did in dpo and
now you know in dpo what we did was we
took these rewards and we plugged them
into the kind of the Bradley Terry
preference function we don't have this
here right we we're not doing pair wise
preferences so we don't actually take
that step. Instead, we write down this
equation and we say we know that for the
optimal policy, we're going to have
equality here. And so, all we're going
to do is we're going to make this a
difference and we're going to add a
squared loss on top, right? We're going
to try to drive the left and the right
sides close by just adding a squared
loss. It's a reasonable thing to do.
People have done things like this
before. Um, and this gives us our loss.
It's basically trying to drive uh the
right side and the left side of
something that should be an equality for
the optimal policy close together. And
well, this is a little bit of an exotic
looking object or maybe exotic looking
initially, but if you take the gradient,
it just looks a lot like gRPO. Uh you
know, you've got your gradients of your
policy, right? This is your policy
gradient stuff. Um and you've got a
baseline reward. And actually, what's
the baseline reward? I'm just going to
average um the R within my batch, right?
Um so here this is actually doing
something different. This is the
normalizing constant um I think over the
batch. Um but you know we're doing
essentially similar kinds of baselining
as GRPO and we've got a slightly
different like square of the the log
loss regularization to keep my policy
close rather than doing clipping. Right?
So zooming out, what what's happening
here? Very similar to GRPO in that this
first part is a baseline loss, but
there's no standard deviation thing
happening. This second part is analogous
to the clipping that happens in GRPO,
but instead of doing clipping, we're
explicitly regularizing the policy,
right? So we've got the same ingredients
just in slightly different form. Um, and
so hopefully you can see, you know, that
as long as you kind of have this policy
gradient thing and the right baselining
and something that looks like
regularization, you can get a working RL
algorithm.
The other thing that the Kimmy folks do,
and in some ways I think this is um more
forward-looking or or they got this more
right than the R1 folks, which is that
they realize that, you know, if you're
shipping a reasoning model, what you
really care about is inference cost. And
if you care about inference cost, you
had better try to control the length of
your uh coots, right? If you have really
long thinking chains, that's going to
cost you a ton of money or cost your
users a ton of money. And so instead of
celebrating the really long coots, the
Kimmy folks say, uh, we want to really
compress the coots as much as possible
while keeping performance high. Um, and
so they have this length reward thing
here. Um, where what they're doing is
for kind of each batch, um, they're
looking at the maximum and the minimum
lengths. And what you have is lambda
where lambda is roughly like, you know,
where are you in the range of lengths
within your batch, right? So if you're
at plus.5
um you know you're really short and
negative.5 uh you are really long right
um and the reward is basically going to
be lambda whenever you get the answer to
be correct. So if your answer is correct
you're going to incentivize yourself to
be really short at the very shortest end
of this range. Whereas if your answers
are incorrect, you're in this bottom
part of this length reward, which means
that you're incentivizing the uh coot
lengths to be roughly shorter than the
center of the range of the rollouts.
This is a somewhat funky loss to me to
be honest, but you can kind of
understand the dynamics of this loss,
which is you're incentivizing um sort of
correct answers to be as short as
possible and incorrect answers are
incentivized to be kind of averageish,
right? Um, and so you don't have as
strong of an optimization pressure to to
push down incorrect answers uh to be
short. And one final note on this length
stuff is the Kimmy folks realize that if
you add this re uh reward early on in
training, it stalls RL because, you
know, it basically forces the model to
say I'm in a local minimum. I don't get
any of my answers correct. The best I
can do is to have my coots really short
and then you just can't get out of that
sort of local minimum. And so they
actually only turn this on later on uh
during training. So they kind of
initially do a bit of unconstrained RL
and then they add this length reward in
um afterwards.
Um and they also have additional cool
details. Who knows how much of this
stuff is necessary or important, but
they actually have a whole curriculum
set up. They basically have assigned
difficulty labels. So the data set uh
just kind of like top down like they
just manually uh or via LMS kind of
annotate uh the difficulty labels. Um,
and then they go from easy to hard in
that order. And then they also as
they're uh going on sample problems
proportional to one minus success rate.
So if you're 100% succeeding, you just
never sample that question uh ever
again. Um, and for the rewards, they
basically um for code they take problems
with ground truth solutions and they
generate a bunch of test cases. Um and
for math they uh basically use actually
a reward model um where that's used to
compare like ground truth human written
answers to the LM output. So instead of
using something like a reg x or using um
simply which is what other people have
done the Kimmy folks actually use a
model to do equivalence checking. It's
kind of surprising to do this in a
verifiable reward case but you know they
don't seem to have a problem. the reward
models are very very accurate um because
it's really all it's doing is advanced
string matching.
Um one of the things uh that's really
cool about the Kimmy paper um is that
they also talk about kind of the infra
issues that arise uh doing RL I think I
don't think I've seen any of the other
um RL reasoning papers actually talk
about systems almost at all. So, it's
nice to see that they're kind of talking
about this, what their structure is,
what their their uh layout of this is.
Um, you'll have to deal with this in A5,
like I think a very mini version of this
as you implement um things like rollouts
in RL. But one thing I'll note, right,
is you know, why is RL so hard to make
efficient? And in many ways, it's harder
than normal pre-training to to have your
GPUs like fully utilized during RL. Um,
and the reason I think is because
there's rollouts involved, right? So you
have to be generating sequences and
whenever you're generating sequences not
only are you kind of you know slow in
the sense of inference is slow but also
you have this other issue which is that
um you have to switch from RL to
inference and back and you have to be
passing sort of data back to the RL
worker and the RL worker has to pass
model weights to the inference server
and vice versa. So you've got all this
sort of message passing um that can
happen. And finally um this is unique to
long coot models, but if you have really
long coots, batches can become very very
uneven. So you have to to handle that
cleverly um somehow. And so um the Kimmy
folks do this, you know, relatively nice
but fairly standard thing of having
different workers that are assigned to
do the RL updates, having different
workers assigned to do inference. Um and
they have basically kind of message
passing to be able to pass the weights
to the inference worker and the
inference worker can basically make data
sets for the RL worker. Um and you know
they have almost the same kinds of
setups that you will have. Um they use
VLM for inference. Um and they also do
very you know advanced stuff where they
have to have VLM with dummy weights and
they have to kill it because of the the
complexities of doing kind of this
passing of weights from one worker um to
another.
Um, finally, I think one thing that I
think is is interesting um that the
Kimmy people show in in their results is
they they have like per iteration
results where they show like as RL
proceeds like how does you know
performance scale and they show really
nice scaling which is in the blue and
they also show the growth of the length
of the responses and much like in Dr.
GRPO because I don't think their their
RL algorithm is inherently sort of
balanced or sorry biased towards longer
responses. Most of the um uh sort of
responses actually sort of plateau out
at a sort of target length like we saw
with Dr. GRPO rather than grow
unboundedly like we did with uh the
vanilla grpo.
Cool. Um any questions on on Kimmy
before we finally conclude with uh Quen
3?
So back to like the RL setup in detail
of Kimmy. Um yeah I was wondering like
so I guess like when you're like doing
the robots during like training like the
robots the inference is done by the app
right? Yes. And as I update the
parameter that will mean that like you
know as they update the model they also
need to sync that to the um to the VM
inference through worker and that's what
this is for. Yeah. So I think you know
the most annoying part at least with
current um libraries of this process is
essentially that step of taking RL
weights and putting it into VL1. Uh
there is an experimental API that is
supposed to allow you to use uh NCCL
collective calls to uh shove a set of
weights into VLM. Um but at least we
were thinking about having you use that
for the assignment actually. Uh but it
has too many undocumented parameters for
it to be a little bit mature. Um and so
maybe next year's iteration this will
actually be you know fairly mature
technology. But right now I think a lot
of people do things like start a VLM
with dummy weights. The weights then get
loaded somehow into memory with sort of
hacks on top of VL1.
And each iteration they often tear down
VLM to make sure they can free the GPU
memory fully.
Yeah, there there's a lot of like I
think you know the RL for LMS I think is
is fairly new still. So I think the
infrastructural support remains a little
bit immature but I think in maybe a year
things will actually just get much
nicer. Yeah, question back there. You
have a lot of like accuracy rewards and
like rewards rewards. How are you
supposed to combine them together? Yeah.
Um so you how do you combine the
different rewards? Um I think this is
one of the RL not quite black magic but
really you know like RL magic things of
like you just tune weights like in all
cases um all the rewards are just added
together but with weights and how are
the weights determined empirically in
order to maximize the downstream
performance right um especially for
things like format rewards you can
almost think of them as like shaping or
like surrogate rewards like you don't
necessarily really care about the
formatting reward it's more of a means
to an end to get a good long coot within
the tags that will get you the answer
Cool.
Okay, so the final uh one I want to talk
about is Quen 3. And thankfully uh Quen
3 released their report before the end
of the class, so I get to include it.
Um, and you know, I think this is the
most recent and modern of the um, RL uh,
for reasoning kind of models to have
come out. And so we can kind of see how
they've like built upon the previous
works like where they've changed things.
Um, and they have actually pretty
interesting scaling and data results
that are are are new and unique.
Um, so the overall picture is very
similar to what um, R1 and Kimmy have
done, right? So Quinn basically take
their base models. um they'll do a long
coot sft stage. So that's this first
stage over here. They'll do their
reasoning RL. Um they'll do something
funky that I'll I'll talk about later
called thinking mode fusion. Um and then
they'll do um RLHF RL and then that's
the model that they ship. Of course they
they then distill that in various ways,
but we can kind of forget about that um
for the moment, right? Um so we've
already seen this in R1, right? RLHF
comes after reasoning um and then
distillation comes yet after uh that.
And we already know a lot of the
playbook. So I can actually go through
this fairly fast. Um much like Kimmy,
they basically curate the data by
filtering for difficulty using best of
end. So if your base model that hasn't
been RL can already answer it, if you
sample like end times, then you can just
get rid of it, right? Um you they also
do some like decontamination things
where they remove things that are too
similar to validation data. Um and then
they also manually filter um essentially
their SFT set. So like for their initial
SFT data uh for long coots they like
manually filter it for whether they are
guessing or whether they actually got it
right. Um the one thing that empirically
I think is really interesting about the
Quen 3 uh RL results is that they are
actually doing this RL only on 3,995
examples um you know which is a very
small number of examples to be doing
this on um and they get pretty good
gains out of the RL process. And so you
can view this as you know um RL on
verified rewards as being very
efficient. You could also think of this
as being um analogous to many sample
efficiency results in the past like
people have shown that you can uh
instruction tune a model with very few
samples or that you can distill a long
coot with very few samples but that
doesn't necessarily mean that it doesn't
continue to scale right we don't really
know why. What this does show is that
even with very few examples, you can
sometimes do RL which is surprising and
cool. Um so what is the two new uh sort
of quen specific stuff that they do? um
the the thing that they do is uh this
thing called thinking mode fusion which
I think is kind of interesting and where
I think the the field or the the various
trends are going is in controlling
inference right so what they do is they
want to have both a thinking model and a
non-thinking model in the same you know
single set of parameters so what do they
do well you know after they train a
model with RL um they have a model that
can do thinking and now they're going to
fine-tune it again to do one of two
things they're going to fine-tune the
model with some data that has a think
tag and then it's going to do the normal
coot thing and you can get this data
from yourself right like the original
thinking model can generate this um or
you can have a no think tag in which
case it should immediately kind of emit
an answer um and you know in this case
they they're going to have to sort of
supervise fine-tune the model to know
what no think means and to immediately
try to emit um the answer um and one
kind of interesting um side effect of
this is that they found that if they do
this training where they train the model
to to have a think and a no think tag.
Then what they can do is they can sort
of if the model continues to think and
you want to terminate the thinking
process, you can kind of actually like
terminate the thinking process, add a
special string that's like considering
the limited time of the user, I have to
give a solution by thinking directly now
and then end think tag and then it sort
of accurately gives the answer. So this
gives them a control knob by which they
can sort of more precisely control a
maximum number of thinking tokens. Um
and this gives them pretty clean test
time scaling from a single model. And so
they can set like a maximum thinking
budget. Um and of course the sort of you
know very very maximum out to infinity
is just the the original thinking model
but they can kind of early terminate to
the left and they can get graceful
degradations uh in model performance.
That's you know not too bad at the very
sort of beginning. You can like have the
the thinking tokens and still get some
pretty good uh performance.
And so you know you can look at um Quen
3 also does a nice ablation where they
give you the performance at the
reasoning RL stage at the thinking mode
fusion stage and at the general RL
stage. Um and one thing that's very
interesting to me here is that if you
look at the first two sets of rows the
general task and the instruction
following ones um reasoning RL helps
thinking mode fusion helps and of course
RLHF continues to help here as well
right like kind of everything helps um
in this regime but if you look at kind
of math or stem performance you know in
the thinking case general RL hurts
performance and in the non-thinking case
it helps performance so there really is
seems to be at least somewhat of a
trade-off in, you know, do I optimize
for general purpose instruction
following up here or do I optimize for
like math encoding kind of down here,
right? Um, and so those are kind of
interesting sort of properties that are
emerging and it'll be cool to see sort
of uh more future models kind of
sidestep these uh tradeoffs um somehow.
Okay, cool. So to put that all together
um our our sort of initial motivation
was to say RL is very powerful. We kind
of figured out that we can do RL with
language models in the RLHF domain. But
you can't just like hill climb on noisy
pair wise preferences forever, right? Um
so one solution is to pick domains in
which you can't do reward hacking and
then just you know go for it, right? RL
and narrow domains is one good solution.
Um and GRPO is one very simple algorithm
and hopefully you all kind of have a
sense of like okay I can just do policy
gradients with some good baselines and
that will enable uh RL on all of these
kinds of verifiable reward domains. Um
and then finally um there's lots of
successful recipes in the wild and you
hopefully now you've seen you know
what's in common, what's different, what
what implementation tricks uh matter.
Cool. Thanks a lot. Um and I will see
you all next week.