at some point you have to believe
something we've reinvented Computing as
we know it what is the vision for what
you see coming next we asked ourselves
if it can do this how far can it go how
do we get from the robots that we have
now to the Future world that you see
Cleo everything that moves will be
robotic someday and it will be soon we
invested tens of billions of dollars
before it really happened no that's very
good you did some research but the big
breakthrough I would
say uh is when we that's Jensen Wong
and whether you know it or not his
decisions are shaping your future he's
the CEO of Nvidia the company that
skyrocketed over the past few years to
become one of the most valuable
companies in the world because they led
a fundamental shift in how computers
work unleashing this current explosion
of what's possible with technology
nvidia's done it again we found
ourselves being one of the most
important technology companies in the
world and potentially ever a huge amount
of the most futuristic Tech that you're
hearing about in Ai and Robotics and
gaming and self-driving cars and
Breakthrough Medical Research relies on
new chips and software designed by him
and his company during the dozens of
background interviews that I did to
prepare for this what struck me most was
how much Jensen Wong has already
influenced all of our Lives over the
last 30 years and how many said it's
just the beginning of something even
bigger we all need to know what he's
building and why and most importantly
what he's trying to build next welcome
to huge conversations
[Music]
thank you so much for doing so happy to
do it before we dive in I wanted to tell
you how this interview is going to be a
little bit different than other
interviews I've seen you do recently
okay I'm not going to ask you any
questions about you could ask company
finances thank you I'm not going to ask
you questions about your management
style or why you don't like one-on ones
I'm not going to ask you about
regulations or politics I think all of
those things are important but I think
that our audience can get them well
covered elsewhere okay what we do on
huge if true is we make optimistic
explainer videos and we've covered I'm
the worst person to be an explainer
video I think you might be the best and
I think that's what I'm really hoping
that we can do together is make a joint
explainer video about how can we
actually use technology to make the
future better yeah and we do it because
we believe that when people see those
better Futures they help build them so
the people that you're going to be
talking to are awesome they are
optimists who want to build those better
Futures but because we cover so many
different topics we've covered
supersonic planes and quantum computers
and particle colliders it means that
millions of people come into every
episode without any prior knowledge
whatsoever you might be talking to an
expert in their field who doesn't know
the difference between a CPU and a GPU
or a 12-year-old who might grow up one
day to be you but is just starting to
learn um for my part I've now been
preparing for this interview for several
months I've including doing background
conversations with many members of your
team but I'm not an engineer so my goal
is to help that audience see the future
that you see so I'm going to ask about
three areas the first is how did we get
here what were the key insights that led
to this big fundamental shift in
Computing that we're in now the second
is what's actually happening right now
how did those insights lead to the world
that we're now living in that seems like
so much is going on all at once and the
third is what is the vision for what you
see coming
next in order to talk about this big
moment we're in with
AI I think we need to go back to video
games in the
9s at the time I know game developers
wanted to create more realistic looking
Graphics but the hardware couldn't keep
up with all of that necessary math not
enough man Nvidia came up with a
solution that would change not just
games but Computing
itself could you take us back there and
explain what was happening and what were
the insights that led you and the Nvidia
team to create the first modern GPU so
in the early '90s when we first started
the company we observed that in a
software program inside it there are
just a few lines of code maybe 10% of
the code does 99% % of the processing
and that 99% of the processing could be
done in parallel however the other 90%
of the code has to be done sequentially
it turns out that the proper computer
the perfect computer is one that could
do sequential processing and parallel
processing not just one or the other
that was the big observation and we set
out to build a company to solve computer
problems that normal computers can't and
that's really the beginning of Nvidia
my favorite visual of why a CPU versus a
GPU really matters so much is a
15-year-old video on the Nvidia YouTube
channel where the Mythbusters they use a
little robot shooting paintballs one by
one to show solving problems one at a
time or sequential processing on a
CPU but then they roll out this huge
robot that shoots all of the paintballs
at once doing smaller problems all at
the same time or parallel processing on
a GPU 3 2
1 so Nvidia unlocks all of this new
power for video games why gaming first
the video games uh requires parallel
processing for uh processing 3D graphics
and we chose video games because one we
loved the application it's a simulation
of virtual worlds and who doesn't want
to go to Virtual Worlds and and we had
the good observation that video games
has potential to be the largest market
for for entertainment ever and it turned
out to be true and having it being a
large Market is important because the
technology is complicated and if we had
a large Market our R&D budget could be
large we could create new technology and
that flywheel between technology and
market and greater technology was was
really the flywheel that got Nvidia to
become one of the most important
technology companies in the world it was
all because of video games I've heard
you say that gpus were a time machine
yeah could you tell me more about what
you me by that a GPU is like a time
machine because it lets you see the
future sooner one of the most amazing
things anybody's ever said to me was a
uh quantum chemistry scientist he said
Jensen because of invidious work I can
do my life's work in my lifetime that's
time travel he was able to do something
that was beyond his lifetime within his
lifetime and and this because we make
applications run so much faster
and you get to see the future and so
when you're doing weather prediction for
example you're seeing the future when
you're doing a a simulation a virtual
City with virtual traffic and we're um
simulating our self-driving car through
that Virtual City we're doing time
travel so parallel processing takes off
in gaming and it's allowing us to create
worlds in computers that we never could
have before and and gaming is sort of
this this first
incredible cas Cas of parallel
processing unlocking a lot more power
and then as you said people begin to use
that power across many different
Industries the case of the of the
quantum chemistry
researcher when I've heard you tell that
story it's that he was running molecular
simulations in a way where it was much
faster to run in parallel on Nvidia gpus
even then than it was to run them on the
supercomputer with the CPU that he had
been using before yeah that's true so oh
my God it's revolutionizing all of these
other Industries as well MH it's
beginning to change how we see what's
possible with computers and my
understanding is that in the early 2000s
you see this and you realize that
actually doing that is a little bit
difficult because what that researcher
had to do is he had to sort of trick the
gpus into thinking that his problem was
a graphics problem that's exactly right
no that's very good well you did some
research so you create a way to make
that a lot easier that's right
specifically it's a platform called cuda
which lets programmers tell the GPU what
to do using programming languages that
they already know like C and that's a
big deal because it gives way more
people easier access to all of this
computing power could you explain what
the vision was that led you to create
Cuda partly uh researchers uh
discovering it partly internal uh
inspiration and um uh and partly solving
a problem and you know a lot of
interesting interesting IDE ideas come
out of that soup you know some of it is
is aspiration and inspiration some of it
is just desperation you know and and so
in in the case of Cudo is very much this
the same way and um probably the first
external ideas of using our gpus for
parallel processing emerged out of some
interesting work in medical imaging a
couple of researchers at Mass General
were using it uh to do uh CT
reconstruction they were using our
Graphics process for that reason and it
inspired us meanwhile the problem that
we're trying to solve inside our company
has to do with the fact that when you're
trying to create these virtual worlds
for video games you would like it to be
beautiful but also
Dynamic water should flow like water and
explosions should be like explosions so
there's particle physics you want to do
fluid dynamics you want to do and uh
that is much harder to do if your
pipeline is only able to do computer
graphics
and so we have a natural reason to want
to do it in in the the the market that
we were serving so researchers were also
um horsing around with using our gpus
for general purpose uh acceleration and
and so there there are multiple multiple
factors that were coming together in
that soup uh we just when the time came
and uh uh we decided to to uh do
something proper and create a Cuda as a
result of that fundamentally the reason
why why I was certain that Cuda was
going to be successful and we we uh put
the whole company behind it was because
fundamentally uh our GPU was going to be
the highest volume parallel processors
built in the world because the market of
video games was so large and so this
architecture has a good chance of
reaching many people it has seemed to me
like creating Cuda was this incredibly
optimistic huge if true thing to do
where you were saying if we create a way
for many more people to use much more
computing power they might create
incredible things and then of course it
came true they did in 2012 a group of
three researchers submits an entry to a
famous competition where the goal is to
create computer systems that could
recognize images and label them with
categories and their entry just crushes
the competition it gets way fewer
answers wrong it was incredible it blows
everyone away it's called alexnet and
it's a kind of AI called the neural
network my understanding is one reason
it was so good is that they used a huge
amount of data to train that system and
they did it on Nvidia gpus all of a
sudden gpus weren't just a way to make
computers faster and more efficient
they're becoming the engines of a whole
new way of computing we're moving from
instructing computers with step-by-step
directions to training computers to
learn by showing them a huge number of
examples this moment in 2012 really
kicked off this truly sizmic shift that
we're all seeing with AI right now could
you describe what that moment was like
from your perspective and what did you
see it would mean for all of our futures
when you create something new like Cuda
if you build it they might not come and
and that's that's always the the cynic
perspective however The Optimist
perspective would say but if you don't
build it they can't come and that's
usually how we look at the world you
know we we have to reason about
intuitively why this would be very
useful and in fact uh in 2012 ilas Suk
and Alis kvki and Jeff Hinton in the
University of Toronto the lab that they
were at they reached out to a gForce GTX
580 because they learned about Cuda and
that Cuda might be able to to be used as
a parallel processor for training
alexnet and uh so our inspiration that
GeForce could be the the vehicle to
bring out this parallel architecture
into the world and that researchers
would somehow find it someday was a good
was a good strategy it was a strategy
based on Hope um but it was also
reasoned hope the the thing that really
caught our attention was simultaneously
we were trying to solve the computer
vision problem inside the company and we
were trying to get Cuda to uh be a good
computer vision uh processor and we were
frustrated by by uh a whole bunch of
early developments internally with
respect to our our um computer vision
effort and getting Cuda to be able to do
it and all of a sudden we saw alexnet um
this new
algorithm that that is uh completely
different than computer vision
algorithms before it uh take a giant
leap in terms of capability for computer
vision and when we saw that it was
partly out of interest but partly
because we were struggling with
something ourselves and so we were we
were highly interested to want to see it
work and so when we when we looked at
alexnet we were inspired by that um but
the big breakthrough I would
say uh is when we when we saw alexnet we
asked ourselves you know
how far can alexnet go if it can do this
with computer vision how far can it go
and if it if it could go to the limits
of what we think it could go um the type
of problems it could solve what would it
mean for the computer industry and what
would it mean for the computer
architecture and we were we were um uh
we rightfully
reasoned that if machine learning if the
Deep learning architecture can scale uh
the vast majority of machine learning
problems could be represented with deep
neural networks and the type of problems
we could solve with machine learning is
so vast that it has the potential of
reshaping the computer industry
altogether and which prompted us to uh
re-engineer the entire Computing stack
which is where uh djx came from and this
little baby djx sitting here um uh all
of this came from from that observation
that we ought to reinvent the entire
Computing stack layer by layer by layer
you know computers after 65 years since
uh IBM system 360 introduced modern
general purpose Computing we've
reinvented Computing as we know it to
think about this as a whole story so
parallel processing reinvents modern
gaming and revolutionizes an entire
industry then that way of computing that
parallel processing begins to be used
across different Industries you invest
in that by building Cuda and then Cuda
and the
use of
gpus allows for a a step change in
neural networks and machine learning and
begins a sort of Revolution that we're
now seeing uh only increase in
importance
today all of a sudden computer vision is
solved all of a sudden speech
recognition is solved all of a sudden
language understanding is solved these
incredible problems associated with
intelligence one by one by one by
one where we had no solutions for in
past desperate desire to have solutions
for all of a sudden one after another
get solved you know every couple of
years it's incredible yeah so you're
seeing that in 2012 you're looking ahead
and and believing that that's the future
that you're going to be living in now
and you're making bets that get you
there really big bets that have very
high stakes and then my perception as a
lay person is that it takes a pretty
long time to get there you make these
best eight years eight uh 10 years so my
question is
if Alex that happened in 2012 and this
audience is probably seeing and hearing
so much more about Ai and Nvidia
specifically 10 years later MH why did
it take a decade and also because you
would Place those bets MH what did the
middle of that decade feel like for you
well that's a good question it probably
felt like today you know to me to me
there's always some problem and then
there's there's some reason to be to be
impatient there's always some reason to
be uh happy about where you are and and
there's always many reasons to carry on
and so so I I think as I was reflecting
a second ago that sounds like this
morning so but I would say that in all
things that we pursue first you have to
have core
beliefs you have to reason from from
your best principles um and ideally
you're reasoning from it from princip of
either physics or uh deep understanding
of of uh of the industry or deep
understanding of the science wherever
you're reasoning from um you reason from
first principles and at some point you
have to believe something and if those
principles don't change and the
assumptions don't change uh then you
there's no reason to change your core
beliefs and then along the way there's
always some uh evidence of of um you
know of success and and that you're
you're leading in the right direction
and sometimes you know you go a long
time without evidence of success and you
might have to course correct a little
but um the evidence comes and and if you
feel like you're going in the right
direction we just keep on going the
question of why did we stay so committed
for so long the answer is actually the
opposite there was no reason to not be
committed because we are we believed it
and and um I've believed in Nvidia for
30 plus years and and I'm still here
working every single day and uh there's
no fundamental reason for me to change
my belief system and um uh I
fundamentally believe that that the work
we're doing in revolutionizing Computing
is as true today even more true today
than it was before and and um uh and so
we'll we'll stick with it you know until
until otherwise um there's of
course very difficult times along the
way you know when you're investing in
something and nobody else believes in it
and cost a lot of money and uh you know
maybe investors or or others would
rather you just keep the profit or you
know whatever it is improve the share
price or whatever it is um but you have
to believe in your future you have to
invest in yourself and and um uh we
believ this so deeply uh that that we we
invested you know tens of billions of
dollars uh before before it really
happened and um uh yeah it it was it was
10 long years but it was it was it was
fun along the way how would you
summarize those core beliefs what is it
that you believe about the way
computers should work and what they can
do for us that keeps you not only coming
through that decade but also doing what
you're doing now making bets I'm sure
you're making for the next few decades
the first core believe uh was our first
discussion was about accelerated
Computing parallel Computing versus
versus general purpose Computing we
would add uh two of those processors
together and we would do accelerated
Computing and I continue to believe that
today the second was was the recognition
that these deep learning networks these
dnns that came to the public during 2012
these deep neural networks have the
ability to learn patterns and
relationships from a whole bunch of
different types of data and that it can
learn more and more uh nuanced features
if it could be larger and larger and
it's easier to make them larger and
larger make them deeper and deeper um or
wider and wider and so the scalability
of the architecture is is um uh
empirically true uh the uh the fact that
model size and the data size being
larger and larger can learn more
knowledge uh is also true uh empirically
true and so uh if that's the case uh you
could you know what what are the limits
there not unless there's a physical
limit or an architect ual limit or
mathematical limit and it was never
found and so we believe that you could
scale it then the question the only
other question is what can you learn
from data what can you learn from
experience data is basically digital
versions of human experience and so what
can you learn uh you obviously can learn
object recognition from images you can
learn speech from just listening to
sound you can learn uh even languages
and vocabulary and syntax and grammar
and all just by studying a whole bunch
of letters and words so we've now
demonstrated that AI or deep learning
has the ability to learn almost any
modality of
data and it can translate to any
modality of data and so what does that
mean you can go from text to text right
summarize a paragraph you can go from
text to text translate from language to
language you can go from text to images
that's image generation you can go from
images to text that's captioning you can
even go from
amino acid sequences to protein
structures in the future you'll go from
protein to words what does this protein
do or um give me an example of a protein
that has these properties you know uh
identifying a drug Target um and so you
could just see that all of these
problems are around the corner to be
solved uh you can go from words to video
why can't you go from words
to action tokens for a
robot you know from the computer's
perspective how is it any different and
so it it opened up this universe of
opportunities and universe of problems
that we can go solve and um that that
that gets us quite
excited it feels like we are on the cusp
of This truly enormous change when I
think about the next 10 years I unlike
the last 10 years I know we've gone
through a lot of change already but I
don't think I can predict anymore how I
will be using the technology that is
currently being developed that's exactly
right I think the last 10 the reason why
you feel that way is the last 10 years
was really about the science of AI the
next 10 years we're going to have plenty
of Science of AI but the next 10 years
is going to be the application science
of AI the fundamental science versus the
application science and so the the
applied research the application side of
AI now becomes how can I apply AI to
digital biology how can I apply AI to
climate technology how can I apply AI to
agriculture to fishery to robotics to
Transportation um optimizing Logistics
how can I apply AI to you know teaching
how do I apply AI to you know podcasting
right and so I'd love to choose a couple
of those to help people see how this
fundamental change in Computing that
we've been talking about is actually
going to change their experience of
their lives how they're actually going
to use technology that is based on
everything we just talked about one of
the things that I've now heard you talk
a lot about and I'm have a particular
interest in is physical AI or in other
words robots my
friends meaning humanoid robots but also
robots like self-driving cars and smart
buildings or autonomous warehouses or
autonomous lawnmowers or more from what
I understand we might be about to see a
huge leap in what all of these robots
are capable of because we're changing
how we train them up until recently
you've either had to train your robot in
the real world where it could get
damaged or wear down or you could get
data from Fairly limited sources like
humans in motion capture suits but that
means that robots aren't getting as many
examples as they'd need to learn more
quickly but now we're starting to train
Rob OTS in digital worlds which means
way more repetitions a day way more
conditions learning way faster so we
could be in a big bang moment for robots
right now and Nvidia is building tools
to make that happen you have Omniverse
and my understanding is this is 3D
worlds that help train robotic systems
so that they don't need to train in the
physical world that's exactly right you
just just announced Cosmos which is ways
to make that 3D Universe much more
realistic so you can get all kinds of
different um if we're training something
on this table many different kinds of
lighting on the table many different
times of day many different you know
experiences for the robot to go through
so that it can get even more out of
Omniverse as a kid who grew up loving
data on Star Trek Isaac asmon's book and
just dreaming about a future with robots
how do we get from the robots that we
have now to the Future world that you
see of Robotics yeah let me use um
language models maybe chat GPT as a
reference for understanding um Omniverse
and Cosmos and so so first of all when
chat GPT first came out it it was it was
um extraordinary and it has the ability
to do uh to basically uh from your promp
uh generate text however as amazing as
it was it has um the tendency to
hallucinate uh if it goes on too long or
if uh it pontificates about a topic it
you know is not informed about it'll
still do a good job generating plausible
answers um it just wasn't grounded in
the truth and so so um uh people people
uh called it
hallucination and so the Next Generation
uh shortly it was it had the ability to
be conditioned by um context so you
could upload your PDF and now it's
grounded by the PDF the PDF becomes the
ground truth it could be it could
actually look up search and then the
search becomes uh its ground truth and
between that it could reason about uh
what is how to produce the answer that
you're asking for and so so the first
part is a generative Ai and the second
part is ground truth okay and so now
let's come into the the the the physical
world uh the world model we need a
foundation model just like we need CH
chat GPT had a core Foundation model
that was the Breakthrough in order for
robotics to to be smart about the
physical world it has to understand
things like gravity friction
inertia um geometric and spatial
awareness it has to uh understand that
an object is sitting there even when I
looked away when I come back it's still
sitting there object permanence um it
has to understand cause and effect if I
tip it it'll fall over um and so so
these kind of physical common sense if
you will has to be captured or encoded
into a world Foundation model so that
the AI has World Common Sense okay and
so so we have to goes somebody has to go
create that and that's what we did with
Cosmos we created a World Language model
just like trpd was a language model this
is a world model the second thing we
have to go do is we have to do the same
thing that we did with PDFs and context
and um grounding it with ground truth
and so the way we augment Cosmos with
ground truth is with physical
simulations because Omniverse uses
physics simulation which is based on
principled solvers the the mathematics
is Newtonian physics is the right it's
the math we know okay all of the the
fundamental laws of physics uh We've
understood for a very long time and it's
encoded into captured into Omniverse
that's why Omniverse is a simulator and
using the simulator to ground or to
condition Cosmos we can now generate an
infinite number of Stories of the future
and they're grounded on physical
truth just like between PDF or sege
plus chat GPT we can generate an
infinite amount of interesting things
answer a whole bunch of interesting
questions the combination of Omniverse
plus Cosmos you could do that for the
physical world so to illustrate this for
the audience if you had a robot in a
factory and you wanted to make it learn
every route that it could take instead
of manually going through all of those
rots which could take days and could be
a lot of wear and tear on the robot
we're now able to simulate all of them
digitally in a fraction of the time and
in many different situations that the
robot might face it's dark it's blocked
it's Etc so the robot is now learning
much much faster it seems to me like the
future might look very different than
today if you play this out 10 years how
do you see people actually interacting
with this technology in the near
future Cleo everything that moves will
be robotic someday and it will be soon
you know the the idea that will'll be
pushing around a lawn mower is already
kind of silly you know maybe people do
it because because it's fun but but
there's no need to and and um uh every
car is going to be robotic human robots
uh the technology necessary to make it
possible uh is just around the corner
and so everything that moves will be
robotic and they'll they'll learn how to
be a robot in Omniverse Cosmos and will
generate
all these plausible physically plausible
Futures and the the robots will learn
from them and then they'll come into the
physical world and you know it's exactly
the same a future where um well you're
just surrounded by robots is for certain
and I'm just excited about having my own
R2-D2 and of course R2-D2 wouldn't be
quite the can that it is and roll roll
around it'll be you know
R2-D2 yeah it'll probably be a different
physic iCal embodiment um but it's
always R2 you know so my R2 is going to
go around with me sometimes it's in my
smart glasses sometimes it's in my phone
sometimes it's in my PC um it's in my
car so R2 is with me all the time
including you know when I get home you
know where I left a physical version of
R2 and you know whatever whatever that
version happens to be you know we we'll
interact with R2 and so I think the idea
that we'll have our own R2-D2 for our
entire life and it grows up with us um
that's a certainty now yeah I think a
lot
of news media when they talk about
Futures like this they focus on what
could go wrong and that makes sense
there is a lot that could go wrong we
should talk about what could go wrong so
we could keep it from from going wrong
yeah that's the approach that we like to
take on the show is what are the big
challenges so that we can overcome them
yeah what buckets do you think about
when you're worrying about this future
well there's there's a whole bunch of
the stuff that everybody talks about
bias or toxicity or or just
hallucination um you know speaking with
great confidence about something it
knows nothing about and as a result we
rely on that information um uh
generating that's a version of
generating uh fake information fake fake
news or fake images or whatever it is of
course impersonation um it it does such
a good job U pretending to be a human it
could be it could do an incredibly good
job pretending to be a specific human
and so so the the um uh the the spectrum
of of um areas we have to be concerned
about uh is fairly clear and there's a
lot of there's a lot of people who are
working on it there's there's a some of
the stuff some of the stuff related to
AI safety um requires deep research and
deep deep engineering and that's simply
it wants to do the right thing it just
didn't perform it right and as a result
hurt somebody you know for example uh
self-driving car that wants to drive
nicely and and drive properly and just
somehow the sensor broke down or or uh
it didn't detect something or um you
know made it to to aggressive turn or
whatever it is it did it poorly it did
it wrong wrongly and so that's that's a
whole bunch of engineering that has to
be done to to make sure that AI safety
is upheld by making sure that the
product function properly and then and
then lastly you know whatever what
happens if the S the the AI wants to do
a good job but the system failed meaning
the AI wanted to stop um stop stop
something from happening and it turned
out just when it wanted to do it um the
machine broke down and so this is no
different than than a flight computer
inside a plane having three versions of
them and then uh so there's there's
triple redundancy inside the system
inside autopilots and then you have two
pilots and then you have um uh
air traffic control and then you have
other Pilots watching out for these P
pilots and so so that the AI Safety
Systems has to be architected as a
community such that such that these AIS
uh one um uh work work function function
properly when they don't function
properly they don't put People In Harm's
Way and that they're sufficiently Safety
and Security Systems all around them uh
to make sure that that um uh we keep AI
safe and so there's this spectrum of
conversation is gigantic and and um uh
you know we have to take the parts take
the parts apart and and build them as
Engineers one of the incredible things
about this moment that we're in right
now is that we no longer have a lot of
the technological limits that we had in
a world of CPUs and sequential
processing and
we've unlocked not only a new way to do
Computing and
and but also a way to continue to
improve parallel processing has a a
different kind of physics to it than the
improvements that we were able to make
on CPUs I'm curious what are the
scientific or technological limitations
that we face now in the current world
that you're thinking a lot about well
everything in the end is about how much
work you can get done within the
limitations of the energy that you
have and so so that that's a that's a
physical limmit and uh the laws of
physics uh about transporting s
information and
um transporting bits flipping bits and
transporting bits um at the end of the
day the energy it takes to do that um
limits what we can get done and the
amount of energy that we have limits
what we can get done we're far from
having any fundamental limits that keep
us from advancing in the meantime we
seek to build better and more energy
efficient computers this this little
computer uh the the big version of it
was uh
$250,000 pick up yeah yeah that's little
baby baby digits yeah this is an AI
supercomputer the version that I
delivered this is just a prototype so
it's a mockup and so the the the very
first version was djx1 I delivered to
open AI in 2016 and that was $250,000
10,000 times more power more energy
necessary uh than this version and this
version has six times more performance W
I know it's incredible we're in a whole
in the world and it's only since 2016
and so eight years later we've in
increased the Energy Efficiency of
computing by 10,000 times and imagine if
we became 10,000 times more energy
efficient or if a car was 10,000 times
more energy efficient or electric light
bulb was 10,000 times more energy
efficient our light bulb would be right
now instead of 100 Watts 10,000 times
less producing the same illumination
yeah and so and so the the Energy
Efficiency of computing particularly for
AI Computing that we've been working on
has advanced incredibly and that's
That's essential because we want to
create you know more intelligent systems
and and we want to use U more
computation to be smarter and and uh so
Energy Efficiency to do the work is our
number one priority When I Was preparing
for this interview I spoke to a lot of
my engineering friends and this is a
question that they really wanted me to
ask so you're really speaking to your
people
here you've shown a value um of
increasing accessibility and abstraction
with Cuda and allowing more people to
use more computing power in all kinds of
other ways as applications of technology
get more specific I'm thinking of
Transformers in AI for example for the
audience a Transformer is a very popular
more recent structure of AI That's now
used in a huge number of the tools that
you've seen the reason that they're
popular is because Transformers are
structured in a way that helps them pay
attention to key bits of information and
give much better results you could build
chips that are perfectly suited for just
one kind of AI model but if you do that
then you're making them less able to do
other things so as these specific
structures or architectures of AI get
more popular my understanding is there's
a debate between how much you place
these bets on burning them into the chip
or designing Hardware that is very
specific to a certain task versus
staying more General and so my question
is how do you make those bets how do you
think about whether the solution is a
car that could go anywhere or it's
really optimizing a train to go from A
to B mhm you're making Bets with huge
stakes and I'm curious how you think
about that yeah and and that that now
comes back to um uh exactly your
question what are your core
beliefs and and the question the the
core belief either one that Transformer
is the
last AI algorithm AI architecture that
any researcher will ever discover again
or that um Transformers is a stepping
stone towards uh evolutions of
Transformers that are uh barely
recognizable as a Transformer uh years
from now and we believe the latter and
the reason for that is because um you
just have to go back in history and ask
yourself in the world of of uh computer
algorithms in the world of software in
the world of of um uh uh engineering and
innovation has one idea stayed along
that long and the answer is no and so
that's the that's kind of the Bea that's
that's in fact the essential beauty of a
computer that it's able to do something
today that no one even imagined possible
10 years ago and if you would have if
you would have turned that computer 10
years ago into a
microwave then why would the
applications keep coming and so we
believe we believe in the in the in the
richness of innovation and the richness
of invention and we want to create an
architecture that let inventors and
innovators and software programmers and
AI researchers swim in the soup and come
up with some Amazing Ideas look at
Transformers the the fundamental
characteristic of a transformer is this
idea called tension mechanism and it
basically says the Transformer is going
to understand the meaning and the
relevance of every single word with
every other word so if you had 10 words
it has to figure out the relationship
across 10 of them but if you have a
100,000 words or if you're Conta text is
now as large as read a PDF and that read
a whole bunch of PDFs and the context
window is now like a million
tokens the processing all of it across
all of it is just impossible and so the
way you solve that problem is there all
kinds of new ideas flash attention or
hierarchical attention or you know all
the wave attention I just WR read about
the other day um the number of different
types of attention mechanisms that have
been invented since the Transformer is
quite
extraordinary and so so I I think that
that's going to continue and um we
believe it's going to continue and that
that computer science hasn't ended and
that AI research have not all given up
and we haven't given up anyhow and and
uh and that that having a computer that
enables the the the flexibility of of
research and Innovation and and um new
ideas is fundamentally the most
important
thing one of the things that I am just
so curious about you design the chips
there are companies that assemble the
chips there are companies that design
Hardware to make it possible to work at
nanometer scale when you're designing
tools like this how do you think about
design in the context of what's
physically possible right now to make
what are the things that you're thinking
about with sort of pushing that limit
today um the way we do it is even though
even though we have things made like for
example our chips are made by
tsmc um even though we have them made by
tsmc we assume that we need to have the
Deep expertise that tsmc has and so we
have people in our company who are
incredibly good at semiconductive
physics so that we have a feeling for we
have an intuition for what are the
limits of of of what today's
semiconductor physics can do and then we
work very closely with them to discover
the limits because we're trying to push
the limits and so we discover the limits
together now we do the same thing in
system engineering and cooling systems
it turns out Plumbing is really
important to us because of liquid
cooling and maybe fans are really
important to us because of air Cooling
and we're trying to design these fans in
a way almost like you know they're
aerodynamically sound so that we could
pass the highest volume of air make the
least amount of noise so we have
aerodynamics engine in our in our
company and so even though even though
we don't make them uh we design them and
we have to ex deep expertise of knowing
how to have them made and and um and and
from that we we uh we try to push the
limits one of the themes of this
conversation is that you are a person
who
makes big bets on the future and time
and time again you've been right about
those bets we've talked about gpus we've
talked about Cuda we've talked about
bets you've made in AI self-driving cars
and we're going to be right on Robotics
and this is my question we're going to
be righte the latest bet of course we
just described at the CES and I'm very
very proud of it and and I'm very
excited about it is the fusion of
Omniverse and Cosmos so that we have
this new type of generative World
Generation system this Multiverse
generation system I I think that's going
to be profoundly important in the future
of of uh Robotics and physical
systems of course the work that we're
doing with human robots developing the
tooling systems and the training systems
and um the human demonstration systems
and all all of this stuff that that
you've already
mentioned we're we're just seeing the
beginnings of of that work and uh I
think the next 5 years are going to be
very interesting in the world of human
robotics of course the work that we're
doing in um digital biology so that we
can understand the language of molecules
and understand the language of cells and
just as we understand the language of
physics and the physical world we' like
to understand the language of the human
body and understand the language of
biology and so if we can learn that uh
and we can predict it then all of a
sudden uh our ability to have a digital
twin of the human is plausible and so
I'm very excited about that work I love
the work that we're doing in uh climate
science and be able to from weather
predictions understand and predict the
high resolution Regional climates the
weather patterns uh within a kilometer
above your head um that we can somehow
predict that with great accuracy uh its
implications is really quite profound uh
and so the number of things that we're
working on is is really cool you know we
we're we're fortunate
that uh We've created this this
instrument that that is a a time
machine and we need time machines in all
of these areas that we just talked about
so that so that we can see the future
and if we could see the future and we
can predict the future then we have a
better chance of making that future the
best version of it and and that's the
reason why scientists want to predict
the future that's the reason why that's
the reason why we try to predict the
future and everything that we try to
design so that we we can um optimize for
the best version so if someone is
watching this and maybe they came into
this video knowing that Nvidia is an
incredibly important company but not
fully understanding why or how it might
affect their life and they're now
hopefully better understanding a big
shift that we've gone through over the
last few decades in Computing this very
exciting very sort of strange moment
that we're in right now where we're sort
of on the precipice of so many different
things if they would like to be able to
look into the future a little bit how
would you advise them to prepare or to
think about this moment that they're in
personally with respect to how these
tools are actually going to affect
them well there are several ways to
reason about about the future that we're
creating um uh one way to reason about
it is
suppose the work that you do uh
continues to be important but but the
effort by which you do it
um went from you know being a week long
to almost instantaneous you know that
that the effort of drudgery uh basically
goes to zero what is the implication of
that uh this is this is very similar to
what would change if
all of a sudden we had highways in this
country and that kind of happened you
know in the last Industrial Revolution
all of a sudden we have interstate
highways and when you have interstate
highways what happens well you know
suburbs start to be created and and all
of a sudden um you
know distribution of goods from east to
west is is is no longer a concern and um
all of a sudden gas stations start
cropping up on highways and uh and uh um
fast food restaurants show up and you
know someone some motels show up because
people you know traveling across the
state across the country and just wanted
to stay somewhere for a few hours or
overnight and and so all of a sudden new
economies and new capabilities new
economies um what would happen if if a
video conference made it possible for us
to see each other uh without having to
travel anymore that all of a sudden it's
actually okay to work far further away
from home and uh from from uh from work
work and live further away uh and so so
you ask yourself kind of these these
questions you know what would happen if
if um uh I have a software programmer
with me all the time and whatever it is
I I Can Dream up the software programmer
could write for me you know what what
would that do uh what would happen if if
um uh if I just had a seed of an idea
and and I rough it out and all of sudden
a you know a prototype of a a production
was put in front of me and what how
would that change my life and how would
that change my opportunity and um you
know what what is it free me to be able
to do and and so on so forth and so so I
think that the next the next decade
intelligence um not for
everything uh but for for some things
would basically become superhuman and
and so so um uh
but I can tell you exactly what that
feels like I'm surrounded by
superhuman people super intelligence
from my perspective because they're the
best in the world at what they do and
they do what they do way better than I
can do it
and and I'm surrounded by thousands of
them and yet what it it never one day um
caused me to to think all of a son I'm
no longer necessary it actually empowers
me and gives me the confidence to go
tackle more and more ambitious
things and so so suppose suppose now
everybody is surrounded by these super
AIS that are very good at specific
things or good at some of the things
what would that make you feel well it's
going to empower you it's going to make
you feel confident uh and and I I'm
pretty sure you probably use cha GPT and
Ai and um I feel I feel more empowered
today more confident to learn something
today the knowledge of almost any
particular field the barriers to that
understanding it has been reduced and I
have a personal tutor with me all of the
time and and so I I think that that
feeling should be Universal and and I if
if there's one thing that I would
encourage everybody to do is to go get
yourself an AI tutor right away and that
AI tutor could of course just teach your
things uh anything you like um uh help
you program uh help you write uh help
you analyze help you think help you
reason uh you know all of those things
uh is going to really make you feel
empowered and and um I think that that's
that's going to be our future we're
going to become we're going to become
super humans not because we have super
we're going to become super humans
because we have super
AIS could you tell us a little bit about
each of these objects
this is a new GeForce graphics card and
yes and uh this is the RTX 50 Series it
is essentially a supercomputer that you
put into your PC and we use it for
gaming of course people today use it for
design and creative arts and it does
amazing Ai and the the real breakthrough
here and this is this is truly an
amazing amazing thing GeForce enable
abled Ai and it enabled Jeff Hinton
Alias es and Alex kushy to be able to
train alexnet we discovered Ai and we
Advanced AI then AI came back to GeForce
to help computer graphics and so here's
the amazing thing out of 8 million
pixels or so in a 4K display we are
Computing we're processing only 500,000
of them the rest of them we use AI to
predict the AI guessed it and yet the
image is perfect we inform it by the
500,000 pixels that we computed And We R
traced every single one and it's all
beautiful it's perfect and then we tell
the AI if these are the 500,000 perfect
pixels in this screen what are the other
8 million and it goes it fills in the
rest of the screen and it's perfect and
if you only have to do fewer pixels are
you able to invest more in doing that
because you have fewer to do so then the
quality is better so the extrapolation
that the AI does exactly because
whatever Computing whatever attention
you have whatever resources you have you
can place it into 500,000 pixels now
this is a perfect example of why AI is
going to make us all superhuman because
all of the other things that it can do
it'll do for us allows us to take our
time and energy and focus it on the
really really valuable things that we do
and so we'll take our own resource which
is you know energy intensive attention
intensive and well dedicated to the few
100,000 pixels and use AI to Super reses
it upres it you know to everything else
and so this this graphics card is now
powered mostly by Ai and uh the computer
Graphics technology inside is incredible
as well and then this next one uh as I
mentioned earlier in 2016 I built the
first one for uh AI researchers and we
delivered the first one to open Ai and
Elon was there to receive it and this
this version um uh I built a mini mini
version and the reason for that is
because AI has now gone from AI
researchers to every engineer every
student every AI scientist and and AI is
going to be everywhere and so instead of
these $250,000 versions we're going to
make these $3,000 versions and schools
can have them you know students can have
them and you set it next to your PC or
Mac and um all of a sudden you have your
own AI
supercomputer and you could you develop
and build AIS build your own AI build
your own R2-D2 what do you feel like is
important for this audience to know that
I haven't asked one of the most
important things I would advise is for
example if I were a student today the
first thing I would do is to learn AI
how do I learn to interact with check
GPT how do I learn to interact with
Gemini Pro and how do I learn to
interact with Gro and and um I these
learning how to interact with with AI is
not unlike being someone who is really
good at asking questions you're
incredibly good at asking questions and
and prompting AI is very very similar
you you you you can't just randomly ask
a bunch of questions and and so asking
asking an AI to be assistant to you
requires requires some expertise in in
Artistry and how to prompt it and so if
I were if I were a student today
irrespective whether it's for uh for
math or for science or chemistry or
biology or doesn't matter what field of
science I'm going to go into or what
profession I am I'm going to ask myself
how can I use AI to do my job better if
I want to be a a lawyer how can I use AI
to be a better lawyer if I want to be a
better do doctor how can I use AI to be
a better doctor if I want to be a
chemist how do I use AI to be a better
chemist if I want to be a biologist I
how do I use AI to be a better biologist
that question should be persistent
across everybody and just as My
Generation Um grew up as the first
generation that has to ask ourselves how
can we use computers to do our jobs
better yeah the generation before us had
no computers my generation was the first
generation that had to ask the question
how do I use computers to do my job
better remember I came into the industry
before Windows
95 right 1984 there were no computers in
offices and after that shortly after
that computers started to emerge and so
we had to ask ourselves how do we use
computers to do our jobs better the Next
Generation doesn't have to ask that
question but it has to ask obviously
next question how can I use AI to do my
job better that is start and finish I
think for everybody it's a really
exciting and scary and therefore
worthwhile question I think for everyone
I think it's it's going to be incredibly
fun AI is obviously a word that people
are just learning now but it's just you
know what would it is it's made your
computer so much more accessible it is
easier to prompt chat GPT to ask it
anything you like than to go do the
research yourself and so we've lowered a
barrier of understanding we've lowered a
barrier of knowledge we've lowered a
barrier of intelligence and
and um uh everybody really had to just
go try it you know the thing that's
really really crazy is if I put a
computer in front of somebody and
they've never used a computer there is
no chance they're going to learn that
computer in a day there's just no chance
somebody really has to show it to you
and uh yet with chat GPT if you don't
know how to use it all you have to do is
type in I don't know how to use Chad GPT
tell me and it would come back and give
you some examples and so that's the
amazing thing you know this the the
amazing thing about intelligence is uh
it'll help you along the way and make
you uh superum you know along the way
all right I have one more question if
you have a second this is not something
that I plan to ask you but on the way
here
uh I'm a little bit afraid of planes
which is not my most reasonable quality
and the flight here was a little bit
bumpy mhm very bumpy and I'm sitting
there and it's moving
and I'm thinking about what they're
going to say at my funeral
and after she asked good questions
that's that's that's what the
tombstone's going to say I hope so yeah
and after I loved my husband and my
friends and my family the thing that I
hoped that they would talk about was
optimism I hope that they would
recognize what I'm trying to do here and
I'm very curious for you youve you've
been doing this a long time it feels
like there's so much that you've
described in this Vision
ahead what would the theme be that you
would want people to say about what
you're trying to
do very
simply they made an extraordinary
impact and I think that we're fortunate
because of some core beliefs a long time
ago and sticking with those core beliefs
and um uh building upon them uh we we
found
ourselves today uh being one of the most
one of the many most important uh and
consequential uh technology companies uh
in the world and potentially ever and
and and so we we take we take that
responsibility very seriously um we work
hard to make sure that
the capabilities that we've created are
available to uh large companies as well
as individual researchers and
developers uh across every field of
science no matter profitable or not uh
big or small famous or
otherwise um and and it's because of
this this understanding of the
consequential work that we're doing and
the potential impact it has on so many
people uh that we want to make make this
capability uh as as uh as pervasively as
possible and um I do think that that
when we look back in a few years
uh and I do hope that what what uh the
Next Generation
realized uh is as they they well first
of all they're going to know us because
of all the you know gaming technology we
create
I I do think that we'll look back and
the whole field of digital biology and
Life Sciences has been transformed our
whole understanding of of um Material
Sciences uh has complet been
revolutionized uh that robots are
helping us do dangerous and mundane
things all over the place uh that if we
wanted to drive we can drive but
otherwise you know take a nap or um
enjoy your car like it's a home theater
of yours uh you know read from work to
home and and at that point you're hoping
that you're you live far away and so you
could be in a car for longer and you
know and and and you look back and you
realize that there's this company almost
at the epicenter of all of that and and
uh happens to be the company that you
grew up playing games with and I I hope
I hope that that to be uh what what the
Next Generation learn thank you so much
for your time I enjoyed it thank you I'm
glad