okay hi everyone I'll get started the
last
class okay um yeah well welcome
congratulations and thank you to making
it to the um last real lecture of
cs224n yeah so so this is the plan for
today um the lecture's titled NLP
Linguistics and philosophy which I took
as meaning that I could talk about
anything I wanted to um and so that is
what I'm going to do um so this is sort
of this um what we're going to go
through talk a bit about the major ideas
of Cs 24n and open problems um some of
the more foundational questions of where
are we with llm symbolic versus neural
systems meaning and Linguistics and NLP
and then I'll close with um some slides
on the future risks of AI in the world
okay so here is an attempt to sort of
lay out the most major things that we
looked at in
cs224n um we started with word vectors
then we developed the idea of neural NP
systems we expanded from a simple feed
forward Network into doing sequence
models language models rnns lstms and
then we introduced this powerful new
model that's been very influential the
Transformer and then we built from there
to the kind of um it's not exactly an
architecture but model that's been built
up in recent years to produce high
performance NLP systems where we're
first doing pre-training and then a uh
post-training phase of various
techniques that we talked about to
produce um these General Foundation
models that understand language so well
and then we went on from there and
talked about various particular topics
like benchmarking and reasoning so a few
of the major ideas that we looked at
were um this idea that you could get a
long way by having dense representations
those are our hidden representations in
new networks and then looking at
distributional semantics representing
words by their context um first slogan
of you shall know a word by the company
it keeps and I'll come back to that a
bit later and talking about um ideas of
meaning but you know that's essentially
been the idea that has driven most of
the successful ideas of modern NLP
whether it's the earli statistical NLP
phase or more modern neural NLP phase
and in this world we start instantiating
that as um these models of word vectors
but the same contextual idea is then
used in all the models up through
Transformers we looked at both the
challenges and
opportunities um of training large deep
newal networks and how gradually people
developed ideas and tricks such as
having residual connections which made
it much more possible and stable to do
successfully um which took us from a
place where a lot of this seemed black
magic that was hard to get right to
people being able to very reliably train
high performance Transformer models um
we talked about sequence models what's
good about them and some of their
problems and how those problems have
been addressed in large measure by
adopting this different architecture of
Transformers which give a form of
parallelization and then we moved into
the modern form of pre-training by
language modeling where language
modeling seems a simple thing predicting
words in context but it emerges as what
we think of as a universal pre-training
task that all kinds of both linguistic
and World Knowledge help you to do this
task of predicting words better and so
this is ended up as just a general
method um to produce the kind of um
powerful knowledgeable models that we
have today and up until now there's been
this amazing property that we see this
empirical fact that we seem to just get
this um basically well not basically
it's extremely linear improvements of
performance as we continue to scale data
and compute and model model size up by
orders of
magnitude um that doesn't mean that all
problems in NLP are solved um there are
lots of things that people um still work
on and see opportunities to try and make
things better and a few of these um are
mentioned on the next few slides um so
there's a real question of how much um
these models are good at actually
learning to be able to do things
generally rather than just being very
good at
memorization um that a lot of the
benefits of what we're getting from
these large pre-trained language models
is that they've seen a huge amount of
stuff and therefore they know everything
they've seen every pattern before and
they know how to use things I've
occasionally use the analogy that um
large language models are sort of like a
talking and encyclopedia that they're
really in many ways more like a huge
knowledge store than necessarily
something that is intelligent in the
sense of being able to work out how to
solve new problems and generalize as
human beings do a kind of interesting
fact actually is that in some ways
Transformer models are actually worse at
generalizing than the older lstms that
preceded them so here's just you know
one little graph I'm not going to spend
a lot of time on but this was looking at
data that's being generated by a finite
autometer and then trying to learn it
from a limited amount of data um with
either an lstm or a Transformer and the
observation is that you know at the
scales that they're working even having
seen quite limited
exemplification the lstm is basically
sealing the entire of this graph right
it's just at the one line um because it
generalizes in good ways because of its
lstm architecture um whereas the
Transformer needs to see a ton more data
before it actually learns the patterns
well and so if we think of one of the
Prime attributes of human intelligence
is actually we're amazing at figuring
out and learning things from very
limited exposure right you know there's
something that you don't know how to do
and a friend shows you once um what you
do to make it work and by and large you
know you'll improve a few times with
practice but you can learn effectively
new skills from these kind of single
shot
examples um and that's not always what
we seem to be seeing in our models um
there's a lot of interest in what's
going on inside newal networks that a
lot of the time newal networks still
appear as blackboxes where we have no
real idea of how they're doing what
they're doing and as perhaps for your
final projects the main thing you're
doing is measuring um the final
performance number and seeing if it goes
up or not um so there's a lot of
interest in better understanding what do
they learn how did they learn it why do
they succeed and fail and a lot of that
work is star to look more closely into
what's happening inside new network
computations um there is some work of
that sort that actually goes back quite
a fair way so here's um an old blog post
by Andre Kathy while he's a grad student
here in
2016 and he he was looking at lstms and
how did they learn and he found that one
of the neurons in an lstm cell was
effectively sort of measuring position
along a line of text and as the line of
text got long its sort of value started
to change because the model was learning
that there was sort of a line length of
this text and that the line was likely
to be ending at that point and in recent
times there started to be with
Transformers as well a lot of work
looking at mechanistic interpretability
or causal abstraction trying to
understand the internals of
models um a problem that's far from
solved and in many respects probably
unsolvable is the multilingual question
of dealing with all the other languages
of the world um that you do have to keep
in your head that whatever you see for
English um it's worse for every other
language um and what they're getting out
of modern language models now you know
there is a good news story here I don't
want to claim that everything is
terrible so in this graph which is kind
of small um the blue line was the
performance of GPT 3.5 English and then
all of the the
green um bars are then the performance
of GPT 4 and so you know there's a
genuine good news story here which is
look not just for English but for a lot
of other languages for Greek lvan um
Arabic Turkish um all of them in GP 4
better than English was in gpt3 3.5 so
you know that's the good news argument
um that um you know building these
models big is in some sense raising all
boats but you know these are still all
huge languages and you know things are
starting to drop off at the bottom of
this table um for um languages where the
performance is worse than than English
and GPT 3.5 but even for those languages
they're they're languages for which much
less written data is available but
they're still large languages so the
ones at the three at the bottom are
actually all Indian languages they're
Punjabi morati and telu um and which are
languages that are each spoken by
millions of people they're not small
languages um so the real question is
what happens when you actually get to
the small resource languages so the vast
majority of languages around the world
don't have millions of speakers they
vary from having hundreds of speakers to
hundreds of thousands of speakers and
there are thousands of such languages a
lot of those languages are primarily
oral and have very limited amounts of um
written text now some of those languages
are likely or many of those languages
are likely to go extinct um in the
coming decades um but many of those
language communities would like to
preserve their languages and it's very
unclear how the kind of language
technologies that we've been talking
about in the later parts of um the
course can be extended to those
languages because there just isn't
sufficient data to build the kind of
models that we've been looking
at so I imagine you've gotten some idea
in this course of how evaluation is a
huge part of what we do that effectively
a lot of the way that progress is being
driven is by defining evaluations of
what models should be able to achieve
and then people working um to measure um
systems and improve systems so they do
better on what we see as good language
other understanding or other properties
um one of the concerns that many people
have about what's happened with the
large recent um Clos models from large
companies is a concern that all of the
benchmarks are being sullied and not to
be trusted um so here's um one example
um that comes from a tweet of Horus
Hurst um and he's noting I suspect gp4s
performance is influenced by data
contamination at least on code forces
one of the coding benchmarks of the
easiest problems on Co code forces it
solved 10 out of 10 pre 2021 problems
but zero out of 10 recent problems this
strongly points to contamination and the
worry is that every time you're seeing
these fantastic results of how well the
latest best language model is performing
that at this point so much data is on
the web that gets included um in the
pre-training data for these large
language models that essentially they're
memorizing at least a good share of the
questions that are appearing in these
challenges so they're not actually
solving them in a fair way as an
independent test set at all they're just
memorizing them and so there are sort of
issues then as to you know what kind of
Thoroughly hidden test sets we can have
or dynamic evaluation mechanisms so we
can actually have Benchmark
Integrity another huge area the number
of us involved in Stanford elsewhere is
making NLP work in different technical
domains so domains including biomedical
or clinical medical NLP have a lot of
differences of vocabulary um and usage
they have a lot of potential good uses
but they also have a lot of potential
risks of doing harm if the language
understanding is incomplete I myself
have been more involved um doing things
in the legal NLP um working with other
people at the reg lab with danho in
building Foundation models for law um
and there are all kinds of ways again in
which um this kind of Technology could
be really useful right the biggest
problem in most countries it's bad in
the United States but it's way worse in
a place like India is that most people
can't get access to the kind of legal
help that they need to solve their
problems because of the cost of it and
the lack of um trained lawyers so if
more could be done to be able to help
people via um NLP tools you know in
principle that would be great but in
practice um the tools still don't have
good enough language understanding um so
um in the reg lab there's a just
completed study out at the moment
looking at um legal NLP systems and we
were finding that the hallucination rate
the rate in which there was madeup stuff
in their legal AR answers was
effectively for one question in six
which isn't a very good accuracy rate if
you're someone who's wanting to rely on
these systems um for legal
advice um there are lots of things also
to work out dealing with the social and
cultural aspects of NLP NLP systems
remain very biased against various
cultures and
religions um
they they have certain social norms you
could say that they pick up from
somewhere but those social norms are
very biased it's against certain groups
and um related to um there being small
languages that I mentioned before that
there are lots of issues with
underrepresented groups in having the
kind of NLP that they'd like to
have okay so um that's sort of the
summary of that bit so for the next bit
I thought I'd just sort of give one more
bit of perspective on where are we um
with um the best um language models like
gp4 I mean I think it's really
interesting at this moment of where we
are CU you know on the one hand the
performance of these models is just
amazing and you know even as someone who
works in NLP and has worked in it for
many many years now I mean you know I
can tell a a sort of story that these
models you know that we do this training
to predict the next word and it's
conditioning on a lot of text and it
knows about things and it does but you
know in some sense these things still
seem like magic right it's just kind of
hard to believe how this could possibly
work so in this example I asked chat GPT
40 I did that this this morning I asked
and um to write a sonnet explaining the
Transformer neet architecture in which
every line begins with the letter t um
and it sort of still frankly blows my
mind and I don't actually feel I can
really explain even to myself in a way
that's convincing how this large
Transformer is able to take all its
pre-training text and reading that
instruction
um and as a next tokken prediction
machine it successfully produces
something that is a Sonet and every line
begins with the letter T I hope you
remember from your high school English
classes sonnets are meant to have AB um
rhyming um it's a little bit imperfect
here net set some people will complain
about that but it's basically a rhyme
behold unfold grasp clasp right so it's
basically doing the writing rhyming
right and um the lines are meant to be
an i Amic pentameter and it's basically
produced lines and I Amic pentameter to
delve into the world of neural Nets you
know I Amic pentam um yeah it's
incredible so here's um it's Sonet it
came up with to delve into the world of
neural Nets Transformers Rise a Marvel
to behold through layers deep the
networks path is set to learn from data
patterns to unfold the tokens feed into
attentions grasp to weigh their import
context to a line the query's keys and
values in a clasp to process sequences
with power fine through heads of many
multifaceted site to parallelize
capturing the span transforming each a
matrix math Delight to synthesize with
elegance and plan the models might in
every task it shows to turn raw data
into wisdom's Pros now now you you could
object um that I'm not sure this exactly
explained the transform new net
architecture um it's a little bit
abstract I'll give it
that but you know in another sense it
did it did in one place or another evoke
quite a bit of stuff about Transformers
with queries keys and values and
multiheaded stuff parallelized with
Matrix math and whatever else um yeah
still still kind of blows my mind how
well that works and you know indeed um
as natural language understanding and
sort of world understanding devices I
mean these devices have clearly crossed
the threshold in which they're very
usable in many contexts so here's
there's now started to be some fairly
good studies um that have been done on
you know how much value people can get
out of using llms like um
gp4 um so this um study by dequa and a
whole lot of colle including Ethan mik
um they took a bunch of Consultants from
the Boston Consulting Group and so you
know what that's like that means you
know 23 year olds graduating from
universities like this one but more on
the East Coast um they become you know
Boston Consultants you know not exactly
um dummies um and so they they found in
this study so you know controlled task
um there are there actually so three
groups but the big contrast is that you
know two of the groups were using gp4 to
do Consulting tasks and one of the
groups wasn't using um gp4 to do tasks
the difference between the two that were
was one of them was giving given more
training on how to use gp4 but that
didn't seem to make much of a difference
um but their result was um that the
groups using
gp4 um in their study completed 12% more
tasks on average they did the task 25%
more com quickly and um the results were
judged 40% higher quality than those not
using AI which I think is a pretty um
stunning success of how um gp4 or
similar llms are good enough to actually
help people get real work done you know
with whatever asteris you want to put
about the quality of Management
Consultant work in various instances um
yeah I mean an interesting result is
that you know using these llms seem to
be a big leveler and actually you see
exactly the same thing for people using
um coding llms that they're a huge
assistance for people whose own skills
are weaker and they're much less of an
are
strong okay so that's the good news
story but you know if on the other hand
you're more like the good news story for
human beings um here's a study um that
goes in the other direction can gp4
write fiction that matches the quality
of New Yorker fiction writers um and the
result of that study was not even close
um that gp4 was measured as 3 to 10
times worse at creative writing than a
New Yorker fiction writer so there's
still hope for human beings hang on
there um and so you know I think that's
kind of the you know the jewel screen
picture that we have at the moment then
in some ways these things are great and
useful in other ways um they're not so
great and I think that's something um
that we're still sort of going to be um
seeing playing out um in the future
years I think um living in Silicon
Valley um we see a lot of the positive
hype so if you just want to um see a
little bit of the negative on the other
side um late last year there was uh
peace in the financial times um which
was titled generative AI hyly
intelligent um and I won't read all of
this um but basically they were a
wanting to express um considerable um
skepticism of the current AI boom
investors should keep their heads
expectations for generative AI are
running way ahead of the limitations
that apply to it as investment in
generative AI grows so does pressure to
create new use cases by 2027 IDC thinks
Enterprise spending on generative AI
will reach 143 billion up from 16
billion this year so 10 times up open AI
hopes for more funding to pursue
humanlike AI it is worth remembering
that when examining alman's plan for
super intelligence models predict they
do not comprehend that limitation cast
out on AI achieving even humanlike
intelligence um and then they sort of
start talking about some the problems um
with you know limited gains for low
skilled workers inaccuracies in the work
they produc um and suggests that the
limitations will become more obvious as
generative AI tools roll out that will
put pressure on providers to address
costs AI could add 4 trillion to profits
says McKenzie but pricing Clarity is
lacking without it companies cannot
predict what Financial gains AI can
accomplish and AI cannot predict that
either okay um that's that topic I'm
chugging through my topics um the next
topic is I wanted to return and say a
bit more about symbolic methods that
dominated AI from the 60s until about
2010 versus um what I termed here is
cybernetics because the original
alternative going back to the 50s and
60s um was called cybernetics and in a
very real sense neural networks is a
continuation of the cybernetics
tradition rather than the AI tradition
that started in the 50s and 60s um in
this context um Stanford is the home of
the symbolic systems program um so at
the moment um we are unique in having a
symbolic systems program um so the name
symbolic systems came about because at
the time it was started um so I guess
philosophy was an active part of the
symbolic systems program and John
barwise um shown in this picture he
actually died young so he he actually
died in 2000 um John barwise um had um a
very strong belief um that you me to be
um dealing with meaning in the world and
the connection between people's thinking
in the world and so he um refused to
allow the program to be called cognitive
science as it's called at most other
places and it ended up being called
symbolic systems um now at one point
there were two universities that had
symbolic systems CU John barise actually
moved away from Stanford and went to
Indiana which is where he originally was
from um and so Indiana also had a
symbolic systems program for a number of
years but they've actually changed
Theirs to cognitive science now since he
died so we are unique in having symbolic
systems and so the idea of symbolic
systems this is sort of what's on the
website website with a bit of
interpretation right so symbolic system
studies systems are meaningful symbols
that represent the world about us like
human languages Logics and programming
languages and the systems that work with
these symbols like brains computers and
complex social systems contrasting that
to the sort of typical view of cognitive
science which is focusing on the mind
and intelligence as a naturally
occurring phenomenon um symbolic systems
gives equal Focus to human constructed
systems that use symbols to communicate
and to represent information
right so um in AI terms um you know AI
as a field and the name AI um
arose um around arguing for a symbolic
approach right that John um John
McCarthy who's the color photo there and
who um founded Stanford's artificial
intelligence um and the St the original
famous Stanford AI lab so John McCarthy
came up with the name artificial
intelligence and he very ex very
explicitly chose a new name to um
disassociate what he was doing um from
the cybernetics approach um which had
been pursued by people including um
Norbert weer um at MIT who's shown on
the right side um so Marvin miny the
Teeny um photo down here um sort of
founded um artificial intelligence at
MIT um McCarthy worked with him for a
few years and then McCarthy came to
Stanford um and two of the other most
prominent early AI people new and Simon
who were at CMU and the other two people
on the right side and
so in particular um new and Simon um
develop well actually no let me say a
sentence first yeah so I mean McCarthy's
own background was a mathematician and
logician right so that he wanted to
construct uh an artificial intelligence
that looked like math and logic
effectively right and that sort of was
AI as a symbolic system and that was
developed as a position in the
philosophy of artificial intelligence by
new and Simon and so they developed what
they called the physical symbol system
hypothesis um so that said a phys iCal
symbol system has the necessary and
sufficient means for General intelligent
action and so you know that's a super
strong claim it's not only claiming that
um having a symbol system allows you to
produce artificial general intelligence
but through um the necessary Clause that
you can't have artificial general
intelligence without having a symbol
system um so that was sort of um the
basis of um classical AI right um so um
and that kind of contrasts a bit with
the you know so cybernetics you know had
its origins in sort of control and
communication so it's much nearer to
sort of an electrical engineering kind
of background um and was wanting to sort
of um unify ideas of control and
communication between animals um maybe
perhaps more than humans and machines um
yeah so I mean you know um sort of in
yeah so cybernetics comes from a Greek
word um kubernetes which is sort of
interesting all the uses it has so it's
exactly the same route that occurs both
in kubernetes if you're are familiar
with that as you know distributed
containers on Modern systems but also
it's actually the same route that the
word government comes from um course
it's a control system as
well
um yeah um so under the cybernetics
tradition was when newal Nets first
started being explored um the very
earliest neuron Nets um the most famous
ones are Frank Rosen blats which were
used for vision the newal net was
actually wired um to say just a teeny
bit about this in case you think that AI
hype is only a thing of the
2020s there was just as much AI hype in
the
1950s when Rosen blat um unveiled his
perceptron um so in the New York Times
article about it new Navy device learns
by doing psychologist shows embryo of
computer design to read and grow wiser
the Navy revealed the embryo of an of an
electronic computer today that it
expects will be able to walk talk see
write reproduce itself and be conscious
of its existence um and this hype is all
the more incredible when you get to the
um later paragraph of the article and
you find out what the demonstration was
actually of and the demonstration that
people were shown um was um that this
device learned to
differentiate between right arrow and
left arrow pictures after 50
[Laughter]
exposures but there you
go okay um yeah so what what do we make
of this in the case of NLP and language
and you know the position I would like
to suggest is you know there's just no
doubt um that language is a Sy symbolic
system right that humans
developed language as a symbolic system
it's perhaps most obvious um that if you
think about it in writing we have
symbols of the letters and words that we
use but even if there's no writing and
you know the majority of human language
use over time has been verbal human
language use that even though the
substrate it's carried on where the
sound waves or in sign languages
movements of hands even though that's a
continuous substrate the structure of
human languages is a symbol system we
have symbols which are the sounds of
human languages for cat we have a c an
at and a t those are symbols and they're
recognized in a symbolic Way by language
users and indeed um the all the
pioneering work and categorical
perception in cognitive psychology is
done with um the sounds of human
languages um the phones as linguists
call them so spoken language also has a
symbolic structure but you know going
against new and Simon the fact that
humans use a symbol system for
communication doesn't mean that the
process of the symbols the human brain
has to be a physical symbol system and
so similarly we don't have to design NLP
our computer processors as physical
symbol systems either um the brain is
you know clearly much more like a newal
network model um and probably newal
models will scale better and capture
language processing better than
something that is a symbolic processor
um in the same way I mean that sort of
leaves behind the question of well why
did humans come up with a symbol system
for communication I mean after all you
know we could have just sort of hummed
at different frequencies and that could
have been used as our system of
communication I mean I think the
dominant idea which seems reasonable to
me but who knows is that um having a
symbolic system gives signaling
reliability right that if you have
discrete Target points that are
separated then that gives you an ability
um when there's degradation of the
signal to recover it
well um yeah so where does that leave
Linguistics which is mainly um been
developed in terms of um describing a
symbolic system I think the right way to
think about it as Linguistics is good
for giving us questions Concepts and
distinctions when thinking about
language acquisition processing and
understanding and indeed one of the
interesting things that's come about is
that sort of as um NLP and AI have been
developed further and as able to do a
lot of low-level stuff that there's
actually the sort of higher level
Concepts that linguists often talk about
a lot things like compositionality and
systematic generalization which I'll
come back to in a few minutes um the
mapping of stable meanings for symbols
the reference of um linguistic
expressions in the world that they get
talked about more and more in artificial
intelligence context building neural
systems and I mean I think one way to
think about is that you know a lot of
the early neural netw work um of um most
notably visual processing but also other
kinds of sensory stuff like sounds I
mean doing that is sort of what gets you
to insect level intelligence and if you
want to get higher up the chain than
insect level intelligence then a lot of
the kind of questions and properties of
linguistic systems become increasingly
relevant um at a slightly more prosaic
level um that I don't think one
necessarily wants to believe all the F
details of different um linguistic
theories but you know for how human
languages are structured and how they
behave I think yeah most of our broad
understanding of linguistics is right
and so therefore when we're thinking
about NP systems and we're thinking
about you know understanding how they
behave wanting to know whether they have
certain properties thinking up ways to
evaluate them a lot of that is done in
terms of linguistic understand standing
wanting to see whether they capture
facts about sentence structure discourse
structure semantic properties like
natural language inference um whether
you can do things like bridging and AFA
which I did not cover this year's class
because we skipped the co- reference
lecture when we slice one lecture off
the class metaphors presuppositions all
of these things are linguistic Notions
that we try and get our NLP models to
capture so I just want to say a couple
more remarks um about you know the role
of human language in human intelligence
I think this is kind of interesting um
so an interesting person in the history
of linguistics um is this guy vilhelm
Von Hot um who is um a prominent German
academic um so um so really the American
education system um was borrowed from
Germany right so up until the second
world war the preeminent place of
Science and learning was Germany and
Germany um essentially via V Von
humber's work developed the idea of
having graduate education and the US
copied graduate education from Germany
and started um doing its own but you
know in in that context it was still the
case that um for people in the United
United States prior to the 1930s that
generally people would go to Germany um
to finish their education either to get
their PHD or to do a postdoc or
something like that right so you know if
you uh Trace back my own academic tree
or most other academic trees of people
who got phds in the US they actually go
back a few generations and then they go
back to Germany um so
uh we don't think of that as much in the
modern world yeah so um hbal was
influential and developing the
university system um but he also um
worked a lot on um language and I he's
someone that um Chomsky always cites um
because he's known for this famous
statement about that human language must
make infinite use of finite means so the
fact that we have a limited um Supply of
words and sentence structures but out of
those we can recursively build up an
infinite number of sentences and that's
in chomsky's view supporting the kind of
um symbolic structured view of language
that he's been advocating but I think
there's sort of another interesting take
of Von Holts which um we can argue
whether it's um right or not but I think
is kind of interesting and one of the
things he want wants to stress is that
language isn't just something um used
for the purpose of
communication um that he
um I should actually introduce something
here so um so caraman and tersi are two
well-known cognitive psychologists and
they introduced this idea that there are
two kinds of thinking system one
cognition and system 2 cognition and
system one is the kind of subconscious
thinking that you're not really thinking
of just we process stuff when it comes
into our heads whether visual signals or
um speech and system 2 Thinking is um
the conscious let me think about this
and try and figure out what's going on
I'm solving a math problem style of
thinking and um you know I think you can
see in Von Holt's writings essentially
the same kind of distinction between
system 1 and system 2 cognition although
he refers to system one cognition as a
of the spirit um and system to cognition
as thinking um yeah and so basically he
argues for a version of the philos
philosophical position of the language
of thought of suggesting that effective
system to thinking um requires extension
of the Mind through the symbols of
language um and so he argued that having
language is absolutely a necessary
foundation for the progress of the human
mind and I think that's actually an
interesting perspective which I have
some sympathy with I mean you know
obviously we can think without language
you know we can feel afraid we can think
visually and about how things that fit
together but I think it's fairly
plausible that for the sort of more
abstract larger scale thinking that
humans engage in and has led them to
sort of higher levels of thought than a
chimpanzee gets to that language gives a
scaffolding Inside the Mind that makes
that possible another version of that um
is from the philosopher Daniel dennet
who just actually died a couple of
months ago um so dennet wrote this book
um called from bacteria to bark and back
and the main thing this book was about
was the origin of human consciousness
and I'm not going to talk about human
consciousness um today um but um he
introduced this model of four grades of
progressively more competent
intelligences um and so the four levels
um he outlined was that the bottom one
was dar wian so darwinian intelligence
was something that was predesigned and
fixed it doesn't improve during its
lifetime Improvement only happens um by
Evolution through genetic selection um
so things like bacteria and viruses are
darwinian
intelligences so then after that was
scaran
intelligences and so they improve
Behavior by learning to respond on to
reinforcement um so something like a
lizard um or you know perhaps a dog we
could um argue about how intelligent
dogs are um has um scaran intelligence
and so then the third level up um
paparian intelligence is things that
learn models of the environment so they
can improve performance by thinking
through plans and then executing them
and seeing how they behave so in a
computational
sense paparian intelligence kind of
means that you can do modelbased
reinforcement
learning um and so um primates like
chimpanzees can definitely um do the
kind of planning and modelbased um
reinforcement learning that gives you a
preparan intelligence but actually a lot
of recent evidence shows that a lot of
simp simpler creatures can also do it um
so I'm not sure the facts here so all
these studies you see are about um crows
from um the South Pacific Australia and
Fiji and places like that so I'm not
sure if Northern Hemisphere crows are
Dumber but at least southern hemisphere
crows um can learn plans so that they
can do multi-stage planning to work out
ways to get a piece of meat that's down
a Hole by learning to pick up a stick
and poke it in and um so you know that
even crows can be paparian intelligences
um but what Dennis suggests is that
there's a stage Beyond um paparian
intelligence which he calls Gregorian
intelligence and the idea of Gregorian
intelligence is that you can build
Thinking Tools which allow you to do a
higher level of control of mental
searches and So He suggests that you
know things like well mathematics is a
thinking tool but well also democracy is
a thinking tool but nevertheless out of
the space of Thinking Tools um that
human language is the preminent thinking
tool that we have and So He suggests
that you know the only biolog iCal
example we have of a Gregorian
intelligence um as human
beings and so that I I think in that
kind of sense you can say that there's a
very important role for
language okay two parts to go in my um
summary okay so the next one is what
kind of semantic should we use for
language um and so this is getting back
to the question I mentioned for word
vectors and this is kind of interesting
so the semantics that's been dominant in
philosophy of language or in linguistic
semantics is a notion of model theoretic
semantics where the meaning of words is
their
denotation what they represent in the
world I mentioned this I think in a
early lecture right so that if you have
a word like computer the meaning of
computer is the set of computers this
one that one that one all the other
computers are out right so it's
denotational relationship between a word
and its denotation in the world or in a
model of the world and that was the um
notion that was used in most of the
history of AI for doing symbolic Ai and
that then contrasts with this sort of
distributional semantics that the
meaning of a word is understanding the
context in which it's used which is
effectively what we're using um for our
neural
models yeah so if if you look at the
traditional view of understand
interpreting the meaning of human
language um and this is what you'll have
seen if you did an intro logic class at
some point right that we have a sentence
the red apple is on the table and you
get to write in some logical
representation first order predicate
calculus or whatever this one's a bit
different to allow in thus where
normally for first order predal calculus
you only do um for all and if there
exists but you have a a sort of a formal
logic and you know in the early week in
weeks one and two of the logic class you
have some English sentences for which
you translate into formal logic and then
after that um you forget about human
languages and you just sort of start
proving stuff about formal logical
systems um and so to some extent what
you get a philosophy class um represents
the tradition of Alfred tasi um so taski
believed that you couldn't talk about
meaning in terms of talking about human
languages because human languages were
quot quote impossibly
incoherent um yeah and so um from about
the sort of 1940s until um 1980 you know
tasy was the preeminent legis um in the
US um he was in Berkeley um and so that
was very much um the view of the
logicians of the world but during that
period one of his students um was this
guy Richard
montigue so um Richard montigue sort of
rebelled against that picture um saying
I reject the contention that an
important theoretical difference exists
between formal and natural languages and
so he then set about um showing that
well you could start building up a
formal semantics for describing the
meaning of natural language sentences
and so Richard monu's work became the
foundation of the work that's used in um
semantics in linguistics as well for
anyone who's done 1 Ling 130 or 230 um
the picture you saw is sort of a
montigue picture of um semantics and so
that was the semantics that
was um taken over and essentially used
as the model of doing natural language
understanding for most of the history of
NLP you know roughly 1960 to
2015 17 you know and so the picture
essentially was that if we wanted to
have a sentence that we interpreted like
the red apple is on the table what we
would do is we'd first produce a
syntactic structure for the sentence so
we would pause it um and then using
ideas roughly along the lines that
montue suggested we would construct its
meaning by looking up meanings of words
in a lexicon and then using the
compositionality of human languages to
work out the meanings of progressively
larger phrases and clauses in terms of
the meanings of those words and the way
that they are combined slightly
reminiscent of my discussion of tree
structures to meanings in the last
lecture I gave and so you would build up
um a meaning representation of a
sentence and so this could then give you
a semantic meaning of a sentence that
you could use in a system um this is
approximately a slide except titled that
I actually used to use in
cs224n um in the
2000s decade right so we have a we have
um or part of a sentence um I get oh no
it's a whole sentence here it is how
many red
cars what can I get this sentence I
think there's a sentence here how many
oh how many red cars in Palo Alo does
Kathy like how many red cars in pal does
Kathy like and sorry yeah the cars sorry
got hidden underneath here um yeah so we
have a sentence we pass it we look up
meanings of words in a lexicon we start
composing them up um we get a semantic
form for the whole sentence which we can
then convert into SQL and we can run
against a database and we can get the
answer and this was a in outline the
kind of technology that was widely used
for natural language understanding
systems that were built anywhere from
the 1960s to the 2s and1s and you know
in particular um they were used not only
in a purely kind of rule based grammar
and lexicon way this same basic
technology was incorporated into a
machine learning context where your goal
was to start to learn various of these
parts you could not only learn the paraa
but you could also um learn semantic
meanings of words and learn composition
rules and so the Acme of that work was
then what was called semantic paring
that was pioneered by Luke zettel moer
and Mike Collins in the 2000th decade
and then taken up by others including um
Percy leang so person's PhD thesis but
also actually his early work at Stanford
before he was convinced to do neural
networks um was doing semantic paing um
work um so you know these systems could
actually work and were used in limited
domains but they're always extremely
brittle um and yeah the interesting
thing is sort of what of humans I mean
there is you know some evidence that
humans do something like this that they
um work out the structure of sentences
and compute um meanings um in a a bottom
up mostly projective way you know
there's a lot of controversy to exactly
how human understanding of sentences
still works but you know there are
certainly people have argued in support
of human brains doing something similar
um that's obviously not what we're
getting with current day
Transformers and so you know the
question is do our current day
um neural language models provide
suitable meaning functions and that's
you know a complex question
CU you know in many ways yeah they seem
to they do an amazing job at
understanding whatever sentences you put
into them but there's still some genuine
concerns as to whether
they are making shortcuts or work to a
certain extent and don't actually have
the same kind of
compositional understanding with
systematic generalization that human
beings
do okay um so that's the traditional
denotational semantics View and that
contrasts um with the kind of use theory
of meaning and in the first or second
lecture and at the beginning of this one
I attributed that to the British
linguist Jr fth you shall know a word by
the company at kees but it's not only a
position of f it's also been a minority
position of philosophers in particular
it was Advanced by viken Stein and his
later work and his work philosophical
invest vation so in that work he writes
when I talk about language words
sentences Etc I must speak the language
of every day is this language somehow
too coarse and material for what we want
to say then how is another one to be
constructed and how strange that we
should be able to do anything at all
with the one we we have um philosophical
investigations is written in this sort
of vaguely poetical literary style but
the point of it is meant to be
saying look these logician people are
claiming you can't use natural langu
human languages to express meaning and
you have to translate into this um
symbol system but isn't that a weird
concept that one symbol system is no
good but this other symbol system
somehow fixes things um and then about
denotational semantics he writes you say
the point isn't the word but it's
meaning and you think of the meaning as
a thing of the same kind as the word
they also different from the word he the
word there the meaning so that's the
symbol and its denotation the money and
the cow that you can buy with it um but
contrast money in its use and he goes on
from there to argue for the kind of you
know the meaning of money is the way
that money can be used in the world the
meaning of money isn't pointing at
pieces of
money okay so this this is what's
referred to as a use theory of meaning
and so the question is is that a good
theory of meaning so some people just
don't accept
um this kind of distributional semantic
use theories of meaning um as a theory
of meaning or semantics most prominently
in recent NLP work that's the position
of Bender and cola that they just take
as axiomatic the only thing that counts
as having a meaning is that you got form
over here and meaning over there
um but I think that that's too narrow I
think we have to argue that meaning
arises from connect meaning of words
arises from connecting words to other
things and although in some sense you
could say connecting um words to things
in the real world is privileged it's not
the only way that you can ground
meanings you can have meanings in a
virtual world but you can also have
meanings by connecting one word to other
things in human language and the other
thing that I think you need to say is
you know meaning isn't a sort of a zero1
thing that you know the denotation of a
word or you don't I think meaning is a
gradient thing and you can understand
meanings of words and phrases either
more or less and so this is an example I
gave in a piece that I wrote a couple of
years ago okay what is the um meaning of
the word
Shai um
well maybe a few of you know it but um
if you don't well what could I do um
well you know if you'd seen or held one
you'd have classic grounded meaning um
know something about the denotation um
well if that's not the case well you
know I could at least show you picture
of one here's a picture of one so that
gives you some information about what a
Shai is but you know is that the only
thing I can do I mean
suppose well sorry I left out a bullet
point you know so this gives you a
partial meaning of a Shai but surely you
have a richer meaning if you'd heard one
being played um and well is showing you
a picture of one the only thing I can do
um suppose you'd never you know seen
felt or heard one but you know I told
you it's a traditional Indian instrument
a bit like an OBO well I think you
understand something about the meaning
of the word at that point um that you
know it's sort of connected to India
it's a wind instrument using reads
that's used for playing music you know I
could tell you some other things about
it I could say it has whole sort of like
a recorder but has multiple reads and a
flared end more like an OBO um then
maybe you know a bit more about a shenai
even though you've never seen one um and
um if you then extend to what we do more
in um our sort of Corpus based
linguistic learning you know you could
imagine it's not that I tried to Define
one for you instead I've just shown you
a textual use example so here or several
of those
so here's one textual use example from a
week before Shai players sat in bamboo
ma CH at the entrance to the house
playing their pipes bash Babu disliked
the Shai's whale but was determined to
fulfill every conventional expectation
the Grooms family might have um so if
that's all you know about a Shai you
know in some ways you understand less of
the mean meaning of the word than if
you'd seen one but actually in other
ways you understand more of the meaning
of the word than if you just seen one
because you know from that one textual
example you know some things you um have
heard a characterization of the sound as
wailing um and um you know that it's
connected with weddings which you don't
get from just having um held or looked
at one or even you know having had
someone stand in front of you and play
it and you know that's an important part
of the meaning of aai to um people and
so that's the sense in which I think so
meaning comes from various kinds of
connections okay last topic our AI
future um yeah so there are different
senses of our AI future and lots of
things um that can we can be worried
about one thing we can be worried about
is whether we're all going to lose our
jobs um interesting question uh here's a
newspaper article from The New York
Times March of the machine makes Idle
Hands prevalence of unemployment with
greatly increased industrial output
points to the influence of Labor saving
devices as an underlying cause um this
was published in the New York Times in
1928 um but you know it turns out that
quite quite a few people like labor
saving machines like washing machines
and dishwashers and um sewing machines
lots of useful labor saving machines um
and well you know this was published in
1928 just before um you know at a time
when a small group of immensely powerful
and rich men dominated the United States
um just before the Great Depression um
but what happened in the decades after
that um greatly changed policies in the
United States led to Boom years that
distributed um wealth and work much more
evenly across the country and the
country
boomed you know here's another one in
the past new Industries hired far more
people than those they put out of
business but this is this is not true of
many today's new Industries today's new
Industries have comparatively few jobs
for the unskilled or semiskilled just
the class of workers whose jobs are
being eliminated by automation you know
this was um Time magazine in
1961 um so this is a longstanding um
fear which at least so far has not been
realized you know here we are um in
which a country in which not everyone
might have the work that they wish they
had but that overall almost everybody
has a job and many people are working a
lot of hours a week whereas Once Upon a
Time the claim was that before the end
of the 20th century we would only have
to do a three-day work week because
there wouldn't be much work to go around
imagine um yeah so another fear is will
almost all the money go to 5 to 10
enormous technology Giants um I actually
think this is a more serious worry this
seems to be the direction that we're
headed in at the moment um I think
there's no doubt that modern networks
and a concentration of AI Talent tend to
encourage this outcome um just but you
know essentially this is the modern
analog of what happened in the early
Decades of the 20th century you know the
equivalent then was Transportation
networks and it was domination of the
new Transportation networks like
Railways that led to a few people
dominating the economic system um but
what happens there um would be you know
essentially comes down to a political
and social question so um as I was
mentioning before after the Great
Depression countes successfully dealt
with the monopolistic power of a small
number of companies um and with
political leadership we could do that
again um the problem is that there's not
much sign of political leadership right
at the moment um but that's um a
political problem to solve rather than
actually being a technological problem
to solve um so the next problem is
should we be afraid of an imminent
Singularity IE when machines have
artificial general intelligence beyond
the human level um in particular um
would such an event threaten human
survival um so this is um
uh concern that is increasingly um explo
exploded into the mainstream with
discussions of AI existential risk and
in quite a few of the discussions that
have been leading to the setting up of
things like AI safety institutes in the
US UK um are motivated by maybe um there
are these worries of out of control
artificial intelligence um taking over
and deciding to eliminate Humanity so we
get these sort of article headlines like
pausing AI developments isn't enough we
need to shut it all down how Rogue AIS
may arise AI Godfather Jeffrey Hinton
warns of dangers as he quits Google we
must slow down the race to Godlike AI
um I don't personally um give these
concerns too much credence um and I
think there's started to be increasing
push back against them um so in the
other direction um franois charal who is
the architect of caras sort of argues
there does not exist any AI model or
technique that could represent an
Extinction risk for Humanity not even if
you extrapolate capabilities far into
the future V scaling laws most arguments
boil down to this is a new type of
Technology it could happen
um Joel Pino who um meta AI leader um
refers to existential risk discour is
unhinged and points out the flaw of the
lot of the utilitarian argumentation
that goes along with discussions of
these risks which is um you know if you
say the elimination of um humanity is
infinitely bad that means you know any
any nonzero chance multiplied by
Infinity will be bigger than the Badness
of anything else that could happen in
the world um but that that isn't
actually a sensible way to have rational
discussion about the outcomes and many
people including Tim n jeu have argued
that a lot of
the well a lot of what the a lot of the
outcome of this focus on existential
risk and if you're more cynical a lot of
the purpose of this focus of on
existential risk is to distract away
from the immediate harms that are
arising from companies deploying
automated systems including their biases
worker exploitation copyright violation
disinformation growing concentration of
power and Regulatory capture by Leading
AI companies and that's something that
is worth you know thinking about that
behind all the discussions of our
amazing AIS and all the things we can do
with them like get our homework done or
generate wonderful images that there are
lots of things underneath about
disinformation deception um
hallucinations um problems of
homogeneity of decision making violation
of copyrights and people's creativity
lots of carbon emissions um erosion of
Rich human practices so we need to be
conscious of the sort of present day
harms that can come about from AI um and
for NLP as well there are various kinds
of harms that we've touched on which
include generating offensive content
generating untruthful content and
enabling disinformation so the
disinformation one is an interesting one
that if models can reason well about
texts can they also be persuasive in
communicating incorrect information or
opinions to users perhaps there are new
possibilities for doing very
personalized um misinformation
propagation that easily persuades human
beings better than traditional methods
of political advertising and there's
starting to be evidence that that's true
it's still being debated in the
literature but there's now multiple
studies suggesting that humans can be
influenced by disinformation generated
by AIS and it seems reasonable to think
that we're going to start to see more
use of that in political systems and
elsewhere which is potentially um quite
scary and you know perhaps the worst of
it isn't going to be text based it's
likely that visual
um fakes are going to be even more
compelling in political context and um
this sort of seems like whether it
happens in the US for this election or
in other countries in their election
that we're likely to see some major
incidents where um AI generated fakes
can be seen of having a major impacts on
political
systems so I sort of think really um
what we should be doing is worrying not
about existential risks but worrying
about what people and organizations with
power will use AI to do um that this is
a pattern that we've noticed multiple
times Al so with social media right in
the early days of social media there was
the idea that this was meant to lead to
new freedoms for people across the globe
bringing the positives of free political
um thought and improved human lives in
lar measure that isn't what's happened
that new technologies get captured by
powerful people and organizations who
Master the new technological options and
Ai and machine learning is being
increasingly used
um for surveillance and control and
we're seeing that around the world at
the
moment um so my final thought to end
with um is a thought about Carl San so
when I was young many decades ago um
Carl Sean did the series Cosmos on
television explaining the Miracles of
the universe and at the time when I was
a teenager I loved Cosmos now this was a
long time ago um so much more recently
there's now a new generation of Cosmos
and the book is advertised on the basis
of with a new forward by Neil degrass
Tyson um I think um K San was a good guy
um and he didn't only write Cosmos he
wrote a number of other books and
another of the books he wrote um was the
demon Haunted World um which has a theme
that's a little bit
um closer um to um some of the things
that connect with um what we're dealing
with here um so in that book um he
writes I have a for boing of a world in
my children's or grandchildren's time
when awesome technological powers are in
the hands of a very few and no one
representing the public interest can
even grasp the issues when the people
have lost the ability to set their own
agendas or knowledgeably question those
in Authority when clutching our crystals
and nervously Consulting our horoscopes
our critical faculties in Decline unable
to distinguish between what feels good
and what's true we slide almost without
noticing back into Superstition and
darkness um I think if you look around
the US and many other parts of the world
today um this is actually much more the
risk um that humanity is facing and why
um education which we try to provide at
Stanford and other places is an
important thing um that should be valued
and all the other things that go along
with this of having things like open
source that supports the broad
dissemination of
learning thank you
[Applause]