And hey uh it's great to see you here.
Um I'm Caillou and um I will talk about
former reasoning meets LMS towards AI
for mathematics and
verification. Okay. Um so we are now
kind of in a arm race of large language
models in which every leading company
releases a new model um in every a few
months. Um so at the center of this arm
race is mass and coding. For example
when open AI introduces 01 uh you
typically see this kind of uh charts
showing that its capability in various
on various benchmarks. Uh and you see um
the mass competition like AIM and coding
competition like code forces are usually
highlighted. And similarly when Google
released Gemini and when XAI released
Grock they also highlight the capability
in mass and
coding. And in uh November 19 in
November 2023 XTX Markets which is a
British hedge fund launched the A IMO
prize. That's $10 million for AI that
can win a gold medal in IMO. And not
long after that in July 2024 uh Google
deep mind announced that uh alpha proof
and alpha geometry have achieved the
silver medal level. I guess that's the
content of the last lecture. Um and if
you want to go beyond um high school
competition math, we have this um
applica AI, it introduced a benchmark
called Frontier Math. Um which includes
research level mathematical questions
that's curated by professional
mathematicians. Um, and not long after
that,
OpenAIO3 announced that it can solve u
more than 20% of that. And which came as
a surprise because when Frontier Mass
benchmark was released, people thought,
okay, this is going to be um it's going
to take a few years for language models
to make real progress. But uh really
after less than one year, we have uh
groundbreaking results from OpenAI.
So why are people interested in math and
coding? Um why are they often
highlighted? Um one reason is that math
and coding are proxies for uh complex
reasoning and planning and reasoning and
planning. They're not only important for
human intelligence, but they are also
one of the major challenges for current
language models. Um, and they can really
unlock unlimited applications if you can
make language models be able to reason
and be able to plan. For example, you
can have them uh do travel planning for
you and also uh have language model
agent scheduling calendar event uh
calendar invites for you. Um, and the
second reason that people are interested
in math and coding is they are
relatively easy to evaluate bas um for a
math problem. you can check the if the
answer is correct and for coding you can
run the unit test to see if they can
pass all the tests. Um but if you ask
your language model to write a like a
crime fiction or uh you ask it to
compose a symphony it's going to be much
much harder to evaluate. Um you can
argue
that like crime fiction also involve
reasoning and composing a symphony
definitely need planning. So they also
need reasoning and planning but they are
just not as easy to
evaluate. Um so I put it relatively easy
here because um that as we will come
back we don't think checking the answers
or running the unit test is a perfect
evaluation. We are just arguing that
it's a reasonable evaluation and uh we
will revisit this point later in the
rest of this lecture.
Uh okay so we know language models are
racing to be good as math and coding. Um
and next we want to briefly introduce
the main techniques behind them like how
do we train language models to solve
math problems. Um here we focus on math
but the discussion largely also applies
to coding as well. uh and we will see
later that math and coding are deeply
connected and state-of-the-art mass
language models are trained using mainly
two techniques. Uh one is supervised
finetuning or SFT and the other is
reinforced learning or RL and we're
going to present a very high level view
uh and emphasizing the need for data and
for uh
verifiability. Uh starting with SFT. So
in SFT you have a base model that's a
generic language model pre which trained
on internet scale data
sets and to learn mathematics you give
it additional data that's focused on
mathematics. So you can grab web pages
from mass overflow or you can have uh
papers from
archive and the result of this
fine-tuning uh is called the base mass
language model. Um well it's it has seen
a lot of mathematics but it still hasn't
yet learned how to solve problems. So
the next step is to uh give it a lot of
problems and with uh with detailed
step-by-step solutions for these
problems. Uh and optionally you uh in
the solution you can use external tools.
So here the model is trained to produce
not only natural language reasoning but
also uh it can call external tools like
Python. So this is this is an example of
a problem it can
solve. So the most important thing in
this pipeline uh as you can see is data
set.
uh you need data set for continue
pre-training that's the web documents uh
collected from web uh from the mass
forums like stack overflow and you also
have to uh to annotate a lot of data for
further fine-tuning uh consisting of
problems with step-by-step solutions and
uh I I would say um collecting this data
set is one of the most expensive part in
this pipeline because uh it cannot be
fully automated. You need human uh to
annotate the data to clean the data and
to uh to transform the data into into
the data set that can you can
use. So what if um our data set has only
the final answer but not the
intermediate steps. Um this is a
scenario where uh you don't want humans
to annotate uh data very expensively but
maybe uh you can more cheaply get the
data um that has only the final answer.
So can we still use this data set to
train the model and the answer is yes we
can use reinforcement learning to train
the model to generate solutions with
only the problem and the final answer.
Here's how it works. So you have the
problem and you give it to the uh
language model and the model generates a
solution that has uh intermediate steps
and that also has a final solution. Um
and you can check if the final solution
is correct. You you uh by comparing it
with the ground truth. So here it's a
correct uh it's a correct
solution uh and the model can also
generate incorrect solution and you can
check. So uh this the result of this
verification um can be used as reward
signal in reinforced learning and you
can use algorithms like GRPO to optimize
the model to achieve high rewards. Um
well you you can uh treat the reward for
a correct solution to be one and if it's
incorrect solution the reward is going
to be zero. So this approach is is very
simple approach and a very powerful
idea. Um it's actually the idea is there
for several decades uh but it was first
shown to work for uh for training
reasoning language models by deepseek R1
that's fairly recently and this idea is
getting uh a lot of momentum um just to
see how much momentum it has uh just one
month ago um two pioneers in
reinforcement learning Richard Sutton
and uh Andrew Bau uh won the ACM touring
award.
So here uh in reinforcement learning the
key is really uh the verifiability. So
you have to be able to verify the
results. You have to be able to tell if
the solution is correct or not.
Otherwise you don't have the reward. Um
so if the solution has a final answer
that's a number if it has a numerical
solution you you can always check by
comparing with the ground truth. But
what if it's a theorem proving problem?
So you are asked to generate a proof but
there's no really no auto uh well no no
no no easy way to tell if the proof is
correct or not. Can we still do
reinforcement learning? Um we will re
revisit this point in the later of this
part of this
talk. So here we have covered the main
techniques to train language models for
math uh supervised learning and
reinforce learning. Um I would say uh
any state-of-the-art uh mass language
models is uh kind of like a um it's a
combination of a very strong base model
and these two techniques for post
training and maybe more importantly uh
marvelous engineering efforts. So the
algorithms are very straightforward.
Pretty much every leading industry lab
is using the same algorithm. But what
what really matters is who has the
better infrastructure, better
engineering and the better data
set. So um then we will ask will AI soon
solve mathematics since we have this
very powerful recipe. Um and the answer
is definitely no. So we have a few gaps.
So the the first gap is how do we go
from pre college math to advanced math?
um existing successes um as we see
they're mostly limited on uh pre-ol math
like IMO or AM and if you give language
models more advanced mathematical
problems they still struggle so this
quote is from Terry to uh who is one of
the uh most prominent mathematicians um
nowadays and he said um he played with
open AI1 and he finds they still
struggle with the most advanced research
mathematical tasks. Um well this is kind
of uh expected because mathematical
research is by definition novel and but
since it's novel you don't have a lot of
data to train language
models and um also 01's O3's results on
frontier math as we mentioned before um
they are on advanced mathematical
problems but they comes with a few
caveats um well the first caveat is um
there are financial ties between uh
epoch AI and open AI that uh were later
uh disclosed but I would say more
importantly
um there's a difference between frontier
math and the real mathematical research
the problems in mathemat frontier math
are designed to have numerical solutions
so they are advanced they are very
advanced math but they are designed to
have a numerical solution so this is
kind of counterintuitive because uh we
we know most uh problems in advanced
math they don't have numerical solutions
uh but they designed the benchmark in
this way uh in order for the models to
be
evaluated and so this is related to an
the second gap um current models are
very good at guessing the answer but how
do we get it to write
proofs and and recent study has found
language models still strugg struggle in
writing even very basic proofs. Um so
putnam bench puten is the mathematical
competition for undergrads. Uh and uh
people recently tried using open AI's
reasoning model uh on putname and here's
the results. Um I'm very unimpressed by
chat GPT in the recent putnam exam. Um
and it can most answers are worth one or
two points out of 10 points. So this is
uh checked by human mathematician and
recently in another paper uh researchers
evaluated um language models proofs for
the USA
uh exam and they showed that all the
models scored uh around 5%. So which is
pretty
low and the errors those language models
are making can be they can be pretty
easy to spot once they you pointed them
out. Uh but if it's in a long proof it's
very hard to detect them. So here's the
example. Um we are asking the model to
prove a very simple
inequality. Um so if ABC satisfy some
condition and then there should be some
you have some results. And here it's
making an arrow. Uh when it tries to
multiply an existing inequality by a
positive number, uh it should preserve
the direction of the inequality, but it
flipped the direction. So that's that's
a very simple arrow if you point it out.
So
um we argue that current language models
the current approach for training
language models um is not sufficient for
solving these problems. Um because it
relies heavily on on data and on
verifiability and when you work with
advanced mathematics as we said you
don't have enough data. The data is very
scarce. Uh and when you work with
proofs, you don't have
verifiability. Um and in in the in
advanced mathematics, most problems
requires
proofs. So if language models are not
enough, what else do we
need? In a recent position paper we
released on archive, uh we argue that
one important missing point is uh formal
reasoning. Um here formal reasoning
means you uh you ground mathematical
reasoning in formal systems and formal
systems they can include like uh first
order logic, higher order logic,
dependent types theory or even computer
programs and their
semantics and the role of formal system
here is to try to verify the proofs and
provide automatic feedback on the
proofs. Um so this is very useful
because the feedback it provides can uh
mitigate data scarcity. You can have the
model learn from automatic feedback and
you don't need to collect as much human
created data. And second uh now you can
do verification which uh enable you to
evaluate the model rigorously.
So therefore we argue that uh to move
forward we really need to integrate
formal reasoning into the current
approach. So uh we're going to very
briefly introduce uh ling which which is
a kind of formal system we focus on in
this talk. Um and it it's also used in
alpha proof. So I guess people already
have some familiarity on link. Um so
here is a pro here's a programming link.
In this program you first define natural
numbers. So a natural number is either
zero or a successor of another natural
number. And then you define addition
between two natural numbers. So this is
just a recursive function. And then you
can state and prove some theorems about
natural numbers and addition. For
example, you can prove a a plus b equals
to b plus a.
And this here is only one file in ling.
And if you are using ling to write
formal mathematics, it's similar to
using Python or another programming
language to develop software. So you
have one file um and this file has a
proof uh and the proof is uh it has
semantics. So it you are starting it
corresponds to a proof tree. At the root
of this tree is the original theorem you
want to prove. Um, and every step in
this proof decomposes the proof goal
into uh several simple sub goals. And
you can do that recursively until all
the sub goals are solved. And this is
one file. And files are organized into
larger units like uh a project can can
have many files. Um, and the project can
be open sourced on GitHub. For example,
uh in your project, you can uh define
real numbers and someone else project
can build on your definitions of real
number and they can formulate for
example uh like optimization theory. So
this is similar to how you develop
software and one example of using AI
with ling is alpha proof. uh that's the
content of the last lecture and they uh
it's a it's a very successful example
and it uses ling to uh generate a lot of
theorems and uh a lot of proofs and use
and verify those proofs and do search
and reinforce learning to learn the
model. So in in the rest of this lecture
we will be talking about mainly two
tasks uh at the center of using ling uh
and AI. So first is theorem proving. Uh
in theorem proving your input is a
theorem statement and you want the model
to generate a proof. Here both the
statement and the proof are written
formally in ling uh and the link can
check if the proof is correct or not. So
there's no room for the model to
hallucinate. And the other task is auto
formalization. In auto formalization you
have the informal mathematics for
example from a textbook and you want to
use your model to translate it into
formal mathematics.
So uh next we will be first focusing on
theorem proving. Um a very
straightforward way to do theorem
proving is you just give the model what
you want to prove and you ask the model
to generate a step in the proof or you
can ask it to generate the entire proof
and um well because they if you if you
can generate the next step you can uh
kind of using search to chain steps
together into a complete proof. So uh I
would say um like the central problem
here is how do you generate the next
step
um and a very straightforward solution
is uh okay we have human written formal
proofs um and we can train a model to uh
to to do supervised learning on those
data so that the model can learn how to
generate the next step and this idea has
been uh actually here for um like for a
while uh and earlier work used classical
machine learning algorithms like uh K
nearest neighborhoods and around 2019
people have started to use uh deep
neuron networks for this task and even
later people are starting to use large
language models um and I would say um
until the use of large language models
uh we really see a boost in the
performance because the model can uh
acquire a lot of mathematical knowledge
during pre-training and use that
knowledge in theorem
proving. Um so we will be mainly talking
about this paper called uh Lindojo which
was published in new
2023. Um so well it in this paper we
provide uh open-source data sets tools
and models for theorem proving link. uh
and compared to previous approaches the
main difference is uh first we are
completely open uh previous approaches
are uh are private and they don't
release the data set and models uh and
they they were done uh in private labs
and second we propose a new model to uh
generate the next step in the proof so
here's an overview um so in ling uh we
can extract data from human written link
code. uh we extract about uh 10,000
theorems and proofs and for each proof
we have the steps in the proof and we
also have uh the the lamas used in the
proof and also the definitions of these
lamas and after extracting this data set
we use this data set to train a machine
learning model and once the model is
trained the model can interact with ling
to prove new theory and so here is the
model we introduced for This task it's
called uh retriever augmented prover or
reprover. Um the motivation is that when
you prove a theorem you almost never
start from scratch. You use existing
lamas. Um and in order to use existing
lamas the model have to know what lemas
are there and try to decide whether a
lamas is useful. So here given a proof
state that's the goal you want to prove
and also given a library of lamas. So we
we first do retrieval uh in this phase
we encode everything into vector. So the
state is is now a vector and each lama
becomes a vector. Uh and we compute the
similarity between the state and each
lama. Uh and we use the result to
retrieve the uh the top
lamas. And after the lamas are
retrieved, we combine the lamas with the
state and use another language model to
generate the next step.
Um so here uh the model is very simple
but the really important point is how do
you get the data set and uh as we said
in uh lin dojo you can extract the data
set from link uh like from l projects
like mass li and other limb
product. So here is a summary of a
typical
neurothe um so on the left you see a
tree. So that's the tree doing proof
search. You have a initial state and
your model can generate multiple
potential next steps and you can run
those steps which gives you the next
proof state and you can do that
repeatedly until you find a proof. Um so
for this part you can use any search
algorithm like uh DFS or moncology
search and the second part is uh how do
you generate the next step. So on the
right you see um at each node in this
proof the tree you have the current
state. So you give the current state to
the language model and it generates
suggestions for you. And here optionally
the language model can take uh a form
library which is the library of lamas
you can use.
And so after the lindogo work we've seen
uh a bunch of work trying to improve on
that. For example, one thing you could
do is um what we call expert iteration.
So which is
um so you have a prover even if it's not
very good you can use it to prove some
uh to attempt to prove some new theorems
and in this process you will get some
new proofs and once you get the new
proofs you can add them into your
training set. So now you have a better
training set and you can use the better
training set to train a better approver
and you can iterate. Uh so in in this
way uh we show that if you run for more
iteration the performance usually
improves until you uh you hit some
saturation
point. So uh we've seen a very simple
way to build a theorem proving model.
you just extract human written proofs
and you train a language model to
generate the next step in the proof. Um
okay, but we would say um it's it's a
great step but it comes with
limitations. So the first limitation is
um still data because language models
work well only if you have a lot of
training data and the amount of human
written proofs on the internet is very
limited compared to say Python
code and also another limitation is
inherit to the task of theorem proving
so if you think uh think about other
tasks that AI has been successful like
playing go. So what's the difference
between playing go and uh proving a
theorem? Um the main difference is in go
you have a 19 by9 board. So the possible
action you can take is uh is constrained
by the size of the board. It's finite.
But in mathematics um arguably you can
uh your action space is infinite. So
there's infinite number of thing you
could potentially do when proving a
theorem.
So since the action space is infinite,
it's really hard to cover this entire
space. Uh if you have only learn from
human created data sets and even if you
use reinforced learning, uh it's very
hard to explore the space efficiently
doing reinforcement learning. Um that's
a good question. So in in the work we've
been we've we have talked up to now, we
are just using supervised learning. Uh
so uh there's no curriculum involved.
But if you use reinforced learning, it's
natural to have the model first learn
from relatively simple examples and then
try to generalize. Uh and if you look at
more recent work in using reinforcement
for the improving uh one major
difficulty is how how do you choose um
examples to present to the model. So you
want examples to be not too easy but
also not too hard.
So um how do we solve the limitation
regarding the uh action space? Um so in
a more recent work we try to take a step
in that direction. Um but we choose a
very limited domain as a as a
playground. So we prove inequalities in
mass olympiate. Um so inequalities in
math Olympia is like you have a few uh
real numbers like ABC and they satisfy
some precondition and you want to prove
a post condition like this and we choose
this domain because the proofs in this
domain is highly regular. Uh so here is
what humans would do. Uh humans would do
typically two things. One is uh you uh
you can apply an existing lema like amgm
inequality or koshwas inequality and the
other thing people typically do is to
rewrite the current formula into into a
form so that an existing lama becomes
applicable. Uh but even with these two
kind of actions the action space is
still very big. uh for example for
proving this particular inequality uh
you can apply AMGM uh and AMGM can be
applied in more than one way. So you uh
you have more you have very big
branching factor and uh you can also
apply other inequality like the T2
inequality and you can also potentially
choose to uh rewrite the formula into
this form. So here the uh the action you
can take is essentially infinite. So uh
how do we navigate this um this kind of
infinite action space? So one thing we
do be uh before trying to solve the
problem is okay let's try to see how 01
solve this problem and we give a lot of
inequality problems to 01 and we
manually check their proofs. So as a
result um we find a lot of errors in
their uh in the O1 produced proofs um
and we checked 20 examples. Um 01
preview proved none of those examples.
Uh and the more powerful O3 and also
deep uh DeepSync R1 uh also only
improved three or four out of 20
examples. uh whereas a typical gold
medalist like a human gold medalist can
prove at least 15. So um then let's come
to our method. So as we said we
categorize the steps you can take in
this particular problem into two kinds.
Um first we call it scaling. um scaling
is you uh you apply an existing lama
like cautious watts to a part of the
current formula. So in this example uh
you find that the left part of the
formula um c can be can be used for
koshwats and which gives you the result
on the right hand
side. Um so what's special about scaling
is the number of scaling you can do is
finite. This is because okay you only
have a finite number of lamas and each
lama can be applied in only a finite
number of ways. So it's actually
possible to enumerate all the scalings u
all all the possible scalings in this
space. And uh besides scaling another
category is called rewriting. Uh
rewriting is you you are given a formula
and you want to trans transform the
current formula into another form. Um
and rewriting is very different from
scaling in the sense that the space is
infinite. So given any formula there are
infinite number of ways you can uh you
can rewrite it. Um so the key insight
here is that after we make this
categorization our algorithm can
enumerate all the possible scalings uh
using a symbolic algorithm whereas the
rewriting like the infinite space can be
handled by large language models.
So uh we combine the next step generated
by the symbolic algorithm with language
models and we use some heristics to
filter the results to reduce the number
of goals you have to improve search and
as a result um we solved a much
more problems compared to deepse R1 and
also uh also 03. So here on the top you
see our proved four theorems humans can
prove 15 whereas uh our system uh called
lips can prove 16 theorems and at the
bottom we evaluate our system with uh a
few benchmarks and compare with existing
method. So here's one example one
interesting example proof discovered by
our system. Um so here it's interesting
because it's from uh Ian Chen who is a
IMO coach for the team USA and uh he has
a problem set and uh he said uh this
problem has no hope to be solved by AMGM
but we find that the proof discovered by
our system uses only AMGM uh combined
with clever rewriting. Uh so it can
actually find proofs that humans do not
know how to find.
So here's a takeaway. Um the challenge
in theorem proving is uh how do you
efficiently explore a potentially
infinite action
space? And while this is a very hard
problem, but if you are working on a
specific domain of mathematics, you can
use domain insight to structure the
action space uh so that the action space
become more feasible.
But it is an open problem of uh like
whether you can generalize this approach
to be domain general. So after talking
about theorem proving um we will be
going to auto formalization and
uh like feel free to re uh to bring it
up any questions any time.
So in auto formalization we have
informal mass and we have formal mass
and we want the model to be able to
build a bridge between them like
translating from informal to
formal and here actually we have two
slightly different sub problems. First
is how do we auto formalize the theorem
statement um and second is how do we
auto formalize the proofs. uh in
statement auto formalization the model
only take the statement and prove the uh
and produce the statement in in link. Um
but in proof auto formalization the
model have uh the informal statement the
informal proof and also the formal
statement and it only produce the formal
proof. So these two sub problems have
different uh challenges. Let's talk
about statement formalization first. For
formalizing the statement, it's really
hard to do the
evaluation because for example uh here
the informal statement says there exists
an infinite number of primes and the
formal statement says for any natural
number n uh there exist a p that's uh
greater than or equal to n uh p is
prime. So, so this is obviously a
correctation of the informal system
because it implies the infinity. Uh, but
the problem is it's not the only
incorrect solution. So, if uh if we
produce this solution, we change p
greater than or equal to n to p strictly
greater than n. Um, well, essentially
it's the same. And we can even make it
more different. We can uh make n also a
prime. And for any human you can easily
see okay this three statements well they
are slightly different but they are
essentially the same thing. Um but this
creates a problem for machine learning.
So if the machine learning model
produces one of them how do you know if
it's equivalent to the ground truth?
uh you may want to say okay uh can I uh
like check the logical equivalence u but
the reality is this kind of uh checking
the equivalence between two theorem is
computationally invisible in
general and uh in practice researchers
have resorted to heristics or human
evaluation uh but if human if you rely
on human evaluation it's going to be
very expensive and not reproducible and
if you uh if you resort to proxy matrix
or heristics it's not going to be
accurate. So that's a challenge for
evaluating the auto formalized
statement. How about
proofs? Proofs we have another
challenge. Um human written proofs are
even if they are very rigorous they are
not rigorous enough to be formalized. Uh
they often have holes like one uh kind
of ho like mathematicians often say okay
this case is left to the reader. So if
if it's left to the reader, your model
has no way to figure it out from the
text. It has to figure it out by their
own. And there are more subtle holes in
the proof that we will cover later. But
in for the model to be able to auto
formalize the proof, it kind of have to
fill in all those kind of gaps which can
be very difficult. So we've covered two
key challenges in auto formalization.
For statement we don't have a reliable
automatic evaluation and for proofs um
the model have to fill in all the
reasoning gaps and in this project we
want to address both problems. So that
sounds very intractable but a lesson we
learned in this project is that um since
intractable in general can be made
tractable if you restrict to a very
specific domain and the domain we choose
is uklidian geometry um ukidian geometry
uh it's it's one of the oldest branches
of in mathematics uh and it has been
used to test human intelligence for more
than 2,000 years and recently it has
become like of a interested by the AI
community because of the alpha geometry
work where uh they have a AI that can
solve IMO level geometry.
So in this work we uh we show that
ukidian geometry is not only a good
domain for theorem proving it's also a
good domain for
automalization and more concretely we
collect a benchmark called ling uklit uh
in uklidian geometry it consists of 48
problems from uh Uklit elements book one
and more than 100 problems from uni geo
which is an an existing data set. So
let's look at one example in our data
set. So this is directly from uh UK
elements. It's proposition one from book
one. It's uh basically you have two
points A and B and you want to show that
it's possible to construct a equilateral
triangle. Uh so for each problem you
have the diagram and the informal
theorean statement and also the informal
proof. And when constructing the
benchmark, we try to manually formalize
this problem in link. So on the right
hand side is our formalization in link.
Um as you can see, it corresponds very
closely to the informal version like the
first step is you you draw a circle BCD
uh that's centered at A and uh the C B
should be on the circle. uh and the
second step is you draw another circle
and you try to find their intersection
and you connect everything u and then
that's a equilateral triangle. So there
are only uh like five or six steps in
the in the formal proof and each step
corresponds perfectly to uh to what's
what's being done in the informal proof.
Uh and we did this for all the 48
theorems and proofs in uh Uklid elements
book one. And this is aesthetically very
pleasing for me uh because um to the
best of our knowledge we are actually
the first to formalize uklid elements in
a proof assistance like link um and well
we we want to keep the proofs very
faithful in the sense that there's a
direct correspondence between formal and
informal and as we will see see later
this is not always uh
trivial and during In this process, we
find a few very interesting arrows in
UCL elements. Um, I think we can
probably go over one of those arrow just
to see how formalization can help you
check mathematical proofs rigorously and
uncover bugs in a proof that you may
think it's already very
rigorous. So, this is proposition 24
from Uklid's book one. Uh it says if you
have two triangle um and then um the two
triangles have two pairs pairs of edges
equal to each other. So AC equals to DF
and A equals to DE. So blue equals to
blue, red two equals to red. And the
angle A is bigger than angle D.
So uh you want to show that BC is
greater than EF. Um well this is doesn't
look very difficult and uh I'm going to
show the original proof by
Uklid. So first you try to move the
triangle from the left to overlap with
the triangle on the right. uh so C will
become
G and then you try to connect F and G.
So now the problem becomes uh proving EF
greater than EG.
Uh this is easier because EF and EG are
now in the same triangle and according
to a previously proved theorem in the
same book in in in the same triangle a
bigger angle corresponds to a bigger
edge. So you only have to
prove the relationship between these two
angles. You have you have to prove the
big angle here is indeed bigger than the
small angle. So how um just notice that
we have a isosilus triangle here. We
have dgf uh dg equals to df and by a
previously proved lama in an isocles
angle in an isocles triangle you have
two angles equal to each other. Um so
then you can you can argue that the
bigger angle is bigger than the uh DFG
because like uh it's a supererset of the
BFG uh and the DFG is equal to DGF and
the DGF is bigger than the smaller angle
then you have proved the bigger angle is
bigger than smaller angle. Okay so this
is very trivial but uh the proof is
actually wrong. Um, anyone knows why?
No. Okay. Um, well, well, technically
it's not wrong for this diagram, but
what if they look like this? Um, so let
me try to replay the proof. First, move
the triangle to the left from the left
to the right. Second, connect G and F.
Now, we want to prove uh EF greater than
EG.
uh and we want to use this associates
triangles alpha. So this alpha are equal
and we want to prove x greater than y uh
using alpha which does not work directly
because in the previous diagram alpha is
a part of x but now alpha is outside x
and y so you cannot use it as angle in
the middle anymore. So the original
argument break in this diagram um so how
do we fix this proof? But luckily it's
fixable otherwise we will we will
probably publish a bigger paper. Um so
um first notice that the angle bge
that's alpha + y it's a inner angle in a
triangle so it's smaller than pi. That's
trivial. And second 2 pi minus alpha
minus x that's df is also smaller than
pi. If you add these inequalities
together, alpha will cancel out and you
get x greater than y. Um, so it can be
fixed but as you see this proof is quite
different from UK proof. Uh, so that's
we why we think UK has made an error
here or technically it's not an error.
It's like this proof has two cases. This
these two cases are slightly different
and one case is more challenging than
the other but you uh
omitted the more challenging case and
focused on the easy
case. Okay. Uh maybe that's a very
interesting digression that's not
related to AI, but it showed um how AI
and link can make things more rigorous.
So let's go back to the to AI. Um so in
our benchmark we uh the first thing good
about it is it enables you to check
whether the auto formalized theorem
statement is correct. So here's how we
check if the statement is correct. We
have a ground truth and we want to check
if it's logically if the model generated
statement is logically equivalent to the
ground truth. Um so given two theorems
T1 and T2 we check it by proving T1
implies T2 and T2 also implies T1. And
here we use a automated reasoning tool
called SMTP solver. Um but if you
remember I said this is infeasible but
how it becomes feasible now and it turns
out now it's feasible because the
theorems in uklidian geometry takes a
particular form they are not general
theorems um so problems in tractable in
general can be made tractable in a
specific
domain and so that's how we check the
the statement another problem is uh auto
formalizing the proofs. So here in
uklidian geometry we want to show that
um we show that um there is a wellknown
kind of gaps in the proofs we call
diagrammatical reasoning gaps. Um I'm
going to show that using an example. So
proposition one from uclit elements book
one. Given two points a and b you can
construct a lit equilateral triangle.
Here is Uklit's proof. Uh draw a circle
centered at A and U B is on the circle.
Uh draw another circle centered at B. A
is on the circle. Take their
intersection C and connect everything.
You get a equilateral triangle. Um
anyone disagree with this proof? No.
Okay. Um the problem is did we prove C
actually exists? Uh did we prove these
two circles actually have an
intersection? Um we didn't. And actually
if you try to prove it because so this
is proposition one. So to uh to prove
this proposition you can only use the
axims. There's no existing lamas and you
if you try to use ukl a xims to try to
prove um these two circles intersect you
cannot prove it actually. Um so it's not
provable. Um but no one bothers to prove
it because it's just so obvious in the
diagram. it becomes a problem if I want
to translate this proof in ling. When I
formalize the proof in ling, ling does
not know what is the diagram or what is
obvious in the diagram. Um so I kind of
try have to formalize what is obvious in
the diagram. I I believe this uh I I was
in the in the zoom last in the last
lecture. I believe someone asked a
question about how do we formalize
ukidian geometry in ling. Uh I think
this is very closely related to that
question to formalize uklidian geometry
in ling the most important thing or one
of the most important thing is how do
you formalize the concept of being
obvious in the
diagram and luckily this uh this problem
has actually be solved before uh so this
is u work from uh Abigard who is a
professor in philosophy uh now in CM MU
um so agate essentially identified a set
of axims that's not in Uklit's axim
system it you can think of it as a like
a unspoken aim or hidden axim and so
what is being obvious in the diagram it
is just uh if a fact is a consequence of
those aim then it's obvious in the
diagram uh so now we have a
computational meaning of obviousness in
the diagram and we can implement a
automated reasoning algorithm to try to
derive things that are
obvious. So uh let me put everything
together. So in this work we have a
benchmark. So in the benchmark we have a
diagram we have informal math and we
have a ground truth formal statements
that's written by human. So now um we
use a model to do autoformalization. it
generates a formal theorem and we can
check whether it's equivalent to the
ground truth using SMT solvers to prove
that they imply each other. So after
checking the statement equivalence the
model can also do proof auto
formalization say it generates this
proof and we give this proof to Ling.
ling will identify a a set of holes in
the proof and we give those holes to the
to SMP solver which will tell us if the
holes are obvious in the diagram and if
everything works then we conclude okay
this is a correct formalization. So what
our benchmark really do here is we
provide um like a protocol that you can
use to rigorously evaluate
autoformalization and um so after
collecting this benchmark we also did
some very simple experiments um using
just GPT4 and the GPT4 vision and uh
here we don't train the model we just
give a few uh demonstration to the model
and ask it to autoformalize the theorem
statement
Um so blue here is GPD4 and green is
GP4V which also takes the diagram as
input and um so here are two takeaways
one is um if you look at the x-axxis you
is how many demonstration demonstrations
you give to the model so if you give the
model more demonstration is going to do
better uh but even if you give five
demonstrations or even more um the model
get only about 20% % which is pretty
low. Uh which shows autoformalization is
very challenging. And if you compare
green with blue, you see green is a
little bit better. Uh which shows if you
give the diagram to the model, um it it
has a stronger understanding of the
geometry
problem. And here are some takeaways. Um
we identified two challenges in
autoformmalization. For theorem
statement, you don't know how to
evaluate. uh for the proofs uh there are
too many holes in the human written
proofs and we address them by limiting
to a specific domain. So in this domain
we can build a equivalence checker to
for the statement and we can build a
tool that can fill in all the gaps. Um
but still the open problem is really how
do you generalize across uh a broader
set of mathematical domains. Um so now
we've covered both task auto
formalization and theorem proving u and
this is the end of this lecture and I'm
happy to take questions.