uh my name is Joe Sullivan I live right
down the street so I thought I could get
here in five minutes and parking here
was rough um when I got out of school I
went straight into the US Department of
Justice I became a federal
prosecutor um I went to law school
obviously and then um when I was a
federal prosecutor I got I I had the
really good fortune of becoming the
First Federal prosecutor in the United
States who was dedicated full-time to
doing cyber crime so people always ask
how did you get into cyber security
it was actually through the back door as
a lawyer um in 2002 I was living here in
San Jose and I moved over uh to uh work
at eBay uh if you know history 2000 to
2001 was like the docon boom so I was
working in the government not making any
money and everybody else was in the
companies and I thought I should go to a
company and then it crashed and I went
to a company um but I stayed at eBay
from 2002 to 20 8 uh I went over to the
PayPal side after a few years and during
that time I moved away from really being
a lawyer to being a security person or
practitioner I don't even know what we
call ourselves and in 2008 I went to
Facebook when it was here in Palo Alto
uh on University AV a small company and
I became the chief security officer
there and I built out security at
Facebook from five people to uh a really
big company I left in 5 I went to Uber I
built out the security team from five
people to really big company in 2018 I
went um to Cloud flare and built a
security team from five people to really
big company um so that's my expertise is
scaling security um but um if you look
at my resume you see some things in
there uh one is I do a lot of volunteer
work over in Ukraine um but you'll also
see that I I was on President Obama's
cyber Commission and I've spent a lot of
time working with government um not just
when I was with the government I've done
a lot of different volunteer things and
in
2025 it seems like there's a lot going
on
between Tech leaders and government I
don't know how much you've been reading
about our inauguration that's coming up
next week but I know a lot of people
from Silicon Valley who are going out to
the inauguration because there are a
bunch of tech leaders who are getting
very actively involved this isn't the
first time that uh the Obama
Administration did a lot and a lot of
the work that's going to be happening in
the future will be through that same
thing but today I want to like um kind
of focus on not like the tech side of
things as much as the collision between
the public and private sector that's
going on right now because I think it's
really fascinating and it's been going
on for 25 years and right now we we
you're lucky because you live in the in
a time of most incredible digital
transformation
I pulled up the top 11 companies in the
world a few weeks ago by market cap um
almost all of them are a in the United
States and B technology companies um and
so if you went 20 years ago it would be
like two tech companies on this top 11
list I made it 11 because the 11th one
was Tesla at the time and wanted to make
sure they were in there um so my
daughter works there um on the security
team um but let's what how is government
reacting to this they're getting really
uncomfortable because government like
when we like this isn't a political
science class but when you go back to
like what is the role of government in
society the role of government is
supposed to be to protect us and to do
the things like as a collective that we
can't do individually and when we look
at what's happened in Tech in the last
25 years like I've gone I've testified
before Congress twice on behalf once on
behalf of PayPal once on behalf of
Faceook Facebook and like here's the
cheat sheet I got it was one sentence we
don't need regulation it will stifle
Innovation and that Mantra has worked
really well except in a few areas um
like Congress has basically listened and
so we don't have a lot of laws around
cyber security
um but people are getting hurt on the
internet and things are all kinds of
things are happening that governments
don't like there feel like a loss of
control control of their job as the
protector of people uh I had an
interesting conversation with a guy who
was at um the
NSA about six months ago and we were
debating this topic and he said well you
don't want to move everything into the
priv from the private to the public
sector is this working that one's good
you need a second one okay okay but so
um we have this tension right now okay
get that sounds better much better
so we have this tension that's happening
right
now between the government and the
private sector but even NSA doesn't want
to just take over all of our Safety and
Security because what they said to me
was if we did we'd have to have access
to all the data that's in the hands of
all the companies and raise your hand if
you want that right so the NSA and the
enforcement agencies that are trying to
protect people are are on one side
companies are on the other side and uh
what we saw in 2023 was the Biden haris
Administration put out a new policy on
cyber security and they said we have to
rebalance the responsibility to defend
cyberspace by Shifting the burden away
from individuals like you away from
governments to the
corporations so what I want to show you
is how things are getting really tense
right now um because companies are just
charging ahead doing their Innovation at
the same time they're not really
thinking about the government that might
come after them them well they're
starting to think about the government
coming after them because I mean we saw
you know the SEC just sued Elon Musk I
think yesterday uh the sec's charged
coinbase they've been in a big fight the
FTC is investigating open AI there's
just like if you take if you take crypto
Ai and cyber security as three separate
Tech advaned areas right now the
conflicts that are going on between the
public and private sector are really
really intense so if you're going to
start a company you're going to work at
a company doing technology stuff you
can't just think about technology
anymore you have to think about
governments around the world and so uh
what's going on with that uh and then a
lot of people are like oh no we have a
new Republican Administration is that
going to change anything like are they
going to be more hands off at the bottom
like I think there's an argument in lots
of different directions um but I think
for the most part when it comes to these
three areas they're going to be Hands-On
they're probably going to get to a
better place in that
they're going to give us more bright
line rules so me as a person who's
worked at all these companies and done
cyber security what do I do now I spend
a lot of time mentoring security
Executives and I go into companies and I
help them with their cyber security um
I'm I'm working with two public
companies and a dozen private companies
right now on kind of like either
mentoring their leaders or developing
their security people so for like two
decades I would get calls all the time
Hey Joe uh
I'm nervous I'm going in for my
interview to become the head of security
at a company can you help me get ready
now I get the opposite I get Hey Joe
I've been asked to become the head of my
of security of my company I don't think
I want to do it uh because you see um
all these different enforcement actions
are happening so you know we have
multiple branches of government right we
have three uh we have the legislative
branch which is supposed to pass the
laws that if we had bright line laws we
would all follow them but in cyber
security and in crypto Etc they haven't
given us bright R rules yet and so the
companies are kind of fumbling around
and the people in the jobs are kind of
fumbling around and in the absence of
Regulation by Congress we have the
executive branch now the executive
branch is supposed to enforce the laws
but instead of just enforcing the laws
what are they doing they're looking at
the old laws and trying to figure out
how can I use them in these new cases
like can I take a a Securities Law from
a hundred years ago and apply it to
cyber security or AI or stuff like that
like if we were over at the law school
here that's the things they're talking
about constantly is is this this
technolog is moving so fast the law
hasn't cuffed up but from an enforcement
Authority standpoint they're like we
have to do something we have to hold the
companies accountable we have to push
them in the right direction so doing
these enforcement actions so I'm going
to take a little bit and tell you about
my Horror Story enforcement action
uh that was just kind of like a Prelude
to in 2017 I was the CSO at Uber in San
Francisco I was living here in pal Alto
commuting up there we had an office here
in pal Alto too but I was mostly in San
Francisco and I was responsible for
safety of riders and drivers fraud
physical security executive protection
for Travis kenic um and a bunch of other
stuff and one day in November of 2017 I
got this message and another message in
my inbox and this one says would
appreciate appreciate comment on your
ouster and the hacking incident and
here's the phone number of Eric newcomer
who is from Bloomberg you can feel free
to harass him if you want um because he
didn't I have no interest in in
protecting him
um but so he he wrote a story about me
that came out like I was on vacation
with my family and I found out basically
from him and from an email from the
company at the same time that I was
getting fired and that the company was
portraying me as having paid uh a hacker
to delete a bunch of data and history um
so what happened uh was uh I was up I
was up by Lake Tahoe I was with my
family we were there for vacation it was
it turned into a nightmare um and then
in 2020 the FBI put out this statement
announcing that they had arrested me my
daughter was at UT Austin moving in uh
for her freshman year and
the FBI did the statement in a press
conference and they didn't tell me and
they didn't actually arrest me so my so
my daughter gets a call from her best
friend being like I heard on NPR your
dad just got arrested by the FBI are you
okay my daughter's like
what I'm I'm at Cloud flare then I'm um
so it it's pandemic 2020 so I'm sitting
at my desk at home in Palo Alto working
in the middle of a meeting and then my
phone blows up because everybody heard I
got arrested well
I didn't get arrested I'm still waiting
for an apology from the FBI but I did
end up getting indicted um and I was
charged with two things and this is an
example of Regulation by enforcement by
the government I was charged with
obstruction of justice because they said
Uber should have told the government
about a security incident and our team's
view was like we we handled this whole
incident and I'll go into the details of
like what happened and what we did and
didn't do in terms of the government and
then the second thing was I was charged
with something called Mis prison of a
felony we'll go into that one too um I
didn't think I did anything wrong so I
went to trial this is a picture from my
trial because federal court here uh
Federal Federal cases are not allowed to
be recorded uh and so I had one of this
is a drawing that one of my daughters
did uh uh I have three daughters so my
but this is my daughter in the courtroom
that's me on the left I wore a mask the
whole trial the jury never ever saw my
face so you know more about me than jury
I also never spoke so you know a lot
more about me than the jury uh this was
the Chief privacy lawyer at uh
testifying named Candace and she
testified that um her team worked on the
incident with my team and her team was
responsible for telling the government
and they didn't tell the
government um she wasn't charged because
the lawyers never get charged I should
have stayed a lawyer
um um so let's talk let me talk you
through kind of like the experience of
the security and
when I was at PayPal in 2007 I think we
published the first ever what's called
responsible disclosure policy does
anybody know what a responsible
disclosure policy is if you do cyber
security research you really want to see
that from a company a responsible
disclosure policy says hey if you find a
vulnerability with regard to our service
and contact us we promise we won't
prosecute you or file a lawsuit against
you so security researchers people who
do bug bounties they love to see a
responsible disclosure policy in 20078
at PayPal I co-authored the first ever
corporate responsible disclosure policy
because we wanted to encourage people to
try and hack PayPal then when I got to
Facebook uh when I took over the
security team in 2009 we published a
responsible disclosure
policy then when I got to Uber in
2015 um in June I I started at the end
of April So within like a month plus we
rolled out a responsible disclosure
policy at Uber and so we basically said
if you find something bad come to us um
the second thing we did was we rolled
out a bug Bounty program have people
heard of bug Bounty programs they're
kind of like you hear a lot more about
them than responsible disclosure
policies because if you go back to
around 2010 there was this big backlash
from the research Community being like
wait a minute it's not enough that you
just don't sue us you should be paying
us because we're giving you information
to make you more secure and I believe
that and I and a lot of people do and
like the people at the kind of security
conferences I go to that's kind of their
philosophy so we launched our bug Bounty
program at Uber we actually uh when we
launched the responsible disclosure we
did what was called a private Bounty
program in 2015 Uber only had a couple
of security people when I got there so
uh I would tell everybody we had the
worst security of a $40 billion company
ever um and we were trying to make it
better really fast um so we didn't make
the program public public for a year
because we were afraid if we made it
public we would just be so swamped with
vulnerabilities um we we'd get
buried um so when I and in fact when I
was at Facebook we launched the third
ever bug Bounty program and most of the
team that was with me they uh either
went and started hacker one so the the
founders of hacker one worked for me at
Facebook and the rest of the team that
built the bug Bounty program at Facebook
moved over to Uber with me and launched
this program there so when I went to
Uber from Facebook 40 people came with
me uh and the general counsel sent me a
very nasty
letter general counsil of Facebook um so
here's the actual incident in 2016 I got
this email in my inbox personal email
and work it said I found a major
vulnerability in
Uber I sent it over to my team Rob
Fletcher who had actually gotten his job
at Uber through the responsible
disclosure program reporting stuff to us
it was his job to engage with
researchers he reached out and said hey
we prefer you go through hacker one but
send us the
details we worked with him this was from
the uh trial exhibits a lot of people
testified at the trial there was nothing
out of the ordinary about the way we did
the bug Bounty with these uh two guys
that were on the other side uh we
documented everything um I have a bunch
of detail in here that's probably not
important for you but when I talk to
like security Executives it's important
to know to show them that we follow all
the standard procedures that they would
follow and the trial testimony showed
that like my whole team worked really
closely with the communications team and
the legal team to handle the incident
because whenever you have a security
incident it's not just Engineers working
together you have to bring in the legal
folks and you have to bring in the
communications folk and we did this
whole thing and also my boss uh my
manager was Travis kalanick and so he
was in the loop because I I wouldn't do
anything uh without running by him on
stuff like that we even had a formal
policy said that said legal needs to
decide uh whether it's uh something you
tell the government about and in this
case legal said we don't need to tell
the government if you protected our
customers basically so what we did was
we had these two guys who were in this
bug Bounty situation with us but they
they were using proton mail they didn't
want to tell us their real identities so
what did we do um we tricked them into
telling us their real identities um
because that's what we do in cyber
security uh and my team was uh I think
literally the best in the world
uh there was another company that these
guys had contacted that was a subsidiary
of LinkedIn LinkedIn didn't know what to
do so they contacted the FBI the FBI
tried to find them and couldn't um and
so my team gives lessons on this to the
FBI um and and a lot of the people who
worked on this do a lot of outside
Consulting for the US government still
to this day including myself um and then
at the end of it we figured out who they
were they were two young guys uh
20-year-old and a 19-year-old 19y old
was up in Toronto and Brandon the
20-year-old he was living uh he had he
had extreme anxiety lives at Home in a
Trailer Park microphone I have a
question Yeah question okay on the prior
slide would you be able just to briefly
talk about
how
yeah yeah this is a 45 minute talk in
itself this in this slide it was an
investigation but we had these guys and
they they were really careful to always
use vpns and other mechanisms to
obfuscate themselves um but what we did
um was we we so in a lot of
Investigations like this people think
they're Anonymous on the internet
they're not really if you have a team
like mine because what we do is we just
try and engage in a lot of back and
forth with them and eventually they'll
expose an IP address or two then it
becomes a question of how do we
associate the IP address with a real
identity um in this case The Way We Were
A ble to get them to expose the IP
addresses was we sent them an NDA
agreement um using Adobe sign so our
theory was and typical in these
investigations we'll we'll try and do
like take them off of their preferred
means of communication because they
don't understand how the internet works
and one of the things we learned was
that um it's really hard and docu like
if you receive a docu sign or something
like that it's going to grab your origin
IP and some other things like that and
so we would always try and do things
like that we would always try and um
fake send money to them we would say let
we're going to send a test amount of
money so we we did we did test sending
of money and we did a bunch of different
kind of like overwhelming them over the
course of two weeks with lots of
different kind of things where they
might screw up they uh usually people
screw up around the cryptocurrency
Bitcoin stuff in this case it was the um
the the docu sign where we would
grabbing IP then we went and through
that I uh we realized that IP was being
used uh in a couple other contexts
related to some things and we had to put
some pressure on uh a guy overseas who
was running a ver VPS virtual private
server that people could rent out um and
then we knew who we knew the customer of
this liquid siga VPS service and we we s
actually liquid Sigma was the name of
the person and then we were able to uh
trace the money paid to liquid Sigma and
then we found out it was Brandon but so
it was um I've done a lot of
Investigations like that and they almost
always kind of end the same way with us
finding the person because sooner or
later they mess up unless they're uh a
government um and sometimes they mess up
too uh so 20-year-old Brandon's living
in his trailer uh with his mom never
comes out best friends with his dog gets
an email from us and it's not in the
name John Doe that he was using it was
hey Brandon
uh and we sent this to his regular email
because we we'd fully
like uh like we we knew all his emails
and everything um and so uh want to
reach out after the holidays on your
Bounty uh great catch blah blah blah
first with regards to the contract you
need to sign with your real names uh and
submit the paperwork through P hacker
one to do it the right way um we said
were you like you're running into issues
with StubHub Angie's List in mircat
because we wanted to know
them to know that we'd hacked their
servers from the outside and so we could
see that they had folders for several
different companies that they were
trying to get bounties from and and then
he said and then we finished it with we
have one we happen to have one of our
team members down in Florida right now
and he can meet with you tomorrow to get
the contract signed we had sent down to
Florida uh someone on my team who was a
top uh he had retired from the CIA as
their top
interrogator so he was there he was
waiting he um he interviewed Brandon and
then he sent me this like I think 8 page
um uh psychological profile of Brandon
uh tldr on Jan 3 2017 I spent 30 minutes
meeting with Brandon subject at his home
and he signed the research agreement he
stated defensive blah blah blah goes
into motivation and realities or the
titles of the next sections uh it's in
the public record if you want to find is
somewhere um so my team at the end of
the day we're like we've made sure our
customers data is protected it's a 19 to
20 year old kid we've educated them
about about bug bounties everything's
good if legal's okay not disclosing it
that's their call we actually wanted to
write a blog post about it and we were
planning to write a blog post
unfortunately in Spring of 2017 Uber
imploded and um that's another story
that's well documented but Travis the
CEO got forced out those of us who were
reporting to him became co-ceos so it
was co-ceo of uber for a few months
until we hired a new CEO who then fired
me and set me down the path of talking
about this um so here I am we go to
trial um it was a uh the government took
a really aggressive legal position in my
case they said that we don't have to
prove that Joe was responsible for the
decision not to tell the government
uh we don't the legal word is Nexus they
said we don't need a
Nexus uh so the at the time the legal
standard was there don't doesn't need to
be a Nexus so this has a lot of security
people freaked out because arguably
anybody could get in um trouble if their
company makes a decision uh and you
happen to have the title Chief security
officer so the interesting thing was the
jury went out to deliberate in my trial
and one of the jurors sent back this
lesson uh this note she said with regard
to 10:30 a2c does Uber legally have the
right to extend authorization after the
access occurred you're probably like
scratching your head what are you
talking about here what what's the point
of this question so for me to be charged
with something called Mis prison of a
felony um they government had to prove
that someone committed a felony and then
essentially I helped cover it up and so
the government's view was when Brandon
and vasil hacked into Uber you know went
into our AWS and and downloaded proof
that they went into our
AWS them doing that was a felony
and then me letting Uber enter into an
NDA with them was helping cover it up
and so the government said all we have
to do to prove uh that Joe is guilty is
those two things we were
arguing what this question asked spot
on um if you have if you if you access
my computer that's a violation of law
10:30 is the federal 18 USC 10:30 is the
don't hack someone else computer and
then there are varying levels of
significance underneath that and um what
our argument has been and what all the
bug Bounty companies and everybody takes
has always been is that if you act if
the company can give permission after
the fact like that's the way bug
bounties work every time someone finds a
vulnerability at my company and they
report it to me they haven't gone and
clicked through the legal ease of the
bug Bounty program until they went to go
ask us to pay them when they were
hacking away they didn't think about
that so I've seen hundreds of cases and
I've talked to people at hacker one and
Bug crowd the big platforms and they've
seen thousands of cases where the
companies take this point of view the
government now disagrees with that and
so they took the view that
um uh no Uber can't bring someone into
their bug Bounty program if they've
accessed the environment without
position permission the felony happened
the second that the environment was
accessed jury heard that they went back
and deliberate it for not very much
longer then came back and said Joe's
guilty of both so I was convicted in
October of 2022 of two felonies
obstruction of justice and Miss prison
of a
felony
um I went into the worst Funk actually
the second worst Funk of my life the
first was when I got fired in 2017 um
but this was just like I was just in the
a really bad place because I was like
really um I had been working at Cloud
flare we had taken the company public I
I love doing cyber security and I was
like now I'm a convicted well I'm not
you know I wasn't quite a convicted
felon because as we learned with
President Trump getting sentenced last
week you're not actually a felon until
you're sentenced which is why he didn't
want to get sentenced last Friday
because you can't now you can call him a
felon you couldn't last Thursday um
that's a little Nuance of like people
are like why was he fighting so hard to
postpone the sentencing hearing even
though the sentence was going to be
nothing because he by not having being
been sentenced he could he wasn't a
felon now he's a felon I at this at this
point I wasn't actually a felon but I
was basically a person that no one
wanted to be associated with Cloud Flair
as a public company can't have me as
their CSO as a as someone who's been
convicted of something like this so I
had to I had to step down um that said
Matthew the
CEO personally paid for a pardon
application for me that was submitted uh
last fall um not granted uh the
Department of Justice tabled it uh
because they don't get along with me um
so I was in this Major Funk at the end
of 2022 and I didn't know what to do
with my life and I I realized um that I
needed to get up and and get motivated
so what I did was I went to Ukraine um
and so I'm the CEO CEO now of a
nonprofit uh we get um companies mostly
us companies to donate their used
laptops we bring them over and I set up
kids in Ukraine uh half the kids in
Ukraine are in remote school to this day
like they were in remote school because
of the pandemic and then just as the
pandemic ended their country got invaded
and all the kids from the eastern half
of the country move to the west or out
of the country and so um and you it's
not like you can go to apple.com and
order a computer ship to ke you can't uh
like none of the big shipping services
will SI there and stuff like that so I
go there a lot I'll be there first week
of February again um every one of our
laptops we put this sticker on this is
an English translation of the Ukrainian
but it's basically mental health
guidance for kids living in a war zone
and it's my favorite thing I do if
you're ever in a situation where you
feel like you're feeling sorry for
yourself and things are kind of crappy
the best thing you can do is go help
someone who's in a worse place and all
of a sudden like my problems are nothing
compared to what these kids have to deal
with so I'm going to Ukraine and hanging
out at home moping around and I'm
scheduled for sentencing in May of
2023 all of a sudden I started getting
letters in my inbox people I had known
and worked with over the years over the
decades uh wrote letters to the judge
asking for lenience on my behalf and the
whole cyber security Community actually
got up in arm py um John sakota from uh
who runs a VC uh around here John
actually got a letter signed by 60
people uh another group a woman I know
who's a lawyer at the ACLU got another
60 people to sign a letter and then
there were 186 letters written by
individuals there were actually hundreds
more letters but a lot of them didn't
have any substance and and my lawyers
had said like can we only give the judge
like 25 best letters and I said no we
have to give them a lot more and so we
did what we call insecurity a Dos denial
service attack on the judge and we gave
him 186 letters um to his credit the
judge read every single one of them and
then we had my sentencing hearing in May
of 2023 the government the Department of
Justice was arguing that I should get
three years in prison if they got their
way I'd be in prison right now um and
the um us probation office read all the
letters and stuff and they said no And
they're they're the they're kind of like
the US probation office works for the
judge and they prepare a report and
recommendation like they do like a
background check of my whole life and
everything thing uh my probation report
is scary um and not because I'm a scary
person but just the level of detail
um and they recommended that I not go to
jail at all and so then the government
at the hearing realized if they came in
and asked for 36 months they would have
no cred with the judge so they asked for
uh 15 months so they were arguing very
aggressively for 15 months in prison
which I due to the delay and stuff I'd
still be in prison now um and thankfully
the judge uh first thing the judge said
he
said it wasn't a cover up I was just
like oh my God thank God someone was
paying attention during this trial um
but the judge said it's never you know
and and it kills me because it's never
been in the new like you know I've been
in the New York Times for this case a
hundred times and hundred other media
outlets and it all says that I did a
cover up but the judge said I didn't do
a cover up and he's the one who knows um
and then he said to the government why
isn't the CEO here where's Mr kalanick
um and then last he said based on my
good character and the circumstances I'm
going to give you probation and I expect
you to go out and do things like you
were doing in Ukraine the rest of your
life so I landed on my feet I'm lucky
these are 12 companies that I advise and
work with right now um so I I have a
security consulting company Joe suvan
security I advise uh I think three of
these are AI companies in the security
space um and stuff like that and so I'm
back to doing security and and my
nonprofit stuff but I also do a lot of
public speaking like um last November I
keynoted the largest cyber security
conference in Australia 6,000 people
uh Denmark in October for deoe the
largest cyber security conference in
Norway in August I only go to cool
places for conferences that's my
strategy but and I have to talk to
Security leaders about this world we're
living in so to go back to the table
setting that I was talking about at the
beginning it's a really hard place and
time to be a cyber security leader so
each leader has to think about do I want
this job if I if I take this job am I
ready to go through the rig roll that
Joe had to go through how do I get
myself stronger and better how do I get
my team ready for these incidents how do
I partner better with the legal team
than Joe's team did how do I make that
my CEO when a new CEO and general
councel come in they don't throw me
under the bus um and I do a lot of
advocacy this was an article I wrote um
last year I I I called it the CEO as
next because um every security leader
when they hear about my sentencing
hearing they're like I need my CEO to
know that the judge said where's the
CEO um uh Jen easterly who's the head of
cisa which is the uh cyber security
agency in the US Department of Homeland
Security the main cyber security agency
for kind of defending the US um she put
out an article last Friday that could
have been titled the CEO is next she
basically I was very happy I because
I've been saying this over and over
again we need to move responsibility
so that's the kind of world we live in
right now on cyber security in my case
there was I'll share with you there was
actually a really interesting twist last
summer anybody heard about the January
6th case this was it was this one where
these people in in 2020 way back in 2020
broke into Congress why did they go into
Congress because there was going to be a
government action of accepting the
vote and so all the people on the
January 6th case they got charged with
obstruction of justice the same thing as
me because they were trying to stop the
government vote that case went all the
way to the Supreme Court last summer and
standing in front of the Supreme Court
one of the Supreme Court Justices said
it's basically government you've been
really wishy-washy about this whole
concept of
Nexus isn't it true that you always
should have to prove Nexus and the
Department of Justice said yes we always
have to prove Nexus and so I'm sitting
at home and I'm reading an article about
that hearing and I'm like they're
literally still so I have appealed my
case to uh the ninth Circ so the way it
works is you have a district court and
then you have this a court of appeal and
then the Supreme Court in the federal
system so I'm half I'm halfway to the
Supreme Court right now in my case
because I'm appealing and I was arguing
the government like we shouldn't have a
law that says no Nexus the law should be
Nexus and so that was my argument and
the government filed a you know 30-page
brief saying we don't need to prove
Nexus and then two weeks later in front
of the Supreme Court they said yes we
agree we always have to prove Nexus and
so I'm like wait a minute I'm entitled
to an automatic redo like in my lawyer's
eyes I'm entitled to an automatic redo
of the whole trial because the jury was
basically said you know you only have to
prove this to convict Joe the reality is
you have to prove this you have to prove
that I intentionally in working on that
investigation was trying to stifle the
government and that obviously wasn't the
case so now um the Department of Justice
has has backed off in my case and I
think we have a decent chance on the
appeal now uh but it's going to take
more years the frustrating part is the
government won't like they they
acknowledged in writing we screwed up we
do need Nexus but they said it was what
they call a less error in Joe's case so
um but the bottom line is I'm not in
jail I'm I'm doing what I love to do and
uh so I'll take
that
and thank you thank you um and in a
weird way I've become this advocate for
a lot of people in the cyber security
industry one on the bug Bounty stuff
because I I've always thought that's
important but even more there are a lot
of good leaders of cyber security teams
across like every company inica not
every company has a good cyber security
leader as we've seen some of the
healthcare companies have really
struggled um but a lot of the best
people are retiring or opting not to go
into leadership in this profession right
now because we live in this world of
Regulation by enforcement so I'll be
I'll be in DC next week I'm not going
for the inauguration with all
the CEOs I'm going later in the week
because I want to try and push this
Administration uh the new administ ation
to like look at this stuff because like
my case is basically over I'm good um
but I think one of my core jobs and
missions going forward is to keep
pushing on this stuff um and so it's a
um I think my story is a is it is a you
know it's it's a data point in this kind
of like bigger conflict and tension
that's going on between government and
Silicon Valley it's been going on for a
long time I you know I lived through and
was on the front line of like fighting
with the NSA over the Snowden
Revelations I could go I could tell you
like 50 different stories about you know
the the tensions between government and
private sector but I could also tell you
awesome stories about you know doing
cyber crime training for law enforcement
like even after I was charged and I was
still working at Cloud
flare I would like have a meeting in the
morning where I would be working with
the FBI and sisa on a you like like say
like the log for J vulnerability issue
was a big one that I spent a bunch of
time working with the government on it's
like in the morning I'm on zooms with
the FBI and everybody working on that
and in the afternoon I'm on zooms with
the Department of Justice and the FBI
where they're trying to put me in jail
so I I I've I've seen government from
all the different angles from inside the
corporation from the defense seat as a
prosecutor as part of the Obama
Administration and so on so um I think
as a country we have a long way to go on
regulation of cyber security and Ai and
crypto and it's interesting because all
of our companies like at the top level
our policy teams are are instructed to
go say we don't need regulation because
regulation is views as causing friction
but the lack of Regulation is also
causing friction and so it's it's
leading to a lot of people like
rethinking about the fact that we don't
have enough good technologists inside
government developing policy on these
things so um for those of you um you
know when I go to Europe and like have
to deal with government agencies the
people sitting across from me are often
engineers and people from universities
working part-time uh when I go to deal
with the government in the United States
it's lawyers whose eyes glaze over when
you start talking about an IP address
and so we actually I think need a lot
more good talented technical people
willing to spend some time in government
uh I'm not I'm not here to Advocate
running away from government I I think
we need to like make government our own
and I think it's really going to be an
important part of the next 203 yeah like
your whole career in technology so much
will be shaped not just by what you
build but the environment you're allowed
to build in