hi okay let me get started for today uh
I guess I'm now down to the the more
select week eight audience of people who
actually want to learn so uh my welcome
and my pleasure for the people who show
up today thank you thank you um okay so
what I want to do today um is Prince
ibly sort of talk about a couple of
other newal network techniques which can
be used for language I mean in some
sense um these two techniques are G ones
that people aren't using very much these
days and that's partly why they get sort
of stuck towards the end of the course
um because we try to teach people early
on in the course um the most essential
things that you should definitely know
about um but you know um the fact of the
matter is you know in any scientific
field there are different ideas and
techniques that bounce around and it's
good to know a few of the different
ideas that are out there because often
what happens is people find new ways to
reinvent things um and put things
together and see different insides from
them so today I'm going to tell you a
little bit about using convolutional new
networks for language Edge and then a
bit about tree recursive neural
networks um but before that um just
course organization um this is a a bit
after it happened but I guess I've never
been back to say it so thanks to
everyone who filled in the mid quarter
surveys um some people said very nice
things about the lecture fantastic
lectures and really interesting content
um some people uh wished that we were
teaching more about State space models I
guess we haven't added those that
lecture in yet um um a couple of people
thought it' be good to have an exam in
this class clearly they weren't people
who have friends in cs231n from what
I've heard but um um yeah uh and then um
in general people are pretty happy how
Ed has been going uh a bit less happy on
how office hours have been going I mean
honestly it's a hard problem I feel to
do office hours you know some people are
saying oh you should just use Q status I
sort of remember badly to a year where
we did everything but Q status and near
the assignments due date the the C would
stretch six hours long and that didn't
seem such a good solution either um but
we'll work along with it um finally yeah
on on cloud compute I know this is
something that people variously do have
issues with so um there are quite a few
people that still trying to do things
with Google collab um which I realize is
sort of a very convenient nice interface
but you sort of do suffer from access to
gpus um on Google collab the best way to
get better access to gpus is to pay 10
bucks for a month of collab Pro um which
perhaps means that you end up paying for
two months um for if it's May and June
um we can't reimburse you for that um
but not so many copies worth of money
and it does just give you better access
to gpus I'm encourage you to use the gcp
credits and together AP API access that
we've given to you um you're also
welcome to try other things kaggle
notebooks can actually give you be
better GPU access but um not as not all
the nice features of collabs um some
groups have started using modal which is
can also be um a good way to get GPU
access okay that was the intro to that
um and so now I wanted to just sort of
talk about convolutional new networks um
for language I mean these slides are
sort of positioned a bit as
convolutional new networks versus rnns
as opposed to versus Transformers I mean
that's um partly you could say because I
haven't updated my slides enough but in
another sense that's partly because
that's how the ideas of convolutional
neural networks really were explored it
was in the days when most people were
using recursive neural networks for NLP
a few people said about saying hey maybe
we should use convolutional newal
networks for language as well um whereas
in truth in The Last 5 Years when
Transformers have dominated there hasn't
been much use of convolutional neural
networks for NLP um so if we think back
to our new networks um if you remember
those that they kind of gave a way of
giving a
representation um for a sentence or part
of a sentence but they sort of computed
forward through the string um and so you
kind of had to get a representation that
included in everything that came before
you and then you so um you didn't really
have a representation of the ceremony
you had a representation of man walked
into the ceremony that you could
use um so in contrast to that
convolutional neural networks basically
say well you know kind of like an engr
model that we should be able to take
engrams of words like two G or three G
so for the example tentative deal reach
to keep the government open that we can
take each Three G tentative deal reach
deal reach to reach to keep keep
government and we can make uh some
neural representation for each of those
so notice just being done for every um
engram for a certain end so there's
nothing linguistically or cognitively
especially plausible here um but we're
just going to sort of form
representations of multi-word units
which will'll then group in some form
further way later on and the standard
way of doing that is with convol
convolutional neural networks um so the
classic case of convolutional neuron
networks is in Vision um the
convolutional neuron networks were
invented for vision where they gave you
a kind of a translation
invariant um model so that you could
recognize your kangaroo no matter where
in the frame it was and so this little
picture here which I'll just do the
lower half side of SL lower half of the
slide is sort of the what a
convolutional new network is doing in 2D
video
so the convolution is like a mask that
you're sliding over the image and the
mask is defined by weights which are the
little things shown in red and so for
each place you slide your masks to
you're then calculating a score by
taking well what's effectively a DOT
product of the Mask terms by the
elements in that patch and that's then
filling in The Matrix on the right um
that's shown in pink and so that's then
calculating our convolved feature um
from the image uh that make
sense yeah so well what happens if we
then want to do that for language well
you know for language we don't have a 2d
picture we've got a 1D picture we've got
a sequence of words so we can have
tentative deal reach to keep government
open so each of our words will have a
word Vector I'm using four-dimensional
in my examples to keep it compact on my
slide and so then we can apply um a
filter that applies to an engr so this
is going to be a filter for trigram and
so then we're going to slide that
downwards in the exactly the same way as
for the vision case apart from we're
just sliding in one dimension so I
calculate um the dot product of the
filter and this three G and that gives
me a value minus one if I did my
arithmetic right then I slide it down to
the next position and work it out and I
get minus
0.5 um slide it down get the other
values and then typically I can add on a
bias term so my bias is plus one in this
example and then I'll stick it through a
nonlinearity like a sigmoid or something
like that and so I'll be calculating a
vector for a term for each um of these
three GRS and so that is a convolution
for a single filter um and then commonly
what I'm doing after that is deciding
that I'm going to have more than one
filter and I'll show that in a minute um
in this example um and in my vision
example earlier we sort of had shrinkage
because we started off with seven words
but course we sort of slid these
um you know trigram over it we only sort
of had space for um five trigrams and so
we ended up with something smaller than
our input sentence often people want to
keep it the same size and the way you
can keep it the same size is by having
padding so if I put a a zero padding at
each end well now I'm going to get seven
trigrams coming out as corresponding to
my original seven words and normally
I'll just sort of pad it with zeros like
that um you can actually increase the
size of things because if you add um
padding of two at each end you can then
have a wide convolution and so seven
will then go to nine different
things okay so if we only had one filter
things are pretty limiting and so
commonly as in the vision case what
we're going to do is um Define multiple
filters and then we're going to be
calculating a value for each of these
filters over each of these triag and so
then we're getting out a new
representation as a vector and you know
depending on how many filters we have
relative to what the word dimensionality
is we might end up with something that's
shorter as in this example the same
length or actually longer than what our
input was in terms of word vectors
um but commonly um when we do that um we
then in some way want to summarize all
of these filters and the most common way
of doing that is to do something that's
called Max pooling and Max pooling is
something you see quite a bit in newal
networks in general and the way to think
of Max pooling that I think makes sense
is that you can think of um max pooling
is doing what you want if you R want to
run something that's like a feature
detector so you know if you imagine that
you'd you learn these functions um that
will look at word vectors and that they
will look for evidence of something
particular so you know maybe this filter
looks for the person is using I language
that it's matches the words I my we our
something like this and you know maybe
this is a filter that matches you know
speech verbs like or thinking verbs like
think say um said told Etc like that um
and so each of these is sort of some
kind of feature of the text that you
might want to detect well if that's your
model of it when you sort of slide your
feature detector down the piece of text
you sort of want to know does this match
anywhere in this piece of text is
somewhere at using an i word regardless
of whether it's in the first second
third or fourth position and so that's
effectively what you're getting out with
Max pooling that a feature is counting
as firing to the extent that it fires
strongly in any position in the text
that you could match um that's not the
only way you can think of doing it an
alternative way you could do it is you
could think of your featured tector as
sort of measuring some quality of the
text like um casualness or learnedness
or something like that and then you
might think oh well for overall wanting
to know how casual the text is maybe I
want to know the average of how casual
it is in different parts of the text and
so then you can do the alternative of
average pooling and sometimes people do
that as well you can do both you can
both work out an average pull and a Max
pull and put both of them into the
feature detector in general for the kind
of features people learn in your
networks if you're just doing one or the
other the result does seem to be that
Max pooling is the most effective that
that kind of does the feature fire
metaphor tends in general um to be um
the best way of thinking about
things okay so if you want to do all of
this in pytorch um con 1D right so um
that guess the one-dimensional
convolutions aren't the most common case
and so you're using com 1D and all these
kind of things that you can then be
specifying so the output channels is the
number of filters you have the kernel
size is saying the size is how big it is
which for my example was three um and
then you can sort of just collapse
things with the max
pulling okay um there's a space of other
things that you can also do with
convolutional newal networks which I
think are sort of less useful and less
used and language cases but I can sort
of say them quickly so one thing you can
do um is sort of have a stride CU When
we sort of did every
trigram of sort of zero tentative deal
then tentative deal reach then deal
reach 2 you could feel like well they're
overlapping each other a lot so they've
actually got very similar stuff in them
and that would be even more so if we
weren't using 3 G we were using
something like five G so something that
you can do is the stride is sort of how
much you move along so if you move along
two you'd have one trigram that's um
padding tentative deal and then the next
one would then be deal reach two and
then the next one would be to keep
government so that they're overlapping
by less as you go through it um
another thing that you can then do um
that's sort of stride like is rather
than um doing Max pulling over the
entire thing you could do more of a
local Max pull so um you could think
that well I want to have this feature
detector for something like use of eye
language but you know if it's a big long
sentence and there's eye language at
four different points points maybe you
should get four points for that rather
than just sort of the one point that
you're going to get from Max pulling so
you could sort of do local Max pulling
sensitive to the stride so here I could
look at the first two of these and Max
pull those two then the next two and Max
pull those the next two and Max pull
those and the next pull two and Max pull
those and you could sort of then end up
with this sort of local Max pooling as
you go along
um okay um and then one other idea
that's sort of related um that you can
um do is well another way of capturing
sort of does something match in multiple
places is rather than only keeping the
One Max in each column maybe you could
just do a k Max so you could keep the
two maximum things in a column and that
might be also be a way of seeing whether
something
is detected in two places or
not um okay um then I've got lots of
Notions here okay so um
dilation is then the notion um that what
we'd like to do is sort of form our
trigrams not only as adjacent things but
things that are spaced out so after
having done our first layer of
convolutional filters that took trigrams
that got us to the sort of top right
part here we could then do a dilated
trigram convolution which means that
we're going to take the first third and
fifth things and um combine them in a
convolutional filter and then we'll take
the second fourth and six things and
combine them in a um convolutional
filter and so we've then got a trigram
filter but it sort of has a bigger range
of size that it can see um and that's
sometimes used more commonly used in
places like speech than a natural
language okay so those are the kind of
tools we have um for calculating things
with these convolutions over text and so
next what I want to do you do is tell
you about a a couple of pieces of work
that made use of convolutions natural
language
processing I guess this is a decade old
now because this is from
2014 um this is um the single most
famous piece of work that made use of
convolutional neural networks for
natural language processing um and Yun
Kim is now an assistant professor at MIT
I mean in retrospect it's sort of
actually pretty simple um but I guess
you know he got in early with the idea
of okay maybe um we could use
convolutions um for NLP and did a kind
of a clear example of that that worked
pretty well um and so this piece of work
is very well known um so this was um
writing a sentiment classifier so
looking at a sentence and deciding
whether it's um positive or negative and
actually for both the kind of models
that I'm going to talk about today we're
going to use examples um that are doing
sentiments classification he also
considered other tasks subjective or
objective language question
classification as to what they were
about but the main application was doing
sentiment
analysis so what you're going to be
doing um this this paper shows things
more in his notation but it's exactly
the same as we've just been talking
about that you're taking engrams of word
vectors you're going to be um
multiplying them by convolution and
calculating new vectors and it's going
to be done in his model for different
sizes of NR so he's going to have some
convolutional filters that look at byrs
some at Tri and some of them that look
at
forrs and then those just slid across
the positions in the
sentence um
then having done that it does Max
pooling as we've been talking about
which gives a single number um coming
out of each filter and those Max pulled
numbers from each filter and then going
to be used as a classifier in a final
simple softmax layer to give the full
answers um there's one other thing that
came up in this paper which is kind of
just an interesting general idea um to
be aware of um and it was something he
sort of pioneered which is the following
that it's a very common case um that
what you for when you're sort of this I
guess this again occurs less with huge
pre-trained Transformers but for sort of
the classic case of models where you had
word vectors and then you were training
some neural network model
um on some supervised data um there was
this following Pitfall of what happened
when you fine-tuned word vectors and so
the setting is you know we've started
off with um our pre-trained word vectors
from glove or word to V or whatever it
is and then we've got a smaller um
sentiment analysis data set and that
we're going to um train a sentiment
classifier and that will involve not
only um learning the parameters of our
sentiment classifier but also we can
back propop into the word Vector
representations um and if you do that I
mean it seems like that should be a good
idea because you
know normal word vectors aren't you know
especially tuned to predicting sentiment
correctly um they're sort of more tuned
to meaning of words as to sort of um
just what words are about and so it
seems like it should help you if you
could um back propop into the word
vectors and change them as you go along
but if you do that there tends to be a
problem and the problem is um what
you'll find is that some words will be
in your sentiment training data set and
when you um learn um with backprop these
word vectors will move but some words
just won't be in your trading data and
they're going to stay exactly where they
were in the word de vectors because
there's nothing to move them around so
what tends to happen is you sort of
started off like this where all of
tedious dull and plotting were close by
each other as having similar meanings
and the indicators of something negative
but after you done your training um
tedious and dull as part of back propop
have moved over here where they're part
of the um negative land and the
classification boundaries moved over
here but plotting wasn't in the training
set so it's just sitting exactly where
it was at the start of the process and
now it's being treated as a positive
word which is completely wrong and so
that's tended to have the result that um
when people sort of train uh Language
new network on a small supervised data
set you got kind of ambivalent results
that sometimes um doing back prop into
the word vectors would help because you
could specialize your word vectors to
your task but sometimes it would hurt
you because of this kind of effect that
you sort of messed up the semantic
relations that applied over the that
were captured reasonably well in the
initial word vectors
um so the way that um Yun Kim dealt with
that was a fairly um simple way um he
just doubled his number of channels and
so he made two copies of each um Channel
each filter in his convolutional neural
network and for one of them it used the
fine-tuned word vectors and for one of
them it kept the original word vectors
and then he could have the best of both
worlds okay um so this picture um
captures the sort of whole of um his
Network um this picture actually comes
on from comes from a followon paper
which produced this nice picture so we
start off with a sentence I like this
movie very much which should be
classified positive um so we have words
and their word vectors and so then
you're going to have convolutional field
filters that are both byr filters trigr
filters and forr filters and at each of
those sizes you're going to have ones
that work on the unfin tuned word
vectors and the fine-tuned word vectors
um and
so you're going to put these filters and
slide them over the text and get um
representations and the way he's doing
this the filters are done without
padding so that the 4 gr filters you're
getting smaller vectors coming out um
and the byr filters you've got bigger
vectors coming out and so then for each
of these you're then going to Max pull
um so you're just getting the highest
value from it and then you're getting a
highest value from the ones with um the
fine tuning of the word vectors and the
ones not and so you're getting one one
feature out of each filter you're then
concatenating all of those Max pulled
outputs together so then one vector for
the entire sentence which is of fixed
size reflecting the number of filters um
and then you're just sticking this as a
straightforward um linear classifier
into a soft Max that's then giving you a
probability of a positive or negative
and that was the entire
model um and the interesting thing was
this actually worked pretty well um for
natural language classification tasks so
um this is a big table of results from
his paper so um there are sentiment data
sets like the Stanford sentiment Tree
Bank two versions of that um movie
reviews there's another sentiment data
set there's a subjectivity
classifier um the Tre was the kind of
question type classifier um so various
data sets
um and um that you know various people
um including us at Stanford I guess all
of these soed hour results were ones we
were doing at Stanford um had built um
lots of models on various of these data
sets and his argument was that by using
this simple convolutional new network um
you could do as as well sometimes better
than any of these other models that were
being considered at the time for
sentiment
analysis now there was at least one way
in which um maybe that comparison was
too generous to the CNN so um because um
if you remember back when we um were
doing Dropout and we said Dropout is
such a good idea I mean Dropout I think
came out in 2012 if I'm remember
remembering correctly so the reality is
a lot of these other methods were being
written before Dropout appeared on the
scene whereas he was using Dropout and
that gave him an advantage and sort of
better experimental technique might have
been to compare to redo the other models
with Dropout um um which he didn't um
but nevertheless it sort of shows that
you could get strong results using
convolutional newal networks um with
just a very simple
architecture yeah um so that's one more
thing that you can do and so I mean the
thing to think about here is you know we
have this sort of toolkit of ways that
you can do things we started off with um
word vectors and bags of vectors which
you could use for simple classification
we talked early on about window models
and your window models are sort of like
what you get for convolutional your
network works but sort of more ad hoc um
then we have convolutional newal
networks which are definitely good for
classification and very easy to paralyze
which is good and we talked about
recurrent newal networks which seem to
be cognitively plausible reading through
sentences from left to right but aren't
easy to
parallelize um and then we've talked
about
Transformers um which to some extent is
our you know best model for NLP and is
being used everywhere and indeed you
know what's happening now is that things
are going in reverse and people are
increasingly using Transformers for
vision as well though there's still I
think more debate in The Vision World as
between CNN and Transformers with some
people arguing that both of them have
complimentary
advantages okay um couple of other just
facts on the side and then I'll um show
you um one other um
bigger fancier convolutional new network
model for language um so we talked about
for Transformer models the use of layer
normalization which sort of um keeps the
size of the numbers in the middle layers
of the newal network about the Same by
giving zero mean and um unit variance um
there are slightly different ways that
you can do that um for tional new
networks the standard thing to be using
is batch normalization and indeed batch
normalization was the thing that was
invented first and sort of layer
normalization and batch normalization
are sort of doing the same thing of sort
of scaling numbers to give them zero
mean and unit variance but the way that
they differ is sort of under what
dimensions they're doing their
calculations
um so that layer Norm is calculating
statistics across the feature Dimension
whereas batch Norm is normalizing all
the elements in the batch for each um
feature
independently okay one other little
concept that turns up um which actually
sort of connects a bit to Transformers
as well there's this sort of funny thing
that you can all of what I've presented
so far was sort of volutions that are
some INR byr Tri for GR and so they're
also size one
convolutions and at first sight that
seems to make no sense at all cuz what's
the point of doing a size one
convolution because you just got one
thing and it's staying just one thing
but it actually does make sense because
it corresponds to having a little fully
connected layer
that's only looking at the
representation in one position so in a
language term is taking a word vector
and putting it through a fully connected
neural network to produce a new
representation just of that word and
that's sort of actually what we also
have with the fully connected layers and
Transformers right that you've got a
fully connected layer that's just at one
well subword token position and
calculates a new representation for it
um and so that's um allows you to sort
of create new representations with
actually many fewer parameters than if
you're allowing a fully connected layer
across the entire
sentence okay and so this is then a more
recent version of a convolutional newal
network still again used for text
classification but a much more complex
one um from Cano Al in
2017 um and again this was still at the
stage um in which lstm sequence models
were dominant in NLP I guess in 2017
this is sort of the same year the first
Transformer paper um came out and you
know there were the motivations were
sort of comparing vision and language um
and so at that point in time um
convolutional new network models and
vision were already very deep models so
people were using things like resnet
models that had 30 50 100 layers in them
and that stood in um stark contrast to
what was happening in the lstm world for
sequence models where commonly people
were just using two layer sequence
models and if you're wanting to go
further you might be using a thre layer
sequence model or four layer sequence
model or occasionally if you got really
really deep um people had used eight
layer sequence models if they had a lot
of data but essentially you know it was
always in a single digit the number of
layers um and then a second thing was
you know in some sense the vision models
were more raw signal models because they
were operating on the individual pixel
level whereas in NLP the standard was
that we were using Word level models
still in the Transformer model so it
sort of seemed like things were much
more grouped before they began and so
the idea of this paper is well maybe we
could do NLP kind of like it was Vision
so we'll start with the raw characters
as our signal we're going to put them
into a deeper convolutional neural
network work and use the same kind of
architecture um we use for vision and
use that for language classification
tasks and so that um led to this VD CNN
architecture which is something um that
looks very like a vision system in
design um and so what do we have here so
at the bottom um we have um individual
characters um
and the individual characters get a 16d
representation um and then you've got
some sort of size of piece of text that
you're classifying um which for them was
1,24 um and then at each stage we're
then going to have convolutional blocks
um and so these convolutional blocks um
have a whole bunch of filters but
they're also then going to group stuff
together um so that we're kind of sort
of starting to collapse into multicar
units um so we're starting off first of
all having you know 64 um size three um
convolutional
filters um and so that gives us a
representation of 64 um times the window
size um and then then um we're going to
do that again and put it um through
another set of convolutional
filters of size three and 64 of them
which gets us sort of up to here um and
then at each point we also have residual
connections which we also saw in
Transformers but were pioneered in the
vision space so that we have a path that
things can just go straight through but
then when we get to here um we then then
going to do local pooling so each pair
of representations here will be pulled
together and so at that point we've no
longer got a length of the initial
length of
1,24 we've now got a a length of um
512 um so now we're going to be putting
it
through again sort of trigram
convolutions but now we're going to have
128 of those
channels um we're going to repeat that
again and then we're going to again
group with pooling so now we're going to
um have
256 um long sequence because we've done
local pooling of each pair um and we're
going to then have 256 filters at each
stage and we go up and then we do local
pulling again so each of them is now
representing an eight G of characters um
and we're putting triam filters over
those 8 G so really the amount of a
sentence that the convolutional filters
is seeing at this point is 24 characters
so you know sort of seeing something
like six-word sequences or something
like that more convolutional blocks
there um then at there they then do this
ke KX pooling so some of the ideas from
the beginning of the lecture um do show
up so you're then doing kmax pooling and
finding the eight highest activations in
the sequence and that sort of makes
sense for something like a text
classifier because you want to count up
the amount of evidence right if you got
some category like is this about I don't
know uh copper mining you want to be
seeing whether there's a bunch of places
in the Tex that's talking about copper
mining um and then right up the top they
have several fully connected layers
which again is very typical of what you
are finding in Vision networks um such
as something like vggnet um that after
you've done a whole bunch of um
convolutional layers You' just stick it
through multiple fully connected layers
at the top and so that's what they're
doing as well and this is your
architecture um for doing text
in
um okay I think I talked through that in
a lot of detail um so I'll skip this
slide um yeah so um their experiments
were done on text classification data
sets so um various news classification
data sets um dbpedia onology um then
doing sentiment analysis on Yelp reviews
and Amazon
reviews um and here here um results um
from their one so you know they're
taking the previous known best published
results which are shown here in table
four and then they're
considering whether they can do better
by using their architecture and that
they um used architectures of different
lengths in terms of the number of um
layers of nine layers 17 and 29 layers
and the result of the paper is in all
cases um they got the best results by
their deepest Network which was a 29
layer model which is sort of then sort
of similar to what people were doing in
Vision um and then you know there's some
variation as to which was best by using
the max pulling or the kmax pulling but
in general was always the Deep model and
it varied a bit according to the data
set
but at least sometimes they were able to
produce the best results that were known
so I mean I guess for these text
classification previous results were
slightly better than their results um
but for some of the other ones like the
DBP and the Yelp that their results uh
or Al well for both the Yelp data sets
their results were better than the best
known previous results um the Amazon
ones one was better one was worse but to
a first approximation this meant that
they could basically reach the
state-ofthe-art of a text classification
system with something that was just a
deep convolutional neural network
starting from the character level with
none of the sort of Having learned word
vectors in advance or anything like that
and so that was a pretty cool
achievement which showed that you could
go a Fair Way um in doing things um with
just this sort of raw character level
convolutional new networks sort of more
like a vision
system okay so that's that and then for
the final piece of the class I then want
to tell tell you about something in The
Other Extreme um which is about um tree
recursive neural networks so tree
recursive neural networks is a framework
um that me and students developed at
Stanford so I mean really um when I
first got into new network day in
2010 that sort of for about the first
five years um that what me and students
worked on was doing these tree recursive
newal networks and so they were sort of
um the Stanford brand um
ultimately um they didn't prove as
successful as other things that came
along but I think they're linguistically
interested in and I think there's a
clear idea here which is still an idea
that exists and um I think there may be
still some things to do with which I'll
come back to but the starting point is
essentially being motivated by structure
of human language um and so most of this
slide is sort of filled um by a paper
from gome Chomsky and colleagues sort of
discussing um their views of the human
faculty of language what it is who has
and how did it evolve um and I don't uh
want to dwell on this in too much detail
but essentially in this paper what they
argue is that you know the defining
property of human language um that's not
observed in other things that humans do
is having that language has this
recursive structure that you have this
hierarchical nesting where the same
structure repeats inside itself so if
you have an example um like the person
standing next to the man from the
company that purchased the firm that you
used to work at um what you have is um
you the whole of this is a noun phrase
the person headed by the person and then
it's standing next to then the first
square brackets here is another noun
phrase the man from then inside that
prepositional phrase there's another
noun phrase the company that
purchased um the firm and then the firm
is another noun phrase that has the uh
relative Clause modifier of the firm
that you used to work at so we have
these embedded layers of noun phrases
with the same syntactic structure
underneath them and so for the kind of
formalisms that we use in linguistics of
context free grammar we they it permits
the kind of infinite embedding of
nesting which is the same kind of
nesting that you get in programming
languages where you can sort of use if
statements and Nest them as deeply as
you want to because you just have the
same repeating recursive structure now
of course human beings can't actually
understand recursive infinite recursion
and people don't actually produce
infinite recursion that you could sort
of say oh in practice no one's going to
go more than eight deep when they're
saying a sentence but in terms of the
structure of what the language looks
like it seems like you should be able to
do it infinitely deep and when you
actually start looking at the structures
of sentences um they do sort of repeat
over the same structure quite deeply so
this is uh example of a pen Tree Bank um
tree which is sort of the best known um
constituency um tree bank and so here's
my random sentence analyst said Mr
stronck wants to resume assum a more
influential role in running the company
and well what we end up with sort of if
we have these nested things of verb
phrases so running the company is a verb
phrase resume a more influential role in
running the company is a bigger verb
phrase um wants to resume a bigger role
in running the company as an even bigger
verb phrase and then said Mr stronck
wants to resume a more influential role
in running the company is an even bigger
verb phrase and so we have sort of one 2
three four verb phrases all nested
inside each other and so the idea was
well maybe we should be thinking of
sentences as having this kind of tree
structure and Computing representations
of meanings of sentences in terms of
this tree structure so um we have words
that have
representations in uh word Vector space
like we saw right at the beginning of
the class but then we're going to have a
phrase like the country of my birth and
the classic linguistic answer that you
find both in linguistic semantics
classes or philosophy of language is
that we could should construct
representations of phrases using the
principle of compositionality which says
that the meaning of a phrase or sentence
is determined by the meanings of its
Words which are our word vectors and the
rules that combine them so maybe we
could take the phrase structure tree of
a sentence and combine the word vectors
together by some means and then we can
construct a representation of the
meaning of phrases in a more linguistic
way giving us a vector representation of
the meaning of the phrase which we could
also put into our Vector space and we'd
hope that a phrase like the country of
my birth would appear in the vector
space in a similar place to where words
representing locations
appeared okay so what we want is to be
able to start with word vectors and Pa
up a
sentence and as we pause the sentence
we're then going to be Computing
representations for the different
phrases of the sentence
um and so the difference here is now you
know um you know the difference between
recursive and recurrent is sort of a
fake difference right they both come
from the same recur word um but rather
than having the recursion Just Happening
along a sequence as in a recurrent newal
Network we're going to have the
recursion happening uper tree structure
so we can Computing representations for
linguistically Meaningful
phrases um and so there sort of um what
we're going to do with that is you know
the easy Cas is if we know um the phrase
structure tree we can take the
representations of the child nodes put
them into a neural network which could
give us the representation of the parent
node but we'd also like to find the tree
structure and so a way we could do that
is then get a second thing out of the
newal network we could get a score for
how plausible something is as a
constituent does it make sense to
combine these two nose together to form
a larger constituent and then we can use
that in
AA so um formerly the very simplest kind
of tral network and the first one we
explored was when we had two child
vectors we're going to be um
representing the parent vector by
concatenating the two children
multiplying them by a matrix adding a
bias putting it through a nonlinearity
to get a parent representation p and
then we'd score whether it's a good
constituent by taking another um Vector
of learn parameters which would um do a
DOT product with p and that would give
us a score as to whether this was a good
constituent to include in your past tree
and the same W parameters were used at
all nodes of the tree in the same way as
a new a current new network kept using
the same
parameters okay um so if we did that if
we had that we could build a greedy paa
cuz what we could do is we could start
with all the word vectors and we could
just take every pair of words and put it
through this system and calculate what
the representation of that pair would be
as a constituent and then get a score as
to whether it seemed a good constituent
or not and then we could just
greedily decide this is the best
constituent the cat and so if we do a
greedy paraa we can commit to that and
then well we already still know the the
possibilities of combining other pairs
of words and we could just additionally
um score how good um the the cat
combined with sat is um so that we
producing binary um PA structures so now
the best pair to combine greedily is the
mat so we can combine them together and
commit to those we can score combining
on with the m that and now that seems
the best thing so we'll commit to that
and we just sort of keep on up and we
produce the binary pars of the sentence
and this gives us our sentence
representation okay which is like
that okay and so that gives us our
simple RNN um and so uh back in 2011 we
got some pretty decent results of
showing that you could use this as a
sentence paa that worked pretty well but
beyond that that the
representations um we calculated for
sentences and phrases were good enough
representations that you would use it
for tasks like sentence classification
sentiment analysis and it works
reasonably well um it only works it only
worked reasonably well um because if you
start thinking about it further you know
there sort of wor strong limitations of
having this single W Matrix that's used
at all points to combine things that
that if you sort of have that
architecture you sort of can't have
different forms of interaction between
the different words you're s just
uniformly Computing things and that sort
of stands in distinction to the fact
that different kinds of things in
natural language seem kind of different
you have um different properties with
verbs and their objects versus an
adjective modifying a noun just in terms
what the roles of the different words
were so we started um to see limitations
of this architecture and so in following
years um we started exploring other ways
to build tree recursive neural networks
which had more flexibility as to how
things were combined together and I'm
not going to show you all the details um
of all of that but I will show you um
one more um model that we use for
building tree recursive newal networks
and that was used in sort of some of our
sentiment analysis work called the
recursive newal tensor Network um it
wasn't actually the final net version
that we did after that we sort of
started taking lstm ideas and extending
those to the tree structured case and we
worked on tree lsdm but I'm not going to
show that this year um but the idea of
recursive newal tensor networks is you
know when pairs of words or phrases
combined together in linguistic
semantics terms depending on the pairs
of words they modify each other in
different ways so if you have an
adjective and a noun like um a red ball
sort of red is giving attributes of the
noun whereas if you have something like
a verb in object um like kick the ball
you've got a very different role for the
object as the right hand side versus the
red ball it's sort of the opposite way
around so we want to have more
flexibility in the way we can calculate
meanings of phrases depending on what's
in it and the way we came up with doing
that is to come up with what's we call
this neural tensil layer and so the idea
in the neural tensil layer is that we
have had um the
representations of um the the child um
words or phrases and so rather than sort
of directly putting rather than directly
concatenating them and
then um putting it through a sort of a
linear transformation like a regular new
network layer instead what we could do
is that we could learn um in between
matrices and if we put several of those
together we're then getting a
three-dimensional tensor and we could
multiply a vector um by a tenser time a
vector and then we'll end up getting out
um vectors for each one we'll have
multiple such
vectors okay and the the place that we
applied this model is for this task of
sentiment analysis so let me just tell
you a little bit more of what we did
here and this is sort of in fact going
backwards to the Stanford sentiment Tree
Bank um that was already used in the Yim
work so the goal of sentiment analysis
is to see whether a piece of text is
positive negative or neutral um so a lot
of the time doing sentiment analysis is
pretty easy um you know in the 2010s and
probably even today you know quite a few
people's sentiment analysis systems are
essentially just um keyword matching
right if you see great marvelous
wonderful positive sentiment if you see
something of poor bad negative sentiment
um and so lots of the time you can sort
of effectively do a kind of dictionary
matching and get pretty good sentiment
especially on longer documents but you
know on the other hand people use
language in lots of interesting ways and
it's not always that easy so if you look
at something like movie reviews such as
the Snippets you get on Rotten Tomatoes
um you get Snippets like this in Rotten
Tomatoes with this cast and this subject
matter the movie should have been
funnier and more entertaining and if you
just think of it as okay we're doing
dictionary matching there's the word
entertaining that's definitely positive
um and funnier that's positive so there
are two positive words so this should be
a positive review but of course it's not
a positive review this is a negative
review um because it's saying um well
I'm just reading it out again with this
cast and subject matter the movie should
have been funnier and more entertaining
right so the compositional structure of
human language goes together to mean
that these um because
it's buried under should have been the
funnier and entertaining are actually
lacking and so it's a negative review
and so these were the kind of examples
that we were interested in and saying
could we sort of actually understand the
structure of sentences more and do a
better job at sentiment analysis and so
up until this time um people are just
sort of had pieces of text and a
classification Judgment of positive and
negative so we decided we're going to do
more than that and come up with the
Stanford sentiment Tree Bank where what
we did was passed up a whole lot of
sentences almost 12,000 of them and then
what we are going to do is put sentiment
judgments on every linguistic phrase of
the sentence so for something like this
example you know with this cast is a
phrase no sentiments so that just be
neutral um entertaining is a phrase a
one-word phrase its sentiment is
positive um um you know funnier and more
entertaining that's a
phrase very positive um but then by the
time we get embedded under should have
been funnier and more entertaining
that's a bigger phrase its sentiment is
now negative and the movie should have
been funnier and more entertaining
that's an even bigger phrase it's
negative and so we were um passing up
trees like that and these examples are
very small I'll show you a big examples
later but you can sort of just see that
in the trees there are blue nodes and
orange nodes corresponding to positive
and negative sentiment reflecting units
at the different sizes and so the
interesting thing is then this gave us a
richer annotated data set because it's
not only sort of whole sentences or
whole articles that were annotated for
sentiment we had annotations for
different phrases and simply the fact
that you were annotating phrases meant
that you could learn more from the
examples so even if you're using
something very simple like a naive based
classifier because there an ations on
Words and smaller phrases you could
learn a bit more about which were
positive and which were negative and so
that was the first result that we could
um people a baseline method of a byr
Nave Bas classifier which is a very
common sentiment classifier that if you
just trained with sentiment classifiers
you got 79% on this data set if you
trained with um if you trained using
every node of the tree Bank um you got
83% so you got a 4% lift and so um that
was kind of good um these other two
lines show two of our early Tre tree
rnns and the negative part of the result
is they weren't really better than a
bite gram um naive Bas classifier they
were better than a unigram naive Bas
classifier but a lot of sort of the
extra information that you want to
capture for sentiment analysis you can
get from byrams because that's can
already tell you sort of not good um
somewhat interesting and things like
that
um but then so the other Hope was to
have a more powerful model and so that
then led into use of this recursive
newal tensor Network which allowed sort
of the mediated multiplicative
interactions between word or phrase
vectors
um and so we built that and so then here
are the results of that model that's
shown in red um so by having our
recursive newal tensor Network we were
able to build um a somewhat better newal
Network that performed at least
reasonably better than a byr naive Bas
model rate that we were getting sort of
about 22% better than a by byr NA Bas
model so that was progress but I think
perhaps the more interesting thing isn't
sort of the aggregate results but the
fact that because we were building up
this
model the computed
representations over a constituency tree
that it actually made judgments of
different parts of sentences and how
they combined so um here's the movie
review sentence there are slow and rep
repetitive Parts but it has just enough
space to keep it interesting um so I
hope you'll agree with the Judgment that
overall that's a positive statement
about the movie um and so the um recurs
of newor tens Network builds the tree
structure over this sentence and it says
you know slow and repetitive that's
negative there are slow um repetitive
Parts it's all negative to hear but for
the part over to the right interesting
um spice they're both positive and spice
to keep it interesting that's positive
it has just enough spice to keep it
interesting positive and it correctly
predicts that when you put these two
halves of these sentences together um
the overall judgment is that this
remains um a positive review and it
gives a positive judgment overall so
that was kind of cool um and in
particular um the fact that we were
building these phrase judgments um meant
that it seemed like we could actually do
a better job of sentence understanding
in the way that sort of any linguist
doing linguistic semantics would like to
see sentence understanding so one of the
things that newal networks when looking
at language have often been faltered for
and are still faled for to this day
using Transformer models is you often
find the result that um new network
models just don't pay attention to
negation that you can be um having some
sentence and you can compare the
sentence of um you know a lot of
students are studying for their final
exams versus a lot of students aren't
studying for their final exams and the
negation just gets lost that it doesn't
produce um the differences and
representation and meaning that you'd
like it to um so somewhat
interestingly um with this model it
seemed like because we were modeling the
the cursive building up of sentence
structure that we actually um could do
interesting things with um modeling
negation right so in particular
um that um what You' the results that
you'd like to get is if you have
something like it's just incredibly dull
so dull is a very negative word um
incredible is a positive word by itself
but when you're sort of saying
incredibly dull it's definitely still
negative um and this um uh our recursive
newor tensor network is um correctly
modeling um it's just incredibly dull is
very negative despite incredible being a
sort of positive word
so um you know actually in this um model
um there was five way classification so
there was very negative somewhat
negative neutral somewhat positive very
positive um so there's sort of some
bouncing around as to whether it's
giving the classification very negative
versus somewhat negative I can't really
explain why in the middle it goes to
somewhat negative and then goes back to
very negative but that's the results
that came out of the the network and at
any rate if it all stays negative the
fact that incredible by itself
incredibly is a positive word it's seen
in the modif modification of dull as
that keeps it negative but on the other
hand if you put a negation in here it's
definitely not Dull um well then what
happens now interestingly the word not
by itself is a negative word that if you
just sort of do the raw statistics of it
um not occurs much more often in
negative sentiment sentences than it
does in positive
sentiment sentences so you know if you
want to be a more positive person use
negation less um so not by itself as
negative but if you then combine it
together not Dull or in this case
definitely not Dull um well not Dull is
you have two negations so that they
cancel each other out and you get
something that's positive and so it's
definitely not Dull comes out as a
positive
sentence and so the interesting result
here is that um if you um compare what
happens between you know if you have
negated positive sentences so you know
it's definitely not good various models
can model that correctly because not is
a negative word and so therefore it
weakens the positivity of the positive
word and so putting a knot in front of a
positive into a positive sentence makes
it less positive and even a not very
well but even a naive Bas model can do
that because not by itself is seen as a
negative word but the hard case is what
happens if you negate a negative
sentence
well the result that you should get is
it becomes more positive and neither a
byr naive based model or our earlier
attempts at recursive models can capture
that whereas this RNN structure was able
to correctly modify capture this sort of
semantic modification um structure and
say hey that's made the sentence much
more positive um so that was a cool
result and to some extent you know this
result I think still isn't captured as
well by any of the um current
Transformer models even though they have
many other advantages and are much
better than a tree recursive neural
network um so I mean yeah so just to say
a couple um this is basically the end um
to just say a couple of final remarks
about these tree recursive new networks
um you know the reason that they became
uncompetitive is because they just
didn't allow the kind of
um associations and information flow
that you have in a Transformer right
that these these models had a strictly
context free backbone and the only
information flow was Tre structured
following the context free backbone um
whereas in the Transformer you've got
this tension function where in every
position you're looking at every other
position and so you can have much more
general information flow and in general
that is just good and Transformers are
much more powerful but you know on the
other hand to the extent that you
actually want to model the sort of
semantics of human language carefully is
to sort of what modifies what and how
does negation or quantifiers in a
sentence behave in some sense these
models were more right and so one of the
things I'm still kind of interested in
is are there any opportunities um to
combine together some of the benefits of
both of these ways of thinking and have
something that's a bit more tree
structured while still more flexible
like a
Transformer okay that's it for today
thanks a lot