my name is y I'm a research scientist
director uh in M AI fair today I'm going
to talk about our recent work uh on the
armm uh us and planning domain and also
agent domain so the title is uh towards
uh UniFi framework of neural and
symbolic decision making okay so we all
know that Lang model is being uh used
very extensively in many different
scenarios so so here I'm basically list
a few uh possible uh applications at lar
model has already proven to be super
useful right so uh people have been
using Electro models for conversational
AIS to generate content right and also
use that to play against each other to
basically do role play and also do AI
agent as well and recently lar mode has
also been used for reasoning and
planning and we also see that by using
for example chain of thoughts uh the
reasoning credability of L model
actually become much better and at the
same time uh we also see uh issues with
the models when we are trying to
leverage that in uh different planning
tasks so uh in this uh in this like a
lecture I'm going to be focus on the
unit and planning component since like
in MAA uh I have been working with a
bunch of very creative and very talented
people together on working on L model
with using and planning and try to find
a way to uh make their planning ring
technique and the strength become much
stronger uh into the Next Level so let's
see uh what are the interesting
components that we can do for read and
planning uh so one thing that we want to
think about is that uh in order to
improve existing reing planning
capabilities of course we want to
understand uh what is weakness and how
can we overcome how can we like overcome
such weakness uh in uh in with different
approaches here's the one example that I
probably uh use it for many different
scenarios uh for uh showing that L model
really does not plan uh very well uh in
different scenarios especially in
scenarios that is common in our da life
right so one is example is the the
travel planning uh provins right so for
travel planning uh the the task is super
simple right we just asked the elect
model about a travel uh plan right so I
want to say I want to go to Hawaii I
want to go to Seattle I want to go to
California uh at some specific day with
some specific budget and then I want the
to give you give me a very clear
executable feedable and even optimal
itinerary uh so this is the task we want
to go right so uh and in order to
achieve this task then people may still
start to think about like uh some
agentic behaviors right so of course we
first want language model to query a few
informations uh a lot of information
from uh outside from etal word right so
for example you can ask model to do like
a search right so and it will give you
some of the uh possible directions a
possible destination you want to go
right you also want to ask model to do a
flight search or the hotel search and
you get multiple uh entries of possible
hotels as well as um uh basically the uh
and also the the the the the fried
informations as well so once you have
all this information putting together
then then of course you want langage
model to plan right so give all
information hopefully the model can
figure out a pass in itinerary that will
connect all the uh in information
together uh into a clear pass or itary
that it can be
executed right so uh the figure to the
bottom right uh basically like the the
figure uh that the basically the the the
real plan that we want to use in order
to exud the plan right okay so uh but
interestingly what happened is that if
we actually use the uh the current
language model uh to do this planning
task it's actually not doing very well
uh so this is a paper that uh we
published in uh this year icmr as a
spotlight and in this paper uh this is
the main table that we put to show the
incapability of language models for
solving this kind of problems right so
first first of all uh the first the the
the top chunk of the table basically
shows that um even with the gp4 turbo
which is the model that is the strongest
at that time uh we actually see that the
final pass rate of the entire travel
itinerary is only
0.6% so here you have percentage here uh
where we don't show in top all right so
uh but even if like we give the language
model the ground truth information of
the tools then we ask the model to
directly plan the travel then the final
pass rate is also only like
4.4% so the the pass the pass rate
definition is very simple right given
the CLE the itinerary you really want to
see whether every stage of the travel
satisfy the constraints B say the
constraint means that uh you might have
a uh a criteria that you don't want to
be in a nonsmoking in a smoking room
right so you might want to say I have a
bget constraint the ver cannot exceed
some fixed amount of numbers Etc so you
can basically have uh some code to check
whether uh uh the trial itinerary really
pass uh all these criterias but
unfortunately the final plan quality is
not great and you have to uh really have
human involved in order to find a plan
that is really
executable of course I mean people will
say okay this is like a paper that only
uh uh that is that basic paper that is
being published at early this year right
so and you know like in L model era
every month counts every week's counts
right so uh and people prob the people
published like half a year ago basically
means like it's like an ages old and
people may not care anymore right so how
about like uh using o o is like the
current St out models for reason and
planning and uh thanks for the courtesy
of the first sour for this paper we also
uh get some over1 numbers um with uh
this short plan Benchmark then what
happened here is that you still see that
the overall pass rate is not great uh
for over many and also preview uh they
are even worse than the model that is
fine-tuned to that particular task so
it's not really uh solving you the
problem for the TR planning problems and
you can actually see the same thing uh
for the a plan and uh and for in the in
other in other scenarios right so uh you
can see that so the figure to left is
actually from the de de mind uh uh
Gemini team right so in that paper uh
what they show here is that uh for
planning problems like two planning and
also meeting planning um you uh you see
that performance actually jobs
potentially with uh uh more complexity
uh in term of the uh number of uh uh
variables and also the scale of the
problem for the planning task right so
while like a Gemini is still is doing
like great in uh this benchmarks you
will see like this a Waring Trend all
the way down to zero uh where you have
more and more cities or more and more
people uh showing that the problem skill
goes up right okay so the figure to the
left basically shows the performance
before o1 release but the figure to the
right actually show what happened after
release uh of course you see that ow is
actually doing a very great job right so
you see super high performance
uh when uh for when this apply to uh
kind of a smaller scale problems like
big gap between o1 and also existing
models however uh if the skill of the
planning problem goes uh goes up right
so the plan L from going from two all
the way to like 14 or 16 then all of a
sudden you see that the curve also drops
to zero right so uh this is actually
from OSU uh the paper is called am not
plan there's a study on that uh so this
actually basically give you this kind of
sense that while um you can see the bias
turn of the curve is moving up
substantially the trend of the entire
curve still goes down substantially uh
and uh it the trend does not change over
time right so this is actually in some
sense a very worrisome uh uh kind of
curve uh that uh even the best model
that we have encountered have have not
solved this kind of
problems of course like next slide will
be what is the solution what are
solutions so in this lecture I'm going
to talk about the three possible
different categories of solutions right
so and they are listed there so the
solution one of course is the scaling
law okay and we say with more data more
compute and larger models and uh
hopefully in one day then we going to
see a better performance and going to
eventually solve this problems with all
these bigger models right so of course
they are very expensive and then this
also involve like a lot of enging
challenges uh but may not necessarily
involve like a new kind of thinking and
thoughts about this how we solve these
problems that's definitely one pass I
don't want to comment on like how uh
good or bad of this comment of this pass
but this just the one option something
that you can think about uh there's a
second option that's called hybrid
systems in that in that option what we
can think about is that okay so we can
see it's very clear that there's two
complimentary pass if we use the models
like Foundation models they are very
good at understanding uh the the natural
language instructions but they are not
doing very well in uh doing like a very
good planning tasks right so they will
have like a bad Solutions the solution
is not high qualtity Etc right so on the
other hand there's another word called
the comori solvers or symbolic solvers
so these solers are basically uh can
give you Optimal Solutions uh in many
different scenarios and we have
guarantees and often uh run super fast
compared to neur networks and do not
require gpus in many cases right so and
these are basically like a very good
sers for complicated planning problems
but at the same time these sers don't
understand natural language they don't
understand users require
you don't understand many flexible
scenarios right so maybe we should
combine them together into the same
system then then uh you're going to see
that these two can be put together and
you give you something that is stronger
than both of the side right so on these
options there were there are like
several different way of combining them
so which are going to uh talk about uh
in the following slides and that's
actually option three uh which is
actually uh say that there's actually a
way to understand the new network and
find that there's a symbolic
representation that emerges
automatically uh from the green descent
optimization so that's something that
could be super interesting and recently
this is something that we have found in
our very recent research but I'm going
to talk about that later after the uh
option two okay so let's start with this
one so uh there's a different ways of
combining the models with sers of course
the first one that we can do is the tool
use right so uh for this we actually
have a uh followup work uh for the tri
planner about uh how can we leverage uh
mixture integer linear programming and
uh new network ler models together in
order to uh solve the uh travel planning
problems right so here instead of asking
the L model to directly uh give you the
optimal itineraries which is very hard
and even INF feasible given the current
problems of uh isues of Lang models how
about that we can ask the language model
uh to First convert the natural language
uh input into a Json file so here's Json
file and given the Json file it give you
all the symbol representation of the
request for the uh for for for uh for
the user and given this request combined
with the flight and hotel information
you can actually call a server uh here
we are using mixed integer linear
programming
sare and that sare will give you some
symbolic description of the optimal
itinerary and you can use the optim
itary and you can convert that back to
the actual sentences uh and this will be
used as the response of the agent right
so uh you can do this instead of like a
do a direct pass you can tiet the tool
through the symbolic solver and that the
tool will give you some solution that is
guaranteed to work
better so we actually build a demo on
top of that and our demo actually was
just accepted in this emrp demo session
uh hold in to be held in Miami if people
are interested and people are joining
enp uh please go ahead and take a look
so this entire thing can be a demo
because it's real time right so here is
like this a breakdown of uh of the speed
right so uh you we actually find you
instruction uh translator and that will
take like two seconds or 2.5 seconds uh
to translate uh from natural language
all the way to the uh Json file and then
we also have MP server intern
programming solver that will uh
basically solve problem and the solving
is actually sufficient very very fast it
takes uh 0
uh 3.5 seconds 7 Seconds uh to solve
problem so that this will make the
entire demo real time and people can
actually play with it and we also have
human uh evalutions and basically like
human ask human subjects ask about this
questions whether this system is useful
well identify the request whether they
offer good amount of value for the money
and whether this is efficient and you
can see that uh most of the uh human uh
subjects uh they are uh in NE positive
uh on our system compared to the
baselines okay so that's actually uh
quite uh uh
interesting of course the next step will
be um multi dialogue right so here in
the previous systems what we do here is
that uh the the agent basically take the
single uh round uh dialogue or take the
US request as one single round of the
request and send this request to the uh
to the new network to the large models
and will convert to a Json file but in
practice people are not doing that right
people always start with uh uh some
rough idea about travel so I want to go
to Hawaii I have no idea what else but I
don't go Hawaii but then the agent will
try to ask a little bit more about
details how much budget like are you are
you a people who really care about uh uh
money or are you people who care about
experience
right so there's actually a lot of
detailed questions you really want to
figure out and this is actually a
natural scenarios for multi round
dialogues and discussions so in order to
achieve that we actually train an agent
uh that can uh basically like
proactively ask questions to the uh to
the agent uh to The Travelers and
traveler will answer these questions
accordingly and uh the agent is aiming
to efficiently get all all the
informations with the minimum round of
dialogue and then convert them into Json
compare this Json with the ground truth
Jon that's being uh created privately uh
from the DAT generation process right so
um and how we achieve this agent uh is
that we actually design our uh agent
constitution in order to uh allow the
agent to uh follow these instructions
right so uh the Constitution that we uh
Dev is called APAC Constitution so it
consists of three four different uh
component right so first you want agent
to be super accurate uh and second you
want agent to be proactive means that
you want agent to ask question
proactively to get answers you don't
want agent to ask random questions that
is not interesting you Al you also don't
want agent to be very impressive right
so agent need to find what are the
interesting question you want to ask and
then answer them and we also want agent
to be efficient which mean that uh a
don't want to waste time and efforts to
irrelevant questions but most important
questions the also need to be adaptive
to different Proto different types of
the of The Travelers so we actually set
like 50 different personal of The
Travelers each personal of traveler will
deposit different behaviors and this
traveler will have private hidden uh
spreadsheet of most most critical
information they really want to get it
correct right so and then we want to
compare whether the agent can actually
uh get all this information in a short
amount of time and finally we also want
agent to be credible which means that
less hydrogenation less inconsistency
Etc so we can use all these Constitution
and we can find T the models and we can
see that after uh several R of fine
tuning using DP uh our uh models
actually become a little bit more
efficient uh in basically like two
categories one is called overall overall
means like all the all the entries and
critical means that critical entries for
particular personal of that of The
Travelers out of like 50 personnal then
we also want to optimize uh the agent
agentic scores involing prac
qualification Etc and we see that after
a few rounds of dpos uh the performance
actually goes up and uh the also doing
good job here right so uh it's
interesting uh showing that if you use
like agent Constitution it's possible
that we can improve the agent
performance along different axis
simultaneously with very simple
techniques and this can be also better
than existing approaches like if you
just use Lama 3.1b uh 18 billion models
uh the performance is actually not great
because it's not been fine-tuned along
these
directions so recently there's a
separate paper uh that uh is also uh is
also like involve like multiple like
meta authors is that uh alternative we
might also use agent as a judge instead
of having humans as a judge right so uh
in this paper what we do here is that uh
uh traditionally we basically use l
model as a judge to judge the behavior
agent and we may only check like the
final results of agent uh given all the
outcomes but in this paper we're trying
to use agent as a judge and agent we try
to check like every steps of the uh of
the target agent and to see like whether
whe they are doing very well or not and
doing that you can we were able to give
you uh more refined and more Rich uh
feedbacks for the man agent to improve
okay okay so uh uh we are finishing this
first part of using deep mod those uh to
call the sers you order to finish the
task so let's proceed with the second
part right so second part is that maybe
there's a different ways of combining
agent uh combining the models with
solvers the second part is like how
about we use the solware to provide data
to De models to train better but this
one we actually have a bunch of
Direction tasks sorry a bunch of uh uh
research directions uh that actually uh
showing this is also a very interesting
and nice uh Trend to follow right so for
this we're going to introduce this
search forer uh results and for search
for uh what we do here is that uh the
goal is to basically predict the outcome
of the of the planet task right so here
it's a very simple Planet task you have
a maze you have multiple walls and you
want to find what is the shortest path
uh between the starting point and the
goal Point okay so here the maze is 3x3
and shortest pass is very simple you
just go all the way down and to the
right uh sorry and uh to the left and
then you go to destination very simple
right so um but if before you actually
get to the destination get to the
optimal plan if you execute a a symbolic
sare here symbolic sare is a star search
right so AAR search is a very uh seminar
work uh that uh try to uh use a
heuristic function to find what is the
optimal pass uh from the beginning State
all the way to the end State it's being
used very extensively in many different
scenarios here we just use the uh uh use
this approach to find the shortest path
so if you think about how a to solve a
problem before it actually give you the
final Optimum plan it also give you all
intermediate steps in order for you to
reach the optim plan right so for
example in this particular case what
happened is that Asar search will start
to create a new node doing the search
and explore different part of the Maze
and to see which paths can lead to the
destination so this this entire
procedure will create this intermediate
steps so which is shown in purple and
also the the T Colors right so this
basically is internal steps of the
search after the search proceed was
finished then we actually find what is
the optimal plan for the entire uh
problems okay so the idea of search
forer is that instead of a trainer model
that directly predict the plan given the
prompt pump is basically the description
of a
problem right which is this is something
that people often do right so uh we have
some description of the problem and then
we directly predict uh what is the
outcome optimal plan of the problem in
our approach what we do is that we start
from initial prompt we can actually
first predict the trace the search trace
of the problems and then given the
search Trace we can predict the final uh
output plan so that's called the search
augmented model that's the model that we
uh we propose in our paper as a first
state
models so and if you check like how many
tokens uh we are using
right so for these two settings so of
course like the SE solution only models
typically will only generate maybe 100
400 tokens but the search all model May
gener much longer tokens uh number of
tokens because um it will also output
the Chace how you do the search and then
the plan okay that people may Wonder
okay now you have some kind of uh uh
tradiction problem that need to take a
detour to the Final Destination do you
think that's a a good idea the answer is
yes you actually find that's a very nice
uh uh scen L curves that associated with
resarch algor models so first let's
check out here the solution only curve
so this is basically the model that uh
uh uh that can be used in many different
cases but also you see uh uh um a
skating LW curve is not so perfect right
so for this from what happen is that you
need to have like a million uh number of
training sequences in order to reach
something that is super high in term of
the performance on the test set right
and this basically is used 1 175 million
parameters in the solution only models
for 30 by3 ma navigation okay not great
however if you use uh uh search
argumented models and you check the the
basically the curve and and you see that
the curve is actually very different
right so all of a sudden what you see is
that with a search augmented model of
only 15 million parameters 10x smaller
than the solution only
models you see a training a curve that
is much better uh than the original
solution only models right so with only
like a 50k samples then what you see
that the performance of the final score
is already like around
80% compared to the 20% with the
solution only models right so when you
have more and more training sequences
the performance is getting even uh
better so now what you will see here is
that this seting model become much more
parameter efficient and much more data
efficient it give you approximate same
performance with a 10x fewer number of
samples 100K versus 1 million and 10 10x
fewer number of parameters like 15
million versus 175 million right so we
this a simple trick by adding this uh uh
search Trace all of a sudden the
performance actually getting much much
better you can also do the same thing
for the uh for the so game so this is a
game uh called soang the game is very
simple right so you have one agent and
you want to push the boxes uh to
different destinations and uh the only
action you can take is to push box
forward right so you cannot pull the box
back from a corner or a phone wall and
you have to basically start over from
the
beginning so then this problem basically
requires a substantial planning because
you cannot just do resing randomly if
you push the box to the corner then
there's no way uh you can put a box uh
back later and this will basically uh
conclude a failure stage of the game you
have to basically restart and you
basically see a very cre also uh similar
Trends uh for the uh solution only
versus the search org
models okay so now we can see like the
scale law of the two kind of models are
very different uh given that we first
predict the search trace and then we
predict the final uh plan then people
may wonder how can we go beyond right so
what we did is just imitation learning
so we start from solver search Trace and
then we use the search tra to Trend the
Transformer we teacher foring to get the
search of wi model and this is already
data efficient and also efficient as
well what we can do further is that
given the search aled models uh which is
already uh end to endend defal models
what you can do here is to F tune this
model to achieve shorter Trace but still
lead to Optimum plan okay so this is
basically the in some sense a very
typical reinforcement learning task and
that is a search former uh model that we
end up with so uh what we want to say is
that uh we don't do really a
reinforcement task but what we do is
very simple we just to expert uation
what it does is that once you have this
search augmented model you can actually
sample this model many many times with
some diversity and this sampling
actually will lead to many different
traces and many different plans you pick
the plan that is optimal and then given
all the optimal plans check the
associate search tra you want to find
which search tra is the shortest you
basically get all the shortest trays
with Optimum plan and use this data use
subset of data as a training set for the
next generation of the search form you
can do this
atively then what happen is that uh you
still keep the uh same or even better
optimality rate but at the same time the
distribution of the sequence
lens per test track uh task now actually
become shorter and shorter right so we
can see you can see that at the
beginning of the top of the figure you
you see that the c or model and a star
they are sharing a similar distribution
of the sequence less uh average per task
because uh the SE augmented model is u
uh imitation learning results of the
original a star search Trace so this is
not surprising but once you have done
multiple step of this boost driving by
itally by like creating a lot of traces
and their plans and picking the trace
that is shortest but still Le to Optimum
plan and put them back into the training
set and ret Trin the model refine to the
model then you can see that over time
the distribution of the sequence lens
average per uh task actually shrink to
the left means that it's become shorter
and
shorter that's why this paper is called
a Beyond a star which means that we are
able to find shorter uh Trace lens while
keeping the auality of the final uh
Solutions so uh and uh in term of
numbers uh we actually also see
improvements right so here we Define a
metric called IR uh which is the
improved lens ratio that's the lens
ratio of the optimal of the a Star
Search Trace divided by uh the the sear
Trace that is discovered uh by the neur
networks so what you see here is that
over time the improved lens ratio
actually become higher and higher which
means that the final uh Trace that is
output by NE TOS become shorter and
shorter over time uh when we go through
uh a step of boost
driving and then people may ask about
like okay what happens uh if you uh if
we check the optimity rate right it's
possible that the trace for optimal uh
optimal results optimal solution is
shorter but it's also possible that
maybe the number of optimality also goes
down but actually it's not the case you
see the numbers and you will see that
the abnormality actually goes up a
little bit every time when you do the
steps obervations which is something
that's kind of mysterious uh but it's
still interesting to see so after this
number of steps uations you see the
automatic rate goes up and the same time
uh the search Trace is uh is become much
more
efficient and you see that uh this
number of parameters uh the performance
is actually comparable when uh you use
this uh uh search foration procedure
with 24 million parameters compared to
the solu only models uh that that has
like a lot large par right so 700
millions and you can see that the aoma
rates become comparable after this boost
dropping
process yeah so let actually show that
this is interesting steps and uh uh our
uh search former uh perance surprisingly
uh after this kind of boost drop steps
actually doing uh very well so recently
we also have a Fallout paper uh called a
du forer that paper is a V2 version of
search for forers so what we do here is
very simple so uh one of the weakness of
the search forer is that uh the trace is
often very long it might basically like
take like a thousand tokens or maybe a
10 of thousand tokens before it actually
uh give you the final outcome of the
solutions then what should we do so in
the DU forward paper what we have what
we do here is that we are trying to uh
reduce the length of the search Trace
but dropping randomly some portion of it
right so we Define different level of
dropping so we can say like maybe the
close cost in a star search is not
important so we can get rid of them
maybe the uh cost tokens in the create
uh Center the create cost is not
important we drop them we can also drop
the entire create cost right so we have
a different level of uh the dropping and
we also Define the F the final the level
four is basically drop the entire trace
and we just use the solution only uh
data to train the models okay so uh then
what happen is that if you train the M
the model with all different
combinations of these levels of
traces then uh what happen is that the
performance actually getting better
compared to the two cases that you Trend
with only solutions and you Trend with
the complete Trace that's very
interesting
so we actually test this on Maze of
different sizes and also scas that we
used in the previous slides we actually
see a much better performance uh
compared to this uh cases and at the
same time the diversity of the uh the
the outcome of the traces is also
getting much higher so diversity
basically defined as uh how many
clusters you see uh out of for example
uh 64 number of routs that you have
generated uh from the
models D is important especially for the
test time compute because if you have
high diversity during doing this during
the generation then uh if you scale up
your uh test time uh compute then the
performance will also getting much
better right so in this paper it look
like it's very simple this simple
approach and automatically give you high
diversity because the input data is also
very diverse and more interestingly
there's a a finding that is also very
surprising is that this approach this
final result called deformer it will
automatically switch between fast mode
and slow mode by
itself depend on the problem uh
specifications and will work better for
delicated modes in either uh either
situations so we all know that usually
people will talk about system one and
system two so for system one settings
what happen me that the model will
directly predict uh final Solutions
without any thinkings and for system to
usually the model will first think
around or what should we do as there
some search process and then come up
with other final Solutions so usually uh
for system syst system two we think like
there are two different discrete mode of
operating and we want two different
models to deal with these two kind of
thinkings uh separately and we can
basically TR control on top of that to
Ure which one to use but now with the DU
forer we actually see thisise behavior
that once the model TR on this mixture
of data it will automatically switch
between system one and system two so
sometimes uh the Dual forer will output
for the great token so when the D output
create token which means that the model
will start this kind of slow thinking
process and here give you the actual
plan sometimes the model will give you a
plan token at the beginning which means
that the model will directly give you
the
answer that's actually quite interesting
so basically you see that this kind of
behavior automatically emerges through
the chy and uh without basically having
human uh giving like explicit evaluation
explicit like signals
there so here you see that for the T for
bracket Auto this mean that this model
is doing an auto mode we are free to let
the Dual forer output any kind of tokens
it might output a a plan token which is
the system one settings it may also
output a create token which is system
two settings and in in the same time uh
you see that the performance is getting
better than if you model only TR system
one and one system
too and moreover it's interesting to see
that we can actually
control how the deformer is operating I
can only control the first tokens right
so if we say the Dual former is forced
to uh generate the first token called
create then dual former is forced to be
entering the system two settings which
is slow settings if the Dual former is
forced to uh create a token called up
plan then it will basically give you a
system one output and interestingly uh
we We compare this dual for fast which
means that D for is forced to operating
in a fast mode with the uh the the
dedicated fast models that's notified by
solution only you see the performance is
also getting better uh if you compare
the Dual forer which is forced to be in
a slow mode and you can actually see
that it performance is also better uh
than the other than the baselines that
is trend on confete Trace which means
that it is forc to the model is
dedicated to to a slow mode right so
it's interesting that the model can
switch to both modes and at the same
time uh if the model is forced to use
one mode is also still better than
dedicated models train on particular
data and uh we also try this idea in
Mass problemin so this problem is more
realistic right so for for Mass problems
what we do here is that so we start from
this uh a Max data set which has a a
very long explanation about how we
arrive at the answers and then we can
basically randomize Rand randomly uh
decimate sentences uh from the uh uh
from the from the channel of thoughts
and there the train models and the
reality model is actually quite
interesting it give you much shorter and
concise steps at the same time you still
give you a little bit better
performance so here's the examples of
the performance that you get right so uh
you see that uh in the when in the
previous work uh people already
discovered that by argumenting the chain
of thoughts uh with the uh exit models
uh we create data set called a mass
which is our Baseline so this this a m
already give you better performance
compared to the original Mass data set
uh but with our approach uh with
different ratio of dropping we actually
see even better performance and at the
same time the Trace lens is also shorter
so uh in end we have this uh uh this
kind of comparisons between du formal
and also the ow right so uh you actually
will see that the Dual foral will give
you the correct path uh towards the
destination uh with all the export
states that show in the red and the O uh
without any training uh does not really
understand uh what's going on uh inside
the uh this this m settings and we only
give you a pass that basically break all
these situations break all the wars
right so uh in this case we show that
after the training uh this deformer is
able to do uh good uh planning and the
planning is reasonable and it's better
uh than the OM preview in this
particular problems but I would say this
is not not a fair comparison because
ideally there should be uh fine tune
version over preview on that particular
data set and see how good performance is
okay so now I conclude the second part
of the option two so let's go to the
option the the last part of the option
two how we can Trad the models and the
solver at the same time in N to
manner so for this for this one we're
talking a little bit about uh little bit
different settings this setting is also
using commentarial solvers uh but uh
it's applied to uh kind of real world
problems that requires
optimization so think about like you
want to optimize uh very complicated
functions uh that are
differentiable but at the same time it
also need to subject to the Comal uh
constraints right so you have some Comal
constraints and the objective is
nonlinear there are many different real
world domains that will actually cover
uh for to this categories right so for
example you want to optimize some
computer systems you want to optimize
some antenna designs optimize some uh
sometime devices in physix so all these
problems usually you cannot write down
the optimization problem in linear form
and this would this basically prevent
you from directly calling aoral solvers
to solve the problems right so here's
one example that we actually encounter
in our Productions uh so this problem is
like a uh inviting table
placement so suppose like you have K
tables they in tables and have n
identical devices here devices means
dpus and then you want to place this K
tables to n identical devices such that
each device uh will have a lot of uh uh
tables but uh does not exceed the memory
capabilities capacities and the goal is
to minimize the latency which is
estimated by neur Network so if you want
to formulate that problem uh in a
mathematical way you actually end up
with the
formulations right so here x is a binary
variable representing that uh this table
I table I is being placed to device J
okay so of course like for each table I
you want to want this one to be placed
to device J some device J so that's why
you have some some j x i j equals to one
and the another constraint is that uh
for all the uh device J you want to
basic
uh you you don't want the the the final
memory consumption exceeding any memory
budget that's why you have this Sigma
ixi j m i smaller than equal to MJ so
you have this three constraints and
because each XI J is binary this make
this entire problem comori and at the
same time the loss function is
nonlinear um because of system issues
right so there's a bing communication
lot different issues that will lead to
uh highly nonlinear Optive functions uh
that is pretty hard and tricky to deal
with for example if you use uh uh any
kind of optimization technique for
example genetic algorithms uh to solve
this problem it may take forever to even
find a feasible Solutions so then the
question is that maybe we should still
find us get like good optimization
problems optimization Solutions and at
the same time uh leveraging the existing
Comal Sol
so then what we can do is to instead of
solving the original problem in the
original space that is nonlinear we can
actually find a lat space such that the
problem become a little bit linear lat
space so what we do here is
that we first basically like try to
learn a c c c and uh basically this C
called C is a function of the problem
description one
so why is some description say like
maybe how many gpus do you have what are
the uh memory capabilities right so
these are basically the problem
descriptions so you first predict some
Sur cost and then give the Sur cost you
want to solve a linear problem which is
shown on the
right the linear problem will give you a
solution X star which is a function of Y
we around this linear problem uh the
final solution to optimize original
nonlinear optimization problems as much
as
possible so you have this kind of a
loop so how you going to solve this
problem it's actually very simple you
can just like a leverage green descent
optimization so here is basically the
computational graph of the good stand
ofs right so you first start from the
description why and that why I first get
into the Cal to c y and this will
basically give you zate coefficient C
and that c will be plugged into a solver
and that solver will give you a solution
that solution will be plug into
objective which give you the loss
function so uh in order to find what is
the best way to represent the uh Sate
coefficients and what we can do is that
we can do that propagation right so our
goal is to find okay what is the best
way to minimize your loss and I don't
care about all intermediate stages but I
just want to find what is the best way
to minimize the loss subject uh so that
uh uh the the the entire pipeline will
will be working right in order to do
that you want to find what is the best
way to specify the coefficiency
but what we can do is we can bate all
the way down and you can actually find
the optimal weights for that associate c
equal to Cy um uh
parameterizations okay so we should try
this ideas uh in this inviting table
shouting and this actually uh doing uh
quite well so what we what we can see
here is that so here there are two
tables or two figures the left figure
basically show the solution qualtity
right so you want the solution to be uh
as low as low loss as possible ideally
you want them to be zero that would be
the best one and uh and and on the on
the right you want also want to care
about the deployment run time you don't
want the deployment to be too slow so
you also want to also reduce the
deployment run time so in that case we
can actually leverage multiple
variations of our approach right so we
have this uh three variations one is
called Circle zero which should
basically do the B pration on the test
time which is slow of course but uh it
will give you good Solutions we also
have the circle prior uh which is
another valuation that directly learn
Cal to C y uh mapping and use the
mapping to directly predict the C and
call the solver once then you get a
solution you also have a hybrid version
of it which means that you first call uh
the the prior module to find the optimal
the initial value of c and you continue
optimizing the C over time so then what
we do what we see here is that our three
variations actually give you a very good
tradeoff between the solution loss and
the deployment time it's actually much
better in solution law compared to the
existing approaches right so this
include domistic uh greedy and also uh
the dream shot this is a kind of word
approach that use reinforcement to
optimize this non optimization
problems on the other hand in term of
deployment run time our uh s approaches
is also uh doing quite well uh
especially for the circle prior because
you only need to predict the uh the the
coefficient C uh in once then it's
actually much much faster and at the
same time the performance is also really
really
good we also apply the same idea to
other design problems so one industry
design problem is called inverse Photon
design so for that problem what we do
here is that you have this kind of very
small uh from 80 by 80 grid so this is
show on the top uh top middle so this
grid is super small as in the
nanometers and the goal of this design
is that once you send the lights to the
top you want the design to uh to change
the uh trace of the light so that it
will land onto different part of the
bottom uh depend on their
wavelength so the reason why this can be
can be done is because once you put
design in this very small nanometer
scale uh plate uh then we can actually
uh the light will basically behave like
a uh like a waves
and the Wes will interfere and the
defraction and defract at different
places so that the way the light the
light will go to different places at
different frequencies right so the
reason why we are not using any uh
mirror to do that is because uh the
place is so small that you cannot place
all the mirrors there you have to use
defraction and interference in order to
uh to make this happen we guide the lies
to different routes
then the optimization problem obviously
is very complicated right so the
optimization loss functions you want to
optimize you have to first do a
simulation uh given the current uh setup
of the design and given the simulation
you want to compute the frequ response
and then compute cutle frequencies and
compute all these um equations uh to
find overall loss quantities okay it's
high lar and but at the same time the
design space is cials because at every
entry of this 80 by 80 grid you can
choose either to put one or put zero
into this grid and this is a binary
problem of course but also you have
linear constraints which mean that you
want to uh find a feedable solution so
the design has to be implemented by a
brush right so when you manufacture the
object you have a brush to move these
things around in order to carve all this
design onto a plate so the size of the
brush become a a constraints now you
don't want to have one single dot out of
nowhere to be uh to be manufactured this
is not manufacturable so this actually
give you a different constraint that can
cannot be can be written as a linear
constraint uh but then the entire
problem actually become uh quite
complicated so there are several
different benchmarks that people are
thinking about right so you can try to
bend the light from Top all the way to
the left uh by using this kind of very
specific and nice align patterns you can
also uh basically like a split the light
into two different streams it's called a
beam splitter you can also do a other
kind of works like the wavelength
mpli so uh then we actually using our
approach uh we able to find the good
designs uh using this optimization
technique uh and uh basically this
basically show that our our approach
called Circle zero and circle hybrid
have a much smoother um uh basically
convergence curve compared to existing
approaches uh which called the pass
through so this is also a Gooden based
approach but there's no neur to involved
and this the the curve looks very
unstable and it takes a long time to
converge okay of course there are some
limitations of uh such approaches right
so first of all uh if the function f is
not differentiable what should we do and
also during the training we actually we
actually need to call or solver every
time so which is slow and you also
require solice
bable uh for this to we actually have uh
uh several followup work in order to
achieve this problems uh due to time
limitation uh I won't be able to tell
you the details but if you are
interested uh please feel free to reach
uh feel free to reach out feel to read
these papers and the code is already
online Okay so this concludes second
part uh which is basically hybrid
systems uh the hybrid system uh that can
uh use both the neur network the ler
models and also uh the and also the
solvers and in the last part of the
lecture I'm going to talk a little bit
about option three uh whether de models
can actually convert to anything
symbolic so this is actually something
that's can be very interesting because
we all know that there's actually two
different uh conflicting narrations in
uh in our daily debates in Twitter oex
right so there's one part of the people
who actually say oh El model can do
everything when the parameter of the
models become larger what you see is
you're going to see so manying behaviors
uh with more and more parameters so when
you have more and more parameters then
we will enjoy all these capabilities
without too much worry then we can just
sit down and do our un work and the
model we'll do en R AGI later that's one
way of uh uh seeing the entire
situations that's another different
directions a different kind of uh uh uh
opinions right so and you actually
people actually also think about
otherwise because from many experiments
uh what people actually see that uh
maybe Lang model is not doing anything
uh really intelligent right so
model is basically just doing retrievals
the reason why it is doing reasoning
reasonable well is because in training
set you already see uh good uh examples
right so Rec in apple apple actually
have one paper uh called GSM AK symbolic
that paper actually give you this kind
of examples that by adding irrelevant uh
topics irrelevant sentences uh into the
GSM AK data set all of a sudden you see
a huge job
of all the models performance on data
set right so uh it's actually very
surprising because uh the final answer
is not supposed to be changed after
these random sentences being inserted
but unfortunately all these models will
experience huge performance
drop okay then like uh how can we
actually address these problems right
how can we understand better why and
what kind of representation language
model is used to do the reasoning and
planning that's one of the core problem
that people may want to ponder on uh
doing the the career and the
studies so in order to achieve that so
here I give you one example about how we
should anal analyze and understand the
representation that is learned uh by the
uh uh by the natural language uh sorry
by by by the training of the lar models
here one simple case which is called the
modu Edition
this is a very simple uh uh read task
it's very simple right so you basically
given a and b you want to predict what
is C so basically predict the answer of
addition but the addition is a modular
which means that uh there's a mode D
here so if the C is too big it will wrap
back to the smaller number of uh that is
in between zero and D minus one okay so
for this task May Wonder it's very
simple right so there's only D to the D
square number of possible inputs so this
should be give you uh something uh
that's super simple then maybe the
network after train this model will have
implicit tables to do
retrials but actually it's not so what
happened here is that people actually
discover the Lear representation of such
a simple problem is a FL
basis so uh there's a many FS that
already show that large model once you
trend on this addition task they will
actually show uh this very nice s cosign
curves as a representation for different
numbers the question is why oh it's very
simple why you can see that so in order
to explore what's happening uh in in in
a very recent look that I did uh we
actually just use the two layer networks
to understand that behavior better so we
have two layer Networks bottom layer and
the top layer and the bottom layer
basically takes uh one H Plantation of A
and B and they are basically be sent
into the two weights matrices and they
add together and then they send to C
different hidden nodes each with
quadratic
activations and then this activations
will be sent to the top layer and it
will give you a oneall representation as
it will give you the output the output
will be compared with the one
representation of C very simple settings
and surprisingly you actually also see a
FL basis that is emerging from the
training so you order to understand
what's going on let's convert everything
to FL domain right obviously we should
do that then uh we'll make things much
easier to an analysis to to analyze so
you basically do the for transform then
you get Za a ZB zc you have all this uh
complex number
coefficients because this original wwwc
are real so so uh there are some
additional con conditions I need to hold
which Theiss conditions for the
associate complex uh uh numbers Z ZB and
zc okay so given all these settings
let's look at at how what the green
descent solution look like it's actually
very regular right so here that the
figure is two dimensional the xaxis is a
hidden node index so here you have a
very simple settings you have D equal =
to 7 and Q equals 20 so Q is the number
of hidden hidden neurons right so these
hidden neurons index from zero all the
way to
19 and for y axis that's the frequency
of the four transform right so what you
you see here is that for each frequency
there's actually a
few uh hi neurons that will show strong
uh frequencies at that particular
frequency k strong response of that's K
so if you check how many neurons are
showing strong uh correspond strong like
a response for that particular frequency
you can see that the number of that
number of neurons is having like a very
interesting structures so if you check
for each uh frequency K so for frequency
k equals to one you see there one two
three four five six there six neurons
that show super high response of thetic
frequency
or k equals 2 you also get one two three
four five six okay you get all the all
the six
Solutions of course you also will see
all the four Solutions so this is
another example right so for equ two you
see 1 2 3 four that's for the solution
but you also see some bias terms across
the other uh other
neurals and so far you have c order six
order four is there any other ERS answer
is interesting no
uh if you check the more statistics on
Green Solutions right so here the
statistics on D equal
23 so the figure to the left shows all
the tring curves right so and the right
shows like distribution of the orders uh
at different frequencies and you see
very sharp picks at four six four and
six right so in this uh figures very
clear and what happened to a larger uh
setups now we have like a three
different settings right so D equals to
23 D = 71 D equal
127 and also with different weight to
case so you see that most of cases you
still see two
paks uh uh order six and other
four unless that you have a very strong
weight decay in which like all the
solutions collaps into all zero which
means that there's no Solutions all
everything zero right so and other than
that you see like a strong Peaks there
okay then why so in this paper what we
see is that we actually come with a we
find a nice structure of the loss
function
solutions that structure can be useful
for general for expanding what's
happening there so first of all you want
to uh rewrite this Ms LW into this form
it has uh quite complicated terms right
has one minus term and also three terms
that are sum of squares okay and this
term is is representing in this way so
we have the red one and the the the blue
one oh sorry and the green one and
people are Wonder okay why want to write
this m laws into such an ugly form that
does seem to be
interesting but interestingly uh given
these forms we first can come with a
sufficient condition of the global
optimization Global Solutions right
obviously if you set this Ark to one and
all the sum of square terms to zero you
get Global optimization global uh
Solutions but then the question is like
why and how to achieve that the
objective is high than linear right
however in order to achieve that you can
actually leverage some very nice albic
structure as happening in the two layer
Network first of all we consider all the
spaces uh of two layer networks but with
different number of hidden nodes so this
space is Big Z it actually have nice
structures
the structure called semi- ring
structure if you define uh a ring
addition to be like a conition of two
hidden neural and multiplication being a
chronical product along the hidden
dimensions then this entire structure
become SAR ring and what makes this
interesting is that uh these two terms
that that is happening in the previous
loss functions they actually the ring
homomorphisms so what is ring
homomorphism it's actually very simple
basically you uh you want that basically
this function is a rorm if that
particular function respect the addition
and multiplication across ring and
normal addition multiplication then they
are doing
homop so what they what does that
implication is that um you actually will
see you can start with parti Solutions
so suppose Z1 is a paral solution that
only satisfy one single term of your
loss functions and Z2 is another partial
solution that only satisfy another
single term of your L Solutions okay
they are par solutions they are not the
entire solution but interestingly
because of the Ring structure if you
multiply these two together then the the
resulting Z will satisfy both of the uh
constraints at the same time
so what that mean what does that mean is
that you can actually start with some
par solutions that are very partial they
only satisfy some part of the
constraints but you can gradually
construct more and more complicated
Solutions with your multiplication and
your addition and then it will actually
give you the global optimization Global
op Global solutions to your original
loss functions right so the entire
process does not require gcent you just
construct this algebraically and then
you will give us you will get a solution
that is global optimal to the original
loss
functions so you can constru a solution
this way you constru solution like order
six by multiplying order three and order
two solution together and add over all
the possible frequencies you can also
construct all the four
Solutions and you also construct
solutions that correspond to the perfect
memorization which is actually all the
the solutions
so this conern solutions are nice but
people may Wonder okay how is this
related to the real world but this is in
some sense a symbolic and Abstract word
created by mathematicians we have
nothing to do with the real word
actually what happened here is that if
you compare the Green Solutions with the
solution that constructed previously we
can actually see an exact match between
the
two so first of all uh in this
particular settings uh you can see many
the almost basic all the prent solutions
there are all four or six which is
already shown in this uh
histogram and also if you pick this all
six all four Solutions and you try to
factorize them according to the previous
defined re multiplication and you
realize that 95% of the solution they
can be factorized into either 2x3 or 2
by two which is the same as the
construction that we previously did in
our experiment in our theoretical
construction and the facturation error
is small and finally if you check every
entries out the factorization what you
see is that 98% of solutions actually
can be factorizable into the constructed
forms they actually fall into the form
uh that we we constructed
previously so which mean that the Green
Solution match very well with the
construction
from the statical side that is quite
interesting and also if you check
distribution of the parameter in this
solutions you actually see very nice
regular structures right there sharp
peaks in different angles that
correspond to the higher symmetries so
this is something that's quite
interesting that haven't been explored
yet uh but that can be a nice uh fallout
papers to understand
better so what are all these uh
implications so first of all so it's
very kind of surprising that uh new
networks if you run GRE s on top of that
it will give you a solution that is very
simple very similar to symbolic
representation right so maybe in general
the new network or maybe large models
will also convert to some solution that
is symbolic that but we don't know about
we haven't constru that yet but here we
just give you example that an a
reasoning task will give you a solution
that is symbolic after the training with
green
Ascent right and second it will give you
a pass alternative pass towards the
solution other than green Ascent right
so you can think about green Ascent can
give you a solution but you can also
have some Advanced algebraic operation
that is also give you the same kind of
solutions so maybe in the future we
don't need GRE anymore we just need
altic constructions to combine small
solution to the larger Solutions and
then uh maybe great c will become
obsolete eventually so that's why I want
to uh introduce this part of work so
this might suggest a different path uh
compared to the existing path that we
have in the future instead of having
people praying about the distributed
system not working well we can open the
black box and have a principal approach
to do this thanks for your attention