so the thing that seems kind of amazing
um to me and us is the fact that well
actually this course was taught um just
last quarter and here we are with the
enormous number of people again taking
this class um I guess that says
something maybe approximately what it
says is chat
GPT um um
um but anyway it's great to have you all
lots of exciting content to have and um
hope you'll all enjoy it so let me get
started and um start telling you a bit
about the course um before diving
straight into um today's content um for
people still coming in you know there
are oodles of seats still right on
either side especially down near the
front there are tons of seats so um do
feel um empowered to go out and seek
those seats if other if people on the
corridors are really nice they could
even move towards the edges to make it
easier for people but um One Way or
Another feel free to find a seat okay so
this is the plan for what I want to get
through today so first of all I'm going
to tell you about the course for a few
minutes um then um have a few remarks
about human language and word meaning um
then the main technical thing we want to
get into today today is start learning
about the word Tove algorithm so the
word Tove algorithm is slightly over a
decade old now it was introduced in um
2013 but it was a wildly successful
simple way of learning Vector
representations of words so I want to
show you um that as a sort of a first
easy baby system for the kind of neural
representations that we're going to talk
about in class um with then going to get
more concrete with that looking at its
objective function gradients and
optimization and then hopefully if all
goes I stick to schedule spend a few
minutes just um playing around an i
python notebook um huh I'm going to have
to change computers for that um than um
sort of um seeing some of the things you
can do with this okay so this is the um
course Logistics and brief I'm
Christopher Manning hi again everyone um
the head ta is who unfortunately has a
bit of a health problem so he's not
actually here today um we've got a
course manager for the course who
is who is up the back there um and then
we've got a whole um lot of teas if
you're a TA who's here you could stand
up and wave or something like that so
people can see a few of the Tas and see
some friendly faces um okay we've got
some Tas um and some other ones and so
you can look at them on the website um
if you're here you know what time the
class is um there's an email list but
preferably don't use it and use the Ed
site that you can find on the course
website so the main place to go and look
for information is the course website
which we've got up here and that then
links in to Ed which is what we're going
to use as the main discussion board
please use that rather than sending
emails um to um the first assignment for
this class it's a sort of an easy one
it's the warm-up assignment but we want
to get people busy and doing stuff um
straight away so the first assignment is
already live on the web page and it's
due next Tuesday before class so um
you're slightly less than seven days
left to do it um so do get started on
that um and to help with that um we're
going to be immediately starting office
hours um tomorrow and they're also
described on the website um we also do a
few tutorials on Friday um the first of
these tutorials is a tutorial on Python
and numpy um many people don't need that
because they've done other classes and
done this um but for some people we try
and make this class accessible to
everybody so if you'd like to um brush
up a bit on python or how to use numpy
it's a great thing to go along to and
who's right over there is going to be
teaching it on Friday
today okay what do we hope to teach you
know at the end of the quarter when you
get the evow you'll be asked to rate
whether this class met its learning
goals these are my learning goals um
what are they so the first one um is to
teach you about the foundations and
current methods for using deep learning
applied to natural language processing
so this class
tries to sort of build up from the
bottom up so we start off doing simple
things like word vectors and feed
forward neural networks recurrent
networks and attention we then fairly
quickly move into the kind of key
methods they Ed for NLP um in
2024 I wrote down here Transformers and
coder decoder models I probably should
have written large language models
somewhere in this list as well um but
then pre-training and post-training of
large language models adaptation model
interpretability agents Etc but that's
not the only thing that we want to do so
there are a couple of other things that
we crucially want to achieve um the
second is to give you
some understanding of human languages
and the difficulties in understanding
and producing them on computers now
there are few of you in this class who
are Linguistics Majors or perhaps the
symbolic systems Majors yay to the
symbolic systems Majors but for quite a
few of the rest of you um you'll never
see any uh Linguistics in the sense of
understanding how language Works apart
from this class so we do want to try and
convey a little bit of a sense of what
some of the issues are in language
structure and why it's proven to be
quite difficult um to get computers to
understand human languages even though
humans seem very good at learning to
understand each other and then the final
thing that we want to make it on to um
is actually concretely Building Systems
so that this isn't just a theory class
that we actually want you to leave this
class thinking oh yeah in my first job
wherever you go whether it's a startup
or a big Tech or um some nonprofit oh
there's something they want to do that
they'd like that would be useful if we
had a text classification system or we
did information extraction to get some
kind of facts out of documents I know to
build that I can build that system
because I did
cs224n okay um here's how you get graded
um so we have four assignments mainly
one and a half weeks long apart from the
first one they make up almost half the
grade the other half of the grade is
made up of a final project which there
are two variants of a custom or default
final project which we'll get on to in a
minute um and then there's a few percent
that go for
participation um six late
days um collaboration policy um like all
other CS classes we've had issues with
people not doing their own work we
really do want you to learn things in
this class and the way you do that is by
doing your own work um so make sure you
understand that um and so for the
assignments everyone is expected to do
their own assign assignments um you can
talk to your friends but you're expected
to do your own assignment for the final
project you can do that as a group um
then we have the issue of um AI tools
now of course in this class we love
large language models but nevertheless
we don't want you to do your assignments
by saying hey chat GPT could you answer
question three for me um that is not the
way to learn things um if you want to
make use of um AI as a tool to assist
you such as for coding assistance go for
it um but we're wanting you to be
working out how to answer assignment
questions by
yourself okay so this is what the
assignments look like so assignment one
is meant to be an easy onramp and it's
done as a Jupiter notebook assignment
two um then has people uh you know what
can I say here we are at this fine
liberal artarts and Engineering
institution we're not at a coding boot
camp so we hope that people have some
deep understanding of how things work so
in assignment two we actually want you
to do some math and understand how
things work in neural networks um so for
some people assignment to is the
scariest assignment in the whole class
um but then it's also the place where we
introduce py talk which is software
package we use for building newal
networks and we build a dependency paa
which we'll get to later as something
more linguistic um then for assignment
three and four we move on to larger
projects using pytorch with gpus and
we'll be making use of Google cloud and
um for those two assignments um we look
at doing machine translation and getting
information um out with Transformers and
then these are the two final project
options so essentially you know we have
a default final project where we give
you a lot of scaffolding and an outline
of what to do but um it's still an
open-ended project there are lots of
different things you can try to make
this system work better and we encourage
you to explore um but nevertheless
you're given a leg up from quite a lot
of um scaffolding we'll talk about this
more but you can either do that option
or you can just come up with totally
your own project and do
that okay that's the course any
questions on the
course yes for the final project how are
mentors assigned um so if you if you can
find your own Mentor your interest in
something and there's someone that's
happy to Mentor you that person can be
your Mentor otherwise one of the course
Tas will be your mentor and how that
person is assigned is uh one of the T
who is in charge of final projects
assigns people and they do the best they
can in terms of finding people with some
expertise and having to divide all the
students across the mentors roughly
equally any other
questions okay I'll power ahead um human
language and word
meaning um so let me just sort of um say
a little bit about the big picture here
um so we're in the area of artificial
intelligence and we've got this idea
that humans are intelligent and then
there's the question of you know how
does language um fit into that and you
know this is something that there is
some argument about and if you want to
you can run off in onto social media and
read some of the arguments about these
things and contribute to it um if you
wish too um but here is my perhaps bias
take as a linguist um well you can
compare human beings um to some of our
nearest neighbors like chimpanzees
bonobos and things like that and you
know well one big distinguishing thing
is we have language and they don't um
but you know in most other respects um
chimps are very similar human beings
right you know in they they can use
tools they can plan how to solve things
um they've got really good memory um
chimps have better short-term memory
than human beings do right so that in
most respects it's hard to show an
intelligence difference between chimps
and people except for the fact that we
have language but us having language has
been this enormous differentiator right
that if you look around um what happened
on the planet you know that there are
creatures that are stronger than us
faster than us more venomous than us
have every possible Advantage um but
human beings took over the whole place
and how did that happen we had language
um so we could communicate and that
communication allowed us to have human
ascendency but I'd like to me so one big
role of language is the fact fact that
it allows communication but I'd like to
suggest it's actually not the only role
of language that language has also
allowed humans I would argue to achieve
a higher level of thought so there are
various kinds of thoughts that you can
have without any language involved you
know you can think about a scene you can
move some bits of furniture around in
your mind and there's no language and
obviously emotional responses of feeling
scared or excited
they happen and there's no language
involved but you know I think most of
the time when we're doing higher level
cognition um if you're thinking to
yourself oh gee my friend seemed upset
about what I said last night my should
probably work out how to fix that or
maybe I could BL BL BL BL I think we
think in language and plan out things
and so that it's given us a scaffolding
to do much more detailed thought and
planning
most recently of all of course human
beings invented ways to write um and
that led so writing is really really
recent I mean no one really knows how
old human languages are you know most
people think a few 100,000 years not
very long by evolutionary time scales
but writing we do know writing is really
really recent so writing is about 5,000
years old um and so but you know writing
proved to be this um again this amazing
cognitive tool that just gave Humanity
an enormous leg up because Suddenly It's
Not only that you could share
information and learn from the people
that were standing within 50 feet of you
you could then um share knowledge across
time and space so really um having
writing was enough to take us from the
Bronze Age very simple um metal working
to the kind of um you know mobile phones
and all the other technology that we
walk around with today in just a very
short amount of time so language is
pretty
cool um but it's you know one shouldn't
only fixate on um the sort of knowledge
side of language and how that's made um
human beings great I mean there's this
other side of language where language is
this very flexible system which is used
as a social tool by human beings um so
that we can speak with a lot of
imprecision and nuance and emotion in
language and we can get people to
understand we can set up sort of new
ways of thinking about things by using
words for them and languages aren't
static languages change as human beings
use them that languages aren't something
that would delivered down on Tablets by
God languages are things that humans
constructed and humans changed them with
each success of generation and indeed
most of the innovation in language
happens among young people you know
people that are either a few years
younger than you are most of you are now
um in their um earlier teens going into
the 20s right that's a big period of
linguistic Innovation where people think
up cool new phrases and ways of saying
things and some of those get embedded
and extended and that then becomes the
future of language um so um herb Clark
used to be a um psychologist um at
Stanford he's now retired but he had
this rather um nice quote the common
misconception is that language use has
primarily to do with words and what they
mean it doesn't it has primarily to do
with people and what they
mean okay so that's language and two
slides for you um so now we'll skip
ahead to deep learning so in the last
decade or so we've been able to make um
fantastic progress in doing more with
computers understanding um human
languages um in using deep learning
we'll say a bit more about the history
later on but you know work on trying to
do things with human language started in
the 1950s so it had been sort of going
for 60 years or so and you know there
was some stuff it's not that nobody
could do anything but you know the
ability to understand and produce
language had always been kind of
questionable where it's really in the
last decade with new networks that just
enormous strides of progress have been
made um and that's led into the world
that we have today so one of the first
big breakthroughs came in the area of
using um neural NLP systems for machine
translation and so this started about
2014 and was already deployed live on
services like Google by 2016 it was so
good that it saw really really rapid um
commercial deployment and I mean overall
this kind of facility um with machine
translation just means that you're
growing up in such a different world um
to people a few Generations back right
people a few Generations back um that
unless you actually knew different
languages of different people you sort
of had no chance to communicate with
them where um now we're very close to
having something like the Babel Fish
from Hitchhiker's Guide to the Galaxy um
for understanding all languages it's
just it's not a Babel Fish it's a cell
phone but you know you can have it out
between two people and have it do
simultaneous translation and you know
it's not perfect people keep on doing
research on this but um you know by and
large it means you can pick anything up
from different areas of the world um as
you can see this example is from a
couple of years ago since it's still
from the um Co pandemic era but you know
I can um see this um Swahili from Kenya
and say oh gee I wonder what that means
stick it into Google translate and um I
can learn that Malawi um lost two
ministers due to um Co infections and
they died right so you know we're just
in this different era of being able to
understand stuff and then there are lots
of other things that we can do with
modern NLP so until a few years ago um
we had web search engines and you put in
some text you could write it as a
sentence if you wanted to but it didn't
really matter whether you wrote a
sentence or not because what you got was
some keywords that were then matched
against index and you were shown some
pages that might have the answers to
your questions but these days um you can
put an actual question into a modern
search engine like when did Kendrick
Lamar's first album come out it can go
and find documents that have relevant
information it can read those documents
and it can give you an answer so that it
actually can become an answer engine
rather than just something that finds
documents that might be relevant to what
you're interested in and the way that
that's done is with big neural networks
so that you might commonly have um for
your query you've got a retrieval neural
network which can find passages that are
similar to The query they might then be
reranked by a second neural network and
then there'll be a third reading neural
network that'll read those passages um
and synthesize information from them
which it then returns as the
answer okay that gets to about
2018 um but then things got more
advanced again so it was really around
2019 that people started to see the
power of large language models and so
back in
2019 those of us in NLP were really
excited about
gpt2 um it didn't make much of an impact
on the Nightly News but it was really
exciting an NLP land um because gpt2
already for the first time time meant
here was a large language model that
could just generate fluent text that
really until then um NLP systems had
done sort of a decent job at
understanding certain facts out of text
but we've just never been able to
generate fluent text that was at all
good um where here what you could do
with gpt2 is you could um write
something like the start of a story a
train Carriage containing controlled
nuclear materials was stolen in cincin
today its whereabouts are unknown and
then GPT 2 would just write a
continuation the incident occurred on
the downtown train line which runs from
Covington ashin stations in an email to
Ohio news outlets the US Department of
energy set is working with the Federal
Railroad Administration to find the
Thief dot dot dot and so the way this is
working is this conditioning on all the
past material and as I show at the very
bottom line down here it's generating
one word at a time as to what word it
thinks would be likely to come next
after that um and so from that simple
method of sort of generating words out
of U one after another it's able to
produce excellent text and the thing to
notice is I mean this text is not only
kind of you know formally correct you
know not the spellings correct and the
sentences are real sentences not
disconnected garbage but you know it
actually understands a lot right so the
prompt that was written said there were
stolen nuclear materials in Cincinnati
but you know gpt2 knows a lot of stuff
it knows that Cincinnati is in Ohio it
knows that in the United States it's the
department of energy that regulates
nuclear materials um it knows if
something is stolen it's a theft and
that that would um make sense that um
people are getting involved with that um
it talks about you know there's train
Carriage So it's talking about the train
line where it goes it really knows a lot
and can write you know coherent
discourse um like a real story so that's
kind of amazing um but you know things
moved on from there and so now we're in
the world of chat GPT and
gp4 and one of the things that we will
talk about later is this was a huge huge
user success because now you could ask
questions or give it commands and it
would do what you wanted and that was
further amazing so here I'm saying hey
please draft a polite email to my boss
Jeremy that I would not be able to come
into the office for the next two days
because my 9-year-old song that's a
misspelling for son but the system works
fine Des spite it um Peter is angry with
me that I'm not giving him much time
and it writes a nice email um it
corrects the spelling mistake because it
knows people make spelling mistakes it
doesn't talk about songs and everything
works out beautifully um you can get it
to do other things so you can um ask it
what is unusual about this image um so
in thinking about meaning one of the
things that's interesting with these
recent models um is that they're
multimodal and can operate across modes
and so um a favorite term that we coined
at Stanford is the term Foundation
models which we use as a generalization
of large language models to have the
same kind of technology used across
different modalities images sound um
various kinds of bioinformatic things
DNA RNA things like that seismic waves
any kind of signal building these same
kind of large
models another place that you can see
that um is going from text to images um
so if I asked for a picture of a train
going over the Golden Gate Bridge um
this is now um darly 2 um it gives me a
picture of a train going over the Golden
Gate Bridge um this is a perfect time to
welcome anyone who's watching this um on
Stanford online um if you're on Stanford
online and are not in the Bay Area the
important thing to know is no trains go
over the Golden Gate Bridge um but you
might not be completely happy with this
picture um because you know it shows the
Golden Gate Bridge and a train going
over it but it doesn't show the bay so
maybe I'd like to um get with the bay in
the background and if I ask for that
well look now I've got um a train going
over the Golden Gate Bridge with the bay
in the background but you still might
not be this this might not be exactly
what you want like maybe you'd prefer
something that's a pencil drawing so I
can say a train going over the Golden
Gate Bridge detailed pencil drawing and
I can get a pencil drawing um or maybe
it's unrealistic that the Golden Gate
Bridge only has trains going over it now
um so maybe it be good to have some cars
as well um so I could ask for a train
and cars and we can get a train and cars
going over it um now I actually made
these ones all by myself so should be
impressed with my generative AI artwork
um but these examples are actually a bit
old now because they're done with DAR 2
and if you keep up with these things
that's a few years ago there now Dary 3
and so on so we can now get much fancier
things again right an illustration from
a graphic novel a bustling City street
under the shine of a full moon the
sidewalks bustling with pedestrians
enjoying the night life at the corner
stall a young woman with fiery red hair
dressed in a signature velvet cloak is
haggling with the grumpy old vendor the
grumpy vendor a tall sophisticated man
is wearing a sharp suit Sports a
noteworthy mustache is animatedly
conversing on his steampunk telephone
and pretty much um we're getting all of
that okay um so let's now get on to
starting to think more about meaning so
perhaps um what can we do for meaning
right so if you think of words and there
meaning um if you look up a dictionary
and say what does meaning mean um
meaning is defined as the idea that is
represented by a word or phrase the idea
that a person wants to express by using
words the idea that is expressed um and
in in linguistics you know if you go and
do a semantics class or something the
commonest way of thinking of of meaning
is somewhat like what's presented up
above there that meaning is thought of
as a pairing between what sometimes
called signifier and signified but it's
perhaps easy to think of as a symbol a
word and then an idea or thing and so
this notion is referred to as
denotational semantics so the idea or
thing is the denotation of the symbol
and so this same idea of denotational
semantics has also been used for
programming languages because in
programming languages you have symbols
like while and if
variables and they have a meaning and
that could be their
denotation um so we sort of would say
that the meaning of tree is all the
trees you can find out around the world
um that's sort of a okay notion of
meaning um it's a popular one it's never
been very
obvious or at least traditionally it
wasn't very obvious as of what we could
do with that to get it into computers so
if you looked in the pre-neural world
when people tried to look at meanings
inside computers they sort of had to do
something much more primitive of looking
at words and their relationship so a
very common traditional solution was to
make use of word net and word net was
kind of a sort of fancy thesaurus that
showed word relations so i' tell you
about synonyms and is a kind of things
um so a panda is a kind of carnivore
which is a placental which is a m
and things like that good has various
meanings it's a trade good or the sense
of goodness and you could explore with
that but systems like wordnet um were
never very good for computational
meaning um they missed a lot of nuance
wordnet would tell you that proficient
is a synonym for good but if you think
about all the things that you would say
were good you know that was a good shot
would you say that was a proficient shot
sounds kind of weird to me um you know
there's a lot of color and Nuance on how
words are used um word net is very
incomplete it's missing anything that's
kind of cooler more modern slang this
maybe isn't very modern slang now but
you won't find more modern slang either
in it it's sort of very human-made Etc
it's got a lot of issues so um this led
into the idea of can we represent
meaning differently and this leads us
into word
vectors um so when we have words Wicked
badass Nifty wizard what do they turn
into when we have
computers um well
effectively um you know words are these
discrete symbols um that they're just
kind of some kind of atom or symbol and
if we then turn those into something
that's closer to math um how symbols are
normally rep presented is you have a
vocabulary and your word is some item in
that vocabulary so Motel is the that
word in the vocabulary and hotel is this
word in the vocabulary and commonly this
is what computational systems do you
take all your strings and you index them
to numbers and that's the sort of
position in a vector that they belong in
um and well we have huge numbers of
words so we might have a huge vocabulary
so we'll have very big and long vectors
and so these get referred to as one hot
vectors um for representing the meaning
of words um but
representing words by one hot vectors
turns out to not be a very good way of
computing with them it was used for
decades um but it turns out to be kind
of problematic and part of why it's
problematic is it doesn't have any
natural inherent sense
of the meanings of words you just have
different words you have hotel and motel
and house and chair and so if you think
about in terms of these Vector
representations that if you have motel
and hotel there's no indication that
they're kind of similar they're just two
different symbols which have ones in
different positions in the vector or
formally in math terms um if you think
about taking the dotproduct of these two
vectors zero um the two vectors are
orthogonal they have nothing to do with
each other now there are things that you
can do with that you can start saying oh
let me start building up some other
resource of word similarity and I'll
consult that resource of word similarity
and it'll tell me that motels and hotels
are similar to each other and people did
things like that right in web search it
was referred to as query expansion
techniques um but still the point is
that there's no natural notion of
similarity in one hot
vectors um and so the the idea was that
maybe we could do better than that that
we could learn to include similarity in
the vectors themselves and so that leads
into the idea of word vectors um but it
also leads into a different way of
thinking about semantics um I just
realized I forgot to say one thing back
two slides um these kind of
representations are referred to as
localist representations meaning that
there's one point in which um something
is represented so that um you've got
here is the representation of motel and
here is the representation of Hotel it's
in one place in the vector that each
word is represented and they'll be
different to what we do next um so
there's an alternative idea of semantic
um which goes back quite a long way
people commonly quote this quote of Jr F
who was a British linguist who said in
1957 you shall know a word by the
company it keeps but also goes back to
philosophical work by binstein and
others that what you should do is
represent a word's meaning by the
context in which it appears um so the
words that appear around the word give
information
um about its meaning and so that's the
idea of what's called distributional
semantics in contrast to denotational
semantics so if I want to know about the
word banking I say give me some
sentences that use the word banking here
are some sentences using the word
banking government debt problems turning
into banking crises as happened in 2009
etc etc and knowing about that context
words that occur around banking
those will become the meaning of banking
and so we're going to use those
statistics um about words and what other
words appear around them in order to
learn a new kind of representation of a
word so our new representation of words
is we're going to represent them now as
a dense a sort of a shorter dense Vector
that giv the meaning of the words now my
vectors are very short here um these are
only eight dimensional if I counted
right so I could fit them on my slide
they're not that short in practice they
might be 200 2,000 but reasonably short
they're not going to be like the half a
million of the half a million different
words in our vocabulary and the idea is
if words have stuff to do with each
other um they'll have sort of similar
vectors which corresponds to their dot
product being large so for Banking and
monetary in my example here both of them
are positive in the First Dimension
positive in the second dimension
negative on the third on the fourth
they've got opposite signs so if we want
to work out the dot product we're taking
the product of the corresponding terms
and it'll get bigger to the extent that
both of the corresponding ones have the
same sides and bigger if they have large
um
magnitude Okay so these are what we call
word vectors which are also known as
embeddings or newal word representations
or phrases like that and so the first
thing we want to do is learn good word
vectors for different words and our word
vectors will be good word vectors if um
they give us a good sense of the
meanings of words they know which words
are similar to other words in meaning
um we refer to them as
embeddings um because we can think of
this as a vector in a high dimensional
space and so that we're embedding each
word as a position in that
high-dimensional space and the
dimensionality of the space um will be
the length of the vector so it might be
something like a 300 dimensional space
um now that kind of gets problematic
because human beings can't look at 300
dimensional spaces and aren't very good
at understanding or visualizing what
goes on in them so the only thing that I
can show you is um two-dimensional
spaces but um a thing that is good to
have somewhat in your head is that
really high-dimensional spaces behave
extremely differently to two-dimensional
spaces in high dimensional spaces things
can in a two-dimensional space you're
only near to something else if you got
similar X and Y coordinates in a high
dimensional space things can be very
near to all sorts of things on different
dimensions in the space and so we can
capture different senses of words and
ways that words are similar to each
other um but here's the kind of picture
we end up with so we're what we're going
to do is learn a way to um represent all
words as vectors based on the other
words that they within context and we
can embed them into this Vector space
and of course you can't read anything
there but you know we can zoom into this
space further and if we zoom into this
space and just show a bit of it well
here's a part of the space um where it's
showing um country words and some other
location words so we've got so of um
countries up the top there we've got
some nationality terms British
Australian American European um further
down or we can go to another piece of
the space and here's a bit of the space
um where we have verbs and not only if
we got verbs but you know there's
actually quite quite a lot of fine
structure here of what's similar that
represents things about verbs so you've
got um sort of verbs of you know
communication statements saying thinking
expecting grouping together come and go
group together down the bottom you've
got forms of the verb have then you've
got forms of the verb to be above them
you've got become and remain which are
actually sort of similar to the verb to
be um because they take these sort of
complements of state so just that you
can same as you can say I am angry you
can say he remained angry or he became
angry right so those verbs are more so
than most verbs sort of similar to the
verb to be so we get these kind of
interesting semantic spaces where things
that have similar meaning are close by
to each other and so the question is how
do we get to those things and how we get
to those things is then um for you know
that there are various ways of doing it
but the one I want to get through um
today is showing you about um word DEC
okay I'll pause for 30 seconds for bread
breath anyone have a question or
anything they want to know yes
so but it doesn't to solve the problem
where the similar meanings um might
depend on context right so let's take
your example about profession
ver so those two words have their own
batteries and we understand similarity
some spectors but it's contact right
because if you have different contact
those two similar and this Al does
not yes correct um so that's a good
thought you can keep it for a few weeks
to some extent yeah so for the first
thing we're going to do we're just going
to learn one word Vector for a string so
we're going to have a word let's say
it's star and we're going to learn one
word Vector for it so that absolutely
doesn't capture the meaning of a word in
context so it won't be saying whether
it's meaning a Hollywood star or an
astronomical star or something like that
and so later on we're going to get on to
contextual meaning representation so
wait for that but the thing I would like
to going along with what I said about
high dimensional spaces being weird the
the cool thing that we will already find
is our representation for Star will be
very close to um the representations for
astronomical words like nebula um and
what other every other astronomical
words you know and
simultaneously um it'll be um very close
to words that mean something like a
Hollywood star
um help me out no any words that mean
something similar um celebrity that's a
good one okay yeah how are youing the
Bing is to a lower dimensional space
visualized um so that pictures I was
showing you used a particular method
called tne um which is a nonliner
dimensionality reduction that tends to
work better for high dimensional new
representations um then PCA which you
might know um but I'm not going to go
into that now yes um how do you know Di
but not
too I mean that's something that people
have worked on it depends on how much it
depends on how much data you've got to
make your representations over you know
so normally you know it's worked out
either empirically for what works best
or practically based on how big vectors
you want to work on I mean to give you
some idea you know things start to work
well when you get to 100 dimensional
space for a long time people used 300
Dimensions because that seemed to work
pretty well but as we people have
started building Huger and Huger models
with way way more data it's now become
increasingly common to use numbers like
1,000 or even 2,000 dimensional vectors
yeah
okay so um you mentioned that there sort
of hidden structur the small areas as
well as large areas of the embeding and
as in pieces different like different
structures will come up but generally we
seem to use distance as the single
metric for closeness which doesn't seem
to me that we get it like distance
between like this and that in space
three will be the same right so how
would that we don't only use distance we
also use directions in the spaces having
semantic meanings and I'll show a
example that soon
yeah the entri they seem to be between1
and one is there a reason for that or do
we have bounds that we them um so good
question I mean you know they don't have
to be um and the way we're going to
learn them they're not bounded but you
know you can bound things sometimes
people length normalize so that um the
vectors are of length one but at any
rate normally in this work we use some
method called you know regularization
that tries to kind of keep coefficients
small so they're generally not getting
huge yeah a specific word for example
like the bank we use as before in the
previous slides um so is there like a
like for the word representation is
there like a single embedding for each
word or do we have multiple embeddings
for each word but what we're doing at
the moment each word each string of
letters has a single embed in and what
you can think of that embedding as as
kind of as an average over all its
senses um so for example like Bank it
can mean like the financial institution
or it can also mean like the river B and
then what I said before about star
applies the interesting thing is you'll
find that we're able to come up with a
representation where our learned
representation because it's kind of an
average of those will end up similar to
words that are semantically evoked by
both senses um I think I probably about
about go on at this point um okay word
to ve okay so word Tove was this method
of learning word vectors um that was
thought up by tamas mikolov and
colleagues at Google um in
2013 you know it wasn't the first method
there are other people that did methods
of learning word vectors that go back to
about um the turn of the Millennium um
it wasn't the last there ones that come
after it as well but it was a
particularly simple one um and this
particularly you know fast running one
and so it really caught people's um
attention so the idea of it is um that
we start off with a large amount of text
so that can just be thought of as a long
list of words and in l p we refer to
that as a corpus Corpus um is just Latin
for body um so you know it's exactly the
same as if you have a dead person on the
floor right that's a corpus no um yeah
so it's just a body but we mean a body
of text um not a live person oh sorry a
dead person um yeah um if you want to
know more about Latin um since some
there isn't very good classical
education these days um Corpus despite
the US ending is a fourth declen neuter
noun and that means um the plural of
Corpus is not corpy the plural of Corpus
is corpora um so I'm sure sometime later
in this class I will read a projector
assignment that refers to corpy and I
will know that that person was not
paying attention um in the first lecture
um or else they should have said corpora
um c r p o r a is the correct um form
for that okay I should move on okay so
we have our text then we know um that
we're going to represent each word so
this is each word type so you know star
or Bank Etc so for wherever it occurs by
a single vector and so what we're going
to do in this algorithm is we're going
to go through each position in the text
and so at each position in the text
which is a list of words we're going to
have a center word and words outside it
um and then what we're going to do is
use the similarity of the word vectors
for C and the outside words to calculate
the probability that they should have
occurred or not um and then we just keep
fiddling and we learn ve word vectors
now you know at First Sight I'll show
this more concretely maybe I'll just
show up more concretely first so here's
the idea we're going to have um a vector
for each word type so a word type means
you know the word problems wherever it
occurs which is differentiated from a
word token which is this instance of the
word problems so we're going to have a
vector for each word type and so I'm
going to want to know look in this text
the word turning occurred before
occurred before the word into How likely
should that have been to happen and what
I'm going to do is calculate a
probability of the word turning
occurring close to the word into and I'm
going to do that for each word in a
narrow context in example here I'm
saying I'm using two words to the left
and two words to the right and what I
want to do is make those probability
estimates as good as possible so in
particular I want the probability of
cooccurrence to be high for words that
actually do occur within the nearby
context of each other and so then the
question is how am I going to oh and
once I've done it for that word I'm
going to go along and do exactly the
same thing for the next
word and so I'll can continue through
the text in that way and so what we want
to do is come up with vector
representations of words that will let
us predict these probabilities quote
unquote well now you know there's a huge
limit to how well we can do it because
you know we've got a simple model
obviously when you see the word banking
I can't tell you that the word into is
going to occur before banking but you
know I want to do it as well as possible
so what I want my model to say is after
the word banking crisis is pretty likely
um but the word skillet is not very
likely and if I can do that I'm doing a
good job and so we turn that into a
piece of math um here's how we do it
turn it into a piece of math so we're
going to go through our Corpus every
position in the Corpus um and we're
going to have a fixed window size M
which was two in my example and then
what we you're going to want to do is
have the probability of words in the
context um being as high as possible so
we want to maximize this likelihood
where we're going through every position
in the text and then we're going through
every word in the context and sort of
wanting to make this
big okay so conceptually that's what
we're doing but in practice um we never
quite do that um we um use two little
tricks here um the first one is you know
for completely arbitrary reasons it
really makes no difference um everyone
got into minimizing things rather than
maximizing things and so the algorithms
that we use get referred to as gradient
descent as you'll see in a moment so the
first thing we do um is put a minor sign
in front so that we can minimize it
rather than maximize it that part's
pretty trivial
but the second part is here we have this
enormous product and working with
enormous products is more difficult for
the math so the second thing that we do
is introduce a logarithm and so once we
take the log of the likelihood um that
then um when we take logs of products
they turn into sums and so now we can
sum over each word position the text sum
over for each word in the context window
and then sum these log probabilities and
then we still got the minus sign in
front so we want to minimize the sum of
log probabilities so what we're doing is
um then wanting to look at the negative
log
likelihood um and then the final thing
that we do is you know to since this
will get um bigger depending on the
number of words in the Corpus um we
divide through by the number of words in
the Corpus and so our objective function
is the average negative log likelihood
um so by minimizing this objective
function we're maximizing the
probability of words in the
context okay um we're almost there
that's what we want to do um we've got a
couple more tricks that we want to get
through the next one is well I've said
we want to maximize the this probability
how do we maximize this probability what
is this probability we haven't defined
how we're going to calculate this
probability and this is where the word
vectors come in so we're going to Define
this
probability in terms of the word Vector
so we're going to say each word type is
represented by a vector of real numbers
these are 100 real numbers and we're
going to have a formula that works out
the probability simply in terms of the
vectors of for each um word that there
are no other parameters in this model so
over here I've shown this Theta which
are the parameters of our model and all
and only the parameters of our model are
these word vectors for each word in the
vocabulary that's a lot of parameters
because we have a lot of words and and
we've got fairly big word vectors but
they are the only parameters
okay and how we do that is um by using
this little um trick here we're going to
say the probability of an outside word
given a center word is going to be
defined in terms of the dotproduct of
the two word vectors so if things have a
high dot product they'll be similar and
therefore they'll have a high
probability of cooccurrence where I mean
similar in a kind of a weird sense right
it is the case that we're going to want
to say hotel and motel are similar but
you know it's also the case that we're
going to want to have the word the able
to appear easily before the word student
so in some weird sense the also has to
be similar to student um that has to be
similar to basically any noun right um
okay so we're going to work witht
products and then we do this funky
little bit of math here and that will
give us our probability
ities okay so let's just go through the
funky bit of math um so here's our
formula for the
probabilities so what we're doing here
is we're starting off with this dot
product right so the dot product is you
take the two vectors you multiply each
component together and you sum them so
if they both the same sign that
increases your dot product and if
they're both big and increases it a lot
okay so that gives us a similarity
between two vectors and that's unbounded
that's that's just a real number it can
be either negative or positive okay but
what we'd like to get out is a
probability so for our next tricks we
first of all exponentiate because if we
take um e to X for any X we now have to
get something positive out right that's
what exponentiation does okay and then
well since it's meant to be a
probability we'd like it to be between 0
and 1 and so we turn it into numbers
between 0 and one in the dumbest way
possible which is we just normalize so
that we work out the quantity in the
numerator for every possible context
word um and so we get the total of all
of those numbers and divide through by
it and then we're getting a probability
distribution of How likely different
words are in this context
text okay um yeah so that this little
trick that we're doing here is referred
to as the softmax function so for the
softmax function you can take um
unbounded real numbers put them through
this little softmax trick that we just
went through the steps of and what
you'll get out is a probability
distribution so I'm now getting in this
example uh probability distribution over
context words my probability estimates
over all the context words in my
vocabulary will sum up to one by
definition by the way that I've con
constructed this um so it's called the
softmax function because it amplifies
the probabilities of the largest things
that's because of the um the X function
but it's soft because it still assigns
some probability to smaller items but
you know it's sort of a funny name
because you know when you think about um
max I mean Max normally picks out just
one thing whereas the soft Max is
turning a bunch of real numbers into a
probability
distribution um so this soft Max is used
everywhere um in deep learning any time
that we're wanting to turn things that
are just vectors in RN into
probabilities we shove them through a
soft Max
function okay
um so
so in some sense this part I think still
seems very abstract and I mean the
reason it seems very abstract is um
because I've sort of said we have
vectors for each word and using these
vectors
we can then calculate
probabilities um but where do the
vectors come from and the answer to
where the vectors are going to come from
is we're going to turn this into an
optimization problem we have a large
amount of text and so therefore we can
hope to find word vectors that make the
contexts of the words in our observed
text as big as possible so literally
what we're going to do is we're going to
start off with random vectors for every
word and then we want to fiddle those
vectors so that the calculated
probabilities of words in a context go
up and we're going to keep fiddling
until they stop going up anymore and
we're getting the highest probability
estimates um that we can and the way
that we do that fiddling um is we use
calculus um so you know what we're going
to do is kind of conceptually exactly
what you do if you're in something like
a two-dimensional space like the picture
on the right right that if you want to
find the minimum in this two-dimensional
space and you start off at the top left
what you can do is say let me work out
the derivatives of the function um at
the top left and they sort of Point sort
of down and a bit to the right and so
you can walk down and a bit to the right
and you can say oh G given where I am
now um let me work out the derivatives
what direction do they point and they're
still pointing down but a bit more to
the right so you can walk a bit further
that way and you can keep on walking and
eventually you'll make it to the minimum
of the space um in our case um we've got
a lot more than two Dimensions so our
parameters for our model are the
concatenation of all the word vectors
but it's even slightly worse than I've
explained um up until now because
actually for each word we assume two
vectors we assume one vector when
they're the center word and one vector
when they're the outside word doing that
just makes the math a bit simpler which
I can explain later so if we say had a
100 dimensional vectors we'll have 100
parameters for ad v as an outside word
100 parameters for um ah as an outside
word all the way through to 100
parameters for zebra as an outside word
then we'd have 100 parameters for arvar
as a um a center word continuing down so
you know if we had a vocabulary of
400,000 words and 100 um dimensional
word vectors that means we'd have
400,000 * 2 is
800,000 time 100 we'd have 80 million
parameters so that's a lot of parameters
in our space to try and Fiddle to
optimize things but luckily we have big
computers um and that's the kind of
thing that we do so we simply um say G
this is our optimization problem we're
going to compute the gradients of all of
these parameters and that will um give
us the answer of what we have um and you
know
this feels like magic I mean it doesn't
really seem like you know we could just
start with nothing we could start with
random word vectors and a pile of text
and say uh do some math and we will get
something useful out um but the miracle
of what happens in these deep learning
spaces is we do get something useful out
we can just um minimize um all of the
parameters and
um then we'll get something useful out
um so what I wanted to uh I guess I'm
not going to quite get to the end of
what I hope to today um but what we I
wanted to do is sort of um get through
um some of um what we do here but you
know I wanted to take a few minutes to
sort of go through concretely how we do
um the math of
minimization now lots of different
people will um take um
cs224n and some of you know way more
math than I do and so if this next 10
minutes might be extremely boring and if
that's the case you can either catch up
on Discord or Instagram or something or
else you can leave but it turns out
there are other people that do
cs224n that can't quite remember um when
they lasted a math course and we'd like
um everybody to be able to learn
something about this um so I do actually
like in the first two weeks to kind of
go through it a bit concretely so let's
um try to do this so this was our
likelihood and then we'd already covered
the fact that what we were going to do
is have an objective function in terms
of our parameters that was the negative
the average negative log likelihood
across all the
words
um if I remember the notation for this
the
sum um in this
oops um I'll probably have a hard time
writing this um the sum of position M
I've got a more neatly written out
version of it that appears on the
version of the slides it's on the
webiz um and then we're going to be
taking this
log of the probability of the word
at
position um t
plus sorry position J um t +
[Music]
J
okay trying to write this on my iPad is
not working super well I'll confess
we'll see how I get on um
WT okay
um okay and so then we had the form of
what we um wanted to use for the
probability and the probability of an
outside word given a context word is was
then this soft maxed equation where
we're taking the x of the outside
vector and the center
Vector over the normalization term where
we sum over the
vocabulary okay um so
to to work out um how to change our
parameters so our parameters are all of
these word vectors that we summarize um
inside Theta
what we're then going to want to do is
work out the partial
derivative of this objective function
with respect to all the parameters Theta
but you know in particular um I'm going
to cons just start doing here the
partial derivatives with respect to um
the
center
word and we can work through the outside
words separately well this partial
derivative is a big a big sum and it's a
big sum of terms like this and so when I
have a partial derivative of a big sum
of terms I can work out the partial
derivatives of each term independently
and then sum them so what I want to be
doing is working out um the partial
derivative
of the log of this probability which
equals the the log of
that with respect to the center Vector
um and so at this point I have a log of
two things being divided and so that
means I can separate that out of the log
of the numerator minus the log of the
denominator and so what I'll be doing is
working out the partial derivative with
respect to the center vector
of the log the
numerator um log X of
utvc
minus um
the partial
derivative um with respect to the
denominator which is then the log of the
sum of w = 1 to V of x
who okay I'm having real trouble here
writing I look at the slides where I
wrote it neatly at home okay um so I
want to work with these two terms now at
this point um part of
it at this point part of it is easy
because here I just have a log of an
exponential and so so those two
functions just cancel out and go away
and so then I want to get the partial
derivative of U outside transpose V
Center um with respect to V Center and
so um what you get for the answer to
that is that that just comes out um as
U and um maybe you remember that but if
you don't remember that the thing to
think about is okay this is a whole
Vector right and so we've got a vector
here and a vector here so what this is
going to be looking like is like sort of
U1 V1 plus U2
V2 um plus u3 V3 Etc long and so what
we're going to want to do is work out
the partial derivative with respect to
each element
um VI right and so if you just think of
a sort of a single element derivative
with respect to um
V1 well it's going to be just U1 because
every other term would go to zero um and
then if you worked it out with respect
to V2 then it would be just U2 and every
other term goes to zero and so since you
keep on doing that along the whole
Vector that what you're going to get out
is the vector
um U1 U2
u3 um down the vocab um for the whole
list of vocab
items okay so that part is easy um but
then we also want to um work out the
partial derivatives of that one and at
that point I maybe have to um go to
another slide so we then want to have
um the partial
derivative
um with respect to
VC of
the
log of the sum equals W 1 to V of the x
u w transvers VC right so at this point
things aren't quite so easy and we have
to remember a little bit more calcul
so in particular what we have to
remember is the chain rule so here we
have this inside function so that we've
got a function um we've got a function G
of VC which you know we might say the
output of that is Zed and then we put
outside that an extra function f and so
when we have something like that what we
get is the derivative of f with respect
to VC we can take the derivative of f
with respect to Z times the derivative
of Z with respect to um VC right that's
the chain rule so we're going to then
apply that here so first of all we're
going to take the derivative of log um
and so the derivative of log is one X
you have to remember that or look it up
or get mathematic to do it for you or
something like that
um and so we're going to have one over
the inside Z part the sum of w equal 1
to V of the X
uwt
VC um and then that's going to be
multiplied by the derivative of the
inside part part
um so then we're going to have the
derivative with respect to VC of the sum
of w =
1 to
V of the X
of okay um
so um so that's um made us a little bit
of progress um but we've still got
something to do here um and so well what
we're going to do here is we're going to
notice Oh wait we're again in the space
to run the chain rule again so now we've
got this function well so first of all
we can move the sum to the outside right
because we've got a sum of terms W = one
to V and so we want to work out the
derivatives of the inside piece um with
respect to it sorry I'm doing this kind
of informally of just doing this piece
now um okay so this again gives us an F
over a function um
G and so we're going to again want to
split the pieces up and so use the chain
rule one more time so we're going to
have the sum of w = 1 to V and now we
have to know what the derivative of x is
and the derivative of x is X so that
will be X of
uux
tv0 and then we're taking the derivative
of the inside part with respect to VC of
ux um T
VC well luckily this was the bit that we
already knew how to do because we worked
it out before and so this is going to be
the sum of w equal 1 to V of this X
times
ux okay so then at this point um we want
to combine these two forms together so
that we want to combine this part that
we worked out and this piece here that
we've worked out and if we canine
combine them together with what we
worked out on the first slide um for
numerator um since this is we have
the U which was the derivative of the
numerator and then for the um derivative
of the denominator we're going to
have um on top this part and then on the
bottom we're going to have that part and
so we can rewrite that as the sum from
wal 1 to V of the
X of
uxt
v0 *
ux over um the
[Music]
sum sorry x = 1 to V sum over W = 1 to V
of the X this part here of UW
okay so we can rearrange things in that
form and then lo and behold we find that
we've recreated here this form of the
softn equation so we end up with
u minus the sum x = 1 to V of the
probability of x given c times um U of x
so what this is saying is we're wanting
to have this quantity which takes the
actual observed U vector and it's
comparing it to the weighted prediction
so we're taking the weight of some of
the our current ux vectors um based on
How likely we we were they were to occur
and so this is a form that you see quite
a bit in these kind of der
you get exer observed minus expected the
weighted average and so what you'd like
to have is your expectation the weighted
average be the same as um the what was
observed because then you'll get a
derivative of zero which means that
you've hit a
maximum um and so that gives us you know
the form of the derivative of the um
that we're having with respect to the
center Vector parameters to finish it
off you'd have to then work it out also
for the um outside Vector parameters but
hey it's officially the end of class
time so I'd better wrap up quickly now
but you know so the deal is we're going
to work out all of these derivatives um
for each parameter and then these
derivatives will give a direction to
change numbers which will let us find
good word vectors
automatically um I do want you to
understand how this works but
fortunately you'll find out very quickly
that computers will do this for you and
on a regular basis you don't actually
have to do it yourself um more about
that on Thursday okay see you everyone