[Music]
Okay. So, in this last of sort of what
we like to think of as the core
foundational lectures for this course,
we're going to focus on a discussion of
kind of where we are at with deep
learning and AI. not only in terms of
limitations but also in terms of some of
the most active areas that are rapidly
undergoing development and what we can
think of as the new frontiers of this
very vast
field. Before that I think at this stage
in the class it's helpful to do a little
bit of a logistics orientation and I
know we've been you know receiving a lot
of questions around that. So we're going
to spend a little bit of time talking
about those components first.
So, as Alexander mentioned, we have this
great tradition of these wonderful
course t-shirts. So, we will start
distributing them tomorrow. If you are
interested in uh obtaining one, please
come to class tomorrow in person to
receive the
t-shirts. So far, where we are in the
class is we have gone through five out
of the six foundational lectures. And
looking forward, we have a series of
four guest lectures that are going to be
from our fantastic industry sponsors
covering a few different topics um at
the new frontiers of deep learning. Some
important deadlines that we're going to
get into a little bit more in detail is
that for the lab competitions for the
software labs, we've extended the
deadline from uh being due tomorrow
night at midnight to being due on Friday
at 11:00 a.m. And additionally, there
are important deadlines for the
submission of the slides to the final
proposal competition also on Friday. And
finally, the proposal competition itself
will occur on
Friday. On that note, as you may know,
and hopefully you've gotten practice
with, starting with labs one and two, we
have three amazing software labs for you
to gain hands-on familiarity with the
concepts that we've talking about been
talking about. All the instructions in
terms of how to submit the labs are
located both on the syllabus and on the
actual notebooks themselves for each of
these three respective labs. So please
look to those resources first for those
types of
questions. For those of you who are MIT
students and are taking this course for
credit, you have two options to fulfill
the requirement for receiving credit for
the class. Note that submission of the
software labs is not required. To get
credit, you have to either um submit a
project proposal and present it on
Friday. And here you will be working
either individually or in a group of up
to five people to develop a cool new
idea about a deep learning algorithm or
application and present it on Friday.
And again, all the instructions and
details are on the syllabus. Important
deadlines. Please submit your groups by
tomorrow night at midnight. And the
slide deck that's linked in the syllabus
will be completely locked for editing at
100 p.m. sharp on Friday. So no more
editing following
that. Importantly to um with the
proposal competition comes the
opportunity to win a few fantastic
prizes that are going to be judged by
myself, Alexander, our TAs, and a couple
of guest uh judges, including from our
industry
sponsors. The second option to fulfill
credit is to write a one-page review of
a recent scientific paper in deep
learning or a or AI. And this is also
due on Friday with instructions on the
syllabus. All right. So if you have been
enjoying these foundational lectures
given by Alexander and I, I hope that
you are ready to really um get excited
for some amazing new content tomorrow
and Friday from our guest lectures from
industry sponsors. We're going to have
two fantastic talks that are going to
dive deep into large language models
from Pet Peter Gowski from Google Deep
Mind and Maxim Labon from Liquid AI. And
then on Thursday, Doug Blank will tell
us about the consequences of deploying
AI in the wild, what risks, what ethical
concerns can come with this. And
finally, I will close out by shifting my
hat from a instructor mode to sharing
some of my own work working at the
interface of AI and
biology. Furthermore, if you're excited
by, you know, what you're seeing and
you're looking for new resources to
extend your knowledge even further, um
there's an amazing series of resources
from uh my team and group at Microsoft
and beyond through the Microsoft
Research Forum. And these are some
completely public open-source talks from
our researchers across a variety of
areas. Everything from the
sociotechnical implications of AI to how
AI is transforming uh the natural
sciences. So please take a moment to um
capture that QR code and register to uh
receive regular updates about content
being distributed on Microsoft Research
Forum. All right. So that concludes kind
of our logistics uh whirlwind to kick
off this lecture and now we can really
transition to the the really fun stuff.
So, so far in this course, introduction
to deep learning, we've appreciated not
only the foundations of these fantastic
algorithms, but also begun to understood
how deep learning has truly
revolutionized so many different fields
and research areas and applications from
advances in autonomous vehicles to
breakthroughs in medicine, healthcare,
reinforcement learning, generative
modeling, robotics, and a whole range of
other applications like natural
language, finance, security and beyond.
And our goal really here is to share
with you a concrete understanding of how
deep learning and neural network models
have enabled these advances across these
ranges of disciplines. And in fact,
we've seen algorithms that can not only
take as input data in the form of
signals, images, other sensory data and
produce a decision out such as a
prediction or a classification, but also
how we can do the inverse, right? going
from desired actions that we seek to
execute and learning policies that will
help us achieve that like in the context
of reinforcement learning but also new
advances in generative modeling that
actually tackle this inverse problem
directly to be able to train models that
can generate brand new data instances.
But at its core, in both cases, whether
we're going from data to decision or
trying to model a distribution of the
data itself, null networks and deep
learning can fundamentally be thought of
as function approximators. They're
really powerful ways to learn this
functional mapping or to learn a
function that captures a probability
distribution.
And to understand this concept in a bit
more detail, I think it's very helpful
to go back to one of the very first and
foundational theories in deep learning
and neural networks which was presented
in
1989. And this is a theorem known as the
universal approximation theorem. And
what it states very simply is that a
neural network with just a single hidden
layer is sufficient to approximate any
function within some level of precision
or
accuracy. Now in this class we've been
talking a lot about deep models right
where we stack multiple neural network
layers together. But this theorem is is
ignoring that for the moment and saying
okay what if we just had one layer. If
we believe that a problem can be
described as this mapping from inputs to
outputs the universal approximation
theorem states that there should exist
some neural network to solve that
problem. Taking a step back right this
seems like a very powerful result. But
if you look more closely, there are a
couple of caveats that we have to
consider. First, this theorem makes no
guarantees on the number of units, the
number of neurons within that layer that
would be needed to solve such a problem.
And it doesn't provide any methodology
or guarantees on how you can actually go
about learning the weights, right, that
would actually support such a neural
network architecture. It just claims
this and proves that one
exists. But right as we saw in back in
lecture one, this process of gradient
descent can actually be very very
complicated. And so it's a highly
non-trivial problem to actually do this
optimization.
What I think this theorem can start to
speak to is an example of how we can
counterbalance our considerations of not
only the strengths of deep learning and
neural networks, but also the hype in
these fields and the potential
limitations that could arise. and
together as a collective community as an
and as individuals in this course and
beyond. I think we always need to be
cognizant of not only the power of any
technology but the limitations that come
with it as we go out and use them in the
real
world. And so in the first part of this
class we're going to talk and touch upon
some of the important limitations of
these algorithms that you've learned
about. One of my very favorite examples
of this concept comes from this now
classic paper that is entitled
understanding deep neural networks
requires rethinking
generalization. And in this paper they
do a really elegant experiment. They
take images from a data set imageet and
their labels that you see here. And what
they do is for every image in this data
set, not considering classes but
individual images, they flip a k-sided
die, right? Where k corresponds to the
total number of classes that are
possible. And basically based on the
result of that random sample, they now
assign a brand new label to each
individual image. What this means,
right, is that these new labels are
associated with no semantic meaning
relative to the image. And what you may
be able to observe here is that you
could have two instances of the same
class that are actually now assigned
different labels. Right? So this mapping
is completely random. We're literally
trying to randomize our labels entirely.
Now with this relabeled re-randomly
labeled training set, what they did was
they trained a deep neural network model
to this sampled data ranging from the
untouched data on the far left of this
plot to completely randomly assigned
class labels on the right.
And now when they do the classic test of
measuring performance on your testing
set, as you expect, the accuracy of the
classification really progressively
decreases as the degree of randomness in
this labeling increases. But what was
really striking was what they saw when
they now looked at the performance on
the training set. This is what they
found. No matter how much they randomize
the labels, the model is able to get one
close to 100% accuracy on the training
set. And this really points to this idea
of relating back to the universal
approximation theorem and thinking about
neural networks as function
approximators. A neural net can
perfectly fit to a function even if that
function has entirely random labels. And
this gets at again that core principle
of what is this notion of fit and how
you can actually me measure
generalization and the fit of your model
on tests versus train data. And so to
drive this point home even further, if
we're operating with this framing of
understanding neural nets as function
approximators, what the universal
approximation theorem tells us is that
they're just really really good at doing
this task.
where given some training set data, we
can learn a maximum likelihood estimate
of that data, fit a function to that
data such that if we give the model a
new data point, say here in purple, we
can use our neural network to predict
the likelihood estimate for that data
point. But what if now we extend the
spread of the data further out out of
distribution relative to these training
examples? what happens to the behavior.
There are no guarantees on what the
training data looks like in these
ranges. And this notion of
generalization is one of the huge
limitations that exists. And further, if
we look here at these places that are
out of distribution where the model was
not trained on enough data, the gets at
this question of how do we actually know
what our network does not
know. And when we consider these
examples or use cases, how can we
calibrate our expectations of the
confidence of the neural network with
its actual performant
ability? And I think this really points
to sort of kind of this magic and
excitement about deep learning and AI.
And there can also sometimes be a
misconception that deep learning is
basically this intuitive art this alche
alchemy uh akin to alchemy right where
maybe you have some problem and task
that you're interested in solving and
you have some data set associated with
that task. What if I just build or
deploy some AI solution or neural
network model on that
task? While the power is really awesome
and we have all this excitement, really
it comes down to a couple of
considerations. One is does that task
really is it really suited to be
addressed by a deep learning solution?
And secondly, what is the quality of the
data that you're able to process and
curate for that task, right? Deep
learning is not some magic crank where
you can uh put anything into to that
crank and and get a magic solution out,
right? There's this famous saying of
garbage in, garbage out. And that's
really holds true. Your model is only
going to be as good as what it sees.
And to make this a little bit more more
concrete, right, this motivates one of
the most powerful and pertinent failure
modes of neural nets and highlights just
kind of how much they depend on the
quality of the data they're trained
with. So let's use this example where we
have images of dogs and say we want to
pass it into a architecture like a CNN
and we want to train the network to now
colorize black and white images go from
black and white to
color. What could happen
here? Let's say we observe this result.
And if you look closely, right, there's
this pink region at the bottom of the
chin of this
dog. Why could this be the case?
Yeah. I mean let's say if we take a take
a look and look at okay what are some
common ways that dogs pose or you know
just are naturally in images we can see
that many many instances of dogs
sticking their tongue out could end up
in this end result and I think this
really highlights very na nicely that
these models are building up these
internal representations again
inherently linked to the data that
they've seen in
training and This raises this question
of now how do we build robust solutions
that are capable to handle instances
that they may not have been uh may not
have been seen in training. And
infamously and very tragically a couple
of years ago there was a car that was
operating autonomously that crashed and
resulted in um a a fatal death of the
driver. And it turned out that actually
the driver had reported in multiple
instances in recent weeks that when
passing on that same road, the car would
begin to start to curve and swivel
towards a barrier that ended up being
what it crashed into. And it turned out
that actually in the images that the the
autonomous system had been trained on,
it lacked that specific barrier. It was
not constructed at the time. So the car
had encountered this instance that was
effectively out of distribution and
resulted in a
crash. And this is this core underlying
concept of uncertainty in deep learning.
And it's failure modes like this that
really motivate the need to be able to
understand where this notion of
uncertainty comes from to quantify it
and to use that information to actually
uh hopefully make models that are more
robust. This is tremendously important
in safety critical applications like
autonomy, medicine, facial recognition,
security and privacy and also in cases
in general where we may have imbalances
or sparsity or data noise in our data
set. Being able to uh reliably detect
and correct for these sources of
uncertainty is extremely important.
A a third failure mode to consider is is
a very famous one that maybe you have
seen uh uh previews of and this is the
notion of adversarial examples or
adversarial attacks and the idea here is
again very elegant and beautiful which
is if we take some data instance in this
case it's an image of this temple and we
have let's say now a CNN a classifier
fire and it does a very good job of
assigning a high likelihood that this
image is that of a
temple. Now the question is can we apply
some small indistinguishable
perturbation to that image that now
results in what we call an adversarial
example that in turn leads the CNN model
to no longer be able to recognize this
image as a temple. assigning a
completely different label with very
high
probability. The core concept behind
these adversarial examples is this
perturbation, what it's doing and how it
is
constructed. Remember that when we train
neural networks with gradient descent,
our task is to shift the weights of the
network according to some objective
function. And what we're trying to
optimize is the set of weights that will
minimize the loss dictated by that
objective. Really, what we're asking is
how does a small change in the weights
decrease our loss? And can we take a
step in that direction to decrease the
loss?
Importantly, what is being changed is
the weights for a fixed image input X
and a fixed label Y.
In adversarial examples or adversarial
attacks, the question is kind of uh
flipped. Now the question is how can we
modify an input image or an input
instance to now increase the error in
the network's prediction. So rather than
perturbing the weights to minimize the
the loss objective, we're trying to
learn a a perturbation to the input to
adversarily affect the decision at the
end. And this actually can be realized
physically in the real world. So a few
years back, a group of students at MIT
took this notion of adversarial examples
to the 3D physical realm where they
actually used 3D printing to synthesize
uh real life adversarial examples that
would fool a computer vision
model. Beyond this and I think you know
this notion of adversaries is both
conceptually very important but also
practically very important and in turn
these collective themes of the
importance of data uncertainty point to
you know considerations that we have to
have in terms of our responsibility as
deployers and developers of AI and as
you may have seen in in the software lab
for the course there's also this
tremendous notion of algorithmic bias.
How could algorithms be perpetuating
some of the cultural societal biases
that exist in our world today and are
inherently represented in the data that
these algorithms are trained
on. So certainly this is not an
exhaustive list of all the limitations
and considerations we have to be mindful
of with deep learning and neural
networks. But hopefully these uh notions
of bias uncertainty get at some of the
core considerations that are
present. And I think you know as
technologists and scientists limitations
present the opportunity for development.
And I hope that this also serves as a
motivation for you all to go out and
continue expanding the new frontiers
yourself to tackle some of these
outstanding questions.
So for the remainder of the talk, I'm
going to focus on some of the work
that's being done with respect to this
and introduce a couple of the leading
edge new frontiers in AI and deep
learning. And as you've seen right, this
notion of extrapolation and
generalization is a very very core
principle of deep learning. And today we
have seen this notion of foundational
and generative models that promise the
ability to achieve really robust
generalization in a way of being purely
datadriven. And I think this is quite
exciting and a really compelling way to
demonstrate how these capabilities in
extrapol extrapolation and
generalization have
been, you know, kind of exponentially
increased as a result of these
foundational models. And so for this
talk, the frontier that we're really
going to focus on is that of generative
models, which we which we saw in lecture
four. um this principle of modeling a
data distribution as a way to expand the
capabilities of
generalization. And so in the first part
of the new frontiers portion, we're
going to focus a bit further and do a
deeper dive on a new class of generative
models that have been introduced
recently called diffusion models.
And so if you think back to yesterday's
lecture on generative modeling, we
discussed two foundational um starting
points of generative models, VAEs and
GANs. And yet as some of the questions
started to raise and we were able to
discuss postclass, these models have a
few key limitations to be mindful of.
First, they can tend to collapse into
producing kind of repeated instances of
what we call the mean or uh the mode
collapse. Meaning like in an example for
facial um im generation of images of
faces, you will result in a mode
collapse resulting in uh the model only
producing the average face quote
unquote. Right?
that's very closely linked to difficulty
in being able to generate diverse
samples and extrapolate out of
distribution. And furthermore, these uh
models such as GANs can be very
difficult and unstable and inefficient
to train. And so these challenges of
stability, the quality of the
generations and the novelty of the
generations have really led to new
methodological advances that have
tackled this headon. And one very
prominent approach to generative
modeling, particularly in the domains of
images and video, is this framework
called diffusion models. And if you have
experimented and played with some of the
leading systems for text to image
generation, the backbone generative
model that's driving the uh image
generation is very often a diffusion
model.
And diffusion models I think are really
really exciting because they have a
beautiful and intuitive idea behind them
that leads to actually quite high
quality in terms of the quality of the
generations that they're able to
produce. So when we learned about VAS
and GANs, the approach to sample
generation for something like images was
what we can think of as a single shot. A
VAE or GAN is trying to learn a mapping
from some compressed data representation
like a latent space or a distribution of
random noise in the case of a GAN to now
produce an image or an instance back in
that original data space in a single
shot. Diffusion models work
fundamentally
differently because instead of rather
than trying to do this in a single shot,
they try to generate new samples
iteratively by repeatedly removing noise
to refine the generative process in this
iterative fashion.
And what this means is that the learning
task is effectively simplified by
breaking up into these iterative chunks
such that the end result is that our
sample generation quality ends up being
much much better. So let's take a look
at how diffusion models work. The core
idea behind diffusion models is this
notion of a diffusion process. this idea
of iteratively adding noise to source
data to create training instances and
then training our neural network to
learn how to selectively and iteratively
undo that noise step by step. So to
illustrate how this comes to life, let's
use examples of images. Say we have a
training data instance like this. In a
diffusion model, there is what we call a
forward process, a forward noising
process where we take our data instances
and progressively and incrementally add
random noise to the instance slowly
wiping out the details in that data
until we reach an endpoint of pure
random
noise. Now, these individual uh
instances are separated by just a
step-wise addition of noise. Right?
Then the task that we actually train the
neural network on is to reverse this
corruption process to now go from noise
to data instance in this denoising
process that
uh such that we can then recover the
information in our data back from these
noisy instances. To break this down step
by step, right, the forward noising
process does not require any training.
All we do is given an instance like this
image on the left, we sample a pattern
of random noise and we progressively add
more and more noise to the image such
that we can have these increasing and
iterative examples lined up right step
by step.
Then we turn to actually the process
that the neural network is trained on
and the neural network learns which is
the reverse dnoising
process. The noising process has given
us these time steps of increasingly
noisier and noisier instances.
Now the task is given an image or an
instance at time step t, can we learn a
neural network that can estimate the
likely image at the prior time step that
has a little bit less noise than what
it's
seen. So here we are trying to learn a
neural network to do this exact
dinoising estimation. Given an image at
t, how can we arrive at the preceding t
minus
one? How can we train such such a
network on this
task? Again, keep in mind that we're
trying to compare these pair-wise
instances that differ by just a step of
random noise. Any ideas on how we can
actually formulate a loss or an
objective to train this model?
Yes, the idea is to compare the image in
the prior state and and concretely how
how can we define this? Let's say we
have
image. Yes. How how do we define the
loss is my question.
Yes. Mean square error. Mean squared
error. Yeah. something as simple as
that, right? It's comparing these two to
actually estimate the noise itself
because the error between these two
instances is effectively what the noise
is contributing. And it turns out that
this is actually leads to a very
effective way to train these types of
models. Effectively, learning training
the neural network to learn these noise
differences themselves.
Now that's really the core concept
behind how you can train a diffusion
model. Once you have trained it, you can
then use the train model for sampling to
produce brand new
instances. The way that we do that to
sample a brand new generation is we
start with random noise and then we take
our trained neural network. The weights
have been updated that has been trained
to predict these residual noise
differences.
And what it does is it samples new
instances of incrementally less noise
starting from this initial state. And
this process repeats. And as this
denoising occurs iteratively, we can see
the data start to peak back at us as we
repeat this uh sampling process until at
the very end at the final time step of
this reverse dnoising process. We're
back to our original data space and we
have produced a brand new instance in
that space. Putting it all together in
training a diffusion model, you're
trying to learn a neural network to
predict this denoising procedure. And
once you have trained, you can sample
from the train model to produce brand
new instances.
What is very very powerful now about
this approach is that in starting with
random noise, we're able to encapsulate
a maximum degree of variability. But by
comparing these iterative steps, we've
deconstructed the learning task into
something that's actually efficient and
effective to train. We can produce now
very high high quality and highfidelity
samples through a process like
this diffusion. And and these are actual
instances that are generated by a
diffusion model. And what is really
striking is starting that with a
completely different instance of random
noise yields a very diverse and very
different sampled image as the end
result. And that's again relating to
this concept of how much variability
you're able to encapsulate in that start
state.
And as I alluded to, right, diffusion
models are underlying the image
generation pipeline for many of these
textto image models and platforms that
you may have seen and experimented with.
And I think that this really comes to
life through these examples where you
can see that the quality and fidelity of
these generations is very high with
respect to the image itself and how
closely it matches uh the input prompt.
It's not just about images or video or
things like this that diffusion has
become very powerful. In fact, in the
natural sciences and in the life
sciences, we've seen tremendous advances
in diffusion models for molecular design
and biological design. And uh on Friday
I will I will share a little bit more
about how some of these approaches work
and the capabilities that we're able to
achieve uh in this
application. All right. So that gives us
a kind of a a foundational understanding
of the the state-of-the-art generative
models uh for image generation and other
modality generation.
In the remaining time for this lecture,
we're going to go into an another new
frontier of large language models and
give you a strong primer on the
fundamental concepts of LLMs in
preparation for uh some of the guest
lectures tomorrow as well as for our
brand new software lab that's released
today.
So I think that it's no secret now at
this point that large language models
have really taken off in the past years
and are truly revolutionizing many
aspects of our daily life. But you know
I'm very passionate about not only
technology but understanding the
fundamentals of technology that I work
with and that I interact with. And so
what I hope to convey is a background on
how LLMs like GPT that power chat GPT
work and why they work the way they do.
And with that knowledge hopefully arms
you with an arsenal to understand the
capabilities of these models and also
their
limitations. So very fundamentally what
are LLMs? On day one, we started out by
defining, you know, proposing a
definition of artificial intelligence
and a definition for deep learning. LLMs
or large language models are very simply
very very large deep neural networks
that are trained on large sets of text
data.
The way that we can think about this is
that these data sets are pretty broad,
pretty agnostic and start out as
effectively
unanotated. In order to train a large
language model like GPT, as we started
to get at a little bit, this data set
needs to be processed and fed into the
model in a particular
way. We then have to define a task,
right? a learning task and an objective
that we want to train the model on. Now
with data of this scale, it's does not
necessarily and it's infeasible to fit
into a classic supervised learning
problem, right? Where for every instance
of data, we have some defined label and
our neural network task is to learn a
mapping of the data to the
label. Instead, what is really the
breakthrough and core idea behind these
LLMs is to use the data itself to define
a
task. And a very common task that powers
these models and in fact is what powers
GPT is a very simple one that we saw
again on day one. Given a sequence of
chunks or words in a sentence, predict
the next word, the next chunk. In
language modeling, this is often called
these chunks are often called tokens.
And the task is called next token
prediction. Given a sequence of tokens,
predict the next token. And we're going
to update our model parameters, our
weights in our neural network based on
how well the model does at this next
token prediction
task. How does this
work? to break it down and hopefully now
these concepts are coming back from the
lecture on sequence modeling as
well. How LLMs like GPT are trained are
by taking raw text in the form of a
sentence for example and the first step
is to split that text up into
chunks and represent it numerically
through this process called
tokenization.
Those tokens are embedded numerically
encoded and provided as input to the
LLM. And the next token prediction task
is simply to be uh simply as follows.
Given a set of tokens, we want to
predict what is the most likely next
token. Estimate the
probabilities of what that next token is
over the whole vocabulary or whole space
of possible tokens.
Looking at this very
concretely, what we can do is actually
compute the probabilities over this
distribution of next possible tokens and
use the signal from the estimated
probabilities to train the model.
What you what is beautiful to realize is
this effectively amounts to a
classification task. By computing the
cross entropy loss over these next token
probabilities compared to the true next
token, we are able to provide a signal
to the model to learn how to compute
this next token prediction
task. The beauty here is this is what we
call a selfs supervised signal. We're
using the data itself to uh define a
signal to train the model on. And again,
we can employ something very simple like
a cross entropy loss to convey the
signal to the
model. The power now comes by doing this
very intuitive next token prediction
task on a very large and broad set of
data that allows the model to learn the
fundamental patterns that underlies
something as complex as human language.
Now when we have trained the model
through the next token prediction task
at deployment you are able to interface
in this way where you can prompt the
model and now uh produce responses
out. In practice though, there are
several steps in what we call LLM post
training that are actually required to
go from that next token prediction task
to something that actually functions as
a chatbot that you can interface with
and interact reasonably with. And in uh
the liquid AI lecture tomorrow, you will
hear from one of the world's experts on
LLM post host training the core
components of this pipeline and how uh
the considerations that need to be made
here. So the capabilities that this
unlocks with today's language models are
really tremendous in terms of their use
as agents for knowledge retrieval,
writing, text generation and so on. And
this mastery over language has really
been
tremendous. Still, there are still key
limitations when it comes to the
deployment of LLMs and places where they
still struggle. First is this notion of
uncertainty and confidence that we
introduced earlier in this lecture. We
still are working very actively on ways
to reliably quantify the robustness and
confidence of models as large as LLMs in
these types of scenarios such that we
can be able to reliably identify what we
call hallucinations where the model may
produce um a generation that sounds very
sensical but is actually not grounded in
reality. and also use this understanding
to consider what model level guard rails
we should deploy on these AI systems
when they're uh interfaced with with
humans and
applications. And finally, a a fourth
and very prominent area of active work
in in language modeling and
um and these AI models is this notion of
logic and long-term planning such that
the models can go beyond this mastery
over over natural language and
generalize to uh very complex reasoning
and planning types of tasks.
Nevertheless, a lot of these
breakthroughs that we have seen with
models like GPT and beyond comes from
observations that pointed to the fact
that these LLMs can pick up these new
emergent abilities as the model size
scales and as the data set size
scales. And there were some seminal
observations in neural scaling laws that
pointed out that as we scale the size of
these models and how long and the extent
to which they're trained, we can see
step changes in the capabilities of
these models in terms of tasks that they
could perform.
And really this this concept comes to
life very beautifully in this
visualization where you can see very
concretely as a function of the model
size in terms of the number of sheer
parameters in these models we see
breakthroughs and blossoming of new
capabilities that these language models
can actually demonstrate and achieve.
So these concepts now get quite quite
heavy and serious when we consider the
capabilities of foundation modeling and
how we are stepping towards closer and
closer of what we can think of as true
artificial
intelligence. And when this course
began, we we spoke about what it means
to be intelligent. the ability to take
information, reason about that
information, and use it to inform future
decision-
makingaking. I would argue that our
learning pipeline is not restricted to
only being able to solve the tasks that
on that we have seen training examples
for, right? We are able to learn
concepts behind tasks that allow us to,
you know, speed up uh our our ability to
learn and generalize and think
creatively on new domains or new areas
that we care
about. As we see these new advances in
generative AI, it motivates a deep
question for ourselves in terms of what
are the connections and distinctions
between what we can do, what our
capabilities are, and what the
capabilities and limitations of these
models are. And moreover, like any
technology, right, AI is just a
technology. We've created it as a
technology and as a tool that we can use
and we can
deploy. And I encourage you all to not
only think about the relative
similarities and differences between
human intelligence and artificial
intelligence, but also about how you can
maximize these tools as tools for you in
your own work and in your own personal
journeys of learning and
creation. So I'll leave you with that
point to think about and meditate on and
I encourage you to discuss further
amongst amongst um each other. Still, I
want to highlight and very excitedly
announce that these themes and concepts
of LLM that uh I just shared, you now
have have the ability to get hands-on
practical experience with actually
experimenting with and fine-tuning an
LLM yourself. And very excitingly, we've
unveiled a brand new software lab. never
before. You're you all are the first
class to have access to this software
lab where you will actually fine-tune an
LLM yourself as a chatbot in a couple of
different fun styles and try to um
experiment with it to optimize the
performance of your chatbot. Um and
hopefully you do this. You don't try
this. You do you do this and this uh is
a preview of what is to come in that
software lab. So thank you all for your
attention. With that we'll close and uh
thank you all so much.