uh pleasure to be here um I'm going to
talk about some of our work on agents
but I want to take a broader view of
what's happening in Ai and focus on the
importance of Open Source um so everyone
has seen some sort of figure like this
where over the last few years the
capabilities of these models have simply
skyrocketed but what's less appreciated
is that the openness and access to these
models has plummeted almost
symmetrically we used to have access to
the full paper weights code data and now
all we have is API it's a very good API
but it's just an API and so the question
is why does access matter at all right
you can do a lot of things with just the
API but I want to make a simple Point
here is that access shapes research this
is something that I don't think we think
about very much because most of the time
we have our heads down we're just
working on whatever problem given what
we have but if you look historically
access has really dramatically changed
the type of work that has happened so
going back to the the 90s where the
entire field of Cisco NLP emerged just
because we had access to Internet scale
data a text and digital
form in the 2010s there was a
proliferation of these organic large
scale annotated data sets like Imad and
Squad and these were available because
we had crowdsourcing platforms like
Amazon Turk and then finally in the
2010s of course we wouldn't be here
without gpus deep learning would not
have taken off so access shapes research
so for foundation models I'm going to
talk about three types of access the
first is API access to a blackbox model
the second is open weight access and the
third is open source so API access think
about it as you're a cognitive scientist
and all you can do is measure the
behavior of this Black Box by putting in
prompts and getting out responses but
you can't look inside the black
box I'm going to talk about how you can
actually do a lot here and in particular
since this is an agent class I'm going
to talk about all the interesting types
of Agents you can build um using just
blackbox
access open weight access you can think
about as you're a neuroscientist who can
now poke at the internals of what's in
this black box now of course real
neuroscientists have it much harder than
we do um but um you can get a little bit
more deeper access which allows you to
sort to begin to understand the
mechanisms behind the models and also to
create novel derivatives such as of
distillations and fine
tunes but both API and open weight
access you have to remember we're still
confined to existing models to their
architectures and to their design
decisions and and what we need instead
is open source access so in open source
access you think like a computer
scientist who is building a system and
who can control every part of it and
this gives you the opportunity to really
question everything to question the data
set to question the model architecture
to question the training procedure you
have the ability to hopefully make
things better as a
result so we're going to go um in the
rest of the talk I'm going to send this
layer cake step by step so starting with
API models so if you think about API
model I wanted you to think about it as
what I call quotequote a universal
function right it's a function such that
if you give a prompt with a natural
language instruction that function can
do a lot of different things it can
summarize it can verify things it can
generate and and that's the the power
for power of these Foundation models is
that you there's so general purpose and
now once you have one of these
apis then you can start thinking about
composing them into larger systems which
we can then think about as
agents and importantly we want to think
about the API as a controller of
execution so it's not the case that you
have just a fixed program and then all
you're doing is calling out to an API at
the leaves as as Primitives but in fact
the API actually controls the execution
flow it controls what the program is
going to do
next so here is um a basic architecture
of an agent that we're going to work
with um through the next uh 10 or 20
minutes or
so and here's the way it works so an
agent takes observations from The Real
World uh it perceives them and adds them
to a memory stream a memory stream is
going to be something that records
everything that has happened
so
far and because it's a digital agent
there's no reason to forget it simply
stores everything so now there stores
too much now you need to U
retrieve the relevant memories and that
gives you a piece of context that you
can use to do one of three things you
can act in the present which means
essentially tool use grounding into the
real world uh taking various actions you
can look backwards and you can reflect
on your memories this is things you can
think about summarizing what you've seen
so far verifying what you've seen so far
and so on and you can plan you can plan
for the future and this gives agents a
sense of long-term direction as opposed
to just simply reacting in the moment
okay so with this basic Eng architecture
where every one of these boxes is
powered by one of these blackbox API um
uh LM apis we can start to build things
I'm going to tell you two types of
Agents we can build one class of Agents
is problem solving agents these are the
agents that you typically think of when
you think of the word agent they solve
problems um the second is going to be
simulation agents which is something
that maybe not all of you have seen but
I think is really really uh fascinating
so let's go through problem solving
agents so I'm going to show you two
Works um that we have recently on
problem solving agents um the first is
ml agent bench this is work uh with my
uh student Chen um and appeared at icml
this year so the problem here is
something that all of you are familiar
with it's you're given a machine
learning problem some data some starter
code and an evaluator for test accuracy
and your goal is simply to build the
best machine learning model you can okay
so what do you do you write some code
you um run the code you get some log of
what has happened and then based on that
you think a little bit and revise the
code and you run the code and so on okay
so this is what all of you have done and
the goal is to build an LM agent that
actually does that okay so um this is in
a slide basically what we do um so we
craft this prompt so uh you're a helpful
research assistant here's the thing you
can do here's a task description and um
I want the agent to reflect on the
observations that it's gone so far um
make a plan of what to do next um fact
check that your plan because sometimes
to to guard against hallucinations um
think a little bit and propose an action
to take okay so then that goes into the
language model the language model um
dutifully does reflection plan fact
checks thinks and then produces an
action and that action is something like
run a script edit a file so on and that
produces through interactions with the
underlying environment a observation in
this case it's executing this train.py
file and produces some log of training
accuracies and now given that
observation it goes back into this
memory stream um and where the memory
stream um when we construct The Prompt
we give the last three um elements of
the memory Stream So the memory stream
has basically the full log of what has
happened so
far okay so basically this is just you
know it goes in a in a loop the LM calls
generates some actions it uh generates
some observations by executing code and
it goes back into memory string so
relatively you know
simple um we created 13 different um
benchmarks um and evaluated a whole host
of different models and the results were
mixed I would say um the best performing
model is Claud 3 and for some of the
more classic kle competitions it does
really well on you know presumably
because it probably has seen some of
this in its it's training data but some
of the newer ones like pblm it just
completely fails on okay so this is you
know a challenging deliberately chosen
to be a challenging problem U but I
think it's something that I think at the
cusp of what current language modeling
agents can actually
do so there's actually a whole bunch of
work in this area which I think is
really exciting um and the idea here is
that I I think of this as
self-improvement so this is not any
agent Benchmark it's an agent Benchmark
that's aimed to improve research which
means that if you solve the task you
actually get better algorithms at you
know you're improving the model and once
you improve the model maybe you can
solve the task better so I think that's
a kind of an interesting um thing to
keep in
mind so now let's talk about a second
type of agent that we've been working on
one for solving cyber security
challenges um so here is the task so you
have an agent it's given access to a
server um running let's say at Port 80
and it's also given the code that's
running on the server so it has a copy
of the code locally and furthermore it
has a bash shell which it can do
whatever it wants okay and the goal of
the agent is essentially into hack into
the server right in or in specifically
what that means is it's going to read
the code understand and identify a
potential security vulnerability exploit
that um by running some sort of bash
command and then retrieving what is
known as a flag which is a secret string
to prove that it has indeed broken into
the server okay so the evaluation here
is very I think uh clear um and these
are called Capture the Flag competitions
which are uh hosted annually um by cyber
security um you know
people and so that's the task the this
is an extremely hard task um I don't
think I could do this uh you know very
well um and to make it a little bit uh
easier we have the option of giving the
agent a set of sub questions which
attempt to break down the the the the
the ultimate task into a bunch of
different substeps um where we can
measure hopefully some partial
progress okay so the way we build agent
to Sol this the cyber security task is
uh essentially the same recipe as we use
for um the ml agent bench so you ask the
agent to reflect make a plan think and
execute a command now that command uh
returns um uh some after the execution
some observations are returned and
that's used to update the memory stream
okay so it's a very general recipe that
you can see applies to a bunch of
different quite radically different um
agent
problems so how the results look so we
benchmarked um a bunch of different uh
models and the best performing model is
again claw 3.5 it solves
17.5% of the benchmarks and the
interesting thing is not all not all the
benchmarks are the same the hardest
Benchmark in our uh a task in our
sidebench took a team of humans 24 hours
to solve and these are people with cyber
security experience they're not just
random people um they're competitors and
the hardest Pro task that the best model
was able to solve at to date uh took uh
humans 11 minutes so quite a bit of Gap
um between what humans can do and what
um uh the best models can do but again
this Gap is you know shrinking over
time okay so again this cyber security
Benchmark is is interesting not just
because it's a difficult and interesting
Asian Benchmark but also because of two
reasons one is that there is a
tremendous amount of uh wonder and and
interest in understanding the risks of
AI in particular with relation to cyber
security so is it the case that once you
develop Frontier models
now we have these enormously powerful
agents that can basically break the
internet um and so from that perspective
AI policy makers are really interested
in the question of risk assessment and
this Benchmark provides an A A
Quantified way of thinking about
risk on the other hand there are cyber
security people who routinely build
penetration testing tools so so these
are tools which try to identify and
break code before the deployment so that
you can fix the problems before um you
put the server up and so these folks are
really excited about this work because
now we suddenly have much
more effective uh penetration testing
tools so so far I've shown you with a
fairly simple uh prompting strategy you
can build problem solving agents in both
ml engineering and cyber security now
let's turn to building simulation
agents so this is a um based on a paper
by June um from from last year and the
goal is can we simulate people or human
behavior um so in order to do that we
built a a virtual world where which we
called Smallville and there are 25
agents um each agent is powered by LM
architecture um Which models uh this uh
architecture in fact this figure comes
from that original paper which we've
sort of repurposed over and over again
for all our agent projects um I'm going
to focus on two pieces of this so
retrieve and
reflect so remember the memory stream
REM remembers everything that happens
and if you think about a human like
yourself um you're wandering around most
things that you experience are fairly
mundane but nonetheless they all go into
the memory Stream So the memory stream
has something like refrigerator is Idol
or desk is neat and organized so hardly
remarkable things to write home about
but you never know what you're going to
need and that's why we store
everything now the problem gets kicked
to at um sort of inference time where
you need to make use of this memory you
can't put everything in the memory
stream in your your prompt so so you
need to retrieve so we retrieve based on
three criteria one is recency so things
that happen in recent memory are
presumably things that you should pay
attention to more um importance which is
things events are generally um marked
with some sort of intrinsic importance
like desk as Idol is not very import
whereas if you got married that's
probably pretty important I would hope
um and the third thing is is relevant so
based on the current context which
things are relevant so for example if
you um are looking for your your water
bottle then maybe the memories of H
where the B water bottle has been is now
suddenly much more relevant than it
would otherwise
be okay so with these three factors uh
we do retrieval to slim down the memory
stream dynamically to a a much smaller
set the second thing I want to mention
is reflection so remember the memory
stream is very very low level and if you
have an agent that just reacts to
individual memories that's going to be
an agent that is is going to be fairly
um sort of in the weeds um so reflection
takes groups of memories and abstracts
them so for example we have this uh guy
in a the small B called whose name is
Claus Miller he's reading about Urban
Design so that's a concrete observation
but then it gets abstracted again and
again into something high level like CL
Miller's highly dedicated research so
this is give what gives the agents a
more Global sense of of purpose rather
than reacting to low-level
details another thing I think is really
important about modeling humans is that
humans are social animals and they talk
to each other and so our agents also
talk to each other so uh in one instance
Isabella is planing a Valentine's Day
party she tells all her friends about it
and then those friends continue to
spread uh the news to other people and
sometimes the the news comes back to um
Isabella and so one thing that's really
interesting about um the simulation that
we observed is how information diffusion
is modeled through the multi-agent
simulation okay so one problem with this
um generative agents is that it's all
made up right these are not real people
these are are just little you know
avatars running around in this virtual
environment so but the true promise I
think of this technology is can we
simulate actual real people so what does
that even mean so this is a paper that
we just put out on archives so as of
like today or yesterday um and this is
our attempt to make it more real so
again led by student June um and the key
Insight here is interviews because
remember people are very You Know Rich
and how do you pack an individual into a
an LM agent so um interviews have been
used as a you know a tool and you know
the social sciences and uh for quite
some time to capture a lot of Rich
information about you know people and so
when we were doing these pilot uh
studies you know an interviewer was
asking June you know to start tell me
the story of your life starting from the
beginning and June talks well I what
born in Korea I moved to Boston um and
then you know then the follows up a
dynamically as like oh tell me about
what was like transitioning um to Boston
from Korea well moving into a different
country is really um you know a heavy
lift and so on so you could see that the
interview content actually captures
enormous amount of information it
captures not only the factual content of
what actually happened but also um the
perspectives and the personalities of of
the
interview and so what we did here was to
try to scale this up so uh we sampled a
thousand
people demographically diverse from the
US we had each of them go through a
two-hour audio interview U with an LM
agent of course um and this produced an
interview
transcript that interview transcript now
becomes the seed of the agent memory
okay so now we have for each human over
here a corresponding agent over here so
we have a thousand humans a thousand
agents and the question is how close are
the agents to the actual corresponding
humans at the individual level to assess
this we ran a battery of surveys uh
games and experiments um which are taken
from you know the social scientists
economics
psychology and we ran the same exx
experiments on the humans as on the
agents and then we're just comparing do
they match or not okay so this is a very
nice quantitative way to answer the
question are these simulated agents
actually behaving like
people and a very quick snapshot of the
result is that yes by and large the
agents are able to capture humans of
course not you know
completely um one I think um factor is
that um humans are themselves not
consistent so if you asked um humans to
do these surveys and then you ask them
two weeks later they're only 81% of the
time matching themselves so that's sort
of a Skyline of how are you can get and
now you have these agents um based on
GPD 40 um trying to answer the same
questions they get around
69% so you can think about about this is
you're capturing 95 oh sorry 85% of the
total accuracy where Baseline is
something like in in the 20s so um so
this is not
bad
um and we we see that if you don't use
the interviews um it's it's worse so the
interviews do actually capture a
tremendous amount of
richness okay so let me reflect a bit on
blackbox API access so we can do a ton
with just blackbox apis you can create
all these agents to solve complex
problems in M Engineering and cyber
security and also to actually create
simulation agents and you can think
about this is really building an
approximate digital twin of society so
social sciences are actually really
excited about this tool because you can
it basically provides an in vitro
laboratory for them to run experiments
and you can go to do cool things like
give the same agent a the control and a
treatment you know and then measure the
difference so and you can you know we
have a thousand you know demographically
diverse so you get sort of breath now of
course it's important to remember that
these are not real humans and your
mileage might vary depending on what
your questions are asked but this
technology again is getting only better
and as long as we're being grounded and
and realistic in our expectations I
think this is going to be a um a very
powerful
tool so one thing that I think is
lacking so far is that so far these
agents have been static we've taken
off-the-shelf language models um such as
gp340 or Claude and we simply prompted
them and what we really like these
agents to be able to do is learn from
experience this is what humans do we're
not static um so you can think about
this analogy of where we are with alphao
so remember alphago had two phases one
is supervised learning on top of human
uh you know games and Then followed by
reinforcement learning where it or sort
of self-improved and I think we're for
LM you know agents or language models
were sort of here right now where we've
invested over the last four years quite
a bit of energy in terms of pre-training
these very very powerful models and now
we're be beginning to build agents and
one opportunity I see with agents is not
that only that they can do interesting
tasks but they also present new
opportunities for
Improvement because once you have an
agent that's operating some uh in
environment it can presumably get some
sort of reward signal and with that
reward signal is now you're off to the
races in terms of improving the agent so
I think it's a lot of exciting stuff to
to come but in order to do all that you
need deeper access to models you can't
just have the blackbox API anymore so
let's now descend the layer cake into
open weight models so what is open
weight model so technically these are
more more accurately they're called dual
use Foundation models with Wily
available weights um this terminology
comes from the executive order from last
year it's a bit of a mouthful so I'm
going to use the term open weights and
just as a kind of technicality um but an
important one the reason that they're
widely available as opposed to just
available is that the licenses of these
models including llama um have
restrictions for example if you're um
you have 700 million monthly active
users then it's not open to you you have
to get a special license from
meta okay so one immediate off the bat
advantage of open we models is
reproducibility so how many of you have
run experiments on text D Vinci 003 or
002 okay so some of you um and well too
bad because it's no longer available um
so one problem with these API models is
that you don't control them and once in
a while they just disappear which is
really bad from reproducibility because
now you can't reproduce any of those
experiments that you had done before
whereas if you had the weights you can
just store them um on your or your
laptop under your mattress wherever and
where they'll be safe and there
forever okay so what can you do from a
research perspective with open weight
models I'm I'm going to give you a few
examples of some of the types of
research you can do so um this is you
know much of this is not my work um
so this is work um by you know folks
from
translo um apparently if you ask llama
3.1 AP instruct this question which is
bigger 9.8 or
9. 11 um it willly 9.11 is bigger than
9.8 so if you're paying attention this
is actually incorrect um I think right
right everyone okay good um so if you
just had an API model You' be scratching
your head like why is this language
model being so ridiculous but if you
have open weights you can open up the
hood and then you can try to figure out
what's going on so this is what the the
transluc folks did which I think is
really which is really cool is that for
every single neuron they looked at um
the examples that trigger that neuron
and Ed that to create a summary of that
neuron so now if you can actually
there's a cool interface you can go play
with online where you Mouse over 11 it
shows you that 11 is triggering this
neuron that fires in references to
September 11 so now you think oh okay I
think I know what's going on is that
this is getting interpreted as a a date
or somewhat as a date and if they're
dates then you know 911 is after 9
8 okay so by looking inside you can
actually get de a deep much deeper
insight into the inner workings of these
models and debug to some of these
Mysteries they also have some examples
you can show see online where you have
um a model that refuses to answer a
question but then if you look inside it
clearly knows the answer and it's not
just just refusing to tell
you okay so here's another um fun paper
from Nvidia where they took a 15 billion
parameter model prun away some of the
layers and resulted in a 8B and a 4B
model with um minimal drop in in
performance so I think that this is one
instance I think of a larger Trend um
that I think is really interesting where
you have um big models that we have
trained but in order to use them you
need to make them smaller and so there's
the question is how do you take the the
power and modeling capab of a larger
model and sort of push it into a smaller
model and I think this relevant for
agents because agents remember it's a
you need an API in the Inner Loop of
perhaps doing some more complicated task
and you want uh potentially your API to
be much faster than just you know just
doing a one-hot um query of
API um here's another um project that uh
I think was really um impactful which is
uh adversary attack so these authors
took um llama um and uh optimized for a
prompt that essentially tries to
jailbreak it to get the mod to do
malicious things and um for this you
need open we access because you need to
um look at the gradients through the
model which is something you can't do
with like GPD
40 and um you optimize um over these um
the the prompt so that's fine but the
really mind-blowing thing is that you
take this prompt that is optimized for
llama 3 and then you just take it and
put it into the prompt for an open AI
model I think this is GPD uh
gp4 and it actually jailbreaks
gp4 so this is really fascinating
because there's something sort of really
deep and mysterious about the
transferability of these attacks and and
also it goes to show that open we models
access open we models actually have
implications on closed models because it
tells us something about closed models
because of
transferability okay so next I'm going
to tell you a little bit more about one
particular project that we've U been
doing with my student Sally Ahmed and
rohad and this is a project that is
definitely used as open weight models
but not only that it's in it exists
because because of open weight models
and I'll explain what that means so if
you go to um hugging face you'll see
that there are a ton of models out there
and some of these models are fine-tuned
on the same Foundation model and some of
them are not or at least it's claimed
that they're not and so in general they
you have these um a sort of a a zoo um
of of models and you want to understand
what what is going on what's the
relationship between those
models um because often documentation is
poor and people might be trying to
mislead other people and so on okay so
concretely what this spils down to is a
model Independence testing problem
you're given two weights sets of weights
and you're asked were these
independently trained or
not full stop and in particularly if
they're not it could be that one was
fine to from another the Theta 2 was
fine to from Theta one or they're both
fine T from a common model we don't
distinguish those cases but what we're
distinguishing is between just full
Independence and not independent okay so
I think this is very clean um so how do
you solve this
problem well and a first idea is that
you might just take the weight and just
compare them compare some cosine
similarity or some sort of similarity
metric um and for NLP weights this means
just taking the the rows and um
computing cosine similarity and
averaging um so this you know has gives
you a number um but the the problem with
this is that well you know is if you get
0.1 does that mean they're independent
or not I don't know are there any you
know guarantees it's not clear where you
set the threshold and does the threshold
depend on the model architecture it's
it's it's not very
rigorous but this is the ort of the
kernel of something we're going to turn
into actual rigorous
test um in order to do that I'm going to
introduce a thought experiment suppose
you knew how Theta 1 was created it was
created through this train function
given some random initialization of the
parameters okay so what I'm going to do
now is I'm going to just retrain a bunch
of copies of theta 1 okay in practice
we're not going to do this but thought
experiment and the idea is that
if Theta 1 and Theta 2 were truly
independent then this similarity metric
should look basically like the
similarity metric of another random
copy okay but if these Were Somehow very
correlated then this would look very
different So based on this Insight you
can construct a actual P value for the
hypothesis test of whether Theta 2 and
Theta 1 are independent by simply
looking at the fraction of times that
this um independent you know statistic
is actually more extreme than the
statistic that you actually observe with
Theta 1 and Theta 2 so this in its
Essence turns a statistic into a
threshold that gives you a formal
guarantee okay so now the problem is
that well you don't know how Theta 1
came about um because you only given the
weights you you can't actually execute
this and furthermore if even if you knew
you probably wouldn't want to train you
know spend millions of dollars training
this model over and again just to do
this
test but we can do something um here and
the goal is to fake it so we're not
actually going to train the model but
we're going to sort of pretend we did
and the idea is leveraging the sort of
natural symmetries of the model and so
we're going to Define per of theta is
you're going to permute the hidden units
defined by Theta so like this so take a
matrix and permute the
rows and the idea is that when you
permute that's kind of like a
counterfactual that's a model that could
have Arisen now I didn't actually train
from scratch to get it but because of
symmetries my I could have started with
a different initialization and also gone
to that model so it turns out you can
actually compute A P value using this um
statistic as well and this is actually a
working you know a very efficient um you
know
algorithm okay so in order to validates
this approach we looked at the subset of
hugging face models where we sort of
understood what ground truth was so in
particular models around llama 2 and
their sort of
replications um and we looked at running
this test on models that were truly
independent and we see that the p P
values are um you know all over the
place which is what you want P values
are supposed to be uniformly distributed
if um under the under n and um if
they're not independent then the P
values are actually minuscule so you ask
about statistical significance well this
is like kind of um blowing out of the
water this is like actually under
flowing to the significant to the point
where it's underflow so this is a very
strong test um and it's sort kind of a
Smoking Gun that these were actually not
independent which
um is true because we know that these
models are fine tunes of llama
to
okay so uh more fun things we can do so
earlier this year there was a
controversy around this mysterious model
Miku that appeared on the on the
internet and people suspected it was a
um a leak that was mistal fine-tuning
llama 2 and uh you know eventually the
mistro CEO said yes it was it was a leak
model um and indeed we were able to
verify with our test that indeed these
two models are um not independent of
each other um there's we also were able
to show that striped hyena which is a
model was derived from
mistol and then finally um llama 3.2 the
their 3B model in their blog post they
show say that this is derived from llama
3.1 B and we also verify that indeed
these are not independent but moreover
what's I think um really interesting is
that our test not only gives you the
single bit of information whether two
models are independent or not but it
actually tells you which layers were
derived from which layer so we were able
to show that certain layers of llama 3
were 8B were used to create the 3B model
so this is information that actually
wasn't um included in the the actual
blog post which is kind of a cool bit of
reverse engineering there okay so some
Reflections on open weight models so
it's very clear that open weight models
such as llama 3 have been immensely
valuable for research I only showed you
a small fraction of all the papers that
have been using llama 3 and I'm sure
some of you are using it in your own
research as well so in enable research
on inability different fine-tuning
techniques distillation model merging
and furthermore you get all this to
these nice reproducible um you know
guarantees and not having to worry about
model
deprecation one I think uh interesting
thing about open weight models is that
you're making these very sort of
arbitrary changes to the weights by by
averaging them by taking out layers and
they're sort of kind of frud in a way
and the question is how do these on
Earth yield any sort of functional uh
changes that are coherent and the answer
is that they don't there's no guarantee
of this and in general you actually have
to go back and fine-tune your model and
sort of heal it after you sort of rip
out like you know half of its um you
know
layers um openway models also teaches of
us about API models and it also opens up
new types of problems for example this
model Independence testing problem would
we wouldn't have worked on this problem
if it weren't for open weight models at
all so but at the end of the day we're
still confined by the blueprint of
existing models so all these models are
still Transformer architectures they're
still the particular set of Weights that
meta has you know given us and so in
order to go deeper to open source we
need to you know open up the the hood
more so
fortunately there have been a lot of
there's a lot of open- source language
um model efforts from you know Lu to ai2
the hugging face and so on um and each
of these is trying to create you know
open source models um the the downside
is at this present moment the open
source models are far uh weaker than the
strongest um you know open weight or API
models um so but you know what is
exactly is you know open source um so a
little bit of kind of historical context
open source clearly comes from the term
open source software and open source
software and free software have had a
long history in in you know computer
science coming stemming from the roots
in you know MIT in the 50s the hacker
culture and it's idea in Academia where
you do open science um these are sort of
the roots that Inspire open source and
it has coess into these values of
creativity exploration transparency
collaboration resistance against
Authority so this sort of defines what
open source sort of stands for and of
course there's famous um you know
figures like Richard stalman and lonus
torold that created this whole ecosystem
around g g Linux and that led to um the
open source initiative founding in 98
which finally defined the term you know
open source and so open source were
practiced long before the term open
source software even was defined and now
OSI is now trying to Define what open
source means for AI and it can be
summarized in terms of Four Freedoms the
ability to use a system without asking
for permission the ability to study the
ability to modify and the ability to
share okay and in more detail open
source definition requires that the
model parameters be available so this is
open weights but without restrictions um
that the code be available and here the
code importantly means not just the the
inference code but the training code and
also the data processing and filtering
code because the data is actually a
vital ingredient in determining the
behavior of these models and without the
knowledge of how the data was
constructed you can't really be truly
open
source and finally there's data
information and so you might answer ask
the question why data information and
not data and the answer is that you
don't want to get sued um so and
basically the longer version is that
most Foundation models are trained on
web data and web data is you know sort
of anything goes it's most of it's
copyrighted or at least it's not clear
that is not copyrighted and so model
developers don't actually own the
license to redistribute or the data so
there are some lawsuits that are going
to settle hopefully you know next year
or something um that are going to rule
on whether training on this data is fair
use but even if training is fair use um
you still can't do redistribute the
copies of someone else's book kind of
verbatim okay so another piece that I
think is critical is the ability to
modify and I would say that compute is
an important ingredient here so this is
not technically part of the open source
definition nowhere does it say you need
a compute but in order to achieve the
spirit of being able to modify a system
it's clear that you need compute
otherwise you have this thing and you
can actually you know you if you want to
change the data well you need to kind of
retrain at least or at least do continue
pre-training or
something
so I'm going to talk about three
projects that we've done that really
require deep access to um the kind of
full training process and and the
weights and the data and so on so the
first paper I'm just going to go these
very you know briefly so there're not
going to be too much detail here there's
a question is what mixture over data
sources do you use so language models
are typically trained over some
combination of Wikipedia books web code
and so on and usually people just set
the weights sort of you know magically 2
uh books you know 04 code looks good to
me based on Vibes but we uh created a a
procedure based on distribution and
robust optimization which automatically
Tunes these mixtur and we show that this
per performs 2.6 times um faster or
trains a model 2.6 times faster than a
manually specified weights so in order
to do this research you clearly need to
be able to train models from
scratch um a second uh project we did
was on um developing a new Optimizer
based on uh second order information in
particular the look at the diagonal hes
with some clipping and this provides a
2X speed up over atom and again of
course in order to do this research you
need to be able to train from scratch to
show um uh that you get improvements
over some atom and the final um
project we did was on Pro producing
another architecture on alternative to a
Transformer that is not as monolithic
and is more
interpretable um so it's called the
backpack language model and without
going to any detail this model architure
allows for precise model editing so you
can take a language model and you can
sort of with a test time intervention of
some hidden uh units get the model to
edit it into a world where it believe
beli that the MacBook was created by HP
rather than Apple
um okay so all this is nice and well we
so we touched the learning algorithm the
architecture and the data you know
recipe now I often get this question
would these results hold if we scaled
out and really what this question is
asking is you know how do you get the
compute to even answer that question and
so for this I think this is where open
source I think is really at um is is
really kind of
bottlenecked um and so I'll give you
three sort of suggestions on how we
might deal with the compute problem the
first is that use scaling laws okay so
typically you think about scaling laws
is telling you about bigger and bigger
models right but one thing that I think
SK law could be made to do but currently
I don't think they do this very well is
sort of extend in the opposite direction
into a smaller
regime where you can operate in a
smaller scale model with a belief or the
hope that whatever you do down here
different data different architecture is
actually going to scale up to larger
scales and this is a way that I think
you can work at small scale but with a
mindset of scaling
up okay second is there are actually a
lot of idle gpus you know everywhere so
most of the time people always complain
not enough compute not compute but there
are pockets of times where there is Idle
compute and so if we were only able to
harness all this globally we could
actually there's probably quite a lot of
compute um available to do certain
things and one technical hurdle to this
is that the interconnect speed when
you're looking at decentralized compute
is just horrible it's you know at least
two orders of magnitude worse than it is
in the data center and training large
Foundation models requires fast
interconnects um two years ago we had
this this paper which show that uh with
some amount of clever scheduling and
some sort of lowlevel systems um work
you can actually train one billion
parameter models at the time um in a way
that's only two times slower than if you
were doing in a data center even though
the interconnects were 100 times slower
okay so this is promising and since then
there's been a lot of work including uh
dloo from from De mine um showing a
better you know an um algorithm to do
this and there's been even this this
effort from Prime intellect where there
is a decentralized training effort
happening of a 10 billion parameter
model where um anyone can just you know
pull compute into this massive pool so I
think this is really exciting to see how
far you can get with the central ized
compute okay so track number three is um
basically ask for more money um and so
there's the N the national AI research
resource um which has a pilot that is
trying to get more compute to fund um
you know a public AC um academic AI
research um and hopefully you know well
we the pilot I think is is
is is ending but hopefully this will be
renewed and hopefully we'll be able to
get see more of this um it is worth
noting that other fields kind of have
figured this out right and by it I mean
being able to harness a um advocate for
the funding of massive infrastructure
projects for example the Human Genome
Project um you know in James web's
telescope the um you know LHC these are
multi-billion
projects that are in service of open
academic research right not just for you
know commercial but for AC academic
research and the idea is that the types
of problems that you would solve if you
were structured in sort of this public
domain is different than what you know
the open AIS and the anthropics would
do okay so um just to conclude we've
talked about the three different levels
of access
um I think um underlying theme here that
I want to stress is that access shapes
the research right so if you have API
access there are a lot of interesting
things you do and we've been doing a lot
of these things building all sorts of
different agents um with open we models
you can do a lot more you can fine-tune
you can do
distillation and you can do a lot um of
interesting things with open we models
as well but I think it's important to
recognize that our research lives more
and more today are living within the
confines of the apis and fixed
weights and in order to make I think
fundamental progress we need to question
more things we need to AG question the
data the the model architecture the
training algorithm in order to make more
uh you know progress and not be stuck in
this local Optimum and the eventual goal
is to really understand the mapping
between data and model architecture to
Model Behavior and this is hard even if
you have full access right in the 2010s
we were complaining about how hard deep
learning was to understand and now
things are a lot worse when you only
have API access there's no hope so at
least if we can get open source access
we have some hope of answering these
sort of deep um fundamental questions
about
Ai and of course compute is a big
challenge here
I think there's still a lot of things
you can do at small scales I think you
can do things at small scale but with a
mindset of scale and also I think it's
really interesting to think about how we
can do decentralized pooling of compute
so we can do more than we together than
we can do
individually okay with that I'll
conclude and take any questions thanks