Okay. So, welcome back to diffusion and
flow models. So, since it's been a
while, I I'm going to briefly basically
review what we have uh discussed so far
and also the today's lecture will be
kind of dense in terms of that we are
going to see lots of the formulations.
uh but the purpose that I'm showing the
all the formulations here is not to just
explain the all the formulations is the
line by line but more about basically to
explain how the things that we have
discussed in this class are basically
all the connected each other uh so
that's kind of the main part of the
today's lecture and especially we are
going to discuss how the DDIM the
sampling uh that we discussed last time
is also kind of connected with some kind
of continuous time deformation So, so
speaking to that uh let's briefly remind
what we have discussed uh before
regarding the DDI and the deterministic
deb process. Uh so what you have seen
last time is that we could basically use
some the pre-trained DDP model which was
basically used for the DDP and the
sampling to make it as kind of the DDI
and the deterministic sampling by
changing the formulation like this and
based on that we could basically have
those kind of like three steps in terms
like know sampling the next one the next
the the noise the sample the XT minus
one given the XT here. Uh so you should
be basically familiar with like this
formulation at this point. Uh so
regarding uh this formulation like let
me start with this quiz. Uh so yeah so
this is the case we can make it this is
kind of zero making it deterministic.
So based on this now what we can do is
that u we can write the single line
expression
excuse me of the xt which see the uh xt
in terms of the x t + one right and also
the noise prediction of the from the xt
+ one right uh so let's first try to
write the expression of the xt uh in
terms of the xt + one and all the the
kind of the coefficients and also the
noise term
Uh
we going to uh see this again at the end
of like this lecture.
Yeah, everyone should now get this
answer, right? So the thing is that yeah
this is literally just like one line of
the code. Uh so every time what you just
need to do is that I guess you already
implement this in the first assignment,
right? uh you could actually implement
the each of the the update step in the
DTI and the sampling uh with the single
line right by just taking the uh
previous noise sample if we just compute
all the things while involving the noise
prediction here then we can directly
compute the activity here right so we're
going to see this formulation again uh
in the previous lecture
and so we are basically seeing some kind
of the sort of more the general
diversion of BP models
uh we started our discussion from the
DDPM and DDIM kind of sort of the the
more the general version of the
diffusion models and then even we
started to see the same model uh in the
continuous time domain. So in the
continence time domain the same
diffusion models could be uh represented
expressed as kind of the stoastically
differential equation uh with the the SD
defined in this way uh by just defining
this like f function here uh and also
the the g function here the the drift
term and also the division the
coefficients term uh and the interesting
thing was that uh given the hourly
definition of the for SDE the
corresponding the reverse SD was could
be derived into this form uh while
basically involving some kind of the
score comes here. Uh so that's al kind
of thing once we define the for SD then
we can also directly define the reverse
SD uh into the this formulation. So this
was kind of the key fact that we
discussed last time and since the score
can be now computed with our the epsilon
predictor the noise predictor here when
you plug this in uh into the liver SD
formulation then now we can see that the
liver SD can be rewritten into this
formulation.
So which means that now if we just like
define our own the f function the g
function here and the then the reverse
process becomes like dissolving this
like sv deformulation. Uh so these are
also things that we have discussed last
time
and we basically have discussed some
kind of specific divergence of division
models last time the dpm and also the uh
the stmm kind of the cases. So those are
some kind of some special uh the cases
of like this general form of the
diffusion models. Uh so these general
form diffusion models are typically
called the variational diffusion models
or the diffusion the pro the
probabilistic models for those kind of
cases we could also define the diffusion
models by defining our own the alpha
function here and also the sigma
function here. So this is kind of the
another way that we can also define uh
the diffusion models with the for the
diffusion the distribution uh like the
this basically sampling the xt the noise
data point given the clean data point x0
here. So uh in this case the only kind
of the constraint that we had for the
definition of the alpha function and the
sigma function here is that we just need
to basically define these two functions
in a way that this the signal to the the
noise ratio the ratio between the rind
sigma becomes like monotonically
decreases over time. So the meaning of
basically having this SNR to be
decreasing over time is that we are
basically gradually adding the noise
into the given the the noise data point
in a way that at the end it becomes the
one of the the samples of the standard
region the distribution. So this
basically means that if we can define
any of some kind of the alpha and the
sigma functions basically satisfying the
this condition so that can be basically
another diversion of the diffusion
models. So we discussed some kind of
some special versions of like the alpha
and the sigma functions but actually it
doesn't need to be that specific form
you can define any forms of the alpha
and the sigma functions
and also the meaning of like basically
defining the fold the diffusion
distribution into this way is that
basically we can uh do the sampling of
the xt uh into this way. So when you
basically uh remember this formulation
what you can do is that the sampling the
xt can be basically considered that
basically sampling the any of the clean
data point x0 and also the standard
denial the sample the z here and just
taking the sort of the linear
interpolation between these two right so
this is exactly the aligned with some
kind of the our definition of the for uh
the the jump distribution right so when
you define the for the jump distriution
into the this gausian deform the
sampling the xt here
basically be it comes that we are taking
any of the x here and then taking the
standard gausian the sample and then
bically you know multiplying those kind
of the coefficients and taking some kind
of the sum of them right
so please uh remember this uh we are
going to see this uh in the next lecture
as well
So given this kind of the um the general
form of the diffusion model with the B
distusion. So what we have seen last
time is that uh we can go like the the
back and forth in terms of that. Uh
given our the definition of the full
process the SD defining the f function
the g function. Uh the question last
time is that how we can also derive the
corresponding the full distriution
defined with the alpha sigma function.
So given the f and the g function now we
could also derive this like alpha and
the sigma function in this way basically
defining the fusion models either into
the form of the sde or into the form of
the full distribution like this or we
could do the other way around but based
on the definition in the previous slide
given the full distribution basically
defined with the alpine sigma function
now we also could derive the f and the g
function into this way. So those are
basically the formulations that we have
seen last time. So please also keep this
in mind in terms of that given the f and
the g function we can also derive these
two and we can go also the other way
around. Given the four distribution we
can also der as well. So how exactly
this like the full distribution and also
the force are defined for the special
cases that we have seen last time.
So for the SM LD case for the uh this
the quality uh the distribution for
those kind of cases what you can see is
that when you take the sigma function as
our kind of the the parameter function
then the full distribution was defined
with this the alpha and the sigma
function. So this is kind of some the
given function the usual defined
function right and we just set the alpha
function to be one. This was the case
and given these RP and the sigma D
function we could also see that L and
the G functions are like defined in this
way right and for the DDPM case that you
already implemented in the assignment
one when the beta function is kind of
our the prompt function then we could
see that the alpine the sigma function
define the full distribution now can be
defined in this way and also the for SD
actually becomes quite simple form in
terms of that the f function becomes
like the minus the half of the val
function and the G function becomes the
square root of the val function. Right?
So these could be all derived based on
the uh the connection between the for
distribution and the for SD uh that we
we have seen in these two slides
and as I said like these are some kind
of the two special cases of like
defining uh the specific the form of the
diffusion the probability model and
actually there are more there are many
many more so uh we are not going to
basically discuss all those kind of the
cases you can see that there are like
DDPM plus like something like something
there's many kind of adult cases. If you
are also interested in some kind of more
the options you can uh check out uh this
kind this paper
and the thing is that one thing that is
very confusing uh last time was that as
I said uh there's no textbook for this
topic so for many of the formulations
here I'm just following the formulations
in the some of the recent papers the
problem is that all the papers are
basically using not using basically the
consistent notations
Which means that there are these kind of
cases like know the alpha basically we
have the introduced the DDP lecture are
basically different with alpha that we
are basically using in the BDM uh the
the variational diffusion model the
formulation. So those are some kind of
the confusions right uh so I'm going to
clarify here so those are some kind of
the definitions that we have seen for
the DDPM case you remember uh so we had
that the once we define the beta
function based on that we defined the
IPA head here basically these are all
the operator we have seen the DDPMD
slice are not related to the alterative
function that we are seeing in the
vision diffusion models so we will need
to clearly see how these are basically
uh they connected each other. So the
thing is that
uh in the DDPM the fourth the jump
distribution uh was defined into this
way right. Uh but in the hourly the
definition of the variation diffusion
model this should be the alpha the
function in the variation diffusion
models right and this should be sigma
the sigma the squared in the vial
diffusion models. So which means that
actually the alpha that we have seen in
the DD formulation as this connection
the square root of the alpha bar here
becomes the alpha function in the PDM
formulation and also the square root of
the one minus the alpha is basically is
the same with the sigma function. So
don't get confused with this kind of
very confusing denotations. So this is
kind of the the problems with the
notations that we are using. But
basically yeah uh we are now going to
switch the hourly discussion into the
more into the general diversion the
variational division models which means
that we are now switching all the kind
of denotations uh into this form
basically introducing like those uh
basically the new the variables here.
So based on those kind of the mapping uh
from the variables that we have seen in
the DDPM case uh with the variational
division models now what we can see is
that we can basically rewrite all the
things that we have seen in the uh the
previous lectures the DDPM DDID case
especially the DDIMD deterministic
reverse process. Now the formulation of
the XT can be seen as basically the
alpha and the sigma functions. those
alpine the sigma are basically not the
things that we have seen in the DDPM
case but coming from the BDM uh the
variational division model uh the the
parameters here. So based on those
parameters in the uh the variational
division models now we can uh see the XT
can be basically written into this
formulation
nothing but just like changing the
variables here right
and also uh for the reverse SD we can
also basically rewrite some part of the
formulation in terms of basically the
alpha the semantic functions that we
using the BM formulations. Okay so those
are some kind of the
uh remarks. So uh please keep these
formulations in mind. Uh we're going to
get back to those formulations. So this
is basically nothing but basically we
are seeing the same the DGI and the
sampling and also the same the uh
reverse process the SD uh based on the
variables that we have seen uh we have
basically used uh to define the uh the
general form of the diffusion models uh
the diffusion deposit models. So we are
going to keep using uh the alpine the
sigma functions in here. Okay, is this
clear? So, please keep this in mind.
And one more basically very confusing
thing might be is that uh I'm just going
to introduce like one more variable uh
the lambda function here. Uh so that's
basically making even more the confusion
here. Uh but we want to get back to this
like why we are basically introducing
this kind of the new variable here. So
basically the meaning of this like this
like lambda the function is basically
nothing but the half of the log of the
SNR. So this this when we have this cur
here this was the SNR right we can see
that this lambda function is the half of
the log of the the SNR. So when you
introduce the lambda function here then
we can also uh know rewrite some part of
the formulation. Basically the g uh this
cur function can be also written into
the form of the lambda function.
So this means that when you introduce
the lambda function here then we can uh
see the basically the conversion from
the full distribution into the full sd
into this formulation uh becomes
basically simpler like this right uh the
g function can be basically simplified
into this way.
So those are some kind of the basic
things to discuss to this topic
actually. So if I just like uh remind
these things that we uh discussed last
time uh the some of the key facts is
that basically the fourth the diffusion
process uh can be described into the
using the SDE uh in the continuous time
domain. So which means that now we can
define a SD uh for the fourth the
difficulty the process and then the
thing is that we can also derive the
corresponding the SD for the reverse
process uh based on the four the process
deformulation. So those are kind of the
some key facts uh in the contain time
deformationations
and also the thing is that uh we start
to see some kind of the some more the
general version of the diffusion models
which we call the variational diffusion
models or so sometimes called the
diffusion the proposity models and the
the two the cases the SMLD and the DDPM
or basically the special cases of like
this kind of general form right so these
are those kind of the key effect and
also the other the key effect was that
the fold SDE uh can be basically derived
from some kind of the our the definition
of the fold distribution and also the
other way can be also done uh by the
conversion that we have seen uh in the
previous slide. So are these clear?
So those are some kind of like some key
connections between the for uh the the
content time deformation and the
discrete time deformation.
And also the more important thing is
that uh for the diffusion uh the model
with the SD deformationation we can
always find some kind of the
corresponding the OD formulation uh
which basically matches the same the
marginal distribution. So which means
that uh we also have seen the DDIMD case
which is kind of the generalization of
the DDPM. So when we also could see that
how we can convert uh the reverse
process of division model into the
deterministic the sampling right. So
actually this kind of the SE due to the
the OD the conversion is kind of like
know changing the stoastic sampling of
the SD into the deterministic sampling
using the OD. So in the SD formulation
we are basically injecting some kind of
the noise every time right some
stocketistic in the OD formulation there
is no some kind of the uh some random
noise which means that we can make the
reverse process to be deterministic
uh when you start from the kind of the
same the starting point we going to
always go to the same end point so
that's kind of something kind of the
similar the connection that we have seen
in the from the DDPM the DDM case we can
basically convert the SD into the
corresponding the OD in terms of that we
can do the same kind of the sampling
without basically involving any kind of
stockistic in the sampling the process.
So which means that uh when you see the
uh reverse the diffusion process
actually we can conduct all those kind
of degeneration process by solving the
OD formulation. So that's kind of the
key idea uh in the diffusion models.
So this is also the formulation that we
have seen. Uh so this kind of
corresponding the OD is what typically
called the property flow the OD. So this
is the the se formulation that we have
seen for the reverse process and then
the corresponding the pod uh basically
matching the same the the marginal
distribution is basically expressed into
this way also having some very similar
deforms right the only difference is
that now we having the uh you know one
over two here and not having some kind
of the uh and also yeah not having the
the the uh the node thumb here right I
think this should not be secured here.
So this is some kind of the the type.
Um
yes and also we have seen that uh the
liverd can be basically written into the
uh the noise prediction term here and
also the same thing also can be applied
into the pod here right. Uh so given
this basically what we can see is that
uh for the hourly definition of the
alpha and the sigma function here. So
once we define the alpha function and
the sigma functions in the uh in the
form of the variation diffusion models
if we plug in those those kind of the f
function the g function into the pod
then now it becomes that the reverse
process becomes like solving this
formulation uh given the our definition
of the alpha and the sigma functions.
So now we can consider all those kind of
the generation the process as basically
solving the od formulation.
Resolving the OD basically means that
every time like given the XT. Now what
we can do is that we can compute the
first the derivative of the XT uh which
means that we have some kind of the uh
way to basically compute the velocity in
the field. So given any kind of the uh
the point in the space uh given the
information of the XT and also the noise
predictor what you can do is that we can
predict the velocity into this
structure. we are having some kind of
the information of the velocity field.
But the the thing is that this velocity
computation involves some kind of the
neural net prediction right. So every
time we just need to basically run the
the the the fit for the the the process
of your network right but given this
kind of the velocity field what we just
need to do is that from the starting
point uh which is the sample from the
spendicion the uh the distribution we
just need to find the trajectory over
the space in terms of that where this
point goes at the end of the all the
kind of the time domain right and the
kind of the one of the n way to
obviously compute this kind of
trajectory might be that we are
basically moving very small step every
case right so every basically the point
what you just need to is that we just
compute the velocity and just while
assuming this kind of some sort of
linearity of the velocity we just like
move a little bit into this fraction and
just compute the velocity again and just
go moving a little bit again right uh
with some kind of a very small the steps
so this is the most the dive way which
is called the oiler the method in terms
of solving the OD the the formulations.
So this is kind of similar that what
what you have done uh in the diffusion
uh delivers process right but the key
thing that we are discussing here is
that we want to compute these kind of
trajectories uh with some kind of the
fear number of the steps and also the
challenges that we are basically doing
for the image generation is basically
how we are going to achieve some kind of
the good uh the image outputs with the
few number of the steps right uh so
that's kind of things so which means
that by just computing the velocity just
for the very few steps. How we also
going to compute some kind of those kind
of trajectory like more the accurate
ways. So that's kind of the key idea
here. So that's also kind of a key idea
in terms of that know how we are going
to basically accelerate uh the reverse
process of the diffusion models and for
that actually without seeing the OD
deformationation that we are having
actually there are quite many the
techniques that I guess some of you
might be familiar with like those kind
of things. So if you took the OD
basically the course uh in the math
department then you might familiar with
those kind of some kind of the
techniques. So those are basically the
all the techniques in terms of then how
we can basically uh compute those kind
of the trajectories uh with the velocity
field uh with the field the number of
steps but these are some kind of some
more the the general method uh without
basically leveraging any kind of the
characteristics of the formulations and
the things that we are going to discuss
for today is basically how we are going
to basically understand some kind of the
the specific characteristics of this
specific the OD formulation and then
make some kind of the more efficient
dissolver for this OD formulation for
this specific the OD formulation not for
some kind of degenerative OD formulation
in terms of that we can basically solve
this OD uh with a few number of steps in
a more effective way so that's kind of
the main thing so uh please keep this in
mind so this is the OD formulation that
we are going to solve right so you can
see that this OD formulation has some
kind of structure
in terms of that actually this form of
the OD formulation is called the uh
semilinear the first order OD in terms
of that this looks like some kind of the
linear formulation right so basically we
have the xd here and some kind of the
coefficient function here so it looks
like some linear function right so
linear basically does not mean that this
function is kind of linear right I mean
so we see it's kind of like the whole
the function is linear with respect to
the xt here right uh so we have XT is
some kind of linear function but this is
actually not linear. This is called the
semi linear in terms of that we having
the nonlinear come here right if we did
not have like this part then this would
be perfect linear function right but
since we have this like the noise
prediction uh this is neural network
obviously this would not be basically
the linear function right uh this having
some kind of nonlinear lineality into
the populations so this is kind of like
know combining some kind of linear part
and some kind of nonlinear part here so
in terms of that this is called some
kind of semilinear DOD deformationation
and we are going to see how we are going
to how we can derive some kind of some
uh some dedicated disorder for those
specific deform of the OD formulations
in terms of that uh we can basically
solve this OD in like more uh effective
way
but before we get into that uh uh just
in case that you are not basically
familiar with OD I'd like to go with
some kind of some or some kind of the
basic things with the OD.
So as I said uh this is kind of the form
of the OD that we are solving not
exactly this because we also having the
XT as kind of the input the parameters
of the Q functions here right but let's
start with some kind of the this like
even simpler form exactly the linear
formulation right uh so as I said the
linear in terms of that this kind of the
function that we are going to obtain
right and given this function this whole
formulation is kind of like this
formulation is linear and this is the
first order the derivatives Right.
Uh so let's think about this simple
deformationation and even simpler one.
Let's assume that this QT term is
basically zero. So we some completely
linear function here and let's also
assume that easier case that the XT is
basically always like non- negative
always the positive in this specific
case.
Then for this kind of the very simple
the form of the OD formulation how we
can find the function that satisfies
this equation
>> yes uh but uh yes we are going to take
some kind of exponential function of the
xt uh but if we get some into some more
the details here
uh let's basically assume that no the x
is bally non zero basically for all the
t then we can basically divide each side
by the one of the basically dividing by
the xt here then you can see that this
left hand side can be simplified uh into
the other way right can you see so we
are having the one over the xt times the
first dative of the xt and then this
left side uh can be basically simplified
into the derivatives of the natural log
of the xt
So if you basically take the the
derivative of the the log of xt then we
get basically this way. So in terms of
that we can see that by dividing both
side with the x by the xt we can see
that the left side actually becomes the
derivatives of the uh the log of the xt
then what you can do is that we can
simply just take the integral for the
both sides and take the exponential term
right then you're going to see that
actually the xt uh becomes those kind of
the exponential the function with
respect to the uh the p function here
make sense right
So yeah, I just like went over all the
things like quite fast but uh let's see
uh let's try yourself. Uh so when you
have like this simple form of the OD
minus one /2 with the XT with some kind
of the initial condition that the X0 is
basically the one. So since this is the
case that we already define kind of the
velocity field, we also need to have
some kind of the starting point, right?
So let's set let's set the starting
points as kind of the when the x0 uh
when the time is zero let's say the x
function becomes the one. So given this
initial condition if we solve uh the xt
uh what's dxt uh
can you try yourself?
Did you all get the answer?
It becomes like very simple right it's
basically exponential of the minus one /
2 * xt right uh so yeah for those kind
of the simple form now we can see how we
can find the solution for the od right
so we are basically getting into some
kind of more the complex case uh so we
have seen this uh let's go into the
general the case and let's go even more
general case the semilinear deformation
so this Exactly the formulation that we
are let's say tackling in the pf case.
So this is kind of the nonlinear term.
We having some kind of linear function
here. Right? So given this kind of
formulation how we can have some kind of
the analytic the solution for this like
the OD right. So basically that's the
main purpose like this discussion why we
can achieve use some kind of some
numerical method. uh the easiest kind of
the uh way to taking some numerical
method is the oil method right just just
like moving uh you know it's very small
step every times right but now what we
are going to do is that we are going to
try our best in terms like dering the
analytic deformulations in terms of that
we can basically achieve some kind of
the better results uh with the few
number of steps
for these like semilinear deformations
uh what we are going to do is that uh we
are going to leverage uh this effect. So
this is basically the solution of this
like simple form that we have seen uh in
the previous slide.
So here to derive the energy
formulations for this like the
generality case what we are going to do
is that we are going to use some kind of
the very well-known some kind of clever
technique which is called the
exponential integrator. So this is the
formulation that we are going to solve
right
to solve this what we are going to do is
that uh I'm going to just briefly
introduce this kind of the new function
which is called the integrating the
factor uh which is basically the
function that basically become the
solution of like this 4D formulation.
Don't ask me why we introduce this
function for now because we're going to
uh get the reason very soon. uh so let's
first def uh define this like the mu
function uh that becomes basically the
solution or like this od formulation
and in the previous slide we have seen
that the solution of like this
formulation becomes like this stuff
right so we're having some kind of
exponential function here right so the
reason like why we are basically
introducing this like integrating factor
is that uh once we define this like the
mu function uh let's basically simply
multiply uh the both sides uh by this
integrating factor
having the mu term here, mu term here
and the mu term here and based on the
product rule of the uh differentiation
that we know here. Uh then now we can
see how this like left hand side can be
also simplified right can you guess like
how this left hand side can be
simplified in this case.
So remember that the mu function is
basically the solution of like this od
the derivative of the mu function
becomes like this term and based on this
product rule how we can simplify this
left hand side
you see that this left hand side the
whole left hand side becomes like
derivative like some function right uh
so we can see that actually the whole
left hand side can be now simplified
into the The derivative of the product
of like these two functions, right?
Because the derivative of the new
function was by definition then we
defined that becomes the uh this term
and this is the derative of the xt and
from the product rules then you can see
that the left hand side simplified into
this way. So that's why we are basically
introducing the mu function to simplify
the formulation into this way.
Then the rest of thing is kind of the
more like the straightforward that is
exactly the same thing. We're just
taking the integral for the both and
also then we are when you say that
actually the mu function is basically
the non- negative. So even positive then
we can also divide all the things into
by the mut. So you can see that we can
also easily derive some kind of the
analytic the solution for the semilinear
reverse of the semilinear formulation.
So we are going to basically leverage
this fact in terms of basically
introducing some kind of the more
efficient the OD solver for the P or the
E formulation.
So the only remaining thing is that we
just need to plug in this hourly
definition of the mu function here right
then it becomes like quite complicated
like this like having all the kind of
exponential terms. The good thing is
that we can simplify this further in
terms of that they are basically sharing
the same base of the integral here. So
by just you know you know simplifying
all the things now we can say that uh
this becomes basically our the analytic
deformation of the semilinear the OD. So
given some kind of the starting the
point of the S here. So this is kind of
the initial the point right. So this
will be some kind of the uh some initial
value the starting point starting from
the S right. So this is kind of the
given information. So given this kind of
the XS and basically we can now compute
the XT by computing those kind of
intermed.
So while basically this looks kind of
complicated like what we also do is that
uh given the kind of the the the in the
exponential the integrator that we have
seen the previous slide now we can
basically just like derive some kind of
the analytic form of the any of the
first order the semlinear the
deformationations.
So keep this in mind complicated. So if
we do one thing more uh then let's also
see some kind of the more the complex
case. So now we have the uh this is
still kind of the constant with respect
to the xt right but when you have some
kind of like so offset term here and be
some kind of same the initial condition
can you also derive the xt satisfying
this formulation.
uh let's try this
is the same uh with what you get.
I just like plugged in all the things
into the formulation that we have seen
and these are cancelled out and we can
say actually the XT becomes like this
simple right.
So in this like short amount of time you
got some kind of the baseline idea in
terms like how we can deal some kind of
the analytic solutions uh for some
simple the OD formation right. So here
basically the key thing is that uh not
in the kind of the sort of the math
perspective but in the some computer
scientific perspective uh what we can
basically do is that whatever the OD
that we have uh we can basically use
some kind of the some numerical the
approaches we don't care like what sort
of the OD formations do we have the the
simplest kind of way as I said is that
basically every time we we while
assuming some kind of linearity we just
like move a little bit and just like go
there and just compute the velocity gate
and just move a little again. Uh so that
can be kind of the simplest way that we
can basically compute the trajectory
right. Uh the thing is that if we want
to basically compute the trajectory like
you know like more accurate way uh we
will need lots of the steps right as we
also have some kind of very complex and
kind of the the trajectory as the
trajectory is basically not straight.
The thing is that if all the
trajectories are basically straight,
then how many steps do we need? We just
need one step, right? From the very
starting the point to the end point. If
that the trajectory is just like
straight line, then what you just need
is the the velocity at the the beginning
point, right? You just go straight until
the end point. So that's kind of thing.
uh in terms like solving the OD
formulation uh if we basically want to
get some kind of the accurate the
results of the computation with the very
few number of steps the key thing is
that we just need need to make all the
trajectories to be straight as much as
possible uh so that's a thing but we
don't know uh for the diffusion models
that we trained how much those kind of
the velocity field that we are getting
with the OD formulation would be uh how
much that would be restraint
So in terms of that uh especially for
some kind of the all the kind of the
very curvy the trajectories uh we will
need to have some kind of the last of
steps uh to get some kind of the
accurate the uh the prediction of the uh
the trajectory and also get some kind of
the accurate outputs for the at the end.
So that's kind of the same uh with like
what we have seen the DDPM case it
should be the same because DDP DDPM is
kind of some kind of discretization case
of the SD formulation. So also in the
DDPM we need to have some kind of the
last of the steps uh to get some kind of
the accurate outputs right uh the same
thing in the OD formulations as well and
there are some kind of the many
well-known techniques uh in the
numerical approaches in terms of that
whatever the OD deformationation that we
have how we can basically get some kind
of the accurate kind of the uh the
trajectories with the few number of
steps there you can basically consider
using those kind of some kind of
techniques in terms of reducing the
number of steps. But those are all the
techniques that are basically not using
any kind of the information or some
characteristics of the specific DOD
formulation. And what we are aiming here
is that uh we are going to basically
consider the characteristics of the OD
formulation the PF OD that we are seeing
uh which is having this kind of the
first over the semi linear structure and
based on the observation of like this
structure how we are going to see some
kind of the more uh the effective way to
solve this like the information by
somehow deriving some kind of the
analytic deformationations as much as
possible.
So that's the basic idea. So if we get
back to the this formation the paper
formation that we have seen in the
previous slide as I said like this is
the semi linear kind of things we but
having the P function here and the Q
function here. So this is the nonlinear
term uh nonlinear because that we are
involving the noise prediction here
right so this is the only nonlinear
terms here the neural network and then
anything else is basically some kind of
the coefficients that we are defining.
So these are basically all the functions
that we defined right. So we can
basically so these are some kind of the
given functions right.
So based on that uh when you basically
compute the exponential of the p
function in this way then we can see
that actually this formulation can be
simplified into this way. So still we
have some kind of the linear comes here
which is kind of some con some kind of
the the the user defined functions and
having those functions.
So the thing is that uh this is already
kind of quite simplified right in terms
of that we have just like uh the noise
prediction here and some kind of terms
here.
uh one kind of the key idea here is that
we are going to further simplify this by
reparizing the second the integral from
here.
So this basically shows the reason
basically why we are introducing the
lambda function here which was the half
of the log of the sn
here the key idea is that uh now we are
going to so this the whole the integral
part was basically parameterized with
the time t right but instead of like
basically seeing the time t what we are
going to see is that this lambda was
basically the log the half of the log
snr which is basically monotonically
decreasing function
which means that there are some kind of
the one one to one correspondence from
the lambda the value into the time t
here. So which means that there are some
kind of the there is basically some
inverse function from the time t. So
there's the the function from the t to
the lambda and also the inverse function
from the lambda to t as well.
So based on this fact what we are going
to do is that in terms like further
simplifying the second part here we are
going to basically reparameterize the
like this whole function uh not based on
the time t here is the to here basically
reparatizing into the lambda here which
is the half of the log uh the effect of
that is that now we can basically cancel
this out because we basically coming
back to the becomes the identity
function right uh so based on that uh we
can see that actually that the complex
the OD formulation for these process
became simplified into this way. So this
is the case that know basically showing
that how we can compute the xt uh from
the any given the initial point the xs
which means that once we basically have
some kind of the initial value at the
time s here then now we can comput the
xt by solving this and this is basically
only involving some kind of the
integration of the noise prediction
while basically simply basically waiting
this term into the some exponential
term. from here. So this is also kind of
the our the given function just like
waiting our noise prediction and just
taking the integral of the noise
prediction.
So the meaning of like this is that we
are basically deriving some kind of the
analytic formulation like solving the OD
in terms of that we only have like this
part. So this is basically the only part
uh that we still need to uh solve in a
kind of numerical way because like this
is involving the noise prediction is
basically neuronet prediction right. So
still there is some kind of the parts
that we need to uh liber some kind of
the numerical method in terms of
computing the integral but we are
simplifying the parts that we are
involving some kind of the numerical the
method in terms of only taking the
integral of like those part. So in terms
of that we can get some kind of the more
the accurate the computation for the
linear part and al only remaining this
like the nonlinear part in terms like
involving some uh the numerical method
and the idea in terms like somehow
involving some the numerical method for
this integration uh is quite simple. uh
what you can basically assume is that
it's basically nothing but just taking
the integral like this kind of noise
prediction uh with some kind of the way
here right
how can you basically do some kind of
the appro achieve some kind of
approximation for this
basically this is basically nothing but
you can think that this is taking the
integral of the the moves
now parameterized into the lambda but
basically it's like taking the integral
over time with some kind of the W from
here, right?
So basically the one way that we can
simply approximate this is that uh we
are basically assuming this noise
prediction function as kind of the
pie-wise linear. So some certain range
of the time we're going to assume that
uh this noise prediction becomes some
kind of a construct. So this is like
coming back to the uh what we have done
uh in the reverse the process sampling.
So what you have done in the first
assignment was basically define some
kind of the time interval right from the
zero to the capital T. You somehow
define the the time interval and
basically updating the XT over time,
right? Starting from the X capital T
going all the way to the X0 basically
updating the XT over time, right? And
what we are going to do is that we are
going to do kind of the same thing in
terms like dividing the time domain into
the multiple intervals. And what we
going to do is that we going to assume
that this ifs function is basically the
constant for each of the interval
make sense. So which means that uh when
you basically compute the the next
sample sorry this should be xt + one
typos here. So when you compute the xt
uh given from the xt + one, we are going
to assume that this noise term that we
are computing from the xt + one becomes
constant in the this interval
and with this simple basically the uh
the assumption the approximation. Now we
can compute this like the analytic
deformations
make sense. This is the case that we are
assuming that those interval is
basically the noise term is basically
the constant over the interval and the
only thing is that we just need to
compute uh this integral terms right
so this is like things uh so let's say
let's recall that how we define the
lambda function here right so based on
the our definition of like the lambda
function here uh can you compute this
can you rewrite this formulation into
the ID sigma that we have seen the
gradient decays.
This will be last quiz uh today.
Did you see this? So the exponential
term basically can be simplified into
this way
just like simple calculation right.
But based on this simple calculation,
what we can see is that kind of
surprisingly
uh if you plug in uh this uh deformation
here into this part here, then we come
back to this formulation.
Do you remember where we have seen this
before?
Uh if you don't remember, I recommend
you to check all the slides again. But
this is exactly the formulation of the
DTIM the deterministic sampling.
So we basically replace some kind of
terms with the alkind sigma function
that we are using in the boostations
right. So it turns out that what we can
see is that this is kind of the another
way uh that we can basically
interpret uh the DDI and the
deterministic sampling. So actually it
turns out that the DTI in the
deterministic sampling was the first
order the discretization of the OD
formulation but not just directly
discretizing the entirety of the OD
formulation but just like leveraging the
semi linear structure in terms of that
we are taking the exact the the solution
for the linear part we only basically uh
do some kind of the first approximation
for the nonlinear part which is the
noise prediction part right so we have
seen that what we are do doing for in
terms of the approximation here is that
uh we could do the first order
approximation for the entire OD
but what we are doing is that we only
take the approximation for this like
second part this part right in terms of
the p assuming some kind of the pie wise
linearity uh for this like noise
prediction right so by just taking only
the numeric the uh the computation for
the nonlinear part with the first order
approxim ation what we can see is that
actually the DDIM the reverse process
the deterministic process was turns out
to be the first order discretization of
the OD formulations based on the semi
linguistic structures
so that's kind of the interesting point
we can basically see the same basically
the generation process from the
different the the the perspectives we
can see that the same thing can be
interpreted as kind of the first order
kind of the approximation of the in the
continuous this time, right?
And the reason why we could achieve some
kind of the good results with DDM
sampling was that uh the basically uh
you know this is kind of the case that
we are analytically integrating the
linear part and only approximating the
nonlinear parts. So that's the basically
the reason that we can typically achieve
some kind of the quite high accuracy uh
with the few number of steps with the DD
sampling because uh it becomes like much
more accurate the approximations uh
compared to the the general case that we
are using the OD servers for the entire
OD formulations
and the good thing of like having this
interpretation of the DTI and the
sampling uh based on the continuous time
domain here is that as I said DDI AM is
basically approximating this simulation,
right? And we just like did some kind of
the first order approximation
and what if we do the second order
approximation and the third order the
approximation. So that would be kind of
the even better way in terms of like
achieving the higher accuracy.
Uh how about the uh the second order
approximation?
So roughly speaking uh the idea the very
basic idea in terms of achieving the
second order approximation is that uh
for the given the time domain the the
the time interval uh we are going to
split each of the the time interval and
basically first performing the first
appro order the approximation by
computing the middle point here.
Uh so now we are basically not computing
the next sample for the entire time
interval but just like half of the time
interval just computing the U here and
based on that we are basically uh do the
second time the update uh basically
updating the noise prediction with the
middle point and based on that we
compute the final uh the data point. So
that becomes some kind of the the basic
idea for the second order approximation
and can you also do the third order
approximation and the first order
approximation?
Yes, we can how we can do uh this kind
of the the things in the recursive rate,
right? So that's kind of the good thing
in terms of that we are having some kind
of the uh different perspectives of the
DDI and the sampling uh into the
continuous time domain which means that
uh also with some kind of even fewer
number of steps by just like
approximating those kind of trajectories
into the second order or the third order
uh for the same number of the steps uh
we can get some kind of even more the
accurate results.
So this is kind of a comparison like
DDPM is just here. So with some kind of
normal steps the FID is like very high
note kind of computation. So as I said
uh DDIM uh is kind of the same with the
DD in the solver one. So one basically
means the first order of the
approximation. So it goes down to here.
So with some kind of the pure number of
steps now we can quite like results. If
we basically go into the higher order
into the second order approximation or
the third order approximation then what
you can see is that even with the 15
steps
uh even with the steps so this kind of
dot line is basically here uh kind of
the accuracy we can achieve some with
some kind of the 1,000 steps with the
DDP and the D and the sampling even for
the 15 steps we can achieve some kind of
the same number of some kind of the
outputs uh the same accuracy here right
so that's kind of the power in terms of
basically understanding all those kind
of the diffusion the process in the
continuous time domain when you see
basically this the SD to the OD the
convergent and basically find some kind
of the better way to solve the OD
deformation uh even with some kind of
the few number of steps and as I keep
saying uh in this class this is quite
interesting the point in terms of that
this is like all done with the same
preun model you don't need to retrain
any kind of the new model using the same
trained model uh only at the inference
time by just changing the formulation uh
that you are performing the reverse
process with some kind of the better
understanding for the OD formulation
that we are solving by just introducing
some kind of better solver with the much
fewer number of steps we can even get
some kind of the uh get some kind of
better results like this so that's kind
of the some interesting aspect of the
diffusion models in terms of that the
different perspectives of the
understanding the vision models can
provide some kind of the better way to
achieve some kind of better results with
the fewer number of steps.
So this is kind of the very basic idea
in terms of basically introducing some
kind of the dedicated OD server for this
like PFOD deformationations and there
are many more in terms of like how we
can also introduce some kind of the uh
better OD servers for the same OD
formulations. So if you are more
interested into the more deeper things
more like mathematical kind of things I
recommend you to check this out check
out those kind of the papers.
Okay. Uh any questions?
So as I said like today's lecture was
kind of dense with some lots of
deformations. I strongly recommend you
to basically check out those
formulations not just like understanding
line by line but just you know more
about like understanding how those
things are basically connect to each
other quite important things in terms of
like The same thing model.