hello everyone I'm really really glad to
be here be able to share a little bit
more about our work and I would of
course like to organize the the
organizers uh for inviting me to be part
of this class um all right so you know
three and a half years ago I had just
finished uh two big projects one of them
was ala code the other one was ala
tensor I'll tell you a little bit more
about those in the future but basically
during the Christmas holidays in
2021 um I stbl on this talk from 2019
called the future of mathematics and uh
the talk is over an hour but the
comments were extremely positive uh one
person was saying you know this is the
best lecture and the best YouTube video
ever I've never watched anything more
enjoyable so you know I was pretty
intrigued and I pressed play and um it
started a chain of in electable events
that basically takes me here in front of
you today um so in this talk uh rather
than focusing on the details I'd really
like to focus on the Big Ideas uh that
allowed us to work on Alpha proof and
why we believe it has an integral role
to play in the future of mathematics so
basically talk first about the rise of
formal mathematics and what that is uh
then about our experience in
reinforcement learning uh and the
lessons we've took away um and how these
two things meet with alha
proof so Galileo said quite a long time
ago that the laws of nature are written
in the language of mathematics uh it was
incredible prediction or Insight because
uh We've made a lot of progress since
Galileo and indeed now just a few
equations on a single page can describe
how the universe works extremely
precisely um also in a famous essay
called the unreasonable effectiveness of
mathematics Eugen vickner argues that
you know mathematics not only have like
a descriptive power they also have
predictive power um one example he gives
if I'm not mistaken um is the
development of Matrix multi Matrix
algebra and it's used in quantum
mechanics of course once you can
describe and predict the natural world
you can start to shape it and um if you
look around us you know in the world we
live in the civilization the culture all
the tech you know that makes our current
world well basically mathematics is just
at the core of everything um and maybe I
would also like to argue that
mathematics is a root to intelligence
the root node is is a word that de
really likes to to to talk about um and
uh basically you know it means that from
from that road is going to Blossom a
whole tree of of possibilities um and
and why could we argue that is because
you know mathematics use requires
reasoning and planning generalization
and abstraction knowledge and creativity
open-ended and unbounded complexity and
over the years I also understood that
mathematics is not just this kind of um
application of logical rules one after
the other it it's really a sort of of a
of Art and so it even requires a KN of
beauty and so I used a lot of keywords
here and that you'll see them
reappearing uh during my talk and I hope
that will make these a bit more concrete
um in summary um I try to uh convey to
you that you know mathematics is a a
root note to understand the natural
world but it also might be a root not
for
intelligence um so I think it's worth
kind of really thinking about
mathematics and see what can we do for
that but before that I'd like to give
you a really super brief history of
formalization in mathematics because
basically mathematics hasn't always
looked the way it looks now um about 500
you know before Christ you know the the
Greeks uh had a great Revelation they
understood the the importance of the
concept of mathematical proof and some
sense can you can you really imagine you
know it's like you find something that
will tell you with certainty that you
have attained kind of Eternal truth and
you can discover more and more truth of
our universe it must have felt
incredible um and and since then you
know PR proofs is at the heart of
mathematics and what constitutes the
proof however has evolved over the
millenniums of mathematical history uh
one of the first breakthroughs I'm sure
that you know uh is with ukl and his
book elements that have definitions and
theorems so that's really kind of the
start of
axiomatization but has really kind
of been developed much more in the early
20th century with Hilbert program uh
that really developed this to land on on
what we have
now so that's kind of atiz on one side
on the other side you know like
mathematics um you know at the beginning
he didn't really use symbols and that
for for a very long time you know even
if the Greeks had can find a ization and
started to use some symbols the rest of
the world kind of describe really
mathematics with with a lot of words um
and so here you have like a square and
10 times its root I equal to 39 so today
we would write this as x s + 10 x = 39
but look at this description of of how
do you solve this thing take the
coefficient of the root divide it into
two parts and multiply one of them by
itself at this 239 etc etc right now you
just write kind of this concise kind of
formula and U and there are two things
here uh that comes you know is first you
know replacing kind of you know using
special I don't in the machine learning
lingo using special tokens uh for for
for numbers right like we represent like
the digits have special special kind of
characters uh but also even more
important well I don't know which one is
more important but that helps with also
kind of I think only in the 17th century
um run deart kind of comes up with the
idea of um using kind of the early of
the alphabets to den note constants and
the end of the letter of the alphabets
XYZ to describe
unknowns and so that's basically how you
you end up with this formula but it
takes you know like I don't know how
many it takes until the 17th century to
really come up with those
notations um and I think it's not hard
to arue that uh precise notation and
atiz really eliminated ambiguities and
logical error that symbolic notation
made complex manipulations more
and requires much less you know
cognitive Lo it also kind of packs
information extremely
densely in terms of notation I can't
remember exactly who said that and if it
was a joke or not but someone was
arguing that maybe the Einstein
notations was his biggest contribution
then might be pushing it a little bit
with given like the impact of general
relativity special relativity and even
his work to introduce quantum mechanics
uh but but certainly kind of um Einstein
notations uh are very important actually
if you read machine learning code you'll
see that appearing a lot as well um but
basically once you you have those
symbols and you can lift yourself uh up
from kind of particular examples you you
start to be able to observe different
common patterns across different context
and so that's where abstraction and
generalization comes up you can unify
disparate areas of mathematics um and
actually you can even create new field
and so my my favorite example here is
really the people who are looking at the
five axioms of ukian geometry and and
and actually I don't know for thousand
of year I think trying to see if they
could remove the fif axium um and and
that actually led to nonan Geometry um
and in particular reman geometry which
you know in in this in the theme of
General reactivity was was essential to
get General
reactivity so um you know this this
formalization uh has helped mathematics
but also the other Sciences in
particular physics and so I would like
to argue that basically computer
formalization which basically means
writing mathematics in code is just the
next logical phase in this gr Arc of
mathematical
formalism so there's been quite a few
languages to describe mathematical
reasoning such as Co and Isabelle and
Lan is one of the most recent ones
originally develop I believe for
software vcation but also with
mathematics in mind uh and and
mathematicians so in lean kind of the
tool that would make the next big step
in in mathematical formal formalism it's
a it's a programming language it's a
theor improver and interactive proof
assistant lean has a really vibrant open
source community of mathematicians it's
been used to formalize like Cutting Edge
mathematics fi metal mathematics and and
the mathematicians are on a huge quest
uh to basically build the math library
of the the future so let me let me go
there uh it's called math Li it's built
open source on basically the free time
of mathematicians and it has um it has
two big goals it aims to be General and
unified so General it means that you
know it has the weakest assumptions and
the strongest results and unified is
that it only has one definition per
concept so I was actually pretty
surprised when I I learned about this
unification idea uh because you know I
thought that mathematics um was written
in a very you know structured way
already but apparently it turns out that
you know like for a given concept you
may have several papers that basically
talk about the same concept but that
Define it in a different way that is not
necessarily compatible with each other
and so you need to do quite a bit of
work to actually kind of try to find the
unifying definition that underlies all
those ideas and so that's actually what
takes the most time in uh in building
Master
um maybe you can see you know in the
representation I gave here that it's one
mon monolithic Library where everything
is connected together and so this is
very important for modern Mass because
basically modern mass is about kind of
trying to connect all areas of mass and
there's been observations that actually
you know like ideas from here can help
ideas from from there and and and for
instance maybe FAS Last Theorem proof is
is a is a great example of this
connecting two different areas to to try
to prove
one huge theem now there is also
something called The Lang length program
that really explicitly tries to do that
and connect all these areas so it's
really important that you have a library
that basically can connect all different
areas of mass uh currently the the
library covers covers about 80% of the
undergrad curriculum uh and most of the
library however is above the
undergraduate but has a lot of you know
or irregular coverage and big I think
particular examples are comp analysis or
PD
Theory okay all great but why do all of
this right um is because U you know
computer formalization unlocks kind know
enormous synergies and maybe to explain
myself a little bit I have to step back
um and and for those of you who are who
are coders maybe you know like just
understanding the right code and be able
to use all the software stack that
should be already a huge win for
mathematics uh but basically the other
property of when you write mathematics
in code with those languages such as
lean is that you get perfect
verification so when you write a proof
uh and you write the correct proof Lin
is going to tell you yes this is correct
and when you've made a mistake L is
going to tell you this is your proof is
not is not correct or is still
incomplete uh so from these two things
uh you get some instant wins first you
know your correctness concerns
completely disappear uh you can trust
giant proofs and you can delegate uh
proof checking entirely to the
computer um and so I think it's
important to note and it's my
understanding that it's not like all
areas of mathematics are suffering from
concerns about correctness I think in
reality most maybe areas where the
mathematicians feel pretty comfortable
about their ability to discern uh you
know correctness from from from mistakes
uh but I've been hearing that in maybe
some of the areas that are more abstract
areas actually they start to be real
concerns for correctness so that's not
everywhere but that starts to be
important um so these are the instant
wins um but those you know those you
know perfect verification and software
stack has really kind of a knock on
effect that could lead to gain
Changers um so first you know I think
for all of you who are coders to bring
all the tools that we have developed for
coding um should already be a big big
win uh next um I have transform method
itics into a video game so what does
this video game look like well you have
what are the levels the levels are the
different theorems um and then you know
you can interact uh in those levels and
basically kind of Lan will tell you yes
you've completed the level or not with
with this pass verification uh feedback
you always have harder level and maybe
contrary to you know other games where
may I don't know you have to shoot other
people this is a super meaningful useful
and and profound game you know you're
basically adding new truths for eternity
and the the the lean people describe
this as as you know they could do this
14 hours a day and they're constantly
getting positive
reinforcements um this this also means
that you know it's it's great for
Education First you know like a lot
younger people now are really used to
using computers and softwares and it's
great because it's interactive right uh
it's when it's fun it's easy to learn
and you can you can also create of
software such that uh you know like the
the detail of the level of detail is
adapted to the person who is reading
rather than um you know the the the the
level that the author thought was
interesting I don't know if you read a
lot of mpers of you look at Solutions of
some problems you are trying to solve
sometimes people this well this this
next step is is is quite obvious uh but
maybe it is not for you and you you
would love to see uh more detail uh I
have an example uh from actually from my
dad who recently tried to learn kind of
galwa theory in in a different online
class and so he went through week one
and week two and week three all good but
then when he was going through week four
and trying to do the homework he
realized that there was something he you
know he he didn't understand and and he
basically U needed someone to explain to
him and he he messaged the professor but
unfortunately the professor didn't reply
and so he was basically completely stuck
uh but imagine that instead you know was
doing this in lean then lean would have
said exactly you know what is right what
is wrong what is missing Etc and he
would be able to have like constant
feedback without having to ask his
teacher um and now I want to go to uh
the the last point it's actually a point
that has been made by ter to I think
about um a year and a half ago at least
um and and and he describes that
basically using computer form ation will
unlock massive collaboration between
mathematicians and so why does he say
that well apparently the the current
state of mathematic kind of
collaboration is that um you can do uh
you know most of the papers are either
single author or two author paper and
kind of the max is really five author
papers uh and the reason why is because
uh every author needs to check everyone
else's work um and so basically kind of
having more and more uh collaboration
collaborators doesn't really scale
because you still need to check everyone
else's work and so that's where like
computerization and per verification
comes in is that um if you could trust
the computer to check the proofs then
suddenly uh you can it opens up kind of
working on in mathematical projects to I
don't know thousands of people because
you could have someone you've never met
who lived in the middle of nowhere who
contributes a little bit your proof L
there and then lean will say yes this is
correct and then you can just move on
right and so there's been um there's
been kind of maybe you know there's been
a few projects like this I think mass
liby is maybe one of the of the cooler
demonstration where you have hundreds of
mathematicians working together to build
this library of the future but I think
terto is also arguing that you could use
that to do new mathematics and has
actually launched a project in the past
called universal algebra where where he
was um exploring that but basically you
know like I think in ml at the moment we
are all about skaing and here basically
you could scale humans to do ma
mathematics and potentially maybe tackle
the harder
problems all right um so you know should
everyone go to you know computer
formalization it's awesome the reality
is that there are still challenges for
computer formalization in my estimates
about only 0.1% to 1% of mathematicians
have adopted Le it's a small community
of mathematicians vibrant one uh but but
why is that is because it's actually not
yet a great tool for mainstream research
like a lot of you know um programming
languages it has a steep learning curve
it also requires a significant time
investment because you know to get
perfect verification you need to be able
to write every single
detail um and so you know that takes a
lot more time maybe that's not the the
place where you want to focus want to
focus on the things you you don't yet
know how to S not on the things that are
are more obvious to you um and so that
will be that will be improved at you
know the the tooling and the and the
library mates um but at the moment there
there's still some some things missing
and obviously you know there is also a
passive lack of necessity for research
but I'm hoping that you know the
arguments I've outlined in the in the
slide before are going to change a
little bit uh with that point so now I
just want to show you a little bit what
it looks like um so you know this is uh
a proof that you may have you may know
about um it's called uh it's about how
many it's about proving that there's an
infinite number of primes um and U okay
so this is what it looks like in lean I
hope you can see that it's it's big
enough and so
uhop okay here it is this is the theorem
statement and I think uh what is kind of
remarkable is that uh because you can
use unic
this looks pretty much what you would
write yourself on a piece of paper says
that for all n natural numbers there is
exist a p that P is bigger than n and p
is prime so that's how one way to say
that there is an infinite number of
primes this is what the proof look like
so fairly compact in this case uh and
and the fact that you can understand all
of this is because basically lean is a
language based high level syntax and a
mirroring normal mathematics
um so let me go a little bit on on on
what it looks like to interact with this
so here is the first line of the proof
and this is actually the the main
Insight that ukl had is to consider
first n factorial plus one and the mean
fact of it so what is the mean fact is
the mean factor of n factorial plus one
so I want to draw your attention on the
on the Box on the right there called the
tactic State and so basically that's
what lean returns to you it says or here
are the things we know and here are the
things we still need to prove so we know
that N is a natural number we know that
P is this mean factor of n factorial
plus one and you still need to show that
exist a p such that P is bigger than n
and p is
prime so let's go second line Second
Line says oh let's prove that n
factorial plus one is not one and you
have actually the the proof in line with
maybe a few more characters and you
really want to prove something uh this
easy uh but on the right you see that
you have a new fact uh in your in your
you know in your in Your Arsenal uh is
that n factorial plus one is not
one and then we are going to say now
let's prove that P is prime um and and
the proof is say well is because it's
basically we took the the minimum Factor
right the minimum factor is is is kind
of is obvious that it's a prime unless
unless you know the the thing you've
taken up is one and so that's why you
have this this thing you need needed to
prove before and then kind of the proof
continues um and at the end you should
see in your tactic State no
goals and uh it used to be I think in
the previous version of Lan that You'
also received kind of this T
emo and I think unfortunately it's been
removed from the current version of of
Lan um but but basically you know it's
your little reward for completing this
this level um so just to recap right
computer formalization um there is
there's a really Vibrant Community that
have a huge enthusiasm for this they are
building the library of the future in
their own time uh it has uh many many
ways in which you know it can unlocks
enormous synergies but it still has some
way to go um and this community and
myself as well um we have the belief
that this will inevitably play an
integral role in the future of
mathematics you know just just this work
kind of pushed the computer
formalization all right so now I want to
talk about some concurrent development
in Ai and focus on something that was
extremely popular a few years ago got
forgotten a bit in the last couple of
years and and now they is making a
comeback big time so hopefully you know
like you you've picked up all my hints
with this little reward uh this
environment this interactiveness this
video game um I want to talk about about
reinforcement
learning um
so what's reinforcement learning also
known as RL uh basically it's just trial
and error learning it's a very very
general framework of an agent trying to
achieve a goal so really this agent
learns by interacting with an
environment to maximize a reward and I
think there is sometimes um
misconception about this reward it has
to be very dense or you know it has to
guide you towards the solution Etc uh
not at all in the you know in the
framework of RL uh the reward can be
basically have I achieved my goal or not
um so basically in R we really need to
have a goal but then your reward can be
goal achieved equal than one otherwise
zero all the
time if you don't really have a goal
that you want to try to achieve then
maybe that doesn't fit very well into
the the AR framework but if you have a
goal then you know um super super
framework to work with uh especially
since you know um it has actually been
proven to work uh really really well so
here is a sample of the most successful
stories coming out of Deep Mind uh when
ARL was basically run at scale um so as
you can see there are a lot of examples
of of games and video games so for
instance you know the seminal work on on
Atari to work on go and Starcraft and
stro but as I said you know RL is is not
confined to games it's about trying to
achieve a goal and so here like on the
on the bottom row there's Alpha death a
tensor which were used to discover new
algorithms and the bottom on the right
is is basically RL was used to try to
control in a toac the shape of the
plasma to get better nuclear fusion
reactions so you can see you know it is
a very general
setup uh now um you know I had myself
the luck to spend my days on alpago and
and its descendants and and this is what
I call the zero series um and especially
from you know AFA gozero um we show that
we could train an agent to master
domains and and when I say master I
actually mean you know being the world
champion hands down at the time when
those things came out um uh and we learn
to do that without any human input
information we basically learned
everything from
scratch um and so I want to talk to you
about the zero philosophy which um I
think is a is a great Philosophy for
research um it's about this so if an
agent can learn to master an environment
tabular without any information
basically you've demonstr shown that you
have a system that is able to discover
and learn new knowledge by itself um
it's also means that you know this
algorithm is is general and should apply
to other domains
um and I think you know like the the
ability of being able to discover new
knowledge um this is particularly
important to Advanced science because a
big part of doing science is to just
explore areas that are not yet well
understood and advanc knowledge and you
need to accumulate knowledge
continuously generate and discover new
interesting truth and and you know
that's a huge part of doing science um
so you know like especially for research
I think this is like a great way to
demonstrate uh that you can discover new
things um I would say that especially
now with the big success of llms you
know maybe a more pragmatic point of you
is to be able to start at a you know at
a certain um knowledge base and then you
want to know that your algorithm is
going to continue to discover new things
from there so you don't really need to
start from zero what you really need is
is to have this algorithm that can
discover new things and we've
demonstrated that you can do this uh
with um with those with this research
and these Al Zer things so let me go
into some kind of examples Al go zero
and Al zero as I said you know they
learn simply by playing against
themselves starting completely from
random play and what we observed is that
um they basically rediscovered human
patterns accumulating thousands of years
of human knowledge maybe in a matter of
days but ultimately some of those
patterns were kind of discarded in
preference of new discoveries that
humans don't even know about they don't
even knew about
so in go I believe that you know AF go
basically starting a new move at move I
would say move five um a move that
wasn't even played by humans and I've
heard if I'm not mistaken that Magnus
Carlson was saying that because his
coach was really good at using engines
and he got to use half a like engines
when those came out he he got a big
Advantage momentarily over the other
chess players because basically things
was playing very differently and and and
and people were not used to it and they
didn't know how to handle those new
situations that's kind of go and uh and
chess and actually if you look at for
instance the figure I showed on the
bottom right uh this is kind of uh this
is trying to show the frequency of alpha
zero playing that particular pattern
called the for instance the caran
defense you can see that you know it
basically discovers it after two hours
of training it plays it for about four
hours quite consistently and then you
know this kind of pattern starts to
disappear from the games azero is
playing probably because has found kind
of a way that that makes this this
pattern not very interesting anymore uh
while uh on the bottom the Queen's
Gambit seems you know the frequency at
which the queen gamb is played uh is is
just increasing over time over training
time all right uh now let me talk about
Alpha tenser um and so this was a work
that was trying to find what is the best
best way to multiply two matrices
together and so maybe the the naive
algorithm that you may have learned at
school requires kind of n Cube
operations when you're trying to
multiply two n byn matrices so for 2 by
two matrices you need eight
multiplications for four
by4 multiplications you need 64
multiplications ET Etc um so there was
at some point a big Discovery from a
person named stren that found that for 2
by two matrices actually you could do it
with only seven multiplications and he
also showed that this was this was
optimal you couldn't do better than that
but as soon as we went to 4x4 kind of
matrices um basically we we we knew
nothing more than applying St algorithm
twice and so you know your still reduces
from 64 to 49
multiplications and so in a tensor um we
try to discover a new efficient and
provably correct algorithm for basically
tasks that look like Matrix
multiplication um and and and and you
know it actually did um it found new
things uh in in actually many different
uh SES discovering like brand new
knowledge that that human never known
about um and so you know if you had only
trained on what human had known then you
would have never discovered those uh as
a big bonus as part of this work we show
that basically you know we could
basically a zero could tackle huge
action spaces uh so so I wrote here 10
to the^ 30 but basically for practical
purposes uh this is um this is just
infinite and so all those successes you
know go chest tensor decomposition uh
are all specific to a certain task if
you write a certain level but under the
hood is basically the same F zero
algorithm that is running and making
those discoveries and so what we had in
mind is like is there an environment
that captures a much broader class of
tasks that are relevant for science um
and guess it our answer is yes it's it's
mathematics U but just before we get
there the lessons we've learned from
from those uh from all this world so
what made those systems super
human I've I've listed up what I believe
are the four most important properties
first is to scale up trial and error um
and basically to discover new knowledge
you need to try something new and be
able to learn based on the feedback you
receive um and if your feedback is not
grounded you know if you vent your own
feedback um then it's really I think
it's really hard once you venture out of
what's known and so you really need a
way to measure if you're achieving your
goals or not where you are in the what
where are you in your solution etc
etc um also alazo uses a lot of search
and and I believe it's my belief that
search can really accelerate the
discovery of new PA and skills um and
it's because most of the time when you
sample you know a different action not
the you know not the action that is uh
that has the the highest probability if
you try that action most of the time
it's going to be bad uh but sometimes
it's going to be good and and you need
to discover why that action might be
good or not and so you need to follow up
on kind of playing well after you play
that action um and I think you know for
instance uh AO and move 37 is a good
example of that um it had a very low
probability of being paid but it was
still exploding in the search and then
it was discovered that I was a really
good moved um and so it became uh you
know it was played and it was um
described as being very
creative uh the final one is you need to
have a good curriculum to take you all
the way to Super and in the alpha zero
case in go and chess and shogi we relied
on the fact that you it was a two-player
game and so you could do self play you
basically always have the right opponent
to play against and that was really
important
okay so now let me try to connect those
two um scale Tri we have uh you know
lean is the environment to explore
mathematics completely in silico and the
algorithm is going to come from F zero
again Lin is going to give you us kind
of this grounded feedback signal it's
going to tell us you know what have we
proved so far what's left to be proved
um and it's going to tell us when we
when we are done uh when we get a
correct proof uh for such we can rely on
on Alpha Z's uh search algorithm it
works pretty well and maybe kind of the
question mark is what do we do with the
curriculum um in some sense you know
where are the levels coming from uh but
so You' understood kind of the idea of
alpha proof is to use Alpha zero for
mathematics um and in particular foral
mathematics so you know let me make kind
of a napkin kind of Master Plan uh for
Alpha proof uh so lean gives us a way to
scale up trial and error with an
environment to explore mathematics
completely in cico and a perfect
feedback signal for proving and then now
if we extrapolate from the work we've
done in the other domains um I conclude
we can therefore reach superhuman
intelligence and discover new truth just
like in goess tensor de composition
provided we can generate high enough
quality and quantity of problems and RL
Works um some very bullish on RN works
and so as I said the kind of the
question that remains is um how can we
generate high enough quality and
quantity of problems where do the
problems come
from um and so I think one of the answer
has to be that you know the problems
partly comes from the humans uh and
maybe the most important reason why is
that is because we want to help human
mathematics
um we could try to create alien
mathematics um but uh really what we
would like is to help human mathematics
and kind of contribute in that in that
community and and maybe a more pragmatic
reason is that humans have already come
up with a lot of of problems that are
quite
interesting uh but of course we
shouldn't throw away the second part
where halfa proof could Define the
problem um and so I think there is maybe
two ways to fly this uh one is um Al
proof defines a problem around human
mathematics and we've done a little bit
of that already with Auto at the so it's
perfectly fine if you don't understand
what I mean here I'll I'll try to
explain those a bit
later but the other part is basically
really augmenting human mathematics so
you know ideally Alpha proof would be
able to discover new areas of
mathematics build new theories Etc that
humans find interesting
um yes so these are maybe where the
problems can come from so uh before we
move on I want to take a step back uh
because if we're thinking about AI for
mathematics um you know there is
potentially a choice uh there is a
choice of doing it in natural language
or in formal language so I've been
arguing a long time now for the the
formal part but but you know uh actually
most effort in AI at the moment is on
informal mathematics or doing basically
mathematics in natural language and um
and the reason why is because basically
all of the data of mathematics you know
the by many ERS of magnitude is uh is
written in natural language of course so
you have this math lib library that is
growing contains quite a lot of mass but
it's still a few orders of magnitude
smaller than the the amount of
mathematics you can find uh in textbooks
in on archive on published papers Etc
that are all written using natural
language um so that's kind of the
trade-off you get when you use formal
mathematics is you you really have a
very small amount of data that's when
again you know you you bum into the
question of how do you get the problems
where the problems come from um however
I guess um it's my opinion that uh the
you know the the because natural
language mathematics at least the
reasoning part is not
verifiable um I believe that this is an
issue if you're read your goal is to
build a system that can go beyond human
knowledge and create new knowledge um
you can of course you know improve the
reliability of of those systems
uh but the problem in mathematics is is
really that any if you build on on any
false statement then um then you know it
destroys everything you do afterwards
you need you really need like a 100%
reliability um that's a property of
mathematics um and and that's why I
think that you know verifiability is is
very important and basically lean is
already super human at
verification um and I I say all of this
for mathematics but actually I believe
this is true for many important
impactful applications that that we
cannot solve yet um and scientific
problem problems in particular so the
you know in the domains we cannot solve
uh There is almost by constructure there
isn't much data available because the
domain is relatively poorly understood
um and maybe you know it could even be a
completely new domain that has just been
discovered um you could also have
application that are somewhere Niche and
maybe if you think about uh what AGI
would do you could argue that maybe
mathematics is a bit Niche but it's
still extremely impactful and it's
conceivable that you know generalization
from all the other data uh would be
somewhat limiting and so if we at data
scarce we already need a process that
can continuously generate and discover
new interesting facts that are not yet
represented in the data and you need a
way to ground those new facts so that
you can you can check that you are
basically constantly adding neutral and
building on top of of neutral and so
this is really a foundational bet is
that perfect verification will in the
long run be the most important property
for
mathemetics let me recap RL meets formal
Mass so we have a proven recipe to build
agent that can discover new knowledge by
themselves and reach super human
intelligence in certain domains uh the
key ingredients have have highlighted
are scand of Tri and error and gred
feedback and basically formal Mass
provid us with those key ingredients uh
so that's these are the big
ideas that U you know behind that appr
so now um let me talk to you a little
bit about the IMO and um our
participation in
2024 um so first what's what's the IMO
the IMO stands for the international
mathematics Olympia it's basically the
world championship level event in
mathematics that brings together the
best young minds from around the world
um so every country brings that top six
high school students and they try to
solve six problems in two sessions of
four and a half hours so basically in
total they have like nine hours to solve
six problems um in these six problems
there are two easy problems two medium
problems and two hard problems uh so let
me first try to illustrate what it what
it means to take the top six high school
students for for the USA so let's say
there is about 17 million high school
students um it's not like kind of every
kid uh loves mass and and is going to do
a mass competition uh they might instead
play video games and maybe in the future
uh actually build the math library of
the future but anyways at the moment
there's about 60,000 of them that
participate in the in these AMC
competitions if they do well and they
are still kind of into into this they
might go and and participate in this aim
competition um and so for those of you
who have been following kind of the
benchmarks that used in AI um you you
may know about this Mass Benchmark that
basically contains a lot of AMC and aim
problems um and so the reason why is
that basically Aime what you need to do
in the Aime is to uh you know the
solution is always an integ between one
and a thousand and so you know it makes
it easy to check whether kind of your
your system has outputed the correct
answer or not like the correct number uh
you can check that very easily and kind
of use that as a as a grounded feedback
the problem is it doesn't tell you
whether your reasoning to get there is
correct or not now you know like if you
need to guess
177 um then I think you know like kind a
I still believe that it's indeed it's
more likely that you have correct
reasoning uh when you come up with the
right answer and so you know that might
still help to improve the reason and
basically what's happening is improving
the reasoning of those of those models
but anyway when you do really well at
the you may participate in the USA Mass
o impant um it's only 250 now um then if
you are in the top there you may go to
the IMO Camp uh and from there only the
top six people are selected you can see
there is like basically six or seven
orders of of of of selection um and I'm
told by my colleague who did the IMO
from for for the UK that um you know
they study for thousand of hours maybe
an average of three hours for three
years so really intense training for
this for this
competition now let me let me share a
little bit about the
problems uh and I'll start with this
quote from poran law the poran law is
not anyone is not new to the IMO he was
actually the coach the national coach
for USA for the last 10 years and uh he
said I tried this problems while at the
IMO it took me hours um and context
about the Imo problems are specifically
selected to be non-standard so during
the IMO itself National coaches meet to
pick the problems to appear on the exam
one of the most important task of that
group um is to avoid problems similar to
problems that appear anywhere before and
so they go through a great length sh
this um and so that's why basically we
really wanted to you know we we pick the
IMO as as a goal for us is because we
thought there was really a test of
reasoning and and and not of knowledge
um and and you know as pan law says even
for Specialists even for the national
coach of the USA has been doing this for
10 years it will take him hours to solve
those problems um the the final property
of participating at the 2024 I know
whether those Pro those problems were
not leaked right and so
um you really needed to kind of be able
to reason to solve those problems um as
I said you know there are like easy
medium and hard problems uh easy is uh
you know in fact those problems are not
easy at all because um only half of the
participants uh solve two or more
problems um and so you know like you
take the top six from each country and
and half of those won't be able to solve
the easy
problem all right so now let's go really
to you know this IMO 2024 and um I'd
like to relieve a part of it with you so
you know we had contacted the Theo
organization um we had um we had agreed
with them that they would send us the
problems we had contacted some judges
also part of that competition uh so they
could grade our Solutions um and
um and we try to participate so I just
want to make sure you know like kind of
I um I clarify exactly what our IMO
participation was and I think a good way
to think about it is more like an Apollo
program and so what we really wanted to
know is can we actually reach the moon
can our solve system solve the 2024 IMO
problem at all um you know given the
computer that Google can give us at that
time and um and enough time for doing
reasoning um so it was really about this
like can we you know can we build a
system that can solve uh those problems
at all and I think at the time where we
got started um it was believed that you
know this was like five or 10 years away
um okay so now let me take you to you
know seven months before January 2024 so
we are seven months away and we need to
make a decision about geometry so why
geometry is because you know math Li is
very sparse in Tod ukian geometry
doesn't have much of what you need to
know about ukan geometry mostly because
you know researchers don't really care
about 2D ukan geometry that is useful
for Theo and so um we're a bit unsure
what to do uh we are debating whether
maybe you know we actually don't do
geometry at all or we we try to fill in
that part in M Li so that our agent has
the basic knowledge that is expected
every students to have um and so we are
debating this when uh you know
miraculously another group within Google
Deep Mind turned out to have been
working exactly the IMO geometry problem
and they already have a system that is
very very strong you know their system
was already approaching gold level uh
metal performance on the geometry
problems and we learn about that because
they publish a paper in nature in in
early January 2024 so Miracle but we
decide to join forces with them for July
and so a geometry will tackle geometry
and a proof will tackle algebra number
Theory and
cetric a couple of months later we're
debating another thing so we've been
training out a proof on proving theorems
but not all questions are on the form
prove that
um actually some require an answer to be
determined like find or X sear that you
know and this is not just a you know an
integer like the it could be you know
it's the set of you know like these
numbers that have this property Etc um
and so this actually not obvious how to
do well in formal language because you
have like this kind of topological case
where you know he says well what are all
the ex that property phols it says where
the is the set of numbers where P holds
and you have like a really easy time to
prove that but that's definitely not
what kind of the the judges were were
after um and so actually you know the
answer itself is is is a bit of a
subjective thing uh and and we debate
you know what we should do either we we
do what you know was known outside as
the easy mode um we basically feed in
the correct answer to the to Al a proof
and we ask Al a proof to prove it or we
go is hard mode where we try to
determine the answer we have something
that determines the answer and we prove
it um I personally don't really like
easy and hard kind of keywords here
because um you know it's um it's fairly
well known that kind of the the bit that
is the hardest for the IMO is the is the
proving part is not really to guess the
answer um but uh but anyway so we are
debating we we we're not sure exactly
what to do but you know after thinking
about it through it's pretty clear that
we need to do hard mode um and and
what's cool is that actually kind of
guessing the answer is exactly what kind
of Gemini is been trained on and so we
decide that we will generate candidates
and ser with Gemini and we'll attempt to
prove and disprove all possible
candidates without appr so that's how we
going to participate now the final thing
we are debating about is about kind of
the the input that the the system should
receive so they receive the natural
language description of problem you know
for instance in English actually you
know if you participate at the IMO you
can choose the language in which you
receive the problems you know you not
everyone has to read it in English you
can have it in Russian or in Chinese or
in Japanese you can you can choose your
own language unfortunately you know they
they don't propose lean as a language um
and so uh we're debating whether you
know we will send kind of English to the
system or uh or we'll ask our our
experts internally to manually formalize
the problem
and and send that as an input to the to
the
system and so we debate this a little
bit with our judges and and you know
very quickly we we we have the same
opinion because what we really care
about is you know the mathematical
reasoning and and problem solving a Dio
right that's what that's what we are
therefore not really about our
capabilities of actually uh translating
the problem in in in formal
language and so we decide that it's okay
for what we want to achieve that we will
give the formalized problems as input um
and so we ask our L experts to manual
formalize the problems for the system so
if I recap you know uh our protocol is
going to look something like this so we
are going to officially receive the
problems at 1M um the lean experts will
first manually formalize the problems uh
and then that's where kind of the after
that the AI comes in so um we'll
generate hundreds of an candidates with
Gemini a proof will try to e filter all
the easily disprovable ones and then we
are going to run test time around again
I haven't told you what is the Sam but
I'm going to get there um okay day one
we are there um Tuesday at 1M we receive
the problem uh P1 is an algebra P2 is a
number Theory and P3 is a Comin Atri and
P1 P2 actually requires an aners to be
guessed um and so you know we ask our
experts to manually formalize the
problem then Gemini to guess and dat and
then we get half proof to try to
disprove all those answer candidates um
and so um we have already very good uh
signs is that ala proof is able to
disprove 99% basically of guesses for
those two problems in a matter of
minutes and so this is a really good
sign because we've observed in the past
that when alha proof understands the
problem is going to be able to disprove
a lot of kind of f Banks but for
problems it doesn't understand at all it
wouldn't be able to disprove much at all
um so that's really good sign for for
day one on day two right we receive
again at 1M the problems we knew
actually that P4 np5 had to be geometry
and combinatorics because there is a
rule that the easy and medium problems
you know all categories have to appear
in easy and medium problems um and but
we are pretty happy to see that P6 was
algebra functional equation uh because
we knew that also ala proof uh was
particularly strong in functional
equation problems that's said P6 is is
in the hard category um and you know
it's the hardest problem so even if it's
you know kind of a good category for for
for Alpha proof uh nothing is nothing is
guaranteed at all um turns out that you
know alha geometry is able to solve the
geometry problem I believe in seconds um
so really really powerful
uh it get there so basically you know
they they came in they run that thing
for for a few seconds and and then it
was done for them the P5 comatrix was
actually very tricky and our our human
experts failed to formalize that problem
on the
day and the P6 algebra you know it also
requires answers to be determined and
gini generated a bunch of answers um and
when we AF tried to disprove it it could
only disprove 7% of gases um so so it
doesn't have zero traction on the
problem but it doesn't have probably as
good an understanding as on P1 and
P2 um all right so you know day three
Thursday um Al proof hasn't proved
anything yet but we had a way to track
progress um and so we observe on the day
one problems that P1 you know Al proof
have actually solved half of the problem
um and so actually in that proof um
there are at least you know two ways to
split that problem into you you know
case on the fact that something is
either either even or odd or that it's
rational or irrational and so a proof
had kind of you know come up with these
ideas of of of splitting this problem in
two by itself and for instance in the
even OD case you had proved the even
case um and hadn't finished proving the
OD case uh it wasn't able to prove the
OD case yet uh in P2 when we look at it
uh a proof had arguably solved the whole
problem so I don't know if you know but
in the IMO there is you know there is a
whole section where after the
competition is you know after the
students have submitted their answers
then the team captains can argue with
the with the the judging committee that
actually you know like this student has
done this much and so therefore they
deserve that much points um and so you
know if we had followed that process we
believe that with whatever a proof had
we may may be able to argue for the
whole problem so let's say you know six
out of seven points there um and then on
P3 uh the comatrix problem a pro had
hadn't made any
progress uh on the day two problem as I
said you know a geometry had already
solved uh in seconds the problem so
seven out of seven points the P5
combinatoric um we had made no progress
I think by that time we had a
formalization of it uh but what was
really cool is that actually
on P6 a proof had made progress and had
proved a particular case that we now
know is wor to out of seven points um so
probably on sday it had actually made
quite a bit of progress on on all the
problems and we may have already have
like about 18
points now Friday uh we received this
email um you know this there is my the
name of my colleague Rishi but actually
sent by Ala proof uh and a proof is
sending an email each time it solves one
of the IMO problems it says I have
discovered a truly marvelous proof of
IMO 2024 P6 but this email is too short
to contain um of course it's a joke and
the whole proof is there in the email
and so when we see that we are extremely
excited because you know uh we know we
kind of half P2 uh Al geometry has P4
we're making progress on P1 uh and and
we we have it seems it looks like we
have solved the hardest problem uh P6 uh
so you know extremely excited I I run uh
to my colleague's desk Oliver Nash who
is one of our Lan experts and so we we
basically copy paste that proof into
official lean and uh it SS a little bit
and says yeah all got proved and so I I
I run back to my desk I don't think too
much I just forward that message uh to
deis and serge so deis has
s
um and and I wanted to share that um for
two things one I think it shows you the
trust I have in L if I didn't trust Lan
I would probably uh wouldn't have sent
that email kind of seconds after kind of
getting confirmation from L that this
was this was all good and the second
thing I I thought a little bit after
that is like oh was this like kind of a
stupid email but I think actually we are
in a company where where it's cool to do
this and and Dem were following a little
bit what was happening during this
competition
so a little bit later in the day
actually uh we receive another mail and
it's a full proof of P2 so now there's
nothing to argue about um you know
perfect proof found by Alpha proof and a
little bit later in the day actually on
that same day we also received a full
proof of
P1 so in conclusion you know final
results uh P1 P2 and P6 were fully
solved by alha proof and P4 was fully
solved by alha
geometry um we actually tried to keep
running over the weekend in the hope of
getting one point on P3 because actually
the agent made some progress on it but
it turned out that it was not enough for
a partial
point so we reached the score of a
silver medalist and missed the goal
thresold by one point um of course I
just want to reiterate that you know we
definitely use more time and more
compute than was available to the to the
human
participant um I want to come back a
little bit on this P6 problem because it
turned out that it was arguably one of
the hardest problems in the last years
at the IMO only five out of 609 of the
participant solve this problem fully and
you know is the top six people of every
country who comes in and only five in
total Sol the problem f um and um 30 m
hours who is Fields medalist and H gold
medalist as well he said that he
actually spent a couple of hours on this
problem and did not solve it and I find
the fact that the program can come up
with a somewhat complicated construction
like this very impressive so in no ways
am I saying that you know we are we are
close to team G's kind of mass abilities
and he may not have spent you know these
two hours really trying to solve this
and these things you know you need to
you know these are kind of you need to
practice to solve these things uh and so
in no ways am I saying that we are close
to Fields metal level but I think this
we we all interpreted this as a really
really encouraging sign for the future
to be able to do something really
non-trivial um let me conclude this IO
part with with some of the challenges
we've observed the first is the gaps in
Muslim and so the the most blatant one
is is geometry actually if geometry was
not there um you know like kind of you
may have required us to actually
completely write that part in mle so
that we could um we could do uh we could
do the the geometry problems or we may
have decided not even to try the
geometric col um also I want to say that
even in P1 uh we observed that actually
there were some gaps in M that were that
we suffered from and so in one of the
proes where you have to prove that it's
you know either rational or irrational F
proof had proved the rational part and
was struggling on the irrational part
um so this is not definitive but um in
fact we observed that you know like the
natural way to prove this would be to
use a certain theorem that turned out to
not exist in m so you know this is not
an excuse a proof could have conjectured
that theorem proed it in line and use it
to finish that proof uh but it turned
out that you know that problem was more
difficult than it it needed to be uh now
combinat Trix problems were also very
difficult uh you know just P5 was
extremely hard to formalize a lot of you
know the necessary API to represent
those problems about you know actually
in ironically about agents environments
and strategies um is not present in M
that was made that problem very hard to
formalize uh and the reality is that
even when we had formalized it we did
not manage to make progress on P3 and P5
so combinat tricks uh were difficult for
AF uh and and of course we use many
orders of magnitude more compute than
than human contestants in some way you
know I think you know um uh we actually
successfully landed on the moon I think
that is the actually the important part
U and and and we will want to be more
efficient uh for the next
trip all right um so now let me go into
you know the methods um and before we
get there I want to remind you that you
know uh when we're talking about the
methods there were two important aspects
we needed to think about
one is where do the problems come from
and and how we how are we going to have
an agent that that learns to prove those
problems so we train several models uh
one model is a formalizing model so it
takes as an input a problem described in
natural language in output lean
formalization so this is based on the
idea that you know we are going to lean
onto human defined problems um instead
of inventing our own problems and we are
going to try to tr translate them in L
because you know they all exist in
natural language but they don't exist in
so we're going to try to do that uh you
know trying to do that with humans uh
don't scale at all takes a long time and
so instead we want to try to train a
model uh that can do this
automatically okay that's uh the
formalized model and now we also have a
Prov model so the the architecture of a
Prov a model is that it takes this kind
of you know the if you remember in my
demonstration before this kind of yellow
box the tactic
State the Le state that tells you you
know what do you know now what do you
need to prove this is the thing we're
going to send as an input to the pro
model and then the Prov model is going
to sample uh and continuation for the
proof uh you know this end things you
might
consider potentially part of the proof
and Alternatives then you take this pro
model and you put it in the alpha zero
search so you're going to search over
actions which are basically one line in
the proof in time you add one line in
the proof you send that to Lin and Lin
tells you oh uh what do I know now what
do I need to prove now
um and and that's basically how the
search works um if you know a little bit
about Ala zero and MCTS like search they
try to exploit you know what kind of the
networks tell you the neural networks
tell you they exploit the high prior and
high value path but it has a mechanism
also to explore low visited path for
instance you know that's how move 37 in
AO discovered is because you know it
might have a low prior might not be
considered the right move by by by by
the network but um but we're still going
to try to visit it in case it might be
an interesting move okay so now now let
me put this thing together in the
pipeline step one we do auto
formalization so we train a
formalization model and auto formalize
human creative problems um so this is
really the answer to the question where
the problems come from uh around human
mathematics uh and here I want to
highlight a few advantages of using kind
of formalization of a problem first is
that when you know like when you send
the problem to lean and you and lean
says this is a valid syntax uh it means
that you know your your question makes
sense um uh it's not kind of something
that doesn't make sense so it's either
true or false you know your generally
something that is either true or false
um okay the problems might not be
interesting you know they might be
triggly true or triggly false uh uh but
but they are either you know true or
false and so one way to see this is you
have the human problem in in the middle
and you try to generate kind of lean
kind of variance of it um and uh and you
know if your trans if your model is
really good then you will do the perfect
translation but maybe also it will
generate problems kind of that are kind
of look like that problem
right and so when we have this
formalization model the way we used it
is we were able to GA about aill ion
informal problems there's a lot of
problems to train for the IMO about a
million of them we pass them through our
formalized model and we generate roughly
for every you know problem described in
natural language we generated roughly
100 possible uh translation for it and
now we've just created a huge database
of foral
problems okay now we need to have uh we
need to train the the prover to be good
at proving um and so that's where you
know you you don't really want to be U
uh completely in the alpha zero
philosophy where you really start from
scratch uh here you you know you you
want to be pragmatic and you want to
start with something that is already you
know can do a few things so you take a
pre- chain model in our case it was pre-
chain on a lot of code um and uh and
then kind of the next step is you're
going to train the Prov model supervis
on MTH Li the MTH Li has about like
100,000 definitions 200,000 here 200,000
lines of proof um and basically you are
really going to do supervised so you
know you're are going to place yourself
inside of a human proof you're going to
look at what is the L State there then
you're going to look at what the human
said was the next step in the proof and
you're going to train the model towards
it um so in some sense very similar to
regular kind of pre-training but you get
much more information from the and so
when you've done that you know your Prov
model has learned a really good prior
over you know the actions to take um
unfortunately uh you know MTH Li is
about or you know I don't know but
especially if you want to do the IMO
Mass Li doesn't contain much IMO like
kind of problems uh it's all about
research mass and so if you take that
Pro a model and you try to apply it on
the IMO
um you get around 0% overate on the Amo
I'm not going to say hard 0% I actually
I'm not sure but close to 0% and so
that's why you start to have to discover
new knowledge about you know how to
solve those problems and and and so that
that's where you enter the next stage of
the alpha zero reinforcement learning
stage and so you you are going to train
the the proval model by R and and the
recipe is very simple it's R recipe um
you know for each formal problem you're
going to generate experience or either
proving or disproving that problem by
searching over L steps um once you've
come up with what you think is is a
proof you're going to use Lan to verify
the proofs uh L is going to say this is
not a proof this is a proof and for the
things that are proof you're going to
reinforce your Prov on network uh on
those proofs uh and so what happens is
that you know at the very beginning uh
the Prov model uh is able to prove the
the very the easiest problems really
really easy problems is going to learn
from that experience and kind of climb
the next rung on the ladder that leads
all the way to IMO strengths right it's
going to be able to then you know solve
a few more problems a bit harder and by
learning from those it will go and get
better and better and better and all the
way to the Amo uh and so for this stage
uh we decided to do a kind of really the
I zero kind of pipeline um because what
we wanted to see is that you know like
of course we want to solve the IMO but
we want to do it in a way that we think
will will you know will generalize Way
Beyond Theo so you know like um our real
goal is to do real mathematics is not to
stop at Theo so we want to have a
method that is not tuned to the IMO we
want to have a method that can discover
new knowledge and so all these proving
strategies for the IMO this is
completely disc discovered by the model
by
itself uh so that's step three and then
final step is this thing called test
time er um and so to give you a bit of
context as I alluded before you know
even for P the USA Coach or team goers
or ter you know the the problems at the
IMO are not obvious so even if you have
like Fields metal level neur network of
mathematic intution you cannot really
solve those IMO problems instantly for
then even for them it takes hours to
solve and and why is that is because you
know those problems have been designed
this way and and you really want to
learn something about those problems
it's almost like kind of a real
scientific kind of experiment you know
you first need to think of experiments
in this Cas is like what could be true
what could be false um then you need to
run the experiments you know try to
prove or disprove those problems and
learn from this experience to learn
about that particular
problem and the the way we did it is
that um you know alha proof is going to
generate variance of the problem we
we're caring about so in this case you
know we have these six problems at Theo
these are the problems we care about uh
can we generate viance of those problems
and basically then run RL exactly as in
the previous step to try to discover
knowledge uh especially about those
problems so I try to illustrate this um
in some hyperplane where you have the
agent and the problem um uh so yeah try
to to imagine this a little bit so on
the bottom left basically you have a
bubble of problems that the pro the
agent can already solve easily so it's a
generous checkpoint every like little
black dots here represent kind of
problem that the agent already knows how
to do and then you know like very far on
the top right you have this very hard
problem that you you want to solve so
imagine maybe it's the P6 problem at the
end and so as I described um the first
thing we did was we generated variants
of that thing so we basically explode
kind of that problem into many many
variants um and if you are doing this
well um you you may hope that you know
it will generate one VAR that is
actually already solvable by by the
agent and so you solve that one and you
learn from that proof exact like before
and and you know you learn a little bit
about that problem and then you repeat
that process you repeat that process you
learn about that problem until you know
you reach uh you reach that problem and
you can solve it and so that's how
actually P1 and P2 and P6 all of them
require the out to be
S okay so I want to finish section uh
with some challenges for Alpha proof um
so we inherit some challenges from
formal mathematics as I said you know
most of human data is in natural
language uh but we started to have a
good handle on how to translate that
human data so that we could learn about
it um so still a big challenge
especially as we move forward uh but
maybe we have some handle on maybe uh
something that is a bit harder is that
we cannot easily learn and work on areas
that are not supported by m um so for
instance you know like in the geometry
case where if you have nothing about it
right you can't even express kind of you
know the the the geometry problems that
humans have come up with and so that's
kind of a real challenge to think about
um and so this could be solved if you
know you you start to understand how to
do creative building of new objects and
theories uh you understand
interestingness and building mathematics
um but this is definitely kind
a a really cool challenge uh for future
work um cool so you know what's next for
for Alpha proof um as I said you know
like kind of um from the very beginning
actually of the AL proof project uh the
idea was to try to see if we could uh
you know learn about mathematics and
potentially go beyond human mathematics
um the IMO has a really really cool
Milestone that I think was extremely
correlated with that go but that's not
where we want to stop um so obviously
what we want to do is is we we want to
Broad to the entire mathematical
landscape we don't want to be stuck at
high school mathematics um we want in
the future to be able to contribute to
the fronti of research mass and um and
going back to you know to you know the
understanding that the Greek got 25 100
years ago of of the importance of proof
um it would be fantastic if we could
democratize democratize kind of this
idea of a proof and share that with
every thinker uh from from an elite
mathematician to you know any other
person and so can we have a proof as a
useful tool for every
thinker and I want to conclude uh saying
that you know the Big Ideas um they're
really important but equally important
if not more is the people you are doing
this with uh and the mindset that
everyone has on the team um I was
pleasantly surprised to hear that you
know in mathematics as well you need to
be really optimistic um otherwise you
will never be able to prove anything I
think this is also true in Ai and
machine learning need to be absurdly
kind of optimistic uh to be able to
achieve kind of absur goals um and
really you know individually this was
almost impossible but you know we had
this belief that together it was
impossible to fil um so these were the
the team members uh that contributed to
to this amazing project um and um and
yeah let me let me conclude that and and
thank you for for listening