I think it should be okay for now. It's
okay. Uh then yeah then let's get
started. Um
so yeah so today we are going to uh
review some very basics about the
generative models especially kind of the
some old ideas like the gen and the
before we get into the diffusion and the
flow models. So I guess many of you
might already have some kind of the
background about the general models. So
this part might be boring for some of
you but let me just like briefly go over
with some kind of the basics before and
we're going to also see some kind of the
how these kind of the ideas begin and
the BAE especially the BAE is basically
the connected uh with the fusion models
that we also going to see.
So for all the genetic models the basic
idea is that as I also mentioned in the
the last time the basic idea is that
let's say like we are having this kind
of the very large the collection of the
images. So as I said there is some kind
of the a data set especially for the
images which includes the 5.8 billions
of images very large scale the infinite
scales of images. So given this kind of
the very large collection of the the
data uh here the question is that how we
are going to make a kind of model that
can produce something that looks like
one of them right so that's basically
what we want to do so given this kind
like very huge collection of the data
points uh what we want to do is that we
are making some kind of the model that
can produce something that looks like
one of those kind of the data points not
exactly just like just picking one of
these uh kind of the given the data
points but making something new but
still that looks like one of those kind
of the images. So that's basically all
about the models how we are going to
basically make a model that can produce
this kind of thing.
So how can you do this? Uh it sounds
like too challenging problem. So but the
thing is that actually the uh your the
course project will be really making
such kind of model that can produce some
kind of a new image. uh but that sounds
like too challenging. So we are going to
uh get into some kind of simpler case.
So instead of like seeing some kind of
the collection of the images, let's
think about like much simpler case say
like we're just having some kind of
collection of the 2D points. So now we
having some kind of the lots of the dots
in the 2D space that forms like this
kind of shape.
Then here the question is that how we
can make a model that can basically pick
kind of the new point but that looks
like uh one of those kind of given the
points.
So that's the the basic idea how we can
make this kind of model
and actually there can be some multiple
kind of the ideas of like doing these
kind of things. uh but what we are going
to discuss in this class over the entire
semester uh is basically seeing this
problem from the uh statistical
perspective. So you're going to see that
actually everything here is basically
all about the statistics. Uh so from the
statistical perspective what we are
going to see is that we are going to
treat all the uh given the set of the 2D
points as kind of the samples from some
kind of the undrawing the probability
distribution. So we are going to assume
that there is some kind of the
underlying the probability distribution
uh which is basically defining our data
distribution and the given set of the 2D
points are basically the samples from
that specific the distribution
then the problem becomes basically how
we going to basically uh sample
basically new data point from that the
underlying distribution right so that's
basically the statistical perspective of
this kind of the the generation problem
make sense.
So basically if the probability
distribution is known and for some
specific types of the distribution what
we can do is we can directly sample the
data points from that specific
distribution. How we can do that?
Do you have any ideas for this?
Uh so we going to this is basically not
the main point here but we're going to
basically very briefly see uh what kind
of things that we can do. uh let's think
about some simplest case that we are
having some kind of the categorical
distribution. Uh so this is even the
case that we are having some kind of the
discrete distates the finite number of
the discrete states and for each of the
states we have some kind of the
probability uh which sum should be one
right uh given this kind of the let's
say like we are having this specific the
categorical distribution having the four
states and having some kind of
probability for each of the case right
for this kind of the case how we can
basically sample uh one of those kind of
the four states
based on this distribution
uh we can do this any ideas
isn't it something that you already
learned from the statistics course
I don't know so that's basically
something uh that we are going to do the
simplest idea for this is that uh we are
going to see not just the probability
dist uh the the distribution but the
cumulative distribution the function
like this uh which is basically nothing
but uh just like accumulating the
probability for the uh states which is
coming before each of the state. So for
each of the like four cases we are
basically summing up the probability for
the previous states. Then we're going to
make this kind of the CTF function right
then what we can do is that actually we
can see this kind of the CDF function uh
not from this axis but from the other
axis here. So basically the point is
that obviously like when we sum up all
the probability until the last distinct
this sum should be one right. So
basically know if we see uh the CDFD
function it should be basically starting
from the zero to one like this
then what we can do is that we can
simply consider basically sampling uh
from this axis.
So basically in any case the range of
the y-axis here should be basically 0 to
one right then what we can do is that we
are sampling from this axis with the
uniform distribution basically getting
some kind of the random the probability
in the range from the range from the 0
to one and see where this point fs into
uh for each of the beam here make sense
that's the very basic idea for the
inverse transform the sampling uh so we
are basically seeing the CDF from the uh
not from the this axis but from the
D-axis in terms of that we are sampling
one of the the point here from the range
from the zero to one. So that basically
becomes the probability and then see
like where this basically point falls
into the one of the beans here. Uh it
should be falling into the any of like
those beans right and as we basically
have some kind of the higher the
probability there will be some more the
chances that the point falls into that
specific
so it's bally very intuitive the idea
right in terms of how we can sample
based on the given the categorical
distribution.
So this is the very basic idea for the
inverse transform desampling and
actually we can extend this idea not
only for the discrete case but also for
the continuous case as well.
It's basically exactly the same thing.
So it's the matter of like know given
any kind of the uh PDF from some
specific range uh of the some kind of
data points we are basically calculating
the cumulative distribution the function
by by just taking the integral onto that
point right so given the kind of the
cumulative distribution function then
what we can do is that now we also
having the same this kind of the plot
but not in the discrete space but in the
continuous space then we can do the same
thing in terms of like sampling ing the
probability from the 0 to one range with
the uniform distribution and see where
these point F into the each of the
infinite small the small bin right which
means that just like computing the
inverse of the uh the CDF of the
function right
so that's the basic idea so which means
that uh if we can if we have the uh
probability distribution function and if
we can compute the CDF and also the
inverse the CDF then we can use this
idea to sample from that the specific
the probability distribution
make sense
very simply so let's do some kind of
exercise you don't need to this you can
just like play with this so given this
kind of the PDF uh 38 of the x squared
uh into this range uh basically how we
going to sample from that specific PDF
Let's try to basically calculate this.
If you have the pen and the uh paper,
try to solve this and see what you get.
So yeah, let me give you a couple of
minutes to see
So over the lectures you're going to see
this kind of very slowly tiny problems
like all the slice
So it's basically very clear to see that
we can be the inverse of the CDF like
this.
So
let's do some kind of some small
practices and see uh what you get. Uh so
yeah here basically the point is that uh
if we can basically uh have the
knowledge about the PDF the distribution
uh and also if we can compute the
cumulative distribution the function and
also the inverse of the CDF then based
on that we can use the simply the idea
in terms of like the inverse transform
the sampling. uh so it's basically all
about like first sampling from the any
uniform distribution and then basically
fitting it to the inverse of the CPF
right
so this is the basic idea and the thing
is that uh what we are going to see uh
in this class is that we are going to
talk about the gausian distribution the
normal distribution all the time I mean
there will be lots of things basically
based on the gausian distribution and
the reason like why we are playing with
the gausian distribution is that we know
how to sample from the gaussian
distribution that's basically very uh
kind of the basic things uh the problem
with the the normal distribution is that
uh we know the form of the pdf right
uh can you find the closed form of the
inverse cdf of this one
uh if you try to find the inverse of the
cumulative distribution function for the
uh standard normal distribution
But you're going to see that uh it's not
possible. So that's the problem. Uh so
we got the idea like in case the case
like when he can compute the inverse C
depth then we can use the idea of the
inverse transform the sampling. But this
is kind of the one of the uh
representative case that we cannot
directly compute the inverse C dep. So
what should you do? Uh so there are also
like lots of the ideas but I'm going to
just give some kind of the age ideas
like what we can do. uh some very
briefly for example so let's say for the
uh the case that we are having the
standard normal distribution
uh let's think about that now we are
taking not only a single sample but like
taking some two independent samples the
x and the y here which are both coming
from the same the standard the normal
distribution
so in this case the joint distribution
will be defined like this simply
multiplying these two right so if we
just like play with the uh standard
normal distribution like this then
there's no way that we can sample from
this. So what we are going to do is that
we are going to change the variables. So
the idea for the changing the variable
is that the actually we are seeing like
why we are having the two samples not a
single sample. uh the basic idea is that
we are going to treat these like two
samples as kind of the 2D the cartis and
the coordinates basically like one of
the point in the 2D space uh in a way
that we can jointly convert uh these two
variables into the uh the variables in
the polar coordinates. So now we are
going to see not the X and the Y
coordinates but the radius R here and
the theta here. Basically changing the
variables especially like we are going
to see not just the radius but the
secured radius R squared there and also
thea there. Then based on this kind of
the new the variables now we can also
compute the same the joint distribution
that becomes like this. And then
obviously the radius and the theta those
two things will be independent each
other right one is about the angle and
the other is basically about the
distance.
Then what you can see is that actually
after changing the uh the the variables
we can see that we are having these two
variables like this and the probability
distribution for each of them becomes
like this. Uh the good thing is that now
for the angle here it becomes the
uniform distribution. So we know how we
can sample from this. So it's very easy.
uh the only thing is that uh now for the
uh security radius which I just denoted
as the d here that's the same as the r
squared for the security the radius we
are basically having this kind of the
form of the the probability distribution
uh which is specifically the the kai
security distribution with the the
degree of the freedom of the two but you
don't need to exactly remember this the
thing is that the pdf looks like this
right so which means that now We know
the PDF and it looks like something that
we can compute the inverse of the CDF
right. So now it becomes the matter of
like how we going to compute the inverse
of the the CDF in terms of that we can
sample the security radius. Uh can you
also try to derive the inverse of the
CDF?
Did everyone get this?
So I mean yeah so you can see like why
we are changing the the variables. The
good thing of like that is that now we
can have the form of the PDF that we can
easily compute the inverse the
accumulation distribution function then
now you got the idea right. So based on
that uh we can sample from the gausian
distribution. So the basic idea is that
uh for the angle uh it's just like
sampling from the uniform distribution.
So it's very easy uh for the security
radius what we need to do is that we
first sample from the another the sample
another the uniform the disc sample and
then let's say computing this right so
that becomes the one of the sample of
the security radius and based on that
just like me computing the x and the y
and the good thing is that now we get
the not the single sample but the two
independent samples from the gausian
distribution.
So now you got the basically the basic
idea right. Uh so even some kind of the
the PDF uh what we can do is that if we
can directly compute the inverse the CDF
then we can basically sample based on
that. Uh by the way all these slides are
already uploaded on the slack and also
the course web page. So you can download
that. Okay. Uh so given that the PDF we
can if we can compute the inverse CDF
then we can basically directly sample
from that. For the other cases we can
consider doing some kind of the uh
changing the variables in terms of that
we are making the form that we can
compute the inverse depth. Uh for the
other the cases we can also do something
like the rejection sampling but we are
not going to get into the deeper into
that but there are some basically the
bunch of the ideas in terms like given
the PDF how we can make some kind of the
new sample. So you can see that uh for
the cases like when the PDF is basically
known and also the when the PDF is the
form that we can compute the inverse
DCDF there is nothing to discuss in
terms of the modeling you can just
directly sample from that that's it so
nothing to discuss that means that
actually the problem that we are
thinking is like much more complicated
right so we are going to get into that
but before we get into that uh here also
the question is that so that is the case
of like the 1D case right what if we
have the multivar of the the normal
distribution. Uh what should you do?
The previous case was like the one the
gausian distribution, right? One
standard denomal distribution with the
multi-dimensional space
how can you do the multiply
very simple thing because like every
dimension will be independent each each
other right? So we just need to sample
for each of the dimension because like
each dimension is basically independent.
Very simple, right? This is the case
like when you sample from the standard
dormal distribution uh when the various
term there is basically identity the
matrix right. Uh what if we have some
kind of the anostropic uh the normal
distribution
when the variance is basically not the
identity the matrix then what we can do
is that we can do something like the var
the v parameterizing the truth in terms
of that we are first sampling from the
standard normal distribution and then
computing that which is basically just
like mapping to the corresponding point
in the anos the gian distribution.
So this sounds like uh for whatever the
gaussian distribution that we have uh
it's basically possible to basically
sample from that distribution right. So
actually that's also the reason like why
we are playing with the gausian for all
the cases because like this is the uh
syn form that in terms like doing some
sampling
and this was like also all the cases
like when you have the set of the 2D
points but actually what we want to do
is like not generating some 2D points we
want to make some images or videos or
something 3D or something bigger right
uh for the cases like when you have some
loss of the images then what we can
So what we are going to do is that we
are also simply going to treat the all
the RGB images especially we are also
going to consider the images in the
certain resolution let's say like we
have images in this resolution the 256
by the 256 uh also then the question
might be is that how can we also handle
some cases like the varying the
resolutions right uh so that's kind of
you know the the the problems that we
need to do some kind of engineering uh
but now let's think about some
simplistic case that we are having the
images some kind of big resolution the
256 by 256
and then what you can see is that each
of the image can be considered as kind
of some sort of the uh very high
dimension vector because like every p
every pixel we we have some kind of 3D
numbers right numbers and then we are
having the 256 by the 256 by the 3D
numbers that is basically representing a
single image
So we can fit each of the RGB image as
kind of like one single vector uh in
this very high dimensional space uh 256x
256 by three dimensional space actually
every image is just like one point uh in
a very high dimensional space right then
the problem becomes the same so we are
talking about the uh the points in the
2D space now the set of images can be
considered in the points in this very
high dimensional space then the problem
become the same in terms of that if we
can somehow get the access of the
undrawing the distributions
uh for the set of the images in this
high dimensional space and if it looks
like something like the gausian
distribution then we can't directly
sample from that that's the basically
the problem is that we don't know the
underlying the data distribution so
that's the
So how we are going to basically get the
information about the underlying
distribution of the the images in the
high dimension space how we can also
derive the DPDF and even in the case
that we know some kind of the have some
information about the underlying
distribution uh can sample from that
which means that we also should be able
to compute the inverse of the C
therefore we can do we need to do
something right so that's kind of the
problem so basically we the only
information that we
is just the samples that we assume that
is a sample from some kind of certainty
the underlying distribution but we don't
have the information about the
underlying distribution.
So in this case that we don't know some
kind of information about the underlying
distribution how we are going to sample
from it. So that's the problem for the
uh the directive modeling.
So the very basic idea for not only for
the diffusion the flow models but for
the all the models is basically uh is
this. So what we are going to do is that
we are going to uh find a mapping from
some kind of a simple distribution uh
that we know how we can sample from it
uh to the data distribution that we
don't know. So we don't have the
information about the data distribution
but we are going to consider finding a
mapping from the some simple
distribution which is typically the
standard normal distribution because we
know how to sample from this right and
then we are mapping the whole
distribution into the the unknown the
data distribution. So that's basically
what we are going to do. So what we are
doing with the either GAN or the BAE
diffusion or the flow model is basically
all about finding this mapping uh from
some kind of some simple distribution uh
to the data distribution.
So over the entire semester uh in this
class uh we are going to use these
notations here. Basically Z represents
some kind of the samples from the uh
some that simple distribution that we
are also going to call as the latent
distribution. So Z basically means the
sample from the typically the standard
the Gaussian distribution and the X
denotes the data point. This is the one
of the reality data point that we have
in our training data set. Right? And P Z
uh the latent distribution is the
information that we know and the PX is
something that we don't know right so
that's basically the setup of the
entirely uh this semester. So the
generation the process will become
basically we are sampling from that the
latent distribution this turn the normal
distribution and the mapping this into
the one of the data point uh that will
be our the generation the process for
everything for the GAN VA diffusion flow
models for everything make sense
here then the question is that how we
can find such kind of the mapping uh how
do we know for this kind of mapping so
that's the kind of the place where the
neuronet network basically comes in. Uh
we are going to train a neural network
in a way to basically find the mapping
from the one of the samples from the
latent distribution to the one of the
samples from the data distribution. So
that will be the role of the neural
network for the old models.
Then in terms like finding this mapping
uh we are going to uh see so this is
kind of similar with the autoenccoder. I
guess everyone would know about the
autoenccoder.
Is there anyone who didn't hear about
the autoenccoder before?
Yeah.
Yeah. So very basic things about the the
the deep learning, right? So uh the all
of the autoenccoding is basically to
some kind of the uh do some sort of the
compression, right? So here we want to
map any kind of input data point into
the latent data point. And then the idea
of like this mapping is that we are
having the encoder and the decoder in a
way that the decoded output should be
the same uh with the input there. Right?
So that's the basic idea and what you
can say is that here the encoder becomes
the function which is mapping the input
data point into the latent data point
and the decoder becomes the mapping from
the latent data point uh into the input
data point. Right? Uh so in our context
uh this is the x the data point x and
this becomes the z the latent the sample
which is typically coming from the
gausian distribution and then we can see
that the encoder is mapping from the x
to z and the decoder is the mapping from
the z to the x and what we need uh is
actually just the decoder we don't need
the encoder right uh if we can basically
have some kind of mapping from the
latent to the data point here uh then we
can use that uh in our generation the
process
So the problem is that that then how we
are going to train this decoder uh while
guaranteeing that basically all the
samples from the latent distribution
basically uh go to the one of the data
points in the data distribution. So for
that we are seeing some kind of the
bunch of the ideas like the gen and the
for many things uh for many of you who
already know about the gen. So let me uh
this plant might be boring so let me go
quickly with the gen. So the basic idea
for the gen is that actually it's coming
from the uh idea of the adversity the
attack. So the basic idea for the other
attack is that uh we know actually
neuronet networks are quite good at for
many things uh especially for the
classification. uh neuronet networks are
really good at classifying the truck and
the whatever some some buildings or
something some other kind of the some
dogs or something right here the thing
is that uh these are all the images that
are correctly declassified with the
pre-trained model and what if we add
some kind of the small noise uh into
these images the thing is that I don't
know whether you can see any kind of
difference even for me actually I cannot
tell tell any kind of difference between
this and this but actually the middle
column here are basically visualizing uh
the difference between the these two
images
also multiplied by 10 in terms like you
know amplifying the difference but
basically these two are almost the same
images while basically adding some small
tiny noise over the images and making
some kind of slightly different images
uh the thing is that if we add this kind
of the noise into the images the thing
is they pre-trained uh the classifier
will see all those images as the
ostrich. Do you guys know the ostrich?
The this one somehow like the pre trend
classifier is basically saying that
these images are in the same class with
this bird, right? So that's kind of the
idea of the other attack. basically
checking how vulnerable the neural
network is in terms of basically even
when you add some kind of some small
noise into the input data point how much
it will be basically declassified uh the
old images in the correct way. So that's
the basic idea.
Uh so this is basically the task which
is called the adversity attack. uh we
are basically making a neuronet in a way
that uh the output of the neuron net
become something that makes the
pre-trained the classifier to fail. Uh
so that's the basic idea for the other
attack. Then when you have this kind of
the neuronet network that plays the role
of the offense then we can also
fine-tune the neural network for the
defense right. So we can consider also
basically pointing the neuron network in
a way that the network also does not
fail for those kind of some uh
degenerated images. Right? So that's the
basic idea. Then what you can do is that
uh we can make them to compete each
other. So we need make some kind of the
some healthy competition uh between
these two neuron networks. Uh we can
basically consider making those the two
networks to uh improve each other in
terms of like we this is like making
some kind of the better images and also
this one is also doing some kind of
better classification. So that's the
basic idea for the GAN. I guess most of
you already know. So we are basically
making a discriminator the classifier
which is classifying whether the output
is some kind of the real image or fake
image that we are generating using the
generator and also we having the another
generator which is making some kind of
the uh some real like images. Uh so in a
way that we want to basically fully
discriminator right so that's the basic
idea.
So in the context of the uh the
generated models we can see that the
generator is basically the decoder in
the autoenccoding the setup which is
basically taking some the uh the sample
from the latent distribution and the
mapping it to the one of the realistic
the data point and then the
discriminator will play the role of
basically classifying whether the output
is something that is the real image or
some kind of the fake image right and
then we are making them to compete each
other.
So if we briefly go over into the the
loss function here uh so this is the
loss function which is training both the
uh discriminator and also the generator.
Uh the meaning of the this loss function
is that basically uh we are taking the
sample of the real image uh the data
point coming from the training the data
set and also the uh the point coming
from the latent uh the distribution
right the typically the standard
decision distribution and then mapping
this like latent sample uh into the
generator in terms like making some fake
image here right
and then uh the what we get with the
this discrim here is basically how
likely the input image will be the real
like image. So we have gain some kind of
probability like how likely this input
will be one of the with the real images
and we can see that this is kind of the
optimation the problem that we are
maximizing the loss function over the
the parameters of the discriminator. uh
which means that so maximizing the all
the loss function basically means that
we want to uh increase the probability
uh of the uh this obviously this is the
uh real image sample right so we need to
maximize the probability of like how
likely this would be the real image
right so we should be maximizing this
and then this is the one minus like dump
here right so which means that we are
going to decrease this so we obviously
the probability of like how likely this
like fake image will be treated as kind
of the real image should be decreased.
Right? So this is the design of loss
function in terms like you know
increasing that and then decreasing that
by basically maximizing the parameters
over dt
and then from the perspective of the
generator actually we are now uh
increasing the probability.
Uh so now in this case like we are the
you know optimizing over the parameters
of the generator here in terms of that
we also want to make this like fake
image to be treated as some kind of one
of the real images. So we can see some
kind of the competition between this
like the discriminator and the generator
in this term right in this loss
function.
So we can see that this is kind of the
optim problem which is basically having
the combining both the minimization and
also the maximization. So for the some
parameters of the neural network we are
maximizing this whole the loss function
and for the some other part of the
neural network we also we are minimizing
this loss function. So this is basically
very uh well known some kind of the
optimization the problem in terms of
that it's really hard to solve. So it's
it's very easy to basically get into
some kind of the local minima. Uh so
that's actually the problem we get. So
when you train the two neuronet networks
uh with this kind of the minimax image
the problem uh there are lots of the
chances that we get born into some kind
of the bad uh the local minimum. So
that's the problem.
So the difficulty failure cases of the
GAN is that uh is there anyone who tried
to uh implement and train the GAN
before?
Have you experienced any kind of problem
from the GAN training?
Yeah.
Any anyone
>> just it keeps shifting.
>> Yeah. Yeah. Yes. So it's also Yeah.
There are lots of the the issues like
it's basically hard to see some kind of
a convergence of the loss and typically
the problem is that uh many failure
cases that you can easily see with the
GAN training is that the discriminator
typically wins. It's very hard very easy
to see that the discriminator basically
converges faster uh and then this
basically results in that know there is
nothing learned with the generator. So
it's kind of the also the life lesson
right I mean for all the things that we
are doing if you first set some kind of
very strongly criteria for the success
then there's nothing we can do I mean
it's the criteria is already too strict
uh so there's nothing we can uh want to
try explore right so that's very also
the very typical the failure cases of
the gant training so the typical uh some
practice for the gant training is that
uh you first need to uh train the
generator first without training uh the
discriminator in terms of that the
generator can prove something and after
that you also need to basically uh you
know combine the both the generator and
the discriminator in terms of like
making them to the compute each other
but for many of the the cases you can
see this failure cases that the
discriminator basically becomes too
strong in terms of the the generator
becomes learns nothing. So that's the
typical failure of the cases
and also the other problem of the GAN is
that even in the case that when the
training goes well uh there are so lots
of the cases it only learns some kind of
the the subset of the uh the
distribution of the the the data points.
So especially for the cases that when we
have some kind of the multiple some the
most moves like this multiple some kind
of some small groups of the the data
points in the space uh the output
basically learns that not the entire
distribution but only capturing some
kind of the subset of the mod in terms
like losing some kind of the diversity
of the data points that we have. So this
is like very typical failure cases and
if you try to train the gen yourself
then you're going to see that actually
the training gen is really really really
difficult. So you will need to do lots
of the engineering. Uh so these days
like for many kind of the companies
there is I think there is no really any
kind of like gen teams really working on
the gen things but until like 2020 I
think all the like gen AI relate kind of
the teams in the companies were really
implementing GANs for the image
generation or the video generation for
the many things and they even had some
kind of some dedicated engineers. The
engineers are just like tuning some
parameters of the all the things in
terms of getting some kind of better
developments. Uh even not just like one
multiple people are just like tuning all
the parameters in the game training uh
to better capture all the diversity. Uh
while it's really really difficult so
that's like very hard
but still this is the very basic idea.
uh after the first idea began uh it's
been introduced in the 2013 there have
been lots of some variants began as you
can see this is even not the full list
so there are alo some of the those were
very successful the the uh the examples
like really making some kind of
realistic images so as I also showed in
the uh last lecture these results of
like making the face images was based on
the style game tool uh which was
introduced in the 2019. So even at that
time without any kind of diffusion flow
models you can see that actually the
quality was not bad right making
something quite the realistic.
Uh so the reason I think the main reason
like why people shifted to the diffusion
flow models from the GAN is not just
because of the quality but actually
because of the uh the difficulty in the
training. So even with the GAN if you do
lots of the engineering will many things
then you can manage to get some kind of
quite good quality of the outputs the
problems or the two problems are
basically the difficulties in the
training and also the diversity. So
there are quite many cases that like
basically losing some kind of the
diversities for the outputs. So that's
kind of the issues we get.
So that's why also people started to
consider some kind of new idea which is
the ba the variation of go.
So here the the question is that how we
can basically train a the models without
solving the minimaxity problem.
Uh so for that basically what we are
going to do is that now we are going to
see the mapping from the latent
distribution to the data distribution.
uh not just like finding a the the
function but actually learning some kind
of the conditional distribution. So here
basically what we are going to see is
that we are going to see this kind of
like mapping problem as kind of another
the sampling the problem given any
sample z there coming from the standard
gausian distribution. uh how we are
going to basically learn this like the
conditional distribution in a way that
we can sample the x the data point
conditioned by the z which is coming
from the standard gausian distribution.
So that's the basic idea
and we are going to simplify all the
things it doesn't need to be gausian
distribution here we basically for many
things we are going to use the gausian
distribution because of the simplicity
and then we are going to model the
conditional distribution in this
specific way. So basically the the
variance is kind of like fixed. So we
are basically fixing some kind of the
variance. We only learn the mean here
and this like mean is learned by the uh
the decoding neural network. So that's
the basic idea.
So somehow if we can basically learn
this kind of the conditional
distribution uh based on that what we
just need to do is that we just sample
the Z here and based on the sample of
the Z we also sample the X and that's
it. uh so that becomes of the our
degenerative models. Then the question
is that how we also going to learn this
kind of conditional distribution right
uh so that's the problem so you see that
all the bae and diffusion models are all
about basically learning this
conditionally distribution so that's the
point
so before we get into some uh details
about that uh I'd like to very briefly
review some very basics about the
statistics I guess all of you would know
about like those things but let Let me
check whether you really know some
details here.
So basically what's the marginality
distribution? So marginality
distribution is the uh the distribution
for the subset of the variables. So when
you have some kind of the multiple the
the random variables here uh given this
kind of like joint distribution uh the
process that we are getting some kind of
the uh the distribution for the subset
of the uh the variables is called the
marginalization.
So this is the case that like when you
have the two variables like the X and
the Z here. uh if we take the integral
of the Z here then this becomes the
marginalization for the X basically
getting some kind of the probability
distribution uh not for those two but
only for the X here right so that's the
process that we're going to call as the
marginalization
then here the quiz is that so let's
think about this uh so given this kind
of a joint probability distribution we
are having the X and the Y and each of
the and X and the Y can have these one
of those three numbers like either one
two three right uh given this kind of
joint probability distribution what's
the probability that the x becomes one
you can just speak up
0.36
do you see like y 0.36
so it's taking the interal right so
which means they're just taking the sum
right so if we want to get the
probability for the x becomes d1 then we
just need to take the sum for this right
uh that is like taking the sum along the
this axis like this
uh things becomes the marginalization uh
with respect to the x right we are
getting the some kind of probability
distribution with respect to the only x
so that's the marginalization
everyone knows the expected value right
so basically it's the weighted sum of
these possibility values that we can
take weighted by the probability right
here right So we can also compute the
expected value for the x here. So what
should you do if you want to take the
expected value over the x here?
I mean we just need first the
marginalize the joint distribution along
like just taking the sum here and then
just like you know taking the weighted
average with these uh uh these three
numbers with the marginalized
probability right then you can also
compute the expected result
these are all the things the base rule
uh this is the basic things like the
joint distribution here can be basically
represented with the products of the
conditional distribution and also the
some marginal distribution here right so
here are basically some kind of the
terminology that we are going to use
that uh so as I said we are keep using
we we are going to keep using basically
these two notations like z is basically
the variables of the lat distribution
and the x is basically the sample from
the data distribution
we know which we know we we the
information that we know is basically
the latent distribution right so this is
basically our prior knowledge so we are
going to call is prior distribution,
right? So given the prior distribution
uh
the
conditional uh distribution uh the the
the probability of like the x given the
one of the sample of the prior
distribution uh will be called the
likelihood distribution. So this like
likelihood distribution is about like
how likely we are going to sample this x
given the latent deb here. That's the
likelihood distribution. I mean it's
just like terminology. So because like
you're going to say that this is like X
conditioned by Z and G conditioned by X.
Like what's the meaning like having the
two different names for these two,
right? Uh so the reason like why we
having the the different name is that uh
basically this is our the prior
distribution
that we know and the like the this
distribution is the marginal
distribution with respect to the X which
is the unknown information. Right? So
what we are going to do is that given
the prior distribution actually this is
something that we want to get right
given the Z uh we want to get the
likelihood distribution in terms of that
we can sample from sample the X uh given
the Z and sampling X basically means
like generating the X right so this is
the about our generation the process
so basically by multiplying the prior
distribution the likelihood distribution
we can get the joint distribution here
and the posterior is basically the
opposite. So given the data point uh
what would be kind of the how likely uh
it would be sampled from the parameter Z
here. So that's the opposite of the
likelihood distribution. So this is the
distribution we're going to call the
posterior distribution. Okay. So don't
get confused like you're going to see
like we going to see lots of like those
things like X conditioned by Z and Z
conditioned by X like the meaning of
like all the thing is that we are
starting from the prior distribution and
then we are going to sample the X from
that. So this this is something that we
want to get the likelihood distribution
and in the process that we are basically
learning the likelihood distribution uh
we we also need to see lots of things
about the posterior distribution as
well. So, so that's kind of the
terminology.
So here the one quick question is that
then how can you compute this
conditional probability? What's the
probability of the y to be two
conditioned by that x becomes the one
>> one over 12
>> one over
>> uh one over 12 uh yeah why is that
can you say like how can you compute
this uh very simple thing right
so from the base rule basically what we
can say is that uh this probability
multiplied by the P you know multiplied
by the the probability of the X equals
one should be the joint probability
right so from the marginalization we can
compute the probability of the X becomes
to one and we also all have the the
information about the joint probability
right so based on that we can now
compute this as well so these all can be
computed with the base scores
and the pull back the liberal
divergence. So this is all about
measuring some kind of how much the
given the probability distribution the P
uh is basically different from the some
kind of reference to distribution the Q
here. So it's basically some kind of the
some notion of the distance between the
two probability distributions but
actually it's not distance because it's
not symmetric. uh so when you basically
change the p and the q when you switch
these two uh the the quantity of the
cact the divergence uh will be changed
so it's you can think it's kind of like
some asymmetric the way to measure some
kind of the not exactly the distance but
some kind of the how likely how much the
uh some kind of the given distribution
is like far from some kind of the the
other the reference distribution the Q
here uh so this is kind of the way to
measure some kind of the some difference
between the two distributions
Uh and then here the question is that uh
what will be the KR divergence for the
same the case when the given
distribution is the same with the
reference distribution
should be zero right I mean by
definition of the care divergence uh
this should be zero and you can we will
check out that like whether this
formulation goes to zero when these two
distribution are sync right so this is
the basic idea and I think we don't have
time to work on this for now but I'd
like to ask you to basically check out
and how we can exactly compute the k
dance for these two gaussian
distribution. So as I said like all of
our things that we're going to play with
in this class will be all based on the
gaussian distribution which means that
we should be able to also measure the k
diverance for these two distributions as
well. So check out how we can exactly
compute the k diverance between the two
gausian distributions.
And one more thing is that uh so let's
briefly talk about the convex function.
So the meaning of the convex function in
the uh one majority case is that uh
basically the function that looks like
this
having some kind of the some the
curvature into the the downward. Uh so
the precise way to define the convex
function is that uh when you take any
kind of the two points here
any two points here uh if you take the
linear interpolation uh between the
function values of like these two points
then all the linear interpolation will
basically form this kind of straight
line right. So when you see the uh here
the linear interpolations of the
function values if you take the uh
interpolation between the function
values so like these two that will
basically form this line right for
whatever t in the range from the 0 to
one uh and if you see that uh you know
not taking the interpolation for the
function values but if you take any kind
of the intermediate data point here and
take the function value of that point if
this value is basically lower than the
any of the the values in the the
straight line. uh that's the the case
that we are having the convex function
for any kind of the two points for any
RBD two points if we draw a basically
the straight line then if we see that
all the intermediate the the points uh
for all the inter the the the points if
the function value is bally same or the
smaller then the basically the function
value straight line uh that's the case
that we having the the convex function
right then what would be the concave
function fun.
The conting
right then be the case that we are
having the function that looks like this
having the cover to the upward. Right?
So this is the case that we are defining
the convex function in the one case.
Obviously we can define the same the
convex function not only one case but
for the arbit dimensional space. So in
any kind of the highdimensional space uh
if we have a function that satisfies
this for any data points the x here uh
for any number of the points uh when you
take some kind of the applying the
combination of like the function values.
So for some of the the cases like for
the 3D case for example like you can
consider like know the case that we are
having some like three points uh making
some kind of plane in the 3D space uh
and for all the intermediate uh some
kind of the points in the the domain
space if we take the function value if
the value is basically lower than the
the plane then that's the case that we
are making having some kind of the the
convex function right so we can also
extend the concept of the convex
function not only for the function in
the one dimensional space but for the
any high dimensional space
obviously the sum of this t here should
be the one
make some kind of a find combination
make sense clear
so this is the case like when you have
the some convex function so I mean this
is the the definition of the convex
function
and based on that uh what we can see is
that uh the genesis inequality is
basically nothing but when it when this
TI the weights the TI is not some kind
of the arbitrary values but some kind of
the probability.
So now let's say that for the each of
the X I here uh we have not only the
function f but some another the
probability distribution defined on the
same the domain space. uh for the case
uh if we also replace all the arbitrary
t here into the probability
uh for each of the the point if the
function f is the convex function then
the same thing should be should hold
right so what we can see here is that
this is exactly the same formulation uh
in the formulation in the previous slide
the same thing the only thing is that
now we are uh having prob probability
for each of the data point here given
any kind of the PDFs. So just like
simply replacing this t as kind of the
probability for the any kind of the
probability distribution over defined
over this space. Uh in that case uh the
definition of the comb function should
go in the same way right and now when
you have the probability here now we can
rewrite this part into the expected
value.
So that becomes like this.
So if x is a random variable and also
the f is a convex function then any kind
of the probability the distribution uh
this basically the definition should
hold which is basically directly just
coming from the definition of the convex
function.
Make sense? Uh nothing special very
simple kind of things. uh and also for
the concave function that will be the
case that we are flipping this sign uh
into this the other way around
basically any questions on this.
So this is like basically the basic idea
about like all the kind of things. So
going back to the bae basically what we
wanted to do was that we wanted to
basically learn this likelihood
distribution in a way that we can sample
from the uh the gausian distribution and
also sampling the x conditioned by the
z. So that's basically what we want to
do then as I said like what's the
question here is that so and also we are
having the some the specific the form of
the likelihood distribution in this way
right it does not need to be gausian but
we are just simplifying everything into
the gausian in this case then here the
question is that how we can learn that
the likelihood of distribution so that's
the question
so what we can do is that we know this
right We know this and we have lots of
the samples of the x this is our
training data right then what we can see
is that uh from the marginalization
uh we can if we have like know this and
also the likelihood distribution this uh
from the marginalization we can compute
the probability for the given the data
point and obviously if we have some kind
of the uh good the likelihood
distribution this probability should be
high right because these these are some
the samples that we know coming from the
data distribution.
So which means that we can consider like
finding some likelihood distribution in
a way that know that basically maximizes
the probabilities for all the data
points X here
that's the basic idea make sense uh we
we know this probability we also
sampling the Z from the Gaussian
distribution and then if we can compute
this uh based on that we can compute the
likelihood of the dx and then we want to
basically uh maximize ize this
probability by finding some good
likelihood distribution. This
the problem of like all the things here
is that this basically involves the
integral integral over the Z which means
that we need to compute this uh not only
for the some single Z but basically need
to take the integral over the entire
space of Z.
How we can compute the integral in this
case?
So actually that's the issue. Uh some
kind of the simple way uh of like doing
this is that uh we are doing some kind
of the approximation. Uh that's the
process called the Monte Carlo method
nothing but just know in terms like
taking the integral the way to simply
like you know approximating this is that
we just take lots of the samples of the
Z.
Yeah. and just taking the sum of these
that can be like one way to some
approximate uh this interval right here.
But if we want to get some kind of
really accurate approximation that we
need to really have tons of Z here this
will involve huge computation which
because like to compute the probability
for the single data point DX we need to
actually have some loss of the uh the
samples from the Gaussian distribution
that makes some kind of loss of the B in
the computation.
So that's the problem we want to
basically find the likelihood and
maximize the px here. uh but we don't
want to really compute the integral. Uh
so that's the kind of the main things.
So how we can do this? It's kind of the
interesting the idea.
So that's basically why the posterior
distribution that comes in here. Uh
while we want to basically learn the
likelihood distribution here actually
now we want to compute the marginal
distribution the px here uh by
leveraging some kind of the information
about the posterior distribution here.
So if we know both the likelihood
likelihood the distribution and also the
posture distribution based on that uh
without really taking the integral uh we
can compute this right
from the base rules that we have seen
the previous slide this clear
then what this mean is that now we need
to have both information both the
likelihood distribution and also the
posteriorly distribution then based on
that uh we can basically consider
jointly learning these two in terms like
that we are maximizing the px
obviously problem is that uh we don't
know uh not only the likelihood
distribution but also post distribution
we don't have this information so that's
also the another problem
so what we are going to do is that so
this is the key idea for the bae and
also we are going to keep seeing this
like same kind of the formulation also
for the diffusion models for the other
things as well. So since we don't know
the posture distribution here the z
conditioned by the x what we are going
to see is that we are going to instead
see some kind of the lower bound for the
marginal distribution.
But what the the basic idea is that uh
what we want to maximize is basically
this right. We want to maximize the
probability for the data point here. But
since we cannot directly compute this,
we are going to consider the uh lower
bound of this probability which is
defined like this. And here the thing is
that this looks very similar uh with the
previous deform here
based on the base row. But the kind of
the difference uh is that now we are
having not the exact the posteriorly
distribution but some sort of the the
proxy distribution something that is not
exactly our the posterior distribution
but some random the the conditional
distribution the distribution of the Z
conditioned by the X. So by having some
kind of some proxy distribution uh we
can consider basically define some kind
of the lower bound of the marginal uh
the probability and then basically we
can uh learn this kind of the uh the
likelihood distribution.
So this is the main idea uh I think we
discussed too many things today. So uh
next Monday uh we're going to continue
discussing this like elbow the the loss
function and see based on this how we
can train the bae and then we're going
to continue how this idea also can be
extended uh to learn the diffusion
models as well.
Don't worry. This is the end of this
discuss.