Okay. So then let's get started. So from
the last week uh we started to discuss
some kind of the some techniques uh that
can basically uh that are basically
about some kind of inference time the
guidance which means that uh with some
kind of the pre-trained diffusion or the
flow the models how can you basically
inject some kind of the usual guidance
at the inference time at the test time
in a way that the output become
something that the user wants to see.
Uh so for that uh while there are
actually lots of the techniques for that
I mainly basically introduced like those
three categories and the first thing was
basically about some kind of like
manipulation of the the core and the the
attention and for that actually there
are some kind of some engineering the
idea in terms of how we can basically
manipulate some kind of the some
intermittent layers of the neuronet
network or how we can also manipulate
the output of the neuronet network uh in
terms of like those things. Uh so those
are the cases that we can provide some
kind of the direct and the strongly
guidance. Obviously the problem is that
there's no theoretical explanation for
this and also it can be only applicable
to the very specific cases for the some
giving some special guidance for the
images can be extended to the other data
model as well but this was kind of the
case. So we started to discuss some kind
of the slightly more kind of the some uh
different way which is having some kind
of the more theoretical explanation and
why we titled this as kind of the
gradient ascent from the future reward
actually the things that we discussed
last time was basically about the
inverse problems right uh so the inverse
problem was defined in this way
basically given some kind of the uh here
basically given the observation d y here
has some kind of a mapping function the
a here. How can he generate the x that
can satisfy this formulation in terms of
that the y the the x is aligned with the
the observation the y we have given this
formulation right for those kind of the
some the inverse of the problems. Oh
yeah. So the problem becomes like know
how we can basically model this kind of
the conditional score here. So this is
basically what we want to compute right
given the condition dy how we can
compute the score for the the xt and
then using the base rule actually what
we could see is that this marginal score
is basically something that we are
predicting using the neuron net right
and basically then we need to basically
compute this kind of some sort of the
offset into the our score which is now
defined as kind of the uh the other way
of the the conditional score basically
the y conditioned XT right so it became
basically all the way to basically uh
how we going to model basically this the
conditional score uh without having any
kind of the extra the training of the
deficiency model and for that we briefly
discuss some kind of the two ideas uh
especially for the case that when you
assume that uh the inverse problem is
basically defined as kind of a linear
function like this then we could
basically derive that this conditional
square term here could be basically
computed it in this way with some kind
of some parameters the R here which was
the case that we are computing the
pseudo inverse of the A and this could
be further the simplified uh when you
have some kind of the even more some
kind of the crude the approximation in
terms like approximating this
conditional distribution into this way
into the this Gaussian distribution.
Obviously this would not be a simple the
gaussian distribution but the benefit of
having this kind of the simple the
approximation is that now we can simply
model the condition square as kind of
the gradient of the L2 loss this way. So
this was kind of like one uh simple very
convenient way uh that we are modeling
the condition score and in a way that we
can inject some kind of the some the
guidance at the the test time
and basically also changing this score
function uh using this term uh could be
basically uh rewritten in our the
generation the process in terms of
basically not changing this core here
the noise here but instead of basically
modifying the final uh the sample at
each step. So once we basically compute
the next the sample basically having the
xt minus one by just like having this
kind of like one step of the back
propagation we could basically update
the xt minus one which was basically
equivalent with basically modifying the
uh the noise term the the there so this
was basically the b idea and also the
good thing of like having this kind of
the idea is that uh while it was kind
like derive some kind of some
formulations. Uh in terms of the
implementation, this is like really
simple just literally just adding like
one line of the code uh into the your
generation the pipeline uh in terms of
that we are basically injecting some
kind of the guidance uh in terms of that
the final output should basically match
the observation that we have. So I
strongly recommend you to try uh this
with your own diffusion model uh in
terms of the whatever kind of some kind
of guidance we can do
and the also the interesting aspect
might be that uh these are all the kind
of the formulation based on the uh this
could the time the space the
formulations of different models right
uh based on the DDPM deformation but we
also discussed that actually there's the
corresponding the content this time the
uh deformation as well right so this is
exactly the same thing that we have seen
uh in the uh the SD deformation so when
the reverse SD is basically defined in
this way uh I'm just like introducing
some kind of the new term here which is
nothing but just like this entirely part
then what we have seen in terms of
basically uh reinterpreting the
generation the process of diffusion
model is that actually the reverse
process of diffusion model could be
interpreted in this way in terms like
just like solving this SD with the time
domain the discretization and for that
basically the whole process could be
considered basically computing the score
and this term and just like know
computing the XT minus the delta t in
this way so this is basically the same
deformation uh but as seeing that as
kind of the discrete the time domain the
discretization of the SD deformation
Then basically what you can see is that
uh here we are seeing basically how we
can compute uh so here the x t minus one
by updating it uh with this kind of like
ext the additional derm here right so
the same thing also can be considered in
the sda formulation as well.
So can you briefly
uh write down in terms like how is the
reverse process of the uh the DPS uh can
be computed also using the reverse SD as
well.
So basically the question is that when
you think about this whole process in
terms of adding this kind of the some
the guidance into the the sampling of
the XT minus one uh how can you
basically write the formulation for the
same thing but based on the reverse SD
deformulation.
So for the reverse SD we are basically
having those kind of the two steps
right. So this is kind of some
simplified form of the the generation
here right should be uh exactly the same
thing.
But if we basically inject this kind of
the usually the guidance into the uh
continuous SD
uh what should it look like?
Did you finish?
I mean this is basically nothing but
exactly the same thing, right? Um
basically once we basically compute
basically sample the XT minus the delta
t here uh we just need to do some kind
of the update uh based on the the
gradient of the out loss here. So
basically the same thing basically can
be seen uh in the continuous time domain
there as well. But uh but here basically
some bunch of the questions is that uh
then can you apply the same idea into
the OD formulation as well? What do you
think?
What if we apply the same idea into the
not the SD but into the OD formulation?
Any thoughts?
So actually I recommend you to try this
yourself. So that's why we also having
the kind of the team project you know
you can uh play with those kind of
things. I strongly recommend you to try
this with the both the SD and the OD
formulation. Uh
there is no reason not to work. It
should work. I mean I guess with the OD
formulation is be basically exactly the
same. uh but basically both for the SD
and the OD formulations there might be
some kind of the some practical the some
kind of the things uh some issues. So
basically as you can see this is like
all uh basically when you solve this
like OD and the SD formulation we might
need to have some kind of the
discretization of the time domain right.
So how many steps should we take in
terms like adding injecting this kind of
noise. Uh would it be better to have
some more number of time steps or the
fewer number of time steps?
any
I mean whatever we see this kind of the
SD formulation or uh sorry this the DDP
formulation uh would it be better to
have some kind of the more the number of
the time steps or the few number of the
time steps
no ideas
I mean obviously it'd be better to have
some more number of the the time steps
because then uh when we can inject
inject this kind of some additional
score the more the number of times.
Right? So as you basically inject this
kind of this core and the more and more
uh that gives some kind of the more the
guidance towards to going to the final
the output that we want to see right
uh then this question uh the basically
the the question becomes that you know
then there is basically some kind of the
tradeoff right uh because like as we
want to basically guide the trajectory
of the the generation the the the
basically the pass into the like going
to the something that we want to
uh it be basically better to have some
kind of more the number of the time
steps which means that the generation
becomes like slower right so that's kind
of the some sort of the downside when he
basically injected this kind of a
guidance uh only at the the test time uh
things without having kind of any
training. So if we want to uh take the
both the advantages in terms of the
acceleration and also adding this kind
of the the guidance that we might need
to have some kind of the training the
scheme as well right the training time
to basically incorporate this kind of
the additional the guidance.
But the equation also might be is that
uh if we basically uh instead of like
taking the not the many the time steps
but few number of the the time steps but
if we basically increase uh these kind
of the the weight uh for the additional
the score then what would happen?
So you can basically play with those
kind of thing, right? Uh you can either
basically increase the number of the
time steps or decrease the number of
time steps but just like increase this
weight here, right? Basically this
basically involves some kind of the
usual parameter that we can choose.
We can also think about like the meaning
of like know increasing the weight here
based on the formulations that we have
uh that will basically become some kind
of even the worst the approximation.
So basically what we typically see uh
when you basically increase the weight
here is that uh we're going to see some
kind of the output that is basically
aligned with some kind of the given the
condition the observation here uh but
there is like more chance that the
output will become unrealistic
uh I mean even without seeing any kind
of deformation basically what you can
basically imagine is that as we have
some kind of the bigger the addition of
the score here the xt or the xus Tus one
there will be will go to some kind of
the region that is basically becoming
some kind of intermediate sample that
the neuronet uh haven't seen uh during
the training. So the noise prediction
will basically become the noisier
basically not the uh the accurate noise
which means that the the trajectory will
go into some kind of the direction that
the finally the output become some kind
of the unrealistic the data point while
the output would be more aligned with
some kind of the G given the usual the
condition.
So there might be some kind of the
tradeoff in terms of that how we can
make some kind of the realistic the
output while also satisfying the given
the condition. Uh so many of the failure
the cases for those kind of the
inference time the guidance is that
either the output does not really
satisfy the condition that we are
providing or the output becomes like
unrealistic while satisfying the
condition that we are providing. So how
we basically control those kind of the
usual parameters and also the number of
time steps in a way that satisfies
basically the both things uh is kind of
the one of the critical part uh in the
infra time the the guidance
make sense.
So this is really easy to try. Uh while
we are not having any kind of assignment
for this, I strongly recommend you to
just implement this uh with your the
code for the assignment one, two or
three. uh literally just like adding one
line of the code into the the the
generation the pipeline then you'll see
that it can it plays some role in terms
of giving some the the guidance but it
may may not be that easy in terms of
basically getting some realistic the
output while still satisfying the
condition.
Any questions on this?
So this is basically relatively well
known the techniques in terms of
basically how we can uh as some kind of
the inference time some kind of user
guidance uh in the generation the
process of the deep and deploy models
and the topics that I'm going to mainly
introduce for today are basically some
more advanced way more advanced
techniques and I don't think that we're
going to have time to basically discuss
all the details for that. So I'm going
to uh focus more on basically giving
some kind of the high level ideas uh for
those kind of the the techniques
and also the context as well basically
why we discuss those kind of inference
time the scaling the idea uh because
actually this is kind of the trend not
only for the diffusion and the flow
models but uh you know more the broader
the genative AI the kind of the
techniques uh especially for them uh we
already seeing some kind of the many
techniques uh for the test times Kelly.
Uh so I guess most of you would know
this person.
Do you know? Yes. No, we don't care.
So this is the Iliad who is the one of
the co-founder of the OpenAI. uh and
actually if you uh are interested in
like reading some of the papers about
different flow models then you'll
actually see that the co-ound of the
open AI is actually one of the authors
of the many uh important papers about
deep flow models this is quite
interesting right uh so even uh if you
see the for example the consist the
consistency the models is also the the
paper having the the skipers like as the
one of the authors
So anyway, so he's uh many kind of like
know talking of like many things about
the AGI uh and one of the things that he
was talking uh even like one year before
uh was about the end of the era uh of
the the pre-training. So basically the
claim is that uh for especially for the
NRM we already used all the data that we
can use everything that you know there
exist in the internet. So uh since we
already used like all the data that we
used uh even when you basically scale up
whatever kind of things in the training
time whatever we scale up the basically
this uh the the size of the neuron net
and also the computation time in the
training uh the performance gain that
we're going to get uh by spending more
compute uh in the training time would be
quite limited
like this. So here the basic idea is
that uh instead of like spending more
compute in the training time uh can you
basically make some kind of the bigger
the improvement in the the performance
by spending more compute uh in the test
time as well. So that was kind of the
big topic over the the year this year
and we already have seen lots of some
kind of good examples for that. uh this
is uh already like it has been a while I
guess the one or the 03 have been
introduced last year or something right
now even we are seeing the GPD5 and the
many recent the models and the kind of
the the shocking thing at the time like
when you see the the 01 and especially
the O3 was that uh there was some kind
of the measure of like measuring the AI
kind of things like how much the uh the
populace of the LRM is close to the
human understanding there was some kind
of the benchmark for that and before the
uh some kind of the previous some kind
of previous models the AI score was like
very low like like something like the uh
10% or the 20% uh but when we see start
to see the O3 here the ages I score uh
exceeded uh the score of the 88 which is
like huge jump uh from here right uh and
this was basically the case that uh the
the the the open model started to spend
some kind of the more time in the the
test time. So if you basically uh also
click something like the thinking model
in the GPT now then it will basically
take some more time uh to improve the
answer. So that's the basic idea for the
test time scaling by expanding the more
computing the test time how we are going
to basically improve the the output of
the generative the AI the the
techniques.
So the open the O1 and the O3 were
basically very representative the case
in terms of the how we can basically
improve the performance of the uh direct
models by spending more compute in the
test time
and also we have seen some kind of the
another good example the only this year
uh do you know the deepse
does everyone know how deepsek work?
No. Yes. Is it too a simple question?
What happens? I mean deepseek was quite
famous early this year, right? Uh and
the basic idea for the deepse I mean the
R1D model basically here. I mean
obviously there are lots of things to
discuss for in terms of deep models but
the one of the main ideas for the deepse
R1D model was basically having this kind
of the thinking process. So it's
basically not just like outputting some
kind of the final kind of things but let
the LM to produce some kind of the some
intermediate tokens uh in the thinking
kind of the phase in terms of that uh
mimicking some kind of differently
thinking the process uh making some kind
of all the intermediate things. Uh so
this aha moment was quite famous in
terms of that the even the deepse is
fixing some of the errors uh in the
previous thinking the process.
So this was basically all the kind of
the basic idea in terms of that how we
can uh basically improve the outputs of
the models by spending the compute not
only in the training time uh but also in
the the test time. So and this like the
in the add side many people are saying
that this is kind of the future
direction uh in terms of improving the
quality of the outputs. So regarding the
test time the skilling I'd like to
recommend you to uh watch this video uh
it's an explanation from the dand which
was the uh the engineer in the open AI.
So let me briefly play this.
Well let's to imagine now let's do a
thought experiments. Who does thought
experiments? Albert Einstein. So let's
do a thought experiment about Einstein.
Um, and let's imagine we go back to 1907
before he started working on general
relativity. And we asked him the final
exam question for general relativity.
Uh, GBT4.5 actually made this up, but I
can verify that this is a valid sort of
question that you might ask. And you
know, we're open AI, so we wouldn't ask
Einstein. We'd ask Einstein B1907-
super-
how, you know, to make sure we get
maximum reasoning effort and and maximum
effort we would get. So Einstein, I
guess, he's he's a visual thinker.
something about elevators in freef fall.
This is when you study gr you learn
about this and you do some calculations
and um there's the rubber sheet in the
ball and he got looks like he got
distracted about quantum mechanics for a
bit. Our models get distracted too.
There we go. That looks like a you know
starting to get to a black hole. I also
don't know why he thinks about himself
in all these scenarios. And there we go.
That's that's like the sort of black
hole thing I was going for with the
wormhole. That's the right answer. Uh
turns out GPD 4.5 couldn't get this
right answer. we needed 03 uh 03 was
able to get it. I think my role at
OpenAI is mostly just checking physics
calculations rather than AI research.
But okay, the point is though it gets
the right answer or Einstein would get
the right answer and it would take him
about eight years and to solve a problem
or what I'm saying is that you know he
would discover and this is what happened
eight years later he discovered general
relativity he'd be able to answer this
question. So our models think for a
minute now and they can reproduce
textbook calculations and and
perturbations thereof but like we want
them to like make major contributions to
the state of human knowledge in science.
So
um coming back to this plot uh how do we
get there? Well now let's focus on the
left plot. Um the performance of the
model improves the more we train it. And
the sort of training we do is is RL or
reinforcement learning. And so the main
thing that I want to communicate in this
talk is that we want to scale that up.
Uh uh a year ago we put out GP40. There
was uh compute used and all pre-trained
compute and as you can imagine then we
started doing this thing that led to
test time compute. So we we added some
reinforcement learning comput RL compute
for 01. I should say this is all cartoon
but uh you know directionally it's
correct. 03 maybe had a little bit more
RL compute.
at some point in the future maybe we'll
have a lot of RL compute and then at
some far point in the future maybe we'll
have just like totally dominated and
crushed by by RL comput and this so like
this is this is I think it's kind of a
contrarian point of view like this is
this is where we're going uh and we we
mean it uh to to point to emphasize sort
of the contrarian nature of this uh this
is somebody who followed AI research
this is a slide that Yan Makun made some
some number of years ago I guess 2019
based um the copyright um that that I
borrow you know I borrow this from
obviously um this is a complicated slide
that's hard to maybe hard to follow
luckily we have models that can
summarize things for us uh the point is
that pre-training is like this big cake
reinforcement learning is supposed to be
like this little cherry on top and and
uh you know that's that's basically what
what this this plot was um the color
scheme actually was accidental but I
think it actually works quite quite
Uh
>> so yeah here the basically idea is that
you know basically this guy wants to
explain like how the GPT can solve the
problem in we needs the problem that the
Einstein was solving for the eight
years. Uh so this is all based on some
kind of the RL based some kind of the uh
some kind of the test time is killing in
terms of having some kind of the more in
compute uh in the test time. So as also
then briefly explained here uh this kind
of test time the skilling the idea is
based on the some reinforcement
learning. uh so and we going to briefly
talk about this without having getting
into any details for that but as you can
see uh if you see some kind of the more
the recent models uh even when you try
the GPT the five for now there will be
some kind of the more the thinking the
phase right the thinking the model and
if you click that it'll take some more
time to provide the the kind of the
output uh this is all involving some
kind of the test time basically uh in
terms of like improving the output in
the the test time uh based on the more
compute uh at the test time. So the
topic that I'm going to briefly talk
about today is that how we can also
apply the same the idea uh not for the
authority models typically used for the
NM but also for the diffusion and the
flow models that we are discussing here.
uh if you are also more interested in
the uh test time the killing the idea uh
there's some kind of the uh some sort of
the survey paper which is talking about
lots of the the techniques for that uh
so check this out so there are also lots
of kind of the things you can try
uh so one kind of a side note is that so
what I basically also heard is that if
you do some kind of the if you see some
kind of research groups working on the
admite Especially for these days uh they
are not really focusing on just making
developing some some single the
technique or just like making some kind
of the papers here. uh they focus more
on basically how to start up uh in terms
like making some kind of a new uh
there's model that can outperform uh
many existing the models but I'm not
sure how this will be kind of promising
the directions but the thing is that uh
after we start to see some kind of more
the technique for the test time scaling
uh this is basically not about basically
how we going to uh use the tones of the
GPUs and handle like lots of the data to
make some kind of the big uh the level
or some big model. It's more about
basically having some kind of the some
smarty techniques that can be also
working with some way fewer normal GPUs
as well compared to the some kind of
train the time the compute right. Uh so
basically this here the hope is that uh
we even with some kind of the much
smaller the amount of the the computing
resource uh even at the the test time by
applying those kind of the techniques uh
we can make some kind of the much
further the improvement uh in the test
time. So this basically motivates kind
of like many people uh to think about
making some kind of uh developing those
kind of techniques and also thinking
about uh starting up uh in terms of
basically beating the the performance of
the many uh existing models. So this is
kind of I think this is quite
interesting direction in terms like how
we can uh what basically we can do uh
even with some kind of the much smaller
the amount of the computing the resource
uh not with some kind of the training uh
the from scratch like those kind of the
models but with some kind of the some
test time kind of things. So this is
kind of the um the direction
and the while there are also as you can
see there are lots of some kind of the
some the techniques for the test time
the scaling uh the but the very basic
idea for the many things the things for
the uh the test time the the scaling is
that we are basically having the
proposer and the verifier. So this
sounds like we are going back to the den
framework right. So actually the
proposer basically means the our
pre-trained uh the JD model and the
verifier is kind of the another model it
can be a neuron network some kind of the
just some kind of the code whatever kind
of things in terms like just really
verifying whether the output from the
proposer is kind of the good or the bad.
uh then based on this kind of the uh the
verifier uh so we can basically guide uh
the the proposer
or we can consider bally selecting uh
some of the good outputs after making
the proposer to basically propose like
multiple the outputs. So that's kind of
the very the high level the idea in
terms of the test and the scaling. So
we're going to get into slightly more
details for that
and at the very beginning what I'm going
to uh introduce here is that how we can
also interpret the idea that we have
seen for the deepest case uh solving the
inverse problem uh in the context of
that know we are having the leode
function.
So basically we can uh interpret this
kind of the the concept of the having
the proposer and the verifier as
basically having some kind of the
pre-trained uh the genetic model. So in
our case that would be diffusion model
and also having some kind of the reward
function. So this reward function is
basically uh giving some kind of the
guidance uh about some kind of usually
the preference. So when you have some
kind of the some final the output the
realistic the data point uh if this like
function the output is basically high
that means that is like more aligned
into the the usual preference and if the
function basically the low which means
that the output is not really aligned
with the usual preference. So we are
basically assuming kind of the case that
know we have this kind of the some le
function that's basically giving some
kind of the the notion of the usual
preference as kind of the some the some
continuous and the differentiable the
function
and what would be such kind of the case
that we can assume some kind of
function.
You can also think about many examples
for that right. Um so basically for any
case when you have any sort of some
differentiable some discriminative D
model uh giving some kind of a score for
the output uh we can consider this is
basically define some kind of the world
function here right and also what you
can see is that the inverse problem the
cases that we have seen last time is
kind of the some special case of the uh
having those kind like function because
we can always bally define our reward
function like this right so the minus of
the L2 loss basically as the L2 loss is
basically small uh is increasing the
reward function right uh when the L2
loss is high which means it's like
decreasing the function so the all the
cases like the inversity problem can be
considered as kind of the some special
case or like the cases like making some
sort of the reward function.
So this is really kind of the generality
framework that can be applied to the
many applications into the also to the
many the modalities as well uh for not
only for the images and the videos that
we have seen multiple times but also for
the many other the cases uh even that I
don't know well but for example for
those kind of the motion generation uh
what we can do is that we can uh guide
this kind of demotion in a way that it
should basically avoid those kind of
collision to some kind of object in the
scene. So if we somehow define some
reward function that is basically
avoiding those kind of collision to the
given some kind of the object that can
be used to this kind of the some
trajectory like basically making the
motion avoiding those kind of the
collision to the kind of given things
and also for the many other some kind of
the the science problems that I'm not
the expert for that uh but for example I
put some kind of the molecule generation
for many kind of things uh we might want
to make some kind of the some molecules
some sort of the graph structure while
satisfying some kind of condition. I
don't know I heard that there are some
kind of questions like you know we have
some kind of the existing some kind of
the molecular structure and we want to
make another the molecular structure
which can be have some kind of the
docking point with some kind of existing
the molecule. So those will be some kind
of the condition that we want to satisfy
right for those kind of the cases if we
can uh define some kind of d function
then we can also consider those are some
the the cases that we can apply the same
technique.
So there are actually lots of some of
those kind of the applications. uh if
you are also working on some specific
applications with the different flow
models then you can also consider uh
finding such kind of the problems that
you can easily define some kind of
reward function.
So here the basic thing is that given
this kind of the reward function uh how
we can provide some kind of the guidance
uh in the uh generation the process
actually see what I'm going to show is
that uh the things that I'm going to
explain here the from the next slide uh
is eventually will be exactly the same
uh with the DPS formulation. So this is
basically all about how we can basically
interpret the same thing uh from the
different perspective again. Okay.
So uh I'm not going to get into any the
details for the kind of the RL
deformation but this is actually based
on some kind of the RL kind of
literature but without like with any
kind of the some background for that uh
basically what we can see is that uh
actually now we want to sample some kind
of the final data point not from the
original data distribution the P 0 but
let's say like we are define some kind
of the new data distribution uh in this
way as some kind of the output of some
kind of the maximization the program. So
this is basically the some kind of the
red defined uh the data distribution and
we want to sample from here and how we
define this is that basically this is
defined as kind of solution of like this
maximization the problem. So basically
what we can see is that we want to
define some kind of the new distribution
the p 0 this time here in a way that uh
that becomes close to the our original
uh the distribution while also basically
maximizing the reward the expected value
of the the reward. So when you basically
sample from the new distribution uh the
rewards for those kind of samples should
be the maximized right. So this is
already showing some kind of the
tradeoff between how much the the uh the
new distribution would be close to the
uh the original distribution and also
how much the the samples from the new
distribution will be maximizing the
reward. So as I also mentioned from the
DPS case uh as we just try to maximize
li more and more and more uh it might be
the case that we are debating more from
the given the original distribution
right but if we just simply sample from
the given distribution then we might
also have some of the cases that the
samples are basically not having the
high reward. So given this kind of the
trade-off we are finding some kind of
the new uh the
data design here in terms like uh
finding some kind of a sweet spot with
some kind of the weight here. So it's
basically matter of like know how much
we are going to maximize the reward with
the samples from the new data the
distribution while basically not being
uh debated too much from the given the
original data distribution
just like the we defining the the
distribution in this way. So the thing
is that now we want to sample the final
data point not from the here uh but from
the here from the P the the star
and if we simplify this uh while
skipping some details here actually this
formulation of the P 0 D star can be
rewritten in this way with some kind of
the complexity formulation the Z0 here
actually it can be simplified in this
way having some kind of reward function
and also the weight
Uh and actually if you are familiar with
some kind of daily personal learning
anyone who took the auto course before
no
uh so yeah so that's why I say that I'm
going to not getting into any kind of
details for the reinforcement learning
but if you take the the RLD course for
now actually you're going to see that uh
many techniques especially this many
recent techniques are bas based on
exactly the same information uh but for
the the training not for some those kind
of test time kind of things. So this is
basically exactly uh the same thing that
we are seeing some kind of the uh
literature of the reinforcement
learning.
So what the thing is that uh we are
basically using some kind of the uh the
diffusion model which means that we're
going to have some kind of the
intermediate the the data points in the
the the noing step right. So then what
we also need to do is that we also need
to uh know the distribution for the not
for the final the output but also for
the intermediate data point as well as I
said like for the diffusion flow model
especially the diffusion model
everything is about computing the score
function right it's all about the score
uh which means that we first need to
know the uh the uh the probability
distribution for the all the
intermediate data point and the purpose
of having this would be obviously would
is to compute this curve function,
right? Uh and also while skipping some
all the details here.
So what we can see is that the uh
probably distribution for the
intermediate data point XT is also
defined in this way. So you can see that
this looks quite similar uh with the
distribution for the final output here.
So here we had that the leode function
for the x0 the clean data point we are
simply replacing this uh as kind of the
value function here. Uh so the this v
function here that satisfies like this
is called the optimal value function
and so I'm going to skip some details
here. So the problem is that uh while
it's relatively like easier to basically
derive this form basically except for
like this zero actually having this is
kind of really kind of the something
that we can compute right the problem is
that for the the distribution for the
intermediate the data points
there is no basically analytic form for
those kind of debris function here. uh
so there's no way to basically we can uh
precisely compute uh this kind of the
the this like debrief function here
which means that uh we also need to have
some kind of the approximation again so
if we follow like what we have done for
the uh the DPSD case uh we are also
going to have some kind of the some
similar some sort of recruit the
approximation in terms like
approximating this value function uh
using the tweet modeler in the rect and
you can see that actually this really
basically um
follows like know how we defined the uh
the the new distribution here uh for the
new distribution for the final output
here uh it was basically the word for
the final output the x0 uh and we are
mimicking this in terms of then now we
are computing the reward for the
expected the output from the xt
uh so that can be kind of the uh can be
considered some kind of good
approximation for the optimal deb
function and you can see that this is
quite similarly like what we have done
for the DPS case right we also need to
basically approximate the score function
of the xt with the score function with
the x0 right using the the twis so doing
the kind of the same thing uh in this
the other based deformation
and the good thing that you know we are
approximating the opt optimal DV value
function into this form is that now we
can compute the score function right. So
as you know like this is like all about
computing score. uh the computing score
is basically made up of like computing
the gradient of the log of the
probability and now we know the uh the
discipline here and if we compute the
gradient of the log of like this one
then what we can see is that actually
this becomes equivalent with basically
having the original score here
and plus some kind of the additional
term uh which is basically defined as
kind of the gradient of the expected the
future reward uh the view of
competitively the expected output.
Make sense? Then what actually we can
see is that uh in the continuous
deformation uh that becomes the same
thing like with this.
So last time actually we have seen that
the inverse problem can be seen as like
define the reward function as kind of
the minus of the outer loss right. So if
you plug that the minus of the L2 loss
then actually you can see that this
becomes exactly the same formulation
with the DPS formulation that we have
seen.
So this is basically
kind of the another way to basically uh
having some interpreting the formulation
of the DPS DPS not based on the uh the
DDPM deformation uh based on but
basically some more like RL style kind
of deformations.
Uh make sense?
So yeah, I skipped some like the the
details here, but uh here the basic idea
is that we explicitly basically
introduce this kind of the trade-off
between the like the word maximization
and also the deviation from the original
the uh the data distribution. So based
on those kind of the trade-off we
basically introduced introduce a new
data distribution here P 0 da uh and
then the problem becomes like you know
how we can sample from that right and
based on the formulation for the new uh
the data distribution. What we just need
to do is that we just need to derive the
uh distribute for the intermedata point
of the xt here
and then also approximate the optimal
value function in this way. I mean there
can be multiple other ways even you can
consider training another neuronet to
learn this. Actually there really some
kind of be some approach for that. Uh
which is basically not uh stable some
kind of reasons. Uh but so this is kind
of like some simple way to approximate
the optimal deb function. uh and based
on this approximation. The good thing is
that now we can simply compute uh this
score in this way and we can say that
this becomes basically uh equivalent in
terms of basically having the original
score plus some kind of some additional
score which is now computed as the
gradient of the uh expected the the
future reward and that becomes basically
identical uh with the the formulation
that we have seen uh in the deepest
case. So I'm just like introducing this
in terms of that there are also kind of
the multiple ways to basically interpret
the same thing uh from the different
perspectives. So you can see that this
is another kind of the way to uh derive
the depacity formulation this way. Any
questions on this?
So if I issue some kind of the more
applications like based on this uh do
you have any kind of the ideas in terms
like what you can do with this kind of
the idea uh using for your team project
or for any other things given any kind
of some pre-trained the model that can
there is some kind of some realistic
data points what kind of some sort of
the guidance we can try to add
to make something
So basically the examples that also I
have shown last time uh were all about
basically were the
image the generation the image models
right and also how about how we can make
some kind of some specific the types of
images based on the pre-trained uh image
generated models
But actually also something that I'm
going to introduce uh today and also the
Wednesday as well are also about how we
can make something uh the new in terms
of that that's not something can be
directly generated from the pre model.
So for example like given some kind of
the pre-trained uh like image the model
how can it generate something more than
images. So those are also some kind of
the interesting questions.
So one kind of the uh example for that
uh is basically also uh that some like
some applications here is that uh we can
also do some kind of the make some kind
of the more than the images using the
print image the genetic models uh
something like the 3D or some kind of
some panoramic images. So for example
like uh one thing that I'd like to show
is that uh if you see some kind of the
many pre-trained uh image diffusion
models including the model that you are
also using for your the team project uh
you'll see that those models are
basically generating some kind of the
images in the certain resolution like
512 by the 512 or some kind of into the
certain resolution. So here the question
is that uh what if we want to make some
kind of the uh images in the much bigger
size or some kind of the random ratio or
some kind of some more like panoramic
images or some 360 images or the many
other things.
Uh for that like the obviously the kind
of the best idea might be is that we are
just training another the diffusion
model for that. uh but one kind of the
idea uh in terms like making some uh
random size kind of the images using the
pre-trend model is that uh we are
performing the diffusion process uh
simultaneously uh from the different
kind of the perspectives.
So this is kind of like one example that
we having some kind of the big canvas uh
for the image for the panorama image
degeneration and we are basically
dividing this big space uh into the
sumless piece where basically we can
directly generate images using the
pre-trained model. So let's say this is
the size uh that has been used to train
the pre uh the diffusion model and we
want to generate some kind of the much
bigger image like this and what we do is
that we are basically making uh some
kind of the bunch of the windows like
this box with some kind of the loss of
the overs here. Then the question
becomes like we are performing uh the
generation the process uh on the this
kind of the multiple those kind of the
some small discurses while making the uh
this over regions to share exactly the
same thing
uh make sense. So every time when you
perform the generation the process uh
through the inside this like the
multiple boxes uh we perform the process
like in parallel uh while just like
ensuring that the the over region here
uh basically shares the exactly the same
thing.
Can you define the reward function for
this
overlap?
Yes, I mean we can come up with some
kind of function for that, right? I mean
we can compute the 2D for the both of
the the part and making the TDs uh the
the over region uh here becomes the same
right we can just define some kind of L2
loss or we can uh use some kind of the
predefined some kind of style loss uh
even to match this tile across the all
the kind of the windows here. So this is
kind of some simple the idea right I
mean we can apply those things into make
some kind of some good panorama images
like this. So these are all kind of
examples like making some panorama
images based on this idea without having
any kind of the new diffusion model or
the flow models for that
and the same thing also can be applied
to the uh some make some kind of a 360
images as well. Obviously there will be
some kind of loss of some kind of the
implementation the details in terms of
how to achieve some kind of best quality
but I'm just like giving you some kind
of some ideas in how we can apply the
same idea to make some many other things
and also the same idea can be applied
not to make some kind of some 2D things
but also the 3D things as well. So if
you are not familiar with some kind of
some graphics kind of a vision uh kind
of the researcher but even without that
basically the thing is that here we want
to add some kind of some color
information defined on the over the
surface here. Uh while we only have the
image diffusion model. Uh for those kind
of cases what we can do is that we are
basically what we want to generate is
some kind of the color information over
the surface here.
But the thing is that we only have some
kind of the some we only have the
diffusion model that can produce some
kind of the some projected images here.
Now we can apply the same idea in terms
of that when you basically sort of do
the reverse of the projection projecting
2D things over the 3D surface uh into
the multiple diffuse we want to make the
overlap over the 3D regions uh to be the
exactly the same. So we can basically
apply the same idea in terms like making
some uh 3D the textures as well. So we
can also make those kind of things in
terms of adding some kind of colors over
the surface uh by having those kind of
some uh synchronization the idea.
So basically I recommend you to try to
consider those kind of some kind of
reward function that can make some kind
of the many new things uh giving you
some kind of the ideas like what you can
do with the pre-trended models. So
actually for those kind of the
synchronization the the easiest way to
perform this is basically exactly the
same thing with the kind of deepest kind
of things. Uh but we can do even like
the easier way in terms of that we first
basically sample the all the XT here
uh in the some kind of the the space
that we call as the instance space and
then project all the things into the
canonical space. This is the real space
that we are generating kind of the data
points and here uh we just make the
toidities uh to be basically exactly the
same in the over region basically
modifying the the tweet and then based
on that we also update the kind of the
xt minus one for the all the instant
spaces. So we can apply the same idea
and actually this simple the idea has
lots of the applications some
interesting some applications. Uh have
you heard about the ambiguous images
some kind of cute examples?
Uh here this is now oil painting of the
people here and if you flip it becomes
the oil painting of the old man and here
the painting of the house plants. And
after some flipping it becomes a
painting of the Einstein. So it's
basically about making some kind of the
images that can have some two or
multiple different kind of the meanings
uh depending on some kind of a
transformation that you applying to the
image.
Some interesting examples uh for those
kind of the cases. Uh can you see how
you can define the canonical space and
the instance spaces?
Yeah, those kind of the outputs can be
uh generated using the exactly the same
idea depending on how we define the
kinical space and the instance spaces
and so some kind of the some function.
Uh another
similar example
infinite zooming in of the images.
Yeah. So let me play this again.
Starting from the image of the galaxy
and getting into
the plate here and all the way to the
some details into the some what's that
some kind of the some some buildings
there. Uh interesting.
So this is actually kind of a video
right. uh but this is also created using
the pre-traint uh immediate model and
can you see basically how you can
basically generate those kind of things
so it's basically having some kind of
the more details uh into the similar
division right so it's also matter of
like how we define some kind of this uh
instance the spaces for each of the
level and and also doing some kind of
the some synchronization
some other examples Okay. Yeah.
Uh obviously for those kind of things
there are some kind of more some details
in the implementation in terms like to
achieve some kind of the best quality.
But I'm just giving you some kind of
examples like what you can do with the
this kind of the some test time kind of
scaling things and also for the motion
generation what we can also do is that
for some kind of the pre model they can
make some kind of the short uh the time
the sequence of the the motions we can
make it the longer in terms of basically
uh somehow combining the multiple the
short motions into the the long motions
while making the transition to be smooth
uh using this kind of some synchronizing
detecting. So those are some kind of
also the all the applications in terms
like what we can do with some kind of
the greater scent from the future
result.
So uh compared to the the previous
technique as I also mentioned last time
the good thing for this is that this is
really some kind of the uh some kind of
some degenerative technique that has
some loss of some broad applications for
whatever the cases like when you define
some kind of the differentiable function
uh you can try to apply this technique
while there might be some kind of some
details in terms how we can achieve some
kind of best quality. uh one kind of the
downside uh for this uh is that uh
actually the real kind of the downside
is that there can be some failure cases
that's kind of the one thing and also
the other the kind of the big downside
is that the reward function should be
differentiable because we are performing
the gradient descent and gradient ascent
in this case right uh so one more kind
of things that I'm going to briefly
mention uh today is that how we can also
apply the kind of the same the idea uh
for the cases that we are not having the
uh differentiable delivered function but
also for the non- differentiable
delivered function and this is kind of
the most general kind of the technique.
So if I go briefly uh with this kind of
things that if we go back to the the
idea of the test time scaling for the
add so this was basically the case that
we are having the proposer and the
verifier.
So if we really think about some kind of
pre-trained the L&Ms uh I mean
pre-trained the proposer and some kind
of the existing debier uh what would be
kind of the best way to I mean some
simplest way to basically achieve some
kind of the better the outputs by
spending more compute at the test time
the easiest idea that you can come up
with any any source for that
you might hear about this but I mean
this Even the the easiest kind of the
way if you have any kind of the proposer
and the bay file and if you have
unlimited amount of the GPU the
resources then what are you going to do
to improve the quality of the outputs
you haven't thought about the case that
you have unlimited GPU resour
I mean you have some proposer and the
pay fire and you have the unlimited the
amount of GPS then the easiest way is
that you just like generate lots of
things and just choose the best one. No
that's kind of the uh easiest way. So
you just like run the proposer multiple
times uh with some kind of some
randomness there uh making some kind of
the multiple uh stoastic randomly
outputs or realistic output checking all
of them with your bay fire and picking
the best one
that's kind of the best thing right
actually this is really something that
the your GPT is doing your the Gemini is
many kind of are already doing this kind
of thing uh this is kind of the easiest
way, right? Uh but what also people are
briefly um here the discussing
what now is being discussed for now is
that uh how can you also make this kind
of the process to be more efficient uh
because you still need to basically run
this kind of degeneration process until
the end especially for the add it alo
take lots of time because it's like
really sampling the token uh
sequentially in iterative manner. So
after basically generating all the to
the tokens we'll be able to compute the
reward right but uh what people are
basically talking especially the side is
that uh there might be some cases that
we can introduce the process reward
the meaning of the process reward is
that in the intermediate the the process
of the generation can we still basically
define some kind of the reward for the
intermediate outputs
for example like for some kind of the
math problems when the LM is producing
some kind of the some mass formulations.
We can still check whether the
formulation is correct or not for the
intermediate outputs, right? And also
for the some code uh we can still check
whether the code will basically make
some kind of the compile error or not
with some kind of intermediate outputs
as well. So for those kind of cases uh
when you have some kind of the process
reward uh we can consider uh reverging
this in a way to basically making the
generation the process to be more
efficient which basically means that uh
you know we are basically making
multiple trajectory of the generation
here and based on the uh basically what
the signal that we are getting from the
process reward we can cut each of the
branch right uh if you see that play
this kind of the some trajection the the
the generation the trajectory is kind of
the bad in terms of the our process
reward that we don't need to generate
more right so we cut those kind of
branches and branching out some kind of
the other some more the pro the
promising the branches like this so we
can consider those kind of some more
like uh making those kind of the some
tree structure uh in terms of making the
generation the the process
make sense
I mean simple some engineering the idea
Then the thing is that obviously we can
consider doing the same thing uh for the
diffusion and the flow models diffusion
the degeneration the process is also
iterative process. So we can also do the
same thing basically branching out into
the multiple trajectory and the cutting
kind of things based on like what we
have uh what we have with the process
and continue for the more the promising
the directions.
The same idea also can be applied to the
diffusion and the flow models. But what
would be some kind of the major
difference between the add and also
diffusion models.
So LM the the iterative process of the
LM is basically making every single the
token like some kind of the word in the
the text right the diffusion is
basically the den noising the process
right having the intermediate XT
and what's the difference between the
two
zero ID
so basically for the diffusion model the
intermediate the data points is really
partial the output. We only have the
partial information. We just have some
kind of in the middle like generations
kind of the default sentence and based
on those kind of the some really some
kind of the partial output we need to be
able to define some kind of the real
function.
So there are very specific cases that we
can define some kind of the process
reward. For many of the other cases,
it's even not kind of clear how we can
really define the process revert before
we are seeing some kind of the full the
outputs.
But one small kind of difference between
the edm and the diffusion flow model is
that for the diffusion and the flow
models the intermediate the outputs are
kind of the partial in terms of that
it's kind of some sort of the blurry and
the noisy the outputs but still it's
having the entire the content right and
even we can easily compute the expected
the final output with the one step from
the any intermediate kind of the outputs
right so which means that the way or
like we are defining the process world
can be different in the LM the process
world should be something that we can
really define with some kind of some
partial observation
but for the diffusion the flow model the
way that we are defining the process
reward can be actually things I mean we
can actually consider any the reord
function that we are computing for the
final the output can serve as some kind
of the process reward because we can
always use some kind of the twisted
formula to compute the expected the
final the outputs
So that's kind of some small difference
in terms of basically how we can uh
define the process reward both for the
LM and also the image and the video
generation. uh in terms of that in this
case we don't need to define any kind of
some special the process reward any of
the reward function that we have defined
for the final outputs actually can be
directly employed as our process reward
which sounds like that know uh this is
kind of the much kind of the uh easier
setup uh in terms of applying the uh
test time scaling in like much more the
efficient way
make sense
Great.
So this is kind of the highway the idea
I'm going to uh so there are some kind
of few more things in terms of how we
can bally apply those things
but uh so let me get back to this uh
next Wednesday before we wrap up for
today uh if I briefly introduce so what
we can do uh with those kind of thing is
that so based on the so what we can do
uh with the those kind of this
particular thing the idea is that now we
can use the any of the non-
differentiable function as
So for example uh if you ask uh whatever
the image the generate model to do like
produce image with the the object here
with the exactly the certain amount uh
you're going to see that there are many
kind of the hallucination uh not really
matching the number of the object that
you need to see. Uh so we can basically
make the the number of objects to match
exactly the same some kind of the amount
that we are specifying
and also for the text alignment. Uh now
we see that the text alignment can be
easily done uh with the classifier the
free guidance right uh but still there
are many kind of the cases that the text
alignment is not very accurate uh with
the pre-trained models. So we can
further improve this kind of the
alignment to the text uh with any kind
of some uh the region language model
with some kind of another some kind of
verifier the model. So this also can be
done and also many other things even for
the cases that we need can have some
kind of the different the function we
can also apply the idea of the particle
filtering in a way that we can further
improve this kind of the quality. So if
I show some kind of the interesting
examples like uh here
uh
obviously there will be some kind of the
no realistic images having like four
drums and the seven tomatoes and the 5D
candles right so this is really unusual
the kind of images for those kind of
cases actually we can make some quite
realistic the images like this with some
exact the exact match of the number of
the objects here uh so let me show some
more extremely cases.
Um can you check like whether this image
really have some like 82 blueberries
and also 33 coins for those kind of some
very extremely cases that we want to
exactly match this kind of number of the
objects. uh we can uh use those kind of
the test time this kill scaling the idea
and also we can do many other things for
example um
uh for actually the many cases even when
you try something like this using the
GPT4 or the five or something then you
can see actually there are some kind of
the failure cases not exactly matching
the given the text so this is not the
meaning of like unoccupied chair right
uh but we are basically having those
kind of chair without without the back
part and we can precisely match this
kind of some text description uh using
the test time scaling the idea.
So those are some kind of the
applications for the infant time
discaling. So next Wednesday I'm going
to briefly wrap up uh those things and
also we also briefly discussed the idea
in terms of how we can make something
new some new kind of the modality of
data using some kind of pre-trained the
models uh like making some 3D or the
panoramic images with the uh image
division models right so I'm going to
get into some more the techniques for
that and I'm going to wrap up the course
let's end