Amazing. Great. So, it's great to be
back at Berkeley. There was a
probabilistic trip um which would have
helped me to be in the US today, but
sadly I took it very short last week.
So, I was in the Bay last week, but not
this week. Um so, we'll have to do this
online. Um but yeah, it's great to be
virtually back. Um I have deep roots in
Berkeley as you might know if you know
me for you have known me for a while.
And today I mean this lecture really
will have kind of two parts and it's a
meta lecture in a way. Uh and it's also
kind of selfishly I'm doing this also to
kind of remind I mean first and foremost
um you know people in the field that
lots of ideas recirculate. And so in a
way I I I put together this slide deck
from or I recovered this slide deck from
the Alpha Star project which is like six
six or so years old and realized that
many of the current um issues uh but
also solutions that we're we're using um
in modern LLMs um trace back further be
before but I mean we we did kind of
encounter many of these issues um
ourselves when we work on a fairly
probably our most um advanced even today
especially on video games agent that
deep mind had built at the time and I'll
get into details now in a second um but
it's good useful to revisit kind of
these ideas to to see them with
perspective and also realize what are
the things that we did you know back
then that currently we can't do or we're
not quite doing at the same level right
in in LLM so this lecture will be bit of
a mixture between Alpha Star and also
Gemini and other LLM agents um but with
a kind of hindsight foresight lens which
hopefully you'll find entertaining.
So let's go through a bit of basics. Now
of course I'm sure you've covered many
of these topics and you probably know
them because they become quite
mainstream but indulge me in into giving
you my my own perspective and point of
view. So this is kind of the OG slide or
of of like uh deep mind actually like
the pitch slide deck had a version of
this that did not have Starcraft but it
had agent environment you know agent
with goals observations and actions that
was at the time not that mainstream
right reinforcement learning wasn't
mainstream in in you know when when deep
mind was eventually acquired and also it
serves a little bit to try to put our
heads on what is an agent since this
this class is about agents And I think
today if you if you think if you ask
people like um is this an agent? Is this
an agentic behavior? You'll probably get
quite a few different answers. Back then
things were a bit simpler though. Um we
were mostly connecting to single
environments with wellsp speced and
defined observations and actions, right?
And the agent had just maximized reward
as a goal. Um, of course in games, um,
many times the reward was fully
specified and fairly simple to compute.
And then this was the loop that agents
lived in forever and their goal was to
optimize reward. Now,
you know, today things are a bit
different, right? Like there's besides I
guess having agents in the traditional
sense, we have assistants that assist
users, right? So then what is the
environment? um what are the actions
start to be a bit more diffused and I
think embracing that is fine. Um um this
is probably the most accurate at least
from you know our site perspective of
what we mean by agents right so so you
know you might you might be a user of a
chatbot or um you know advanced system
and you're going to interact with
something right this object uh we can
call this the agent and and as a user
you'll ask questions you'll you know
maybe give feedback etc etc and then
this agent now actually is more complex
in a in a way I think it's more useful
to think about uh the environment being
part of the whole package right so
you'll get sort of an agent harness that
that's controlling how um you call the
LLMs to issue an action or issue a
search or issue a terminal command etc
to this very rich environment that could
be a you know a digital computer uh a
network of computers it could be
anything it could be a game of course as
well right very general um and then you
know there's that's kind of how we
orchestrate the whole thing right so
it's doesn't quite fit the paradigm um
as neatly um but that doesn't that
actually thinks makes it more exciting
so sometimes when I'm presenting some of
the results and observations you know
especially from alphaar it's going to
become come from a more simplistic world
where single environment clearly defined
um and no user so to speak so the world
has changed and this will keep evolving
especially as we get to an exciting
topic that I think is the one I want to
leave you maybe with some
thoughtprovoking
um ideas and observations on multi- aent
systems and what does that even mean
here right um so a bit of history right
like the deep deep mind at the time of
acquisition had just mastered Atari I
remember fondly the the new rips in
which um Vlad presented the results and
they felt really refreshing I believe
that was the sequence to sequence in
Europe. Maybe it was the year before, I
can't remember. It was a while ago. Um,
and then in the internal program for
Deep Mine, there was sort of a
curriculum of difficulty of games that
we were going to tackle and you know,
famously go um came a few years after
Atari and then I would say maybe
Starcraft graduated us to just kind of
master all due to its complexity.
Although of course there's many
interesting games that have slightly
different complexities but Starcraft
clearly for AI felt like a good um you
know kind of ending note although even
today we are working on on games still
as as you might you know you might have
seen with with things like world models
and um Sema 2 was just released that can
play uh 3D games and so on but the
approach uh is quite different now blast
from the past as well so 2011 ages ago I
used to be a grad student and um very
exciting from Dan Clean's group was this
project that tried to tackle sort of um
solving Starcraft with machine learning
and there was a whole class set for you
know for testing kind of maybe somewhat
good old style fashion fashion AI
although some machine learning as well
um inter interle with just trying to
play the game or play um different
aspects of the game. Um so it was
recognized of course as a domain and
personally of course this resonated very
much when I saw Deep Mind for the first
time applying ML which I love to video
games which I love. I used to play
Starcraft um to eventually become um the
the the lead of the Alpha Star project.
Uh so very very interesting domain. at
the time in 2011 really seemed quite
impossible that a single neuronet could
play the game but that's basically what
we did right and for those of you who
don't know do not know Starcraft I mean
it's very hard to give you a twominut
overview but it's essentially sort of a
a chess in which you don't see the board
all the time and you know things are
fairly continuous like actions um it's a
it's a real-time strategy game uh so
there's lots of hiding information from
the enemy because it's partial
observable. Um, and generally the action
space is quite complex because you have
to control not only the strategy at the
high level but also the micro strategy
about how to move your units about the
map. Right? So here you have a map, it
has resources, you gather resources, you
get money, you build buildings, you
build units, you engage the enemy. Um,
and if you destroy all the enemy
buildings, that's the winning or losing
condition. Um, so it's kind of a fun
game. Um it's been quite um heavily
played over the years, different
versions of it and it brought esports to
life um in South Korea certainly very
early early days like in the in the late
90s even. So this is kind of pioneered
in a way also um certain aspects of
video gaming
different points of view. This is the
one you might have actually seen uh
that's rendered directly from the game.
This is your UI. You can see sort of you
only see on the bottom left here part of
the map. You need to move the camera,
right? Send the units around, build
buildings, issue commands. It's fairly
fast-paced. Um, so there's lots of cool
sub problems, right, that you could
tackle as an AI uh domain. Um, but as I
was saying, what we actually end up
doing, and I'll describe bits and
pieces, but not in full. We trained a
single neuronet network basically that
was issuing all these commands and the
how when it matters to LLM or current uh
trends that we're seeing I'll describe
uh in the second part of the talk and
then in the third part we'll cover
multi.
So achievement wise I mean it was um fun
and um I remember fondly when our agent
achieved grandmaster status which is
given only the to the I believe top 100
players in any given region. So we were
playing online literally in our office.
So imagine, right, playing video games
at work. That was pretty fun. And we
were all sitting around playing games
against people that didn't know they
were playing against Alpha Star,
although many could guess and and there
was lots of speculation because you had
to opt in to play against uh possibly
advanced AIs. But eventually we reached
the Grandmaster milestone. And then
later we also went sort of in the wild
in Blisscon, which is a new rips for
startup so to speak.
uh where we played many many folks who
just were mesmerized by playing against
an AI at the time. This was I believe
our first AI system in the wild from
from deep mine actually. Uh so it was
quite nice to just interact with people
see how they felt about the game AI etc.
This was 2019 right before the pandemic
hit. And so we visited the this
wonderful very different style
conference I would say than Nurips
although I think Nurips is becoming a
bit like this as well lately. Um and it
was fun. We played um a bunch of people
including Sarah who is one of the
legends of the game. If you want to sort
of see the games um the five games we
played um I believe YouTube links are
here at your disposal. You can see here
me a bit tense to see what the agent
would do a under such strong opponent,
but it was all fun. And I think probably
the most profound realization was um you
know a couple of weeks after here you
see November 24th, Sarel um mentioned
that he actually copied Starcraft or
Alpha Star, one of the builds that he
had played against. Um and of course an
obvious um comment that that again kind
of in a way concluded this this epoch uh
we had at deep mind on on mastering
games in one-on-one setting was that you
know we got you know a player learning
from Alpha Star but of course Alphaar
had learned from several as uh you will
see in a second. So that was pretty fun.
So let's start to see kind of maybe some
obvious some less obvious connections.
Um and then um yeah like basically
why does it all make sense right like
even even when we talked to reporters at
the time very early days they didn't
understand the impact of playing games
in real world right so here I try to map
fairly imperfectly right sort of the the
the timeline of certain major projects
alpha asterisk projects if you will um
that kind of in a way took inspiration
um either algorithmically or learnings
or you know whatnot from the previous
projects that had come right because
because games were such a good um
sandbox to try some ideas to scale up
neuronet networks um and I mean at the
time it was a bit hard to convey this to
maybe general public um but it's great
to see that this kind of plan for for
that really the whole company was set
about um is taking shape and games still
have a role to play by the way into kind
of building pursuing AGI in the context
of LLMs but here there's a few sort of
projects I didn't put all of them
certainly there's no Atari for example
um but certainly as I mentioned after go
we decided to tackle Starcraft and then
there's no other games but after that we
had huge inspiration to start working on
coding early days or our first LLMs uh
chinchilla visual language models
flamingo um Orgato uh and AlphaFold also
took inspiration of I mean certain
aspects of transformers, distillation of
data etc. And today as you probably can
guess a lot of the research um and
resources are now heavily invested into
a single project almost although it's
very large so there's many many
different components called Gemini which
I'm called tech leading together with
Jeff and Noam and of course in there
we're just trying to build the most
general system we can so you know it's
you know a game or playing a single game
might be one of the many many things the
incredible things that these models can
do today, but it's nice to also look
back and attribute a bit of ideas or
where things come from.
So, more specifically, right, let's dive
into some technical details um and some
have striking closeness I would say with
how today we're creating some of these
amazing LLMs. So this is from from the
nature paper that was eventually
published and we'll discuss the three
aspects but in sequence we did basically
three things to create this single
neuronet network. We had first
supervised learning as we called it in
this figure um learning from human data.
Then we had the step of reinforcement
learning um and this reinforcement
learning didn't happen in a vacuum. It
happened in a massive multi- aent system
like as follows.
So mapping to today's projects or work
um this is what we commonly now call
pre-trading this is post trading and I
don't think there's a massive amount of
motivation work although there is more
and more um of course as we get more
mature in the technology for LLMs
um but there's even at the highest level
of how this this different steps of
creating this agent we already could see
or we already can see that um much many
of the problems we faced um back then
apply today uh and you'll see why in
more detail now for each of these
stages.
So let's start with actually something
that at the time felt felt kind of
complicated and and also in a way
obvious in hindsight having worked on
sequence models which is how to deal
with actions the actions that you needed
to issue to activate or to operate
Starcraft.
So the actions were fixed. There was an
API and as an API you basically had you
know all sorts of different um functions
that you could call and different
functions required different arguments.
Right? So this is basically an API that
Blizzard has and had before we started
working with them already to interact or
to send network messages actually
between players in Starcraft and we just
used it as is. Right? So you can imagine
in this instance there's this thing here
that blocks this ramp. So there's an
action called force field which is the
name of this thing and you know you
issue this action to this set of units.
So you say a set of units try to issue a
force field in this coordinates 6A 82.
Um and then you also say um delay from
current you know you can wait 10 steps
which is kind of half a second or
something and only repeat this action
once right so that's kind of how you do
everything in the game and it was a bit
tricky to how would we be able to issue
these commands so the solution we found
um is to just lay out an auto
reggressive model with kind of a little
recurrent neural network that was
structured so that all these arguments
were lining up with different soft maxes
right that would basically say Q yes or
no um when and then it's a softmax
between zero and you know 128 steps or
whatever maximum we decided what is also
a softmax a categor categorical softmax
over over positions etc etc right so we
we handcrafted this architecture
um and then we obviously learned both
imitation and reinforcement learning to
finesse how to issue this sequence of
instructions or um commands that form an
API call that then we would send to the
game and this is strikingly close to
tool use in general right because in
tool use in LLMs what we have is an
access to an API like there's MCP
there's so many different protocols but
essentially there's an API there's a way
to define how to call search engine or
issue a command on a terminal or click
on the screen for that matter all these
things and then this is sort of defined
now in in natural language but um but
actually lots of different problems and
solutions again align here and it's was
cool to at the time I mentioned when I
talk about alpha star alpha star is like
a language right you just need to issue
these um you know literally code calls
or API calls into the game and there are
some differences that are you know
notable as well right here this
architecture is setting the API right so
the the regressive actions are expressed
through this particular architecture um
as cool as it is it's fixed whereas
today we know that to issue API calls
using the power of generalization of
text or code or combinations allows us
to issue API calls to all sorts of
different environments that agents might
be connected to. We also have now a
single transformer architecture that
just writes this text or code for us uh
that then is interpreted and sent to the
environment. Um and then there's
actually a lot of flexibility even in
the formats because you can instruct the
models to change the formats if you want
to be empirical about which formats
might be best versus here where there's
a certain architecture rigidity. And so
of course um we did ablate many
decisions and we had to retrain the
models and then try which ones play the
game better. Uh but but it was much more
cumbersome to be to need to retrain.
Now another very big problem and I think
this is actually a key debate even today
still pretty hot between uh many folks
which are the issue of using imitation
learning right which you know we
commonly denote as pre-training in the
LLM world.
So in Starcraft unlike let's say Go or
Atari um where the the action space
however large was literally not um as
large as it is in Starcraft where it's
very combinatorial
um and also the time horizon was much
longer etc etc exploration is and was
very challenging and I'll demonstrate
that kind of pretty sharply in the next
video.
So problem is random policy will not do
much in this game that is that useful.
Um and so in a way the bitter lesson
discussion which is should you gather as
much imitation learning experience to
bootstrap the knowledge about the domain
even in a game like Starcraft which
arguably is not AGI complete um as as
complex as it is uh didn't work to the
best of our abilities right so um for us
it was very clear we would need an
imitation learning plus then an
experience learning learning a
reinforcement learning uh loop on top.
Um and that was kind of a nice merging
of deep learning and reinforcement
learning uh which I very much welcome
also in LLMs. Uh although it can be
debated whether ultimately um pure
reinforcement learning for example could
get us all the way there. I strongly
believe the answer is no as you can
probably guess. Um, so what happens when
you apply pure reinforcement learning is
that it actually discovers how to beat
the enemy, but in a way that is
unsatisfactory. It takes all your
workers and then it just sends them to
attack. It's not this is not an uncommon
technique. I mean, it's it's it's if
you're a newbie, you might do it. Some
professional gamers do it at some point
with allins especially that they also
bring all the workers to attack. This
one beat the the hardest AI in the game
by exploiting it basically with
something that was not pre-programmed to
defend very well against this kind of
attack. Um, but clearly we just kept
seeing these results. Um, and we had to
resort to essentially using human data,
which luckily we did. We open source
over 1 million games of Starcraft thanks
to Blizzard collecting anonymous replays
online. um they're still available today
hopefully and there's a good cool way to
do research on imitation learning. Um
but that's basically kind of getting
lots of human data online was felt
necessary and was part of the solution.
And then something else we did which
also at the time was felt very different
but we also besides saying hey imitate
every human move from these millions of
games. We also said look hold on a
second from the whole game we know what
happened. We know um how good the
players were. We have some metadata. We
know what the players eventually built,
what units they did. Um so this metadata
we decided to encode it. It's a bit of a
cheating information because as you
start the game, you don't know the
future um units that will appear etc.
But it was sort of a guiding signal to
condition uh the neuronet network to
look at this for correlations. Right? So
for instance the neuronet would know
okay I need to do you know this kind of
unit will appear. It would learn the
correlation between this unit and then
how to build it even in imitation
learning setting even though the
correlations are fairly weak. And so
that was kind of a powerful thing to do
for many reasons. And I'll I'll go get
back to these conditioning signals again
as well during during the lecture. But
again contrasting this with current
LLMs, this actually was a form of prompt
or instruction following, right? So we
all start a model and we tell it what we
wanted to do and that was our way
without obviously knowing about about
this yet of doing the same to a fairly
complex system, right? We would tell
this agent to either do this sequence of
buildings and or to construct these
units and or to behave like a
professional gamer or like a novice in
advance. That was our instruction. And
then by doing this, the agent was
reconfigurable to do to play in many
different styles controlled by the user,
right? Prompted by the user. Um, now
that's a similarity. Many differences. I
mean this um this agent was trained on
about five billion tokens. Um we know of
course LLMs train on over one trillion
tokens. So the order of magnitude is
quite different. Um these prompts were
structured were kind of again hand tuned
to the to the style of vectors binary
vectors that we expected rather than
expressed through language. Right? It
was not that we were writing hey build
an overlord and then build a zer, right?
um these was these were like binary
encoded so to speak and then these
prompts unlike in today's LLMs were
derived by just looking at the whole
game right we could look at the future
we saw the whole game we summarize it
into these vectors that were given from
sort of the first frame of the game
versus of course in current LLMs often
times we have a prompt or an instruction
that's requires human annotation in some
form Not always but it's generally hey
there's coding competition someone comes
up with a nice coding competition
problem uh with some instructions and
then you know we let the agents try to
try to um solve for that particular
coding problem for example or a theorem
proved um by by LLMs etc. So again, some
similarities, some differences here as
well. But with this, we actually went
from that state of degeneracy of RL to
actually being able to start to see
believable game states being achieved by
these agents that they didn't experience
the game, but they imitated the human uh
knowledge, same as uh what we see with
LMS before we do any post- training
step.
Now I want to I think a very exciting
area of progress um and I would say
probably not the most mature even in LMS
uh despite all the all the investment
which is post training or using
reinforcement learning.
So in Starcraft we did a few things all
of which actually we also see in some
form or another done uh for similar
reasons to be honest in current large
language models.
So here is a fairly imperfect way to
measure ELO scores. Um you might be now
fairly familiar with ELO scores thanks
to LMC's for example which scores um of
course um your your favorite LLM
providers against each other. Uh but of
course I mean chess and many other games
use ELO as a system right and think of
things like 40 ELO difference is not
super large but it starts to be
significant 400 is fairly significant
difference. So if we train from scratch
without human data we didn't get a very
strong agent just the supervised
learning policy was at 900 ELO. So that
that's a fairly no strong initial state
to then kickstart the whole
reinforcement learning multi- aent
system that we had. Um
now the obvious thing is take this this
policy initialize it and then add just
use reinforcement learning vanilla. um
and you get a bit of a boost but what
tends to happen is you might see some
collapse of behaviors which also is
quite commonly seen in LLMs right so the
diversity of the whole distribution that
you've gathered over imitation learning
is lost so to speak so we added a
supervised KL penalty which is fancy way
to say we distill the policy the
original policy onto the one we were
training with reinforcement learning So
in a way um you don't overcommit too
early to certain particular way of
playing. You keep kind of the diversity
of um styles, strategies etc. Although
that itself was not easy to do. So we'll
get back to that in a second. But that
helped quite a bit keep things much
better. So that boosted ELO by 400. And
then the last thing which is this
conditioning
explicit conditioning on the kinds of
things we want the agents to do. further
boost um the ELO score by almost 150 or
so. Um so all these aspects right came
together and we we see obviously all
these being employed as well um in LLMs.
Another trick we find which was neat is
that for the value function, right,
which tells you whether you're winning
or losing, even though it's a partial
observable game, we found that the value
function seeing the whole board so to
speak was much more accurate and um
helped reducing variance in training
which was problematic and always is in
reinforcement learning. So that's
another trick we did which also in
different shapes and forms um is seen as
as positive when you apply to certain
domains in uh large current large
language models.
So all these tricks and more right are
used in modern LLMs. Um but what are the
differences right between what we were
doing here and and LLMs? I mean most
crucially that rewards
can't be fully specifies specified
always mean Starcraft you win you lose
um you know there are interesting things
Starcraft actually many people resign
before losing right so not it's not that
all the data you get to the winning
condition necessarily so there's some
fun problems there but by and by and
large you can compute you know success
or not success whereas of course in LLMs
I mean write me a nice poem. It's just
good luck, you know, getting humans to
agree on that. Um, so it's very very
tricky, right, to uh to reward behaviors
when you're going to much more general
problems. Um, now that's kind of
annoying um definitely to me, which is
compute envelope for LLMs are heavily
skewed towards pre-training, right? So
you spend most of our flops in
pre-training and only a little bit in
post- training. And that feels wrong for
a variety of reasons. And certainly for
Alphaar, it was not an exception. Most
of the compute, most of the weights
updates were done in this experience,
experiential or reinforcement learning
stage. And then overfitting is very
common in LLMs because it turns out we
do not have an infinite amount of tasks
that are interesting for humans to to
solve or to to perform that would help
uh train LLMs in when they deploy it
against you know real humans or with
real humans uh in the loop um that the
kinds of things they would ask right
there's there's a limited amount of data
whereas for Starcraft every game is
unique and because it's constrained by
the environment. You don't see this
overfitting issue which of course is
related. Second and third bullet points
here are quite related.
So let me take a sip of my tea and let's
get into slightly more technical more
intuitive part of the talk about why you
know why do we need multi- aent systems
what did we do in alphaar
so this was quite fun at the time I had
certainly um you know I I enjoyed of
course the imitation learning sequence
to sequence was an example of imitation
learning very heavily reinforcement
learning
I kind of hey I know what's going on
right as a scientist you learn you learn
that domain as you join deep mind um so
it was kind of everywhere multi- aent
was all that I learned was during the
project and it was very fun um and very
intuitive and very simple to see results
very drastic results very quickly just
by trying some sometimes extremely
simple ideas
so why did we want motivation learning
in astar was to add robustness so
hopefully you'll get what that what that
means through my explanations.
So
you have these models, they do amazing
things, but we see them fail often and
that happened certainly in Alphaar and
we see this happen in LMS all the time
as well, right? You ask simple
questions, right? Like is this number
larger than this number? How many Rs are
in strawberry? And these models tend to
flop uh quite dramatically. Even though
they might be uh I mean you know fields
medal levels in some aspects right of of
mathematics they might fail miserably in
other aspects right. So
kind of notionally that is very similar
to the kinds of issues we encounter. We
are we train a very good policy uh with
imitation learning and reinforcement
learning. We then play the game as
humans, right? Not in the self-play way
that you keep, you know, getting better
ELO scores. And then we found that
simple strategies, right, made the
agent, it didn't react properly and they
were fairly simple. It would, if you
played very at the high level, it would
really react to your moves and feel like
superhuman, but it would not understand
some basics, right? So it very much
feels similar to um although of course
we're doing a lot of advancements in um
LLMs but it feel it felt similar
and using game nomenclature although
you'll appreciate this is similar to um
the failures you're you're seeing right
we have different policies or different
sort of examples that we could um get
against our agents um from some are like
very exploitative not that interesting
to actual strategies that we would
certainly encounter if we had this agent
online in the wild. Right? So
adversarial policies, these would be
like making the agent flip is almost
like adversarial examples, right? In in
neuron nets, you change a pixel a little
bit and a panda becomes an airplane,
right? according to a neural net build.
Similar things you can get with a policy
where maybe you you bring a unit and you
move it in certain ways and you know the
the neural network just degenerates,
right? So that's unlikely to be found
unless you let of course users probe it.
Um but it's still like kind of the most
basic kind of exploit you could think
about from a neuronet network
perspective. Then we have exploiters
that are just repeatedly playing
properly so to speak against a single
policy but eventually they might find a
weakness and then they go deep into that
weakness strategically speaking um until
they just basically beat you all the
time. Um and that's in a way um similar
like both exploer and the next level are
similar to what we're seeing in LLMs uh
these days. The third level is cheese,
which is a strategy that might
generalize, might be actually fairly
robust against many different opponents
versus the second one, which is against
just one opponent. Um, but of course,
it's not probably the best optimal
strategy for this game. Although mix and
matching cheese and normal policies um
is commonly done at the professional
level of styraph as well because you
always need to be worried that this
strategy might occur at any time. You're
not seeing the board all the time,
right? So to play the game optimally
similar to of course things like you see
in poker, right? You always need to be
worried about many things. So you cannot
go too far into optimizing against an
opponent that even though you're not
seeing what they're doing, you know what
they're doing, right? So
unpredictability is is is is important.
So the third kind the cheeses you
usually see them at even the highest
level. And then there's normal policies
and optimal policies.
Now putting it differently right this is
called non-transitiveness. What this
means is would this policy work against
a different um opponent. Right? So the
adversarial thing most likely not,
right? Like you know the the adversarial
attack might be specific to the the
weights of your neural network. Then the
exploiter policy you train or you
repeatedly play against the same
opponent who cannot update their
weights. So that one is specific to one
opponent. Cheese tends to generalize,
right? So maybe what when we're talking
about the RS in strawberry and so on, we
see many models trained not very
differently but somewhat differently by
different companies have these
weaknesses, right? So maybe th those
kind of exploits are more in this cheese
category which are reasonably
generalizable but of course not very
kind of interesting or or strong. Um I
mean no one hopefully just uses this to
cheese the model so to speak. Then we
have normal policies um and then the
optimal policy which of course is very
very hard to find um with deep deep
reinforcement learning and multi- aent.
So if we put this figure differently one
observation that my colleague did is
that most interesting games have this
different axis. the the Z-axis here is
the strength the the inherent strength
of the of the player right the ELO score
um or the LMC is a score but then within
a slice right of this of this thing you
would actually find um different cycles
of non-transitivity meaning that three
models at the same ELO score especially
if the ELO score is not very high might
beat each other in a way that's
non-transitive like rock paper scissors
or cycles. Actually, that's a common
commonly used um abstraction that's very
clear, right? Uh rock, paper, scissors.
One beats the other. So, think of um we
might have three three models, three
agents at the same level, but one very
strongly beats the next and the the next
one very strongly beats the next one and
so on. Right? So, there's these cycles
of non-transitiveness.
And many interesting games studied here
possess this this kind of um this
property, right? And this is obviously
designed for zero sum games. So for
LLMs, you need to kind of make some
abstractions to think about what that
means. But we do we certainly have ELO
scores and we certainly see models
having strengths that are not uniformly
the same across the same let's say level
of LMC's performance for example, right?
Um so that is an interesting aspect of
the complexity of the kind of task we're
trying to solve.
Um I'll skip this slide just there's the
reference from 2020 but that explains
this intuitively this this issue of um
there's an area where you're not so good
that things are very non-transitive and
then as you become very very good then
there's a dominant strategy that no one
can beat. Um, so that's kind of how
we're seeing in most games, this kind of
behavior. Um, now
switching gears a bit, how do you
actually train these models? Um, there's
a few techniques, but all of them have
some issues, especially as the games
become strategically complex. So here is
rock, paper, scissors, actually. So each
of the um of the vertices here are um
rock paper or scissors. A strategy is
just a distribution of what will you
play, right? So if you play against an
opponent that always plays rock, well
that's a very bad strategy. And the
optimal strategy is uniform, right? Um
so if you do selfplay kind of naively
and you try to say I'm going to learn an
agent that plays rock paper scissors,
you see this effect of kind of
oscillating around the middle and
locally you're very strongly into one
strategy, right? So um sadly that makes
convergence very hard. Now what you can
start thinking about is hey let's add
population populations of of of policies
all play against each other right so
there's several ways to do this here are
the the three figures but this starting
to be to feel a bit better like
intuitively as well right like if I want
to learn to play rock paper for scissors
I'm exposed to many players maybe
someone who has very suboptimal strategy
playing only Caesars but at least I
wouldn't know that that player a
priority Um so I might learn to
eventually that I have to play you know
the optimal or the nash here which is
the middle point equal distribution of
um the symbols. Very simple game though.
So obviously very toy and different
strategies yield different results. The
one that is most hopeful, but even in
this toy example, it doesn't quite get
always the result that is desired is the
right most, which is you have a
population of these agents that you play
against and you play always against the
strongest opponent, right? That feels
like a good strategy to maybe set
yourself up. And we didn't quite do this
um in Starcraft, but there's a lot of
these intuitions that played a big role.
Let's see this played kind of we saw
this. This is a real example of what we
saw as we trained using sort of selfplay
in Alpha Star in the early days. And
let's use a equivalent of rock paper
scissors in Starcraft World, which is um
three different kinds of units. Boy,
which is an air unit.
immortal, which is a very strong ground
unit, but that cannot attack the air.
And then stalker, which is kind of a a
unit that can attack the air, but is not
the strongest ground unit. So, void rate
beats immortal. Immortal build beats
stalker, stalker beats boy rate. And
it's kind of true. If you do it just
naively, you just build lots of these
units, you most likely will will see
this is actually like represents the
game reasonably faithfully. So, so great
right we said this and we start from
imitation learning. So we have that
players I mean there's a distribution
over different strategies that people
will will have done um when they play
online and our initial policy is in the
middle right is not very good at either
of these but it represents the whole
distribution and as we train what
happened is our policies even with the
distillation losses and so on started to
only do void rays really well lots of
them very good micromanagement but they
became really really really specialized.
So the whole population which was not
really a population this is just pure
selfplay actually everything the only
strategy that became
present dur during during training was
boy rays and of course that washed out a
little bit the prior knowledge that we
came in even with distillation and that
meant that from the agent's perspective
it was delusional right it was it was
playing against itself and buay versus
boy ray great battles awesome games that
we recorded during that time. Um, if the
enemy happened to do immortals,
no issue, right? These these these units
dominate this. But if someone just said,
"Okay, I'm going to do these other
units," then this agent didn't even
encounter this anymore, right? Because
all it saw in its games were massive
amounts of void rays. So sadly, this was
not a very robust strategy. I mean, if
you force a pro player to, hey, you'll
have to do race. um only do that no
cheese, no different strategies, then
this agent was very good. But of course,
people are diversifying what they do.
These are not the only three strategies.
There's early rashes, all sorts of
things that happen in these domains. So
that really didn't work well.
What we added though, the the key notion
in the league is to add exploiters,
right? So as you train the model, the
main agent, this this steel agent, um it
might still specialize to do void race,
but then at some point during the
training um process like the
reinforcement learning, you're going to
add a second agent. And this agent is
going to be an exploer, meaning that is
only going to care about beating this
agent here, right? It's its goal is
going to be beat this agent. This agent
cannot train against this. So there's an
asymmetry. The red gets to see the games
and learn from them, but the teal does
not. Okay. So then what happens
naturally is that if the agent starts to
specialize to void race, naturally the
exploer will start doing stalkers,
right? So now at least this agent has
seen that, hey, this there are very good
players out there that will do this
other unit that beats me. So it's going
to be exposed right to this strategy and
be able to react properly and even say
you know run out of the optimum which is
to build lots of void rays to say hey
maybe I actually should also build
immortals if I see that the enemy is
doing lots of stalkers etc. Right? So
this is simplistic but I think it gets
the idea of the algorithm we end up
developing uh intuitively
in full what we do is this in steroids
right. So we had many different agents
that were created with the sole goal of
making the main agents the the agents we
actually deployed and became grandmaster
against the global population of
players. Right? So you can imagine we
have these three main agents one per
race. Right? And then we have different
agents whose goal is just to make the
main agent stronger. Right? So that's
the whole multi- aent system we
designed. And the way it works is
actually super simple. We didn't
experiment a lot with this. So the main
agents are essentially playing against
themselves, playing against the other
main agents, and playing against the
whole population all the time, right?
They're playing kind of against
everyone. Um I'll get to how that
distribution of everyone evolves over
time. But then these main exploit agents
they will basically say hey start from
the prior try to beat let's say the
three agents maximally right so just
cheat right cheat in the sense of I can
train against you you cannot train
against me develop a policy that
eventually reaches a certain win rate
when the win rate is very high meaning I
exploited you successfully only then you
say hey here I am I'm beating you I'm a
new player in this world, deal with it.
Right? So, this agent was secretly
training until it became good at
exploiting and when it became good, it
dropped a checkpoint. It it showed
itself against the main agents which now
all of a sudden could play against it
and it it went and it restarted the same
process again from the prior. Right? So,
over over time you will find different
exploiters at different stages of
training um against the main agent. And
then we also added league exploiters
which are is the same concept but
instead of beating only the main agents
these agents try to beat everyone in the
population by finding exploits that work
against everyone rather than just the
main agent. Uh which is a bit more like
um cheese right so we have main
exploiters league exploiters and then of
course main agents. This was very fun to
see like the dynamics, the learning
dynamics. Very hard to understand even
in a game, right? What's actually going
on? I mean, intuitively we know, but
lots to do that are left on the table
from this Alpha Star League, as we call
it. Um, but it was very powerful. And
then over the over over time, we have
over a thousand agents that have
different strengths, right? They will
beat a previous agent. Um but eventually
the main agents catch up and beat the
exploiters. So there's all sorts of
interesting win rate dynamics and it can
be represented in this shape of the the
the spinning top a little bit. Right? So
the weakest agents here are highly
non-transitive. There are 30,000
RPS cycles. That means um the the cycle
length of non-transitivity
is 30,000. Right? So you have you can
find 30,000 agents um I believe that's
what it means that beat the next one the
next one and so on so forth and as the
agents become stronger they start to
fully dominate which is also commonly
seen I mean in in this in these
interesting games um so that's an
analysis this this what happens in rock
paper scissors um to give you an example
so much more complex game dynamics
um and then as I said it was very fun to
see this happen right so you would be
training And all of a sudden, this red
agent is an exploer that finds a cheese
that's called cannon rush. Right? So the
blue agent that's the main agent
can't really has not seen this strategy
enough. So can't really defend very
well. But eventually by now playing
against this red agent that's now frozen
in time and it will just do the same
strategy, eventually we'll be able to
defend um and so on so forth. Right? So
with workers which is the right reaction
and scout right to find that you've been
indeed in this situation and and so on
so forth and we saw all sorts of
interesting dynamics as well. Um anyways
like there's lots of cool games and and
and hopefully analysis that you can see
online. I don't want to talk about Sag
too much but it's a passion of mine as
you can see. Um but yeah this was kind
of very critical and then in the results
you could see that if you only train
with a population still but only of main
agents right so just you have three
agents playing against each other and
against them themselves in the past
that's called fictitious selfplay um you
know they you achieve certain strength
and this this this score is not that
perfect if you play as a human you would
not be that that strong I mean these
differences were probably less than
reality
Um and we we checked this a little bit
but it was hard to do this experiment in
the wild. Um then by adding main
exploiters we became much stronger and
by adding on top of that leak exploiters
we had the final system that was um
robust against many different strategies
and of course very strong at uh at
playing the game.
Now couple of details uh and then I'll
conclude is that the path of learning
matters and it's so hard to know how it
matters right like basically if you're
now an agent and it is exploited very
often or very rarely or initially is
never exploited I mean all these changes
heavily the policy you end up with at
the end of this process um so
there's lots of details that I mean are
to be worked out even from a theory
perspective but you know in these games
and with deep reinforcement learning
theory is also hard to come by. Um we
had a couple of strategies on how to
matchmake. So I'm the main agent. There
is like literally thousand agents which
should I play against? So we had two
strategies. One is play against the one
that beats you the most which is hard
opponents. And one the other one is play
against the one that you're 50/50.
You're closest to maximum entropy,
right? Um because the one if the one
that beats you the most beats you all
the time, there's not going to be a
learning signal. So we tried these both
strategies. Um variance was a little
better like this one that maximizes kind
of that tries to get to the sweet spot
of 5050.
But also I mean this is one of the many
parameters that tells you that the
process in which you create these main
policies matters a whole lot. And then
the other part that was important is
that to generate interesting counter
strategies or exploiters or cheeses um
having controllability mattered. So not
only we started from the prior
distribution that we had trained in
imitation learning and say hey go and
exploit the main agent we also were
opinionated about how you should exploit
it right so we would sometimes not
always say I want you to exploit the
main agent but please do it with this
unit type right like I mentioned how we
did this prompting so it was kind of
tying your hands behind a little bit say
hey I want you to beat me but you have
to use this unit Right. And that added a
component of robustness and
diversification that also helped. Um, so
lots of different choices here. Not a
lot of time we had during the project to
fully study this, but you can see lots
of different possibilities and it was
very important to have this diversity in
the main policy. Of course, in LLMs that
is trivial, right? So, um, you have you
they're very promptable. There's a lot
of diversity. So there's not a problem
at all um to think about hey I don't
know solve this theorem but do it in
Catalon or in Spanish or do it in you
know very boss right all these things
will add some sort of robustness to
maybe new um encounters that you'll find
meaning new prompts in LLMs and so on so
forth.
So contrasting these very exciting
multi- aent ideas and space with LLMs
um mean one one difference is that users
are in general collaborative right like
it's not a zero game that we play zero
sum game that we play I go online and I
want to achieve something get some
information help me with some problem
that I'm having so I'm actually
collaborative with the other agent right
um so that's an interesting difference.
That being said, we also have
adversarial users, right? I mean, who
doesn't like to find weird failure modes
and then Twitter likes are obviously one
of the reward signals that humans like
to optimize? Um or also more seriously,
right, we will have, you know,
eventually these systems become close
closer and closer to AGI, very powerful.
So, you might want to them for doing
something that they shouldn't be doing,
right? So there's going to be
adversariality as well trying to
go around how the system is designed to
be used. So both aspects could use
multi- aent techniques such as the one I
described from the Alpha Star League
differently.
Complexity is massive compared to even a
game as complex as Starcraft, right? So
there's no clear reward. We discussed
this. um prompting is much less clean
than a bit of bits of which units should
you build right it's prompting can be
vast is natural language um is unbounded
it's it's very very interesting uh the
amount of complexity we'll deal with
here to the extent that even these LLMs
playing Starcraft which is a dream of
mine um they can kind of play they're
not very good is actually one of the
many domains right so you could see a
particular case of current models is
that we might just instruct them to hey
be a very good start of player and then
give them control of the environment and
see what they do right and in fact games
more and more are starting to be reused
turn around be used as an evaluation
there's a game arena I believe on Kaggle
that is very popular for example and
famously I think some of the LLMs try to
complete Pokemon etc so very cool domain
as well right um to test ideas um I will
say some amount of outer teaming right
um etc has been using multi-agent
techniques but I think overall is still
in its infancy so there's lots and lots
of research to be done here
so to conclude this sort of past and
future combination and and of course
present of LLMs
um I would say there's lots you know
prelimm agents right there's lots of
gems to learn from from many different
papers and different problems um you
know tool was discussed architectures,
losses, regularization, value functions.
I mean, lots of things we can probably
revisit very seriously and we should.
Um, my strong belief is that human
priors are going to be part of the path
to Agi. Um, but we need to obviously
also build knowledge and experience on
top of that prior knowledge. I've seen
it succeed enough times now including in
AlphaGo which also use imitation plus RL
um that I believe that's certainly the
shortest path uh to AGI although happy
to you know um discuss that if if if
useful um then in general like RL or
post training on top of LLMs still feels
in their infancy when I think and
compared to a system like the alphaar
system um you know we can train on
thousands of steps maybe um versus in
this alpha star league we use 10 to the
10 training steps in post training right
so vastly more compute used in post
training rather than in pre-training
um of course we also have this issue
that the rewards are fuzzily specified
so that is um definitely a challenge and
last but not least multi- Asian RL in
whichever way you can think of creating
a population of users and agents talking
to one another and really optimize and
train for that. I think that's very
exciting and it's going to have probably
a new scalability breakthrough I can
imagine in the next few years. Maybe
from some of you.