we are very fortunate today to have with
us Todd McKinnon I'll let Todd go
through his background with just some
quick highlights uh you probably heard
of a company called OCTA um Todd started
that company in in
2009 um before that spend time at
Salesforce um and then people saw before
that um I remember meeting Todd uh when
I was actually at Twitter and when he
was telling me his idea of what he was
going to go build my first R was
brilliant idea and unfortunately I was
too busy to not I didn't take the time
to convinced hey take a check for me um
because I was dealing with so many fires
at uh Twitter but uh anyway with that
I'll I'll pass it to you and the the
format today unlike last week is going
to be very conversational so as you have
questions for Todd put them in the
Discord and we will pause periodically
and so you can ask those questions and
so again
the goal here is we have this valuable
time with Tod and let's leverage it and
learn as much as we can from him from
his journey there's two parts of the
answer on like what inspired me to start
OCTA or why I started OCTA the first
answer is uh um maybe one you'll hear
from a lot of people that you're hear
from in the class and people that
started companies which is there was
really a opportunity I saw at the time a
lot of software was installed in the
data center companies manag themselves
there's cloud computing SAS applications
were starting to take off and I knew
that there was going to be that was a
big technological transformation and if
you want to start a new company you want
to innovate you can't just go right up
against the big entrenched players you
know on their Turf there has to be a
change there has to be a transition like
what what like what's happening right
now with AI and and there's tons of
change and ton of tons of markets are
going to be disruptive or disrupted
there's a lot of opportunity to start
companies and innovate like at the time
16 years ago transition to the cloud
there was a lot of opportunity to uh
build new products and services that the
incumbents the big companies wouldn't
necessarily be able to compete with
because they were used to doing it the
old way and so my co-founder and I who
is actually a Stanford Alum Freddy
Carris went Stanford he tells me how
wonderful it is every day um he he
actually we we worked at Salesforce and
we decided to there was you know this
transition you know we could go out and
kind of do some build some it products
that would help companies it departments
adopt cloud computing and get on this
new wave and ride this new train of
technology that was coming and so we had
a different few different ideas we had
this idea to build a like a really good
monitoring system that would monitor all
of your Cloud applications and tell you
if they were working or not and we built
a prototype of that and we talked to a
bunch of people that might want to buy
that product and the the reception was
kind of like ho home it's like like H we
don't really know if we buy that we use
cloud computing because we just want it
to work so we didn't get super psyched
about that idea but then uh this I this
simple idea that hey you know we're
starting to use all these Cloud
applications like Dropbox and Gmail and
all this stuff and the it's really kind
of hard to log into them you know we we
have our work account and the login for
Dropbox is different and maybe if you
could just solve this problem of making
that really easy for companies to log
into these Cloud applications that I
would pay for that cuz when you do a
startup you need you need two things
like we wanted to build a big impactful
company for the long term but you need
two things you need you know like
something that can turn out to be big a
lot of startups actually fail because
they just don't do something that can
turn out to be big you know so you got
to do something that can turn out to be
big and really could build a big company
around second thing is you you have to
you know it's kind of hard but you have
to actually have something that people
will pay for soon you can't wait 10
years when it's really big theoretically
you have to get money today so um we got
this feedback an identity like helping
people log into this stuff was a problem
people would pay for and we knew enough
from our experience cuz I when I started
OCT I'd already been working for like 15
years and um so I had enough experience
working with big companies in my
previous jobs and um looking at the
software industry to know that you know
if you can actually solve this simple
problem of helping people at companies
log into their workouts in a really easy
way you actually had to build a lot of
infrastructure and had to be very
reliable and very very very very
scalable and once you do that and you
bootstrap it with this business of what
seems like a pretty tactical use case
single sign on you actually can build a
lot of other things around that and the
company could be big over time um so
yeah that that's a little bit about um
the story of OCTA and started so you you
trained as an engineer you had spent you
know you said close to 15 years as an
engineer and now you're starting this
new company as a CEO like what were the
things that were difficult for you to
like TR like to learn sales like to
learn marketing or yeah it's it was very
um it was it was quite a challenge and
like you know a lot of the stories and
people the the entrepreneurs are
lionized or the real young entrepreneurs
they're the you know like the people
that are you know just out of college or
in college or don't go to college they
start these companies um I was a little
different I was when I started OCTA I
was in my mid-30s I was 36 years old and
um so what what I had some success I had
at Salesforce I had you know 500 people
worked for me I had an executive
assistant and you know I was kind of
like it was comfortable you know I was
like I got this money this good salary
and
uh of all the things of all the
challenges to overcome when you start a
company and there are many like the odds
are against you almost all startups fail
it's super the odds are super long the
hardest thing about it was leaving that
comfortable job because that's a status
symbol people socially like oh Todd he's
the SVP of engineering and Salesforce
I've heard it's Salesforce oh look at my
team I got my resources and the hardest
thing about was like giving that up in
fact when I when I um I was thinking a
lot about like oh this is a big
opportunity um you know it's like Cloud
transition we could really do something
here we could have an impact you build
this big company I didn't tell you the
other thing that was the motivation and
this is a thing that like was very real
but like when you hear these stories
they don't always tell you the real
story the other story about my
motivation was
I just wanted to be the
boss nothing wrong with that's true I
just being honest right I wanted to be
the boss I'd worked with bosses and they
were great but I said I could do that um
so that was like personal angle but the
hardest thing about it was I had to go
to my wife and convince her that I
should leave my job and do this
company and my wife is roxan is
amazing she's um a little bit more um
risk averse than I am
like in her thinking and her you know
her you know family and Social Circle
and stuff it's like you either have a
job at a company like a company people
have heard of or you're a bum there's no
like there's no like entrepreneur um I
mean that c being a little like over the
top to be funny but you know it's a lot
of concern and so I had to convince her
and that was quite challenging because
there was you know had a new baby
six-month old baby and also the
financial crisis of 2008 was very recent
it was like like banks are collapsing
and the economy is crashing and so I you
know the hardest thing was quitting my
job and I think by the way to round out
the story is I think a lot of the
reasons why you don't see more like
older Founders is that it's like they
get successful and it's really hard to
leave where these young kids you know
like yourselves that you're going to do
in the next few years got nothing to
lose right it's like go out there and do
it and crank and but there are different
paths and uh so uh so yeah that's a
little bit of the backstory there um but
you asked me something else was I was
just curious like you know as an
engineer oh yeah what what all a sudden
you had to learn functions that you had
never been exposed to yeah no I had a
point Sorry I was it just rambling um
the I think one of the things that I'm
very proud of is the ability the the
adaptability the ability to um go from
this kind big it wasn't a huge company
Salesforce was like thousand like a
thousand people coming up on a billion
dollars of Revenue actually it's a
couple thousand people billion dollars
Revenue much smaller than it is today
and but I had all this infrastructure
around me and the ability to be flexible
enough to quit and start this new
company with nothing I remember I still
remember the first day I woke up not
working in Salesforce it's like I had
nothing I had no admin I had no no one
really wanted to talk to me anymore and
just the ability to kind of like day by
day step by step make progress toward
that goal and here's the hardest thing
about it the hardest thing about it was
up until until everything in my life up
until that point you know high school or
college and jobs um I felt like if I
worked hard and I was smart and I was a
good
teammate I was going to be successful or
there was a high chance of success think
about starting a company you can be
smart you can be hardworking you can
work your ass off you can be the best
teammate and it's probably still not
going to work and that was hard mentally
to adjust to yeah it's like how do you
actually attack the problem get up every
day drive keep going and you know it's
like the odds are super against you and
not only is that hard psychologically to
yourself and and I don't mean to say
this like there are problems in the
world and people that have problems and
then there's me and us right we don't
have well I can't speak for everyone but
the entrepreneur starting a company
that's had a successful job and saved up
some money is it's hardly like you don't
cry too hard for that person but my
point is like it's psychologically
pretty hard to be comfortable and and
dve and do the work and attack the
problem with knowing that it's most
likely you're gonna fail and so not only
is that hard but then you got to like
bring a team of people along with you
and so I like started saying like
basically you got to learn how to
believe even when you don't believe and
what I mean by that is you got to be
able to inspire people and uh be
positive and drive forward even though
intellectually like my I'm an engineer
you know I think very logically you kind
of do the run the odds and you realize
that the odds are against you but you
got to be able to believe even you know
when the odds are against you and I
think that was probably the hardest
thing for me did you one of the things
at least in I I encountered when I was I
didn't had the success that you have had
with with OCTA but I composite like when
you're a CEO founder you know you have
your board that requires a certain
dialogue you have your employees and it
can be a very lonely role and I don't
think a lot of times people talk about I
mean did you encounter that or maybe it
was just
me because like to your point like you
have to project to your team hey we're
going to take that mountain even if
you're not sure yeah inside yeah it's it
definitely feels Lon
um and I actually made the mistake early
on of trying to um trying to like
address that issue of loneliness by
working with my board as if they were uh
people navigating this uncertain
environment with me in an exploratory
brainstorming kind of way which was a
mistake because it was a mistake right
because you know if you're on the board
and you put your money in this company
you know this you've been on board you
invested in company
and then you know like you go to these
board meetings and the CEO comes in is
like I'm not sure what to do what do you
guys think I mean we'll try a couple
things but I'm not sure if it's going to
work that's like red flags you know yeah
they they know that they're smart they
know that you know I had I was lucky
enough to have some of the best Venture
investors in the world and they know
it's a long shot they want people to
come in there and say like this is what
we're doing this is why we're doing it
we're going forward and we we're
optimistic and if it doesn't doesn't
work will let you know and that like
tone change was very powerful like the
board kind of really reacted to that
it's like all right we got a leader like
he has some confidence he's not like
grasping with straws and and you know I
learned that lesson and it's actually
the thing that another Super interesting
thing about doing this for so long 16
years a long
time the that core thing still applies
today you know as a public company CEO
and you know talking to investors all
the time and um they want strong
Direction Visionary clear you know
confident um you know like can't say
like oh I hope I hope we hit the quarter
fish gross that's right I mean it's a
tough economy out there so
like so just thinking of uh challenging
situations that test you your leadership
maybe you could speak to the some of the
breaches that you encountered or the
firms encountered over the last couple
of years yeah o got hacked
yeah twice it's very painful um and I
think you know like when I was kind of
talking a mic and thinking about what
would be interesting for folks here is
uh maybe this cyber the Cyber War that's
going on is very real um there's and
it's you know like economically it makes
a lot of sense there's a lot of money to
be made by stealing data and doing
ransomware and stealing crypto and and
um there's a lot of motivations for uh
just like nation states and controlling
information assets there's a lot of
motivation and and people thinking about
just you know damage and and increasing
their reputation in the hacker community
and hurting the reputation of these big
companies there's it's a real war and
you know our Evolution as a company we
started off
as we were enabling cloud computing
right you heard the story of how we
started it's like we were going to help
these organizations free them to use
this new wave of technology and help
them of course we were going to help
them be secure in doing it with single
login and multiactor authentication but
really it was about helping them adopt
this new pattern and like these
applications can be rolled out and this
you can use infrastructures as a service
and containers and not all this old
stuff um we didn't really grow up as a
company that was a cyber company through
and through like oh my God we're going
to start this company and it's going to
be about finding cyber criminals and
shutting them down and our risk model is
all about we got to address every single
risk we kind of grew up in this world of
um enablement and like fast and easy and
quick to deploy and so you fast forward
we we had you know like a lot of hard
work and a lot of good fortune we were
able to be in this position where we
were the leader of this industry and
like did you know that um each month a
billion people log in to something
through OCTA every month uh which is
pretty crazy right um there's 10 billion
authentications over that month so not
just once but on average 10 times
through the month so the scale is quite
large and by because of that there's a
lot of incentive to attack us and and
hack into us and our we didn't change
our company's culture we didn't change
our company's risk model fast enough we
should have changed it five years ago we
should have Chang seven years ago like
this is happening
um we're having success we're a public
company now we have to treat every risk
every uh potential issue in the company
vulnerability the way we're configuring
it the way we're configuring
infrastructure has to be super paranoid
and risk averse and I'm not I'm talk I
mean of course we were took security
seriously and we um addressed risks but
I'm talking about things
like um do we want to use do we want to
let salese use their personal cell
phone seem like it's easy we wanted the
best people to work for us in sales yeah
but no that's a risk because they could
be fished there's malware and so like no
shut that down so the risk model changed
and um going through these hacks was was
super painful because your you the
headlines are that you got hacked and
your investors are worried and your
customers are very concerned that
they're trusting you at their cyber
security and now how can we trust you
when you know you're getting hacked
yourself and you know it's it's uh the
instinct is a lot of companies do this
the instinct is to like not talk and not
be in front of the group and not be in
front of the investors and like you want
to go hide and bury your head in the
sand but you got to get out there in
front of it you got to go on you know TV
news and um talk about your problems and
do it in a way that assure like I was
saying before like reassures people um
they have confidence they have a plan
they're taking accountability for it
they are not trying to do this bunch of
snow Job saying there's no issues you
own it and you talk about a plan you
articulate that clearly and you move on
but it sucks and it's hard
mhm um the answer is it hasn't um it
hasn't recovered and I I don't mean that
all dim and Gloom but I think that I
would say it's changed um and our
opportunity at OCTA is to make that
change positive so what we're doing
there is we're like you know like kind
of what I was just saying but the next
step in that is we want to tell the
prospects and tell the customers share
what we've learned and share how we're
doing things differently and using our
own products to make us one of the most
secure organizations in the world so
instead of trying to say like is there
damage like will the reputation ever
recover I think it's healthier to say
it's different and our opportunity is we
need to you know become give build this
reputation of like the most hardened
solution so the solution that went
through the trials and the travails and
was hardened and um you like the it's
might be not a great analogy but it's
like would you rather uh fly on a plane
that's brand new or like a Triple 7
that's been flying since the 90s and
like super robust and a great safety
record that's kind of the idea it's like
we're the one that's super Reliant
robust um it is a it's like a the
technology part of it is I don't know if
this is what you meant by your question
but the technology part of it is the
transformation is not easy but it's
almost the easier part the harder part
is the cultural aspect you have to you
have to take a company that as a team
and we have to go from a model of like
we got we're trying to grow we're trying
to build new products we're trying to do
all these things to security is first
and we do all the security stuff first
and that's a non-negotiable we get that
done and we prioritize that we execute
that not only in the corporate
infrastructure but in the products we
build and making they're secure by
default and making sure that the
industry knows about our best practices
and our standards and making sure so
that's a cultural thing like a values
thing what the what the company is
running after and chasing after and
sometimes that stuff's harder culture is
like culture is super powerful and you
see great differentiating cultures in
all the great companies um it's also
it's also hard to quantify and qu and um
change sometimes which is why makes it
problem M and if you can get it at scale
this class is about infrastructure of
scale but if you can get culture of
scale it's like magic actually on that
topic what have you found that works to
manage culture scale and as well as what
works and what things maybe you tried
that didn't work yeah it's the simp like
here's my um you want to hear my you
want to hear my Ted Talk on culture I
sure know you're coming to a TED Talk uh
it's it's all about like tone from the
top and what the leaders do and how they
act
and what and and it's the it's very
simple culture is not complicated you
know culture is how the leaders act what
they value what they reward who gets
promoted what the feedback loop to make
people successful in that company that's
culture that's what it is so for us it's
like really we really play on the um we
double down on the fact that I'm a
Founder CEO
uh you know been doing this a long time
I'm very committed to it uh when I stand
up there and all meeting which we have
every week and I say we're doing
security that's the first important
thing we're stopping everything else for
security the resonates and I and you
know Tac is cheap right I can at the
same time and like a week later be like
all right I got this new product idea
security is not the most important then
new I mean you got to like walk the walk
and you got to get people around you and
promote leaders in the company that
Express that value too and you can say
that for any kind of
cultural um cultural uh Direction you
want to go but I think it's got to be
very simple and when people try to
complicate it and it's like oh the
culture is bad why is the culture bad
and it's like a like a 22 minute
explanation it's probably over
complicated yeah yeah that's really
good we have people that focus on it
like uh cyber defense team and threat
intelligence team but so the the reality
is though that
the it's always tricky to talk about
past cyber attacks Because by the
definition it's an it's a adversarial
environment and the next attack is
always different so I don't mean to like
say I think the future is always going
to be like the past but most of the
attacks are quite simple um and it's the
the hardest challenge is to cover all of
the holes or all of the issues all of
the identities all of the accounts all
of the admin accounts all of the
computers making sure they're patched
and managed no one ever again could
change but people don't break crypto we
talk about quantum computers and if that
might change really other great
conversation to have the reality is if
you're controlling security for a large
organization your main challenge is
comprehensiveness it's not like
sophistication and so we try to take the
approach how do we solve that like how
do we make it simpler how do we make it
so it's um you know like everyone should
have multiactor
authentication and it's like not it's
not like these people are um incapable
understanding that intellectually it's
just hard to do it's hard to roll it out
if you have a you know like an hour
before I was talking to the chief
Security Office of one of the major
financial services companies in the
world and it's he's a smart person the
challenge is he's got he's got like
75,000 people they all have different
computers different phones different
offices and it's like very complex so we
got it it's like Simplicity and
standardization and how do we flatten
that in the sense of making it more easy
to manage and and so forth well at the
same time though you got to be looking
at what people are doing and you got to
be like um collaborating with other
people in Industry we try to work with
our a lot of our top customers are the
pure cyber companies the crowdstrike
power to networks we work with them to
have thread Intel and share information
the other challenging thing about cyber
is that um is that it's people you know
there's a lot of legal
liability so when you start having cyber
issues the first thing the legal team
wants to do is like don't talk to anyone
and that the reason why is because if
you talk to people there's records and
when you get sued or you're in court
that's going to be in the case and so a
lot of people really clam up and don't
collaborate and communicate it's hard to
get information which impedes the
information sharing and it's to the to
the benefit of the adversaries a lot so
um again that's another real world thing
you might not expect without being
through it a few times I'm gonna switch
gears a bit thinking more to the Future
so you know our final project in this
class which by the way we're going to
talk a little bit more at the end
involves agents and you know I think
every day there's like at least 20
articles that use that term and I'm
curious like in that world one of the
things that I haven't seen enough
discussion on is around identity of
these agents and I'd love to hear your
thoughts as the the leader so this is uh
are all like you know who in the room
knows what a Damon
is yeah so like like yeah like Linux you
know like you put a service up there and
it listens on the network and you can
like talk to it so that's that's an
agent so we've had agents for a long
time
and yeah I mean like it's like not that
revolutionary we have Bots right you
know Bots some slack there's bots so
that's an agent so I think that as you
all know the the the the Breakthrough is
that that you know to the with llms it's
just the conversational interaction it
makes these things much easier to
because like I don't know the UI of a of
a Linux Damon is not great but you can
put a conversational UI on it that's
very very good now so it's basically
like it's almost like how I know this is
real because these things are so if
there's some new trend that's like
really hot and like getting all this
hype but it's kind of like this new
thing that's kind of made up and you're
not really sure like really but this is
a trend that is so valuable it's been
around for 40 years in these service
accounts and these processes that weigh
on demand and do things for you whether
it's the like in the Linux operating
system or Unix or um Bots we know it's
super valuable and now we have this like
catalyzation which is this
conversational interface that really
works and really has great ability to
control these things and then you the
actual work it can do is trainable by
these same llm that's a magic
combination this is real um and these
are really going to be a big deal and
Powerful um and I think that the like a
lot of these things the use cases of
them and the value of them are being
understood and people are really excited
like I talked a bunch of it leaders at
companies and CEOs and people on boards
is like how do we automate more of our
company with a agents and how do we like
supplement our workers or how do we
change our Workforce etc etc um but a
lot of the stuff around it's kind of
like cloud computing you know 15 17 18
years ago it's like how do you actually
secure it how do you make it easy to use
a lot of these things are yet to be
figured out uh and so like if you look
at a lot of these agent Frameworks that
you're going to use right when you do
your final project um Lang chain these
other things um you're going to realize
that like the security in there is a
little bit uh let's put it like not
totally thought out right yeah it's like
you're going to put you're going to
you're going to have your agents going
to log into all these services to do
stuff calendar to schedule stuff or
whatever and it's going to take the
token from that API and maybe just like
put it in memory or put it on the file
system whatever right it's like it's not
great for security perspective because
that machine gets hacked and the hacker
has like all the tokens and again like
it's not like the super sophisticated
breach it's like oh yeah they found the
passwords um so the security needs to be
figured out but that that'll happen you
know we'll help there and other
companies will help there and there'll
be development platforms to build these
things and it's going to be exciting
yeah it seems like a huge huge up
chain honestly uh I've been discouraged
I've been frustrated I've been tired but
I've never seriously thought about
quitting
um never seriously thought about
quitting uh you know the security
breaches were super hard but I think the
hardest time was really early days is
like you know when I thought that oh
I've been working my ass off for four
years and I quit my job and chances are
it's probably not going to work I think
that was the hardest um once you get to
his like there there's still lots of
risks and things we could mess up and
opportunities but
um it feels it feels less ephemeral now
and it has for many years uh which kind
of gives that Foundation
of um stability not it's not stable I
don't mean to say like there's no risk
or anything but it's gives that
foundational stability that's quite you
know comforting compared to the early
days we have another question but it's
great entrepreneurship is great you
should definitely try
it I think the key thing is that it is
great but it's not always as uh romantic
will say that pet Crunch and other yeah
Publications sometimes make it out to be
yeah yeah the um and this you're smart
this probably seems clear obvious to you
but romantic reminded me that it's kind
of like a relationship um meaning that
it's like super like lots of Sparks and
in the beginning everything is great and
then like it's still great but it's just
it's you got to keep working at it and
you got to like stick with it and you
can't um you got to keep investing in it
and if it's one of the I think one of
the most defining characteristics of um
entrepreneurs and people that are
successful is they they don't get bored
like they can they can grind through
through something for a long time
because most companies are a grind and
if you can't if you get bored and fickle
and you want to move on and do something
else uh I would definitely recommend a
different industry like there's lots of
Industries where you can go from Project
to
project like it's why like if you look
at Hollywood I think there a lot of
people get bored in Hollywood they want
to move on it's like kind of like the
movie business right you're like I make
a movie and I work on it for a year and
then I move on y Consulting not us we
keep doing the same thing over and over
well I can tell you I had an honest
thought today like when I was thinking
about this because I was thinking about
this on the drive down here
coincidentally
um and my honest thought was like this
is something like in six months like
we're gonna never hear from
again I love you everyone I love you Sam
Alman and it's just my honest
thought I think I think that there's
like um there it's it's it's
uh all the these things this is a big
deal like Ai and this like training
these models and it's a big deal it's a
big shift and that's why you get these
crazy announcements and I'm not being
negative on it it's like but I just I'm
a little um I think it's likely that you
know it'll kind of drift away and not be
I they'll be like things like it big
Stacks to train these you know big
infrastructure Investments and a lot of
um serious uh decisions to make from the
infrastructure companies and the
platform companies and I I just think
it's likely that probably Fades
away the the challenge so the challenge
is that it's an integration challenge
meaning that you know the folks running
it at Stanford are I'm sure like a lot a
lot of organizations it's super complex
everyone wants their own infrastructure
everyone wants their own apps everyone's
flexibility in devices and their their
challenge is like manage it all and make
it secure and they're like okay so we
basically have to embed this single
login into everything into personal
devices work devices all the crazy stuff
that's in all the different departments
universities are
incredibly there's some companies that
are super standard like when you go to
those companies this is you can get
every computer you want as long as it's
this kind of computer with this kind of
operating system with this kind of
applications University is not like that
super distributed it's one of the
reasons like we're really good at this
is because our bread and butter is like
integrating with all this stuff Macs
Linux Chromebooks and we don't we're not
trying to sell our customers 50 you know
other products that are come along with
identity like collaboration or Cloud
Computing Services we just sell identity
and so we can focus on making sure that
it's very integrated to everything and
that's why we give folks a Fighting
Chance at
this we have not integrated the
infrastructures at all we've kept it
separate on the infrastructure
perspective the integration of the
companies has been GNA sales and
marketing customer support customer
success so more of a business
integration um and I think that the
reason for that is the premise of the
whole thing is is capture more market
share capture more growth um and my
judgment call at the time and still is
true I believe that if you take those
two infrastructures and merge them
together you're going to slow down each
team
you're going to get some cost benefit
some commonality across the compute and
across the security which would be
beneficial you know like more leverage
on you know infrastructure security
Investments but I believe that the um
the slowdown in Innovation wouldn't be
worth it that might not always be the
case but that's how we've done it so
far so I think the hard the biggest hard
skill I would say or maybe it's a soft
skill I don't know you can you can
decide I was starting a company that was
basically selling critical
infrastructure identity management login
for companies they have to trust it they
have to believe it's going to be secure
they believe it's going to work not go
down for maintenance it's the front door
right and
so they had to in the early days
especially they had to believe that I
could do this and so like and it wasn't
uh random I knew when I was thinking
about what area to go into like I tried
to pick an area where as my background
at the time would have an advantage and
this was an advantage of I I would have
because I could look at them at least
and say I built this in sales for us I
know how to do it you can trust me for a
lot of these early buyers that was
important so that was I don't know if
you call that a hard skill because I did
have it was true I was not lying you
know I had built it and like that gave
me some credibility but it was also a
soft skill because this is about trust
and this is about them looking in my
eyes and thinking like I believe this
guy he's not going to like kind of like
be off to the next sale and not make it
work so I my biggest learnings were from
ozero the first one was
um that I think investors are much more
skeptical of m&a than I thought um
they're very smart they realize that a
lot of them aren't successful they
realize that there are challenges
unforeseen and risks and so that was you
know uh a learning I wasn't like totally
shocked but it was a learning um the
other uh the other learning from the
integration was um I think if I had to
do over again I would probably uh go a
little slower on like some of the
business integration um I think we the
first year was the we did the Clos
acquisition and the sales were super
super fast so we made some integration
decisions to really like compound that
growth very broadly and it turns out
that I think a lot of that first year
results were a result of like zero
interest rates in the economy of the
time which mean I meant I think we kind
of did some of the integration steps a
little bit too fast or Too Soon hard to
ding myself too much because it was like
with the information at the time it was
not a crazy idea but in retrospect I
probably would have you know let things
keep things less integrated longer
yeah um I think it's not clear like it's
not clear as much as I would love to
have a crisp answer to this I just
don't because it's back to what I said
earlier I think a lot of the most
pressing issues
are way more basic than how is something
as amazing as this new way of Technology
going to change how we do things because
a lot of the issues that people are
dealing with are very basic um I think
there's all kinds of possibil like I
think one of the um this stuff is going
to be so impactful I think one of the
challenges is just you know companies
like OCTA that have 16 years of history
and 6,000 people and a culture you know
it's it's hard to change and it's hard
to reimagine how things could be done in
the company in the products for sure but
just in the company like we've always
done it this way it's like inertia it's
like we have support people and they do
this and then the business operations
people do this it's like maybe you don't
need that anymore but that's what we do
so that cultural change and that shift
and that adaptability is super important
um but I'm sure that we will find
technology and cyber reasons and um
product ramifications of using this new
technology because it's it's quite I
think it will be quite
impactful I don't think we've had the um
a simple analogy I use I'm sure you know
you guys have heard this or thought
about it but um when
so people forever talked about uh
like basically smartphones right we had
cell phones and then like people could
see that they were getting powerful and
it was really going to be a computer and
smartphone smartphon smartphones um and
then we got the iPhone of course and
everyone thought it was awesome um but
then they did the apps for iPhones and
it was like the apps were all kind of
like stupid it's like we had I remember
we had like a Mr T app that would like
say funny Mr TSS a television character
this guy used to say funny things um and
so like that's kind of like what I feel
like we're are with AI right now it's
like we kind of know it's going to be
big and we got these funny applications
but we haven't found Uber yet where it's
like oh my God I can get a car anywhere
because I had this phone that's like
that ain't Mr
T um so I think that that hasn't
happened yet with AI like the killer use
case that was like totally different
like I didn't even think of that like
that's cool we haven't had that yet and
that's and I'm not like a I don't a lot
of people are Doom and Gloom about AI
I'm not like
that I think it's you know there's we
got to manage it and there's got risks
I'm sure but you know mostly it's going
to be amazing technology and I'm excited
to see what
happens well thank you Todd for taking
the time to hang out with us
today thank you