Today we have uh our co-instructor
Divins inspired approaches to agents and
how the path to AGI requires a
rethinking of how we design, evaluate
and deploy intelligence. Divgar is the
founder and CEO of AGI Inc. a new
applied AI lab redefining AI human
interaction with the mission to bring
AGI into everyday life. Div previously
founded Multicon, the first AI agent
startup developing agents that can
interact with computers and assist with
everyday tasks funded by top Silicon
Valley uh VCs. Deb has spent his career
at the intersection of AI research and
startups and was previously a CS PhD
student here at Stanford focused on RL.
His work spans across various high
impact areas ranging from self-driving
cars, robotics, computer control, and
Minecraft AI agents. Uh with that I'll
hand it to him. So take it away. Uh yeah
uh excited to be here. Great. Um so yeah
excited to be here and uh the topic for
this lecture is uh uh we wanted to like
talk about a lot of like new things that
are happening in the AI world right now.
So there's been a lot of developments
with agents and like all the new models
that are coming out. Um and it seems
like you have like some sort of super
intelligence when it comes to like chat
and reasoning already there uh compared
to like average humans. And it it's
going to be very interesting like over
the next few years as we figure out uh
what does intelligence look like? What
is the uh what is like something like hi
and what's the form factor? How can this
be something that's useful and like how
will this be applied in
society? Cool. Uh so that's like the
first thing uh like we want to touch on
like what does AGI look like? It's like
uh AGI is such a abstract concept right
now. It's like no one has like
visualized it or given it a meaning.
It's like is this some sort of
supercomput? Is it just like chipity but
just like 10x better? Is it something
that's more of a personal companion? Is
it something that's embedded in your
life? And like that's not clear yet. And
like those are like kind of the
questions I think we really need to go
and figure out.
Uh this is one uh diagram on how AI
agents work. So this is architecture
from a open eye researcher Lilian Wang.
She uh recently left and join joined a
new company. Uh so this is showing how
you can think about agents and like how
they can be broken down into like
different like subpaths and there's a
lot of different things uh that you
require to make this agents work. So the
first layer is memory. You need to have
like uh like some sort of short-term
memory. You want to have some sort of
long-term memory. And this is like you
have some sort of shorter presentation
that's maybe like a chat window if you
use something like chat GPD and you
might also have like a personal history
of the user where like okay like this is
maybe like what the user likes this is
what they don't like. Uh the second
thing that you need is tools like you
want this kind of agents to be able to
use uh tools like how humans use tools.
So you want them to be able to use
calculators you want them to be able to
use like calendars, web search, coding
and so on. Uh the third part over here
is like you want to have advanced
planning and that means like you want to
the agents to be able to like use
reflection where like if something goes
wrong they can like have failover
mechanisms error correct and like
recover. You want like selfcriticism and
you want like decomposition where like
you have like chains of thoughts so the
agent can do like their own reasoning
loops. They can also break down a
complex task into sub goals. And the
final fourth ingredient is actions where
like you want these agents to be able to
act uh on your behalf and like go do
things and this is kind of like high
level encapsulates like how uh agents
look like uh fundamentally and this is
maybe like what will like uh as this
systems become power more powerful over
time uh will eventually lead to
something that's like
AGI this is uh one thing uh that we're
also building um um so I recently
started this new AI lab we're called AGI
Inc. Uh, and we're looking at a lot into
like what does AGI look like for
everyday purposes and like how can this
be applied to daily
[Music]
life. Uh, this is one of the demos of uh
some technologies we built in the past.
Uh, this shows an how an AI agent can be
applied in the real world. Um, so this
is uh a bit old and this shows like uh
how an AI agent can be applied to pass a
real driving test in California. And uh
so this is like an actual DMV test uh
that the agent took. Um and then u let
me share the screen and talk about the
setup. So in this screen what's
happening is u
u there's uh someone attempting the the
DMV online test and there's a human who
has their hands over the keyboard.
They're not actually touching the screen
and it's a agent that's going and taking
all the exams. And there's like 40
questions in this test and the agent's
really good. So you can go and like pass
the whole thing and we did this live. So
the DMV was actually like screen
recording uh uh what we're doing. They
were also like watching like the person
on camera. Uh but even then like the
agent was successfully able to evade
like the whole startup and like pass the
exam. Um so this was really fun. We did
this as a white hacking attempt. So we
informed the DMV afterwards uh that we
did this. Uh funnily enough they
actually sent us a driving license
afterwards. Uh so that was really fun
actually. So the at the end the agent is
able to pass and get a pass uh get a
full score on this test here and so yeah
so this is like a very fun experiment
showing like how agents can be applied
in the real world and like there's so
many things that are possible
um in this vein like how can we make
agents more useful apply them in in real
life uh we've been like working on a lot
of like different efforts along with uh
a lot of like the AI community um one of
those things is like agent evaluations
how can we evaluate this kind of agents
in the real world and make sure like we
have standards and benchmarks that
allows us to know okay like how well are
these agents working on like different
websites or different use cases how can
we trust them how can we know okay like
where to deploy them how and how to use
them um another thing we doing have been
doing is agent training can we train
agents uh to be able to do advanced
planning selfcorrection and improve
themselves and that this uses the
combination of like reinforcement
learning and a bunch of other advanced
techniques and finally ly we have also
been looking a lot into like agent
communication like how can you have
agent communicate with other agents and
there's been a lot of like new
breakthroughs in this area recently. So
if you have looked at model context
protocol MCP that's a very new thing
that has been coming out. Uh similarly
like there's a lot of work around like
A2A that's like Google's agent to agent
communication protocol that recently
came out. Uh we also have been working
on some like open source projects uh uh
called agent protocol where you also we
have been allowing other different kind
of agents to communicate to each other.
So you can have a coding agent that can
talk to like a web agent that can talk
to like a API based agent and so on and
that allows you to like do like much
much more complex things than what's
possible with just a single
agent. Cool. Uh so before we dive more
deeper into like okay how a lot of these
things works let's I want to bring about
like why do we need agents like why are
they useful why do we actually want to
go and build them and there's a lot of
things we need to talk think about here
um and I will touch on a lot of
different different topics um in the
introduction going from like the
architectures building like more like
human like agents using computer
interactions maybe like memory
communication and like what are the
future actions
And so like when you think about
building agents, there's a lot of things
uh or questions you have to answer. The
first one is okay like why is this
useful? How can you actually build them?
What are the different building blocks?
And finally, what can you do with them?
And to first answer the why question, uh
we have this key thesis that uh agents
will be more efficient in uh interfacing
with computers in the digital world
compared to humans. And that's the the
reason that we want to go and apply uh
agents to be able to like do things for
us. So you can imagine you have a army
of virtual assistants that are like
fully digital that can go and like do
whatever you want uh on your behalf and
you can just talk to them using a human
interface and that's kind of the vision
we have been like moving
towards. Uh also have a blog post about
this called software 3.0 that you can
check out uh which touches on with some
of the
ideas.
Cool. So we want to go and build agents
because usually like large language
models are not good enough and we want
like action capabilities that allows us
to unlock more productivity and go do
things and this also allows us to build
more complex systems. There's a lot of
techniques involved in actually building
this such as like chaining different
models together uh reflection and bunch
of other
mechanisms and u as I showed before in
the architecture uh on slide two there's
a lot of like different components like
memory actions personalization uh access
to the internet and so
on and finally the questions become like
what are the different applications you
can apply them
There's also a question of why do we
want to build humanlike agents like why
can't we just have API agents or why
can't we have um a bunch of like other
kind of agents you can imagine which are
not mimicking human
interactions and uh one reason we want
to push towards more humanlike agents is
these agents can operate interfaces like
how we do and usually the internet and
the web and computers are designed for
humans so they're they're designed for
like uh uh keyboard and mouse
interaction
So that we can go and like navigate
interfaces. We can like use our
keyboards and if agents are able to like
use interfaces like we do that allows
them to like directly communicate and
like do a lot of things without changing
uh how current software programs work
and that becomes very very effective
because that allows you to like work on
the 100% of the internet uh without any
sort of bottlenecks. If you think about
APIs, there's only like 5% of APIs on
the internet are public that are
accessible and it's very hard to build
agents that are fully reliable over
APIs. And so there's like a lot of
contention between like human like
agents versus API agents and that's like
ongoing battle that's happening right
now. Um second thing is you can imagine
a lot of human like agents as becoming a
digital extension of you. So they can
learn about you. They can have a context
about you. They can do tasks like how
you will do
it. They also have less restrictive
boundaries. Um this kind of human like
agents can handle login. they can handle
payments and they're able to interact
with any of the services without
restrictions in on terms of AP access.
So you don't need to pay for like uh
using an API or you don't need to like
go to like a service provider and ask
them for okay like can you give me
access to this API you can just go and
use an interface how like you normally
do and the final thing is like there's a
very simple action space um the agents
only need to learn how to click and type
and if they're able to do that very
effectively they can generalize to any
sort of
interface and they can also improve over
time so the more you teach them the more
data you can give they can learn from
like user recordings, feedback and
become better and better over
time. And so when it comes to this API
versus more direct computer control
agents, um these are kind of like how we
think about like the pros and cons. API
agents are usually easier to build. Uh
they are more controllable. They are
more safer. Um but APIs are more have
high v variability. So you have to build
like different agents for each API and
then APIs can keep changing. You never
have like a full guarantee that this
agent will always work
100%. When it comes to this more direct
interaction computer control agents uh
there it's easier to take actions in
this case um it's also more free form
interactions because you're not
restricted by the API boundaries but
it's also hard to provide guarantees
because you don't know what the agent
will do. So if anyone here has played
with like agents like operator um it's a
work in progress. It's not like clearly
there there's a lot of like issues that
it runs into and that's kind of the
boundaries where like agents are at
now. There's also like different levels
of autonomy when you think about agents.
Um this is usually goes from level one
to level five. So level one to level two
is when a human is in control and the
agent is acting like a co-pilot. So it's
helping the human. Um so this is
something like if you use like a code
editor like cursor that's a L2 agent
where you have partial automation where
the human is in control. The human is
directing the code but the agent is
helping them. When it comes to like
something like L3 this is where uh
there's still a human fallback mechanism
but the agent is in control. So this is
like if you use like cursor composer or
winds surf or any of the newer code
editors that are more agentic. The agent
is writing most of the code but a human
is monitoring giving it feedback. Okay
this went wrong. can you correct that
for me? Can you fix this issue? And that
is like more for L3 system. And then you
have more advanced systems which are
like L4 and L5. In L4 systems, you don't
have a human in the loop. So it's the
agent that's going and doing everything.
You might still have some sort of like
automated fallback layers. So if you
look at Whimo in SF, that's a L4 system
because the self-driving car is driving
itself, but there's like human operators
that are remotely monitoring it, making
sure like nothing goes wrong. And when
you have a L5 system, in that case
there's no humans in the loop. There's
no monitoring. And the AI agent is able
to operate itself autonomously uh fully
fully
independently.
Okay. So when we are building these
agents, one hard thing is trust. How do
we trust these agents actually going to
go do what we want them to do? How can
we go and deploy them in the real world?
uh to solve this issues. One effort uh
that we have been building is
a a miniature version of the internet
where we have cloned like the top 20
websites on the internet and we are
benchmarking okay like how do agents go
and perform on all these
interfaces. Uh this is actually live so
you can go check it out on really.xyc
XYZ and what we have done is we have
built like uh digital clones of uh
websites like Airbnb and Amazon and Door
Dash and LinkedIn and the agents can go
and navigate this interfaces on
predefined tasks and you can get a final
score. This is uh showing the evaluation
results for GP40.
uh we find that GBD40 actually is not
very good on when it comes to being
agentic and it only reaches 14%
successful uh accuracy in this case. Um
we tried this on like 11 different
environments that we are showing on the
right.
Um what else? And uh that's uh we have
our different environments. We have dish
which is our do- clone and on and so on.
Um so you can actually go and check this
environment out.
We also compare a lot of like uh open
source frameworks um out there. Uh some
of them are like the open computer use
model that's powering operator. Uh we
actually find it's not very good when it
comes to this tasks. Uh so it's only
able to reach maximum 20% accuracy on
some of the environments like uh uh our
email environment or our calendar
environments but on a lot of the other
environments it's not able to actually
go and do really well. Um we also tried
a bunch of other frameworks out there.
Uh stage hand if you're famili if you
have seen that it's a open source
framework for automating web agents uh
browser use and one of our own custom
agents which we're calling agent zero
and we find like like agents are still
like early when it comes to like
actually automating a lot of these
interfaces and we are able to reach
maybe like I would say like up to 50%
success rate but a lot of the agents are
actually failing when you are applying
them in the a lot of these real world
websites.
Similarly, we benchmark all the
different models that are available
including including all the closed
source APIs and all the open source
models and um we find again on tasks
most models are doing like decently well
but no no one is like really really good
right now. The maximum success we have
seen is with like claude 3.7 where it
can reach around 40% accuracy. Um Gemini
2.5 and 03 follow very closely with it.
the other models like tend to taper
off. And so the interesting learning has
been for us is that a lot of these
models are not fully ready to be
deployed in the real world because if uh
you have say like a agent that's powered
by cloud and then you're applying that
you can only expect a 41% success rate
that this will actually go do what you
want it to do and that's not good
enough. And this brings a question okay
like what is it that is required to make
this agency even better? how can they
like improve and how can they be applied
uh for your actual practical use
cases and so this brings us to our next
topic for the lecture uh which is like
how can we train AI um agentic models so
how can we have models that are more
custo custom fine-tuned and are better
on this agentic
tasks this is one of our past works
called agent Q which is a self-improving
agent
So this is agent Q. That's a system that
can self-improve. It can like learn by
uh corrections and planning. And how the
system works is it's able to go and
selfcorrect itself. So whenever it makes
a mistake, it can save that mistake in
its past memory and it's able to like
use that to like uh do a lot of like
trial and error learning similar to
humans. So like suppose uh the first
time you learn how to ride a bike, you
make a lot of mistakes, you follow a lot
of clients, but over time you're able to
improve your policy and go and like do
that really well. Um we apply similar
mechanisms to make this agents actually
work really really well in in the real
world. And so what's happening in the
system is the agent can like uh explore
the space of interfaces and uh see okay
like what are the things that it did
that went wrong what are the things that
went right and it's able to use
reinforcement learning to self-improve
and become better and
better. So agent Q combines a lot of
different techniques. The first method
is Monteol research. uh this is borrowed
from like uh other RL techniques like
AlphaGo that allow you to plan over like
search space of U tasks and like uh
unlock like advanced
reasoning. A second thing that we do is
selfcritic mechanisms. So the agent can
like self-verify and get feedback
whenever it makes a mistake and it's
able to learn from that feedback.
And finally we use uh RL AIF techniques
like DPO uh direct preference
optimization to be able to like improve
the agent uh using RL and by combining
all these three techniques together we
able to build like some very powerful
systems. Um agent Q is uh also available
on archive as a research paper. So you
can go and check it out.
Okay, for the sake of time, I will skip
some of the lectures here. Um, but how
agent K normally works is we have this
Monte Carlo research where
uh the agent is exploring the different
states. It's estimating like uh rewards
on okay if we were to visit like this
state what's expected value of the
future uh predicted
reward and based on that it's able to
like uh improve its prediction model
like like should we go take this path or
a different path in the
tree and then over time the agent can
become very good at exploring the right
states and figuring out like what are
the right parts in the state space and
what are the wrong
ones. We also do like self critic
mechanism. Um in this case what happens
is if you have a particular task in this
case where like say a user says like
book me a reservation for a restaurant
for the chiao on open table for two
people on August 14, 2024 at 7 p.m. And
like this is the current like state of
the screen where you can see the
screenshot. Then the agent can go and
propose a bunch of different actions. So
it can choose to go and select the date
and time. It can choose to also like
select the number of people and then
open the date selector. It can instead
search for Terra Italy uh Silicon Valley
restaurant and type that in the search
bar or it can maybe like decide to go to
the open table
homepage. And how the self critic
mechanism works is like all these
proposed actions are passed to a critic
network and the critic
uh LM is able to go and predict like
okay what's the best action to take and
it's able to give a ranking order okay
like this is the best action that we
should go and use this is like so this
is like rank one this is rank two and
this is rank three and based on that we
can go and optimize the system to take
the correct actions and improve over
And finally we use like uh reinforcement
learning from human feedback uh where we
used methods like gRPO and DPO which are
different algorithms to be able to like
use all the um the failures and like
successful trajectories you've collected
so far and improve the agent over them.
And so DPO is a is a special um
technique uh based on RLF where you can
train LM uh using preference datas of
like failures and successes and use that
to improve the model
overall. And so this is how agent Q
works where we create this multicolored
research to create like uh trajectories
of successes and
failures. We can then use uh selfcritic
mechanisms to identify uh what are the
proposed actions that actually succeeded
and failed and then we able to pass them
through DPO to actually go and optimize
the
network. This is an example of how this
works.
So the agent starts in like uh the first
state and the task in this case is we
want to go and um book a restaurant
reservation on open table. Um so first
it makes a mistake and goes to the the
homepage. Then it recognizes that made a
mistake and can backtrack. So the blue
arrow here shows that it's going and
backtracking.
then it can go and navigate to the right
restaurant. In this case, if the agent
accidentally makes a mistake and choose
the incorrect date, then it can again
backtrack, recover back, open the date
selector, choose the right
date, open the seat selection, and then
finally come to the reservation. And so
this is kind of how the system is
learning over time. Um, it's making a
lot of mistakes, but it's saving the
mistakes and over time improving on
them.
We tried agent Q in a lot of real world
scenarios um including like OpenT actual
reservations. Uh so we actually spun up
thousands of or I would say like more
like 100 thousands of bots that are ran
on Open Table and like used our method
to like create agents that are able to
book restaurants and like um make
reservations and do a bunch of other
things. And we tried this with a lot of
different methods and models out there.
Uh so we tried GBD 40 and then we found
like on this open table reservation
tasks uh we are only able to reach
around 62.6% accuracies. When it comes
to something like DPO uh the accuracies
actually go to something like
71%. When we try agent Q uh we are able
to like make this
um work much much better. So we are able
to reach 81% accuracy without any MCTS
as part of the method. And when we apply
the whole technique with MCTS and DPO
and like uh the self critic mechanisms
we actually able to reach close to
95.44% accuracies and uh this is using a
lot like self-arning to for the agent to
improve itself. Uh this takes usually
less than one day of training for the
agent to go from I would say here like
20% accuracy that's 18.6 that's roughly
20% all the way to 95.4. Um so that's a
4x improvement in like agent performance
uh in lesson
Monday. All
right, cool. Um as the next topic, uh
I'll touch on memory and
personalization.
So one way to think about AI agents uh
is that they
are taking information processing them
and like
and
okay so imagine like you have a model
what a model is doing it's taking some
like prompts so it's taking some like
language tokens and outputting like some
new language tokens and so this is
acting like similar to processor where
you if you have a CPU what happens is
you have some instructions which are
usually binary encoded that go into the
CPU and then you have some like
instructions that come out which are
also binary encoded and then you do a
loop over them again and again uh and
that's how like normal computers work
you can do a very similar thing and have
this abstraction of a AI model as acting
similar to a computer chip where you
have uh language tokens that are going
in that are encoded in the prompt and
you have like language tokens coming out
And this allows you to think about like
a AI model as being a processor that's
operating over natural
language. So this is something that you
can think about GBD4 for example going
and doing
this. Um this is similar to some of the
older processor like my 32 that use
32-bit instructions. Right now if you
look at GPD4 uh we are able to reach
like very big context lengths.
Um so that's very interesting and when
like GPD4 initially came out it was
constrained to like 8K tokens. Now we
have 32K tokens and 128K tokens and like
1 million tokens. So the context length
of this models is just increasing and
increasing over
time and as the context length increases
that also allows us to
have a question from online. Can you
speak to the compute budget for the
dayong run like was it eight H100s or
like a cluster
the results you show? Yes. Yes. Yes. So
that was all H100s actually. Uh we train
the whole models on uh 50 H100s in less
than one day. Gotcha. Uh and then one
question from before. Um as AI agents
increasingly emulate human behavior,
what protocols do you foresee being
implemented to help users distinguish
between AI and humans in conversation?
Yeah, that's very interesting. I think
that becomes a question of security of
how can we identify is whether it's a
human or agent. Uh it's actually a very
hard question right now because you
actually have voice agents that are
effectively able to mimic humans and are
able to pass as humans and that's
actually happening in the real world
right
now. Uh over time we will need like
human proof of identity. So this could
be like biometrics. Uh this could also
be combination of uh maybe like some
sort of like personal data or like some
sort of like password or secrets that
only you know and you can use that to
authenticate that you're talking to an
actual human and not an
agent.
Cool. Any more questions or Yeah. So you
know Berkeley just published a paper
five professors
student why do multi- aent system fail
right so they did some comprehensive
study first of all they say m has been
there for more than 20 years right you
have distributed systems transaction
processing so we have we are just having
AI covered by by the same name and uh so
so far I really haven't seen anything
new except for you have a agent which
instead of just having API people coding
all the logic in the program you have a
agent will be able to do something uh
you're given a prompt will give you some
results right so how can you just
putting all agent together the
intelligence suddenly elevated so
communicating between agents my point is
just have communication between agent is
exactly the same as mas before 20 years
ago I collaboration between agents is
only vehicle to anyway intelligence but
I'm missing that part today in lecture
correct uh this is actually something
that's coming uh next uh but just to
answer your
question the biggest issue is just to
elaborate correct what happens is when
all these agents are communicating using
natural language that causes a lot of
miscommunication where like like maybe
your agent got the wrong instruction or
failed to understand what's happening
and the more agents you had the more
communication overhead is there. So you
can imagine if you have a aentic system
with n different aents then there's n
squ communication loops and so like the
amount of error in that system increases
like uh as quadratic and that makes that
allows for like a lot of different
mistakes that can happen. I'm suggesting
you to book
me that all pretty much all the problems
solved 13 chapters of the book.
Great. Yeah
totally. Yeah, that's could be very
interesting also for the audience
here. So let's come back to this. Um, so
one way to think
about agents is when you have this
transform model, the transform model is
acting as this processor. So it's taking
this input prompts and it's giving out
the output
prompts. And what you want to do is you
want to be able to like have a memory
system. So you want to have something
like a file disk or RAM where you are
saving what's happening and being able
to process that over time. So you want
to have repeated operations. So you do
for the first pass over a model you get
some output tokens. You can save them in
a random like system and then you have
like some like new instructions that
come out. Okay, like now here's step two
of the plan. Coexecute that. Here's step
three of the plan. Here's step four of
the plan. And that looping behavior this
is what's in a sense giving rise to like
agents where you can imagine this
is the transformer is the processor the
memory system and the instructions and
the planning are acting similar to the
file system and the RAM and so they
are overall like giving rise to this
computer architecture where you have um
the agent acting as like a computer
system with memory
uh processors which is the compute and
then being able to use like browsers and
actions and multiodility which can be
like inputs like audio and voice and so
on.
Okay, when we think about long-term
memory, there's based on the analogy
before, you can think of this as similar
to a disk. Um, where you want a user
memory that's long lived and persistent
and so that you can like save context
about the user. You can like load that
on the fly whenever you want to. There's
different mechanisms uh for long-term
memories. Uh the prevalent one is
embeddings. So you have retrieval models
that can go and fetch the right user
embeddings on the fly. Um so if I have a
question like okay like does this uh
person Joe uh is he allergic to
peanuts then can the system go and find
out and if we have a lot of user data
about the user then we can use a retable
model to to do like embedding lookup
find out okay like if this is something
that we already know about the user or
not and based on that make a right
judgment and this is something that is
very important and you are able to see
early traces of this in systems like
chbd right now. Um there's still a lot
of open questions when it comes to
long-term memory. Uh the first one is
hierarchy. Um how do we decompose memory
into like more uh graphical structures
where you can have uh temporal
persistence. You can have more
structures. And you might also want to
think about memory as something that is
adaptable because human memory is
usually not static. It's changing over
time. And so you also want to think
about when you have agent memory, how
can it change? How can it be dynamic?
How can it self adjust? Because the
systems are also learning. They're
improving. And what does this dynamic
memory systems look
like? Cool.
And with memory like leads to
personalization
um where uh the goal with having
long-term memory is that you can
personalize this agents to the user. Um
and they're able to understand what you
like, what you don't like, and they're
aligned with their preferences. Um, so
if you have this uh case of like maybe
someone is allergic to peanuts and you
want to have an agent that's ordering
food on Door Dash, then you want it to
be personalized so it doesn't
accidentally order something that you're
allergic to and how can you go and build
that and everyone has different
preferences, likes and dislikes. So when
you're designing agents, it's very
important to actually make sure that you
can account for this. So there might be
a lot of explicit personalization
information that is that you can collect
like like what does the user like? Are
they allergic to something? What are
their favorite dishes? uh what seat
preferences they have if they're flying
um and so on. There's also a lot of
implicit preferences. So there's a lot
of things around like like which brand
do you like? Do you like IDAS versus
Nike? Um if there were like 10 items on
a list like suppose you're looking for
like a housing which uh which one do you
prefer and why and those things are very
implicit. So they're not explicitly
known and then there there are
mechanisms where you can collect a lot
of this implicit preferences and then
personalize over time.
There's a lot of challenges when you're
building this personalization systems.
Uh the first one is just user privacy
and trust. How do you actually go and
act actively collect this information
and how do you get people to give it
that to
you? There's different methods you can
go and use to actually collect this
information. So one is just actively
active learning where you're explicitly
asking the user for their preferences.
You're asking them okay like are you
allergic to something or do you have the
seat preference and so on and there
might also be like passive learning
where the if you can like record the
users and see what they're doing then
you're able to passively learn from
their preferences maybe this person
likes Nike shoes because like that's
where uh what we have seen them do on
the computer and the agent is learning
from your behavior and become better and
better and you can learn to personalize
by supervised fine tuning where you are
collecting a lot of interactions this
can also be through human feedback where
you can get thumbs thumb or thumbs down
and use that to like improve okay like
this this agent go and do the right
thing. Um and this is something similar
to chat GPD where if you like the chat
uh outputs then you can give it a thumbs
up. If you don't like it you give it a
thumbs down and you can then this can be
used to like personalize the system over
time. Okay. So now going to agent to
agent
communication. Uh one question online.
How do you do evaluations on the
performance of agents that collaborate
with humans and is it a moving target?
At what point are is a human performance
redundant and agents can be fully
autonomous? I would say I'll say it's a
hard question. You just have to go and
build benchmarks. Uh because it's very
hard to know what's going to happen in
the real world. Um right now I would say
like uh based on like a lot of like
current state of evaluations and like
what I showed before like agents are not
fully there. The most successful agents
we have seen so far are coding agents.
So if you have um uh your whatever like
intelligent code editor um and you can
already see the traces like they are
automating a lot of engineering for for
you already that you don't have to go
and write a lot of boiler plate code or
you don't have to like spend a lot of
your own time fixing books. So at some
point we'll see this thing where like
humans become more like uh managers and
we giving them feedback. We giving them
direction okay like we want this uh like
suppose you have like systems of
different agents. So you give them okay
like I want agent one to go and do this
agent to go and do this so on see what
the final output is and over over using
that uh improve the overall like uh the
generation process that you are going
towards um and so this is likely what's
going to happen is like the agentic
systems will become better and better
executors where like the humans become
the managers for the systems of
agents.
Okay,
cool. So when it comes to agent to
communication um we think about like
multi- aent
uh architectures and multi- aent systems
where you have all this like cute little
like digital robots that can go and talk
to each other, communicate and like go
do your work in a very coordinated
coordinated and streamlined
manner. There's reasons that you want to
go and build multi-en systems. The first
one is
paralization. Um by dividing a task into
smaller chunks and having like uh
multiple agents like if you have n
agents instead of one agent, you can
improve the overall like speeds and
efficiencies. The second thing is
specialization. If you have like
different specialized agents, so you
have a maybe like a spreadsheet agent
and you have a slack agent and you have
a web browser agent, then you can also
route different tasks to different
agents. Each agent can become really
really good at their tasks. And this is
similar to like uh having like a like a
degree in a specific major or having an
occupation specializing in that
occupation. There's a lot of challenges
when it comes to agent agent
communication. Um the biggest one is u
that this kind of communication is
lossy. Um when you have a one agent
commun communicating to another agent,
it's possible that it might make a
mistake. So like it's like uh this is
similar to what happens in human
organizations. Maybe your manager will
ask you to go do something but you maybe
misunderstood them and like did
something different or they were like oh
like why does this happen? And similarly
like agent to agent communication is
also fundamentally lossy uh where like
whenever you are communing information
from one agent to another you're losing
some percentage of that information and
that allows for mistakes to like
propagate in that system and become like
uh increasingly more prevalent.
And uh there's different mechanisms for
multi-ented system. This is a very novel
field right now. Like people are still
trying to figure this out. No one has
actually cracked this right now. Um what
you want to do is you want to like build
the right system of hierarchies where
like you might have manager agents that
are working with like worker agents. You
might have managers of manager agents
and you might have like uh maybe like
flat agents organizations where like
maybe like one manager is managing
hundreds of agents or it could be like a
big like uh uh vertical tree where you
have like maybe like like 10 different
hierarchies of agents that are managing
each other. And so a lot of the systems
are possible and this just depends on
the task or what you're going and
specializing
on. And the biggest challenge with this
kind of systems is like how do you
exchange communication effectively
without losing that information? How do
you build syncing primitives? Like how
can uh communication from one agent
that's very far away from the maybe like
another agent in the hierarchy go and
like um be communicated very very
effectively across the
chain. There's a couple of frameworks
out there that are looking to solve
these problems on how do we make this
communication protocols robust and how
can we had mechanisms to reduce this
miscommunication. Uh a big one in this
part is MCP which is model context
protocol. Uh this is a protocol that
came from anthropic um that a lot of
people are using right now. It's a
simple wrapper around APIs. So what does
it it does is it gives you like a
streamlined standard format around each
API. Um and by creating an MCP wrapper
uh around your service. So this could
maybe like you have a file server
service that's like exposes an API. You
can create like MCP wrapper for your
file server or maybe for your email
client or for your maybe your Slack
client or something running on your
computer. Then all this MCP connected
servers can go and communicate with each
other and like uh uh do things for you.
And so this allows for very effective
communication where you are able to
control the routing and like make the
systems modular. So you're able to plug
in like new services as you want
to. Similarly uh another framework in
this space is agent to agent protocol.
So this is a new protocol that came from
Google uh very recently uh that's
allowing for agents to also cocom other
agents and add a lot of reliability and
fallback
mechanisms and um I'm not sure how many
people here in the room have used
MCPS.
Okay. Yeah, not many. Okay. Okay. Cool.
So MCPS are actually very cool like what
they are doing is uh they are
abstracting your APIs and making them
very like very very modular so that you
can go and plug in a plug your API into
an MCP protocol and once it's wrapped
around that then you can go and like
interconnect it to any other service on
the on that's supported by MCPS. So it's
kind of becomes
um in a sense like having a standard
interface for communication for your uh
different uh services or applications
you have and exposing them and like
letting them connect and talk to each
other. So similar to like how you have
something like HTTPS for communication
on the normal internet, MCV becomes like
an interesting protocol for
communication to happen uh over
different
agents and yep so if you have like a
client like cloud or replet or some
other model um you can connect that to
servers that are supporting the NCV
protocol. You can have like bunch of
like different services. Each services
could be like some sort of data tool
like a database API or pretty much else
and they can all interconnect and like
do like modular things for
you and because MCPS are not dependent
on the the spec of your API um they can
allow you to absorb a lot of changes and
add this level of modularity and
abstraction by standardizing the whole
interface.
You can also have like dynamic tool
discovery because uh you can find
different MCP servers uh that are
exposed in some sort of directories and
then you can also like plug in MCP
servers that you like and like connect
to
them. So you can plug in new tools, try
them
out and uh you can route information
based on like what you want to
do. Okay.
Um finally like touching on like uh some
of the issues when it comes to agent
existence. Um so so far we have seen a
lot of different things. Okay like how
can this agents work? How can we
evaluate them? How can we train them?
How can we think about communicating
with different agent
systems? And uh even though a lot of the
things are very interesting, a lot of
these things are taking off, there
remains a lot of like key problems in
the space uh that we still have to solve
for this agent to be practical for them
to be applied uh in everyday life and
for them to become useful for you. Uh
the biggest one is just reliability that
the systems have to become very very
reliable like they need to be close to
99.9% reliable if you're giving them
access to your uh payments and your bank
details for example or maybe they're
connected to your emails calendars and
whatever services and then you want to
really trust them that you don't want
the systems to go rogue and maybe like
post something wrong for you on socials
on your Twitter or your LinkedIn or you
don't want them to go and create a havoc
or or make a wrong transaction for on
your behalf and so that becomes like
like how can you trust an agentic system
that's operating autonomously and that's
where like reliability becomes a big
thing. Uh second issue with autonomous
agents is looping like this agents can
go uh do something wrong so they can get
get stuck in a loop and they might just
go and repeat that process again and
again. So if you give them a task and
like maybe like if you remember like the
uh the restaurant booking task uh that I
showed before and like maybe like the
agent uh went to the wrong restaurant
and it got stuck and maybe just trying
to do the same thing again and again. it
doesn't know what to do and that kind of
issues can happen in a lot of the agents
where you might end up wasting a lot of
money in compute and it's very important
to be able to like figure that out and
correct that and that leads to a lot of
use cases around like how can we test
agents how can we properly benchmark
them in the real world on a lot of like
different use cases and make sure like
we are learning from that and how can we
also once we deploy the systems be able
to like observe them and that becomes
like how can we know what is happening
can we monitor them online can we have
some sort of like safety um which could
be based on audit trails that we can
audit all the operations that this agent
has done so far and we can have maybe
also have human overrides that if
something goes wrong we have some sort
of human fallback where maybe like a
remote operator can take control of the
agent and correct it fix it or maybe you
are able to go and like rightly take
control and fix it. Uh this is similar
to like autopilot in Tesla. So when
you're driving autopilot maybe like you
see like okay something uh maybe it's
going going to go do something wrong and
you can take over control and override
the system. Um and that becomes very
interesting when you're thinking about
real world deployment um of
agents. Uh cool. Okay. So that was uh
yeah so that was the whole lecture on
agents. Uh sorry there was like uh some
things that were a bit messy. Uh yeah we
had to put together some like final
slides. Uh happy to take questions and
yeah go on. So when you see like an
accuracy say like
so when you see accuracy of say like 40%
or something on a task over the course
of a day um do you think that there's a
plan to get to you know 99 or
99.999 and do you have a thought just is
that just iterations on research or is
it actually things that you need to try?
Uh so I would say like this is
definitely possible especially with like
reinforcement learning and like uh like
we I showed the agent Q method before.
So right now a lot of these models like
even if you have like cloud sonnet or
GP4 GP40 or Gemini they're not trained
on this agentic interfaces tasks. So
that's why like they're kind of they're
working zero shot. So they're not never
trained in their distribution uh
training set on actually going and
optimizing these problems. And so when
they encounter this like new interfaces
or this kind of new tasks in the real
world they often fail. But if you're
able to like train the systems directly
to work on this task using reinforcement
learning and like collections and like
self-improvement then you can actually
reach like very very high accuracies. Uh
so in the open table task with agent Q
we reach like 95% accuracies and if you
go keep and going and training the
systems you can like fully saturate them
like reach close to like 99.9%. The hard
thing becomes is there's a diversity of
tasks. So I can imagine there's like
millions of websites and if you want to
create an agent that's using 99.9% on
each website that's a hard challenge and
uh and that's uh something I think
that's very interesting like how can you
build a generalized agent that can work
on the whole internet that can
generalize to everything maybe in the
future you will have agents that can do
like automate all of voice calling all
of like computer control uh maybe like
they can also use all of the APIs and
everything and something like that is
possible theoretically it's just like
very hard to build out.
Yeah. Do you know whether AI agents are
able to solve captures? Uh, they can.
What do you think the implications of
that are for like how the internet's
going to work in the next 10 years?
Um, yeah, it's definitely very
interesting. I would say it's a cat and
mouse game. So, if you have seen like
the new generation of capt, they're
becoming harder and harder to solve. Um,
and I think like it's very hard to beat
this because like if a human can do it,
theoretically like a agent can also go
and do the same thing. Um so so over
time I think we'll have to just figure
out like a better methods of identity.
Biometrics can be a big part of that.
Like if you're able to use fingerprints
or uh some sort of 2FA mechanisms then
we know like this is an actual human not
an agent.
Mhm. Yeah.
So in the there's this article called AI
2027 that you probably heard of that you
know outlined you know like where AI
research is going to go and what might
happen and in 2027 after 27 uh when you
know AI we automate programming and then
we automate AI research and you know
after your lecture I was wondering do
you think we could automate the process
of creating AI agents because from what
I understand the main bottleneck is how
am I going to access UIs, APIs. How am I
going to be able to access data that is
enclosed in those like I guess complex
and somewhat dynamic systems? So, what
if very simply someone designed an agent
that could that was optimized to
vectorize APIs and UIs and then you
designed an agent that was optimized to
train agents on different vectorized
data sets because they're like specific
architectures that you can use to train
agents whatever. Do you think we will
see in the future people
automating with
confidence our process of creating AI
agents making all these niche specific
AI agents that we're seeing on the
market obsolete? Um yeah absolutely I
absolutely think so. So this is going to
happen and um I think it's already
happening in the bigger labs. So if you
have like labs like open they have a lot
of research aents. uh there's also like
papers from like if you have seen from
Sakana AI people are working on like AI
research uh agents that can go and write
research papers and like train models
and do a bunch of things. Uh so it's
totally possible for agents to go and
self-improve and like build other agents
and like you can have a whole process on
like how can how that can happen and
definitely like it's possible to like
train on a lot of this like data sources
and APIs and find ways to like represent
them and like uh collect the right sets
of datas and improve that. Um I I I do
think that seems to be the future of a
lot of like maybe hard research uh
especially around like protein designs
and like a lot of like hard sciences. So
we'll definitely see a lot of that
happen.
Hi Greg, nice to meet you again. Um just
to give you context, we're building like
the Slack for AI agents. Basically, it's
like Uber for AI agents, right? So, I've
been working for agents on the agents
for a long time. The biggest problem
with agents has been, as you said,
reliability and hallucination. Um, the
first thing is the first thing we try to
work on is how do we prevent agent
prevention from hallucinating? Um, the
next thing is what models we're best at
executing actions. So, for my for my
research, we realized that um Claude is
great, right? Um better stills we have
um GP at the end. So we have like just
like Slack. So we have like a team of
agent doing work and then the one that
does the action seem to be GP agent
because we struggle with some agents
doing as you said um um GPT 40 is great
at you know taking action and other
models of GPT seem to not work well and
plot and other stuff. So I think the
biggest challenge with building agents
is also the third one is the fact that
end users can't take one hit. So my wife
here doesn't give like if I give her to
test the product and he makes one
mistake there's no space for
reinforcement learning in the sense that
if I say book my flight like I told
manos to do yesterday and he made one
mistake I lost trust. So the problem is
to work in the real world our agents
should prevent making mistake in the
real world. So that brings us to sandbox
which I I love what you're doing with
sandbox and doing clones of this
website. The challenge with sandbox is
you can't clone all the website on the
internet and where human excel is the
fact that if given a new task they
figure their way around. So these are
challenges that um we we we have with
agent and I'm happy if you can talk more
about it or we can talk about later. Uh
totally totally just get a g gist of it.
What's the exact question there? So I
think the question is how do we make
them ready for the real world right? Um
we have um body which does good job with
calling but makes mistakes. Um we have
um email agent my own that went stop got
stopped in a loop and kept he sent email
five times to an investor. Um we have um
coding agent that wiped up 3,000 lines
of code for me yesterday. I had to redo
it. So we have these challenges in the
real world and people like my wife are
not going to take one shot hit and they
will just stop using it. So I think the
question is how do we prevent agent from
hallucinating right? Yeah. So it's
definitely a like a hard problem where
like you can go and like keep improving
the agents. Um even if you look at like
maybe uh a lot of like the initial
models that came out like when you had
like the first versions of uh like GBD3
and so on they hallucinate a lot but
like as you have bigger models uh that
like uh more parameter size and they
train on more data uh they start
hallucinating less. So like if you see
the new generation of models GB4 and
claude um I think like over time I think
as you figure out how to make better
foundation models a lot of this errors
in the systems go down uh especially
hallucinations and other things that can
happen uh you just require a lot of like
monitoring and evaluations and like a
lot of testing. Um and this also becomes
very domain specific. So like if you're
working on something that's a domain
specific problem and you're like okay
like like you want an agent that can
work 99.9% on this domain then you what
you want to do is like you want to cate
the right test cases. So you can be like
okay here's thousand scenarios that we
really really go and care about. Can we
go and test this agents on this thousand
scenarios all the time which could be in
production when you're like actually
running this with your users or this
could be like some sort of offline
simulation where you're like daily
testing. Is there any regressions in the
system? What happens if you change a
prompt like what will this look like?
And if you're able to build a lot of
like very robust testing then you can
like also verify okay like your
accuracies are going up and and and then
it kind of becomes like okay can you
find tune this aent to become better and
better for your use cases. Um so I think
I would say the correct answer is a
combination of like like models to
become better and better over time so
you can just simplicity trust them more
as new model comes out and the second
thing becomes is like just you want to
have like very domain specific testing
and evaluation. So like for your own use
case, can you go and have like some sort
of ways to rank which model is doing
what? How good is it and make the right
judgment and be able to like fine-tune
and like do use like reinforcement
learning and other techniques to like
make them better over time.
small because I think the problem
large I don't think you need bigger
brains you just need
small language model
um so just question is what do you think
a small language model versus large four
agents specifically yeah so that's
Interesting question. Um, also we are
already seeing some hints of this. So if
you look at a lot of the newer models,
they're trained on reasoning traces and
uh we have found like you can actually
train smaller models on reasoning traces
and have like better accuracies. Uh so a
lot of the newer like GBD4 models like
all the GBD40 and like all the new
series of like 03 mini and so on they're
actually distilled uh small models but
they're just like fine-tuned using
reinforcement learning and the
techniques to uh be very good at
reasoning and so we're already seeing
that with all the new generation of like
uh all the thinking models that are
coming out and all the 01 and 03 series.
So that's showing this that smaller
models with better reasoning better
processing is actually the right answer.
Um it'll be interesting to see like how
far can you push the limits and like
what will this look like is like like
maybe like over this year uh what are
the best accuracies we can expect from
this kind of reasoning things can we
actually go and be like PhD level at
mathematics and like uh even like super
intelligence um on a lot of this like
specific domains I think the lit test is
um real world and my approach
architecture which I think may work is
the manager manager agent could be large
language model then the worker agents
could be small language models because I
think there's distillation happening
when they're collaborating in a like a
team um yeah what the last question is
regarding
memory when the analogy you gave with
respect to a computer we have random
access memory we have the room and then
we have the you know hard drive right
with AI agents right now I just think
they have random access memory and with
me zero we are just giving it room. I
don't think they have the hard drive and
this the consciousness right while they
working. I think that's a challenge. I
would like to know how do we implement
that kind of system to make it sort of
like a computer.
Um yeah, that's again an interesting
question like I'll be curious if you
actually try and experiment and like see
how that
works. Like I would say there's no
straight answer to this. It just depends
on what you're building, what your
applications are. Um, and then just
depending on what you're doing like
there can be different size of models
that might work better. If you're doing
a coding task, you might want like a
more of a coding model versus like if
you're doing something more chat based
or actions and so on. And I I think you
just have to like find the right uh
ingredients uh in a sense like the right
components uh for your application and
like go and build out. Yeah. So there's
no right answer to it in a sense. Yeah.