okay I should try and get
started okay so what we're going to do
today is we're going to try and um do
everything else that you need to know
about word vectors and start to learn a
teeny bit about new Nets and then we'll
kind of get much further into sort of
doing more with the math of new or Nets
next week so this is the general plan um
so I'm going to sort of uh sort of
finish up from where I was last time
with optimization Basics then look a
little bit more about word to V and word
vectors and then some of the variants of
word to v um and then I'm going to
briefly consider alternatives sort of
like what can you get from just counting
words in different ways um then we're
going to go on and talk a little bit
about the evaluation of word vectors um
the topic of word sensor that already
came up a couple of times um last time
when people were asking questions and
then towards the end um start to
introduce the idea of classification
doing new classification and um what new
networks are about which is something
that they'll then expand on more in the
second
week um before I get into that just
notes on course um organization um so
remember the first assignment is already
out and it's it's due before class next
Tuesday um so then um our python review
session is going to be taught this
Friday um 3:30 to 4:20 it's not going to
be taught here it's going to be taught
in gates bo1 the gates basement um and
encourage everyone again to um come to
office hours and help sessions they've
already started they're listed on the
website um we're having these sort of um
office our help sessions in classrooms
with multiple Tas so um just turn up if
you're on campus and you can be helped
and if you are on campus we'd like you
to just turn up that we do also have a
zoom option for Stanford online
students um finally I have office hours
which I have not yet open but I will
open sometime tonight um they're going
to be on Monday afternoons now obviously
given the number of people not everyone
can make it into my office hours and I'm
going to do these by appointment so
they're by 15minute appointments on
kendley um but you know I'm very happy
to talk to some people um and you know
uh I put this little note at the end
saying don't hog the slots um some
people think it'd be a really good idea
if they really work out how to sign up
every week for an office hour session
than me with me and that's sort of a
little bit antisocial um so um
think about that um okay so at the end
of last time I did a sort of bad job of
trying to write on write on slides of
working out the derivatives of word to
be um and hopefully you could read it
much more clearly in the the version
that appears on the website where I was
doing it at home more carefully um so
that was saying that we had this lock
function and our job was to work out its
derivatives which would tell us which
direction to go to walk downhill um and
so I didn't really quite finish the loop
here so you know we have some cost
function that we want to minimize and
then we work out the gradients of that
the gradient of that function to work
out which direction is downhill and then
the simplest algorithm is then that we
that we work out the direction downhill
we walk a little bit in that direction
ction and then we repeat we work out the
gradient at this point we walk downhill
a little bit and we keep on going and
we'll get to the minimum and with a sort
of a one-dimensional function like this
it's sort of very simple we're just
walking down hill but when we have a
function of many many dimensions when we
calculate the gradient at different
points we might be starting to um walk
in different directions and so that's
why we need to do calculus and have
gradients and so this gives us the basic
algorithm of gradient
descent um and so under the gradient
descent algorithm um what we're doing is
that we've got um our loss function J
we're working out its gradient um and
then we're taking a little bit of a
little multipli of the gradient so that
Alpha is our step size or learning rate
um and that's normally Alpha is a very
small number number something like 10- 3
or 10-4 or maybe even 10- 5 so we're
taking a really little bit of the
gradient and then we're subtracting it
from our parameters to get new
parameters and as we do that we will
walk downhill and the reason why we want
to have a small learning rate is we
don't want to walk too fast so if from
here we worked out the gradient and said
it's in this direction and we just kept
on walking we sort of might end up way
over here or if we had a really big step
size we might even end up at a worse
Point than we started with so we want to
take little steps to walk downhill and
so that's the very basic gradient
descent algorithm now the very basic
gradient descent algorithm we never use
what we actually use is the next thing
up which is called stochastic gradient
descent so the problem is for the basic
gradient Cent algorithm we've worked out
um for an entire set of data um what the
objective function is and what the um
slope at the point of evaluation is and
in general um we've got a lot of data in
which we're Computing models so simply
trying to calculate our objective
function over all of our data for our
model the training data for the model
would take us a very very long time um
and so that's very um very expensive to
compute and so we'd wait a very long
time before we make even a single step
of gradient update um so for neural Nets
what you're always doing is using this
variant that's called stochastic
gradient descent and so for stochastic
gradient descent what that means is we
pick a very small subset of our data
like maybe we pick 16 or 2 Data items
and we pretend that's all of our data
and we evaluate the function J based on
that small subset and work out the
gradient based on that small subset so
it's a noisy inaccurate estimate of the
gradient and we use that um to be the
direction in which we walk um so that's
normally referred to also as having mini
batches or mini batch gradient
descent um and in theory working out the
gradient based on this small subset um
is an approximation but one of the
interesting things in the way things
have emerged in new network land is it
turns out that new networks actually
often work better when you throw some
noise into the system that having this
noise in the system gives you jiggle and
moves things around and so actually
stochastic gradient descent not only is
way way faster but actually works better
as a system for optimization of neural
networks okay so if you remember from
last time um for um word de the idea was
we started by just saying each word has
a random um Vector representing it so we
will literally sort of just get random
small numbers and fill up the vectors
with those random small numbers um
there's an important point there which
is you do have to initialize your
vectors with random small numbers if you
just leave the all the vectors as zero
then nothing works um and that's because
if everything starts off the same you
get these sort of false symmetries which
means that you can't learn so you always
do want to be initializing your vectors
with random numbers and then we're going
to go through each position in the
Corpus using our estimates we're going
to try try and predict the probability
of words in the context as we talked
about last time then we so that gives us
an objective function from which we can
then look at our errors look at our
gradient um and update the vectors so
that they learn to predict surrounding
words better and so the incredible thing
is that we can do no more than that and
we end up learning word vectors which
actually capture quite a lot of the
semantics the meaning and relationships
between different words so you know when
this was first
um discovered um for these algorithms I
mean it really feels like magic that you
can just sort of do this math simple
math over a lot of text um and actually
learn about the meanings of words that
it's sort of just sort of surprising
that something so simple could work but
as time has gone on this same recipe has
then been for all kinds of learning
about
um um the behavior of language from new
networks um so let's just um go through
a sense of how that is but before we do
that so
um let me just mention so for our word
toac algorithms the only parameters of
the model are these word vectors they're
the outside word vectors and the center
word vectors which we actually treat as
disjoint as I mentioned last time and
when we do the computations we're
considering the dot product between the
various um possible outside words with
our Center word and we using those to
get a probability distribution over How
likely the model thinks that different
outside words were and then we're
comparing that to the actual outside
word in the context and that gives us
our source of error so as such this is
what's referred to in NLP as a bag of
words model that it doesn't actually
know about the structure of sentences
and or even what's to the left and
what's to the right it's predicting
exactly the same probabilities at each
position to the left or right um but
it's wanting to know about what kind of
words appear in the context of the
center word um so I just wanted to uh
stop this for a minute and um
let's see not that one
um so give you some kind of a sense that
this really um does work um so this is a
little Jupiter notebook um that I've got
um for this
um okay and so this is using and here
I'm using a package um gen Sim which we
don't continue to use after that really
um but it's sort of one package that let
you load and play with word vectors and
the word vectors I'm going to use here
are are glove word vectors and actually
I'm going to um glove was a model we
built at Stanford and I'm going to
actually talk about it a little bit
later um so strictly speaking um these
aren't exactly word to ve word vectors
but they behave in exactly the same way
um and so okay so now it's loaded up by
word vectors because the word vectors
are a big data file and so as we've
discussed um for a word right that the
representation of any word here is bread
is just um a vector of real numbers
right so um I'm using a 100 dimensional
word vectors to keep things quicker um
for my class demo so this is the word
bread um and then I can say well what's
the representation for
croissant
um and um this is croissant and we can
sort of get a visual sense of oh they're
at least a little bit similar right so
the first components are both negative
the second components are both positive
the third components are both negative
and large the fourth components are both
positive right they they seem like
they're kind of similar vectors so that
seems kind of hopeful because that means
that it knows that bread and croissant
are a bit um similar to each other um
the this package has a nice simple
function where rather than doing that by
hand you can just ask it about all the
word vectors and say which ones are most
similar so I can ask it um what um words
in its vocabulary most similar to USA
and in this model everything's been
lowercased I should mention um and so if
I do that it has Canada America U.S.A
then United States Australia well those
seem a fairly reasonable list of most
similar words though you might think
it's a little strange that Canada wins
out over the USA with dots over it
um um similarly I can ask if what's most
similar to banana and I get coconut
mango bananas potato pineapple fruit Etc
again pretty sensible you know a little
bit of a bias to more tropical fruits or
I can go to cron and ask what's most
similar to cran the most similar things
to cron isn't bread but it's things like
Brios bagette fatcha um which sort of
basically makes sense though here's
pudding here um and I've got wait I'd
already done oh sorry yeah I remember
what this is right so with this most
similar you've got a positive word
vector and you're saying what other
words are most similar in position to
that that um there's something else you
can do which you can say is this is let
me take the negative of that word vector
and say what's most similar to the
negative of it and you could possibly
think a that might be useful to find
antonyms or something like that I mean
the truth is it isn't if you ask for the
things that are most similar to the
negative of the banana Vector um and in
most other vectors it's the same you get
off out these weirdo things things that
you're not really sure if they're words
at all or maybe they are in some other
language or some of them are names right
like shichi is a Japanese name um but
not very useful stuff don't that um they
not don't really feel like a negative of
banana but it turns out that from there
we get this um powerful ability of um
that was observed for word to ve which
is that we could isolate semantic
components um and then put them together
in interesting ways so um looking at
this picture what we could do is start
with a positive Vector for King from the
origin up the king then we could use the
negation to say subtract out the vector
for man and then we could have another
positive Vector of add on the um Vector
for woman and then we can ask the model
is if you're over here in the space um
what is the nearest word to you over
there and so um that's what this um next
thing does right it's sort of says
positive Vector for King negative for
man also positive for Queen where does
that get you to and that gets you to
Queen yay um and so this was the most
celebrated property that was discovered
with these word vectors that they
weren't only good for meaning similarity
but that they were good um for doing
these kind of meaning components and
these got referred to as analogies
because that's you can think of them as
a is to B as C is to what so it's sort
of like um woman is to King no sorry um
man is to King or King is to man as um
I'm saying this the wrong way around man
is to King as woman is to what um in the
analogies and so here I've defined a
little function that is now saying this
little function just automates that and
we'll compute
analogies um and so now I can ask it in
just this analogy format um man is to
King as woman is to queen and um that
one was sort of the canonical example
but you know you can actually sort of
has have fun with this and I mean you
know uh this is pretty oldfashioned
stuff you know know I I feel like I'm
maybe like now at this point an old guy
talking about how much fun we used to
have sitting around the radio listening
to radio plays um because you know
basically no one uses this stuff anymore
and there are much much better and
fancier things like chat GPT but you
know back in the day when I was younger
um you know it was really stunning
already just how this very simple model
built on very simple data um could just
have quite good semantic understanding
and do quite good analogies so you can
actually you know play with this quite a
bit and have a bit of fun so you can do
something like analogy Australia comma
be
France okay what people think the answer
will
be close the answer gives us Champagne
but that seems a pretty good answer um I
could then put in Russia what what
people think vodka yeah it'll see you
can get back vodka you know this is
actually works kind of
interestingly um you know I could do a
different one I can do the test
something different I can do something
like pencil is
to
sketching as
camera is
to photographing yeah that works quite
well um so um we built this model in
2014 so it's a little bit out of date in
politics so you know well we we can't do
the last decade of politics which is
maybe unfortunate but you know we could
try out older politics questions so we
could try um
Obama is to
Clinton
as
Reagan is to if you remember your Us
world history class any guesses what
it's going to
say there's a bush one any other
ideas some people have different
opinions of Bill Clinton
any uh um what it answers is Nixon which
I think is actually kind of fair
um
but um you can also get it to do some
just sort of language syntactic facts so
you can do something like tallest to
tallest as long
oops as long is to this one's
easy um yeah so you know with this simp
simple method of learning with this
simple bag of words model it's enough to
learn a lot about the semantics of words
and you know stuff that's beyond
conventional semantics right you know
like our examples with Australia De Beer
as Russia as to vodka I mean that sort
of cultural World Knowledge which goes a
little bit beyond um what people
normally think of as sort of word
meaning semantics but it's also in there
yes if you perhaps subract the distance
from let's say like man and King does
that also capture a concept of
relationship between two words like
would that give you back like ruler like
something like that we taking the like
the difference between two vectors does
capture
some
right the distance between man so so Man
compared to King should be a ruler
concept but isn't that what I'm using CU
then I'm taking that I'm taking the
distance between man and
King is what I'm adding on to woman to
get the queen
right right yeah so I can depending on
if you think of these words depending on
which thing you think of as the analogy
you can think of it you've both got um a
a vector a difference Vector between
words that gives you a gender analogy
and one that gives you a ruler analogy
yeah absolutely
any other
questions yeah um in the watch ve umm we
get two vectors like for each one a u
and a v but here you only have one
vector so how do you go from two to one
yeah good question I mean the commonest
way in practice was you just average the
two of them and and and really you sort
of find out that they um end up very
close you
know um because if you think of it since
you're going along every position of the
text you're both going to be the case
where if the text is sort of you know
the octopus has legs you know you're
going to have octopus in the center with
legs in the context and a couple of time
steps later it's going to be legs in the
center with octavus in the context so
you know although they vary a bit for
all the regions of the neuron Nets very
basically they end up very similar and
people normally just average them yeah
can you
this process so use this uh the answer
of one to then be placed into the
analogy function of the another and see
how far away you can go before it SS
break
down I think you can um so you what wait
you're wanting to how far away how
distant of a relation between two words
can you do before it starts providing
incorrect relationship
between but are you wanting to sort of
make two steps from somewhere or yeah
St many St go away
froming so it doesn't always work I mean
there are so examples that are fail um
I'm sort of shy to try that now because
I don't have a predefined function that
did it and that might take me um too
long but you could play with it at home
and see how it works for you
curious is a clarification why is it
that we use two separate sets of vectors
for word uh is it just to get more
parameters or is there um I'll get back
to that maybe I should go on at this
point um let me move on and kind of just
get through some more details of the
word Tove algorithm um so um just a
technical point on this class so you
don't make any big mistakes and waste
your weekend I mean for most instances
of 224n we've actually had people
Implement from scratch word to VC as
assignment to um but you know for this
quarter doing it in Spring quarter as
you probably know Spring quarter is
actually a little shorter than the other
two quarters um we decided to skip
having people Implement word to VC um so
don't look at the old assignment to that
says Implement word to V or else you'll
be misspending your time wait for the
newer assignment to to come out um but
you know despite that let me just sort
of um say a little bit more about some
of the details right yeah so why two
vectors um so the two vectors is it just
makes the math a little bit easy so if
you think about the math right if you
have the same vectors for the center
word and for the outside words well for
whatever the the center word is let's
say it's octopus that when you're going
through the trying out every possible
context word for the normalization at
some point you'll hit octopus again and
so at that point you'll have a quadratic
term right you'll have the x squared of
the octopus vector and that kind of
messes up I mean you're clever people
you could work out the math of it but it
makes the math more of a mess right CU
every other term it's something
different and it's just like a X and
then at one position you've got an x s
um so it just makes the math Messier and
so they kept it really simple by just
having them be disjoint vectors but it
it doesn't make it better I mean it
actually turns out it works a fraction
better if you do it right um but in
practice people have usually just
estimated them separately and then
average them at the end um there if if
you actually look at the paper here's m
of it out you can find it 2013 paper um
there's actually sort of a family of
methods that they describe um so they
described two methods one of which um
was that you have an inside word that's
predicting the words around it and then
the other one tried to predict the
center word from all the words in the
context which was called continuous bag
of words in their paper um the one that
I've described is Skip gram which is
simpler and works just great um but then
the other part of it is um for working
out um what loss function to be used for
training and what I've um presented so
far um is naive soft Max where we just
consider every possible choice of a
context word and just run all the math
um you know that's totally doable and
with our modern super fast computers
it's not even that unreasonable to do we
do things like this all the time but at
least at the time that they um wrote
their paper this seemed kind of
expensive and they considered other
Alternatives um like a hierarchical
softmax which I'm not going to explain
right now but I do just want to explain
negative
sampling okay so this is just to sort of
see a bit of a different way of doing
things so for what we did last time we
had this sort of straightforward soft
Max equation and so in the denominator
you're summing over every word in the
vocabulary um and so if you might have
400,000 words in your vocabulary a lot
of words in human languages you know
that's kind of a a big sum especially
when for each element of the sum you're
taking a DOT product between 100
dimensional or 300 dimensional vectors
and then exponentiating it right a lot
of math going on somewhere in there um
so
maybe we could short circuit that and so
the idea of the negative sampling was to
say well rather than evaluating it for
every single possible word maybe we
could just sort of train some simple
logistic regressions where they're going
to say you should like the true word
that's in the context and if we randomly
pick a few other words you shouldn't
like them very much um and that's skip
gram negative sampling so that's what
this looks like as an equation um so
we've got our Center word and our actual
context word and we're um saying well
let's work out the term for the actual
Center word we'd like this to be um high
probability um so since we're minimizing
we're going to negate that and have it
go down and then we're going to sample
some other words and we'd like this to
be the opposite um but the the other
thing that we've changed here is now
we're not using the soft Max anymore
we're using this Sigma which stands for
the logistic function which is often
called the sigmoid um sigmoid just means
s-shaped and but you know you could
actually have an Infinity of s-shaped
functions and the one that we actually
use is the logistic function so the
logistic function has this form and and
Maps um from any real number to a
probability between zero and one um so
what we're wanting to say at that point
is for the real outside world we're
hoping that this dot product is large so
its probability is near one um and so
that will then sort of help with the
minimization and for the other words
we'd like their probability to be small
um so we what like them to appear sort
of over here um and that's what this is
calculating but as written it's sort of
sticking the minus sign on the inside
there which works because of the this is
symmetric right so you're wanting to be
over here which means that if you negate
it you'll be on this side which will be
large okay um
and so then the final bit of this which
is the asterisk is so we're going to
pick a few words you know it might only
be five or 10 that are our negative
samples um but for picking those words
what works well is not just to sort of
pick sort of randomly uniformly from all
the 400,000 words in our vocab what you
basically want to do is sort of be
paying attention to how common the words
are something like that is a really
common word and so we refer to that as
the unigram distribution that means
you're s just taking individual words
independently how commonly they are so
about 10% of the time you'd be choosing
the um but so that's sort of roughly
what you want to do for sampling but
people have found that you can actually
do even a bit better than that so the
standard thing that they presented for
word DEC is you're taking the unigram
probability of the word and raising it
to the power of
34 uh what does that end up
doing question for the audience if I
take probabilities and raise them to the
three
quarters some less frequent words just
become sing more correct yeah so the
raising to the
34s means that you're sort of somewhat
upping the probability
of the less frequent words so you're
sort of in between you know between
having every word uniform and exactly
using their relative frequencies in the
text you're sort of moving a little bit
in the direction of uniform and so you
get better results by going somewhat in
the distance of sampling more uniformly
but you don't want to go all the way
there which should correspond to I guess
putting um a zero in there rather than
three
quarters okay um
yeah okay uh let's see I had a side here
but Time Rushes along so let's not
bother with this side it's not that
important um okay so that's um the word
to VC algorithm that we've seen all of
um in its different forms um a
reasonable uh wonder that you have at
this point is you
know this seems a kind of a weird way of
doing what we're wanting to do right the
idea is look we have this text we have
words and we have words in the context
of words it sort of seems like an
obvious thing to do would be to say
let's just count some statistics we have
words and there are other words that
occur in their context so let's just see
how often the word word swim occurs next
to octopus and how often the word fish
occurs next to octopus let's get some
counts um and see how often words occur
in the context of other words and maybe
we could use that um to calculate some
form of word vectors um and so that's
something that people have already also
considered so if we use the same kind of
idea of a context window we could just
make a matrix of how often words occur
in the context of other words and so you
know here's a baby example my Corpus is
I like deep learning I like NLP I enjoy
flying um and my context window I'm
using is just one word to the left and
the right and then I can make this kind
of um co-occurrence count Matrix um
where I'm putting in the counts of
different words in every context and you
know because my Corpus is so small um
every thing in the Matrix is a zero or
one except for right here where I've got
the twos because I have I like twice
right but in principle I've got a matrix
of counts for all the different counts
here um so maybe you know this gives
this gives me a word Vector right you
know here's a word Vector for deep um is
this long Vector here and you know I
could just say that is my word vector
and indeed sometimes people have done
that but they're kind of of ungainly
word vectors because if we have 400,000
words in our vocabulary the size of this
Matrix is 400,000 by
400,000 which is a lot worse than our
word ve word vectors because if we're
making them only 100 dimensional um
we've only got 400,000 by 100 which is
still a big number but it's a lot
smaller than 400,000 time 400,000 so
that's inconvenient so when people have
started with um these kind of
cooccurrence Matrix um the general thing
that people have done is to say well
somehow we want to reduce the
dimensionality of that Matrix so that we
have a smaller Matrix to deal with um
and so then how can we reduce the
dimensionality of the Matrix and at this
point if you remember your linear
algebra and stuff like that you should
be thinking of things like PCA and
particular if you want it to work for
any Matrix of any shape there's the um
singular value decomposition so there
the classic singular value decomposition
for any Matrix you can rewrite it as a
product of three matrices a u and a v
which are both
orthonormal um which means that um you
get these um
independent
um vectors um they orthog to each other
um and then in the middle we have the
singular vectors which are ordered in
size is the most important singular
vector and these are sort of waiting
terms on the different number of uh the
different dimensions and so this is sort
of the full SVD
decomposition um but you know part of it
is a relevant because if I've got this
picture you know nothing is happening in
the part that's sort of shown in yellow
there um but if you want you know at the
moment you know this is just an a a good
a full decomposition but if we wanting
to have sort of smaller low dimensional
vectors well the next trick we pull is
we say well we know where the smallest
singular vectors are so we could just
set them to zero and if we did that then
more of this goes away and we end up
with two-dimensional representation
of our words and so that gives us
another way of um forming
low-dimensional word
representations um and this had actually
been explored before modern new word
vectors and using algorithms such as
latent semantic analysis um and it is
sort of half worked but it never worked
very well but you know some people
especially in psychology had kept on
working on it um and among other people
in the early 2000s there was this grad
student um Doug roie who kept on working
on it and he came up with an algorithm
um that he called Kohl's and you know he
he had known as other people before him
had known that just sort of doing an SVD
on Raw counts didn't seem to give you
word vectors that worked very well um
but he had some ideas to do better than
that um so one thing that helps a lot is
if you log the
frequencies so you can put log
frequencies in the cells um but then um
he sort of used some other ideas some of
which were also picked up in word to V
one of which is ramping the windows so
that you count closer words more than
further away words um he used piercon
correlations instead of counts Etc but
he ended up coming up with a low dial
version of Word vectors that are sort of
ultimately still based on an SVD um and
he got out these word vectors and you
know interestingly sort of no one really
noticed at the time but Doug roie in his
dissertation effectively discovered this
same property of having linear semantic
components so look here we go here's one
of so this is actually you know picture
from his dissertation and look here you
know we've got this meaning component
which is doer of an event and he's
essentially shown with the way he's
processed his word vectors that the do
of an event is a linear meaning
component that you can use to move
between a verb and the doer of the verb
kind of cool but he didn't become famous
because no one was paying attention to
what he had come up with so that so once
word DEC um became popular that was
something that I was kind of interested
in and so um working together with a
postto Jeffrey Pennington um we thought
that you know you there was interest in
this sort of space of having doing
things with matrices of counts and how
do you then get them to work well as
word vectors in the same way that word
de V worked well as word vectors and so
that's what led um into the glove
algorithm that was what I was actually
showing you and so um what we wanted was
to say look we want a model in which um
linear components sort of adding or
subtracting a vector in a vector space
correspond to a meaning difference how
can we do that um and Jeffrey um did
good thinking and uh math and um thought
about that for a bit and his solution
was to say well if we think of um that
ratios of cooccurrence probabilities can
encode meaning components so if we can
make a ratio of cooccurrence
probabilities into something linear in
the vector space will get the kind of
result that word DEC or Doug Ro got um
so what does that mean well so if you
start thinking of words occurring in the
context of I ice you might think that
sort of solid and water are likely to K
near ice and gas or a random word like
random aren't likely to occur near ice
but and similar for steam you'd expect
um that you know gas and water are
likely to occur near steam but probably
not solid or random and well if you're
just looking at one of these you don't
really get meaning components because
you get something that's large here or
large here but if you then look at the
ratio of two of these cooccurrence
probabilities then what you get out is
that for solid it's going to be large
and small is going to be um and for gas
it's going to be small and so you're
getting a direction in the space which
will correspond to the um solid liquid
gas dimension of physics um whereas for
the other words it will be about one um
this is just uh uh the wave your hands
this was the conception of the idea but
if you actually do the counts this
actually works out so using real data
this is what you get for cooccurrence
and indeed you kind of get these sort of
factors of 10 um in both of these
directions of these two and the numbers
are over there are approximately one um
so um Jeffrey's idea was well we going
to start with a cooccurrence count
Matrix and we want to make this turn
into a linear component and well how do
you do that well first of all it sort of
makes sense immediately that you should
be putting a login right because once
you put a log in um this ratio will be
being turned into something that's
subtracted um and so simply all you have
to do is have a log by linear model
where the um dotproduct of two word
vectors models this conditional
probability and then the difference
between two vectors will be
corresponding to this log of the ratio
of their cooccurrence
probabilities um so that was basically
the glove model um so you're wanting to
you know model this dot product um such
that it's being close to the log of the
cooccur Cur probability but you sort of
do a little bit of extra work to have
some biased terms and and some frequency
thresholds which aren't very important
um so I'm going to skip past them but I
think that basic intuition as to what's
the important thing to get linear
meaning components is a good one to know
about okay is everyone good
today
cool yes all right noticed the the
original X Matrix you show was like 3x 5
or something shouldn't It Be Square so
yeah I mean if you're doing sorry yeah I
maybe should have just shown you a
square one if you're just doing
vocabulary to vocabulary yes it should
be square um but there was a bit in the
slides that I didn't mention that there
was another way you could do it where
you did it words versus documents and
then it would be non Square um but yeah
you're right so let we can just just um
consider the square case Okay
um so you know hey I showed you that
demo of the glove vectors and they work
great didn't
they um so you know these are good
vectors um but in general in NLP we'd
like to have things that we can evaluate
and know whether things are really good
um and
so everywhere through the course we're
going to want to evaluate things and
work out how good they are and what's
better and what's worse um and so one of
the fundamental Notions of evaluation
that will come up again and again is
intrinsic and extrinsic evaluations so
an intrinsic evaluation is where you are
doing a very specific internal subtask
and you just try and score whether it's
good or bad so normally intrinsic
evaluations are fast to compute help you
understand the component you're building
but they are sort of distant from your
Downstream task and improving the
numbers internally may or may not help
you and that's um the contrast with an
extrinsic evaluation um which is that
you've got some real task you want to do
question answering or document
summarization or machine
translation um and you want to know
whether some clever bit of um internal
modeling will help you on that task so
then you have to sort of run an entire
system and work out Downstream
accuracies um and find out whether it
actually helps you at the end of the day
um but that often means it's kind of you
know indirect so harder to see exactly
what's happening in your task um so for
something like word vectors you know if
we just sort of measure are they
modeling word similarity well that's an
intrinsic
evaluation but you know we'd probably
like to know whether they model word
similarity well for some Downstream task
which might be um doing web search right
we'd like um when you say you know cell
phone or mobile phone that it comes out
at about the same um so that would then
be web search might be our extrinsic
evaluation okay so for word factors um
two two intrinsic evaluations the ones
we've already seen
so there's the word Vector analogies um
you know I cheated when I showed you the
glove demo I only showed you ones that
work but if you play for it yourself you
can find some that don't work um so what
we can do is sort of have a set of um
word analogies and find out which ones
work now you know in general glove does
work you know here's a set of word
vectors um showing you um the sort of
um female distinction it's kind of good
and linear but in general for different
ones it's going to work and it's not
work and you're going to be able to
score what percentage of the time it
works um or we can do um word similarity
How We Do word similarity is we actually
use human judgments of similarity so um
psychologists ask undergrads and they
say here is the word plane and car how
similar are they on a scale of 1 to 10
or 0 to 10 maybe actually I think it's 0
to 10 here on a scale of 0 to 10 and the
person says seven and then they ask
another person um and uh they average
what the undergrads say and they come
out with these numbers so you know Tiger
Tiger gets 10 book and paper got a an
average of
7.46 um plane and car got
5.77 um stock and phone got 1.62 and
stock and jaguar got
0.92 um noisy process but you roughly
get to see how similar people think
words are and so then we ask our models
to also score how similar they think
words are and then we get models of how
well the scores are correlated um
between um human judgments and our
models judgments um and so here are sort
of a big table of numbers that we um
don't need to go through all of but you
know it sort of shows that a plain SVD
Works terribly simply doing SVD over log
counts already starts to work reasonably
um and then you know here's um the two
word DEC algorithms sibo and Skip gram
and here are numbers from our glove
vectors and so you get these kind of
scores that you can then score different
models as to how good they are
and well then you can ALS oh sorry yeah
um that's the only thing I have there
but you know what can you do for
Downstream evaluation well then you want
to um pick some Downstream task and so a
simple Downstream task that's been used
a lot um in NLP is what's called named
entity recognition and so that's
recognizing names of things and what
type they are um so if the sentence is
Chris Manning lives in poo Alto you want
to say Chris and Manning that's the name
of a person and poo and outto that's the
name of a place um so that can be the
task and well that's the kind of task
which you might think word vectors would
help you with um and it's um indeed the
case right so he what's label was
discreet was a baseline symbolic um
probabilistic um name entity recognition
task and by putting word vectors into it
you can make them the numbers go up so
these numbers for glav are higher than
the ones on the first line and so I'm
getting substantial improvements from
adding word vectors to my system yay
um okay
um I'll pile ahead into the next thing
this next one I think is interesting we
should spend a minute on and it came up
in your questions last time words have
lots of meanings most words um have a
whole bunch of meanings words that don't
have a lot of different meanings are
only some very specialized scientific
words okay so my example of of word with
multiple meanings is probably not the
first one you think of all the time um
the most famous example of a word with a
lot of meanings is bank which already
came up last time and I use star which
is another one here's a word that you
probably don't use that often um but it
you know it still has lots of meaning so
the word Pike what are some things that
the word Pike can
mean fish a fish yes it's a kind of fish
okay we've got one what else can a pike
be yeah a spear a spear yeah for the
Dungeons and Dragons crowd yeah there's
a long arm right yep that's another one
yeah a road right yes so Pike is used as
a shorthand well a shorthand for a ter
Turn Pike why it's called a Turnpike
where yeah originally you had you know
this the spey looking thing um at the
start of it as sort of count people okay
we've got three other thing meanings for
pike yeah is it also a crap like a
[Music]
fraternity I'll believe you I can't say
I know that one
um are
Pikes sharp as like a needle something
Sharp
maybe I mean I think it's really the
sort of Pike as the
weapon other scratch your heads um one
that I think a lot of you will have seen
um in diving and swimming you can do a
pike Olympics if you see olympic diving
there are Pikes anyone seen
those um trust me that's a pike um okay
um and we've sort of been doing um the
noun uses but you know you can also use
Pike as a verb right you know like once
you've got your medieval weapon you can
Pike somebody um and that's a usage of
Pike um and you can do other ones right
so uh here we go here's
um um ones I got from a dictionary we
got most of those there are sort of
weirder usages right like coming down
the pike that's kind of a metaphorical
use that comes um from the the road
sense but it sort of ends up meaning the
future um yeah um in Australia we also
use Pike to mean um sort of chicken out
of doing something um but I don't think
that usage is really used in the US
anyway words have lots of meanings so
how can you deal with that well one way
you could deal with it is to say okay
words have several meanings
and so we're just going to say words
have several meanings and then we're
going to take instances of words in text
we're going to Cluster them based on
their similarity of occurrence to decide
which sense of the word to regard each
token as and then we're going to learn
word vectors for those token clusters
which are our sensors and you can do
that um we did it in 2012
before word de came out um so you see
here we have bank one and somewhere over
here we have Bank two and here we have
Jaguar one Jaguar 2 Jaguar 3 Jaguar 4
and you know this really works out great
right so Jaguar one um picks out the
sense of the um kind of car right and
it's close to luxury and convertible
Jaguar 2
comes right close to software in
Microsoft and this one's a bit of a
historical one but you know it's when
you were when most of you were five or
whatever you might remember um Apple
used to use large cats for versions of
um Mac OS right so sort of Mac OS 10.3
or something like that a long time ago
was called Jaguar right so it's software
close to Microsoft um Jaguar 3 um okay
string keyboard solo musical um drum
base that's because there's a Jaguar
keyboard um and then finally um the sort
of what we think of is the basic sense
but turns out turns up rather Less in
text corpor normally um Jaguar next to
Hunter is the animal right so it's done
a good job at learning the different
sensors but you know that's not what's
actually usually done these days and
instead you know what's usually done is
you do only have one vector for Jaguar
and when you do that um or Pike here the
one vector you learn is a weighted a
weighted average of the vectors that you
would have learned for the
senses um it's often referred to as a
superposition because somehow um neet
math people like to use physics terms um
and
so they call it a superposition but it's
a weighted average so you're taking the
relative frequency of the different
senses and multiplying the vectors you
would have learned if you'd had sense
vectors and that's what you get as the
representation as a whole
um and um you know I can make a sort of
a linguistic argument as to why you
might want to do that um which is you
know although this model of words have
senses is you know very longstanding and
common I mean it's essentially the way
dictionaries are built right you look up
a word in the dictionary and it says
sense one sense 2 sense three and you
get them for things like bank or Jaguars
we're talking about I mean it's sort of
really a broken model right that
like word meanings have a lot of nuance
they're used in a lot of different
contexts they are extreme examples like
Bank wherever it was where we have
Finance bank and Bank of a river bank
over here where it seems like the senses
are this far apart but you know most
words have sort of different meanings
but they're not actually that far apart
and trying to cut them into senses seems
actually very artificial and you know
there you know if you look up different
dictionaries and you say how many senses
does this word have pretty much everyone
will give you a different answer so the
kind of situation you have is a word
like like field well a field can be used
for a place where you grow a crop um it
can be used for sort of natural things
like a a rock field or an ice field it
can be used for a sporting field um
there's the mathematical sense of field
now all of these things sort of have
something to do with each other I mean
the math one's further away but the
physical ones are sort sort of flat
spaces um but you know the the the sense
of it being a sporting field is clearly
kind of different from the sense of it
being an ice field is the ice field and
The Rock field different or am I just
modifying they are they different senses
right so really you sort of have a kind
of a a
uh what a math person say is sort of
like some probability density
distribution over things that can be
meant by the meaning of a word so it
sort of maybe makes sense to more use
this model where you're just actually
saying we have a vector that's an
average of all the contexts and we'll
see more of that when we get to
contextual word vectors um later on um
but one more surprising result on this
is um since you you have um the vector
for pike overall being the sum of these
different um sense vectors you know
standard math would tell you that if you
just have the single Vector there's no
way that you can recover the individual
sense
vectors but um higher maath tells you um
that actually these um Vector spaces are
so high dimensional and sparse that you
can use ideas from sparse coding Theory
to reconstruct the sense vectors out of
the whole vector and if you actually
want to understand this um some of the
people in statistics David Dono I think
is one of them um teach courses on
sparse coding Theory um but um I'm not
going to try and teach that but you know
here's an example um from this paper the
San
Al where one of the ATS is tar who's now
faculty in computer science here where
they uh starting off with the word
vector and using sparse coding um to
divide out sense vectors from one um
word vector and they work pretty well
right so here's one sense of tie which
is piece of clothing another sense of
tie which is ties in the game um this
one is sort of similar to that one and
I'll admit but this sense of tie here is
then a tie as sort of you put on your
electrical cables um then you have the
musical sense of tie right at least four
out of five they've done a pretty good
job of getting senses out of this single
um word vector by sparse coding so
sparse coding must be cool if you want
to go off and learn more about
it
okay okay so that's everything I was
going to say about words vectors and
word
senses is everyone good to there any
questions I'll Rush ahead for the last
two pieces okay so I just wanted to
start to introdu in the last 15 minutes
um the ideas of how we can build neural
classifiers um and how we start to build
in general neural network works I mean
in a sense we've already built a very
simple neural classifier our word DEC
model is predicting what words are
likely to occur in the context of
another word um and you can think of
that as a classifier but let's look at a
simple classifier like our named entity
recognizers I mentioned before so for
the named entity recognizer we want to
label words with their class so we want
to say these two words are a person but
the same words Paris and Hilton are then
locations in this second sentence so
words can be ambiguous as to what their
class is um and the other state is that
they're not a named entity at all
they're just a word um that is some
other word and this is something that's
used in lots of places um as a a bit of
understanding so if you've seen any of
those web pages um where they've sort of
you know tagged company names with a
stock ticker or um there links on a
Wikipedia page to a Wikipedia page or
something like that right you've got
named entities where commonly after
finding the named entities um you're
doing this second stage of entity
linking where you're then linking the
named entity to some canonical form of
it like a wikkipedia page but we're not
going to talk about the second part of
it um for the rest of the day
um and
so um we could say that building with
our word vectors we've got this simple
task where what we're going to do is
we're going to look at a word in context
because sometimes Paris is a name of a
person sometimes it's a location and so
we're going to want to look at this word
in its context and say aha this is a
name of a location in this instance and
so the way that we going to do it um is
we're going to form a a window
classifier so we're going to take a word
with a couple of words of context on
each side and for the words in our
context window we're going to use our
word vectors because we want to show
they're useful for something and then we
want to feed this into something that is
a classifier and our classifier um it's
actually going to be a really simple loc
classifier we're only here going to do
location or not a location so this one
here we're W to say for this um window
here yes it's a location um and whereas
if it had
been I what I love Paris Hilton greatly
um then we'd be saying no because Paris
the word in the middle of the context
then isn't um a location so that's sort
of the idea of a classification or
classifier we're making assigning some
set of classes um to things right so in
general for
classifiers um we do supervised learning
which means we have some labeled
examples our training data set so we
have input items XI and for each one
we've got a class Yi so I had for my ex
example training examples ones like I
love Paris Hilton greatly that
was negative not a location and I visit
Paris Every Spring that's positive that
is a location where I'm actually
classifying the middle word okay so
inputs labels and in general we've got
um labels are a set of classes so my set
here is simply location not a location
but I could get fancier and I could say
I've got five classes I've got location
person name
uh whatever other ones there are um
company name drug name right I could be
assigning a bunch of or other not a name
a bunch of different classes but I'm
going to be doing it with only two
because I'm using this example on next
Tuesday's lecture as well and I'm
wanting to keep it simple um so that's
what we're going to do and so what we're
going to be using in our class um is
neural classifiers and so I just wanted
to sort of um sort of just sort of go
through quickly just the sort of food
for thought as we go into it so for a
typical um stats machine learning
classifier you can build classifiers
like logistic regression or softmax
classifiers or other ones like support
Vector machines or naive Bays or
whatever else you might have seen the
vast majority of these classifiers are
linear classifiers meaning that they
have a linear decision boundary and when
we're learning these classifiers we're
learning parameters here W but our the
our inputs are fixed that our inputs are
represented by symbols like um or
quantities so we have fixed inputs we
learn parameters as weights into that
are used to multiply the inputs and then
we use a linear decision boundary
so when we have our neural classifier
we're kind of getting some more power um
so first of all we're not only learning
weights W for our classifier we're also
learning distributed representations for
our words so our words can sort of re
represent our word vectors re represent
the actual words of symbols and can move
them around in the space so that in
terms of the original space we've got a
nonlinear classifier that can represent
much more complex functions um but we
will then sort of use the word vectors
to re-represent um those words to do a
final classification so at the end of
our deep Network which we're about to
build we will have a linear classifier
in terms of our re-represented vectors
but not in terms of our original space
let me try and be concrete about that
okay so here's what I'm going to use and
we'll use again next Tuesday um as my um
little neural network um and so I start
with some words museums and Paris are
amazing I first of
all come up with the word embedding of
those using my word vectors so now I'm
got this sort of high dimensional Vector
which is just a concatenation of five
word vectors so you know if I have 100
dimensional word vectors this is 500
dimensional and then I'm going to put it
through a neural network layer which is
simply multiplying that vector by a
matrix and adding on a bias um vector
and then I'm going to put it through
some
nonlinearity which might be for example
the logistic function that we've already
seen so that will give me a new
representation and in particular um if
the w is say 8 by 500 I'll be reducing
it to a much or what yeah 8 by 500 I'll
be reducing it to a much smaller Vector
right so then I can do after that I can
multiply my hidden representation the
middle of my neural network by another
vector and that will give me a score and
I'm going to put the score into the
logistic um function that we saw earlier
to say what's the probability this is
the location so at this point um my
classifier is going to be a linear
classifier in terms of this internal
representation that's used right at the
end but it's going to be a nonlinear
classifier in terms of my word
vectors
um
okay
uh great um here's one other thing this
is just sort of uh uh a note for learner
ahead um since you want to know this
when we start doing the next assignments
I mean up until now I've presented
everything as you know doing log
likelihood and negative log likelihood
for building our models um very soon now
assignment two we're going to be
starting to do things um with pytorch
and when you um start working out your
um losses with payto watch um what
you're going to be wanting to use is
cross entropy loss and so just let me
quickly say what cross entropy loss is
so cross entropy is from information
Theory so if you have a true probability
distribution p and you're Computing a
probability distribution Q your cross
entropy loss is like this um so it's the
log of your um model probability
um the expectation of that under your um
true probability distribution but
there's sort of a special case whereas
if you have ground truth or gold or
Target data where things are labeled one
zero so like for examples of um I love
Paris um when warm right I'm just
labeling it one for location probability
one it's a location probability zero is
not a location so if you're just
labeling the right class as probability
one then in this summation every other
term goes to zero and the only thing
you're left with is what probability is
my model what log probability is my
model giving to the right class and so
that then is um your log likelihood
which we can use for um the negative log
likelihood um little bit of a
complication here just remember that you
want to use cross entry loss in py tort
when building the model okay um before
we end today um here is um my obligatory
one picture of human neurons don't miss
it because I'm not going to show any
more of these um okay these are human
neurons right human neurons um were
the um inspiration for neural networks
right so human neurons have a single
output which comes down this axon um and
then um when you have these
outputs um they then feed into other
neurons I guess I don't really have an
example here but in general one output
can feed into multiple different neurons
you can see the different things hanging
into it so you know you have the output
connecting to the input and sort of
where you make this connection right
that's the synapses that people talk
about and so one neuron will normally
have many many inputs where it picks
things up from other neurons and they
all go into the nucleus of the cell and
the nucleus combines together all those
inputs and kind of what happens is if
there's enough positive activation from
all of these um inputs it then sends
signals down its output now strictly how
um neurons work is that they send spikes
so the level of activation a neuron is
its rate of spiking um but that
immediately got turned in artificial
neural networks into just a real value
as to what is its level of activation um
and so it does this so this was kind of
the genuine inspiration of all of our
neural networks right so a binary
logistic regression is kind of a bit
similar to a neuron right it has
multiple inputs you're working out your
total level of excitation where in
particular you can have inputs that are
both exciting positive inputs and inputs
that are um negative um which are then
inhibitory inputs you combine them all
together and you get an output that's
your level of exit
excitation and you're then sort of
converting that through some
nonlinearity and so this was proposed as
a very simple model of human neurons now
human neurons are way more complex than
this um and some people like
neuroscientists think we maybe should be
doing a better model of actual human
neurons but um
in terms of what's being done in the
current neural networks eat the World
Revolution everyone's forgotten about
that and is just sticking with this very
very simple model um which conveniently
turns into linear algebra in a very
simple way um so this gives us sort of
like a single neuron but then precise
right so this is which this s single
neuron if you use the logistic function
is identical to logistic regression
which you've probably seen in some stats
class or something but the difference is
that for newal networks we don't just
have one logistic regression we have a
bunch of logistic regressions at once
and well that' be tricky if we had to
Define what each of these logistic
regressions was calculating but what we
don't what we do is we just feed them
into another logistic regression and so
we have some eventual output that we
want to be something like we want it to
say you know this is or isn't a location
but then what will happen is by our
machine learning these intermediate
logistic regressions will figure out all
by themselves something useful to do
that's the magic um right so that you
get this sort of self-learning prop
where the model has a lot of parameters
and internally um will work out useful
things to do so in general we can get
more Magic by having more layers in the
neural network and that we will um build
up functions so effectively these
intermediate layers let us learn a model
that re represents the input data in
ways that will make it easier to
classify or easier to interpret and do
things with Downstream in our new
network um and it's time so I should
stop there thank you