Okay, then let's get started. So,
welcome back to the diffusion and the
poor models. Uh, so we're going to
continue the discussions for the some
the basics of the division models today.
Uh, so from the last time uh what we are
discussing is that basically what we
want to do is like all about basically
modeling the marginal data distribution,
right? Basically it's all about how we
going to model this kind of the marginal
distribution and the basic idea for that
is to basically model the the prior
distribution which is typically defined
as the standard the gaussian
distribution and it's also all about how
we going to basically learn some kind of
the proper the likelihood distribution
in a way that this combination can model
the marginal distribution and the
question is that how we are going to
basically learn the likelihood of the
distribution uh only by just having some
kind the a set of the samples from this
distribution. And for that the idea that
we have seen in the BAE case is to
basically jointly learn both the
likelihood distribution which is also
represented with the decoder and also
the uh the variation of the posterior
which is this part which is also
basically represented with another the
encoding the network. So that is the
basic idea and also the limitation that
we have seen for the BAE is that
basically everything is the gausian
right. So especially for the likelihood
distribution, we are also modeling this
part as kind of the the Gaussian
distribution in a way to basically have
the fixed the variance and also only
predicting the mean using the decoding
the network and this is basically
limiting some kind of the expressibility
uh for the marginal distribution because
the our marginal distribution will be
basically represented as the combination
like these two. And now these each of
these two both of them are basically
modeled as the gausian distribution. But
the uh the complexity of the data
distribution here that we are having
might be something that might be too
complex to be expressed with the the
combinations of the two gauss and the
distributions. So here the question is
that how we are going to basically
design the new gen model in a way that
this likelihood distribution becomes
something more the complex right not
just the gausian distribution but
something that is basically the more the
complex the distribution.
So for that uh we started to discuss the
basic idea for the uh some diffusion
models starting from the recursive deep
in terms of basically having some
multiple the layers of the latent the
variables and from that we also started
to discuss the diffusion models.
So the the very basic ideas for the
diffusion model is that we are basically
having some kind of the sequentiality
processes starting from the data point
from the x0 there all the way to the x
capital t. So as I also mentioned from
the last lecture. So these are the
notations that we are going to use for
now. Uh but as I also said we might also
need to change the notations later. But
here basically you should basically
remember this the x0 indicates the the
sample of the clean data point right the
the data point that we have and x
capital t here is basically the sample
from the unique gausian the distribution
so that's the kind of the final the
latent the variables right and then we
are having some kind of the bunch of the
some intermediate some latent the the
variables as well from the ones x1 to
the all the way to the xt minus one
right and both for the mapping from the
data point to the uh the final the
latent variable and also for the other
way around we are having some kind of
the sequential the process which is
basically going from the this way and
the other way around and actually also
the mapping from the x0 row to the x
capital t will be uh called as kind of
the for process so that's the process
that we are uh so let's see like this is
kind of the indicating kind of the time
step right uh when you see that this t
is kind of time step the process that we
are increasing the time step is the for
process mapping the data point to the x
capital t the final latent variable and
the other way around we call the reverse
the process so that's kind of basic
thing
and also the key idea for the diffusion
model is that we are basically
predefining the fold process basically
defining all the transition the
distribution for the pro the fold
process uh into some kind of a specific
form
in a way that we don't need to learn the
for process. We are only going to learn
the reverse process. So that's the basic
idea in terms like making it like easy
to uh retrain the neural network.
And one more thing is that as I also
mentioned the last time we are going to
define all the latent variables in the
same dimensional space. So we are
basically matching the the dimensions
for the all the the variables and also
the data points as well. So this was
kind of the basic the setup for the
diffusion models
and also we started to see some uh one
specific version of the diffusion
models. So these are some kind of some
specific kind of the way to define the
division models. But the thing is that
uh in this class we are also going to uh
discuss some kind of the different
versions or different kind of the models
uh some kind specific models in the
division the in the family of the
diffusion models. So you're going to see
that actually this is kind of like the
one version and we also going to discuss
some the other divergence in the the
other directors and this is basically
the basic model and also the your
assignment one will be uh the part of
the assignment one will bally
implementing this the basic model you're
going to see that actually it quite
works well. Uh so for this kind of the
most the basic model what we are going
to assume is that uh the for both the
fold and the voiced processes will be
defined as kind of the the marco
processes. uh which means that in the
forward process like when you know
iteratively like sampling each of the XT
here from the previous step the XT minus
one uh the XT will only depends on the
right before the one the XT minus one
not depending on the other the previous
the states. So when you see this kind of
the some conditional distribution
sampling XT conditioned by the XT minus
one the X0 we can easily drop this part
because we know that by the hourly
definition XT is not dependent to the X0
here right so we can basically easily
drop the X0 here.
that basically makes it easy to
basically define all the other kind of
things
and also we are going to specifically
define the fault the transition the
distribution into this kind of the way
so you can see that this is basically
defined as kind of the gausian
distribution and you're going to see
that we are defining many things into
the gausian otherwise I mean there are
actually the other divergence in terms
like not defining this into the gausian
but something else but we're gonna make
it simple in terms like making a bit
gausian And we have some kind of the
some parameters here. So here basically
the beta t is the parameters which is
the nondereasing function over time in
terms of that it's basically having some
numbers in the range from the zero to
one while keep increasing over time. So
you can see that it's kind of the
process that we are somehow injecting
the noise right. uh you see that this is
the gausian distribution while taking
the xt uh and the multiplied by this
parameters kind of center uh which means
that we are slightly shifting the xt min
into some kind of scale so this scale
vector is uh one or the smaller than the
one right so if the beta t is bally zero
you can see that this is kind of the
direct delta d distribution in terms of
that the sampling of the xt T should be
the same with XT minus one, right? But
as we keep increasing the beta T, we can
see that it's basically slightly moving
this XT minus one into the center the
origin of the the coordinate system
while basically adding some kind of the
Gaussian noise, right? So you can see
that this is kind of the process that we
are iteratively injecting some kind of
the noise uh into some kind of the data
points which means that the reverb
process is the opposite, right? So that
will be the process that we are
iteratively deducting removing some kind
of the noise from some kind of pure the
gausian noise. So actually you can see
that the generation process of the
diffusion model actually can be seen as
kind of the dnoising the process we are
gradually removing some kind of the
noise starting from the purely unique
gausian the noise in a way that that is
basically mapped to the uh the clean
data point. So this is the so basically
the very specific way uh to define the
default the transition the distribution
and then as I said uh in the later the
lectures we're going to see the other
ways of to define the uh the same
default the transition distribution
but basically so why we are defining the
for transition distribution in this way
so what you can see is that so from this
kind of the our definition of the for
process what we are going to do is that
we are also going to find uh the reverse
process in a way to basically maximize
uh the elbow function. So the in the
same way that the minimizing the
negative the elbow function right. So
here the question is that how we can
basically define the reverse process in
a way to basically minimize this
negative elbow function right. Uh so we
have seen how we can decompose this
complex the elbow function into the
three terms. Uh and the thing is that
after we decompose this into the three
terms uh what you can see is that yeah
so basically we are having these three
and the first term is the same the recon
term that we have seen in the BA case
and this is only for the very last step
in the reverse the process for example
the x0 from the from the x1. So actually
this is like comparable uh this is like
compared to the other kind of loss terms
this is like much smaller kind of terms
in terms of it the magnitude. So in
practice we can simply ignore this part
uh in the the loss function
and the second thing is that so for like
the prior matching here. Uh the good
thing like defining the for the
transition the distribution uh in that
way that we have seen in the previous
slide uh is that uh the good thing for
this definition is that it naturally
basically minimizes uh this to be zero
right especially in the case like when
you have some kind of the uh lots of
kind of the time steps. So as we
basically have some kind of the more
some kind of the time steps in the both
the fold and the reverse the process
reverse the processes we can see that
this will goes down to the zero uh by
our definition of the fold uh the the
transition the distribution. So that is
kind of the reason like why we are
defining the uh the fold process in that
way.
So which means that uh we are going to
ignore this part and we are we don't
need to care about this part because
like this will go down to zero naturally
by the definition of default process. So
the only thing that we need to care
about would be this part right. So
basically how we are going to define uh
this we can say that this is the
sampling the xt minus one from the xt.
So that's the reverse transition the
distribution. So for each of the
consecutive the steps of the reverse the
process uh this is the sampling like the
one the uh the intermediate the variable
from the previous one which is x here.
So here the all the question is
basically how we are going to define
this one uh the reverse the transition
the distribution in a way to basically
minimize uh this the the term of the
loss function. So that's basically what
we are going to see.
So see uh again the this is the saying
the the denoing the matching term uh
minimizing the k divergence between
these two uh the distributions and you
can see that actually after rewriting
all this function uh we can see that
this uh reverse the transition
distribution actually should be the same
uh with this form of the conditional
distribution
uh doesn't look that kind of like uh
natural control in terms of the we are
sampling the XT minus one conditioned by
both the XT and the X0 and we're going
to get into that like how we going to
basically derive some kind of closed
form of like this distribution but
basically what you can say is that uh we
need to define our the reverse the
transition distribution in a way that
this basically matches uh this
distribution that means basically we
need to know uh how this distribution
would look like right so that's kind of
the key
So before we get into that so uh so
let's see how we can basically derive
some kind of closed form of like this
distribution. So what we can see is that
using the base rule if you basically
ignore the x0 here x0 x0 x0 we can see
that this is exactly the base rule the
form right. Uh so from based on the base
rule actually we can see that these can
be basically decomposed into these three
terms like this. Uh make sense if you
basically uh ignore this aial part. This
is exactly the same form of the base
rule right that we have seen in the
previous lect right. So which means that
this is the same with the multiplication
like those kind of three terms and then
now these are all some kind of the some
familiar uh some distributions right
uh as I mentioned in the previous slide
uh for this distribution uh we can
ignore this x0 right because of the all
the we are assuming that the fold and
reverse the processes are basically the
marovian process which means that
sampling the xt would not depends
on the x0 right so we can drop the x0
then we can see that this is the the
fourth the transition the distribution
that we have already defined right this
is basically what we know and also in
the previous lecture
we have seen how we can derive the
closed form for this do you remember how
we d these things
uh so actually that's the first quiz uh
so before we get into some more det For
this uh based on the definition of the B
process here and also how we define the
alpha t hat here uh let's basically uh
see how we can derive the closed form
all those returns.
So continue. So if we see how these are
developed. So these are basically all
the things that we have seen in the
previous lecture right. Uh so so this
might be also the confusing that we are
define introducing the beta t which was
basically parameter defining the both
tend distribution and then we are also
defining the alpha t and the alpha t
head like these are some kind of new
parameters but actually these are all
the connected to the beta t right uh so
actually you need to really uh see how
these are basically defined because
these are really something that you're
going to keep seeing for the rest of the
all the the direct lectures in this
class. Uh so please keep this in mind in
terms of that. But here the key thing is
that uh once we define the for detention
the distribution uh based on that we can
derive the closed form of the things
that I'm going to call as kind of the
full jump the distribution jumping uh
from the x0 to the xt right and the
thing is that this is also defined as
kind of the gausian the distribution
and then we started to see uh this
distribution because basically this is
something that we need to match using
our the reverse the uh the transition
the distribution
and then uh after also some kind of the
slightly the dirty mess here what you
can see is that based on the all the
closed form of these 3D distributions
after doing all the kind of the
derivation what you can see is that it
turns out to be that the this
distribution is also another the
Gaussian distribution uh which the mean
and the variance are basically defined
in that way. So now we can see that
interesting that everything is basically
gausian here but we now we have some
kind of the slightly more the complex of
the mean and the variance here. So these
are basically the three the main kind of
the um the distributions that we are
going to see uh in the fold process as
you have seen uh this is basically
something that we defined right the fold
the transition distribution based on
that we derived this uh this is the the
jumping distribution so let me go one by
one uh so this is basically the
distribution that we defined two
consecutive deentariables
now we can sample the xt from the xt
minus part and this is something that we
defined right and based on that now we
also could uh derive the closed form for
this something that I call the full jump
distribution like jumping from the x0 to
the xt here. So which means that uh
without really doing some any iterative
process in the for the process we can
directly sample XT from the X0. So
that's something that you really need to
remember. Uh while we will need to do
the iterative process uh in the the
reverse the generated process uh in the
fold process actually we don't need to
do any kind of iteration. We just need
to directly uh we can directly sample
the XT from the X0. So that's also kind
of the one interesting point, right?
And what we just basically defined
derived was basically sampling the xt
minus one by seeing both the x0 and the
xt. So that is kind of interesting
because like without the x0 here, if we
didn't have that the uh where is it? No.
Yeah, if we didn't have the the
conditioning the x0 here, that's exactly
the reverse transition the process,
right? sampling the XT minus one from
the XT. But here the thing is that uh
what if we map not only the XT but some
kind of the provisioning X0 that was
kind of some future kind of things in
the reverse process right uh so in the
kind of the reverse process uh we going
to only have the XT information and
something the XT minus one from this but
what if we have the both the XT and also
the X0 so that's kind of the the future
output process for those case when you
have the conditions of like both of them
now we can have the uh information about
the some closed form of the distribution
which is another the gaussian
distribution.
So these are basically some key 3D
distributions that you need to uh
remember in the fold process
and also the thing is that uh the mean
and the coariance of this Gaussian
distribution the good thing is that for
the coariance the matrix these are
something that we can just like
calculate right uh we define the beta t
and based on that we can also calculate
those two things which means that we can
just directly calculate the co the term
in the this gausian the distri division.
But how about the mean? For the mean, we
also have some kind of the some
coefficients here that we can calculate.
And you can see that actually the mean
becomes some kind of the some linear
function taking both the xt and the x0.
So that now we can basically know um see
that the gausian distribution here can
be basically defined as some kind of the
mean function taking the xt and x0 and
the the the variance here which we can
just directly compute
and do you remember like why we are
seeing this distribution. Uh this was
the distribution that we wanted to match
using the our reverse uh detention the
distribution
right. So in terms of like know
minimizing this loss function uh the the
question is that basically how we are
going to model this reverse differenti
distribution in a way to minimize the k
difference with this uh the probability
the distribution right then how should
we model this
now the this question is quite simple
right how should we model this we we
know how this looks like Right? This was
the Gaussian distribution. Even we know
the the variance. Right? The only thing
that we need to know we we don't know
for this term is basically the mean
function because the mean function is
basically involving the x0 while we do
not have the xu information the real
diversity process
which means that uh in terms of binary
modeling the reverse the transition the
distribution.
What we just need to do is that we will
just need to uh also make uh this
reversely transition distribution as the
another distribution obviously because
like we want to basically match this to
this one and since we want to match this
to this we can set the same the the
coance here right
the same the coience and the only thing
that we need to learn using the neural
network is actually this like the mean
uh because here the mean computed based
on the X0 but why we don't have the X
information right so this is the only
the information that we need to predict
using the neural network
so that's the basic idea so we need
basically the model the reverse
detention the distribution into this way
then what we need to do is that we need
to basically minimize the KD divergence
uh between these two right so if we also
recall like what we have seen with the
KL divergence In the case that like when
you have the two Gaussian distributions
like this and this for especially for
the same the coians here uh what's the
key levels between these two
do you remember?
Yes. Uh this is actually what we have
seen this was the quiz uh last time
right? So you you can check out the
lecture slides there. Uh so if you
basically compute the KRW between these
these two distributions when you match
the the co term here then actually what
you can say is that this become nothing
but just like
uh the L to norm of the difference for
the these two the the the means of the
two distributions.
See uh you need to check out how exactly
we derive this right but basically you
see the basic idea what we just need to
do uh is that in the expected value uh
uh so basically we are computing the
expected value for the arbitrary time t
and also the x0 and the the sample of
the xt right given this kind of sample
of x0 and xt uh in the training time we
will be able to basically compute the
mean of the this distribution
given the sample of the XT and the X XT
and the X0 right and then what we are
going to do is that we are we are
basically modeling this reverse
transition distribution as the Gaussian
and then we just need to bally minimize
the L2 difference between these two uh
the means here. So this is the mean that
we are calculating from this and this is
the mean predictor uh for the this uh
the the reverse state transition
distribution.
So typically for this like the mean
prediction in neural network we are
feeding the XT and also time step t as
well. So given this like two information
we need to basically the predict the
mean of like this this distribution in a
way to basically minimizing the out loss
for the arbitrary samples of the x0 and
the xt here.
Great. Yes.
Uh and then also typically in practice
uh there are some kind of the waiting
thumb here uh you you can usually just
like put this like waiting thumb here
but uh in practice many people just like
ignore this term because like without
even the waiting thumb is it still works
well.
So the very interesting thing here is
that uh after like all this kind of the
derivation like seeing like how we
define the default process and how the
elbow function can be decomposed and
also minimized. Uh after all those kind
of things the interesting point is that
it turns out to be that the training of
the mean prediction network becomes
pretty simple. Actually this will be
something that you need to implement in
your the assignment one and you're going
to see that actually this is really just
like few lines of the code in the
pytorch.
Uh so basically this is something that
we are going to minimize right expected
value over the time t and also the x0
for the samples of x0 and also the
sample of the xt here and then basically
minimizing the expected value for this
right then we can either like follow
like one by one we are just sampling the
x0 here
and then sampling the time t and then
what's the meaning like this this is
bally sampling the XT uh from this
distribution right because you know you
can see that this is kind of the
reparation of the this gausian
distribution right
uh
yeah so this becomes basically just like
nothing but sampling the xt given the x0
and the time t here and then what you do
is that we just like compute this this
mean uh using this our sample of the xt
and the x0 and then we predict the mean
using the mean predictor and then run
the back propagation while minimizing
this L2 loss
make sense.
So actually know if you understood all
the details uh the all the basics here
uh this is actually quite surprisingly
point in terms of that after like all
those kind of the derivations everything
it turns out to be that the the neuron
net training becomes very simple it's
really just like few lines of the code.
Uh so now you can see that how we
carefully designed all the the reward
process and also how we carefully
decomposed the elbow function uh in a
way that the like modeling the reverse
the tradition the the distribution
become just like learning the Gaussian
distribution and also especially just
like learning the mean of the the
gausian distribution and becomes like
quite simple.
Any questions on this?
>> Before you said that 38
doesn't just distribution, but it looks
like it also follow.
>> Uh that's the yeah really good question
and we're going to get back to that
point later. Yeah, that's a really good
point. Any other questions?
So, so here the the things that you need
to basically you know uh see is that you
know uh why we define the for you know
in that way and why we see this kind of
the de composition of the the elbow
function. So all the basically the kind
of things that we are seeing here is to
basically make it easy to model the
reverse the transition the distribution
and also make it easy to learn uh the
proper the the reverse the transition
the distribution. So after all those
kind of things what we are seeing is
that if we can actually compute uh the
variance term in the reverse the
transition the distribution the only
thing that we need to learn is basically
the mean of that the distribution and
like learning the mean becomes such a
simple just like sampling the x0 and the
time t and sampling the xt like sampling
x0 and the time t and the xt here and
then basically computing this mean and
also the getting the prediction of the
mean predictor and minimizing the L2
loss using the veations.
So that's kind of the interesting point
of the division models like everything
is quite clear.
So here just like one more thing is that
so I introduced the idea that we are
basically predicting the mean of that
the our delivers the transition the
distribution right but we know that we
know the formulation of the mean
actually right that is basically the uh
the function of the xt and the x0 right
so what we can do is that instead of
like directly predicting the mean here
we can consider just like predicting the
x0 given the xt.
So what if we consider not the mean
predictor but the x0 predictor here in a
way that we can compute the mean from
the xt and the x0. Well what's the x0
here?
x0 was the one of the the training the
data point right basically the clean
data sample. uh while the XT is some
kind of noise data the the point after
we injecting some kind of noise.
So that's kind of thing. So now we can
consider having some kind of a clean
sample the predictor which is like
predicting the X0 from the XT instead of
basically directly predicting the mean
here. So that's the kind of the just
like the other option. So what happens
with the the clean sample the predictor
is that actually it becomes the same in
terms of the to derive all the things
that you can see that uh the saying the
elbow function especially like this the
matching term here becomes the same in
terms of the we are still minimizing the
L2 the difference between these two with
some kind of the new weight term here
and also here we are going to simply
ignore the weight term you can really
just like put the the waiting there But
in practice even without the waiting
term actually it works well. Then it
means that now we can uh do the same
thing in the the training time now we
can basically have some kind of the
clean sample the predictor the x0
predictor while matching the x0 here and
at the end like in the generation the
process we just need to compute the mean
from the prediction of the x0.
So that's the same thing.
Then the question might be that so
what's the meaning of like predicting
the x0 from the xt. So what you can see
is that so from this loss function what
we are basically doing here is that uh
given the xt so xt was a sample from the
given the any kind of xio here but what
we are doing is that uh using this loss
function uh we are basically predicting
some kind of the some uh expected value
of the x0 that would resulting in
basically sampling the xt from it from
the full the jump the prediction.
So actually if we see uh the real some
kind of the generation the process. So
this is kind of the 1D example.
You want to say that this is kind of the
obviously our the prior uh the
distribution uh the the gausian
distribution and and let's say that this
is kind of the some complex some kind of
the data distribution. So we're going to
start like sampling the x in the forward
process. Uh we're going to start
basically sampling some X0 here and then
adding some kind of the noise in a way
to make some kind of some sort of the
trajectory of the XT all the way to the
X capital T here and as you can see that
you know from the arbitrary XT
actually there can be some multiple
possible XO that would result in
basically reaching to this point through
the default process right and what we
are doing uh with the XO the prediction
Here basically we the this loss function
and also the this network uh is to
basically predict some kind of the
expected value some kind of average
value of the XU that would resulting in
basically sampling the XT from the V
process
make sense.
So if we consider this like the clean
sample the predictor the interesting the
point uh is that actually if we recall
the the kind of the the goal of the kind
of the diffusion model is that we are
going to basically sample the x0 in a
kind of the iterative way right so
that's kind of the idea of the some kind
of recursive kind of the uh the sampling
in the deep models so starting from the
x capital t we are recursively basically
sampling the xt X t - 1 t -2 all the way
to the x0 right which means that at the
intermediate step we don't know what
sort of to x0 that we're going to get is
the need to iterate the steps right but
the interesting kind of thing the clean
sample the predictor is that every time
in the every intermediate step of the xt
uh actually we are seeing some kind of
the expected value of the x0
and that means that our sampling of the
xt minus one is actually based on some
kind of the our the uh you know the
prediction of the final the output of
the exo. So every time from the xt we
are seeing basically what we are going
to get at the very end of the all the
process and based on that we are not
just taking the final the output but
just taking the next step sampling the
xt minus one. So that means that we are
basically somehow refining our kind of
the some expectation of the final the
output every step and we are not just
directly taking that expectation but
just like based on that we just like go
one more step xt minus one and then also
basically defining our kind of
prediction and also the refine doing the
iterations right so that's kind of the
interesting the point of the diffusion
models so we can interpret the diffusion
model as kind of like defining the
process of the our the final the uh the
the prediction of the expected uh the
value for the x0 here
is this clear.
So let me first show this. I think it
might be good to show the this first.
So this is like one example of the uh
image generation. Uh so you can see that
at the very beginning we are starting
from some kind of the pure the unique g
and the noise right and over time we are
seeing some kind of the d the noise the
outputs uh so because like we are
following some kind of reverse process
of like injecting the noise right so if
we visualize the xt then you're going to
see that it's like gradually den noising
the uh all the intermediate the vables
here in a way that we are getting to the
x0
but actually if we see visualize the
prediction of the x0. So every time at
the xt we can consider basically
predicting the expected value of the x0
right we can also visualize that then
you can see that it becomes like know
every time we are seeing some kind of
the blurry the output of the the final
kind of things right while basically
refining every step uh so we are not
just directly taking the actual
prediction the inter step but based on
the final the output we just let go one
more step and then refining this and
also So the go one more step right
actually this is kind of the life lesson
I mean for all the things that we do we
also need to do this kind of training.
So before we really go like some like
step by step uh we just need to first
basically visualize what we going to end
up getting at the end of the all the
process right based on that we need to
do some kind of planning right and def
model is really doing this kind of thing
uh getting the prediction for the final
the output and just like going one more
step and just like repeating this kind
of
So that's the idea of the clean the
sample the predictor. Uh so this can
basically replace the mean prediction.
So instead of like directly predicting
the mean we can consider predicting the
x0. So that's the one the idea
actually the thing is that uh we can do
one more thing. Uh so the one more thing
is that uh so so this was the case that
we are basically sampling the XT from
the X0 first right and based on these
two samples like we are sampling the XT
minus one as well right so if we see
basically how we compute the sample of
the XT actually the XT can be seen like
this right so sampling the XT from this
default the jump distribution can be
seen as we're computing this with some
kind of the standard gausian the the the
noise here right with the
reparameterization is basically the same
uh so which means that uh so now we can
define this epsilon t which is now
defined based on the xt and the x0 so
the meaning like the epsilon t is the
that is that the standard the gausian
that result in basically the jump from
the x0 to the xt right so we are you can
define the epsilon t as kind of the uh
with the xt and the x0 here as well. So
now what we can do is that even we can
also consider uh redefining this kind of
the mean function not with respect to
the xt and the x0 but with respect to
the xt and then epsilon t.
Uh can you quickly write down like what
we going to get uh with the uh for the
mean function for these two terms
This is not something that you need to
submit. So let me continue. Uh so but
yeah uh you can check out that if you
just plug in the definition x and you're
going to see that actually it becomes
like this. So that means that uh
actually we can also define this like
the mean function with respect to the xt
and this epsilon t right. uh then you
can feel that no now we can also define
the new predictor right uh that means uh
instead of like also having the uh mean
predictor and also the clean sample the
predictor now we can also consider the
the other one which is the noise
predictor which is predicting this like
standard G and the noise t in a way that
we can just like compute the mean based
on the XT and also the prediction of the
noise and then it's the same all the
things kind of thing the Same thing in
terms of it becomes alo the same the uh
the out loss term with some kind of the
another the waiting term here which we
going to also ignore the practice then
you can see that this also becomes like
all the same we are just simply
replacing the mean predictor into the
clean sample the predictor and also now
this is the case that we are replacing
that into the noise predictor right so
the other kind of the cases
so you can see that actually there are a
bunch of the options here right we have
seen the three options Uh this is be the
most the natural option in terms of that
we directly predict the mean of that the
noise uh sorry the reverse the
transition the distribution right most
kind of the natural kind of the option
but instead of directly predicting the
mean what you can do is that we can
consider predicting the clean sample
and this becomes the interesting the
idea in terms of that now we are kind of
like foreseeing the final the output and
based on that we basically decide the
next step. Uh so that's kind of the
basic idea and this is actually really
key idea uh in the different models. So
what we are even going to see probably
after the midterm week is that so you
can see this is kind of like making some
sort of the trajectory starting from the
X capital T all the way to the XO we are
making some kind of the tra the
trajectory in the space right and every
time we are basically forcing some kind
of the final the destination final the
output and what we can do is that based
on the final the output that the
expected the output for that uh we can
see uh whether this is kind the right
trajectory that we want to go. Uh which
means that we're going to eventually go
to some kind of the clean data point
basically realistically data point but
that may not be something that you want.
you might have some kind of the more
some kind of the conditions or some kind
of the some the constraints for example
I don't know like you might want to
um what should I say uh you might want
to basically make some kind of the red
car uh not just the car uh but some of
those kind like red cur condition that's
some kind of very specific kind of the
types of the output that we want to get
right uh but then what you can get is
that based on the some kind of the our
forecasting of the final output. If that
is basically not close to what we want
to see based on that we can consider
basically adjusting our the trajectory.
Uh so that's kind of the interesting
aspect of the digital models we can do
some kind of the provide some kind of
the guidance uh in the trajectory
generation uh based on the prediction of
the final the output. Uh so that's the
kind of thing
and one more thing is basically this
like epsilon t prediction which is the
noise prediction in this case. So there
are basically these three options and
whatever that we predict using the
neuron net what we will need to do in
the kind of reverse process is to
basically compute the mean of this like
reverse the transition the uh
distribution uh based on those kind of
formulations and then doing some
iterative sampling
and as you can see basically for one of
those kind of things given the xt
whatever you have the mean or the xio or
the epsilon t given the one of those
kind of things you can also compute the
other things. uh which means that even
when you have some kind of the mean
predictor or the noise the predictor
based on that you can also compute uh
the expected the final the output as
well and you can also compute the the
noise from the uh this like the mean the
the clean sample the predictor right so
those are basically some kind of
interchangeable kind of things
so then here the question is that so
which one you going to use so as I said
implementing this will be the part of
the the first assignment Right? Uh you
can choose one of those three mean
predictor and coincent predictor and the
noise predictor. Uh which one you going
to choose?
One of the many reasons like why
diffusion model is basically more stable
in terms of the in the training uh is
that uh we can do this basically
typically people use the noise
predictor. Actually there are some cases
like using the clean sample predictor
and the other things for but you're
going to see that for many of the cases
people use the noise predictor uh
because of that we know that those the
noise are basically the the standard the
gausian the samples which means that the
these are really wellnormalized and also
the scaled the values
uh for the all the neuronet training you
know that it's very important to
basically do some kind of
prep-processing in terms of normalizing
all the input data set
uh which means that you can see that
these are naturally normalized as kind
of the standard Gaussian samples. Uh so
this basically also makes it very easy
to basically uh train this kind of noise
predictor using the neural network. So
that's kind of the one of the many
reasons like why the training of the
neuronet uh the diffusion model is quite
the stable and that's kind of reason
like why we also consider the noise
predictor. We're going to also see like
what's the meaning of the having the
noise here. So in any case basically
with the noise predictor is the same
thing. We just need to sample the x the
time t and also the epsilon t and
computing xt and running the back
propagation with the out loss. Uh the
same thing and based on this kind of the
trained the noise predictor uh what
should we do uh in the generation
process?
I mean you know I mean in the reverse
process what we need to do is basically
iteratively sampling the next one
starting from the x capital t all the
way to the xu we just need to sample the
next one xt xt -1 xt -2 those things by
computing the mean using the noise
prediction.
So at each step in the reverse process
what we need to do is that first
basically predicting the expected demos
here uh by feeding the XT and thet
compute this mean that the this reverse
uh the the transition the the
distribution here and based on that
sample the XT minus one repeat this
until you reach to the X0 right so you
can see that actually this is also just
like few lines of the code in the P
torch you just need to given starting
from the x capital t all the way to the
from the capital t to the one basically
predict this uh running the uh the you
know bitboard in the neuron network
computing the mean and then just like
sampling the xt minus one make sense
read is just like few lines of the code
in the pytor you're going to say that
after all kind of the derivations like
lots of them details in the mess you're
going to say that actually the
implementation is super simple uh so
that's also the power of the deep models
Yeah. So this no so as I said uh since
we can also compute the expected value
of the x0 from the prediction of the
epsilon t and the xt we can see the
whole process as kind of the refinement
process. Uh so that's kind of the key
idea.
Then here the one more quiz uh is that
so given the XT and also the predicted
the noise here uh what will be the
estimate of the expected clean sample.
So as I said this is really something
that you need to do. So every step uh
you're going to get the XT and also the
prediction of the noise and then we uh
before we just go to the next step we
want to see what we going to eventually
get at the end.
uh basically for seeing the final the
output from the XP right uh so you will
be able to basically get some uh
expected clean sample from these two
information right so
let's see how we can compute this
and here one question uh was that uh in
the low function like this
after we driving all the things we
basically drop this weight right uh then
what's the point like know did we really
need to basically follow all those kind
of kind of things right uh I recommend
you really basically uh in your
assignment one I recommend you really
just try to put this weight uh and
having this weight uh might
you know improve the training the
conversions a little bit uh so actually
for all the things you basically need to
uh know precisely have the this like all
expression we did this kind of waiting
term right but you can also see that
this waiting is only for basically
waiting the for each of the time t
so it means that like having this like
the weight here uh is basically how much
we going to basically put the more the
weights for each of the time t
uh so actually know there are a bunch of
the ways to basically replace this
waiting in terms of the actually we can
also control the number of the samples
of the time t and also if you train more
and more and more sufficient amount of
time with the loss of this the samples
of the time t then you know that becomes
something that we can basically ignore
this kind of the waste right because we
already have like lots of the samples
for the old kind of the time t so that
that's kind of the reason this is like
only depends on some kind of time t
which means that you know how much we
going to basically do some kind of the
impulses for each of the time step and
also that's true for example like for
the almost the last step of the reverse
the process uh for the x1 for example
from the varian x capital k all the way
to the x1 to the x0 right if you reach
to the x2 and the x1 this will be
already very close to the clean data
sample right uh for those kind of cases
even when you stopped at that point that
might be already look close to the kind
of clean kind of data samples so might
be also interesting to see uh the graph
of these kind of the weight and what
kind of the weight that you're going to
See typically you're going to see that
the weight for the at the very beginning
and at the very beginning and also at
the very end would be kind of be small
because like whatever you sample there
it does not affect much of in terms like
uh making some good trajectory
so that's kind of thing
uh one more thing is that
so as I said uh this and and also yeah
you won't need to you don't need to
implement this part but the the first
assignment will be basically simply
working on the 2D data points. Uh
because you will need to use the Google
cloud you just need to this simple kind
of thing and the basic idea will be
basically starting from some kind of the
unique gausian distribution in the 2D
space you're basically generating the
the one of the points in this kind of
spiral kind of the the the graph. uh and
I strongly recommend not just like
solving uh this kind of problem but also
try to visualize all the thing the
intermediate xt and also the expected
the output of x0 as well. So what you
get every kind of the time steps uh that
might be very uh interesting to see
and lastly let me get into this
question.
Uh so in the B process actually we model
this like the transition distribution as
kind of the Gaussian distribution and
based on that we could say that and also
this like the all the for jump from all
the way from the x0 to the x capital t
also becomes the gausian right then the
question is that uh when you also define
this like reverse uh the transition
distribution as the gausian distribution
as well does this mean that also this
whole likelihood distribution becomes
the gausian
Yes or no?
Yes.
No.
It looks like the answer is no, right?
If if the answer uh was the yes then
what's the point of like having the
division models because as I said like
the the kind of limitation the the bae
was that we are modeling this as kind of
the uh the gausian distribution that is
b limiting the expressibility uh in
terms like for the marginal
distribution. The thing is that now we
are basically defining this the the the
uh the likelihood of the distribution as
kind of the sequence of this reverse the
transition distribution.
The difference between the fourth and
the reverse process uh was that uh in
the fourth process uh the mean of the uh
this distribution was the linear
function with respect to the xt.
So since the mean was the linear
function just multiplying some kind of
scalar term here right to define this
for the the the transition. Since this
is the the case that the mean is defined
with some kind of linear function with
respect to t xt we can see that the the
sequence of that also becomes another
gaussian distribution right but now what
we are seeing for the reverse process is
that we are predicting the mean of this
this uh this distribution using the xt
uh which means that the mean is computed
using the neuron net uh which will be
typically nonlinearly function
I mean if you make as like the linear
function that is the same but you're
going to typically have some kind of the
nonlinearity into your linear net. Uh so
that's kind of the point uh that is
basically making uh the the our
likelihood distribution becomes
something more complex uh than the
typical Gaussian distribution
uh because of the fact that we are bally
predicting the mean of that the uh this
transition distribution which ft using
the nonlinear linear network that is
basically making some kind of the more
the complexity into our the likelihood
distribution and that allows us to
capture some more the complex uh uh
distribution of the marginal
distribution as well. So that's the key
idea in the diffusion models. While the
kind of the big posterior distribution
the fourth process becomes of the
gausian the the g the distribution and
this is something that we are not
learning right it's the predefined
distribution but based on that we can
still define each of the consecutive
this kind of the the transition the
distribution as the gausian uh while the
entire the likelihood distribution
becomes something more complex than the
uh the gausian so we are making the
training uh of the learning of the uh
reverse the transition to be simple as
much as it possible while still
basically uh having some the more the
place of the ability with the likelihood
distribution by basically stacking this
kind of the reverse the the transitions.
So that's the key idea in the diffusion
models
clip. No. Yes. So we have seen lots of
the details in the mess here. Actually
there are much more things that we
needed to actually discuss for today. Uh
but I'm going to continue uh the
discussion in terms of so basically the
thing is that we have seen these three
the options for the neuron net training
right the mean prediction and the clean
data the the point uh the prediction and
also the noise prediction right so the
meaning of having the noise prediction
is to make it the training to be uh
easier and also faster. uh but we're
going to also see the meaning of the the
noise uh in in the formulation and how
this also can be uh connected to the
score based models. So we're going to
continue next Monday.