okay uh so yeah here's the agenda it's
very simple you have two parts as a
general and then uh we'll dive into the
autogen framework the uh for the both
for both parts uh there are two big
motivating questions I want to cover uh
number one is what are the future AI
applications like and then number two is
how do we Empower every developer to
build them so uh let's start with the
first question uh what are the future AI
applications like uh so starting from
around the year like 2022 we see the big
Power of the language models and other
generative models uh so the generative
AI uh people have seen a superior
cability of generating content like uh
text and images um they are much better
than the generative techniques like 20
years ago or 15 years ago where I was
doing uh my PhD and study like topic
modeling and other older generative
modeling techniques apparently these
days the new technique has pass a bar
that uh we can think about in more
creative applications higher level of AI
capabilities and uh so what's the next
what what are the best way to leverage
these uh AG of AI techniques so starting
from last year early last year we start
to think about that question and we made
a lot of technical BS along the way uh
the most important bet would be that uh
we think the future
applications uh can be agentic and the
Agents can be a new way for human to
interact with the digital world and uh
help us execute more complex tasks um on
behal of human and uh get to uh higher
and higher level of uh
complexity uh and uh we got a lot uh at
that time many people have still have
doubts about whether atics AI can be
avable notion but uh as time goes by we
have seen more and more confirmation and
evidence including earlier this year
there's a article published by Berkeley
uh talking about uh how we're in uh how
we're observing more and more AI results
uh shifting from using a simple language
model to building compound a systems so
that's U uh one of the similar
observations and Technical B made we
made so if we think about the examples
of agentic AI uh you'll notice that
building a AI agents like a personal
assistants autonomous BS or gaming
agents
um there's um uh the notion of agent AI
is not new uh but what was new is that
with the power of the new generative AI
techniques and the L models for example
uh we're able to build uh some of the uh
old agenic applications much easier and
much more capable uh and at the same
time we are also seeing some very new
novel agentic
applications uh that uh go over go
beyond uh the imagination we had before
uh such as some science agents that can
do science Discovery automatically web
agents that can automate some web
browsing and web automation tasks and
also software agents that can build even
software from beginning to the
scratch I bet you have't seen a lot of
demos before but today let me show you a
very recent demo I just got this uh this
morning from sarup called zinle uh this
uh is example of building a website to
uh exract the models from huging pH and
download automatically uh so after you
give the request to the AI uh they
started working on them automatically
starting from analyzing the
task looking for information and
installing the necessary
dependencies they are they they do use a
multi-agent framework to have agents of
different roles to finish the task and
uh can uh do multi step of uh tasks now
we are seeing uh that AI is creating uh
different
files all the reasoning and uh between
the agents are are done automatically uh
using both language models and
tools so AA agents are talking to each
other now they're developing the website
and finally they're trying to build and
compile the
website okay here we go this is a
website bu by the
AI it looks like uh functioning there
are many models already listed in the
website and user can search model and
Export model data and download the data
download the models
so it looks like the video is uh playing
in the slower speed than
normal not sure if that's because of the
internet
issue and uh furthermore uh if you uh if
you happen to make some mistakes for
example if you remove the very critical
line of code from the
uh the files that are recreated let's
see what
happens so we are running the AI again
uh for for executing the same task so
this time the AI is able
to as trying to also perform the same
task but because of that removal of the
critical lines of code we're supposed to
hit some
error yeah so we see error message there
it's missing script so let's see what AI
will
do so uh just within a few steps the AI
is able to correct the mistake and
finish the exact line which is removed
so complete the task so that shows some
self-healing and the self- recovery uh
ability of the AI agents so um hope that
give us idea about uh the potential kind
of Promise uh the a can give us in
future we may build the software in a
totally different way um so to summarize
the key benefits of agen AI uh number
one is uh many people understand uh that
AI is able to use a more natural
interface to talk with humans so you can
tell them what you want exactly in this
case you just tell them we want to build
a website with certain requirements and
then you can iterate over the natural
language and uh also uh by uh giving the
agents Mark ability they are able to
operate and finish more compx tasks with
minimal human supervision so that has
tremendous value in terms of Automation
and the third point I think it's less
talk about among people but I have a a
strong emphasis that is uh uh agent AI
can be also a very useful software
architecture to enable us to build
software in a totally different way uh
so that you can have multiple agents
working with each other and to uh finish
much more Contex in a recursive way so I
will use a simple example to go over
these benefits so let's look at one
particular example application uh about
uh solving some sping oranization on
cloud this application is built by my
former colleague from Microsoft research
that allows users like coffee shop
owners to answer questions like what if
we change the shipping constraints uh
what how would that affect my operating
cost so this is difficult question they
can't get answers from like chbt because
the the II needs to understand the user
specific data constraints and even some
optimization tools uh to be able to
understand the the question and get the
answer uh but with uh in this case they
use autogen to build three agents that
can solve this uh question very nicely
the three agents are Commander writer
and Safeguard so let's see how that
works uh so initially the user s the
question what if we prohibit shipping
from Supply one to R three two the
commander receive that question before
it tries to answer that question it will
hold the current conversation and
initiate another nessage chat between
the commander and the writer the writer
in this case is using large Lang model
as a backend try to understand question
and proposes some code that can be used
to answer this question in this case
it's just some python code of adding a
specific spefic constraint into opition
problem and returns that code to
Commander the commander sees that code
again it holds the
conversation uh with writer and starts
another nessage chat between the
commander and Safeguard the Safeguard is
another agent using language model to
check whether the code is safe so in
this case it turns safe the commander
will finish that conversation with the
CFT card and start executing the code so
here's called execution result it runs
the oranization program with updated
constraint and check the new result so
uh Commander will then go back to the
previous conversation with writer send
the execution result back to the writer
here are the extion results and after
writer sees that it try to come up with
the final answer uh this is a simple
example of uh like using multiple agents
and multiple steps to finish the task in
general there can be all sorts of
problems like the code can be unsave in
that case the counter will not execute
the code and in case there's an
execution error the commander will
return the execution error back to the
writer and writer needs to rewrite the
code so in general that can be multiple
turns back and forth to finish the
complex task uh but here we're just
showing one simplest case that is uh at
a smooth uh
trace and and you can tell how the end
user now is able to still use a
relatively simple
doesn't need to know there are M
multiple agents running at the back end
they just ask a simple question and then
can answer natural language back the
user doesn't know understand any uh Lang
any knowledge about the coding or
oration uh so this is a example of using
multiple agents we allows end user to
achieve task data much harder than
before uh now if you look at the
programming perspective how do they
construct such a program the way they do
this is also very different from
traditional programs uh there are
several steps the first step is to
create these several agents so in this
case they're creating the writer
Safeguard commander and user using one
line for each and then they need to
define the interaction patents among
these agents uh so here they registered
two Ness chats to the commander for for
each chat we need to Define who are the
agents involved in the chat who are the
sender and are the receiver and what's
the s method from that
conversation and uh and then uh their
behavior patterns are defined this way
and finally we just initiate the chat
from the user proxy agent to the
commander agent by sending the initial
task
requirements and then every uh other
steps also follow automatically so the
framework will handle all the uh all the
steps and N chats and in eventually
return the result back
so hope that giv us an intu intuity idea
what the agentic programming
means and uh also uh uh I'm using two
slides to summarize their benefits the
one number one is to uh enable us using
this multiple agents to handle more
complex tasks and improve the response
quality for multiple reasons uh you see
that the multi agents talking to each
other can be a very natural way to make
improvement over interactions and we can
divide and concur a complex task to
decompose that to smaller tasks and have
more uh uh quality result for each step
and finally we can Define agents uh that
are not necessarily depending on land
models we can have special purpose
agents that perform grounding or
validation uh using knowledge outside of
the agent uh sorry outside of the models
so that we can address the weakness uh
inherent in the models
if you look at the chart on the right
this uh it's a experiment result about
uh if we if we decompose the task into
two agents for the rightand Safeguard
versus if we put all the instructions in
one single agent how is the performance
on the Safeguard side so if we compare
the performance we see that for gbd4 the
multi- agent setup has a 20% higher
record than single agent setup and for
GB 3.5 the difference is even higher so
it indicates that for certain scenarios
it's beneficial to decompose the tasks
and have agents to perform relatively
simple tasks uh and uh compared to just
asking the agent to do too too much work
in in one in one uh try uh and this is
especially um depending on the task
complexity and model capacity right so
in general the more complex the task and
the weaker the model there's a stronger
need to uh have this multi-agent
workflows uh and another perspective is
from the pro programming perspective uh
so in general it's easier to understand
maintain and extend the system if you
have a modular design uh for example if
you want to keep uh most of Agents
unchanged but just change for example
how you change the Safeguard Behavior if
you want to switch from using language
model to using tools or using human uh
it's very easy to do that with a modular
design um and this allows natural human
participation because uh human can take
over any of the agent in the system and
by having natural conversation with
other agents there's no need to change
how human interact with other agents so
combining these benefits uh we see that
the ageny programming has a pro has a
promising uh potential to uh enable fast
and creative experimentation and build
novel
applications but it's not easy to design
a framework to that can meet all these
uh promises in general we need to
consider several factors to design such
a
framework we want to have a unified
agentic abstraction that can unify all
these different type of entities and we
want to accommodate all the flexible
needs for multi-agent orchestrations and
satisfy all the different application
needs and uh we also need to make sure
we have effective implementation of all
the agentic design patterns
let me let me use the next few slides to
explain them so first of all for uh
agenting abstraction we want to unify
the notion so that uh we don't need to
have hard time to reason about all these
different type of entities like such as
humans of different roles tools or
language models uh from different
providers uh in general these are all
needed for building a common AI systems
but if we can uh have a single concept
to think about them it will bre
uh make it easier to to reason about
them so let me explain more in
the in the uh rest of the talk uh one
immediate benefit of that is now we can
use multi-agent orchestration uh for
building actually complex uh
applications of common AI systems and uh
but to do that we also need to think
about all the different requirements of
uh different AI agent um pattern
patterns of interactions for example
sometimes the developer want a more
static over workflow so that they can
clearly Define each step and the Order
of agents for the tasks but in other
cases uh if it's hard to know all the
possible
situations uh that agent need to handle
um then we want give agents more
autonomous uh and enable them to create
more Dynamic workflows and similarly
sometimes they want to use natural
language to tell the agents to perform
the task and any other times they want
to use program language to have a more
recess control so there's a tradeoff
between the flexibility and the um
controllability and there are many other
tradeoffs you to consider for example
when do we share the contacts among
agents and when do we isolate them have
a hierarchical setup for example and
when do do we want agent to cooporate
when do we want them to compete uh to
finish
task better and uh there's also
consideration about centralized versus
decentralized and automation versus
intervention so uh a good framework
should be able to accommodate all these
different
requirements and also as people develop
agents more and more they there are are
sorts of like good a good design
patterns emerging and uh we need to also
check whether a framewor can meet all
these uh design patents requirements uh
there's a conversation we want the agent
to be able to deal with flexible
conversations there's also prompting and
reasoning techniques like react
reflection Chin off thought Tre off
thoughts and so on so there are more of
such emerging reasoning techniques
including like monal research based
methods uh twool using is a very
important part of the agent design
patterns and so is planning and
integrating with multiple models
modality and memories and um it looks
like a lot right so it's hard to have a
framework that can consider all these
different factors in the beginning but
if you think about this from the first
order principle uh you may Wonder like
um is it possible to have a single kind
of design point to start with and have
all the other patterns to be able to uh
so so that we can uh derive all the
other patterns from that um so yeah so
can anyone think about among all these
different different patterns can you
think of using just one single Des
patter of them to accommodate all of uh
all of the others yeah I I believe that
different people will have maybe
different uh like ideas and started from
the different uh part you can you may
pick either one of them um so here I I
want to mention one personal kind of um
design point of view that is a
conversation so uh this this is has a
like a long time history back in college
I learned that conversation is a impr
way of making a progress in learning and
prove theorum uh and that's that's a
takeway and when I see the power of chbt
I immediately read that back to my
person experience and uh decide okay so
let's consider trying to use the multi
conversation as a central mechanism and
see how far we can go so it turns out uh
we can go very far um so here I'm
listing some examples of
aging AI Frameworks uh like autogen and
as I mentioned is based on this
multi-agent conversation programming and
uh it's uh it turns out to be very
comprehensive and flexible that's able
to integrate with all the different
design patterns I mentioned and also
other
Frameworks uh and you will hear more
from uh Jerry about Lama index uh and
there are also some other like L chain
based Frameworks such as Lang graph and
crew AI they focus on different uh also
star reasoning points like L graph for
example focus on providing some graph
based control flows and cow AI focus on
providing some high level static agent
task
workflows yeah so that's a very brief
overview of the AI agent uh sorry agent
Frameworks in general uh next I will uh
go into the specific uh autogen uh I
will try to explain more about
that uh so autogen is a program
framework for agent AI it was ini
developed inside another open source
project called Flo uh flamm is for
Automated machine learning and Hyper PR
tuning uh and uh later we spin off to
Stone rapo and uh this year recently we
also created a stone GitHub organization
uh to have a open governance structure
uh so everyone is welcome to join the
contribute um and here's a brief history
about the journey uh in early last year
we started prototyping this Frameworks
and initially we just built a multi
agent conversation framework with the
capability of code
execution and in August we published the
first version of the research paper uh
in August uh sorry in October we uh
moved this rep Standalone gith up repo
and it's got a lot of recognition from
community and uh uh such as this year we
got also a best paper at Clear 2024 RM
agents
Workshop uh and we're seeing more and
more interesting use cases from
Community including both uh Enterprise
companies and startup companies uh we
just also offered a online course on de.
about AI agent pendence with
autogen so uh that's uh just very brief
hisory about it uh in general uh autogen
has very rich features about um all the
different aign patterns but today I
mainly want to focus on the most
essential concept um because this is a
key to understand all the other
patterns so we want up uh any developer
to listen about a very complex workflow
in simply two steps the first step is to
define the agents and second step is to
get them to talk so here where there we
see two uh key Concepts one is a
conversible agent another is
conversation program so the agent
Concept in autogen is very generic can
abstract a lot of different entities uh
you can choose to use language model as
a backend for agent or you can use a
tool or human input as a back end and
you can also mix uh multiple types of
entities together and furthermore if you
use this multi-agent conversation
patterns like you see on the right hand
side you can build uh agents that can
contain other agents inside it have
inner conversations uh and uh and then
uh wrap them up as a interface to talk
to other agents so in this way you can
Nest multiple chats inside a agent have
inner conversations and build more and
more complex agent in a recursive way
and the the examples of conversation
pents include sequential chats Nessy
chat and group chat I will explain a few
of them in the next few slides uh the
simplest one is a two agent conversation
uh even though this is a very simple
conversation content it already allows
us to perform some Advanced reasoning
such as reflection for example we can
construct the writer for writing blog
post and another critic agent to make
suggestions to the blog post and you can
have these two agents iterate and uh uh
uh improve the quality of the blog post
in this way uh and uh now if you think
that's not good enough we can uh add U
more um other reasoning text advanced
techniques using this Nessy chat for
example instead of using a single
language model to do the CTIC we can use
a Nessy chat and and in the NY chat we
construct a sequential chats that
contain multiple steps of chats uh we
first uh send the message to the SEO
reviewer and uh then we send it to a
legal reviewer ethics reviewer and so on
and finally you can have a meta reviewer
that summarizes all the reviewed
comments in different areas and gives
the final
comment and uh from the writers Point
View it's still talking to a single
writer a single CTIC agent uh but
underneath critic agent uses multiple
other agents so that's idea how we can
use n chat to potentially extend the
agent capability using
conversations and uh think about two
using how do we enable two using using
conversations uh here's the example of
um building a game of conversational
chance we want the AI to be able to play
the chat while chitchatting with each
other and making fun of each other so if
you just ask two language model agents
to play the chat directly they often
make mistakes and form like random moves
on the board which are not legal so the
game is not um uh watchable at all uh
now uh the solution can be that we can
add a third agents called chessboard
this board agent is a toolbase agent it
uses some python tools uh python library
to manage the chessboard and uh provide
the tools to other language model agents
so the language model agents can only
make legal moves and uh otherwise they
need to be iteratively refined their
moves until the moves are legal uh in
that way we can make sure the game can
carry on nicely and uh again we're using
NY chat between a two proposal agent
using language model and two execution
agent that using two as a back end and
having them talk to each other to finish
that to execution
functionality and there can be other
more complex uh work workflow patterns
uh and solving more Compass task using
planning uh and using more Dynamic way
like group chat in group chat uh the
users uh only need to Define agents of
different roles and then can put them in
a group chat and they can automatically
decide uh which agent to speak next
depending on the current progress of the
task uh there there'll be a group chat
manager which can monitor the progress
and make the selection of the
speakers and furthermore you could add
more constraints uh or Finance dat
machine transation logic about uh what
orders should the agents follow uh you
don't have to make a very strict order
you can just give some candidates about
like agent a after agent a speaks only
Agent B and C can speak not other agents
things like that so there's still some
decision made by the language model and
some autonomous there but you can add
certain constraints to um to uh make
sure at least uh the selection is within
within the scope uh and you can further
add some transition logic to tell the
agent uh when you see certain situations
you should go this route otherwise you
go to the other parts and you can use
either natural language or PR language
to specify
that yeah uh in general there are many
other uh type of uh conversation and uh
applications enabled by these
conversation patterns uh for to check
our website for more notebook examples
uh they are nicely taged so you can
search for anything question for example
search for how to integrate autogen with
L index and there are notbook examples
like that um and uh and in the paper we
just showed a few like very simple
examples using simple conversation
patterns but in general we can build
many more complex tasks using this
building blogs I've seen uh developers
building all kind of sorts of complex
tasks um so here's the overview of like
the uh categories uh of domains that I'm
we are seeing from the community uh the
top two categories are software
development and agent platforms buing
research data processing game long taale
there's a web browsing tasks Finance
Health Care education and even
blockchain which is not shown in the
list
uh and here I want to select a few
interesting examples uh the first one is
in the science and engineering domain um
this uh uh Professor Marx Boer from MIT
has uh has done multiple work in
different sense domains including
protein design material design using
autogen to build uh teams of agents that
simulate the behavior of a scientific
team or engineering team all the way
from like collecting the data generating
hypothesis and then conduct experiments
and verify the hypothesis uh they have
also built a very recent work called a
sign agents which can use colge
Knowledge Graph to Reas about any
scientific domain and make interesting
connections and do Advanced reasoning
using that Knowledge Graph they contract
a team of uh agents of multiple roles
and uh they can start from understanding
antology and then make multiple science
and critics to finish the very complex
work flow uh including generate uh all
the different concepts and possible
hypothesis and then select the best of
out of them so this a very promising and
use case I see that uh in future has a
potential to accelerate our SCI
Discovery and maybe soon after we'll
have some AI designed uh medicine or AI
designed uh architectures and so on or
or or
um interesting law and materials here's
another uh domain of web agents uh this
is a agent Called Agent e uh developed
by a startup called Emergen AI they use
autogen to build a hierarchical agent
team so that um they can perform some
very complex uh tasks on on the web like
automatically book a flight tickets or
automatic uh form
for medical clinics um this um this
leverage some planning agent uh some um
uh web browsing agent and have some
deeper understanding of the content from
HTML Dom they they haven't used any
multimodal models so they're only
leveraging the HTML content and not
leveraging the images uh and the vision
models they already achieved the SE of
the art performance on this web Voyager
Benchmark uh and other performance of
previous
techniques using multimod models uh the
there's still a large room for
improvement you can see the overall uh
success rate is just 73% so by combining
multi model models and the more agentic
uh workflows it's there's a potential to
get it higher even higher um but there's
some very good like foundational design
principles uh we can learn from
Network and uh I also want to share a a
very recent quote I learn from a company
doing uh construction uh they're trying
to use autogen to uh help the users
without the special knowledge or expert
knowledge to be able to finish their
construction projects and uh they
mentioned the benefit of aigin as uh
being able to rapidly explore many
different a agentic design patterns did
configurations and conducting
experiments at
[Music]
scale um and that to summarize we have
seen a big Enterprise customer interest
from pretty much every vertical domain
and got contributors or users from
universities organizations or companies
from all over the world including uh
some uh contribut from
Berkeley uh there's a work called mgbt
uh created by brookly students and they
also have integration of autogen um very
nice work um so we see that there's do a
lot of like changes and progress uh in
in autogen and uh here are just a few
examples in several uh categories
including evaluation interface
learningteaching
optimization in the evaluation category
we're building accident based evaluation
tools to help developers understand how
effective their application is how good
their agent are uh it's it's really
difficult task because uh there are a
lot of text generated and it's hard to
um understand what exactly is going on
but using agents they're able to
automatically uh come up with success
criteria based on the application and
task and then suggest uh the the scores
for each
Dimension uh and furthermore we can
extend that idea to improve agents over
time right by uh providing the feedback
to the agents themselves and have agent
based
optimizations uh or or learning on
teaching
capabilities uh one Center piece of
autogen is still to uh improve the
program interface to make it even easier
for people to build all sorts of uh
agenting applications uh so I want to
talk about one particular research that
uh excites
me uh this is called autobuild uh so uh
one uh remaining question uh for many
developers is what is the most effective
multi-agent workflow I should use what
agent should I create for my particular
task so autobuild is designed to uh
address that issue as initial attempt uh
so it works in this way the user first
provide a task uh to describe the high
level requirements and the the system
will suggest agents of different roles
automatically and these agents can be
put together in the group chat to solve
the task and uh for new task more
specific task the other task we can
revie this created a teams uh to to
solve that without users need to
specifically specify which agents to
use and we can further extend that idea
from static agent team to Adaptive agent
Team U so there there a technique called
adaptive build uh and in this case we
can uh first decompose a complex task
into smaller steps and then for each
step we propose uh a spe agent team for
it we can use choose from existing
library of Agents or decide to create
new agents that don't existed before and
after finishing one step one step we uh
now check what new agents do we need for
the next step so these agents can be
dynamically conected and as we create
more agents we can also add them back to
the library to improve overall system
over
time uh and we make uh experiments on
several different benchmarks including
math programming data analytics and so
on and find the uh very prom result at
out firms previous uh techniques of
similar
kind yeah this is just one particular
example of research uh we're doing there
are many more challenging questions uh
we still need the community to work on
them together uh the biggest question is
how to design optimal MTI agent workflow
for any application and considering
multiple factors like quality the
monitary cost latency and manual effort
uh in general we still want to improve
the agent capability from the reasoning
planning multimodalities or learning
capabilities and uh we also want to
ensure like scalability and uh make sure
human has a good way to uh uh guide
their safety and so on yeah so so that
that's the uh that's the end of my
lecture so I want to ackowledge uh all
the open source contributors and you can
find our discr community we have very
large community on Discord and find this
new Kap organization um and uh I'm happy
to follow up with with questions thank
you very much um hey everyone uh that
was a great talk by by tree uh from
autogen and yeah you know I hope to
build upon that I I think I think this
is uh this talk is a bit less like um
generic I guess like in terms of the
covering a lot of the different agent
architectures and stuff this is actually
quite about like a specific use case
around building a multimodel knowledge
assistant um and so it's really focused
on on maybe some principles around like
Rag and how do you actually extend that
building like a research agent and it's
like a use case that we've been
exploring pretty deeply as a company uh
but of course you know there's plenty of
agent stuff out there you should
definitely check out autogen um check
out you know W index try building stuff
on your own um and then see what we can
come up with uh so let's get started um
and first um if you're not familiar with
lendex lendex is a company that helps
any developer build context augmented LM
from prototype to production so we have
an open source toolkit the open source
toolkit is a developer toolkit for
building agents over your data um well
different types of llm applications
these days there's a lot of people
building you know agents uh we started
off helping people build like rag
systems um and now you know we're going
into territories where people are
building slightly more advanced stuff
where you're using llms for multi-step
reasoning as opposed to just like single
shot you know synthesis and and uh PRT
like uh generation
um we also have an Enterprise product
which I probably won't talk about too
much today um but it's basically like a
managed service to help you you know
offload your data indexing and Rag and
all that stuff I'll talk a little bit
about one specific piece of this which
is uh document parsing or you know data
parsing and we think this is like a
pretty important piece in any sort of
like context augmented pipeline so let's
get started um how many of you know what
rag is yes um so one part of rag is you
have a database
and so a database of some knowledge and
the way it works is you first want to do
retrieval from that database to return
basically just a bunch of text to chunk
it and then you know given the chunk
context uh embed it and put it into for
instance a vector database uh and we'll
talk a little bit about that as well so
um this overall goal of building a
knowledge assistant is that you know um
a lot of companies have these types of
use cases where they have like a lot of
data they have like million PDFs they
have a bunch of PowerPoint presentations
they have Excel files and you want to
build some interface where you can take
in some task as input and give back an
output it's that's really it if you
think about a trap bot that's basically
a trap bot um so you have a lot of data
you want your llms basically understand
that data and then you want uh you know
the LM to do stuff with that data um an
example could be generating like a short
answer it could also be generating like
a structured output a research report it
could take actions for you like send an
email it could schedule a calendar
meeting write code uh do a lot of these
things um we talk a lot about like rag
um as a company and especially if you're
just getting started if you follow like
rag 101 on how this works we call that
basic Rag and so what is basic rag basic
rag is you take like your unstructured
data you do you you load it with some
you know standard document parser and
then you chunk it into you know uh every
thousand tokens or so you just just
slice that text up into a bunch of
slices and then you stuff each slice
into an embedding model uh like open Ai
embeddings and then you put it into a
vector store then when you uh return
stuff or you do retrieval from this
database you typically do you know
semantic search or vector search to
return the most relevant items from this
knowledge base uh and stuff it into the
L and prompt window this entire pipeline
gives what I call like a basic rag
pipeline it'll work uh kind of in being
being able to answer basic questions you
have over that data um however there's a
bunch of limitations um and the four
limitations we list here is one is the
data processing layer is pretty
primitive um when you do the chunking
you're not really doing uh or taking
into account all the different elements
within that data um you're not really
taking into account you know are there
tables or images or weird sections and
you want to semantically preserve
different chunks together um you're only
using the llm for synthesis and so
you're not using it for any sort of
reasoning or planning and so if you
think about all of what like G just
talked about with respect to agentic
coordination and stuff you're doing none
of that with a basic rag Pipeline and so
it's kind of a waste of LM capabilities
especially with the latest models like
01 uh 3.5 like cide and whatever um like
a lot of these models have much greater
capabilities and just being able to
summarize over a piece of text and so
you want to figure out how do you
actually use the model capabilities to
do you know more advanced reasoning or
planning the other piece you know
standard rag pipelines are typically one
shot so they're not personalized um it's
just like uh after you ask a question
it's going to forget about it and so
every new like interaction will
basically be stateless this has certain
advantages but you know if you're
building a personalized knowledge
assistant ideally you're able to add
like a memory layer to that so uh a lot
of what we asked ourselves is can we do
more than a basic rag pipeline there's a
lot of like questions or tasks that a
naive rag pipeline can't give an answer
to this leads to hallucinations uh for
the end user like uh you doing like like
having a chat bot where it can't answer
like 80% of the questions you might want
to ask it uh is kind of like a limited
value ad and so how do you you know
build uh this more generalized knowledge
assistant that can take in questions of
like arbitrary complexity and answer
that over arbitrary amounts of
data uh we think a better knowledge
assistant has four main ingredients um
so uh and and actually specifically the
focus of of this talk is is on like how
do you um take in like a multimodal or
build a multimodal knowledge assistant
so instead of just you know uh reasoning
over like uh like standard text file how
do you reason over like an entire
research report with a lot of diagrams
and pictures images how do you uh like
basically reason over all the visual
data that exists uh you know on the
internet uh in addition to just text so
the first piece is we need a core
highquality multimodel retrieval
pipeline um we we want to then U maybe
generalize the output and think about
something that's a little bit more
complex than your standard chat barot
response so generating a research report
doing data analysis taking
actions three is agentic reasoning over
the inputs so this is where you know
instead of just uh you know taking in
the user question and only using the LM
for synthesis um like applying Chain of
Thought uh tool use reflection all that
fancy stuff uh to try to you know break
down the question do some planning and
actually stepbystep work towards an
overall goal um and last is deployment
uh we'll see how long I have I plan to
probably talk for 15 20 more minutes um
so just cover some of the high level
details and for some of the actual like
uh like the examples uh they're
basically Linked In the slides in case
you want to check them
out the first piece is setting up a
multimodal rag if you're familiar with
rag you might be familiar with rag over
text Data uh but what we're really
interested in is having rag actually op
over just like visual data and by visual
data I don't just mean like a JPEG file
um I mean even if your PowerPoints for
instance like uh or or like a research
like archive paper it's going to have
like you know charts diagrams it's going
to have like weird layouts and the issue
with a lot of standard rag pipelines is
they do a terrible job at actually
extracting out that information for you
um and so like like I mentioned uh any
llm or rag or agent application is only
as good as your data processing Pipeline
and if you're familiar with the garbage
in garbage out principle in traditional
machine learning I think for llm
application development uh it's no
different so you basically want to have
good data quality as a necessary
component of any production L map this
ETL layer for llms uh consists of
basically you want to do some parsing
from the document um you want to figure
out a smart way to chunk it and then you
need a smart way to you know index it
and put it into the LM prompt window
um this data source that I talked about
like this case study of complex
documents uh is uh pretty common data
format that we see across a lot of
different companies and so a lot of
documents can be classified as complex
uh like embedded tables charts images um
there's like irregular layouts there's
like headers and Footers um and a lot of
times um you know when you kind of apply
like uh like uh off-the-shelf components
to parse a lot of this data it ends up
in a broken format and the LM huc
hallucinates the answer users want to
ask different types of questions over
this data so you have a bank of like say
PDFs you want to ask questions over it
it could be simple pointed questions it
could be multi-document comparisons it
could be longer running like research
tasks a research task could be you know
given these 10 archive papers around
like you know like LM quantization or
something generate like a condensed
summary or like a survey paper right and
so that's something that's a bit longer
or higher level in nature compared to
something that's just a simple search
and retrieval
task um so we'll start with the basics
which is just parsing um ideally a
document parser can actually um
structure these this complex data for
any Downstream use case I won't talk
about it too much because you know the
goal of this is really about agents but
really like uh without needing to know
the internals of like document parsing
you need to have like a good PDF parser
basically um because if you have a bad
PDF parser then you're going to load in
some PowerPoint or PDF it's going to not
really extract out the right text from
that PDF and then when you feed in text
that's been hallucinated by the parser
the LM is going to have a really hard
time understanding that no matter how
good the LM is um so ideally you
basically want a parser that can parse
out like text chunks tables diagrams all
that stuff into like semantically
consistent ways um that is one of the
things that we do is we make a pretty
good J powered PDF parer um we're at
like 30,000 plus users right now um uh
and and yeah I mean if you're interested
in trying it out everybody gets like a
thousand credits or pages per day um and
so it's used at you know different small
companies to to larger
Enterprises so you want to have a good
parser and what this enables is um it's
actually uh an important piece in being
able to structure your data in the right
way if you think about different types
of data so here is like maybe like an
investor slide deck here's a 10K annual
financial report here's like an Excel
sheet here's a form um having that
parsing and extraction step to extract
out stuff in a clean format of data
gives like it's just much easier for
llms and retrieval processes to
understand
that afterwards once you've actually you
know parsed out a PDF into its
consistent elements in uh a good way you
can then leverage like hierarchical
indexing and retrieval to um uh do
something more fancy than your standard
rag pipeline so given this like you know
structure or document structure of like
text trunks tables and diagrams um for
each of these elements um you know a
standard rag pipeline will basically
directly try to embed each of these
trunks but we found for instance a
better approach is you actually extract
out a bunch of different representations
that point to the source trunk so for
instance for a table you might want to
extract out a variety of different
summaries that point to that table for a
picture um I mean a picture you can't
feed into a Tex Ting model anyways and
so you need to maybe use some model to
extract out a variety of different
summaries that point to that picture um
for bigger text chunks you might want to
extract out like smaller text chunks
that feed to that bigger text
Chunk once you uh you know extract out
these representations we call these
nodes because these are the things that
will be embedded and indexed by the
vector database that you're using so if
you're using a vector database like pine
cone or whatnot um you know you can
basically extract and index uh this
metadata that is associated with the
source element but is not like the
direct source element itself then during
the retrieval process uh you know given
a user question it'll first retrieve the
nodes and because the nodes have a
reference to the source document you can
basically dreference it and then feed
the resulting element into the model
notice that most models these days are
multimodal in nature if you look at 01
uh gbd 40 uh CLA like 3.5 Sonet the
latest gini models by Google they can
take in both text and images and so the
nice thing here is that you can still
use text embedding models to represent
the element itself but then like you
know when you actually feed stuff into
the llm you're able to feed in both text
and images and so what I just outlined
to is a basic way of like you know of
building a multimodel rag
pipeline so a multimol rag pipeline can
take in you know any sort of document it
could have uh different types of visual
elements in that document and it will
store both text and image chunks um and
so in order to index the image chunks
you could use like clip embeddings or
you could do what I said which is like
you know use a model to extract out text
representations and Link the text
representation to the image trunk um and
so when you set this up then during
retrieval you feed in uh or you return
both the text and the image Trunks and
you feed both to a multimodal model
I'm going to skip this example but here
is like a basic uh example here that
shows you uh how to build like a
standard multimodal rag pipeline notice
up until now you know I haven't really
talked about agents yet this is just
like setting up the basics of a you know
multimodel Rag and so you don't get the
benefits of like train of thought or
reasoning or tool use quite yet all this
is doing is saying you know given a
specific question you have about maybe a
more complex data set like research
reports or slide decks you're able to
ask questions and get answers over you
know the visual elements on the
page so the next piece uh actually I
might skip this uh just due a time but
basically the high level idea here is
you know a lot of the promise of Agents
is that it's not just going to give you
back a response in the form of like a
chat response but actually generate
entire like units of output for you so
producing like its own PowerPoint or PDF
or you know taking actions for you or
you know do you guys use anybody use
Claud like instead of tragic anyone use
Claud you know how like when you ask it
to write a paper for you for your
Berkeley essay then it'll actually
generate like an entire thing on the
side that's an example of like report
generation right it'll actually you know
give you like a thing that you can just
directly copy and paste uh into uh
something that you then later edit so
for instance like that this is like a
pretty common use case we're seeing in
the Enterprise too so a lot of you know
Consultants uh like knowledge workers
are interested in like basically like uh
generalizing beyond the capabilities of
just like giving you back unformatted
response but giving you something that
you can just directly use on its own so
whether that's code whether that's like
uh reports um it's all very interesting
and I'll probably um skip some of the
like architectures of how to you
actually build this for now and now we
we talk about agentic reasoning over
your inputs so this is a third section
so we have like you know multimodal rag
pipeline in place now let's add some
layers of ACH reasoning to basically
build a jch
rag um naive rag works well for pointed
questions but fails on more complex
tasks um and again this is due to all
the reasons I mentioned above right
you're just retrieving a fixed number of
chunks um you're not really using the
llm to break down the question in the
beginning um and so if you ask a
question like summarization questions
where you need the entire document
instead of just a set of chunks
comparison questions where you know you
actually need to look into two or three
or more documents multi-part questions
same thing or a highle task uh you don't
really get good results if you use a
standard rag
pipeline so there's a wide spectrum of
different types of agentic applications
you can build and I think CH probably
gave much better architectures of like
you know how multi-agents can
collaborate with each other and and
Achieve very Advanced things um the way
we think about it is like there's kind
of both like simple to Advanced agent
components um at the at the right you
basically have entire like generalized
agent architectures right and so this
includes like you know a react Loop for
for instance which is like one of the
most common agent architectures these
days came out like about two years ago
almost um and you know basically just
uses some Chain of Thought Plus tool use
to basically give you some generic you
know agent architecture you can plug in
whatever tools you want and it'll
roughly try to reason over them to solve
the task at hand this also includes LM
compiler right which is um you know seg
paper and so this basically uh
generalizes a little bit beyond react
into doing some uh pre-planning right so
instead of just planning that next step
at a time I'll actually plan out a dag
optimize it run it and basically replan
uh
periodically um what we actually see a
lot of people these days build is some
people do use react um it's a pretty
easy architecture to get started but
other people just like take some of the
existing components and build more
constraint architectures um and part of
this is just due to the desire for
reliability um even though it's less
expressive even though it can't do
everything um some people are still
building up that trust towards Ai and so
they're trying to solve a specific use
case uh in in the beginning um and so by
solving this specific use case they can
leverage more specific components and
try to you know maybe solve in a more
constraint fashion this includes by the
way like tool use uh like maybe
leveraging a memory module like function
calling we see at a lot of places uh
people are very interested in uh like
structured output generation tool use
being able to call um like an existing
API uh and then also doing some basic
like query decomposition whether that is
Chain of Thought or like parallel like
given a question break it down into a
bunch of different sub
questions this overall thing we call
agentic rag because it really is just
like an agent layer on top of rag if you
think about like rag or retrieval or you
know retrieval from a vector database as
a tool you can think about an agent that
operates on top of these tools um so
instead of like you know giving a query
directly feeding it to the vector
database first passing it through this
General agent reasoning layer um and
this reason layer can you know decide to
do to to to do a bunch of things to the
query and also decide what tools to call
in order to give back the right response
um the end result is that you're able to
build a more personalized QA system that
can handle more complex questions and
this is an example of what I mean by
unconstrained versus uh constrained
flows so for instance a more constrained
flow might just be you know you uh have
a task and you just have a simple router
prompt um a router prompt is just a llm
prompt that just selects um you know one
option out of n um and all it does is
given this task feed the task to one of
the you know Downstream tools based on
you know the decision in the router
prompt um and then feed it to maybe like
reflection layer and then give back a
response there's no Loops in this uh
orchestration all all that happens is uh
you know it will hit the router uh go
through a tool go through you know
another prompt that just reflects and
tries to validate if it's correct um and
then generates a response this I defined
as more constrained because a lot of the
control flow is actually defined through
humans you know through you guys versus
through the agent um and typically the
programs that you know are more
constrained look like IFL statements and
like while Loops that you actually write
instead of the agent um if you're using
like a more generalized agent
architecture like if you're using uh you
know like react or Allen compiler or
triath or whatever um then it's a little
bit more General because you're
basically saying I don't actually know
what the specific plan I want the agent
to follow is I'm just going to give the
agent a bunch of tools and let it figure
it out and so this is more expressive
because it can technically solve a
greater variety of different tasks than
you trying to you know hardcode that
flow beforehand but it's also less
reliable right um it might Veer off and
call stuff like call tools that you
really didn't want it to call um it
might you know um just repeat get stuck
in infinite Loop somewhere and never
converge and it's also more expensive uh
typically these types of agent
architectures use bigger prompts you're
stuffing in more tools at once and so
the marginal token costs are are much
higher um and so uh we see a little bit
fewer um architectures being built with
very wide unconstrained flows But A good
rule of thumb is if you're interested in
you know using react or something TR try
to stuff in like four or five tools and
try to limit it like to to less and like
10 with the current models um we have
core capabilities in L index basically
help you build uh workflows uh so we
call all these things like workflows um
they're basically all agentic in some
nature the very rough definition of an
agent everyone has a different
definition you guys might disagree with
me a very rough definition is just a you
know program like a computer program
that has nonzero LM calls that's like a
very general definition and we basically
help you uh write those types of
programs so whether you try to um you
know Define a very constrained program
where you're writing the if else
conditions or you're letting an agent
handle that task we basically have like
an event driven orchestration system
where you know every step uh you can
listen for a message uh you can pass a
message to a downstream step you can
pass messages back and forth between two
two different steps and basically at a
certain point you know these steps can
be just like regular python code they
could be llm calls they could be
anything you want um at a certain point
the program stops and it gives you back
a response um and so we we're building
out this like very fundamental low-level
orchestration because we believe that
there's some like interesting properties
among like agentic Behavior where it is
fundamentally a little bit event driven
um and this also provides like a nice
base to help like users deploy workflows
to production in the event that you want
to translate your program into like a
python service so track it out I mean I
think um I guess there are some links
here but um you know the the stuff is
all Linked In the
docs um I'm going to skip this piece and
then yeah um some use cases that maybe
uh are are interesting to cover which um
you know I think the the links are
basically here in case you want to check
it out is like we're very interested in
like a report generation use case um so
this is again something that we see pop
up across a lot of different companies
and basically given a bank of data you
want to actually produce some output
from that data an example architecture
for this is you have like a researcher
and a writer um and maybe like a
reviewer as well and you can think about
this as like a multi-agent system uh
depends on how you define it but
basically you have like a researcher
that you know does a little bit of rag
it retrieves relevant chunks and
documents from some database and maybe
like given a task like uh make sure that
it basically it's like going on the
internet and fetching stuff like and
storing it in your notes uh it'll put
that stuff in a data cach like basically
this contains all the relevant
information you need to you know
generate the report the second step is
like a writer um and this writer might
use this data cache to then make like an
llm call that will then you know
generate this inter leaving sequence of
like text image blocks tables and give
you back a full output um so we have an
example architecture here and you know
um we also have some example repos where
you generate like an entire slide deck
instead of just a
report another use Case by the way which
isn't in these slides but is very
interesting is uh is uh customer support
um I think if you look at just practical
Enterprise use cases of Agents customer
support for external facing use cases is
probably number one um this is uh you
know basically like there's uh like just
a lot of automation that could be baked
into the decision flow to basically
increase your deflection rate and
basically ensure that the H like the
user ends up having like a much better
experience and going through like you
know those automated phon many and so we
see that popping up in in a lot of
different places
too um and then the last bit is really
around running agents in production um I
think you know so far if you start off
like building a lot of these components
um you're probably going to start off in
like a Jupiter notebook um and that's
totally fine you know when you start off
building a prototype it makes sense to
do something that's very local um that's
very narrowly scoped and you basically
see if it works over test dat an
interesting design exercise is to think
about what a like complex multi-agent
architecture looks like and how we can
leverage like existing production
infrastructure components to like
achieve uh that vision of like you know
multi-agents in production um ideally
you know if you think about agent One
agent two agent three every agent is
responsible for solving some task and
they can all communicate with each other
in some way so you ideally can
encapsulate their behavior behind some
API interface and then you can you know
standardize the way they communicate
with each other uh through some sort of
core messaging layer you can easily
scale up the number of agents in this
overall system to add more um to this
like multi-agent Network and you can
also take into account you know a large
volume of client requests with different
sessions so this is basically what we're
building uh and you know we're we're
it's it's like a work in progress but uh
We've made a lot of progress in the past
few months is like how do you actually
deploy um you know agentic workflows as
microservices and production um so you
model every agent workflow as like a
service API um we allow you to you know
spin this up locally and also deploy
this on for instance like kubernetes um
all agent communication happens via like
a central message Cu uh you can have
like human in the loop as a service so
for instance like you know if um like
this agent actually needs your input
it'll send a message back to you await
your response and then you give it you
know an input uh before it resumes
execution um how many of you have seen
like the the Devon demo like the
cognition Labs Devon you I'm talking
about how many of you know what like
Devon
is all right so so like half of you um I
think if you took a look at the demo one
example that does is like this coding
agent will just generate an entire
repository for you but sometimes it will
stop right sometimes it will say I don't
actually have enough clar Clarity to
basically kind of give you the response
can you actually tell me what to do next
um and so if you played around with Deon
that's basically what does and that's an
example of the human in the loop this
like kind of interesting back and forth
like client server communication where
the server is actually waiting on the
client to send like a like a human
feedback message so that's basically it
um all these components I think are kind
of like step by step towards this idea
of building a production grade uh
multimodal knowledge assistant over your
data um and yeah thanks