Thanks Don for for inviting me and
thanks all of you for for being here.
It's a it's a pleasure to be uh to be
joining you. Um so what I'm going to do
in this uh in this session in this talk
is is um as advertised by the title I'm
going to talk about my view of
autonomous agents and uh in particular
um a broad view not just you know the
the re the latest incarnation of you
know quote agentic um artificial
intelligence or agentic large language
models but really the roots of the term
autonomous agents um with emphasis on
embodiment interaction and learning and
what what I mean by embodiment is really
robots. I know I've looked through you
know sort of the um the topics that have
been covered so far this semester and uh
there's been a bunch on learning and a
bunch on interaction um some uh so you
had you know from Noah Brown you heard
about multi-agent systems and also I
think your last session was on
multi-agent systems um and and also a
lot on on learning and scientific
discovery but I think there's been less
coverage so far of the embodiment side
or um which sometimes is physical robots
sometimes um simulated robots. And so
I'm going to going to place an emphasis
there. The I'm going to start by giving
sort of a broad overview of um where I'm
coming from, what my what I the kind of
research I do in my lab. Um and so tell
you about a lot of things in very
briefly. So you know, almost nothing
about a whole bunch of things, but then
I'll do a deeper dive on on one or two
things depending on how much time we
have um that go into more of the of the
technical details. Um, and uh, of course
there's there's more information on my
web page and my papers about all the
things I'm gonna going to talk about
here. And you're always welcome to to
reach out if you have um, questions
about things that I only only touch on
briefly. Um, so first I'm going to uh
just talk about what my view is. And I'm
jumping between a bunch of different
slide decks here. So, you know,
apologies if it's not one unified view.
Hopefully things will go smoothly
enough. Um but my view of you know
agents autonomous agents um have been a
focus of study in the field of
artificial intelligence for a long time
um for for at least three decades
actually more than that which is I've
been involved in the in the field for
around three decades um and you know so
much longer than than this sort of this
year's uh buzzword of agentic uh AI but
what is you know fundamentally what is
an an agent Um my view is you know very
simply it's an agent is an intelligent
system that interacts with the
environment through sensors andectors um
as shown in the diagram here and um and
so you know I mean you could ask the
question is a chatbot uh an agent and
you know you usually uh we think of of
an autonomous agent as one where there's
not necessarily an input output sequence
and then it sort of waits for more
input, but but rather more of a
continuous loop where where there's
sensors coming in from the environment
or sensations coming in from the
environment, actions that are taken that
affect the next sensations, but you
don't have to wait to be called or
invoked. And so, you know, there are
software agents. Um there are also
physical or embodied agents which
usually go by the term robot. So this is
a mod the first slide was a modified
slide from um from a definition in in a
term when I a class when I teach
robotics in the first session I usually
ask what what's the um what is a robot
and it's almost the same definition.
It's a robot is an intelligent system
that interacts with the physical
environment through sensors andectors.
So the only word I've added here is the
word physical. Um but otherwise you know
so all robots are are agents not all
agents are robots.
And uh and then I often we often think
about what's an intelligent complete
robot or you could substitute the word
agent here. An intelligent complete
agent um is one that has some cognition
you know the the intelligence aspect. So
it gets the sensations it has the the
actions um and uh you know there's the
raw sensors and the raw actuators which
you if you're if it's a robot you can
think of as being the cameras and the
the motors. Um but then there's the
intelligent part shown in green here
which is the the you know sensing and
modeling the world based on the raw
sensor perceptions uh sensor readings
that that is the sort of perception
module. Um on the other side, the far
other side, there's the action aspect,
um which is, you know, how do you once
you've decided what you want to do, how
do you actually do it? And and then
translate that into the motor commands,
the low-level actuators. And in between
is, you know, what many people consider
the, you know, the the the brains of the
of the system or the cognition where
you're deciding what actions to take.
And that could be through planning,
through multi- aent co coordination,
teamwork, um opponent modeling, or
teammate modeling, etc. So all of my
research is is sort of, you know, takes
this view of of um what an agent is. And
I just wanted to to you know uh to frame
that in the context of of this of this
talk because um you know I think like I
said nowadays there's sort of a some
people take a more narrow view of what
an agent is or an agentic system is but
really it's quite a broad term and and
broadly encompassing.
Um so as I said and I'm going to start
by by t telling you almost uh almost
nothing about a lot of things. Um and uh
starting from where I'm coming from, I
am here at at UT Austin um where there's
a lot of exciting things happening um
the we were awarded one of the first um
National Science Foundation foundation
AI institutes the institute for
foundations of machine learning. This is
an organization spawned the the machine
learning lab that's headed by Adam Clins
and Sanjay Shakotai. Um, we also have a
an ethical AI system on campus um that's
inspired by the 100-year study of AI
that I've been a leader in. Um, but the
one on campus here at UT is called Good
Systems and involves people from from
many different disciplines. It's sort of
the ethical AI initiative. Um, I was the
uh the founding director of Texas
Robotics. We have a um we have a
beautiful new space we're going to be
hosting. Uh this is before we filled it
with robots. It's an old gymnasium
that's now uh filled with robots from
across campus. Um, we're going to be
hosting the conference on robot learning
here in about a year, next November. So,
I hope many of you will be have a chance
to come on campus and and see that. Um,
and there's also a lot of innovative AI
education going on here. Um, we have an
AI an online AI masters program uh at at
a price point of $10,000. We have uh I
um created an AI literacy c uh course
for the entire entire campus with all of
the materials online. Um, so these are
all things I'd be happy to talk about in
much more detail, but from the
perspective of my own research and the
things I'm going to talk to you about
today, the unifying question that's sort
of um held together all of the different
things that go in my that go on in my
lab and have over the past several
decades is this. It's what degree can
autonomous intelligent agents learn in
the presence of teammates and or
adversaries in real time dynamic
domains? And I'll emphasize again, this
question was a was the core question of
my PhD thesis back in 1998. Um, and uh,
it has appeared in almost every talk
I've given since then. And it has
include this included this term agent.
So that's a way of emphasizing that this
is not a new term. Um, it's not a new
buzzword, but really something that's
that's been around for um, for a very
long time in the community.
This question uh causes us to focus in
my my group on publishing in several
different sub areas of of AI, autonomous
agents, multi- aent systems, robotics,
um machine learning, especially
reinforcement learning. And we do both
sort of foundational bottomup research
and more use inspired research. And when
I give a one slide introduction um to
things that go on in my lab, it's a lot
easier to talk about those use inspired
or the use cases that motivate the
research. So, um, one has been, uh, that
that I focused on a lot and found
inspiring is robot soccer. So, here's
some of the old, uh, Sony Ibo robots.
This is a video from from probably
almost 20 years ago of the robots
sensing, deciding, and acting, no, uh,
remote control from the from the Robocop
or robot soccer competitions. Um, they
we've now moved towards uh, humanoid
robots. So, this is a clip from uh, also
a competition several years ago where we
were playing a team from the University
of Braymond. Our robots are the ones
with their hands behind their backs um
and the pink uh the pink waistbands. And
um again, remember that they're they're
fully autonomous. They're sensing,
deciding, and acting like an agent does.
This in is a multi- aent system. So
there's several robots cooperating on
their uh together. Um here you see a a
robot going in on a breakaway. Um and uh
it'll end up um end up scoring a goal.
We went on to win this game and and
winning the competition that year. Um,
and you know, there's all kinds of of
agent challenges that come up in this
kind of a um of a setting. The goal of
RoboCop, the Robot Soccer World Cup, is
to create a team of humanoid robots that
can beat the best World Cup champion on
a real soccer field by the year 2050.
Um, and so this is an ambitious goal,
but it's sort of in that line of um, AI
systems that have done better than the
best humans at various tasks um, from
chess to go to poker. Um, you heard
about uh, I think about Starcraft um, in
this course already. And I'll talk about
another one um, as we go. But soccer
would sort of be taking it to the uh, to
the next level in in many ways. And if
you watch that video, you might be
saying, "Oh, well that's not even close
to to human level." The robots are still
not close to human level, but there's
been big leaps. So, um, that's roughly
what it looked like at the competition
two or two years ago. But at this year's
competition, we had a a game of humanoid
robots for the first time with people.
Um, and you'll see me here with the
ball. And, uh, I was playing on the team
with the robots because it's still too
easy for the player the people to beat
the robots. So, it was three people
against uh me and and the robots. And I
had no idea what was going to happen.
The robots didn't actually even sense
me, but I left the ball for this robot
here that I'm put using showing with my
pointer. And you'll see what happened.
And this was very unexpected. Um but
shows you sort of the level at which
we're um we're getting to now with robot
soccer. So, the robot just turned around
and kicked it between um the Robocop
president's legs. That's Ubu Visser. I
tried to get the robot to give me a high
five afterwards. It didn't. Um but in
any case we're you know at this level
where you know and we would never have
been able to see that um I think even a
couple years ago or even even a couple
months ago let me say um and so there's
there's there is a lot of progress and I
think it's not completely out of
question that by the year 2050 we would
have uh humanoid robots playing at at
human professional level. I wouldn't bet
my life on it. Um it's still I think you
know the the trying to make make systems
like that happen in the real world and
physical systems is much harder than
doing it all in software. Um but there's
been a lot of progress in the past 25 25
years or so. Um I'm also inspired by
general purpose service robots. If you
come to my lab, you'll often see robots
like this one just sort of wandering uh
through the hallways, you know, sort of
in in this kind of a setting. Um, and
actually the Robocup competitions
involve uh general purpose service
robots as well, doing things like acting
as a as a host. Um, having to uh to pick
up items to set the table. Um, put away
groceries.
Um, here's the task serving breakfast.
So, there's a competition called Robocop
at home trying to create robots that are
sort of generally um capable um in this
way. And that's been very inspiring to
my research as well. And then like many
um I've been inspired by autonomous
driving which is you know an autonomous
car is an agent. It has to sense decide
and act. I had a car in the DARPA urban
challenge the one pictured here. Um I
don't have that car anymore as you know
there's the car companies and and
companies like Whimo and and Zuks are
putting a lot of money into making this
a reality. Um but we we've thought over
the course of several decades
now what the world would look like when
all the cars on the road are autonomous.
Would we still need traffic signals and
stop signs or will we be able to see
systems more like this? Um, this was the
basis for Kirk Dresner's thesis back in
might have been 2010 or so. Um, uh, but
this video I think came out first in in
2004. And what's happening is that the
each car is sort of is an agent calling
ahead for a reservation through the
intersection. Um, and once it turns
white, it has a guaranteed path through
the intersection that won't um interfere
with any of the other cars. when they're
yellow, they don't have a reservation
yet, so they often have to stop. Um, but
um the um you know, this is when all the
cars are autonomous. We may be able to
see intersections like that. We've also
looked at what happens if you have human
drivers mixed with autonomous drivers
and um and things like that. And so
there's I could give a whole talk on any
of these these topics. Most recently, I
mentioned that I've been inspired by
these challenges of trying to get AI
agents to be better than than humans at
various tasks. And so, with my group at
um at Sony AI, um we had we actually a
couple of years ago contributed to that
stream of of results. We had a paper on
the cover of Nature um where we created
uh reinforcement learning agents that
were able to drive faster than the very
best human drivers at the game Gran
Turismo um which is a very physically
realistic um simulation environment. And
uh so this was the first time the reason
it was um picked up by nature this was
the first time that AI agents were
better than humans at a real-time
control task not turn taking like poker
and and chess and go and and things like
that. Um but or I should say a
physically realistic um uh real-time
control task. Um and uh you know the one
way to get a sense of that is to watch
above and below a a um an expert human
driver Ken Chan driving um in the
simulator on uh on the top half of the
screen and in the real car on the bottom
half of the screen where he's
controlling the same car on the same
track in the simulator versus in the
real world. Um and it models
sufficiently the slip tree stream and
tire tire slip and traction and things
like that. um so that he was able to
finish the you know driving at his best
in both the real world and the
simulator. He finished the lap within a
tenth of a second of the the times um in
the two you know sort of modalities and
um and there are people who have trained
in this simulator to become professional
race car drivers. And so we did a a race
against um five of the or four of the
best human drivers. Um this was in
October of 20 we first raced them in
July of 2021 and did not win. the humans
were still better than than the um the
AI agents. But then by October of 2021,
um there was an event that's that that's
the basis for the Nature article from
February of 2022 where we beat the the
four uh four of the best drivers in the
world who've put in their 10,000 hours
to become real experts um on three
different uh race car track
combinations.
And since then, it's actually been
deployed in the video game. If you have
a PlayStation um and the game Gran
Turismo, you can race against uh GT.
Sophie, there's been a lot of research
beyond the the paper to make it more
engaging um and fun. But, you know,
fundamentally, this was an a success
story for end-to-end reinforcement
learning where um the agent started
acting randomly, literally just driving
in circles or backwards or off the
track, crashing into things um and
getting reward for moving fast around
the track. And um and after uh about a
day of training on a bank of
PlayStations, um it was able to do
better than the the best humans on an
empty track and after about a week
better than the best humans in a
competitive racing scenario where it
learned skills like this one. Um uh
where the the colored car is the agent
in GT Sophie. The white ones are all
human drivers. Um and uh you know here
you see it learning to take a defensive
line. So, it's not going the fastest it
can around the track, but rather
positioning itself in such a way that
it's hard for the humans to pass it. And
it's learned to do that entirely on its
own. So, this is uh a lot, you know,
work from a large team of people um at
at Sony. Um and uh and like I said, it's
it's ongoing um and uh something that
we're we're really proud of. most
recently that uh with a different team
at at Sony AI in fact very recently this
is just last week or maybe within the
last two weeks that this was published
in nature um we uh we contributed a a
new human centric image benchmark um for
uh basically it's as said here in the in
the tagline and this was led by Alice
Jang um it's the first globally diverse
consensually collected fairness
evaluation data set for a wide variety
of human- centered computer vision
tasks. So really, you know, what what
sets it apart, our goals were to um
identify the ethical and legal issues of
creating data sets rather than just
scraping YouTube and uh you know and
Instagram and Reddit and things that
that go into training these large
models. Um we you know our goal was to
try to um at least at the scale that you
could for evaluation um create a a data
set that where all of the participants
everybody who appears in the pictures
has been compensated and um has
self-identified what the labels should
be that describe them. Um and uh you
know so tried to with Phoebe tried to
establish an industry standard for AI
ethics and also um it's uh you know it's
built ethically but also to evaluate
bias in um in AI models and uh so in a
in a way of of um creating and I'm not
going to read through the slide here but
you can you know you can see some of the
features of of Phoebe um and it it
comprises 10,000 images so it's not
enough to train a model on, but it's
enough to evaluate a model for um for
for biases. It it's the first one that
that sort of goes across the whole uh
global geography, 81 countries and areas
um and categorizes a whole bunch of
different features as you can see here.
um and in you know annotations of the
camera that were that are used the
environment and the the um features of
the the people in in the image itself as
labeled by the person who appears in the
um in the image in in many cases.
Um, and so there's a, you know, we use
this for in the Nature article, which
you can find online now. Um, do analyses
of the sorts of biases that that, uh,
that happen in visual language models
and I verified some existing ones that
were known and also identified some, um,
some new ones.
So that's sort of uh, you know, in a
nutshell, um, the the kinds of things
that inspire me and the research that I
that I do. Um
you you have as I said you have uh one
one another theme that I think comes up
a lot in in agents and you've heard a
little bit about during this semester is
um is human in the loop uh learning
which is uh um learning from from
interaction.
Um and uh there's a system that was
developed by a former student of mine,
Brad Knox, who's now faculty here at at
uh at UT um UT Austin that um was a
system called Tamer teaching an agent
manually v via evaluative reinforcement.
And uh the idea here was it was the f
actually I think you know has a claim to
being the first system to do
reinforcement learning from human
feedback or RLHF which is a key point a
key aspect of training language models
now but sort of his core demonstration
was in the game of te Tetris um that you
see here the you know most of you are
probably familiar you're trying to clear
rows and what's happening in the top
left corner a person is saying good move
or bad move green for good and red for
bad. And uh at first it was random. Um
this was a task that at the time of of
the system you could do with
reinforcement learning if you trained
for hundreds of thousands of games. Um
but Brad was able to show that even in
the first game it can with this human
feedback you can start doing much better
than random. So it's you know already
starting to clear some lines. And um
oops uh and then by the um by the third
game it's able to so this is after just
two games of a person you know prov two
episodes of a person providing positive
and negative feedback it's already able
to to clear hundreds of lines and so
this was sort of one of the early
examples or demonstrations of the power
of learning from human interaction um as
opposed to just random exploration. GT
Sophie was purely from random
exploration. It was all reinforcement
learning. This is reinforcement learning
from um human feedback.
And uh and one of the key lessons here
was that that Tamer learns more quickly
than um autonomous learning from you
know straight reinforcement learning. Um
it doesn't take you know hundreds of
thousands of games. It takes three games
to get to quite a good level. But
ultimately doesn't do as well as if you
allow for the for reinforcement learning
uh to learn from scratch. That's sort of
you may have heard of the bitter lesson
from um from Rich Sutton that you know
injecting human uh input could um bring
down the you know the ultimate
performance but there are also ways of
combining them. So we had an
award-winning winning paper tamer plus
RL which learned both from human
feedback and autonomously. Um and so
this was with also with Brad Knox part
of his thesis. Then collaborating with
Garrett Warell pictured on the right. Um
we had an extension to uh to video in or
image input a system called deep tamer.
And like I said, this really was um I
think the first example of of RHF um in
which has has really uh been super
impactful lately. Um
and so uh and then this has been
extended to um to also uh learning not
just from explicit feedback but learning
from implicit feedback. So, not just a
person explicitly saying good move or
bad move, but you know, you can imagine
if you were an autonomous car and your
passengers looked like this, you
wouldn't need somebody to tell you
shouldn't need somebody to tell you that
you've done something wrong. You've
scared them. Um, and so this is, you
know, should should allow you to learn
from from implicit feedback. So, we a
couple years ago uh in a coral paper
introduced um a system called empathic
for evaluative mapping for effective
task learning uh via human implicit
cues. But it's about learning from
implicit human feedback. Um
and uh and then we've you know we've
gone on to um to think about all the
different ways in or many of the
different ways in which humans can um
provide uh input in in machine learning
um through um the the robot navigation
problem where a robot has to start at a
point and get to a a global goal by
while avoiding obstacles. I'm not going
to go into the details on this is again
I'm just going to um sort of show you
the the the punch line um where we were
but we're it's trying to learn to have
the robots move through very constrained
spaces
um which is not a solved problem yet you
know so it's navigation is pretty well
known how to do it but um but if but if
you're trying to navigate through very
constrained spaces that are not much
bigger than the robot um there are you
sort of navigation packages out there
Oops. Uh, I wanted to go to the previous
slide here. Um,
well, yeah, there's navigation packages
out there, but they require lots of sort
of opaque parameters, things like this
that you wouldn't really know how to to
tune if you wanted the robot to work
well. And they're different in very
different settings, whether the robot's
in a corridor or an open space or or
sort of an obstacle course or, you know,
sort of a pinch. And so, um, it you
right now if you want to get a robot to
navigate effectively in these kinds of
spaces, it takes a a roboticist to
fine-tune those those, um, planet
parameters, or at least it did. And so,
we explored various ways of using um
human input to um to allow for a robot
to learn how to do this. So ranging from
a teleyoperated demonstration where a
person is literally just remote
controlling the robot um and then the ro
then we have the robot explore in
parameter space to come up with the
parameters that would lead to the most
similar behavior um to sort of the less
slightly less demanding corrective
information interventions where a person
doesn't need to always be um remote
controlling the robot but can just sort
of step in when the robot is doing
something wrong. And again now the robot
can try to emulate or predict when a
person would uh step in to intervene. Um
we had a system called uh for for doing
it from a value to feedback which is
much closer to the tamer system um where
the you know where the person just has
to say good move or bad move give
positive and negative feedback all the
way up to reinforcement learning uh
systems. And so um you know you can also
find a full talk on my on my website
about the various different technical
algorithms behind doing this adaptive
planner parameter learning. um where
we're you know rather than learning the
all of the different parameters of a of
a of a navigation stack we're instead
treating that navigation stack like a
like a black box and um and learning the
param just the parameters that will lead
to the behavior that you want um and so
you know the way we the way I think of
this is is in the machine language of
machine learning um we're learning a
parameter policy rather than outputting
the raw actions we're outputting the
parameters to a navigation stack or a
classical motion planner and trying to
learn which ones lead to the actions
that that uh that you most desire.
So, um
so that's the that's I think that that's
where I'll stop in terms of telling you
almost nothing about a lot of different
things.
the one you know I did like I said I
when I looked through what you the
topics that you've covered um so far the
there have been I think less on the
physical robots than on um on the multi-
aent systems and the reinforcement
learning that I um that I focused on a
lot um oh actually sorry I take that
back there was one more thing I wanted
to tell you almost nothing about um
which is on the interaction side uh a a
problem that's fascinated me um over the
last um decade and a half or so called
ad hoc teamwork. Um which is a
particular type of interaction where the
goal is to try to create um an
individual agent that is good at
cooperating with teammates, but you
don't necessarily get to or you don't at
all get to control who those teammates
are. the kind of thing that people can
really do well when they're playing
pickup soccer or pickup basketball or
you know the um but now we want robots
to be able to do by um creating by by uh
you know if there were a disaster rescue
scenario and lots of different people
brought the robots together. We don't
want to have to reprogram them to work
as a team. We want them to be able to
figure out on the fly how to be able to
work together. And so there's a bunch of
work in my lab also on how on this
problem of of creating a good team
player which is I think a part of the
the you know sort of multi- aent systems
challenge or the interaction challenge.
Um and there is a there's a challen
there's a challenge paper from triple AI
2010 that introduces ad hoc teamwork as
a problem and then it's been there've
had been a bunch of theoretical research
and experimental research um on the
topic. Okay. Now I really do uh you know
that that's sort of my um the the
whirlwind part of this talk where I've
told you very little about a lot of work
that pertains to machine learning
especially reinforcement learning um and
interaction especially ad hoc teamwork
multi- aent systems but you you know
you've seen some coverage of those in
the semester already um with regards to
embodiment I'm going to take a little
bit of a deeper dive um and show you a
paper from just uh from just it was
presented at Coral just about a month
ago. Um, and let me put this into full
screen mode. Um,
wait, why is this not working? Um,
try it again. Um
and uh and this is going to this is the
goal of um
uh
I'm sorry this should be
coming up. Um the goal of trying to to
do um reinforcement learning Oh, there
we go. Um
in the real world. So um so the the
motivation here is and I should say this
is the the PhD thesis work of um of
Jahen Hu shown here um and it's and he's
co-advised by myself and Roberto Martin
and this paper was published like I said
at Coral the conference on robot
learning um recently and so the uh the
paper is it's slack for simulation uh um
pre-trained latent action space for
whole body real world RL. And so the key
here is trying to do um real world RL.
Um I want to get rid of that little
thing there. Um
oh that's not what I want to do. I'm
sorry. This is not going exactly how I
was hoping. Uh let's just keep it in
this mode. Um okay. So it's it's
learning visual motor contactrich whole
body mobile manipulation um
with real world reinforcement learning
without a single demonstration. So when
you're doing learning in robotics,
you can't do what we did with GT Sophie,
which was learn on a bank of of
PlayStations, you know, hundreds of
thousands or millions of of interactions
while we were all sleeping. The
computers would be working. Um, when
you're working on a real robot, you have
to work very very efficiently with with
with very little data. And so you have
to you have to learn um very
efficiently. So, and and the motivating
task here is uh we want to do whole body
mobile manipulation. So, um this is you
know a task such as uh wiping the blue
mark you the blue off of the whiteboard
while avoiding the obstacle of this
trash band. So it requires the robot to
know how to move to um to avoid
obstacles and not just to you know like
the standard way to do this with
reinforcement learning um would be you
know to to just explore lots and lots of
random actions first and you can do that
if you have a simulator. Um but it's
costly to build highfidelity simulators.
sometimes infeasible to to build a
simulator that that you know simulates
your robot well enough that if you just
um you know learn in simulation you
apply the policy in the real world it
would just work. There have been some
successes of that but it's not uh you
know it's not always straightforward. Um
and so you know we want to try to learn
without the the benefit of the learning
happening in the simulator. Uh one way
people often get around that is through
imitation learning or some kind of
learning from human feedback as I showed
with the adaptive planet parameter
learning but that can be very costly uh
to collect and the high quality
demonstrations. So our goal is to do
real world reinforcement learning uh
with directly learning from from real uh
interactions without this high fidelity
simulation or demonstrations.
And so, you know, like I said, if you
just, you know, use a standard
state-of-the-art reinforcement learning
method, um, you're going to just flail,
right? So, if you're trying to learn to
to wipe the blue mark and you're getting
reward for for wiping the blue mark, and
you're just sending random commands to
the all the motors of the robot, moving
the base around randomly, moving the arm
around randomly, you're not going to get
very far. It's going to, you know, um,
probably the battery is going to die or
you're going to lose patience before it
learns to do anything correctly.
And so the there's a huge challenge for
trying to um learn with sufficient
sample efficiency and safety um in the
real world. And so the system that uh
that Jen came up with is um like I said
called Slack. And the key here is that
we need a um a good action space to um
to facilitate sample efficiency and
safety in the in the real world. If we
if we have rather than sending raw
commands to the robot, but have a much
more abstract action space, then there's
much less to explore and we're going to
use this a lowfidelity simulator to come
up with that latent action space. So,
um, so we're going to, you know, assume
that it's not that hard to come up with
sort of a rough simulator of the robot.
um and that um and that we can then use
that to uh so you know here's a like a
picture of what a low-fidelity simulator
would might look like. So it sort of
models the robot but it's not going to
be perfect. Um and uh and we want to use
um what's known as unsupervised
reinforcement learning to learn task
agnostic behaviors in a low-fidelity
simulator. So what does that what do I
mean by unsupervised reinforcement
learning? That means a giving a um a
robot or an agent a an environment to
explore in but no reward signal, no
task. So it's unsupervised because
there's no reward signal and t and get
it to try to just figure out all of the
actions that it might want to take that
might be useful when it is given a
reward function down the stream
downstream. So in in the future. So, you
know, the kind of thing when we put a a
you know, a baby in a playpen,
um a human baby in a playpen, they tend
to like, you know, um try stacking the
stacking blocks up or squeezing things
to see what noise they make. They don't
really have any task to do, but they're
in some sense training themselves to do
things that might be useful once they
are given tasks. And so, that's the idea
is trying to get a robot to do the same
uh the same sort of thing. That's what
the unsupervised reinforcement learning
idea is. And the goal here is to come up
with this the types of actions that you
might want a robot to do. Um and so you
know what we're trying to learn is a
latent action space. Um that where you
give just a you know you define a number
of dimensions you know some small set of
dimensions. Um
and uh and then try to make it so that
when you change, you know, when you
change these um the latent uh the latent
actions, you get meaningfully different
um behaviors in the real world. So that
um so that you you're getting a uh that
this latent action space can um you know
create you you might imagine that the
robot would would learn to get close to
the whiteboard um versus getting far
away from the whiteboard. Those are
those are something that you can do by
just moving the base of the robot. Um or
you could imagine another action
dimension controlling the arm or where
the camera is pointing. Um and so we
came up with a with a method called
dusty or disentangled unsupervised skill
discovery. Um and this was you know
before the slack paper that does learn
this sort of diverse temporally extended
behaviors. Um by trying to come up with
um by maximizing or minimizing the
mutual information between the behaviors
you get um when you uh when you change
the lat the the latent action features.
There's there's been previous work uh
there was a paper called diversity is
all you need or Diane from Sergey
Lavine's group that that had that that
insight initially um but one of the
things we added is that we tried to do
it in a disentangled way um so to create
a structured oops a structured action
space um by which we mean that if you
vary one latent variable it only changes
one dimension of the action space um and
also add safety. So what I mean by that
is um we want to add two different
reward signals. One is such that if you
you know if you change one of the latent
action features it only changes one
aspect of the of the robot's behavior.
So here the red indicates where the
camera is pointing and the blue
indicates where the uh the arm is moving
and the red indicates where the base is
moving. We wanted sort of a nice
structured action space so that the you
know you can um if you vary one of the
latent action features and hold the
others constant it'll only move you know
the base the arm or the camera and so
that was something that we were able to
do using dusty um using what we called a
skill empowerment reward um and then uh
we also added this handcoded safety
reward that's like don't collide with
yourself something like that um and when
you put those together you can you know
come up with I uh train the the action
decoder and this and the latent actions
um such that you get this structured and
safe set of actions in the lowfidelity
simulator.
And then once you have that in the
second step of Slack, you can then um
you can then take the the learned latent
action space and use it for downstream
task learning in the real world. Um and
so you know again you have this lower
dimensional action space where each
dimension changes the you know different
aspect of the robot. And so then we're
going to separately um develop a
factorized version of soft actor critic.
Soft actor critic is one of the popular
reinforcement learning algorithms. It's
actually the basis for the one that we
used in GT Sophie as well. Um and it uh
leverage leverages the structure of the
latent action space.
Um, and so what what I mean by that is
that once you're given a um a reward uh
you know once you know what your reward
terms are um you might have sort of uh
you know a reward for where the robot is
located um that can be controlled by
where the base is a reward for where the
robot is looking that could be
controlled by where the camera is
pointing a reward for what the what
you're picking up or touching based
which is controlled by where the arm is.
Um and the the uh the idea is that not
every um latent factor controls every
reward term. So you can get a much
sparer and more accurate Q pred uh
prediction of the value function in
reinforcement learning terms um if you
can learn to separate which factors
control um which action factors control
which which reward terms. And um and so
we did this in a in a paper that
appeared at at RSS 20 2023. Um we used a
a conditional mutual information um
metric that uh that you know that allows
us to to say well if I change um a
particular action dimension, how does it
change the uh the reward factors that I
um that I get? Um, and so you can sort
of learn a masking matrix that says if
you want to if you have a reward term
that only depends on where the base of
the robot is, which um action factors do
you need to vary or you know or can you
vary to get that reward and so on for
every other um other factor. I know I'm
going sort of quickly here uh from a
technical perspective. I'm not going
through all of the math, but you can you
can find this in the papers that are
referenced on the on the slide. And um
and so then we can uh you know we can
use all the the data that's that's used
to infer which action factors affect
which reward terms um in uh for for
learning. And I'll get to the you know
sort of the punchline and the video
demonstrations here coming up. um we can
take some real world tasks um and then
do learning entirely from um the onboard
observations um from the robot's camera
and proprioception which is you know
sort of where the joint angles are at
any given time. Um, and now learn a task
policy, the one that actually gets
rewards for the task. Like in this case,
it's sweeping something into a into a
basket. Um, with your frozen pre-trained
latent action model, which is what you
use the low-fidelity simulation for to
come up with this structured action
space.
And then um if the you know if the
action space is lowdimensional enough
you can actually learn um to you know to
control the various reward factors where
to look where to move your hand where to
move the the um the base um by
exploiting that causal matrix from the
previous slide that you know allows you
to to um to change the uh the a various
action um factors to get the various uh
to maximize the various reward terms. Um
and uh and then here's a demonstration.
So you know at the start of training um
a robot has no idea how to solve its
task just like in the previous video I
showed you. So it's sort of moving
around randomly. So here's the first
minute or so of of training minute or
two. Um but after only 40 minutes so you
know uh it it gets a behavior now where
we we've given it reward for um for
being able to uh um successfully wipe
off the blue marks from the board and
it's learned to successfully move the
base camera and the arm in unison to be
able to achieve that task. Um and again
with all of the starting from random
behavior and 40 minutes later having
having learned this skill but by
leveraging this very efficient action
space that was learned in simulation
using exactly the same methodology we
can in that same latent action space it
can learn to um to you sweep garbage
onto a tray or garbage into a bag
um and uh and also it can learn to wipe
the the whiteboard with or without an
obstacle in front of it. And so we've
done these four different tasks that I
just mentioned um and compared to doing
all of the simula all of the learning in
simulation or um a couple of existing
methods um that one that surl which
learns entirely in the low-level action
space rather than in this more
factorized abstract action space. um
also uh another method called RLPD and
we both have higher success rate at
those four tasks and importantly fewer
safety violations during um during
learning so that the robot can actually
do this learning efficiently um in the
real world and in all cases all of those
policies trained in less than one hour
on the real robot so that we end up with
a with an autonomous agent that's able
to um to learn in that in that case. So
you can learn a lot more uh details um
from the paper. Um and uh and this is
you know a a theme for a lot of the
recent research in my lab is trying to
to use simulation but uh to allow for
learning in the real world world but not
necessarily um by just learning all in
simulation then transferring the policy
directly but instead leveraging the
simulation in more creative ways like
here to to pre-train a a um an efficient
action space. And of course, like many,
we've also been exploring now, can we
use foundation models, large language
models, and visual language models to um
to not necessarily control the low-level
actions of the robot, but to provide
some of the common sense um knowledge
for the robot.
Okay. Um so that's what I wanted to do
in terms of uh the embody you know sort
of a somewhat deep dive into a
particular research uh paper on the um
on embodiment. Um I think I have time uh
to to also go in a little bit of a deep
dive um onto on GT Sophie as well. So
I've given you sort of an overview of
this um oops where is it um
uh
oh I think I have it right. There we go.
Um,
so, uh, I've given you a sort of an
introduction to GT Sophie, but I'm going
to tell you a little bit more about it
now and then I'll, um, and then I'll
pause for for questions. So, again, to
remind you, this is the the work that
was done at Sony AI on out racing
champion Gran Turismo drivers with deep
reinforcement learning. So, this is
going to that other extreme where we now
do have a simulation. Um, and actually
the whole task is to to do well in the
simulation. So, this is not embodiment
anymore. This is to build a um a real
you know worldclass world expert agent
um at race car driving. Um and uh I
showed you this slide already but the
success was you know just like in the
the success cases of chess and and poker
and go um it relied on a great compute
architecture. There was a lot of data
that went in a lot of engineering. It
wasn't just sort of a new uh you know
out of the blue um principle. Um so
there's there's a lot of you know
there's a lot of uh data top-notch
engineering and compute but there also
were a few um algorithmic and
methodological insights that went into
making it possible and I'll try to give
you a sense of those right now. Those
are what are featured in the um in the
in the article. Uh, just as a reminder,
in every video I show you, the the um
the colored cars are going to be GT
Sophie and the white ones are are
controlled by one of the very best
drivers at um at GT Sophie. Um I've
already told you about the simulator
itself. Um
and uh that we do this with with
reinforcement learning. Um oops. the the
main challenges that made this sort of
you know more difficult than previous
previous tasks was that it's real-time
control. So you we had to come up with
actions at 10 times per second where
it's acquiring a deep understanding of
the car dynamics understanding in quotes
but the ability to control a car um
following racing lines precision racing
maneuvers to um and it's you know when I
say at the edge it means you know if the
the car has the the controller has to
figure out if it goes you know how fast
it can go. So if it goes any faster it's
going to spin out but you know if it
goes any slower it's going to be easy
for a human to pass. It's got to be
right at that edge of being staying in
control. There's also tactics like I
showed you already the example of
defensive moves, but there's many more
um that I'll show you about. And also,
there's this really sort of interesting
and illdefined aspect of etiquette where
um you know, you can't just push another
car off the track. There's a human judge
that decides what's sportsmanlike and
and not and the the agent has to be you
sort of have that encoded um as well. So
in this case, the actions um that the
the car used were um at 10 hertz, it
could either control the brake or the
throttle uh to be full backwards or full
forwards, can turn full left or full
right. It's really already a factored
low lowdimensional action space. There
just two dimensions to it. So you we
don't have to go through what we did
with Slack to try to discover that we we
gave, you know, the agent already has
this natural factored lowdimensional
action space. The rewards initially are
just how fast it moves along the tracks
and then we added that's mainly you know
the positive rewards and then also
penalties for the tires slipping or
going off the track or hitting a wall.
And then there were initially in the in
the initial work we we had um not visual
features. Um we have some a couple of
papers since uh since then where we have
used visual inputs to to help the the
car control. But in the initial paper,
we were giving things like the car's
velocity, acceleration, roll, pitch, and
yaw, load on the tires um and position
along the track um to help it. And um
um the uh the compute infrastructure was
really important. By doing this within
um uh within the Sony ecosystem, we we
were able to partner with uh Polifany
Digital and uh Sony Interactive
Entertainment, the play the PlayStation
group to to have access to a large bank
of of PlayStations, which we could then
use in a sort of an actor kind of uh
scenario where we have a lot of rollout
workers getting um getting data on what
happens when you take an action and what
state uh comes back. And then we used a
um you know and we store that data in an
experience in experience replay buffer
and then use an actor critic method
based on soft actor critic um but
introduced a new algorithm called
quantile regression or QRSA quantile
regression soft actor critic um to be
able to train the policy uh which is pi
that's what actions you take and the
critic which is the value function which
is basically an estimate of how good how
good it is to be where you currently are
in the state that you're Right. Um and
so here's a slide of technical details
for people who are familiar with
reinforcement learning. Don't worry if
this doesn't all speak to you, but um
but basically uh you know QRSA was was
learning not just the um the average uh
or the mean value of taking an action
but the full distribution. What's the
likelihood of a really bad thing
happening versus a really good thing
happening when you take an action? Um so
it's you know sort of learning a
quantile or you know a distributional RL
value function as as it's called. Um and
was also using nstep returns rather than
onestep returns to to improve its
performance. The numbers here on the
right are the lap time in a particular
configuration on on a particular track.
And so smaller is better. If you can get
around the track in 114 seconds that's
better than um 115 seconds. So it's
about almost a second one second
improvement which is pretty huge in this
domain between this the vanilla soft
actor critic and our new algorithm. Um,
and we also found the sweet spot for how
the endstep returns. The details are in
the paper and I have talks that go into
the much more detail on how QRSAC works.
Um, and the neural net training details.
But the bottom line is that um, is that
you know after an hour um, the car is
able to move forwards, not run into
walls or drive off the track, but not
very efficiently. After four hours um,
to move, you know, sort of much more
smoothly. after eight hours um pretty
expertly and actually after a day
although you know we can run it for a
week it's really at superhuman
performance like a person can't control
and it's hard to see I know uh on online
in zoom but it's you know cutting the
corners just exactly right at the at the
you know in the optimal way um and uh in
a way that a person can't do any better
um and in fact it does better than
almost every person in the world we we
tracked it against you know after four
hours eight hours and 24 hours we the
the blue uh here is a histogram of the
best lap 100 lap times reported by
people on a worldwide server and um
after 24 hours it's better than almost
all of the the reported lap times and if
you take the average of um of a person
you know the best person's average is
shown here on the left and the
distribution of GT Sophie's times are
you know better than the second third
fourth and fifth and on par with the
best person in the world and that's just
on this one track on the other two
tracks is significantly better than the
best person's uh average time
and um so you know that was sort of the
the first step but in this domain being
faster wasn't enough um there were two
other challenges to to solve um like I
said you know there's the race car
control which which I showed you we can
do but there's also the tactics and the
and the etiquette so to be able to do uh
to to bring that we augmented the state
space to include knowledge of where the
other cars are nearby their relative
position velocity and acceleration for
the cars in front of beyond and behind.
Also a reward for passing, a penalty for
being passed that encourages cars to be
a little more risky when they're near
other cars to get around them. Um, and
then importantly, we had to curate the
data. This was another one of the, you
know, sort of innovations. Um, so so
that you know the car gets the
experience that it needs. So we put
like, you know, a bunch of scenarios
where it's just r where it's just racing
on the empty track. We can put 20 cars.
An important thing to note is you could
put 20 cars on the track at any one time
on a place on in the game. And so, you
know, we could put just 20 cars spread
out around to get a lot of data. But
then we also created some situations
where there's one car behind one other
car or one behind two or one behind
three or one behind seven. So, it gets
experience driving in traffic. And um
and in particular, you know, to it gets
experienced where it starts behind
another car on a straightaway where it
can it's encouraged to but not
explicitly told to learn what's known as
a slipstream pass where just sort of
like bicycle racing, you draft behind
the other car so that you have lower air
resistance and you can get a lot of
momentum and then bounce out from behind
them and and be able to pass them. Um
that to be able to learn that you it's
important that the simulator actually
models this slipstream effect and it
does. Um, and then also, you know, where
you start behind another car in a
corner. So, you learn these sort of
crossover pass maneuvers. Um, and also a
bunch of other tactics like what happens
when you're in a grid of, you know, the
start of the car or if you've got these
sort of particularly difficult parts of
the track. And so um one of the things
that that was a key to the success here
was was creating a carefully engineered
mix of data in the experience replay
buffer so that various ports points
along the track it would have be
learning from data from different places
um and uh and then create a mini batch
for training that gives the car the
right mix of experience. And for the
nature paper we did this manually but
then since then we have worked on
automated methods for coming up with the
right mix of data um in this experience
replay buffer. So some of the skills
that were uh that were learned by this
agent um were things like that
slipstream pass where and and these are
narrated and you can find some talks
online where you hear hear the sound as
well. I don't have that working right
now. Um but like you know where the GT
Sophie is the colored car again it
starts behind the other car gets in that
low air resistance mode and then is or
location and is able to pass. Um so
that's an example of of that happening.
Um I already showed you the defensive
skill. Um, and uh here's here's a really
that that a double crossover where
you're going to see um the uh two
different cars um the green and the and
the gray I think start out behind the
two human drivers. Um but by the end of
this turn they come out um both of them
in front of the of the human drivers.
And so you see on the right sort of the
position or the line that they took to
be able to successfully do that that
crossover pass. And again, this was not
handp programmed in or explicitly
rewarded in any way. It was just part of
the overall um uh learning process and
the experience that we gave them. And
then finally, there was this uh aspect
of of etiquette. Um, I'm not going going
to go into the details either here, but
there's, you know, the things like
trying to um avoid uh you avoidable
collisions, forcing a driver off the t
track, doing things illegitimately that
are all sort of judgment words, things
that a human steward would have to um
have to, you know, assess whether
they're happening or not. Um, but, you
know, if you don't do this, you'll end
up with aggressive agents like the one
shown here. Here's also showing the
interface of a person controlling the
car. But here's what's you're not
allowed to do. You can't just push a car
off the track like that. Um, but you
also don't want to be too timid. So,
this was a clip where GT Sophie was in
front and the human um announcer was
saying there's there's no way that the
person's going to be able to pass. It's
a commanding lead. But then GT Sophie
actually hit the brakes because it was
too timid. It was too concerned about
causing a collision and allowed the
person to um to pass. And so we needed
to come up with ways of sort of um
mitigating that. I think the the human
pass is coming up right around here. Um
right now GT Sophie is still in the
front, but I think uh you'll see uh
yeah, here's the the um Tamoaki
Yamanaka, the human extra. Now he's
finally passed GT Sophie um because of
that that timidity.
Um, so we added a bunch of sort of uh
reward signals to to make sure the agent
wouldn't be too um to uh sort of um
wouldn't get into collisions um and and
also especially wouldn't cause
collisions that it's that it would be
judged as being at fault for and
penalized for. And so we did an analysis
in the paper of how this uh how you know
the different mix of opponents and the
reward um functions would lead to
different uh aspects or different uh
agents. Um I'm running out of time so
I'm not going to I want to leave time
for plenty of time for questions. So um
you know there's also an important
aspect here of like you know we train
lots of different agents but how do we
choose the one that that's going to go
into the uh to the actual race? That's
an interesting aspect that's covered in
the paper. Um but the bottom line is
that you know in July we the humans
outgraced the the people um and so we
had a we had a rematch and in um we
analyzed what went what went wrong. We
spent a few months improving it. Um and
by uh October um oops by October created
a a set of agents um that was able to
finish first and second place in an
eight car race, four four GT Sophie cars
against four humans in a set setting
where you got points based on like 10
points for finishing first, eight for
second. Um and then uh I think 76543 for
the rest or something like that. Um that
was on the previous slide I think what
the scoring was. Um uh
yeah uh 108 and six for the first three
places and then 54 321 for the other
places and double points for the the
harder uh start test. And so you know
but the bottom line is by October we
were able to finish first and second in
all the races. And interestingly you
know there were some quotes from um from
some of the drivers including Emily
Jones. Uh I'm not going to play you that
that's her there, but saying things like
I've learned something from the uh from
the agents. I watch them. They're
driving differently than I would and
they've improved. Uh they're things that
I ought to try. Um and now like I like I
said earlier, this has been permanently
deployed in the game in GT Sophie. Um
and there's been a lot of testimonials
from gamers um that this is a real big
addition to to Gran Turismo. Um and uh
and now it's you know it's out there on
many more uh cars and tracks and um but
you know there's still a lot to do. Um
one of the things that we're trying to
get the agent to drive with style. So
here's if we you know added a a reward
for drifting the car learns to do
something like this to come to go around
turns which is not something any human
driver would do. Um but it sort of does
a little spin move uh moving into a turn
and sort of optimally comes out of it.
Um, and uh, and you know, also, um,
trying to make it more, uh, fun. Uh,
that was an important part of putting it
into the game. It wouldn't be fun if we
you could just race against an agent
that can, um, outra all of the best
people. At least if I were playing the
game, I would see the agent, you know,
just for the first couple of seconds and
then it would be gone ahead of me for
the rest. So, we needed to have sort of,
you know, a way to make it also
adjustable in terms of its skill level.
So again, this was work of a a huge um
uh group of people at at Sony AI and uh
and so I encourage you like you know
there are hourlong talk talks about this
on my web page. You can get the the um
you can get the paper as well. Um but uh
that's mainly what I wanted to what I
wanted to show you um today. I know it's
been a little bit of a oops a little bit
of a whirlwind. Um but I wanted to you
know the the one of the main things I
wanted to drive home is that you know
autonomous agents research has been
around for a long time. Agents are you
know quite a general thing. Um they're
you know they're they're um oops
intelligent uh systems that interact
with the environment through sensors.
Sorry this is getting this has gotten
jumpy. Um there we go. Through uh
sensors andectors.
Um, and that an intelligent complete
agent is one that has perception,
cognition, and action from those sensor
in between the sensors and the and the
actuators. And that key components of
autonomous agents from my perspective
are interaction and learning for sure,
as I think have been big big themes
throughout your semester, but also
embodiment, trying to get things working
on real robots. And so, um, with that, I
I invite you to again learn many more
details about all of the things I
mentioned today, um, from my, uh, from
my web page, from publications, um,
from, uh, if you look at my teaching
page, there's a lot more online talks
that have in some cases full one-hour
talks on things I just mentioned for a
minute here. Um but with that I'll thank
you for your attention.