We're super lucky to have today with us
Sham Sanker who is the CTO and executive
vice president of Palunteer and has been
with the company for 19 years. So Sham
is one of the few people who has seen uh
Palunteer go from being basically a uh
Stanford side project as as I understand
it for you know a few for a few uh CS
seniors and Peter to being one of the
biggest um computing infrastructure
businesses in the world. just gonna get
started with how you got
from being a Stanford alum to your
journey at Valente. Why don't we start
there? We we could even start with why I
came to Stanford. And speaking of the
rain, I my first three weeks at
Stanford, I felt like something is
really odd about this place is that
there had been no rain. You someone who
grew up on the East Coast, it rains all
the time. I grew up in Florida, it rains
every day, right? you know, and and you
have that like one shower that happens
in September and then you don't get you
don't see rain again until maybe January
or or or March here. But I I really came
to I went to undergrad at Cornell and
when I graduated in ' 03, most of my
computer science and e classmates went
into consulting or banking. Uh the only
tech company that recruited on campus
was Microsoft. Like even Google didn't
come to Cornell then. So if you were
actually interested in tech, you had to
figure something out. and I came to
Stanford as a way of getting to the
valley. Within two months of being at
Stanford, I I was a fifth employee at
Zoom with an ex, the a company that
Kevin Hartz had co-founded. Um, and I
only met Kevin because I took a business
um I guess a a business plan class at
Stanford that led me down the path of
remittances, which is what Zoom did for
a living. And uh I had just, you know,
doing competitive research, I found out
there's this small company in San
Francisco. I went to meet him once he
realized I wasn't an actual competitor.
I was begging hat in hand for a job, you
know. Uh he whisked me into the office
and my next meetings were with Rolock,
who just joined as the partner at
Sequoa, with Keith Ra Boy, who was at
the time starting a NASCAR magazine, if
you could believe that. Um and that's
how I got uh into the PayPal mafia,
which is a kind of a prerequisite to how
I ended up at Palunteer, right? So I did
that for three years. It was a ton of
fun. Um, but I had always had my heart
in national security. So my path to
America was, you know, I was born in
India. My family lived in Nigeria for a
long period of time. My father was a
pharmacist. He set up the first
pharmaceutical manufacturing facility in
Africa until he built that facility in
Nigeria. All drugs were
imported. But there was a horrible armed
robbery at the house. The the robbers
decapitated the dog. They threatened my
mom. They almost executed dad. One of
the five armed robbers kind of
intervened to to save him. and he just
he exited just being pistol whipped. Uh
and we left all of our earthly
possessions behind and resettled in
Orlando as as essentially refugees. We
started over selling knickknacks at
theme parks. And dad never really was
commercially successful again in his
life, but he died the happiest man just
knowing that we were safe and could
prosper here. You know, he reminded
every every day of the counterfactual,
but for the grace of this nation, you'd
be dead in a ditch in Lagos. I actually
tried to drop I was at Cornell during
911. and I tried to drop out of Cornell
and join CIA. I think like me and 100
100,000 other people had that idea. So,
they didn't really return my my
application. Um, but when I found 12
other people at the time, I joined Pal
as the 13th employee who really wanted
to work on problems of national
security, I was ruined. What was I going
to do? Work on a Ajax calendar app after
that? you know uh and and so I had a
single track mind of of joining the
company and um at the time you know the
the the world of sort of traditional
Silicon Valley software in the post.com
era which was largely consumer internet
companies and government really did not
interact. Yeah. I think there's a couple
of phases to what we could call as like
Silicon Valley's resistance to what
Palanter was working on. Right. The
first phase was just it was actually not
a political statement. They people
literally like very famous VCs that you
would all know would say like this is a
real waste of talent. Like maybe you
should make software for banks. You know
it's it's really sad that you're wasting
your life working on problems for
government. So it was kind of like a
political apathy and not believing the
problems are important. About 10 years
later it became more of a political
statement. Something like we think the
government's evil. You shouldn't do this
sort of work. And obviously we're in a
very different place which I think is
awesome. Uh it also hearkens back to our
history. We forget that in the 50s
Loheed Martin was the largest employer
in Silicon Valley, right? Do you do you
feel like we are
now if if you step back and you chart
the the evolution from the moment you
you joined Palunteer as you know first
15 folks to where we are now. Um
obviously a ton has changed like you
said about the interaction between the
cultural interaction between Silicon
Valley and and government. What's
changed most in your mind about the
technology stack have have at the time
infrastructure private infrastructure
was kind of and civil infrastructure the
internet stack was quite different from
the government stack. Not sure there was
an internet stack, right? Like when I
joined, S3 hadn't even been released.
There was no AWS, right? Um I I I think
we've gone through like multiple epochs
of infrastructure evolutionary and and
they're pretty profound. Um we really
started the business at a time where
everything had to be on prem, right? You
know, um and
everyone was building essentially big
monolithic applications. That's all
there was. You know, building uh
scaleout infrastructure. was like a new
concept that was really suited for kind
of research where these onrem stacks you
know people like Google were making
headway of do doing on their own uh
and it sucked you know it was just
really hard to do particularly in our
case you can think about all of our
customers were airgapped you know they
were not connected to the internet
couldn't SSH to it from your office in
Palo Alto you had to physically go there
because it's a classified it's not the
internet right uh and then you have
additional constraints like you you know
you need more hardware it's like it
turns out that's like a six-month
process to go get more hardware. And so
you're thinking about the need to
optimize was very very strong early on
and um you know you you talked
about if customer in contrast to let's
say a company like Google where scaling
if there was an incident with
infoscaling the s sur team you know was
basically here and was able
to had full root access to the
infrastructure. Yeah. Um if you didn't
have that privilege with a government
customer then what did you do? Uh well
in the beginning we had to actually kind
of forward deploy our S surres to the
customers environments. That's obviously
very like manpower intensive and it's
very hard to scale. I think that's one
of the interesting scaling challenges at
Pounder. It's not just how big is the
infrastructure. I mean it is quite big
and any given hour for our our cloud
infrastructure we might be destroying
and creating 20,000 pods but it's
actually how heterogeneous it is. is not
that we have a handful of multi-tenant
cloud stacks. It's that I have a
thousand production environments, a
hundred of which are airgapped uh and
that you know some of these are single
tenant stacks for specific customers.
Some of those environments are running
on an M1 Abrams tank, some of them are
in a submarine and some of them are just
giant, you know, EU multi-tenant cloud
stacks. Uh and so then as an engineer,
how do you how do you write your code in
a way that's going to run across this
heterogeneity? how do you get the
observability you need to make that all
work uh in a world where you're not
going to be able to afford deploy all of
your S surres and that that was a
journey for us that took about a decade
that I think is is probably the
infrastructure thing I'm most proud of
having built at Palunteer is what we
call Apollo our software delivery
infrastructure so we have about 5,000
I'm just going to use rough orders of
magnitude 5,000 discrete microservices
you can think about those as products
you know different engineers will own
different surface area across that a
thousand production environments 100 of
which are air gaps so they're not
connected to anything. Uh, and you have
we do about 100,000 upgrades across that
infrastructure a week. And the only way
to do this stuff at scale is to build
robots, you know, and it took us the
better part of seven years to really
build all these robots. But really, um,
we wanted to to replace our FTEEs or I'm
sorry, our SRRES with these robots so
that the engineers, the product
development engineers are operationally
responsible for their code. You might be
sitting in Palo Alto. You have a handful
of microservices that you own. You write
the code. It doesn't matter which one of
these thousand environments is having a
problem. You're actually going to get
paged at 2 am to have to deal with it.
And you have all of the infrastructure
you need to cut a new release, hand it
over to the robots, and let it
orchestrate and fix and remediate the
problem across that surface.
Before we go deeper on it, could you
just take a second explaining what
Apollo is and why it was necessary to
build? You could say what was our life
like without Apollo? you know, you had a
thousand production environments, but
let's call it hundreds of environments.
And um, you know, you would you would
have to go to the environment with this
DVD, maybe multiple DVDs of all the
binaries of the latest versions of the
software. And you'd be you'd SSH in and
you'd start like trying to upgrade the
stuff and you'd be trying to manage the
dependencies in your head of what what
services to upgrade in which order to
manage these things. If something went
wrong, you'd have to roll back. It could
get very very complicated. Um, well,
actually, I I should start even before
this. Let's go back to the monolithic
world, right? You know, our software
development life cycle of 2006 to
2009, these were big quarterly releases.
We were only releasing once a quarter.
Uh, you know, you would do as much
testing as you could. The engineers be
really happy. And then you you enter
upgrade hell. You have to go environment
by environment and try to upgrade them.
Inevitably, there'd be some problem in
one of these environments. So, you'd
have to roll back and figure out what
was wrong. How do I cut a new release to
deal with this? Uh, the the environments
are mission critical. So some of these
places like our early deployments in
Iraq or Afghanistan, you have uh a
daytime window because all the
operations are happening at night. You
have a daytime window to do the upgrade
in. If you can't succeed inside of that
window, you actually have to roll back
because the you know if the software is
down, the mission screw up, right? So
you have like the weight of the world it
feels like on your shoulders as the
engineer to go get this done. Um, and
what would happen is you'd have these
environment drifts. Like inevitably
things would, you know, you'd be one
release behind, which means you're six
months behind or two releases behind,
right? Engineers are trying to manage
code that's so old relative to what
they're trying to work on now. Um, it
was just wildly inefficient. So in a at
the same time as we were rearchitecting
the entire stack to be microservices
oriented, we were building robots to
help us to actually deploy and manage
this so that every team could release
truly independently on their own
schedule with no willingness of any of
the other teams. And that required us to
come up with an abstraction between the
products and the environment. Every
environment has different constraints.
Okay, this is these these are when the
upgrade windows make sense or you know
this environment is going to be
disconnected for a few months because
it's going underwater something like
that. Um uh and this environment is an
on-prem environment with different
resources in this cloud environment. But
then you also have the products as as
the engineer. If you have 5,000
microservices, you don't want to think
about and have to know about all of the
other microservices, right? You just
want to think about your world. And
getting to a declarative approach where
the engineers can say these are my
dependencies. Uh these are the versions
of other services I require. This is my
upgrade strategy. I'm doing a blue green
upgrade. These are my health metrics. I
and here's my you know I I I am going to
use a fivem minute soak time and this is
how I measure whether the upgrade's
healthy or not and I can I can
declaratively describe how I expect auto
roll back to work etc. And once I do
that and package all that up with my
microser you hand it off to Apollo and
it will orchestrate everything. It will
figure out the canary paths the it'll
it'll it'll do the blue green upgrades
for you. It'll provide you all the
observability and telemetry that you
need. Uh and so you can just keep
focusing on releasing code and not have
to worry about your environments. So
well speaking about upgrade hell the
first version of Apollo
um was deployed in 2006 or so is that
right? Well uh really like I'd say 14 I
mean before then it was we were just
like musling it ah right okay got it
yeah and uh you could say it was like
the pre-appollo dark ages where humans
were sres and had to do all this work.
Got it. So the first nine years was
basically onrem customer by customer
instance uh sort of um versioning. Then
2014 was when Apollo became a the
horizontal plat deployment platform
across all the different business units.
Um what has changed the most since you
you moved from uh pre-Apollo to post AAO
world in now 10 years later world? Well,
it just enabled us to go so fast. You
know, with this sort of mission critical
software that the typical way that
people think about it is when a crisis
happens, right, you're going to enter
code freeze. Like change is risky in the
context of a crisis. But if we think
about like the Afghan evacuation, um
there was no notion of a passenger
manifesting software. So if you were
going to go code freeze in that crisis,
you you'd be basically managing the
passenger manifest on Excel or
something, right? So if we do 100,000
upgrades a week on a normal week,
actually in crisis we do more because
code velocity increases. Software turns
out it's your most malleable weapon
system, right? So why wouldn't you lean
into that? So it allowed us to turn what
was historically viewed as a constraint
into a capability, right? And you know,
we built the operation warp speed uh
COVID vaccine distribution supply chain
in two weeks and that that I think
that's a great illustration of what
malleability can get you. C could we uh
go a little bit deeper on you know you
just talked about crisis versus not.
We've had previous speakers in the class
talk about what incident response looks
like for them in a traditional
infrastructure environment like at
Cloudflare um like at Uber um what does
that look like in a post Apollo world
for you guys? Is there an incident or
story that comes to mind that is most
memorable? Well, one I'd give you it's
like what it it makes it makes most
incidents look like non- incidents. So
like let's take log for J for example.
Right? You have a thousand production
environments. You have this critical
vulnerability. Um I think most most of
these enterprises that we deal with,
they don't even actually know what
versions of what libraries are running
where. They start at the starting point
have an inventory of the vulnerability
surface area. Well, Apollo, we actually
know that with precise detail of what
versions of what software is running in
every one of these environments. So with
you know t equals z, we knew the
complete vulnerability surface area. uh
Apollo actually you can you you in it
has an awareness of CVEes. So if there
is a new CVE that comes out and uh
there's a prior known previous version
without it, it will auto roll back,
right? There's no paging, no engineer
gets involved. It's already it already
does that. That probably happens, you
know, I don't know, 20,000 times a week.
Uh with log 4j, we had to cut a new
release of the of a patched library and
within 24 hours, it had it had deployed
that everywhere across the entire
surface area. And so there's basically
no manual intervention and there's no
crisis that you have to deal with. Now,
I'm not saying incidents don't happen,
but we were able to massively reduce the
surface area of incidents that we do
actually have. And the incidents that we
do have to tend to um have to do with
usually responding to real world events.
You know, when ballistic missiles are
flying at Israel, you have an
instantaneous spike of 10 times the
number of users on your stack. And uh
unlike the commercial cloud, the the
high-side clouds, the classwide clouds
aren't actually infinite. You know, it's
like when those when that stuff happens,
you actually have to get on the phone
with AWS and ask them to rack more
servers. uh and and so how do you manage
that? You have a different category of
incidents of the consequence. Um one of
the you know Palunteer has this uh
long-standing tradition of
producing really talented engineers who
then go on to start other companies. Um
because they they get this incredible
boot camp in what it t what kind of
infrastructure
uh challenges you have to solve if
you're actually solving um mission
critical problems. And it's quite rare
to to be able to get that exposure
anywhere else outside in in Silicon
Valley. And then one of the things I've
heard those alums often complain about
the most, what they miss about Palanteer
once they leave is Apollo and Rubik's.
Can you talk for a second about why
Rubik's what led to the need for
Rubik's? Well, Rubik's so because we
have heterogeneous environments, right?
Our production engineering
infrastructure like our production
infrastructure is a big deal to us is
it's the core abstraction between the
environment and the engineer, right? So,
if you're the engineer and you have to
be burdened with all the knowledge of
Kubernetes and the and how is this
Kubernetes on prem different than this
Kubernetes in the cloud like your
velocity goes to It's just too
much it's too much knowledge, too much
burden. Uh so Rubix acts as our
multi-tenant Kubernetes orchestrator on
top of all this environment and because
we work in very regulated
complianceoriented environments. The
typical way of dealing with compliance
you have these controls actually you
know they exist for a reason. They're
actually they're reasonable that you
need these controls. The way that most
people go about implementing them is
with humans with process. So it's by
convention you follow these controls and
and that's really hard to scale across a
thousand environments. You have three
environments you can probably muscle
your way through it right at a thousand
environments you have to encode all the
controls in software and then you have
to think about really clever ways of
enforcing. So I'll give you one example
of this um you know keeping your
environments uh as secure as possible.
It's obviously critical as part part of
these controls. One of the things Apollo
uh Rubik's does is it treats all
container images as immutable. You get a
lot of benefits from a security
perspective if container images cannot
change. Then there's a question of well
how do you do patching? Well the the
answer is we don't we don't patch the
container images. We every container
image can live at most for 72 hours and
it's randomly destroyed between 40 and
72 hours and when it's rehydrated it's
pulled from a fully patched new
container image. Right? If you think
about how hard that makes your surface
area for an advanced persistent threat
for a nation state actor to go after you
have to compromise every host every 72
hours. It's like good luck. Right. Um
but now I've removed all of that toil
away from anyone. So even the production
engineering team is not thinking about
are these images patched. The the
software engineers don't have to think
about that. Um you have a declarative
approach to managing ingress egress out
of your environments. It's so a lot of
the stuff that ends up being where you
kind of leave the door open and create
vulnerabilities and create challenges.
It just goes away. And that's as true
whether you're in a closet in a broom
closet running on an on-prem stack or
you have the modern infrastructure of
commercial cloud. And at what point do
you decide that some part of the
application level that an FTE or forward
deployed engineering team is building
for the customer actually then belongs
in the Rubik's layer versus living at
the on the application layer. Well,
ideally the Rubik's layer, it's like the
the least susceptible to to changes from
the customer because it's kind of like
the abstraction that all the software is
running on top of, right? But I think
that that is a that that's kind of part
of the secret sauce of the application
layer, right? So if you have all of
this, you can go about creating the rate
of experimentation at the application
layer. You're now liberated. You can go
really fast. You don't have to worry
about, hey, I just built a little
prototype and then there's a million
questions. Well, how is it secure and
are you allowed to deploy in this
environment? all the bureaucracy that
ends up building up because you encoded
in software it's by default on your
first commit was actually allowed to go
into that environment and it's
production ready as a consequence. So
it's like how much of the production
readiness can you move into software
instead of into convention and that's
what gives a lot of speed and the reason
that I think is important is like with
consumer software there's probably more
of kind of a Gaussian distribution like
it's it's it's a normal curve you take
you take a bunch of inputs from a bunch
of customers so you kind of make some
sort of sense to average them out and
see where the signal is and then build
that one thing.
Uh I think the enterprise is pretty
different. Uh it ought to be pretty
different. You know, I think it's more
power law. Like some of our customers
have a problem today that they're
actually living in the future. They if
you if you service the the service area,
you'd be like, "Oh, only this customer
has this problem." But if you look at
that problem with taste with product
strategy, you're like this problem
everyone is going to have in five years.
They just don't know that. And it's
really
work this thing and solving this thing.
uh and uh and you can almost really
solve it because the problem only exists
in one place. You need to solve it
inductively. So from induction, how do
you figure out the general solution over
time? So I solved it once, I solved it
three times. Now I've earned enough of
an opinion to figure out how how to say
visually solved, right? the I think a
fairer accounting of the operation warp
speed example I gave I could only do it
in two weeks for the US government
because two years earlier I had solved a
problem that was structurally identical
in oil and gas to optimize hydrocarbon
production for BP you know when I solved
that problem I didn't know it was going
to be what was going to be involved
worth you can't connect those dots
looking forward only only looking
backwards but I knew that this is a very
valuable problem to solve uh and if you
can solve this problem we will figure
out a way to demonetize it over time Um
let's talk about an example
where responding to real world events
was much faster um and allowed much more
experimentation as a result of building
the platform right getting the right
getting the abstractions right enough in
enough advance that then when it came
time to deployment the team was able to
do it super fast uh which is project
maven can you just walk us through the
the the story there yeah maven started
in in the US government roughly 2017
where the government they called it
algorithmic warfare like what is our
next offset you know um uh how do we
drive more deterrence and and really the
the question there is John Boyd had this
concept of the udaloop observe or decide
act whoever can go around this loop as
quickly as possible is going to win he
really came up with that that doctrine
for dog fighting like because we were
getting our ass kicked by the MiGs and
we couldn't understand why why are these
Soviet MiGs better than us and really
the our airframes were just less agile
you couldn't get around that loop fast
enough. Could you take a second to
explain what algorithmic warfare meant
in this context? So in this context it
was really about how can you you know
how many of you guys have used global
entry and come through like okay two of
you. So it's actually you know it's
actually kind of a pretty pleasant
experience now. You show up it sees your
face and it's like you you get a you
don't have to like scan your passport
anymore. If you think about the global
entry sensor, your face is about 80% of
the field of view of the sensor, right?
If you think about a space-based sensor
taking a picture of the Earth, the thing
you're looking for is less than a thou
two two 10,000 of a percent of the field
of view. So, okay, you took this
picture. What are you supposed to do
with this now? Right? in in the
classical way before alic warfare is
like a human is scanning panning through
probably what is like a 10 mile by 10
mile photo of the earth looking for
something an analyst
it's ridiculous you know so you could
you you're always looking for the keys
where the lights are on you know uh and
so this is an you think about 2017 where
we were see computer vision was you know
getting mature it was the first place to
start it's like great so I should be
able to take pictures of areas of the
world I care about and look for missile
silos. Look for uh transporter erector
launchers. So like you could have
ballistic missiles that are driven
around on trucks, right? And they're
always driving them around because they
want you to not be able to find where
they are, right? Uh and if you want to
drive deterrence, you want to be able to
tell your enemies, I know where every
one of your ballistic missiles is. You
know, don't it's not worth today is not
the day to to start because I know
where everything you have is. Right.
Right. And that's how you preserve the
peace. So it's a clear application of
how can you use that to to to determine
where all the targets are. But as you
start pulling on that thread, you know,
the journey from say 2017 to the present
is uh you start by saying we we all have
this like top gun maverick view of the
world where it's like well don't we
already know that? So if you think about
military doctrine
um actually any strike that that takes
less than 96 hours of planning is
considered a dynamic strike. You know
for the history of warfare we've always
thought we'll have plenty of time to
plan things and the planning phase is
actually quite slow. They call that
deliberate planning. It's quite
deliberate. Um the logistics are
complicated. That's why you kind of need
this. So, you know, our our ability to
actually respond to unanticipated moves
of the adversary is is low. You know,
you get into a cycle where you you're
like, I don't know how to do this yet.
Uh so, the first challenge that was
given to us is, hey, how can I even find
a thousand things to go destroy in 24
hours? That was hard. It was hard to go
find those things in a in a
circumscribed set of area.
Once you solve that problem, you realize
like, oh, I can find these things, but I
don't know how to process them. Like, I
what what am I supposed to do about
them? And that's the next kind of
challenge with alphabetic warfare, which
is like, okay, well, how do I figure out
what are the right weapons to use? What
what units would I dispatch that? How do
I get through the process? How do I get
the the the JAG, the lawyer, to sign off
on this? How do I know that I have
positive ID of what I'm shooting at? Uh,
and then once you solve that problem,
you realize, well, I'm logist I'm
logistics constraint. I'm actually out
of ammo. I can't even do this mission if
I wanted to do it. So, how do I now
solve those problems? That goes to
predictive resupply? Like, how do I know
what to order before I'm even doing this
mission? How do I start evaluing
evaluating the counterfactual regret?
Like, if I take this shot, actually
tomorrow there would have been something
more valuable to go shoot at. And you
can see how if you get really good at
this, if you're 10 times better at this
than your adversary, that is a very
powerful deterrent.
And at what point I mean part part of
the the the deterrence doctrine there is
that your adversary needs to understand
your capability. Yeah. So at what point
when you're building this capability did
you was your calculus that okay now
we've got to actually broadcast this
capability to the adversary because if
they don't know about it then we're not
effectively deterring them. Yeah. Well
the military has regular what they call
exercises. you know, they're always
exercising and part of the exercise, you
know, there's the it's really their
calculus, not mine on what do you reveal
and what do you conceal, right? Right.
And so the point of revealing
capabilities is to deter is to like look
look how good we are, right? You know,
uh and of course your your adversary is
always studying what's going on in the
exercises and they're trying to think
about what could I build that would
counteract your advantages here. And as
a consequence, you're always concealing
things because you want to make sure
that you have some capability in reserve
that they haven't been able to plan for,
haven't been able to think about, right?
And if the moment came, would would in
like in your war games at least would
suggest that you're likely to win? So to
to put it in sort of traditional infer
terms, would an exercise like that be
the equivalent of a dubdubdc keynote
where you're trying to tell the
developer ecosystem, these are the
capabilities coming? I think that's a
pretty good metaphor. Um, except you're
actually doing it in the real world,
right? So there's like the the adversary
sensor should be able to look at this,
perceive it, see it, right? Um, but
yeah, I think that's a good metaphor.
Now, I I think, you know, we we focus
very much on the the government side of
what we do here, and that's obviously
what we're best known for, but it's only
50% of our business, right? The other
50% is commercial. Like I our software
is used to build every BMW, every
Chrysler, every HD Hyundai ship, every
Airbus airframe. Uh, and I think that's
really important. It it can seem like
two wildly
disjoint businesses, but they're
actually very very related. Uh, and
that's because in the government, you
call it a kill chain from sensor to
shooter, right? In the commercial world,
you call it a value chain from the hand
of your supplier to the hand of your
customer. And then I think a computer
scientist would look at this and say the
abstraction is this is a decision chain.
And I I'm making a series of decisions.
Every decision I make constrains the
options I have downstream of that. and I
want to actually think about this more
holistically and figure out ways of
optimizing it. That's your udaloop
there, right? Uh and that's how you can
see how the capabilities you deliver in
one area actually are relevant R&D to
the capabilities you're going to deliver
in other areas. I see. So the compliance
requirements might be different but
really the architecture is fairly shared
across commercial. They are that
different like if you you know we've
automated AIG's insurance underwriting
process, right? Um insurance is
regulated in every state. So you have 50
regulators to deal with the amount of
observability data, what they expect of
you, it's it's really not that
different. And I think by by building
for that high bar in government, you
actually get a lot of you it's like
superset of everything you need in
commercial.
Um we we have a bunch of student
questions piling up. So why don't we
switch to student questions and we'll
come back to if we have time to talk
about the the setup of the FD program
which I've always been interested in. Um
how did Palunteer change if at all uh
after IPO? Well, I actually I don't
think the culture changed
um after going public. I think going
public is a dislocating experience.
Partly it's dislocating in ways that you
don't expect it to be. Like, you know,
it turns out like if you have too much
to drink, you still get a hangover the
next day. Like somehow like the world is
not different because you've gone
public. Um and on the other hand, the
world is incredibly different because
you've gone public. And so I think I
think actually what what makes really
hard is the human factors of dealing
with it particularly when you know
you've been there long enough to know
what it was like when you were getting
kicked in the teeth and not you know
you're private company that everyone
thought was going to fail to being
public. I think there's a there's
another part of it that is it brings
what it really does it changes the cycle
time like when you're private you really
think about the year and like the
numbers matter but you got to make the
numbers for the year right when you go
public you got to think about the
quarter and you know the numbers still
matter but really you're getting mark
every quarter and there's just there is
more overhead like you're you're
basically losing a week every 13 weeks
in order to go service your investors
and communicate what's actually
happening. Um I think to the extent
something did change which I we we
learned from is once we went public it
felt like the only real communication
was public communication like and and
the sort of differentiated way in which
you could communicate internally versus
externally got minimized and I I I think
that's its own form of dislocation where
you felt like as an employee before you
had a privileged sense of what was going
on because actually we had no obligation
to communicate to the outside world so
that's what we could focus on entirely
and then we kind of swung the pendulum
swing to like actually there's only
communicating externally, right? And
then you don't really feel like you're
part of the thing, right? And so we had
to figure out along the way, how do we
do both of these things? Well, yeah,
that's a great question. So, I mean, it
starts with the the might be a little
bit of a long answer, but I think it's
relevant. It's like with AI, I think
we're very focused. You can there's a
supply demand dynamic here, and people
are very focused on AI supply. That's
like creating the models. Um but if AI
is like electricity like all you know
where did the value accrete? I don't
think it accreted to the utility
companies that generate the electricity.
You needed the machine companies that
built machines that required electricity
as the output to create economic value.
Um and where I where I think we have the
greatest opportunity as a nation is
leaning harder into the demand dynamic
with AI which is like why does this
soastic genie matter? What economic
decisions are we able to get value out
of by leveraging it? Uh, and that's
where I think the the country should
really be focused. Like I'm not quite
sure why we don't have like 10 Manhattan
projects on fixing healthcare, fixing,
you know, you don't actually frame the
problems you're going after AI first.
They're the same problems that mattered
before AI before the chat GPT moment,
but now you're going to use this new
form of electricity to go solve them.
Um, I don't think you can, you know, we
should do everything we can to uh
our enemy's ability to leverage the
technology, but that's not enough.
Actually, the most important thing is
you wake up every day, and caffeinate
yourself and go as hard as possible
after actually being faster than they
are at implementing this and using that
to learn about ways that you can
continue to to defend against
adversarial uses of the AI. Um, but I I
think it starts with, you know, Peter
had this saying a while ago, which is if
you look at the essentially the Chinese
propaganda from roughly a decade ago, it
it really took two forms. one one form
was why you know why are you even
bothering we've already won the other
form which is a contradiction to that is
why are you even bothering we're not a
threat we're so you know we're we're
just like we're not a threat at all but
the thing that both of these forms of of
reasoning have in common is that they're
saying we're not competing and it was
intended to obuscate the the truth which
is we are every day we are competing and
I think as long as we as a nation
recognize that that's actually what's
hap we are in a competition that
um we can win. My question was about
founder ship building. Yes. Well, I I
will answer the question in in the
specific and the broader sense, which is
really like why does this even matter?
So, at the dawn of World War II, America
had just figured out mass production.
You know, we had Bill Nudson, a Danish
immigr. He was the number two at Ford
and then he was the number two at GM
because he didn't get on with with with
Henry Ford who was a notoriously
difficult person. Um but we direct
commissioned Nudson as a three-star
general. He was he was actually in
charge of war mobilization. He was a
real engineer. He he was the guy who
invented mass production. Um and you
know World War II really was a war of
the factories. Like we outproduced our
adversaries by an astonishing amount.
The Germans were by far the better
engineers but they built exquisite
things in small numbers and we built
less exquisite things in just massive
numbers. And it turns out that really
matters. Um, unfortunately today our
adversary is the best at mass production
and and we build exquisite things in
small numbers. Uh, and I don't think
it's a true statement to say we're not
good at building things anymore in this
country. It's just that our legacy
industrial base is not. You know, uh, if
you look at Tesla or SpaceX, how they
build things through vertical
integration, how the the actual R&D
engineers are on the factory floor, like
there's an entirely different way of
conceiving of production that is David's
slingshot in this competition. And we
are good at that. and we have to kind of
rebuild the Nudian figures of the modern
era exist in Elsagundo, not in Detroit.
Um, and then our our unique contribution
here is this software platform that we
call Warp Speed. Um, for the better part
of 15 years, we've helped I I mentioned
earlier, we built every Chrysler, every
BMW. When the Ukraine war broke out,
there was a $5 wiring harness that BMW
sourced from Ukraine, but now had
intermittent supply, right? Okay, so it
didn't go to zero, but like it it was
never delivered on time and in full. And
this affected their production planning.
You know that it's a proud German
company with a beautiful implementation
of SAP as you'd expect. But the way it
was set up, it was it was set up to go
from left to right from your customer
orders to a bill of materials and
suddenly on a dime you needed to go from
right to left, which is based on what I
have in inventory, which customer orders
are worth building. You know, I don't
want to build a one series if I can
build a seven series. Obviously, very
different margin in those products. and
how do I rearrange production
dynamically to do that? They couldn't do
that. So, they're on the verge of having
to shut down the Munich factory unless
they could use software to solve this
problem in a different way, which we did
in a couple days. Um, but there's this
sense in which in the legacy industrial
base that they don't recognize this
fundamental truth that the manufacturing
software stack does not work. And um,
which is really shocking to me because
this this belief kind of persisted even
after COVID. So if you think about
COVID, people had invested tens of
billions of dollars into their supply
chain software stack. COVID comes around
and all this fell over in two
weeks. You know, it's like a paper
tiger. And I think that was a real kind
of marktomarket moment of like this is
crazy. Like go back to the earnings
calls around COVID and you'll see that
the only thing CEOs were talking about
was Zoom and Teams. Like the IT
investments that saved them were video
conferencing software. I I I mean that's
that's Palenter's broader critique of
the software industry which is like it
is a software industrial complex. People
build things that are designed to be
sellable, not inherently things that are
designed to be valuable. And our
approach is really to build really thick
software, not thin software that that
solved the problem. To do that, you had
to go deploy with your customers to
empirically observe what didn't work to
the point of manufacturing. You go to
the factory floor and it's like why is
the Airbus being built in Excel? If you
have all this fancy software, why are
the blue collar workers in the end of
the day escaping your software and going
to Excel? There's some truth to go there
learn like a secret in the Tian sense. I
had to hide that strength for the last
10 years or so because none of my
customers wanted to believe that their
software stack sucked. So it was just,
you know, you had to b your time, hide
your strength, be as valuable as you
could be. But you know who does believe
the software stack suck? American modern
American manufacturing companies. So if
you go to any alumni of Elon's world,
there's a reason Elon built his entire,
you know, software stack for
manufacturing from scratch. The only
thing he uses that's a C's product is
the accounting soft, the general ledger.
Everything else he had to build. So if
you're a startup, you can you can hire
500 devs and try to go do that or you
can build it on top of of Warp Speed.
You know, Matt Graham at Androl just
tweeted out today that 1/8 of Androl
uses Palunteer every single week to help
them build things, right? Like we're
going to power the production of the the
next generation of these defense tech
companies, whether Shield AI or Androl
or Eperis or Seronic in their autonomous
factories they're building for maritime.
Now to ship building in particular,
China has about 250 times the ship
building capacity of the US. um and it
plays to a broader theme like why why do
I think it's really important that our
business is 50-50 government and
commercial because this is what it
looked like when America was winning
right used to build cars and missiles
sat uh Ford built satellites until 1990
General Mills the serial company used to
build torpedoes why why did they build
torpedoes because they had a mechanics
division that build um serial processing
equipment everything they learned about
building the machines to process cereal
gave them an advantage in terms of
thinking about how to build the machines
to build torpedoes Um that is what
unfortunately
uh the the Chinese primes look like
today. If you go to the Chinese defense
contractors, only 27% of the revenue
comes from the PLA. The rest comes from
us as cheap psies buying crap on Amazon.
Like the toaster you're buying is
potentially subsidizing lethality again
future US service members. So you need
this diversified R&D base to the point
of how the BP project led to the
delivery of warp speed. How can we learn
across the 50 different industries that
we have to actually deliver more
national security? Now, to ship building
in particular, we are it's kind of like
a a fertility rate problem. We're
retiring more ships than we're able to
build. There's a huge capacity issue.
We're building them the same old way.
We're not using the Elsaundo way of
doing these things. Um, and the the
larger ship builder outside of China is
HD Hyundai. We power their ship building
operations. Everything from ship design
to ship repair and maintenance. Uh, and
I think the the intuition I'd give you,
what we're really doing there is we're
creating a a we're integrating that
value chain. Like you're living in your
PLM software, you have the 3D models,
you're designing the product. When you
make design decisions, you need to have
some visibility into what is the
implication for part obsolescence. Um,
how does this impact my supply chain?
How does it impact any of the dynamics
of the ship like the center of gravity,
the center of mass, my ability to
produce it? But usually the engineers
can't see all that. So, they're really
happy with the design change they made.
It's a better product in theory. It's a
worse product in practice because it's
going to take an extra eight months to
build. Uh, how can you see that up
front? It's it's kind of bringing like
CI/CD to to design, you know, to
production. If you think about the whole
chain where usually when people talk
about production, they mean literally
just building something that's already
been designed. But in reality, the
reason the Starlink engineers sit on the
factory floor is they're watching how
the Starlinks are being assembled and
then changing the design based on it to
make it they're designing for
manufacturability. And that's what we're
going to need again to do this
asymmetrically. So that's a big part of
what we're focused on with with chip
building. And so how can we use the
experiences we have outside the US uh to
help modernize the US maritime
industrial base?
The question is how do you think about
responsibility within volunteer? We we
think about it a lot. Uh you know the
very one of the very first engineering
teams that was built was the privacy and
civil liberties engineering team. If you
go back to uh the founding mission of
counterterrorism you know famously Alex
is is very far on the left and Peter is
very far on the right and they became
friends by arguing with each other at
Kthers at the Stanford Law School dorm
and they respected each other the
quality of each other's arguments that
that's where that friendship was
birthed. Um and the view both these
people are kind of a lot of they're
basically philosophers. The view is like
terrorism is really bad but just as bad
as terrorism maybe worse is the reaction
to terrorism and how how society
responds to it. So it usually results in
a very a very kind of reflexive
deprivation of civil liberties uh and
and empowers a surveillance state. So if
you you you have to figure out there's
like a dialectical thing here of how can
you you can think about as an efficient
frontier. You have trade-offs between
privacy and
security. Politics is about arguing
about where you need to be as a society
on that efficient frontier. Engineering
is about pushing out the efficient
frontier. So for any given level of
privacy that a democratic society wants,
you're going to get more security.
You're making the trade-offs as false as
possible. Um I I think it's it's there's
like a it's a very academic to live on
any either extreme of these things.
That's why like pure libertarianism
doesn't work and pure socialism doesn't
work either. Uh so like now for where a
society wants to be, how can you have
more of both?
That's the first time I've heard the
burrito optimal frontier for for ethics,
but that's uh that's a cool framework.
Thank you for that. I think it's it's
practical, right? Yeah. Yeah. Um I used
to write for the Stanford Review, which
was a libertarian newspaper on campus.
Um, and I think I agree that the
pendulum, the problem with the dialectic
around what you're describing is that
the pendulum would swing far too too too
far right or too far left often and that
made it very difficult for people
anywhere in the middle to participate in
any kind of productive engineering
conversation about it. But often like
what you're saying when you think about
capabilities as a way to keep moderation
in policy then it becomes much easier to
talk about the trade-off. I didn't get
into since we're on philosophy, you
know, I I didn't get into this, but the
other way of thinking about, you know,
so 50/50 government commercial, you can
think about that as freedom and
prosperity. That's how we think about
what our mission is. Um, and you can
say, well, what is the problem? The
problem is there's a legitimation
crisis. Our institutions, government and
commercial, don't work. Why do doors
fall off planes? You know, why is intel
about to not exist anymore? Why do
people not have faith that these
government organizations are being run
competently? Right? And my diagnosis of
this whether it's the factory floor or a
government organization is that you have
a a seauite that they have a steering
wheel and they're diligently trying to
steer their organization. They really
care. They wake up every day trying
their best. What they don't realize is
the steering wheel is a prop from the
Jungle Cruise ride at Disneyland. It's
not connected to anything. Uh and then
the people on the facet metaphorical
factory floor look up and say, "How
could these people be so dumb?" You
know, it's like so there's this
discount. How can they not see what?
Well, there's no udal loop basically,
right? And and the point of the software
having this integrated decision chain is
to actually connect what's actually, you
know, give these people real steering
wheel, precision control. How can you
even improve on policy if you don't have
real-time feedback on how the policies,
you call it business strategy in the
commercial world, call it policy in the
government world, it's same thing,
right? Like we're set I here's where I
want to go. Are we getting there? What
did I learn about doing this or not? It
takes three months to figure that out.
If everyone is escaping your software to
go solve the problem in Excel, you have
no clue what's actually happening,
right? and the these errors compound and
propagate. Um so the very first basis of
this is these these institutions all of
them need to work right in the absence
of this what you really saw in the last
like 10 years or so is this like this
nealism like it none of these
institutions work let's just tear them
all down uh that doesn't work that's
definitely not the answer you know that
so then who's waking up every day trying
to make these institutions better than
they were the day before
well that systems analysis I think is a
great note to end on because we're out
of time but thank you so much for coming
Sham and I we'll go to
Thank you.
Happy. All right.