Today's lecture topic will be about uh
regularization and optimization which
are two very important concepts more
broadly in deep learning and machine
learning uh but especially important for
computer vision. And we're going to
start with a recap from last week and
discuss some of the topics that we
discussed last time.
So um we really honed in on this idea of
image classification as a core task in
computer vision. And what this task is
is given an image as input you try to
map this image to um a a label inside of
a set of labels. So here we have five
different labels uh cat, dog, bird,
deer, and truck. And the goal is to
assign the correct label to the input
image. and you're creating some model or
some function that takes an image as
input and outputs the specific label
here.
And we also talked about you know a lot
of the challenges for classification. So
one of the main challenges is uh shown
in the top left here but it's this idea
of the uh semantic gap between what we
as humans perceive in the image which is
the cat and what it's actually
represented uh as in the computer which
is this grid of uh pixel values where uh
you know you have this multi-dimensional
array or tensor um and you have discrete
values for each of the pixels. This is
very different from how we're perceiving
the image and deciding that this is a
cat. So being able to map from this uh
complex numeric representation into one
that we humans understand is the core
challenge here. But also there's
challenges uh surrounding the images
themselves. So if you look at something
like the uh illumination of the scene.
So here you'll have different pixel
intensities based on where the lighting
is in the scene. Uh also you know you
could have certain parts of your object
are in the shade and harder to see. Um
cats by nature are very deformable. So
you talk about deformable objects. They
can move around and twist and bend in
different ways, so they won't always
have the same shape. And this can prove
challenging if you're trying to design
an algorithm to detect objects. Uh
there's also the challenge of occlusion.
So you could have a cat that's like
hiding underneath the couch uh cushions
here, but we as a human can clearly tell
this a cat because of the tail uh how
it's sort of sticking out at the end
here. And then you know the way that
cats behave, we can infer that this is a
cat. Uh you'll also have things like
background clutter where the object
could blend into the background. So we
need to account for this somehow as
well. And finally, there's this idea of
interclass variation where different
objects in the same category can look
very different from each other, but we
still need to group them all into the
same category. So here are a lot of just
the challenges of recognition and why it
isn't such a simple problem where you
can just sort of write if else rules to
account for everything and just simple
logic to classify. So if logic's sort of
thrown out the window, you can't just
create these logic rules. um how do you
actually create a classifier? Here's
where we talked about datadriven
approaches. And we talked about
basically the simplest uh machine
learning model which is this K nearest
neighbors model. And the idea is that
you look at for a given data point, what
are the existing data points in your
training set that uh are very close in
distance to your new data point coming
in. And for the one nearest neighbor
case, uh this just results in, you know,
you find the closest data point, you
assign it that class label. And you can
also look at multiple nearest neighbors
where you're assigning the most common
class label among those nearest
neighbors. So we talked about these two
different approaches. We talked about
how um you ideally don't want to split
your data set into train and test but
you can do train validation and test so
that you can use this validation set
here to actually uh help you choose your
hyperparameters. So the main
hyperparameter for k nearest neighbors
is this k uh one or five in these
examples. And what we showed is an
example where you're plotting what is
your accuracy on this validation set
here um over the different k values
here. and you would, you know, you would
choose the one that has the highest
accuracy. Um, so this is how you'd use
the validation set and then you would
reserve this test set for okay, how does
your model do on completely new data
it's never seen before. That would be
the purpose of the test set. This is all
just recap. Um, there was a bit of
confusion about uh distance metrics. We
put a post on ED that explains this in
more detail. Um but um we've talked
about two different distance me metrics.
The most two commonly used ones in
machine learning which are the sort of
Manhattan distance and or L1 distance
and L2 distance or uklidian distance. Um
L2 distance is like um if you imagine
just the straight line distance
sort of how we think of distance in
everyday usage of the word uh
geometrically. And then Manhattan
distance is this idea where you can only
sort of traverse left and right and up
and down in this diagram. and you can't
move diagonally. So specifically looking
at just one quick example here um the
reason why all these points on the line
are the same distance from the origin
here um is because you can't move
diagonally. So you have to move in this
case up 0.5 and to the right 0.5. So the
total distance is one whereas you know
here you're just going a straight line
but it's uh one also the same distance
here whereas in the L2 distance um all
the points equidistant from the origin
here form a circle because you can you
can just go in the direct line here. So
this is maybe a brief explanation. The
final thing we sort of honed in on last
time was this idea of a linear
classifier. So um the basic idea in the
in the basic setting that we did is we
have an image which is you know say
width 32 and height 32 and there are
three uh pixel values for each of the
spatial locations in our image
representing the red, green and blue uh
intensities
forming the color. And the idea is we
take this array of numbers for our image
and we flatten it out into an array of
just 3,000 different uh numbers 372. And
then we're multiplying this vector by
our weight matrix W. And um the basic
idea is if we have a weight matrix W
that has uh you know uh height here of
uh 10 and then the width is 3 372. We're
multiplying each of these rows by uh our
input sample X and this will give us 10
resulting uh class scores. So um often
times we'll add a bias term as well
which would just be one bias term for
each class. So this would be you know a
size 10 vector here. And we also talked
about three different ways you can view
or think about this these linear models.
One is the algebraic viewpoint which I
described here where each row is um
represented sort of independently
representing the class and you multiply
it by the input vector x. You get your
uh score and you add the bias to get
your your final score. um you do each
row sort of independently in this sense.
You can also view um these uh learned
class uh weights here as templates where
if we then uh sort of reravel the uh
vector into the original shape of the
image uh we could plot the intensities
here and understand what um what is sort
of the uh template per class which is
what this visualization represents. And
then the final way you can think about
it is a sort of geometric viewpoint
where uh each of these um rows in our
weight matrix are represented by these
lines here in our um input space and
specifically the line is where we set
this equation to zero um which is the
decision boundary. So this forms the
point where uh you know above the line
you could have a positive score and
below the line you would have a negative
score for the for the for the class. So
these are sort of the different
viewpoints for how you can view these
linear models. They're all doing the
same thing. And one nice thing about the
geometric viewpoint is that uh if you
visualize your data like say you want to
classify uh blue versus red here it's
very easy to tell that you can't draw a
line that perfectly separates um the
data here. So it's kind of a nice uh way
you can gain intuition about what is
possible for a linear model to do.
Okay. Um I think that's sort of the
highle recap of what we discussed last
time. Um I'll actually be going into a
little bit more detail on sort of the
new content for uh this lecture now but
I just wanted to pause briefly if anyone
had any questions about what we
discussed last time or at the beginning
of this lecture feel free to ask.
>> Yeah. So the question for those online
is for this uh visual viewpoint is this
the same as um sort of running K nearest
neighbors and this would be maybe one of
the neighbors that you're comparing
against uh are they mathematically
equivalent? Um no they're not the same
because um these templates are formed
from this line. And so it's not like one
specific uh data point but you can still
calculate the templates based on the uh
this sort of uh they would represent
more like if we see in this diagram here
there's the line pointing in the
direction of the class. So it would be
sort of representing this point here.
Yeah. So the question is how did we get
this like 372 number? So the idea here
is that um if the height of our image is
32 pixels and the width is 32 pixels and
then each location in the image is
represented by three values the red,
green and blue pixel intensities um we
would then get 32 * 32 * 3 total values
to represent the entire image and that's
how we get this 3,72 number.
So um here's a I guess very specific
example of a uh linear model here. And
we when we multiply our input X by our
weight matrix W we get the resulting
scores for these different classes. And
you can see that uh for cat it's not
doing so well because car has a higher
score and we want the highest score for
the uh correct class. Also here on the
second example does pretty well because
it's doing it correctly. But then in the
frog example, it sort of gets it
completely wrong where it's by far the
lowest score of the three. So um
intuitively we can tell that these
scores are not very good. But how do we
sort of mathematically formalize this
intuition and how do we determine how
good a given model is? And this is the
idea of a loss function which tells you
how good or specifically tells you how
bad uh a classifier is. So given a data
set of examples uh where we're indexing
by with this uh letter I we have X I is
each of the training examples Yi is each
of the training labels. Um we can
compute the loss over our entire data
set where we calculate this uh loss for
each training example by sending it
through our model here which is this f
ofxi w. We get our label and then we
compute it compared to the ground truth
label yi and we just take the average
over our whole data set. So this is how
we do this. We talked about um in last
lecture the softmax loss or the cross
entropy loss which is the most commonly
used loss for classification. And um so
I won't discuss that again in so much
detail here, but um basically it's very
high uh it's very high loss when you
predict low probability of the correct
class. It's very low loss when you're
predicting the correct class at very
high probability.
Um so these this what I just uh
explained is all uh contained within
what we call the data loss. So this is a
loss that tells you how well do the
model predictions match our training
data. And obviously we want this to be
very low and if it's very low it means
our model's fitting our training data
well. Um but there's a second component
which I'll discuss today which is this
regularization term of the loss
function. So what this does is it's
intended to it's intended to prevent the
model from doing too well on the
training data. Uh so it actually does
worse on the training data, but the goal
is to make it do better on new test data
or unseen data. So worse on training,
but better on on a test set. That's the
point of regularization. Um and we'll go
over a lot of the intuition for how to
think about it in the in the next slides
here. But the highle goal is to do worse
on the training data, but then better on
the test data or just unseen data.
That's the point of regularization.
>> Yeah. So we're computing the loss on
each of the eye training examples. Yeah.
So the loss of the i example uses the x
i and the y i. Um
does that make sense? I mean you you
could not have an i here, but
this is just saying the i the loss term.
Yeah. Yeah. You you normally don't have
a different loss for each I if that's
what you're asking. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. So
this is just you could we describe li as
the loss for the training example. So
we're just using here. But yeah, it
could be.
Um so for regularization um people
usually have this intuition when
thinking about it where this is sort of
like a toy example and the the idea is
we want to fit some function to these
points where our input is x and our
output is y and uh you say have two
different types of models f_sub_1 and
f_sub_2 um and you're trying to decide
which of these is better. So F1 goes
through all of our data points. So the
training or the data loss will be very
low because it's basically doing it
perfectly. Whereas F2 um doesn't go
through every point perfectly, but
intuitively it feels like probably F2 is
a better model when we're now testing on
new data we've never seen before. So um
regularization sort of captures this
intuition of you don't want to overfit
your data so hard and you might actually
be better off with a model that fits the
data less but is either simpler or has
some other properties that uh make it a
better choice. And so if we you know ask
okay how is this how are these models
going to do on new data that's within
our same distribution you'll find that
you know F2 does a much better job at
modeling. So here's it's doing better on
the unseen data. Um
so um I think there's also an intuition
in this previous example that's
demonstrated very well where we're
preferring simpler models uh where it's
sort of like AAM's razor which is this
idea in uh philosophy and also
scientific discovery where if you have
multiple competing hypotheses you should
go with the simplest one first and then
if that if you know for sure that's
wrong then you can start trying out more
complicated ones as you go. This is
maybe also some intuition you can have
for why regularization can be useful.
Okay. And then one final thing about
this equation that I didn't touch on yet
is this lambda parameter here. So this
is the regularization strength which is
another hyperparameter. So we might use
uh training validation sets to set what
is the optimal lambda here as well. But
the basic idea is we can set this to a
floating point between I guess zero and
infinity where zero would be basically
there is no regularization infinity you
know up to infinity you have really
strong progressively stronger uh
regularization. So um it's very much a
tunable knob you have for determining
how much you want to prevent the model
from fitting to your training data.
And I'll go through some simple examples
now of regularization. So here we have
L2 regularization which uh basically
what you do is you have your weight
matrix you square each of the terms in
your weight matrix and then you sum them
all together. That gives you your your
score here that you then multiply by
lambda and you add to your total loss.
That's L2 regularization. L1
regularization is very similar but
instead of squaring you're taking the
absolute value. So in practice there are
some differences between uh how these
two regularizations uh perform when
you're training models. So one of the
things that happens with L2
regularization because you're squaring
each of the values when you have a
really small value it gets squared like
say you have you know 0.001 you square
it becomes even smaller. Um so L2
regularization allows for sort of these
really small values close to zero
because you then square them so they
become even smaller and so your your
your penalty here is very very low if
you have these very small values with L2
whereas L1 you're not squaring it. So
it's sort of just whatever the the
baseline value was. It's not like it's
getting smaller before you're uh
computing this regularization term. So
in practice what this leads to is L1
regularization you get a lot more values
that are zero actually in your weight
matrix um or very close to zero whereas
L2 you can have generally it's more
spread out where you have values that
are small but uh but but non zero
because the penalty becomes so small
seems pretty clear to you why L2 prefers
sort of spread out weights that are all
small but why does L1 prefer sparse uh
vectors so I think the way to think of
it is that if a value can be zero uh and
your performance is roughly the same uh
then this would push you towards zeroing
that value whereas for L2 what you might
have is the value just becomes very
small but non zero because of the
squaring
so uh the question is can we talk about
what does pushing towards a zero value
mean so um we're going to talk about
more how we use this loss term but the
basic idea is we're trying to minimize
it so um we're trying to minimize the
loss or minimize the error of our model
and um if we have a term here which is
giving us positive values that don't
it's sort of not affecting the model
performance and the data loss we will uh
sort of remove those through the
optimization procedure. It's sort of a
trade-off. You're trying to optimize the
joint uh sum of the regularization term
and the data loss term. So if your data
loss isn't changing much but you're able
to go lower on the regularization term,
you'll get a more optimized model. So it
will it will uh it will be preferred
based on trying to minimize the overall
term. Um so uh I think we'll also touch
later in the course about much more
complex forms of regularization where
they're all doing this basic idea of
worse on the training data to do better
on the test data. Um but some of them
you will even like change the layers of
your model. So um they actually get
pretty complicated. This is like an
ongoing research area of how to
regularize models. Uh there's new papers
each year. So lots of stuff here and
we'll only cover a small subset in this
course.
So to summarize why do we regularize
models? Um the first is you know it
allows us to express some sort of
preference over weights. So if for some
reason in our problem we think the
solution should be spread out or should
contain a lot of sparity where a lot of
the values in the weight matrix are
zero, we might prefer one set of
regularization L2 versus L1 over
another. Um it also can depending on how
we're regularizing make the model
simpler um so that it works better on
test data. So it could simplify the
model if we're say uh heavily
regularizing really high polomial terms
in our model. Uh for example in what I
showed earlier or and something we won't
touch on in too much detail is uh
especially L2 regularization can
actually improve the optimization
process because um if you imagine like
the squared is like a parabola. Uh so if
you're plotting y equals x^2 it's a
parabola and uh these are like convex so
you get a lot of nice optimization
properties where there's a global
minimum. Uh we won't touch on that in
this course that's like beyond the scope
but know that for certain types of
optimization the regularization actually
helps train the model faster too.
Okay. Um I guess I have a question for
you all and what we'll do is you'll do
uh um uh one if it's W1 and two with
your hand if it's W2. So uh which of
these two um weights w1 w2 would l the
l2 regularizer prefer? So we have our
input x. It's when you multiply it, you
do the dotproduct with the weights, you
get the same score. So you get a score
of one either way. And here's where the
data loss would be the same. And we're
trying to determine which of the uh
weights would our regularizer prefer. So
go one if you think it's W1 and go two
if you think it's W2.
All right, lots of twos. Yeah, it's W2
because as you said, it's more spread
out. You're going to be squaring each of
these turns. So, it's 1/4. You square
it, becomes 1/16th. You sum it all
together, it's 1/4 is the total
regularization term here. And then here,
it's, you know, you square it, so it's
one. So, it's four times lower in terms
of the regularization loss.
Um, and as we said, the intuition is you
like more spread out weights. Um, and
then here's another question. Which one
would L1 prefer? Now, so you do one if
it's uh weight one and two if it's
weight two.
Okay, we got a lot of ones. Uh so this
one's actually a bit of a trick
question. So um what L1 regularization
is, you sum each of the terms so they'll
both be sum to one. Uh in practice, you
probably would see this one because as
we said, sparity, but in terms of a loss
standpoint, these two um weights would
actually be equivalent uh in terms of L1
because one is just the sum of uh the
0.25 25 uh four times and then the other
one's just one. So they're both summed
to one and so the the actual um
regularization term is the same for
these.
Yeah. Okay. So what's an example where
L1 would be preferred if this is like
0.9 for example?
Okay. So just to recap um we have a data
set of XY pairs and we have some way to
calculate scores for each of the classes
uh with which in our case is just a
linear model. You're doing a matrix
multiply. Um the loss for each of the I
training examples in the softmax loss
which we discussed last time is you
exponentiate each of your scores
um and then you divide by the total sum
of the scores. So you exponentiate to
make them all positive and then you sum
to get a probability distribution. So
they all the final values in this all
sum to one and you have a score for each
class and you take the minus log of your
of the correct label. So this is uh of
the the probability of the correct label
which is given here. Um and the full
loss is you just run this over each of
your training examples, calculate li for
each of those and then you um add your
regularization term here depending on
what is the weights of your model. Why
do we use softmax in general? So soft is
great because um what it does as a
function is it converts any set of
floatingoint numbers into a probability
distribution where uh they will sum to
one and uh depending on the value of the
score that will translate to the
relative probability of that value. So
if you have a really high positive
number and everything else is very low
negative you'll have merely one for
softmax and zeros almost for the the
other values. So it's nice because it
converts any list of uh floatingoint
numbers into a list of probabilities
based on the uh the the values of the of
the list. That's the main utility of
softmax. So the question is that you can
view the regularization we talked about
which is L1 L2 as um a way of
regularizing based on the magnitude of
the weights which is true and how does
that translate to simpler models? So I
think in L1's explanation is actually
pretty simple because uh if we prefer
say um terms that have a lot of zeros in
it, it's basically a linear model with
fewer coefficients. So that one is
actually I think relatively
straightforward. But I think in general
regularization is not always going to
give you a simpler model. It depends on
how it's used. So for example in the
diagram we showed at the very beginning
here um here you could imagine that um
you have L2 regularization or L1
regularization where you're penalizing
more the higher degree polinomial terms
of your function. So in that sense it's
pretty clear how you could design
regularization to prefer a simpler
model. But it doesn't always need to be
that way. Really what it is is this idea
of uh doing worse on the training data
to do better on the test data. And uh
that's not always going to give you a
simpler model. And in fact, there are
many types of uh uh um regularization
like dropout that actually make your
model more complex uh but give you
better performance on the on the test
data.
Cool. Um so now that we've talked about
how we can calculate how good a given W
is based on the training data and uh
this regularization term, the question
now is like how do we actually find the
best W?
uh and this is what optimization is
which is the second half of today's
lecture. So I think when people describe
uh optimization they will usually use
this idea of a loss landscape which you
can think of as like a normal landscape
like on planet earth where the up and
down vertical or z-axis direction is the
loss. So this is the value you're trying
to minimize and then say in this example
you have two uh parameters in your model
which is sort of the x and y direction
of where you are in this landscape. And
the idea is you're just like uh
basically a person. You're walking
around this landscape and you're trying
to find what is the smallest or lowest
point in the entire landscape. I think
one of the reasons this analogy and this
is a very commonly used analogy. Um a
little bit falls apart is because you
know as humans we can just see like
visually we can look into the distance
and see what is the lowest point of the
valley. But I think this analogy is
actually pretty accurate if you think of
the person as being blindfolded. They
don't have access to any visual
information. they can only feel sort of
the earth where they are right now and
understand what is the slope of the
ground on the current point in which
they're standing. I think if you view it
in mat lens this analogies actually
becomes extremely accurate um for how uh
we're trying to find the best model and
we have this complex landscape of uh
different loss values depending on the
parameters of our model which translate
to the location of the person in this uh
landscape.
So how can you find the best point? uh
we could go with like a really simple
idea which is maybe a really bad uh you
know bad idea but it could work. So here
it's just basically a for loop where
we're trying a thousand different values
of W randomly and we're just choosing
the best one. So obviously not very
mathematically rigorous but you know you
will do better than uh a random baseline
and if you had nothing else to go for
maybe this isn't so bad. um you would
get like 15.5% accuracy on the uh
sciphar 10 data set which is the one I
showed earlier with the frog and the car
and things like that uh with the 10
different categories. Uh but it doesn't
perform very good. I mean the
state-of-the-art on this data set it's
basically solved through modern uh deep
learning. You get 99.7% accuracy. So uh
clearly it's not bad but it's also I
wouldn't say particularly good.
Uh strategy number two, which is sort of
what I maybe uh explained a bit earlier,
is this idea of following the slope. So
for this um you can imagine you're like
blindfolded on the lost landscape and
you're feeling the ground underneath you
and you're thinking okay which you know
which way is the slope of the earth
pointing me and I should walk in that
direction at all times. This basic idea
is the fundamental way in which we train
all the models in this course and in
which basically all deep learning models
are trained where you're feeling the
location of the current place in the
lost landscape and you're going down the
hill. Um so this is very intuitive way
to explain it. We'll now go over more of
the math uh behind it but this is what
you should be maybe visualizing in your
head.
So uh how do you actually follow the
slope? Um so in one dimension I'm sure
you all are familiar with the idea of a
derivative which in calculus we can
think of as uh this limit h definition
where we add a very small number to uh
our current location. We calculate the
value of the function at that new
location. We subtract the current
location and then we divide by the step
size. And as we take the limit uh for h
approaching zero this gives us the uh
derivative of the uh of the function at
that point. Now uh this is for 1D but in
multiple dimensions you use the gradient
which is where you're calculating
essentially this limit definition for
each of the values uh uh separately. So
you'll have a different derivative for
each of your values and the and you get
a vector instead. Um and this gives you
the direction along each dimension. So
um you can actually calculate the slope
in the dimension by taking the
dotproduct of the gradient with the
direction and specifically the direction
of the steepest descent or down the hill
is the negative gradient. So the
gradient points up the hill, the
negative gradient points uh down the
hill. So this is the you know the
direction we should be traveling if
we're trying to get to the bottom of
this lost landscape.
So you know maybe what are some ways you
can calculate the uh derivative? A
really simple one is you could just
actually try to use the limit h
definition with a very small h. Uh so
you add you know 0.00001
you uh actually can compute you know the
last two digits of the loss change
slightly. So you can compute the
difference divide by the step size and
you can get like an approximation of
your derivative here. And you could
actually do this for each of your uh
values in your w. You just do this
procedure over and over again. Um but it
has a few problems. is very slow because
you just need to loop through each of
the values. It's also approximate. So
you're not even calculating the actual
derivative and especially with floating
point arithmetic you can get pretty
significant errors here. So uh this is
not really preferred but this basic idea
or intuition of what we could be doing
is to calculate the derivative this way.
But really we have the loss as a
function of w. So um we know how to
calculate the scores to calculate uh to
get our loss which is given by our
function for our model and we can then
compute the total loss with the
regularization terms as well. And this
entire uh loss is a function of uh
basically w's the w's the x i's and the
y i's. So you have your w matrix, you
have your x i's and y i's and then you
have this formula with you know maybe
some logs and exponents but
fundamentally um this is a function of w
x and y and we specifically want to
calculate the gradient which is given by
this Greek letter naba of our loss with
respect to the weights. So we can
imagine our x and i uh x i and y i's are
held constant and we're trying to
calculate the uh the derivative just
with respect to the weights.
So to do this we can just uh use
calculus use the chain rule use the
different methods we've learned for
calculating derivatives based on uh sort
of complex equations uh or not so
complex but you know you need to have
some logs and exponents and chain rules
here to solve it. Um so this will be an
exercise in the homework so I won't go
through step by step how to do it now
but it is relatively straightforward I
think conceptually it should make sense
to you all how you do this. You assume
the x and the y's are constant and you
solve for what is the derivative as you
change w. So now we actually have a way
where we can calculate W based on our uh
or sorry DW the gradient of W with
respect to our data and the current W
and whatever our loss function is which
is how to compute the error.
So this is I guess summary. So um you
could do a numerical gradient but it's
approximate slow and uh the nice thing
is that it's very easy to write. you
just add a really small h, take the
difference, divide by h. Um, the
analytic gradient is nice because it's
exact, it's fast, but you could like
potentially if you're creating a new
gradient from scratch, like new code to
calculate from scratch, you could have
an error in it. So, if you are doing
this, people normally will have a
gradient check, which is where they try
the h uh version where they have a
really small h value and then they uh
make sure that it's around the same
neighborhood and that's a good way to
make sure you don't have any bugs in
your code. Um so um you'll be doing in
there'll be gradient checks in your
homework assignments to make sure your
implementations are correct also.
>> Yeah. So the question is um we often say
we want a loss function that's
differentiable uh because then we can
calculate the gradients but if we have a
better loss function somehow and uh we
can't analytically calculate the
gradient but we could use uh this h kind
of numerical method. Could we do that? I
think um in general it's hard to
construct a better loss function that
would be um non uh like non
non-ifferiable. You could possibly
though and if you there is just a true
loss function that is the best for your
case but it is non-ifferiable you could
go with uh this approach and it it may
work. I think it would struggle if like
for example your loss uh is just truly
non-ifferiable across all points and
it's basically like a cluster of
non-connected uh points then you know
moving in the step of deepest steepest
descent wouldn't really get you
necessarily at your best solution uh if
they're not well connected and forming
sort of this geography so uh it could
work but I would think that if your loss
is non- differentiable across most of
the domain then probably you wouldn't be
able to use these approaches to find the
uh the bottom point.
>> Yeah. So the I guess TLDDR of the
explanation is that if your function's
convex then uh it works very well with
this sort of gradient uh descent or
steepest descent type of approach. But
if you have a non- differentiable
non-convex function probably this
approach won't work uh as well because
you're not going to be stepping in the
right direction. It's not necessarily
errorprone if your code is perfectly
good but maybe you have a mistake in
your code and it's hard to tell right
away. uh and but the h uh the limit h
definition is very easy to code up right
you just set h to be a very small value
you run it through your function and you
add a very small amount so that's less
errorrone for implementation
>> okay
>> for implementation
>> okay not more errorrone if it's working
correctly
>> okay so um now I'll talk about this
fundamental algorithm for optimization
called gradient descent and the basic
intuition is what we already explained
before we calculate the slope at each
point when we're on our loss landscape
and we take a step in the direction
downwards towards the bottom of the loss
landscape. So what we do is we calculate
the um gradients of our weights given
the loss function, the data and our
current weight values. This tells us how
much we should change each of the
weights to go down the slope. And then
we have to have a step size. So how far
down the hill are we taking a step in
the direction. Um and so you go down the
hill, so it's the minus sign here and
the step size times uh the gradient. So
this is basically what gradient descent
is. Uh you're calculating the gradient
at each step and you're moving a fixed
direction uh in the direction of the
negative gradient down the hill.
Um so given a concrete example here. So
instead of this being like a 3D loss
landscape, often people will visualize
it like this where we're sort of looking
down at the landscape and uh purple
would represent the highest points and
red would represent the bottom or the
valley here. Um and we could imagine we
have our original W. We can calculate
the loss. We know the direction of the
slope of the negative gradient
direction. And this arrow might
represent the uh fixed step size that we
talked about before. We're taking a
fixed uh step size in that direction.
Yes. So you can see it's fixed step
size, but as the uh gradient becomes
smaller, we're still multiplying it by
this fixed step size. So the step the
effective step size actually does become
smaller because the gradient is smaller
near the end where it's flat or near the
end where it's more flat. So this is
what it looks like when we're always
heading in the direction of the steepest
descent. So the question is when we step
down, how do we know when we're going to
stop? Well, I guess in uh in this
formula, right, like you just keep
looping forever, so you never stop. Uh
so this was probably not the best.
Normally you have a predetermined number
of iterations that you run it for. Or
you can look at um if the loss is not
significantly changing by a fixed
amount. Also you could have like a
tolerance for how much you're expecting
the loss to keep decreasing by and if
it's no longer decreasing. You know it's
only decreasing by one e minus 5 or 1 e
- 9 you know maybe you maybe you stop
there because it's good enough. Um so
those are the two ways you can determine
when to stop is fixed number of
iterations or a a stopping criteria of
you know how much we're not really
improving that much anymore.
Okay. Um so now I'll talk about the sort
of most popular variant of gradient
descent which is called stochastic
gradient descent.
And when we talked about gradient
descent before we talked about
calculating the loss of our weights by
summing over our entire training set the
loss of li for each i in our entire n
training sets. Um but this is like
potentially a lot of computation if we
have a very large data set. So what uh
stochastic gradient descent is is it
basically now instead of looking at the
entire data set we're looking at a
subset each time which we call a mini
batch or a batch of data. And um so here
if we look at the code it's like you
know we're sampling 256 data points from
our data set. So the batch size is 256.
We evaluate the gradients of this 256
subset of our data set and then we do
the same thing as before. So the reason
why it's called stochcastic gradient
descent is because we're sampling a
random subset of our data set each time
we're running the algorithm uh each step
of the algorithm. So um this is
stochastic gradient descent. You're
basically on a running it on a random
subset each time.
And in practice people won't just sample
it completely random. They'll make sure
to um get through all the examples in
their data set and then sort of loop
around again. And that's called one
epoch of training where you loop through
all your data samples once in a random
order.
Okay. Um there are some problems with uh
gradient descent or stocastic gradient
descent. So um this visualization is
sort of the same type as the colored one
I showed before where we're looking down
the loss landscape. But these curves are
called the level set where it's a set of
points where the loss is the same on all
of them. So this is another way of
visualizing sort of very popular way to
visualize top down looking at the loss
but it's without the colors. Um and so
you could imagine that you have uh this
phenomenon where it's like a really
narrow valley where it's really steep
along the sides and you're trying to
traverse the center of the valley and um
you know gradient descent actually does
run into issues here. Does anyone um
have any ideas for what could go wrong?
>> Yeah. So, one of the things you could do
is overshoot. Um, where you're sort of
moving up and down along this direction.
Um, and if the if it's steep enough and
your step size is large enough, you you
might actually oscillate out of the
valley. So, uh you can imagine if your
step size is very large and this is
really steep, you're actually going to
be gaining like you're moving out and
out each time because you're you always
have this fixed step size. So, um if
it's steep enough, you could just like
bounce out of the valley. Uh that that
that actually does happen if your
learning rate is too large. So that's
one thing that can happen. And then also
um even if your learning rate's not too
large or your step size is not too large
um you can have this phenomenon where
you're sort of jittering because the
gradient is much larger in the steep
direction. So uh you're sort of
jittering but you're not making very
much meaningful progress towards the
actual center because you're spending
all this time oscillating back and forth
up and down. So this is a pretty big
issue with just default SGD.
Um and then mathematically just an aside
um the loss function we consider here to
have a high condition number which is
the ratio of the largest
to smallest singular value of the hessen
matrix which is the second derivative.
So you can imagine like the second
derivative along this up and down
direction is very high but then side to
side it's very low because it's very
flat. So that's what causes this
phenomenon.
All right. Um so one of the things we
also might have an issue with SGD is um
what happens if the loss function has a
local minima or local minimum or a
saddle point. So um for example here
it's it for like just the very end of
this curve it's completely flat. So if
we were to imagine um there's like we're
moving down the hill here um we would
just get stuck here because it's flat
and we wouldn't be able to progress any
further because when we take the
gradient here is zero. Um so this is
actually a pretty big uh issue where
it'll get stuck either in a local
minimum because we you know once we
reach here we don't really have any
direction to go the gradient is zero or
it's very small and we'll just sort of
oscillate back and forth here. And then
here it could actually get stuck on this
uh bottom example because uh the
gradient zero here even though if it
went a little bit further it could go
down significantly more.
>> Yeah. So the question is um you know
maybe we can change the way we're doing
the steps. Maybe we could use the hessen
to determine the direction we go. Um we
actually do have a brief slide talking
about the sort of hessen style approach
at the very end. That's not very
commonly used in deep learning. But the
short answer is yes. There are going to
be actually several ways in which you
can account for this that we're going to
go into in like 5 minutes. So it's a
good question. Yeah, we'll get to that.
Okay. Um so um I think one of the other
things that you might not know is that
empirically saddle points are actually
much more common as you move to higher
dimensional models. So as your weight uh
matrix gets larger and larger um you're
more likely to find these saddle points.
And there's this paper describing the
frequency of them. Uh if you don't know
a saddle point uh it's called a saddle
point because it's shaped like a like a
saddle like on a horse. And at the
center of this saddle uh the uh gradient
is actually zero in all directions. So
it's like the bottom of this and at the
top of this sort of uh curvature and so
in both the x and the y directions the
gradient zero. So you could get stuck
here despite being very close to like
going significantly down the lost
landscape on either side. So this is
also a pretty common issue with SGD
where these saddle points and as we move
to higher dimensional spaces or this is
equivalent to models with more
parameters uh this is more and more
common. This is a big issue. Um and then
a final issue with SGD is that um we are
sampling a subset of our data each time.
Right? So we're not looking at the whole
this represents the entire loss across
all the data but we're looking at just a
subset each time. So we'll actually have
somewhat noisy update steps because
we're not looking at the entire data uh
set. So we'll sort of be stepping
towards the center uh towards this sort
of uh local minimum that we're trying to
reach here. But uh each step doesn't go
directly in that direction. So there's
some noise in how we're progressing
because we're subsampling the data set.
Okay, cool. Um I think uh to summarize
these are the main issues and there's a
pretty neat trick you can do uh where
you just basically add momentum and you
can really think of this as the same way
as like if you have a ball that's
rolling down the hill where it gains
momentum. It's actually very similar to
how it's modeled in terms of the
physical properties. So u it's a good
way to gain intuition about it at the
very least. So um you can imagine that
um it could help with the you have these
local minimum because if you're rolling
down with enough velocity you'll be able
to come out of it. Um if you have the
saddle points or the like the just uh
flat point here, the model has been
rolling down the entire hill. So it
won't get stuck here anymore. It will
continue. Um also um if you have this
poor conditioning
value, you will still have maybe some uh
oscillation, but the nice thing is that
um it will sort of accumulate speed in
this direction to the right because it
will have multiple steps that keep going
that way. So it'll gain faster and
faster uh towards the center here. So it
also helps with this problem. Finally,
it can also help sort of average out
some of the noise with the gradients
because they all sort of have a
direction in common uh which is towards
this uh minimum here. And so um as
you're computing the momentum it sort of
builds on itself and it will converge
faster because um it sort of the noise
uh is uh accounted for by looking at the
direction they all share in common which
is uh uh which is included in the
momentum. So let me show you how to
actually do it. But this is sort of the
general intuition for how momentum
works.
So we have SGD here. We have our uh mini
batch x. We're computing the gradient
which is dx. We have the learning rate
or the step size. If you multiply and
then we do the negative because we need
to go down the hill. This gives us our
new x. So this is sgd for with momentum.
We're now updating by this velocity
term. So instead of updating by the
gradient at the specific point, we're
updating by the velocity. And the
velocity at a given time step is given
by the previous velocity uh plus the
current uh slope. So this is sort of how
you calculate it. And you have this row
value which is the momentum the actual
like how much momentum you want to have.
And if you have it very high then your
new velocity is more dependent on the
previous uh time steps velocity. And
this sort of is a running average uh
therefore of the uh last gradients uh
depend and the momentum term here gives
you how much to weight the past versus
the present. So now we're updating by
this and we still have this alpha which
is the step size. So um it's actually a
very simple change, right? You just are
now computing the velocity which is a
function of the current velocity plus
our gradient. So I think I'll pause for
questions here. Um this is the
explanation of momentum and um maybe I
could also recap briefly how it resolves
all these issues we saw. So um you know
if now that you're adding momentum in
the past uh over the past gradient steps
you could see how it would keep
continuing along this direction and
depending on your row if your momentum
is very high it would keep going and be
able to account for a very large sort of
hump here with the local minimum. Also
it's very good at sort of these saddle
points because it will just continue
along the direction in which it was
going previously for a significant
amount of time. and uh poor
conditioning. You know, if we're having
cumulatively going to the right upon
each step, the momentum will also um be
consistent there and build up. And then
if uh we're oscillating significantly
here, it will move less um it will move
less in the direction because it's sort
of the values will cancel out um in
terms of the current direction and the
velocity. Um they'll be pointing the
opposite direction so it will get
minimized. The question is what happens
if you're rolling like right along the
saddle? I mean I think in practice it's
very unlikely but in that case yeah you
would be you would just get stuck uh in
the saddle. Yeah I think that's like you
know your initial conditions like
wherever you start is very unfortunate.
So uh yeah sometimes I guess that could
happen but it's very unlikely. Yeah. And
it's also why in practice people won't
run like a single model um training run.
Often they'll run multiple ones with
different random seeds just in case
something like that could happen.
Another thing is if you're doing
stochastic uh gradient descent, you're
much more likely to have at least a
little bit of noise to get you out of
like directly in that saddle uh back and
forth. So I think it's basically it
never would happen because of the
randomness, but I hypothetically I think
it could that could occur. Yeah.
>> So the question is why is the saddle
just an issue with SGD and not
optimization in general? Um it would
also be an issue with the entire data
set. It might even be more common with
the entire data set. So uh it's an issue
that SGD faces but it's also an issue
that other optimization algorithms that
just rely on gradient descent with no uh
sort of bells and whistles attached
would also um they would face the same
thing. Yeah.
>> Yeah. So the question is does uh adding
the momentum make it more difficult to
converge because we'll overshoot and
then you know have to come back. Uh I
think the short answer is yeah it might
not help with converging but it will
help you find uh on average it will help
you find a better uh minimum point to
converge to. So it will converge maybe
more slowly because you won't get stuck
on a in a local minimum uh like you
would just converge here if there was no
momentum right versus overshooting. So I
think a lot of this stuff is empirically
uh shown where it's like it happens to
be with the specific class of neural
networks the momentum does help uh
training but um this is the intuition
for why we prefer it. Uh I think to be
honest um people will use whatever works
best and there are cases where people
have found that stocastic gradient
descent without momentum would
outperform for a particular model. So,
uh, here's the intuition about why it
could perform better, but in practice,
people will just try a bunch of
different ones and see what works best.
And I'm going over the most common ones
that people try now. Yeah. But yeah,
you're right. It could hurt convergence
potentially.
Okay. Um, all right. I'll continue then.
So, um, uh, yeah, I think we went
through this. Um, and, uh, one other
thing I wanted to point out is that
there are different ways you can
formulate this. So these equations are
identical but you'll sometimes depending
on the implementation see it written in
different ways but they you know they're
doing the same thing. Uh maybe in
interest of time I'll skip over why
they're identical but you could go over
in the slide and prove to yourself that
these are essentially the same
formulations.
Okay. Um I think the next thing I'll
talk about is a different optimizer. So
we talked about momentum and now we'll
talk about something called RMS prop. So
um RMS prop is a bit you know bit of an
older method now 2012 but uh came out by
Jeffrey Hinton's group and the basic
idea is to instead of just having this
running um velocity which the momentum
captures it's to actually add u
elementwise scaling of the gradient. So
um when we're when we're how do we do
this is we have this gradient squared
term and the decay rate here is very
much like the momentum that we the
momentum term we explained before but
now it's on the squared gradient. So uh
we have this sort of running average
where we take the previous term here the
gradient squared and then we do 1 minus
times and then here it is the literally
the gradient squared and so this is a
running average of our squared
gradients. So uh you know bigger values
will get much bigger, smaller values
will get much smaller and if there are
consistently large gradients in certain
values those will get very large as we
continue our uh running average here and
we're actually going to divide here in
the update step we divide by the square
root of it. So the basic idea here is
we're actually now stepping someone
asked earlier I think there was a
question what if we change the direction
in which we're stepping. uh this is
exactly the type of thing you can do and
this is what this is doing where we're
dividing by this squared gradient term.
So for values in which uh we have very
large squared gradients for the values
of w in which the derivative is very
large um we'll we'll uh divide by a
larger value. So we'll step not as far
in that direction. In the more flat
regions we'll step farther because we're
dividing by a smaller term here. So this
is the basic intuition behind it and it
very much addresses one of the questions
someone had earlier about can we change
the way we're stepping in the direction
and that's exactly what this is doing
here. So you still have a learning rate
but you're dividing it by this uh square
root of the cumulative uh squared
gradients which gives you larger steps
in the flatter areas of your loss
landscape and shorter steps in the very
steep areas. Can anyone explain? I sort
of just gave a brief summary, but what
happens in this specific line here of
the code? Why does uh what happens with
our gradient step direction? How does it
change? We're dividing by this value
which is dependent on the current
gradient and also the past gradients. So
the values one of these values are very
large. So these are you know you know
these are vector operations. So we have
a set of um derivatives here and we're
dividing elementwise by another set of
uh squared gradient values. So when it's
very large well the denominator is very
large then the step becomes effectively
less in that direction because we're
dividing by a large value. And when it's
a very small value the step becomes much
larger because uh the gradient squared
term is small. So it's in the
denominator and we're uh increasing the
effective step size. Oh yeah. So it's uh
specifically for this type of example
here where you have maybe a very narrow
valley where you want to be moving more
uh in the flatter direction.
>> Yeah. The question is what does a small
gradient mean in this context and how
does this help us move uh along the
steep directions less and along the flat
directions more?
Yeah. Yeah. So I think actually this is
maybe a great visual because it compares
the three different approaches here. So
we have uh with momentum which you can
see sort of it overshoots as there was a
question about earlier but then it kind
of comes back. Um you have SGD which is
slower because it's not it's just sort
of always moving in the fixed direction
and then you have RMS prop which we just
mentioned. So uh the way that RMS prop
works is because the gradient and the
direction that I'm moving my mouse here
is uh is higher uh the gradient square
term is larger. So we move less in that
sorry we move less in that direction. So
it's you can see it actually quickly
starts turning here towards the center
where it's a flatter landscape at this
point but it's traversing more in that
direction. So we're actually sort of
changing the direction we're going based
on uh going less in the steep direction
and more in the flat direction. So these
are the uh sort of three and then
there's one more we'll discuss which is
by far the most popular optimizer used
uh in modern deep learning. Um so it's
sort of just a combination of the SGD
momentum and RMS prop. So here is almost
what the atom optimizer is which is the
most popular optimizer in deep learning
and you also have all the prerequisite
knowledge now to understand it. Um so
you look at it and this first term here
in the red is basically the momentum we
described before where we have uh the
current uh so the beta 1 is like the
momentum term and then we have the
velocity here and we're taking a running
average. Um the second moment here is
like the gradient squared term for uh
RMS prop and we're doing the same thing
here where we're multiplying the
learning rate instead of by the step
size by the velocity but now we're still
doing the thing where we take the square
root. Um and it's the second moment
here. And the reason they use first
moment second moment is like a relation
to physics and mechanics. Um, but it's
basically just a combination of the two
things we explained earlier where you're
accelerating movement along the flat
directions, dampening it among the steep
ones, and then you're also adding this
notion of momentum and velocity. So, you
gradually build up speed if you're
continuously moving in the same
direction. Um, so, uh, as it's written
right now, this will actually run into
issues at the very first time step. And
it might be a little bit uh unclear to
you why, but I'll actually wait for
someone to have a guess. So, one thing
to note is that these betas beta 1 beta
2 are usually initialized very close to
one. So, like 0.9 0.999
uh and that these two values are also
initialized to zero. So, uh during your
first time step, if you just use this
formulation of atom, you would run into
potentially unwanted behavior. So um one
of the other things is it has to do with
the second moment calculation. So this
is the main issue here. When you
calculate the second moment and then use
it on the next line, you sort of run
into an issue. Yeah. So the denominator
is zero basically. Yeah, that's the
exact issue. So it starts at zero. So
this term is zero. Um you have a very
large beta. Uh so this value is very
small. And if your gradient is not very
large in your first step, you can have
this whole term basically be very close
to zero. Now we're dividing by something
very close to zero and it just creates a
very large initial step even though our
gradient was small. So that's probably
not something we really want. And so the
final thing that Adam has is it adds
these bias terms here which is
specifically to account for this issue
where it's dependent now on the time
step of training. So uh you know I think
this is also something you'll go into in
the homework. I just want to give the u
basically intuition behind atom why the
naive implementation wouldn't work which
is this really large initial step and
you'll go over in the homework
implementing this and you'll see how the
time step is used but the basic idea is
this is to account for that very large
initial step and uh as your time step
increases these uh bias terms are not
needed as much
okay cool um these are some like good
defaults that people normally use um if
you're training a model with atom you
could go with these and you know maybe
it'll work maybe it won't but it's a
good starting point and you can then
tell from the remaining slides we'll
talk about how do you know if your
learning rate's right how do you know if
uh these other values are right so I'll
I'll speed up a little bit um just to in
the interest of time but the basic idea
is that you can see these all all these
different optimizers converging um they
all have different properties you can
sort of see how atom is this combination
of RMS prop and SGD with momentum where
it has characteristics of both which is
very neat to see visually it aligns with
our intuition.
Um one final topic related to atom is
that um we could look at how
regularization interacts with the
optimizer. So um for example if we have
L2 regularization how does this affect
how the optimizer uh works and I think
the answer is it's actually not
immediately obvious and you can do it in
different ways. So uh in default atom
they compute L2 when they're computing
their gradient. So you know we looked at
the gradient and there was the loss
portion of our so the data loss portion
and then the regularization loss for
atom it's using both of those when it
computes the gradient um but atom w
basically does only looks at the data
loss for doing all of these moment
calculations and all these steps and it
just adds the regularization term at the
end here. Um so basically all I'm trying
to describe to you all is there is
flexibility for how you incorporate
regularization into your optimizers. Um
weight decay is generally when you just
add it at the end L2 regularization at
the end and you don't includes it
include it in the uh actual optimizer
for how you're calculating the
velocities and momentum etc. Um so this
is the main difference and sometimes uh
under a lot of settings atom w works
slightly better like I think the llama
series from meta they all use atom w uh
assuming I assume because it does
slightly better for them. So we have one
function optimize why are you splitting
it into two? Yeah. So if you mix it into
one function, that's what atom does. And
atom w is specifically the separating it
into two. So why you might want to do
that is because if you don't want your
velocities, your momentums to actually
be a function of the weights, you want
it to be a function of the loss. So if
you're trying to traverse your loss
landscape sort of more independent of
your actual weight values, that's why
you might want to separate it. But you
still might want a regularization term,
but you don't want it to interfere with
the moment calculation. So this is the
specific reason why they do it.
Ultimately it's empirical. You try both
and you see which one works better. But
this is why you would do it that way.
Okay cool. Um so we'll talk about
learning rates. So um there are
different uh ways in which uh learning
rates can be chosen and sometimes you'll
get a very high learning rate where what
will happen is basically your loss will
uh get very large as you sort of
oscillate out of the loss landscape as
we described earlier. Um if you have a
very low learning rate your issue is you
just converge very slowly. If you have a
high learning rate, but you're not
oscillating out, but you might not be
able to converge because you're sort of
bumping around the uh local minimum, but
you're not actually able to get uh any
any lower in because your learning
rate's too high. And ideally, a good
learning rate would have this property
where it decreere it causes your loss to
decrease quickly over time, but then you
see continued improvements as you
continue to train the model.
Um in reality actually depending on the
situation a lot of these could be good
learning rates and also depending on the
step in training which is the final uh
thing we'll discuss in lecture today. So
you can actually change your learning
rate as you train your model. You don't
need to always have a fixed learning
rate or step size and pretty much all
modern uh deep learning like all the
best models coming out have different
ways they vary the learning rate during
training. So one really simple way you
could do it is after a fixed number of
iterations
you just uh take onetenth of the
learning rate and you continue training.
So this can resolve the issue of where
uh your learning rate is too high for
you to be able to converge any further.
So then you reduce it and you're able to
get lower into the loss landscape. Uh
and this is really commonly used when
training ResNets. So that's a very
popular type of convolutional neural
network which we'll discuss later in the
course. Um another thing you could do is
sort of cosine learning rate decay. So
this is one is also extremely popular.
So um here you have uh basically this is
like half of a cosine wave where you're
uh starting at your maximum learning
rate here and then you go down to zero
to the end and it follows this sort of
half cosine uh shape. And here's the
formula for calculating it. I won't go
into too many any details but the basic
idea is there's a ton of different ways
to do it. when your loss uses a cosign
uh learning rateuler, you'll often see a
shape like this where um it sort of you
get pretty good continued gains in the
middle part of training. But the basic
idea is that the actual shape of your
loss during training will highly depend
on whatuler you use. So this is the
basic idea I'm trying to convey. It
looks very different for example than
this one where you can literally see
where we're uh taking onetenth of the
learning rate during training.
Um another thing you do is just a linear
learning rate decay. So um it just
follows a straight line. uh you could do
inverse square root etc etc. There's
basically an unlimited number of ways
you could uh mess with your learning
rate during training and depending on
the type of model you're training and
depending on what works best you you
just choose the one that works best but
here are some ones you could try that uh
could perform well in your setting. Uh
also a really really popular strategy is
to have a linear warm-up. So instead of
just starting at your maximum learning
rate, you spend a fixed number of
iterations to sort of linearly warm up
to whatever your maximum value is and
then you go about doing whateveruler you
had afterwards. So for example, linear
warm-up and then this would be like the
inverse square root or linear warm-up
and then um like cosine is a very
popular setup for training models. Uh
one final thing is that there is this
empirical rule of thumb uh or called the
linear uh scaling um linear scaling
hypothesis or linear scaling law or
something like that. I forget the name.
I think it's linear scaling law where it
shows the uh that if you increase your
batch size or the number of training
examples per update by n uh you could
you should also scale your learning rate
by n. So as you increase your batch
size, you should increase your learning
rate uh directly proportionally. So uh I
think the math behind this is a bit
involved and also it's more of an
empirical rule of thumb. So people have
like tried to show uh mathematical
proofs for why this could be useful but
and based on you know the variation of
gradients and your batch and the number
of uh gradients you calculate per batch
etc. But really this is just shown
empirically to be true for a large
number of problems. So uh this is a good
rule of thumb. If you have a winning
recipe but you want to increase the
batch size then also increase your
learning rate by the same amount.
Cool. Um and then the final thing I'll
talk I'll touch upon very briefly is
this idea of uh second order
optimization which is uses the hessen
that someone asked a question about
earlier too. So we won't talk about this
very much in depth but just to let you
know this exists. It's not something we
cover in the course very much, but um
the basic idea is right now we're using
the gradient to form a linear
approximation of basically where is the
downward direction where we're trying to
traverse this lost landscape. Um and we
just sort of look at the direction and
we take a general step in that
direction. And we added fancy things
like momentum and uh you know the RMS
prop where we're de accelerating along
the steep directions. But this is the
basic idea. We're using this uh gradient
uh at each time step.
The idea of the hessen is instead of
using the gradient you basically try to
fit a uh pol a quadratic or um like a
two second degree polinomial to your uh
function based on the derivatives at
that point or the hessions at that point
and uh you you then try to find the
minimum this way and in certain uh
optimization problems this actually
works extremely well but generally um we
don't use it in deep learning because it
requires two things. So one you have to
do this like tailaylor series expansion
whereas right now we're just sort of
doing the first part where we're taking
the derivative but you would need to be
able to calculate the second mixed
derivatives which is already uh maybe
difficult and then on top of that this
mixed uh derivative of all of your uh
parameters in your model by all the
other parameters in your model can get
very large as you have like these many
million or billion parameter neural
networks. So in practice uh we don't use
it because um these values have the the
matrices become way too large and so you
run out of memory on your computer if
you try to run it specifically your GPU
memory. But if you're training a smaller
model or if you're okay with spending
much more time uh to get better steps
towards your uh minimum then maybe you
want to look into this. Depends on the
problem set but for smaller models this
actually works quite well. But for these
large neural networks we're training, we
basically never do this due to the
memory restrictions and all the time you
spent uh computationally trying to
calculate the hashing etc. You would
rather just see more data during
training.
All right. So um some I guess uh
concluding uh thoughts for you all that
can be useful. So um Adam or Adamw is a
really good default choice for training
your first model. If you're working on a
new problem in a domain, I would
recommend it. Um, and it could even work
okay even if you do constant learning
rate. So, usually people will try Adam
W's constant learning rate or with like
a linear warm-up and then a cosine
decay. Those are like a really uh
popular combination. Uh, also um I think
SGD and momentum can sometimes
outperform atom. But the tricky thing is
because you uh you you generally have to
like tune the values more. So you have
to try many more learning rates because
uh you don't have this like RMS prop
term to account for the steep directions
and also you might have to try different
scheduling values whereas in practice
atoms sort of like best by test like
people have tried in a bunch of
different domains and it works very
well. It's very uh adaptive to the loss
landscape.
If you're doing like a full batch update
where you're already at each step, you
can fit basically your entire training
set into your batch size, uh you might
want to look beyond first order
optimization into second order and
beyond because it seems like your data
set's not very large or maybe your model
is not very large and you could
potentially benefit from having these uh
non nonlinear sort of update steps and
uh computing more sophisticated
strategies for going down the uh trying
to find the the minimum here.
Um yeah so I think uh we're essentially
done with the lecture. I'll give some
slides about uh looking forward. So how
do we optimize more complex functions
than linear models which is what we
covered in this lecture and uh next
lecture specifically we'll be looking at
uh neural networks which uh you know is
very exciting topic. um a two-layer
neural network the one we'll discuss in
class is basically you have two of these
weight matrices now one for each layer
and you have something called a
nonlinearity sort of stuck between so um
in this case the most common sorry not
the most common but the most simple one
is just this uh ru function which you'll
learn about more but basic idea is now
we have two weight matrices and we have
this additional function that's done in
between the weight matrix calculations
this is nice because as I said it's
nonlinear So, you know, if we're trying
to build a linear classifier to classify
data like this, you'll run into an issue
where the blue points and the red points
are not linearly separable. But maybe
there's some transformations we can do
or through many layers of a model, we
can eventually transform the data into a
way in which it is separable by a line,
which would be our then sort of final
layer of the model.