Okay, today we'll be talking about
different tasks of um core computer
vision
algorithms and tasks detection and
segmentation. We will also be covering
topics around visualization and
understanding. I will cover the the most
important ones. All right. So last le
the the previous lecture last time what
we discussed was around the topic of um
transitioning from sequence to sequence
models RNN's through uh two transformers
and we saw that transformers were
defined by um having some sort of
encoder a number of layers which had had
multi-headed self attention and layer
norm norm as well as some MLP norm uh
layers and this was
ultimately called something that we now
refer to as encoder encoding the
sequence and then if we need to decode
an image or a language a sequence as the
output then similar type of architecture
is used for decoder getting the
uh encoded tokens as input taking those
as input and then generating what is um
I'm hoping that you can see my cursor
too what is um
the
uh the the output the desired output we
did talk Justin talked extensively quite
extensively about the differences of
modeling sequences
recurrence neural networks RNN's and and
their variation ations that we've talked
um last week I think on Tuesday uh about
and then using convolution also as as
another approach but we talked about
ultimately that um self attention is
what we
work with in many of the applications
these days they work uh much better than
the other other two they do add they are
more expensive they do add computation
and and memory requirements for um and
um but but that comes with much better
modeling of the sequence and uh better
results in terms of any of the tasks. So
until here
uh it was it was mostly talking about
self attention. We also talked a little
bit about cross attention and
related topics. And then we got to the
topic of vision transformers which is
one of the core models that is being
used in modern applications computer
vision applications. We did go through
this um
in the
last minutes of last lecture and I want
to the previous lecture and I want to
revisit the topic and after that I'll
stop and and and hear any questions or
comments you may have regarding the
assignments and everything that I talked
about so far. We talked about the fact
that what we do with um transformers
when we want to process images, we
split the image into patches
basically creating a kind of sequence,
right? So the image was split to S bys
or um in in this case maybe uh 3x3
patches and each of those patches are
then represented by what we call tokens.
And tokens are often a linear
projection of the the the vector the
reshaped version of the image into a
vector and um it's it's basically a
D-dimensional vector as you can see in
this slide. But because we have turned
the image into patches what becomes
important? What are we losing here? It's
it's basically we're losing the
location, the position, the 2D position
of of the image, right? So that's why we
often create or add something that we
call positional embedding. And there are
many different ways of doing this. You
can create a sequence just put numbers
of sequence as 1 2 3 and and so on. or
you can do
uh a 2D version of X and Y u coordinates
and adding these two together creates
the the new token that goes to the
transformer layer the same way all of
the self attention layer norm and um
everything that we've talked about NMLP
everything we talked about last last
week. So and then the output layer will
will generate the output vectors for us
could be used for any application. One
of the major applications in computer
vision has been classification. We
started with image classification.
Right? So with image classification what
what uh becomes important is to somehow
be able to encode
or um generate something as the output
that is is uh representative of the
class. So what we do is often we add one
token a special extra input to the
transformer which is of the same
dimensionality but it's a learnable
parameter that
in the output space whatever that
represents is going to be turned into
the class um probability vector. So a cd
dimensional vector which is the class
probabilities and that's what we often
call the the class token. So this is one
of the base
u and and most standard way of doing uh
using vits vision transformers for image
classification
but transformers are not only used for
classification they could be used for
for many other tasks that we'll be
covering some of those uh today as well
but last week we also talked about this
other variant of the transformers again
tokens And from the tokens we we go with
uh the transformer layers. If you
remember last time we talked about these
multiple um layers of transformers as I
said positional embeddings are added and
here because images are they we we see
the entire image all together. We don't
have to do masking like we did for
language because language is really a
sequence uh that we shouldn't be using
the future information for. And then
ultimately
transformers um give an output of a
uh a vector uh patch for for each of the
inputs. And the other option for
training a transformer is actually to
instead of having a separate class token
just take the outputs run it pulling
layer and then turn that into a
probability vector for for C different
classes. So I talked about two versions
of transformers, right? One of them was
we're using a class token and the other
one was for we take all of the output
tokens. We apply pulling and projection
into a vector that represents the class
probabilities. How we supervise this?
It's the exact same thing that we talked
about earlier and that was uh back
propagation defining a loss function
binary cross entropy the soft max loss
and and so on.
So this was VITS uh this is VIT in a
nutshell but and and and over the years
this type of architecture um for many
different applications have have
remained the same. Um many modern
architectures right now use many of
these components very similar to what we
presented here. But there are some
optimizations that we had in the slides
last uh last week. But I think I'll I'll
just spend quick um quickly a couple of
minutes um on on them. But I want you to
understand that there are many different
tweaks and optimizations for better
performance and also making the
transformers the training a little bit
more stable.
One of them was is actually the residual
connections. This layer norm is is
basically at outside the residual
connection. So this means that whatever
we get here, we normalize it, right? So
this doesn't really mean that we we
can't replicate any form of identity
function anymore that ResNets really
wanted to to do, right? So the solution
for that is to bring in the layer
normalization. we often put it uh before
self attention and the second one right
before the MLP layer. So normalization
is there but we also preserve our
identity function. There are al also
other ways of normalizing. There is this
RMS norm root mean square normalization
which is actually a very um basic type
of normalization. It doesn't it doesn't
use the for each of the features it
doesn't use the the mean value of the
feature for normalization but this makes
the training a little bit more uh
stable. Again there are the these are
all empirically shown to be
uh better options.
Uh although there are some
justifications why they work well but
most of mostly the reason uh for
adopting these is is just um the fact
that they are uh they perform they make
the trainings more stable. The other
option is is to instead of using a
simple MLP, we use a uh sugloo MLP where
we actually do some sort of this is what
we call gated non nonlinearity. Instead
of having two vectors of U weight
matrices of W1 and W2, we add a third
one 1 2 and three. But here we create
some sort of gated non nonlinearity
which basically what what it uh does is
um
is is um
getting more um trainable uh parameters
and not just necessarily trainable
parameters but creating a better
nonlinearity for a small architecture.
Even if we select the hidden layer um
value equal to 8 di divided by 3, it
keeps the the same size of the network
in terms of the number of parameters but
it does um learn higher dimensional
nonlinearities um in
uh in in that layer. The last piece is
mixture of extra experts that is often
used in even the very modern
architectures these days. Instead of
having one set of MLP layers, you can
have multiple sets of MLP layers. Each
of those will be an expert and what we
do is you through a a router the tokens
will be routed to a of those e experts
and in in this uh way we actually have a
active experts but then again this what
it does is it increases
the
number of parameters and It helps
learning more robust models without
increasing too much in the uh on the
compute and these again are all parallel
MLPS. So we can have multiple experts in
parallel. As I said, they are used in
all LLMs these days, large language
models and um all of the modern LLMs up
to the level that we know of know about
are using these types of tweaks and this
is the summary of all of the tweaks that
I just mentioned. This is similar to
bias. No, this is this is completely a
trainable parameter by itself that you
train either a feed forward network or
or just a linear projection to turn that
into the probability vector. No. So it's
it's it's not uh it's not just then
again remember that you have so many
uh self attention networks here, right?
layers here and those self attention
layers are basically fusing the
information creating attention between
all of the tokens and this class token.
So when you supervise it from here the
loss function comes in this will
represent as the will represent the
class uh class token uh the class
probabilities vector. So the question is
if there are nice intuitions uh what
different experts are doing. Uh that's a
great question
because they are trained in parallel and
they are initialized differently. They
often try to learn one aspect or uh or a
related maybe also sometimes very much
related aspect but um it's just adding
more more u compute and more parameters
giving the network to learn different
things um if if it does have to uh learn
multiple concepts for example if you
have to cover multiple probability
distributions then then with these ops
you often have the power to like
separate those modes of um data. So the
question is if the the number of experts
is a hyperparameter or or not. Yes,
definitely it's a hyperparameter. From
what I know, it's often predefined. Uh
don't necessarily like uh over fine-tune
them, but yes, they are all
hyperparameters.
>> Yes. And they are. So why moving the the
layer norm helps us learn identifi
identity transformation. So look at this
architecture will you be able to create
any form of identity because right after
that uh residual connection the feature
values are changed because you have a
normalization. you will never have the
identity in the features, right? Because
right after that you see the layer norm
normalization,
right? And that's why what we do is we
bring it in.
We have a few quite a few different
tasks in computer vision and these these
were the core and more important the
most important tasks over the years for
computer vision applications. Although
these days we we're solving much much
harder tasks and nobody cares about
object detection anymore because now we
can just do it with one line of code but
over the past 10 15 years there has been
a lot of advances and we want to cover I
want to really cover some of those today
just so if you have to design something
new yourself you know uh where to look
and how to design your models and then
ultimately there is the topic Think of
visualization and understanding which is
very important in in many applications.
For example, if you're working with
medical data, often the visualization
understanding is more important than the
classification itself or detection of
tumor for example. You want to know
where, why and so on.
And um the way we started the class and
this this slide is probably uh very much
familiar to everybody.
We talked about different tasks and for
object classification for for the task
of classification. We talked about this.
We spent quite a lot of time over the
first few lectures saying how we can
create a classifier that classifies
images from pixels into labels. But then
one of the other tasks important
um similarly is is semantic
segmentation. And within semantic
segmentation what we care about is to
assign a label for to every single pixel
inside the image.
turn each each of the pixels into a
label that
is is the label for that object or or um
anything in the scene.
So basically at the when we train a
model that does this at the test time we
want to take an image and generate the
same map as the output. How do we do
that? There are many different options.
So let's say um I can what I can do is
just look at each pixel every single
pixel and say what the value or what the
label for that pixel should be. Some it
in in the very basic form as you can see
here it's it's actually very much
impossible. It's hard to say what pixel
that
um represent that that specific what
what object that specific pixel
represents.
because there's no context if you only
look at the the pixel itself. So
that's why context is important. We look
at the surrounding areas and um and then
if I take these patches the pixel in the
center and the surrounding areas. Now I
can train a convolutional neural network
or any network that generates the output
label for us. Right? It's the same
architecture that we've talked about
over the quarter and you can select any
of those that we used for for image
classification because now you're
classifying the image the entire image.
It could be a CNN, could be a ResNet,
could be a VIT or whatever.
This is really time consuming because if
you want to run one full network for
every single p pixel in an image, it
will take forever to to turn this into a
segmentation map. The other option that
we often uh we can use is to
instead of running one network for every
single pixel, what if we train a neural
network that takes the image as the
input and outputs the entire pixel map,
the segmentation map, not just one
single label, a matrix of labels, right?
And in that case
um we will have our segmentation task
solved. And in order to do that we need
to have
a layer in the in the input that is the
same size of as the image. And also in
the in the output you also need some
sort of an inflated layer. You can't go
to fully connected layers and so on
because now we are generating an image
and because of that we need to
keep the the network inflated and and
then um that's what we call often fully
convolutional neural networks or or FCN.
So with fully connection uh
convolutional neural networks this is
this is definitely a great idea but
there is a caveat there is a problem
these images are are large and and these
networks these uh layers will become
very large and there will be so many
parameters to optimize especially in the
early years that we didn't have powerful
GPUs this was a bottleneck a problem a
challenge for training algorithms
And that's why the algorithms evolved
into starting from full size images
going down in terms of the resolution
making the convolutions the the special
resolutions smaller and smaller through
down sampling operations. And then
somewhere in the in the middle we'll
have a low resolution but but somehow
thick in terms of the number of
channels. And and then from there what
we do is we go back up to the same size
of the image to create the output pixel.
And in order to do that we know how to
do the down sampling. Right?
Downsampling was was easy. We've talked
about it. We talked about um pulling
operation, strided convolution and um
several other
um
steps or operations that could be used
here.
But on the upsampling side, we don't we
don't really how know how to to do the
upsampling, right? because we don't have
pulling or reverse of uppooling or
reverse uh reverse right convolutions
right and and because of that we had to
invent some new operations that reverses
down sampling
uh by itself but before I go to the
upsampling
uh defining what upsampling is I just
briefly want to tell you that um
how this uh maybe I can ask you a
question. How do you think this network
is trained? Because now we have a
network that starts from an image and
ends with an image and then the tools
that we have for training this network
was a loss function, right?
How do you think is the best to train or
or define a loss function for this
network?
We talked about softmax loss, right? We
talked also about a little bit about
some regression losses and SVM loss. But
assuming that we want to use softmax
loss function,
how could we define this uh or train
this network?
What would the objective be? So mean you
said mean classification loss for each
of the pixels and that's uh that's
correct. You can add the loss function
for every single pixel because every
single pixel is like is doing a
classification right. So you will have a
sigma over all pixels of the image and
the loss function is just a simple soft
max and then you can back prop that's
that's that's the entire loss function
that you need. The question is um do we
need what we call ground truth for
training? So that's that's actually the
ground truth of segmentation and that
yes for these types of algorithms
because they are fully supervised. We do
need the ground truth label maps and
early years there has been a lot of work
doing and sitting down and and and u
manually labeling the the pixels to be
able to train these algorithms. Yes,
these days we don't need that because we
have tools. But early on in order to
train these algorithms, we needed the
ground truth.
Okay, very briefly let me tell you what
we do with upsampling. Upsampling is
actually not that hard. We can use an
unpulling operation. There are different
ways of doing it. One is nearest
neighbor. If I want to go from a two 2x
two
As an example here, a matrix 2 to 4x4. I
just need to copy
the data kind of for each of these. Take
the nearest neighbor in the in the lower
resolution one or bed of nails is you
just select one of those in in the
upsampled version. You only select one
of those or the one on the corner
to copy the data. replace everything
else with zero and through multiple
layers of convolution these values will
will start um appearing.
If we used max pooling in our
um in our network in the in the encoding
side, what we can do is we can save the
locations of the max um the the ones
that were selected and then copy the
data in the unpulling max unpulling
stage right over there that the
the uh max was defined. So basically we
we save the locations in the encoding
part and in decoding part in the
upsampling step we reuse those saved
coordinates.
The other option is to to do a learned
upsampling.
All of these that I I showed there is no
parameter to be learned. It's just an
operation. But learned upsamplings are
also possible. Very simply, let's let's
revisit the convolution. In the
convolution layer, what we we did was
applying a convolution filter for a
pixel and generating the output and do
this repeatedly for all of the pixels,
right?
And when we wanted to do um to to down
sample what we did was strided
convolution where instead of taking
steps of one we take steps of two and
generate the outputs step by step. If
you don't remember this part go back to
the lecture we talked about it third
lecture I think and um and then we can
replicate the same for the offsampling
process. So this one will represent this
area in the upsampled image. And then we
define some weights here to map that to
the output um map. And then for the next
one, same story, but there will be
overlaps. And for the overlaps, you
often sum over the the values. Let me
give you an example. Sum over the
outputs. Let me give you an example. And
that's with a simple 1D
uh function. If the input is um just two
values of A and B, we learn a filter
that that filter maps it to the higher
resolution output, right? And for doing
that, we just apply the filter to each
of the values and write the outputs
here. for the parts that there's an
overlap, it's a summation addition of
what is um
coming from each of the two uh
locations.
So
we did talk about this um fully
convolutional neural networks and and
how they are being used. This these are
actually some of the most basic and
mostly widely used algor algorithms for
segmentation. Um and I want to also very
quickly highlight one of the widely used
networks unit as you can see the the the
shape U. It's actually the same
architecture as I showed here just let's
let's uh draw it as a similar to a U
shape. And
uh the reason that I'm highlighting this
is that still today some of the medical
applications uh that that work on
segmentation use segmentation algorithms
still this is uh the this this unit or
its variance generate the
state-of-the-art um results if you don't
want to use any foundation model. So
what it does is exactly what we
explained a down sampling phase that
increases the field of view and loses
some special uh information and then
upsampling
phase that um goes back to the image
resolution. The only difference that
unit has is because it's the it's used
for segmentation.
There is this
um understanding that we need to keep
the the the
special uh information in the decoder
side because when we down sample we
somehow lose resolution. And then
upsampling if you don't have the
information it's going to be a little
bit um hard and we often get into
sometimes boundaries are are faded and
in order not to um get there the feature
maps in the encoder side are actually
copied
as inputs to the decoder layers. In that
way you are act you're you're keeping
this structural
information within the image and
generate the outputs that are much
sharper. So this was the idea about um
behind unit and as I said it's actually
being used quite often. Summary of
semantic segmentation. Um what we talked
about today the fully convolutional
neural networks you have same filter as
um as before
that we had for down sampling here. So
you have a um a
actually so
for to save time I actually removed some
of the slides from this part and I have
it in the backup slides you should check
it out. This is a reverse um this is a
transform transpose convolution. So we
do have a 3x3 matrix here and then
instead of convolving the input image
input data we convolve we we do the
convolution on the applied convolution
on the transposed version of the input
and it actually generates an a larger
output. So it's the transposed
convolution it's it's uh it's the
reverse of the regular convolution. But
why transposed? I would refer you to
take a look at the the additional
slides. So the question is is that
filter trained? Yes, it's very much
similar to other convolution layers. All
of the filters are trained. Yes. Yeah.
Okay. Um
great. This was uh the topic of semantic
segmentation. And as we talked about
this, we only get labels for the pixels.
But if there are two instances of the
same object, we have no idea which one
is which, right? Because this is just
generating or outputting the the labels,
pixel labels. And this brings us to that
brings us to the topic of instance
segmentation where now we not only care
about the pixel uh classes but also I
want to know that um these pixels belong
to one instance of the dog and this uh
next one is actually a different dog
right and and for doing that what we
need is
understanding objects multiple objects
in the image and brings us to the topic
of object detection. Object detection
has been one of the uh besides image
classification or after image
classification has been one of the core
computer vision
problems and and tasks. And for many
years many many different algorithms
were proposed for just doing the task of
object detection. We are going to fly
over some of them and highlight a couple
of important ones but again there are so
many works in the literature that even
in literature of deep learning that I'm
not covering uh here. So in the past 101
15 years
how we can do that um and and solve the
problem of object detection if it's just
a single object it means that we need to
generate we need to do the
classification
generate a label class scores as well as
getting a bounding box coordinates of a
box right so you need the coordinates of
the box XY and H and and W as the output
as well as what class it is. Right? So
this is exactly the task of object
detection. How can we solve this? It's
very simple. Right? We can define a
softmax loss soft max loss function for
the class scores. And we can define an
L2 loss function which is a simple
distance metric a regression loss for
the box coordinates. And having these
two defined we have a multitask loss. We
are solving two tasks at the same time.
And for doing that we again uh add the
loss values and generate a
compound loss function as you can see
here.
So this is simple. It's doable. If we
have one single object, we can for sure
um
solve this problem using this
architecture that I talked about. But
this is not that easy if we have
multiple objects in the in the scene. So
for three objects, we have to generate
12 output numbers and and if there are
more then it it's going to be too many
uh numbers to generate. So this is this
algorithm is not really scalable. it's
it's it's just extending the
classification into some sort of object
detection which is fine but it's not
really scalable.
So um
if the when there are multiple objects,
one solution is
um instead of going or or getting the
entire image as the input, why not to
look at bounding boxes for each bounding
box, we can say we only have one label
and um whether it's a cat or a dog or or
the background, right? And if I
have this this um way of classifying
each of the bounding boxes, I can do a
sliding window. I can create just
bounding boxes slided over the image
from coordinate 0 0 to all combination
of XY and H and W and see if we can
detect the object. So step by step I can
I can create uh I can find the bounding
boxes that have the the maximum
probability of each of the objects.
But there is a huge problem here right
again there are so many different
combinations of bounding boxes that we
can use and again this algorithm is not
scalable.
what we've been doing in the literature
again early early years if you look at
the
uh the years these articles were
published 2014 and before
there has been a lot of research around
finding regions
that are um they have high probability
of having the object in them. So region
proposals and if I have a way to find
region proposals that's actually going
to be a easyish
problem. I can do the same thing as as I
explained earlier, right? For a for an
image, what we can do is if if I have
region proposals, I can just take that
part that patch out
and run a CNN on that on that patch,
right? And convolutional neuronet
network on the patch and then classify
it. And in order to even I can I can
refine the bounding boxes.
So classify oops classify and then
refine the bounding boxes to have um the
object detected. So we can we can
classify the boxes and also refine the
bounding boxes if if I have to change
the coordinates a little bit.
And this is what is called um RCNN um
algorithm.
And uh although it's it's it's it works
and again this is one of the early
algorithms CPR 2014
there are these are very slow because
for each of these box boxes again we are
running a full convolutional neural
network. But there is one catch that um
um what what we can do is
um is instead of
running convolution neural network on
each of these boxes because convo
operations convolution operations they
preserve the special information right
they either down sample or or upsample
we always have a a way to to track them
where in the pixel space they are Right.
So in that uh case what we do is instead
of running the
convolutional neural network on the
patches let's say we run one big
convolution on the entire image and then
now we have the regions in that feature
map which is corresponding to the entire
image. Let's look at those regions and
now run a smaller CNN for on top of
those and generate the outputs.
for each of these two um outputs that I
want. First the box offset like should I
move the bounding box a little bit or
what the object category is. So this is
the the fast version of RCNN. These are
some uh some basic algorithms that you
can use convolutional neural networks
for detecting objects their bounding
boxes and so on. The question is if the
number of pre proposed uh regions are
predefined. Uh that is the the short
answer to that is yes. I will talk very
briefly about the region proposal
networks too.
So easy algorithms right? One puts the
bounding boxes of the regions the
proposed regions um on the images one
puts it on the feature maps of the
connet and both of those generate the
output class label as well as offset of
improving the the location of the
detected object. But this will mean this
requires us to do um that bounding box
uh region proposal um first and and have
a region proposal network that tells us
where to in image we should look at uh
look for and uh there has been research
on on building region proposal networks
RPNs and here what we do is we just
randomly start with with a CNN we try to
randomly start in in different locations
in the image and through layers of
convolution
we refine those regions where they have
the higher probability of having an
object in them because we have the
object labels and and and locations. So
we can optim we can uh supervise this
and then each of those also refine the
box coordinates. So basically a neural u
a region proposal network what it does
is it
refineses the boxes each of those boxes
that have a probability a high
probability of an object in them and the
box
uh the output boxes the box corrections
again I'm I'm leaving all of the details
about the coordinate uh coordinates and
all of these u dimensionalities
for you to pick uh afterwards because
you it will take too much time and we
don't want to spend too much time on
this uh algorithm. But what's important
here is back to your question, we often
take the top k the ones that have the
highest probability of having an object
in them as the proposals for this image.
This is an simple image. So then then
most of the and only has one object. So
most of the regions are centered around
that single object but in general that's
not the case. So in in many setups we
can have region proposals used in in
different setups. um we can get
different objects and with higher
probabilities with
that and after talking a little bit
about RCNN and mask RCNN which again for
you it's it's important to to go through
the details and if you can spend some
time um doing the calculations yourself
that would be very good but those types
of algorithms RCNN mask RCNN they're not
being used anymore more these days
because because they are very heavy
computationally.
Although it's important to understand
how we got to this point but but those
are for uh for many reasons. One of
those reasons is that we we need two
separate networks. One region proposal
network and then one um classification
and box refundment network. So it's like
at least two passes for detecting
objects on the on the uh for each image
right and that's why there has been
advances after these um using single
single stage object detectors SSDs and
one of the most popular ones is called
YOLO. YOLO is um probably if if you work
with any computer vision problem you've
you've heard about YOLO even to date
although it's a it's a convolution um
heavy network today uh at least its
earlier versions
uh in many even industrial applications
YOLO is being used as as the base for
object detection because it's a fast uh
object detector and It's um very good in
terms of detecting uh the objects. What
YOLO does I want to very briefly uh tell
you a little bit about. It's basically
you look only once with one single pass
on the image. You generate all of the
bounding boxes. How it does it is it
maps it. It divides the image into S bys
S
grid of S bys and in this example it's 7
by 7. What happens is that for each
single box in that grid it tries to
output it. It it creates a fully con
convolutional network that outputs the
probability of an object being in that
location.
refinements of the bounding boxes. So it
generates Bbounding boxes and new
hyperparameters B bounding boxes that is
the refinement of the object that is
present in that box and also it
generates a probability the class uh
class probability object class
probabilities and um in this case for
example if it's B equal to two it
generates just two B bounding boxes with
different probabilities.
It it does this for all of the
boxes at the same time. So basically
it's the it's the same network that is
being uh generating something as the
output for each of these
bounding boxes and it it it does
generate a number of different options
for the for the for the object and as I
said each of those boxes are associated
with a probability and pro in this
example the probability is shown with
the weight of the edges
uh in each of those boxes.
And um for these many different bounding
boxes and object probabilities now we
can do thresholding
and also
um
there is an algorithm that they used in
the paper again I don't want to go into
the details uh non uh maximal
suppression and um some some algorithms
uh with thresholding involved that that
identifies the ones that have the
highest
probabilities. So this is this is a
simple implementation or or use of the
uh
object detection. Again this is this is
something very useful if you have time
spend time with the repositories of
YOLO. There are so many different uh
newer versions of YOLO that is being
used for many applications in in
medicine robotics and also in many
industrial applications. So the question
is how do we get this uh second image
and what's the intuition behind it right
as I said for each of the grids we
generate B bounding boxes like for for
this one we generated two for all of all
others we also generate two this B is
again a a probability vector and each of
these boxes are associated with
probability of uh existing an object in
them and then if I put all of them
together for all of the patches I have
so many boxes
And now each of those are associated
with a probability
right.
Um
let's move on. Um
and one of the more recent
approaches for object detection is deter
a detection transformer. This is purely
based on transformers
and the topic that we did discuss last
uh week and also I started today same
type of self attention and cross
attention modules could also generate
some
uh some object detections and bounding
boxes for us and how this works. This is
actually not a very old paper 2020 uh
almost 5 years ago although it's it's
now kind of deprecated. Nobody uses this
for real applications but but it's a
it's a very good example of how to use
transformers for object detection. And
what we do here is basically similar to
what we've explained earlier. We make
turn the image into patches and then
those patches are passed through CNN's
creating a token. Then we add positional
encoding the same way that I explained
to the patches and those define our
tokens for the input uh which are inputs
to the transformer encoder. a
transformer encoder again a bunch of
self attention
layer normalization or any normalization
as well as MLP layers that generates the
output tokens after multiple layers of
uh transformer encoder.
Then in order to generate the bounding
boxes, this is this is the smart part
for this algorithm that it does take the
encoder output tokens as input in the
transformer decoder. But we also define
some queries
which are trainable parameters
themselves that
each of those for example if I add five
five queries as input four queries as
input or 10 or 20 inquiries as input I'm
seeking
up to 20 objects to be detected in that
image and then again through a
combination of self attention
layers in the beginning of this
transformer decoder as well as cross
attention with the encoder
output.
So cross attention and self attention
networks layers. It generates it it it
generates the output values for each of
these queries which are passed through
an FFN uh freeforward network to
generate either class
um
labels and and the bounding boxes very
similar to what we discussed earlier
or even uh in some cases it it just says
there's no object to be detected and and
at the end we have the bounding boxes
and the classes associated with bounding
boxes as the output.
So the question is are we inputting
every possible box to the transformer?
No, the input here are some general
parameters that are representing they
are queries
uh representing
asking the question that I actually want
an object to be outputed in in in place
of this input query. Right? So there is
no box or anything as the input. It's
part of the output that it generates the
class label and the box coordinates.
So the question is um if the queries are
formed in a way that's it it it actually
represents what we want to look for and
where in the image right so in this case
um what we are looking for is defined by
class labels which are defined uh
predefined and they are as part of the
output. So our supervision is based on
the class labels. We have a class
probability vector same same way that we
defined it for the other algorithms.
Right? So that's how um the algorithm
knows what type of classes to look for.
And then in terms of the outputs
uh again these outputs are supervised if
you remember based on the L2 norm L2
loss of the ground truth boxes right. So
we're not telling anything in the query
part
um what to or where to look uh for any
of the objects. The training the the
process itself is back propagating um if
there are any losses any any errors it
back propagates the the outputs. So
basically it's
um we are not determining anything in
the beginning or in in this part. So the
question was
the query is give me up to nine objects
and uh and yes the that's the that's
that that's basically what this means
and through the self attention and cost
attention it will turn try to generate
output tokens that are turned into class
and box coordinates through that FFN
operation. Your question is if the
queries over there if they are image
patches or not.
>> No, they are they are not image patches.
They are just uh queries for uh
trainable parameters to to you you put
them in to generate the outputs for each
of the inputs. You you get the value as
the output and that value is turned into
class and box coordinates.
Again the question is what is object
queries? They are trainable learnable
parameters. So you initialize them, the
network finds the best values for them
and that's what you get as the output.
The question is if uh if there's any
intuition uh which FFN gets which box,
right? The short answer to that is no.
uh there's there's nothing that stops
the network from I mean we are not
including anything that stops the
network from uh generating multiple but
remember that are so many self attention
and cross attention layers over there
that they are actually interacting with
each other and and makes each of those
queries match with one of the uh output
layer. So it's it's not generating the
exact same thing at the as the output.
And we also have control over how to
supervise supervising those uh FFNS as
well. So your question is if there are
image segmentations pixel level
segmentations as part of the training.
This algorithm does not require the
segment level um pixel level
segmentations. It it's only supervised
based on class labels and bounding
boxes. But if you have the b the pixel
level segmentations, you can always turn
the pixel level segmentations into a
bounding box to train this algorithm,
right? But it doesn't necessarily
require that. So the question is if it's
possible to generalize unseen objects.
Um
and by unseen you mean a new class
label.
uh for these types of algorithms that
they are fully supervised often there is
no way because you are creating class
probability vector there's no way of
like adding something at the end for a
new class um
without previously knowing there's
there's some some other classes right so
fully supervised networks they are often
there's no new object we can have a
background object or no object as you
can see we have the the label of no
object
But there are many algorithms and
extensions of these types of algorithms
that are used for zeroot learning. Zero
shot means understanding something new
without having an example of those in
the training data. But uh it's beyond
this this topic. What happens if you
have more objects in the scene than um
what you uh put in as the query? Right.
So that's a that's a great question. it
often generates the ones that have the
has has the highest confidence on the
objects. So bounding boxes with the
highest confidence and in in those cases
you often want to add more queries just
so you can get more objects, right?
Okay. Um I'll be here to answer
questions if you have any uh after after
the class, but we have a bunch of other
topics to cover and I want to make sure
we we go over them. at least you get uh
familiar with the topics. So with the
object detections now back to the
question that was asked earlier, how can
we use those types of algorithms for
instance segmentation and that's
actually not too hard. We talked about
this um when when we were talking about
our CNN algorithms where we run a CNN on
the image then we have a region proposal
network that gives us the bounding boxes
and those bounding boxes are
turned into either class labels and
bounding box refinements. Right? So this
is what we've talked so far
with RCNN and so on. Now we can turn
this into a mask RCNN that also
generates the mask. So, so basically
same architecture that we talked about
earlier. Now we can we can uh take one
more output make it more multitask
and generate the mask predictions. So
what we used to be doing before was
again image region proposals CNN gives
us class label and the box coordinates.
Now we add another layer of convolution
that generates the mask the the mask for
for that object on in the pixel level.
And that mask again could be the same
size as the input and the and the image
and basically on the on the layer
itself. If we use fully convolutional
neural network that's that's what we
often get as the output for each of the
objects. When we have that box tiny box
we can always get the mask for that. the
chair in different settings of the box
itself if you have different boxes, the
bed uh and the human the baby in the
image and this is what we an extension
of the RCNN algorithm which we call
mascarn
and um
with mascarn it's actually the the
results have been very very good in
detecting different objects different
um
known objects that we could train the
algorithms for. And then um there are so
many APIs and and open-source versions
of object detectors that you can um
explore. There are some some links and
resources here. But this all basically
rounds up and summarizes some of the
tasks that we wanted to cover and and
they are actually very important for you
to understand these tasks. They have
been core computer revision tasks.
Although these days computer vision is
is way more advanced, they're not bound
to these tasks. But if if you have
industrial applications of for example
uh quality control of
separating rotten tomatoes and and good
tomatoes in an industrial pipeline then
with computer vision you need to be able
to detect objects and then classify them
into good or bad. Right? So so that
that's why it's important to still
understand and know these um steps and
pipelines and how to do them in real
time. But now there are larger scale
models that you're all familiar with.
This um summarizes the first part the
computer vision tasks that I wanted to
talk about. And the last piece that I
want to spend 10 minutes on is around
visualization and understanding.
Again this has been a big lecture by
itself and and in 2050s60s until 2020s
that the topic of computer u and and and
even before that 2014 13 the topic of
visualizing neural networks has been
very hot and very uh much
it gained it it helped us gain
understanding into what the networks are
learning and I'm going to summarize some
of those the most important ones here
that you may need to un to use in your
applications. But before that, let me go
back to the linear classifier that we
talked about. Um, we spent quite a lot
of time on linear classifiers. And with
the linear classifiers what we we did
was at the end we said if if I look at
the linear function the the what what
the network is learning I can have a
template for each of those classes like
for example for this car you can always
see a front-facing car um as a template
right we can do the same with neural
networks if I visualize one of the
filters so here we visualize the weights
of the linear function it was the visual
viewpoint point I can do the same with
linear uh sorry with visualizing the
filters in the neural networks. So for
each of the filters the the network is
for example is learning something that
is basically some of the basic shapes um
orientations or or simple shapes as you
can see here.
Although this visualization is it's we
can only do it for the layers that we
have few channels like for example if we
have three three channels I can put them
in an RGB image and just just visualize
it but as you remember in in CNN's that
was not the case in CNN's we had
different um sometimes
quite a few uh channels in the middle
layer so it's not easy to visualize
those in something that we can see but
but that's that's what you basically in
early layers that we have fewer channels
we can visualize them and see the
network is actually learning some
patterns. So we start it starts learning
patterns and then later stages it um
gets
uh more holistic and and bigger patterns
as um
if if we train um sorry if we run some
something that we call guided back
propagation we can also visualize those
but not as simple as this. I want to
highlight an a couple of ways of
evaluating uh understanding and
visualizing the neural networks which
are actually kind of important. One is
uh the concept of salencies. So in many
applications it's very important for you
to know which pixel matters. For
example, in a medical application when
you do a classification of tumor versus
none, you want to see which parts of
that image is actually the the tumor
because if you want to automate this,
nobody cares about knowing if there is
tumor or not. Everybody cares about
where in the image the tumor is, right?
So
in order to do that simplest application
is we train a network a feed forward um
neural network that generates the value
or the class label doc. But what we can
do is we can um
actually before I showed you that in in
this case in order to train this network
what we've done was we always took the
derivative derivative of the neural
network the weights sorry of the loss or
of the class score with respect to the
weights in order to update the weights.
Right now what I need is for each pixel
I want to see how much changing the
pixel value how much changing the pixel
value
would affect the dog score right what
does this mean what I explained is is
the the meaning of derivation right so
if I u this means that the meaning of
basically gradient so if I take the
gradient of the core with respect to now
the pixel values not the network weights
anymore with pixel values I can
visualize those gradients
and visualizing those means that these
are the pixels that are that that matter
in order to classify dog
on this image those are the pixels that
matter. So if I change the values of
those pixels the score the dog score
will change will be changed right again
this is the basic meaning and definition
of gradients that uh we've talked about.
So this is one way if you run this on on
different objects
uh that you've trained in in the network
then this is what you get.
So that's one way of understanding
salency. Uh and it's very effective in
many cases. But sometimes it's not just
about the the pixel values all the way
to the to the back. You want to see
um for each of the classes how the
activations
uh work. And this brings us to class
activation maps or CAM algorithm. uh
class activation mapping cam or grat cam
that I will talk about in a in two
minutes are uh one of the most and
widely used algorithms for understanding
CNN's and also could be used for other
architectures too but for transformers
we we have a much better way of um
making sense of those which actually we
talked last uh in the last lecture. So
what happens is that for each of the
convolution layers um we often do
pooling and the pooling generates
feature maps. The feature maps are then
turned into scores and those scores with
with those uh values of the
uh weights.
If I if we extend the math, basically we
simply can highlight the class scores in
a weighted sum form. And this means that
um you can trace back class predictions
all the way back to the feature maps
and a specific locations of the space
because convolution layers are always
mapped to a space in the image space
too, right? we do convolution that's the
the special uh consistency across all of
the operations can can help us trace
back all the way to the image space. So
anyways we can we can look at the
feature maps and see how the class
activations each of these classes are
actually impacting those locations in
the in the image. And with that now if I
if I do this um multiplication of
weights versus uh the the the weights
that we've learned on top of the feature
values we create some class activations.
And this means that I have a way now to
go back to the image space because as
long as I'm in the convolutional space,
I can go all the way back to the image
and create these maps of like for
example for each of the classes, palace,
dome, church, u altar and and uh
monastery. We can have different class
activation maps. These are the weights.
These are the pixels or areas of the
convolution layer that have been driving
the scores for these specific
uh classes. It's the same for for others
um like class activation maps for one
single object in different images.
But there's a problem with this and that
problem is that we can only apply this
to the last convolution layer because
this is the only way we can do it. Like
we can only go to the last convolution
layer the way that we did the
calculations here. And in order to solve
that problem there is one variant of the
algorithm called grat cam. So gradient
weighted class activation maps. It's
basically the same algorithm just we
need to weight calculate the weights
with respect to the we basically take
one of the
uh layers
that created some sort of activation in
the class class uh level. We compute the
gradients instead of just calculating
the multiplication between W and
feature. we all we go all the way back
with the gradients and create a weight
based on the gradients um and then that
is used instead of the weights it's
aggregate of all of the weights and
gradients up to that specific layer and
then we weigh that with with that and
then we also use ReLU to only map uh to
pass the uh be the positive ones and And
that could also be all the way shown in
the class in the image space. So I
talked about cam which was only applied
to the last convolution layer. If you
wants to but but this is not possible
because in most of the CNN algorithms we
don't have just u like one convolution
layer at the end right we always have
some operations fully connected and so
on. So in order to be able to carry this
class activation to the convolution
layer if there is something else in the
middle we often use the gradients and
weight basically weigh the maps with
with the gradients uh aggregates and
then we can actually do the
visualization they create these heat
maps for each of the objects. So this
was about CNN's but we talked about u
transformers last week right u last in
the last lecture that they actually they
inherently come with the activation
maps. Did you do you remember that
language um matrix that that Justin
showed that for each of the output words
there is a tension weight for the input.
We can do that the the same thing for
the pixels for each of the outputs we
can create these maps in the pixel space
and and visualize the features of the
VITs in the pixel space. So basically
with vit and and transformers this is
much easier. you already have a way to
to visualize the ch the attentions the
weights but with
CNN's we often use grat cam or these
types of algorithms that said
I did this u task that I thought I
wouldn't be able to completing the the
the topics I wanted to talk about today
and next session we'll have the lecture
around video understanding. Thank you.