this is work with a very large number of
people over 200 contributors and I
include a lot of slides adapted from a
couple of these folks Christa and
Michael so the context of this lecture
is that it's never been easier as we're
all aware to build really impressive AI
demos and you know pretty obviously one
of the best examples of this is none
other than chat GPT it's this one
interface um where you can ask just
about any questions that come to your
mind and not only will the system find
answers that suit your uh your questions
it will synthesize them on the fly
conversationally now we're all taking
that for granted but let's just marvel
at how amazing that is now what makes it
really cool uh and a big step forward
compared to before is that it could also
help us with tasks so I have here an
example of uh me asking Chad JP to help
with a piece of code I'm asking it to
parallelize uh sequential python loop I
had now you know and it does exactly as
I asked now at this stage uh we're all
extremely familiar with the primary
weakness of these language models which
is in some sense precisely their key
strength which is that they are so
fluent in fact that when they make
mistakes um they can be incredibly hard
to uh incredibly hard to detect so
Stanford uh was not founded in 1891
although it's close maybe using that
example at berley is weird but anyway um
and the whole reason I asked for help
with this piece of code was that um you
know I wanted to avoid data races so
when I was given a piece of code that
simply naively parallelized the code and
had a bug in it I was glad I didn't
trust that model um and you know didn't
simply plug in this code into my code
base so the big picture here is that
even though it's incredibly impress
incredibly easy to build impressive
demos turning monolithic language models
into reliable AI systems remains really
hard and that's what the rest of this
talk uh will focus
on now these are not just problems you
know you see in your kind of personal
interactions with a with a chat bot
these have real implications all over
the place and that's just one example um
of this happening in
practice now I'm not saying Chad GPT is
is bad or language models are bad
because it made a mistake or two um what
I'm saying though uh and that's because
every AI system and everything we'll
talk about today will always make
mistakes what I'm saying though is that
fundamentally the monolithic nature of
language models uh makes them
particularly hard to control when we are
Building Systems to debug when they do
make mistakes and to improve uh when we
want to iterate on the development of
our systems and increasingly the way
people are tackling this as we had in
the title of the of the lecture is by
building compound AI systems so if you
haven't heard of this term before it
just means modular systems or modular
programs in which language models are
not serving as the user facing endtoend
system but they're actually playing
specialized modular roles inside this
bigger architecture
so you know a very familiar example of
that that I'm sure sort of Prior talks
discussed a lot in this in this class uh
is retrieval augmented systems so you
know instead of building a system that
takes a question like this and just
gives it to your monolithic language
model just a blackbox deep Neer Network
and basically hopes that the system does
the right thing um you might break it
down into smaller pieces where you have
a retrieval model consult a massive
corpus with the question as a search
query retrieve the topk you know most
relevant results feed those as context
to the language model and then basically
prompt the model to use the information
there and cite it in its
answer now there are lots of reasons
that might be attractive one of those is
transparency this system might still
make mistakes or it might say the right
thing but either way uh we can always
inspect sort of the trace of the system
Behavior see what it retrieved and see
why it generated what what you know the
information it did that would help us
see when it's right you know it says
something Justified based on a citation
that's factual um it could also help us
see it when it's wrong uh for example it
made uh an incorrect inference based on
a relevant piece of information or maybe
it simply retrieved something irrelevant
and extrapolated in a weird way there's
another reason this is really attractive
which is that um you know a system like
this can be a lot more efficient it has
more steps for sure um but now the
language model does not necessarily need
to know everything about old topics
because we've sort of offloaded that
knowledge and a lot of that like
basically uh step-by-step control flow
either to a knowledge base from which
we're retrieving um or to Simply a
program that is executing these steps so
we've gained a lot from having these
sort of uh this compositional
approach another another example of a
compound AI system Beyond Rag and
something slightly more sophisticated is
taking that to the next step and asking
well one of the biggest sort of powers
of language models is that they are not
limited to answering questions they've
seen exactly before they can sort of
synthesize or compose informations or at
least that's the that's just the hope um
so this is exactly what a compound AI
systems system that does multihop
reasoning or multihop retrieval
augmented generation would do it's the
fact that we can now take questions uh
and instead of simply giving them to a
dumb search engine we can ask our
language model itself to act as a module
that breaks down this question into
little pieces finds information about
each piece and then basically returns
that to the language model whose job is
to then take uh you know whatever got
retrieved and produce answers that maybe
synthesize information in a more
holistic
way what's really great about sort of
compound AI systems uh continuing that
line of thought is that we have a lot of
control as the people building this
system um you know you're not sort of
bottlenecked at the next release of a
language model whether you're the one
building it which might be unlikely or
not uh you actually have a lot of
control over the development um of your
architecture and that allows you to it
at much faster and to build systems like
this system here bin that I built near
the start of my PhD that do things that
your individual language models at that
time absolutely couldn't do another
example is to take this an even you know
another step further uh and to basically
say uh could we have these systems
generate long reports like maybe
articles with citations like a Wikipedia
page and that's where uh you know maybe
you could say something like write me an
article on the on the kar retrieval
model and a system like this which is
Storm from Stanford um could then
basically have a lot of modular
components that are at a much finer
level of granularity so it could
brainstorm uh it could uh generate
outlines it could revise these outlines
uh it could then basically ask a model
to generate questions about each part of
the outline retrieve sources uh
synthesize information in a much more
systematic way uh you know than a
simpler architecture
would and what's really great here is
that because we have sort of this
ability to compose um better scoped uh
uses of our language models we can
really iterate on the quality we get out
of these systems um so it's much easier
for a language model to you know take
information that's given to it and
synthesize something reasonable as
opposed to maybe tackle a bigger problem
of trying to sort of um remember facts
for example so by by being able to
manage all of these little compositions
we can do a lot more uh in terms of
quality and lastly uh the sort of final
uh advantage of building these types of
systems is inference time uh uh scaling
so basically uh if you have a language
model it's pretty clear at this point
that if you intelligently spend more
compute at test time so you have a
question and you're trying to sort of
Leverage The Language model maybe to
search over a large space of potential
paths for example that that's something
that can really help so an example of a
compound AI system where this really
helps here is Alpha codium uh which
basically is the system that is uh
targeted at generating code but instead
of simply asking a model to produce a
you know a piece of code it has all
these steps in which it would for
example um you know reflect on the
problem um reflect on public tests that
you know maybe exist uh for a for a
given for a given task that you have
generate various Solutions rank them
based on their performance and then
basically iterate from there and it's
not you know unintuitive that this that
type of decomposition which reflects the
way you might instruct a you know uh a
intern or a friend or something to to
approach a task like this it's not
unintuitive that that can really help
quite a bit and that's what this type of
work shows and this something that keeps
popping up in many many many
applications uh in many cases also uh
you know in task agnostic form you know
in the form of methods that basically
can scale compute um independently of a
particular task so we talked about how
amazing compound AI systems are and how
sort of they give us these five things
from quality uh to control to
transparency to inference time scaling
so they're awesome but the problem is
unfortunately we're working with highly
limited modules at the end of the day
our language models um themselves um are
extremely sensitive to how you ask them
to play these roles of these little
things you're trying to compose and
because of that under the hood these
really beautiful diagrams we looked at
they are typically implemented uh you
know and we're all guilty of this myself
included they're typically implemented
with you know thousands of tokens of of
English or some other natural language
trying to coers a language model uh to
play a to play that role of each of
these
modules and so this is something we see
across all types of tasks uh where we're
writing sort of tens of kilobytes of
strings in Json files uh trying to
Define our our language model systems
and of course if we could just do that
and then succeed in a way that is sort
of Highly portable and in a way that's
highly General maybe it's fine maybe
it's a fine price to pay uh but the
problem is that it's not uh it's not
something that will generalize or sort
of will systematically allow us to
compose these systems so the problem
here at a high level is that each of
these prompts implementing each of the
modules we looked at is sort of coupling
five different
roles so first role it's sort of trying
to uh to to cover is the role of a
signature the role of like I want a
function that's playing this this module
and essentially it's just a
specification of here are your inputs
and here's what they mean and here's
what here's the transformation I want
you to make to give me the outputs it's
also specifying the computation uh sort
of that tries to specialize this
signature uh with some kind of inference
time strategy so you might tell the
model hey please think step by step or
you might tell the model hey you're an
agent and you have these tools and you
should call these tools and when you
call them I'll intercept it I'll give
you back the response or you might say
something like you know I'll I'll
generate 10 different things and explore
all of them with some kind of reward
model for example um so these cases
we're sort of expressing a lot of that
in the prompt and in the code around the
prompt um The Prompt is also trying to
sort of couple with all of that the
computation that's well formatting all
of the inputs we want to give to this
sort of function or the signature um and
is also encapsulating the logic for how
we want to get several things and sort
of parse them and cast them to the right
types and maybe retry if they're not
really formatted properly and all that
stuff it's also on top of that
expressing well the objective you know
you're you're not just telling
uh you know you're not simply describing
what the inputs and and output behavior
is you're really also trying to encode
and your prompt a lot of information
about dos and don'ts and basically what
you're trying to maximize you know be
factual or don't hallucinate or you know
uh don't site pages that don't exist or
whatever um and so you know that's
that's essentially a different notion uh
from Simply declaring with the what what
that module is doing as we see in the
diagrams and lastly um for any given
language model as we said they are super
sensitive and these pipelines are really
complex so you're going to see in
practice that people work really hard to
sort of um CSE the model to basically do
the right thing through a lot of trial
and error in English or in some natural
language uh and maybe there's also sort
of fine tuning of the weights around
that if if you're doing a you know a
more advanced application so the bigger
picture here across these five roles is
that existing compound AI systems are
awesome they have a lot of potential to
be really modular and to sort of solve
problems we can't solve with neural
networks alone or with language models
Alone um but the problem is they're too
stringly typed if you will uh they
couple the fundamental architecture of
the system design that the developer
wants to express which nicely is the
thing we see in the diagrams we saw of
compound AI systems um they couple that
with incidental choices that are super
specific to the specific pipeline you
have or the language model Choice you've
made which are things that change all
the time so you have a pipeline that has
five pieces you go in and you want to
slightly change the objective or
introduce a six module or maybe change
the language model to a cheaper thing
that just came out that is supposed to
be as good good luck your entire
sequence of you know thousands of words
of of prompts are basically irrelevant
at that point and this is something that
really blocks adoption in practice as
well as portability of a lot of the cool
systems we we we covered where people in
industry for example could um approach
you and say well we really love that
paper um but it's clear that the prompts
there were tuned sort of and developed
with a particular data or Benchmark in
mind that's not our use case we have no
visibility or clue how you decided to
arrive at those prompts so we're
basically practically unable to use the
stuff you built so uh an argument I'll
be making today and I'll be relying on
in the rest of this lecture is that we
do know how to iteratively uh and
controllably build systems and improve
them in a modular way and that sort of
elusive concept is called programming um
so a lot of the rest of this talk will
be about sort of this ambition of what
if we could build compound AI systems as
programs right just computer code
standard python um but with fuzzy
natural language functions or natural
language modules that can learn their
behavior from data so you're basically
thinking of just writing code and then
inserting these little pieces that are
supposed to represent the boxes we saw
earlier that are sort of exhibiting
intelligent behavior and then you
specify an objective and you have the
system try to learn sort of behavior
around the natural language
specifications that you're putting
around these modules if we could do that
we could lose a lot of the problems that
we saw with existing compound AI systems
where you're not going to have to be
writing these prompts you're going to be
building a general design that could
sort of be ported from a language model
to another language model and in this
analogy the portability is sort of like
working with uh with Hardware you know
if you write a piece of code in C on a
certain CPU architecture and you move to
a different CPU architecture a good
compiler is going to take your same high
level C high level between codes and
then compile it to potentially very
different lower level uh machine code on
different architectures that makes sure
that it works so here we want to uh the
sort of the ambition that we have is
that we want to write code in higher
level uh uh higher level abstractions
that are sort of um independent as much
as possible uh of these low-level
details of how to get a language model
to do the thing you want it to do and
then we're going to build compilers U or
optimizers to take that and spit out
specific sort of uh strategies for
working on a given uh in a given
infrastructure which in this case means
a language model or other things so
these are some of the systems we saw
earlier and so you know the approach
that we will take sort of to where it's
this vision is called DSP um someone
said I think Alex said data science
python it has nothing to do with data
science it's a long story uh but DS is
declaratively self-improving
declaratively self-improving python so
it's a python but it's smarter um and
the way in which we're going to do this
is we going to say well let's define
this thing called the language model
program which is just a Python program
just a python class or function um and
in that function uh you know it's going
to take it's a function that takes
inputs in natural language maybe a
question that we want to answer uh or
maybe like a report we want to summarize
or a topic we want to generate a I don't
know an email about or something and the
output is also a natural language maybe
the answer or the report or the email or
whatever it is and maybe you know the
output could be several pieces of these
and what makes this interesting as a
function is that in the normal course of
its execution it's just kind of loops
and exceptions and go-to statements and
all the things you shouldn't use and all
that stuff but in the in the course of
its execution it's calling these
functions that are modules that are
fuzzy so it's basically making calls
like hey generate a search qu for me or
turn this natural language into SQL or
whatever it is so it's making these kind
of like high level natural language
claims which look like prompts but
they're sort of much more structured and
much shorter because they are only
expressing uh sort of the the stuff that
you need to declare like what is the
actual Behavior not how should the model
Do
It um so we have this function in which
in it in its course of execution it's
calling uh these modules and each module
is basically defined by simply a
declaration of what it should do what
inputs it takes and what outputs it
produce it produces usually that's one
liner basically in in many cases so
here's an example um of an actual sort
of simple DSP run I put before the talk
so basically you can say I want to
factchecking module you know before that
there might be like loops and exceptions
and commented out code and all sorts of
mess and then you have basically uh you
know I want to apply a chain of thoughts
strategy over this function signature
that says I want you to take a set of
claims and give me a list of booleans
that is the verdicts of you know are
these claims true or not and then I get
a module as this function I can give it
a set a list of claims and it can
basically think and then it can tell me
well the first one is true and the
second one is false right so so far this
is basically just kind of an interface
of a function that is declared you know
with natural language types we're
basically just saying you know the the
keywords here are not special but I can
understand them because I understand
English as a language model and I can
sort of see that okay the verdicts here
is is going to sort of suggest that
probably until I optimize this or learn
somehow you know this is this is a true
statement and python is not a compiled
language in standard usage so this
basically defines for us an optimization
problem uh under the hood which is
basically you're given this set of
modules in our program that your program
calls um and for every module our goal
is going to be uh to sort of basically
decide how should we take this call and
actually call a language model which
means coming up with the string that
goes into the model uh which might be a
lot more you know sophisticated or or
just very different from how looked at
the specification level we saw earlier
in the signature um the other thing we
also can control in some cases although
we're not cover a lot of that today is
well you know what are sort of the
weight settings that we want to assign
our language model you know in the sense
of if we want to fine-tune the model uh
to sort of perform better at our
task so you know the idea is now we have
this function with all these modules and
if you can give me a training set you
know of inputs to that function and
maybe some kind of hint or find a label
or some kind of metadata um I should be
able to basically try to find the
settings of the of the prompts and the
weights such that on average or you know
in expectation um some kind of metric uh
of calling the the program with modules
assigned in this way is maximized that's
the optimization problem that we will be
dealing with you know once someone uh
writes a program in an abstraction that
could support uh this type of Behavior
Uh which which is the SP now um you know
the problem here is that this is really
hard um so we don't have and we're not
asking anywhere um for you know
gradients across the system system might
generate code and execute it it might
call external tools it might run a
calculator um so we don't necessarily
know how to optimize a system like this
certainly not not directly with
gradients and we can't sort of like
cheat and try to optimize each module on
its own because we are not in general
asking for labels for every step of the
system if we were to ask for labels for
every step of the system the whole
argument about iterative development and
modularity would collapse because I
added the module and now you're asking
me to go label some data uh whereas the
ideal sort of um you know development
cycle that we want is that you're
building a system you notice a need uh
you notice a need to add a module of
some sort or you want to experiment you
just inject it you recompile you see
what happens and see if your system is
better or not so basically we can't
assume the existence of of um of labels
for each of these modules so that's a
problem because it's not obvious how to
go about sort of optimizing this and
that's one of the things we'll talk
about in the rest of these uh this slide
and let's take a concrete example here
so that the rest of this sort of is
developed in a way we can uh we can
follow so suppose that we wanted to
build this uh simple multihop retrieval
augmented generation Pipeline and have
it in visual form here although the DSP
code is basically the same um you know
it's a function that takes a question
which is a and it's going to Output an
answer which is also a string and in
that function you know the last step is
this question that we got with some
context we want to give it to a language
model in some way and basically have it
generate our answer but the question is
how do we get this context so the
multihop thing here is that we will have
a loop maybe the loop could be smarter
it could like decide when to stop or
something but for now we'll just hard
code that it goes twice and in every
iteration we'll ask our language model
to take whatever context we've built up
so far which is empty at the beginning
um generate a search query take this
query dump it into the context maybe
append it or something and then
basically we can loop again so that the
system is generating queries to seek
things that we haven't found so far um
so a question that you know is is would
come up in in this in this scope would
be something like I don't know how many
floors are in the castle that David
Gregory inherited an example I like to
use so the first qu you might ask is
well who is David Gregory um and then
you might learn that he's a Scottish guy
from I don't know the 1600s or something
and that he inherited a castle called
kenady Castle then you might ask well
how many Flo are in Canard Castle given
that the original question was trying to
seek that um and sort of that gives you
the behavior that we're seeing here in
terms of the multihop U
Behavior so that sort of visual function
can be written in DSP code as as as like
here we're not going to look at too much
code uh but this is just a module if
you're familiar with something like
pytorch or just de networks in en we're
kind of borrowing some of the syntax um
but in this module uh we're going to uh
have an initialization sort of method
that just declares the uh sub modules
that we have in our compound AI system
so we're going to have a sort of a Chain
of Thought strategy express our sort of
signature that says you take some
context you take a question and you
generate a search query and all of these
are strings so we're not telling you
they strings because that's the default
and then there's another module that
takes the same inputs or same types of
inputs and generates an answer now the
sort of part of your code that is the
actual sort of program logic is here
where you're simply just you know the
loop we saw in the last slide can sort
of be
expressed so that's the forward method
can Define the program logic that we
have we talked about signatures so they
are telling the system what the module
should do uh as opposed to working
really hard with a certain language
model as to how it should Express that
behavior and the modules as we said you
know know there are many uh sort of
strategies to spend compute uh you know
given the language model so sort of
Define a general sort of um um approach
to take a signature and actually express
it in terms of Co language model and
those sort of help uh you know uh
improve quality in many settings so
there are sort of puristic that we can
apply very similar to layers in neur
networks so I'll go sort of an a tangent
here and say like you could if you want
and this is sort of like if if if that's
this is not essential to understanding
the rest of the talk but sort of
intuitively you could think of this as
these are normally Chain of Thought or
other things just conceptual things that
you can't actually compose because the
Chain of Thought you know in the
original paper which is super cool is
basically just a bunch of prompts they
wrote for individual tasks so for
answering math questions you you write
some examples and you ask the model to
do stuff you going to apply to different
task you got write different prompts but
what we're saying here is why can't we
borrow from layers in Neo networks where
you give them Dimensions that sort of
just describe what type of types of
tensors they accept and what types of
tensors they give you um and then have
that behavior be expressed so in a
neural network architecture you could
say I want attention that takes a
following sort of vectors and gives me
those other vectors and sort of you
could have that or you could have an RNN
do this or a linear layer or convolution
or whatever so similarly here we're
asking why can't we take these uh sort
of inference strategies and make them
General in a sort of meta programming
sense and sort of Define these you know
Define them over these signatures uh and
have them Express that behavior in a
general way that can be composed a aome
so the question here is this is the
abstraction this is how you write the
program how do you actually sort of what
are we supposed to do so this actually
works as a system because it looks
pretty to me it looks pretty maybe not
to everybody but to me this looks really
elegant but the question is how do we
take this and actually sort of give you
a system that you know you could
actually deploy and that you're happy
with and you could iterate on and all
that so iterating on it is easy because
you could come in and like add one more
module add an if statement throw an
exception and Gadget and you can do all
kinds of things but the question is
really how do we uh sort of translate
these strategies with signatures into
actual prompts under the hood so you can
take this here and the very first step
is pretty trivial although it's
important to do it right uh which is
that sort of internally we can sort of
translate this into a basic prompt one
that will not necessarily work really
well or anything there's no guarantees
about it um through sort of buil-in
adapters and predictors so predictors
are just this guy which is basically
another module that has some logic
inside and really what it does
fundamentally is it adds one more output
here another field here that asks for
reasoning um but the adapter is going to
take this guy and is going to say well
you know depending on how you implement
it or which which one you choose or
whatever um it's going to say well I
have a model here that's maybe a chat
model or maybe it's an instruct model
and I want to sort of format these
fields in a certain way just to
Kickstart the process so it's going to
basically give us a basic prompt under
the hood that's something like hey give
a field context and question you know
give me a query and here is the format
you want to follow because I want to be
able to parse the stuff that you give me
nothing about this is going to work
particularly well but it's is going to
get us
started now the role of optimizers on
top of this which is sort of a different
component many algorithms we'll discuss
um is to take this initial prompt and to
take the whole program in which there
are many of these modules many of these
prompts and to sort of look at them as
parameters or look at them as like you
know having a lot of variables that we
can Tinker with and figure out how to
maximize sort of the metric that we saw
in the in the objective we wanted to
maximize a few slides
ago um so we might start here and maybe
the system would perform and you know at
37% accuracy on a given you know strict
metric so the actual quality might be a
bit higher but you let's say this is
something that has uh you know we're
trying to sort of have a metric that's
highly precise but has somewhat lower
recal um and we might then basically
just ask hey I like the MEO V2 Optimizer
in DSP much the same way as in a neural
network sort of situation you might say
I like Adam or I like I don't know RMS
prop you give it some data you give it
the program you give it a metric and you
ask it to do a good job and it spits out
you know a better prompt maybe fancier
instructions and gives it some examples
uh sort of and sticks them into this
into the prompt of one of the modules or
several of the modules such that the
quality is you know substantially higher
so you know on a certain real task sort
of uh instead of tweaking you know 2,000
tokens of prompts that look something
like this and you know at the end of the
day sort of getting an accuracy like 33%
with a certain model from open AR
um we can sort of explore a much larger
design space and get higher scores in
interesting ways you know through these
compositions so let's look at at sort of
a results table here on the multihop
question answering task that we've been
sort of using as a running
example the simplest thing you could do
in in dsy or sort of just when you're
thinking about a compound AI system is
the trival is a trivial compound AI
system that's not actually compound uh
in which you just ask the system to take
the input and just predict the output
and you don't bother optimizing it so if
you do that so we did this a while back
this is you know exactly a year ago uh
this result um you can get GPT 3.5 to
perform you know sort of at this at this
level and a llama 2 model sort of is a
little bit uh
behind but you could say well we know
that a decomposition like rag could help
especially that this is a factual task
we're answering questions um so we could
do a rag system and the interesting
thing is well we could also try you know
running one of the optimizers that we'll
talk about in a minute and what you
start seeing is the cool thing that
already you know a small model um can
start to perform better than a larger
model uh with a sort of simpler
architecture or even with a
sophisticated architecture without
optimization but the large model can
preserve a lot of its Advantage uh here
as well now you could iterate on your
program and build a multihop compound AI
system and there you can see that you
know with optimization you can boost the
quality quite a bit with large models as
well as sort of with open models and
with more recent models all these
numbers are substantially higher
nowadays
now what's really cool uh although we're
not going to be able to spend a lot of
time on that is the very same program
that we wrote here which is giving us
all of these results across models and
across sort of optimiz optimization uh
decisions that we can make we can also
use optimizers that sort of update the
weights that do fine tuning essentially
uh a whole Space of reinforcement
learning is open in front of us um and
we can get very small models to sort of
um imitate these bigger ones and we can
have like a model beneath a billion
parameters that's like many years old T5
is I don't know 2019 uh score
competitively in fact better than you
know uh close sort of at that at that
time Frontier models uh sort of um uh
on uh on uh the the given task so
question is uh that we will be looking
at over the rest of the lecture is what
are the what is the space of optimizers
like and what are the interesting
choices we can make and what works and
what doesn't um so in general uh there
are too many DSi optimizers to discuss
today they vary in how they tune the
prompts and weights in a program but
there's actually kind of a general
pattern that you can see in many of them
in most of them um the first thing is in
general as we saw earlier you're going
to for every module just guess an
initial prompt and this is actually
something in DP happening outside the
optimizer in general it's happening
through what we call the adapter that
just sort of like takes your signature
and makes a sort of a deterministic
construction most of the time
deterministic sometimes with the
language model um of what the initial
prompt should look
like and then the next thing we'll do is
rejection sampling so we're going to
take the inputs that you gave us in the
sort of in in your problem specification
maybe we'll raise the temperature of the
language model uh maybe we'll plug in a
large model uh maybe we just keep the
system simple um and then we'll
basically run through your program with
these basic prompts to sort of try to
collect trajectories throughout all of
these steps um that lead your metric to
sort of assign High scores so you've
basically given us this program you've
given us a bunch of inputs and you've
given us a metric that can assess when
things are good or bad maybe it's just
checking if the answer is correct or
maybe it's asking a language model or
maybe asking a DSP program to sort of
evaluate the system on the rubric or any
number of other design choices that
you're allowed to sort of you know
experiment with um so we're going to use
those in order to basically start to
collect traces um of every module or
examples of every module of its inputs
and outputs when they're chained
together sort of uh lead to high scores
through your through your
metric we can then use these examples in
a bunch of different ways to update the
modules of your program the simplest
thing you could think of is if you have
examples of every module that have sort
of proven to work in the past it doesn't
mean that they're correct but it means
that maybe there's some hope that
they're useful and the simplest thing
you could do is try to stick them into
the prompt as demonstrations as examples
that just say hey when I got this input
and I did this Behavior it seemed to
work pretty well in the past um and you
know once you do that maybe you can
actually start exploring well which of
the examples and can we try to be
intelligent about this or not which of
these examples that we just built uh can
be useful um for actually taking this
module plugging it into a program and
getting the program to work better on a
bunch of other
examples another thing you can do is you
could try to sort of induct instructions
if you have a lot of examples of a
module you have a better sense of
understanding of what the module should
do uh and when that leads to good
behavior and when that doesn't lead to
good behavior and you can give those to
a language model and ask basically you
know what is the thing that we're trying
to ask here and I thing to keep in mind
is that in all of these cases language
models are being used to build these
components but we're not assuming that
language models are good at it language
models are going to give you 20
different things and you know 19 of them
are going to suck but because we can try
so many and we can explore that space to
varying level levels of intelligence we
can basically strike gold fairly often
and find the combination of these pieces
that leads uh leads to better prompts in
a way that is basically independent of a
particular setup that you have so you
can adjust your program or your language
model choices rerun the system and and
you know have optimization
happen and then of course you could run
you know once you've build these
examples if you have enough of them you
know you could basically uh fine-tune
the model on them or do reinforcement
learning uh depending on how you're
sampling uh or do you know preference
fine tuning and other other approaches
there as
well so you know there are various
papers uh that we have that explore
these types of strategies the two ones I
I I sort of requested in the in the uh
suggested readings where uh sort of the
one introducing Meo and the one
introducing a strategy uh for combining
prompt optimization and fine tuning and
the rest of this talk will be
about the MEO the MEO paper so before we
discuss Meo um you know this stuff this
is sort of we discussed a sequence of
abstractions and sort of at a high level
how a set of algorithms that we call
optimizers take programs written with
these abstractions and sort of give you
compound AI systems that work well but
you're expressing in a way that is sort
of more portable and I think a lot more
elegant um but what's cool here is that
these things actually work pretty well
in practice so a few months ago
University of Toronto researchers
participated in this Meda competition
against 15 other you know schools and
Industry uh groups and whatnot um and
they won the competition in sort of
building question answering systems for
medical um you know domains by uh 20% by
20 point margin against the next best
system and you know one of the biggest
differences between that their approach
and others is they use thepi to sort of
Express their system and they use dpy
prompt optimizers they used an early
version of Meo in fact uh um to to
achieve this result on three different
you know they sort of won three
different settings of that competition
which had three settings
um a month later uh Folks at the
University of Maryland uh who also sort
of whose lead author um sort of is
responsible or is leading this uh
prompting guide with I think like tens
of thousands of users or or more um sort
of worked on a suicide detection task
that I believe he got from industry they
wrote a really nice paper about it he
worked for 20 hours uh they documented
all of the sort of prompting strategies
that he explored for building this
system for suicide detection basically
it's a glorified classifier um and you
know he documented all the approaches he
tried the prompts he explored and then
you know in his words he applied DSP in
10 minutes and it sort of outperformed
his best system by 40 to
50% so they have a really nice paper
about this from the University of medine
and then you know it has enabled sort of
a lot of State of-the-art systems um
from path uh for training retrieval
models where we're optimizing prompts
that synthesize the data uh that sort of
is used to train to train small models
uh under the hood I think there's a lot
of sort of uh interesting ideas there um
to uh AA which is a system for
classifying with language models uh when
you have like 50 labels but 10,000
classes which I thought was an
impossible thing just didn't make sense
for the language models uh but Carl
built this in dpy and sort of showed
that it's possible um and then storm
which generates Wikipedia articles um
from a topic that you give it
so now sort of having see some of these
examples uh let's uh sort of uh look
more closely at the paper optimizing
instructions and demonstrations for
multi-stage language model programs uh
by co-first authors Christa Opel long
and Michael Ryan at at Stanford and a
lot of the slides that I have next sort
of uh are are sort of uh borrowed from
Krista and
Michael uh you know in the dsy
work so the problem setting just to
restate it is we are given a bunch of
inputs examples of a task so maybe
questions let's say and we are given
that you know the developer built
language model program of the S we
discussed earlier just a function with a
bunch of modules uh expressed in natural
language um and you know each of them
might look like this so you know we
looked at the context question give me
an answer any it's just kind of just
trying to do this
Behavior Uh I don't know if example is
very useful at that point but the
victorians is a documentary series
written by an author born in what year
so you know maybe you want to answer
that 1950 by have looking at context
that you received in the earlier Loop
that we have
here we're also asking for a metric um
some metrics you know by Nature require
labels like for example here if we know
that the answer is 1950 we don't need
labels for the whole thing but you know
if we know the answer is 1950 evaluation
is easy um other times maybe the metric
is like I don't actually know what the
answer is but I want to get answers that
are grounded in the context that got
retrieved because I trust the context
and if the answer is grounded in it and
is relevant then that probably means is
correct uh that's a different metric
that does not need labels um so there
are sort of a very large scope of things
but it's really important that you sort
of explicitly Define what is it that
you're trying to maximize um and once
you've done that you don't do this sort
of as part of your prompts you do this
in a way that's independent of your
program um so that you can explore sort
of along both axes uh pretty modularly
that's something important that you
should keep in mind and that abstraction
sort of really forces you to do that
okay yeah so the goal is to give us an
optimized language model program Prime
uh by in the case of the in the
optimizers we look at next we're going
to keep the weights Frozen in fact we'll
assume we don't have access to them um
instead we are going to uh optimize the
instructions so like the descriptions of
the task that goes to the model as well
as the
demonstrations uh which are sort of
these few shot examples that just show
the model in the prompt you know here
are some inputs and here's the
corresponding Behavior we saw in the
outputs that seem to work well in the
past some assumptions that we are making
is that we don't want to um assume any
access to you know log probabilities or
model weights um because you want to
iterate sort of fast you want to work in
in natural language space with apis that
are high level we have a lot of work
where we relax this assumption and we
look it into fine tuning um but that's
sort of uh you know uh and actually
there's we have work that shows you
really need both uh to get the best
performance in many cases but if you had
to pick one prompt optimization tends to
be more powerful um we also assume no
intermediate metrics or labels as we
said earlier and we want to be very
budget conscious so we want to minimize
two things we don't want to ask you for
a lot of example inputs of your task
because it's hard to create inputs
although technically inputs is the
easiest thing to scale because you can
build a demo and then put in front of
your friends and then you have a lot of
inputs when they ask questions you know
if if your privacy policy allows you to
do that um but we don't we don't want to
sort of ask for a lot of input so maybe
want 50 or couple hundred uh you know
not tens of thousands for example um and
we don't want to call the language model
too many times because it takes time or
is expensive Etc so these are the
assumptions that we want to sort of or
the constraints that we have uh on this
problem now there are two types of
problems we want to tackle in general um
the first is that well what's a prompt
like is this long sort of combinatorial
string and it's you know anything really
goes it's it's all valid so how do you
even Explore the space especially if you
don't have gradients and if you don't
want to call the model too many times
seems basically hopeless um and the
second problem is well if you have so
many modules which is really this is
kind of an I think an even worse one
when you combine the two together is if
you have so many modules you know and
you're changing things all over the
place how do you know what is leading to
Improvement or what's sort of hurting
because these pieces interact you know
you might improve the prompt in one part
locally but actually hurts because the
other part made an assumption about the
output of the first part and now you
sort of have to account for these types
of uh blame
assignment so I'll sort of cover three
methods uh this is not exhausted by any
stretch of the imagination but these
three are sort of like really good sort
of uh different methods of of tackling
this problem so the simplest thing you
could do in my opinion you know you know
is is at least at least for the value it
gives you is to sort of bootstrap or
self-generate few short examples by
running a dumb version of your program
to build examples and then to plug them
in and to search over that space and the
cool thing is you can iterate that you
can take the better program build even
better examples you know build ensembles
of them use larger models to build ex
it's a very sort of large compositional
space but in a sort of simplest form um
you know you have the program you take a
training input you basically say like
I'll execute the python in here some of
these are just normal python you know
return statements or Loops or I don't
know like you call code executor or
whatever but some of them are modules
and so we sort of they are special
they're we're sort of tracking them um
and and tracing their inputs and outputs
and basically we say well you know these
things are generating sour queries and
generating answ and if the metric at the
end ends up liking the answer and tells
me that's good well that whole
trajectory of like inputs and outputs
seems interesting enough to keep it
around now this can be a sort of a set
of demonstrations of all our modules and
we can simply basically say what if we
take those we plug into them we plug
them into the modules of our program and
then we could do in the simplest case
just a random search take a kind of a
bag of of our subset of these
demonstrations plug them into the
respective you know three or four
prompts and
take that run it on a small validation
set maybe could be try to be smart about
sort of how you're doing that evaluation
and then basically look at that score
and try to maximize that score so that's
sort of like the you know I think the
the the the the simplest successful
thing you could
try a different approach is to look into
the prompt optimization literature not
for language model programs but for
language model calls and those folks
sort of have a lot of Rich sort of uh
you know uh concurrent sort of research
but under much stronger constraints so
in the prompt optimization literature
which is you know I mean these things
are sort of of course morphing closer
together but they started pretty
separately um you are assuming that you
have labels so you have inputs and
outputs and it's one prompt that's the
whole system there's no like program
involved um and you're assuming that
sort of there's this little part like
you know a one liner somewhere that you
want to search over the space of this
sort of exploration is very large people
do all sorts of things from you know
gradient based exploration to other
sorts of forms of reinforcement learning
and all types of stuff but one approach
that's really cool and really high level
is called optimization through prompting
um from Deep Mind and the way that works
is basically they want to plug in a
little prefix at the end of The Prompt
sort of to just get the model on the
right track and so you know they start
with think step by step but they want to
end up at the end with like I don't know
take a deep breath and think step by
step um and they show that that could
actually help some models you know do a
lot better it's a much smaller sort of
scope but it's an interesting space of
what to explore and we want to sort of
see if we could take this and apply it
to language model programs with the
weaker assumptions we have so uh you
know the way opro works for a single
prompt is they basically go to a model
and say here is the original thing give
me 10 variants or 100 variants and let
me basically just evaluate all of them
on a little CER evaluation set and let
me basically um look at which ones work
best maybe the top 10 go back to the
model and say Here's the top 10 here is
how well they performed give me more and
the idea now is the model might be smart
enough to say I see some patterns
between the successful things and the
unsuccessful instructions that I can
sort of do essentially a form of um you
know you might call that I don't know uh
you know basically mutating mutating
these these uh these instructions and
and I can basically try them again and
repeat this process so that's the the
the opro approach so how could you take
sort of opro and naively apply it to a
language model program well the simplest
thing I think is uh coordinate Ascent so
what that means is uh and we're not
going to spend too much time here I
don't know if the figure is big enough
uh but you know let's say you have two
modules the simplest thing you could do
is basically go to the model generate a
lot of these proposals plug one at a
time keeping the other one sort of fixed
uh keeping the other modules uh fixed at
the at the initial instruction evaluate
all 10 approaches and then basically see
which one worked best and maybe freeze
it and sort of repeat for optimizing the
next stage and it can sort of loop uh
through this process um of of
optimization the problem is this is
horrendously expensive because you know
every time you're exploring optimizing
one module you're sort of running the
whole program uh while freezing the
other modules and you're making this big
greedy assumption that the best sort of
uh choice at any given stage is going to
be useful uh once you freeze it and try
to optimize the rest of the parts you're
not co-optimizing uh these
pieces it's very expensive and actually
doesn't even work that
well a different approach here would be
uh to to give up an assumption or to
sort of make an assumption so you could
give up on the Assumption of explicit
credit assignment you don't really care
uh to figure out sort of fixing all
variables and changing one at a time you
could just ask the models to generate
prompts for every stage all at once and
Sort of hope that that process converges
in a nice place or you could go to the
model and say actually it's a bit of a
harder task it's a bit of a harder ask
but here is the sequence of all prompts
of modules and I want you to propose you
know new prompts for all of the other
modules and you could try to do it
jointly which of course has the risk of
potentially confusing the model it's a
much harder task but it um you know is
is is something that let's say um you
know with with an oracle language model
it's strictly more powerful by far now
if you want this whole thing to work
well in a language model program it is
really important that you're not myopic
about optimization so you don't just
look at a signature just saying generate
a search quity and you you know the user
didn't say search quid the user just
said quy is it a SQL quitty a search quy
for Google for retrieval model that is
you have offline these things are
different and sort of you at the mercy
of the quality of the proposals you're
getting so you might as well try to make
sure that they're
contextualized um sort of appropriately
with respect to the uh program you have
so that's this notion of you want the
proposals to be grounded so sort of in a
traditional prompt optimization setting
there is the history of the prior steps
how we got here what things we tried how
well they performed and then there is
maybe a training set of explicit
examples that you sort of got from the
user because your whole system sort of
doesn't have any missing pieces it's
just input and
output so um you know we have this
intuition that to take this and to sort
of generalize it to language model
programs uh it would be very useful to
provide a lot of contextual information
about the program setup that we have um
and so the first thing is because we
don't have these training input output
labels for every module in general um or
for any modules in many cases we can
start plugging in the bootstrap demos
that we looked at earlier so we you know
they're basically as good um you know
for all we know um and they seem to be
successful when you're doing bootstrap
you shot so maybe we could just plug
them in as the examples that we'll use
for constructing these prompts now that
by itself is gives you a lot because you
could sort of see what works and
potentially what doesn't um but and
here's a sort of an you know an example
of a question you want to generate a
search query um and sort of the
reasoning that the model generates when
it's building the search query that that
It produced that eventually sort of led
to a trajectory that was successful um
on a certain
question the other thing is well you
know you want to give the model sort of
an understanding of the whole task so it
would be useful if the of the if the
model building your instructions could
see a summary of the data set um that
we're playing with um and so this is you
know sort of an example of that where
the model basically says looks like this
is on the uh multihop data set consists
of factual trivia style questions across
a wide range of topics Etc so you
basically have a component that builds
up the summary by you know essentially
some sort of uh you could think of it as
a map reduce over the data set with the
language model um and then an
interesting thing that you know you
might want to ground your system in is
well could it actually see the whole
pipeline so it understands the role of
every module in it and this basically
works by literally taking the sort of
you know inspecting the code that you
have for a program and then giving it to
the language model that understands the
syntax and basically it builds a
representation of the uh you know uh the
the program here in natural language
that says hey we have a program that
appears to be designed to answer complex
questions by retrieving and processing
information from multiple sources in
this case it's set up for two hops
Etc and you know the module in this
program is responsible for generating a
search query Etc
and you might also uh sort of try to
maximize sort of the diversity of the
stuff here by just sampling a random
instruction that's you know that from
the standard literature and just kind of
plugging those in um for your uh
proposer so like hey don't be afraid to
be creative or all these things we could
just take them out of the loop you know
you don't have to write them we will
write them once and then we can
basically reuse them for building these
uh these systems so we just discussed
sort of extending uh optimization uh
proposing with language models um so uh
We've covered sort of two two general
strategies for optimization here one is
building examples and searching over
them uh the second is giving the model
as much grounding as possible in the
language model program and um asking it
to propose instructions that we can sort
of uh iterate over you know through
learning from the previous attempts and
then the last approach here is going to
be a little bit different where our goal
is to optimize both the instructions and
the few shot examp
but in an efficient way uh of of dealing
with credit assignment the intuition
here is language models are not
particularly good yet at uh sort of
dealing with crit assignment themselves
um but because we're working with all of
these sort of spaces of discrete
proposals like a lot of instructions or
a lot of examples that we're building uh
we could actually borrow a lot of
intuition from the literature on
hyperparameter optimization um and we
can sort of build what is called a
surrogate model uh a model that is
basically um optimized to predict the
quality of uh any configuration um
possible of our system and that we can
use to uh sample sort of uh proposals
for the entire system that we can
actually test so Meo uh the MEO
Optimizer Works in three steps first
thing is it bootst demonstrations of the
task we've explained what that means um
it builds candidate instructions um
using a language model program inside
the optimizer that has all these pieces
we looked at earlier like the summarizer
the language model program you know uh
uh you know describer all these all
these little
pieces and um you know that handles this
form of credit assignment here by
relying on just a simple probabilistic
model from the hyper parameter
optimization
literature so what we have here is a
language model program with two modules
and in every module we have essentially
two bulky parameters one is what's the
string describing the task which is the
instruction
and we get a basic one from the adapter
that we discussed earlier and then no
examples at first but this is the list
that we can learn sort of uh as a bunch
of these input output
examples and that fact that we've done
the bootstrapping and the candidate
proposal in a grounded way means that we
can basically start exploring this
discreete space of what is the right
combination across these modules of
instructions and of sets of examples or
lists of examples in each module that
would lead to the highest quality and of
course we can try all of them so we're
going to rely on this ban Optimizer to
sort of basically um help us uh give us
an acquisition function that allows us
to sort of like make good guesses as to
which combinations we should try once we
pick a pick a com a combination we can
plug it into a version of the program
and then basically evaluate it on a mini
batch of the data set that we have on
the validation set that we have so maybe
the data set has like 200 examples we
could sample 30 of them get a score and
then go back with that score let's say
75% 50% whatever and feed it back to
update the sort of the surrogate model
that we have so it's like hey if this is
the set of combinations I chose that got
gets me I think 50% I think because well
depends on the random sample in the mini
batch um so in the future you know we're
trying to sort of uh uh get an
acquisition function that sort of has a
one or you know let's say a property
like I I would like to get the most
promising uh Improvement uh in in future
proposals and there are of course many
sorts of such choices you could make and
we can sort of repeat this this process
and trials um until um we sort of uh
find a really good combination at the
end of the
day and what's happening here is that
this thing gets smarter over time so the
combinations of proposes tend to go up
um sort of over time as opposed to say
random search where you're just trying
combinations so how do these things
compare uh we looked earlier at a slide
that had results sort of with like
pretty powerful optimizers with like yes
optimizing or like just using the offthe
Shelf thing we also looked at the
results sort of with people writing
prompts by their own hand but it's also
sometimes instructive to try to think of
like ways of benchmarking these
different optimizers against each other
it's actually really hard and it's a
place where we need more contributions
because you want to build tasks that are
representative tasks that are hard not
overfit by given language models but
where you also can sort of build
interesting and realistic compound AI
systems that we can sort of um optimize
and explore um so an attempt at this is
Lang probe language model program
Benchmark um that uh sort of has these
tasks so like multihop stuff
classification inference
whatever and you know some of them have
two modules some have four modules some
have one
module so here are some sort of initial
kind of part of the of the test set
results on a bunch of these tasks um and
we're looking at optimizing instructions
only uh through we looked at sort of
module level Oo we discussed before
without grounding and with grounding and
then zero shot me Pro does not allowed
to use examples but only uses
instructions and the first thing that
jumps at you is that well you know on
average optimizing instructions compared
to like using a you know basic kind of
adapter can help quite a bit so you know
can get a few points here or uh you know
a bunch of points there can get some
nice BMP there uh sometimes it overfits
to the training set if it's really small
and it's actually worse um but in
General it really does struggle with a
lot of these tasks to optimize prompts
alone instructions Alone um and it's not
really obvious which of these wins if
you look into optimizing with
demonstrations that picture is pretty
different like you can already get you
know 10o jumps um several Point jumps
here uh several here as well you know
overfits here um and it seems that
instructions are actually quite powerful
um and you know here you can get very
large gains as well and the interesting
thing is when you look under the hood at
sort of this process of just random
search over bootstrap demonstrations
that the system generated um it's wild
how much they vary you have stuff that's
worse uh here than the initial sort of
zero shot approach but you have stuff
sort of on the frontier that's way
better and it's really interesting what
you know all of these were generated in
the same way um by running the the
program and basically doing rejection
sampling so it is interesting to see
like how big of a difference uh sort of
they can make when you plug them into
the program and the last thing is well
you could take me Pro which does few
shot instruction optimization both
together um and you can get sort of the
best results you know quite often most
of the time with with some nice jumps
across various pieces of these um an
interesting thing is well you know
optimizing examples tends to be a winner
but there's sort of patterns where you
can spot that focusing on instruction
optimization is actually leading to more
visible improvements uh which is
basically cases where the original
basically cases where the task has this
property of like a conditional um you
know uh pattern where seeing one example
doesn't actually teach you the whole
pattern or seeing two examples doesn't
teach you the whole pattern because
there are sort of more cases than you
can cover with just examples or the kind
of the uh precise threshold or the
precise kind of region in which a rule
applies is not clear from examples by
themselves so kind of concluding here um
and maybe opening for questions more
explicitly since they're open anyway um
sort of just some set of lessons on what
you might call natural language
programming which is sort of what these
Set uh what this set of abstractions in
dpy allow us to do um a big lesson uh
not to forget compound AI systems is
that programs can be a lot more accurate
more controllable and more transparent
than using deep Neer networks alone
models Alone um and that we sort of just
need the cative program you don't need
to sit down and write sorts of 10,000
token sequence of five prompts um you
can really write 10 lines of code just
Express an objective and pick an
Optimizer and run this thing on your
favorite language model um and the high
level optimizers can bootstrap you know
examples for prompts or propose
instructions and explore that space and
that they're pretty bad at any
individual proposal on average but you
can sort of uh run a large scale search
on this that does actually find things
that in in some cases in many cases uh
sort of outperform the stuff you you can
do by hand but the real power here is
because you're freed sort of from the
choices of of how do I tune each module
you can explore the space of compound AI
systems more directly where you're
getting a lot of value from iterating on
the modules You're Building how they're
connected together um you know what is
the exact right objective that I want to
maximize in many cases it's not obvious
um etc etc so dsy makes it possible to
approach this sort of natural language
programming by sort of yanking out uh
handrim prompts and giving us these this
notion of signatures um throwing away
prompting techniques and inference time
strategies um that are sort of really
fuzzy and you know you know what is a I
don't know what is a Chain of Thought
really uh and giving you actual sort of
predictors uh you can compose as modules
that can take your signatures and sort
of apply in a metaprogramming sense the
strategy on top um manual prompt
engineering you throw that away and you
sort of work with optimized uh programs
where tuning the instructions uh or the
weights sort of in a given uh strategy
and this is something that's sort of
being widely used in production and in
open source everything is at ds. a
including links to all the papers I
discussed or didn't discuss uh so it's
used a jet blue data bricks Walmart
VMware repet Haze laughs you know
Sephora Moody and other stuff you can
sort of find a nice list of public uh
facing use cases people that are sort of
fine going on the record uh sort of to
learn what people are actually doing
with it this and it's a really great way
actually to learn of like not just what
people are doing with dpy but like what
kinds of compound AI systems are getting
actually deployed and sort of who's
deploying them and how are they
optimizing them many of these folks sort
of go on podcasts and describe how
they're optimizing their systems for I
don't know law firms or other things um
yeah so this is sort of a nice uh great
folks and in the open source Community
uh cool collaborators that sort of make
all the stuff possible and uh you know
you could pip install DSP and get
started uh right now
just to conclude key lessons on
optimization in natural language um in
many cases in isolation nothing seems to
be building good examples of the task
automatically what we call bootstrapping
um seems to be this notion of show don't
tell but on tasks where there are these
conditional rules that are sort of
scoped in hard to to detect ways
optimizing instructions seems powerful
and I should make it super clear that
the biggest coolest thing in dspi is
that we've isolated signature from
optimizers from adapters from you know
metrics and basically and from inference
time strategies and that you can iterate
on any of these four or five things uh
independently and compose with everyone
else so all of the programs that exist
right now if you decide to build an RL
based prompt Optimizer you know or if
you decide to introduce an inference
time strategy as a predictor everybody
could just like you know change one line
in their code and then you know you
could see boost across the entire set of
you know use cases that exist out there
if you do it well
um and you know there are sorts of
tricks that make this work that we've
discussed here all right so actually I
had this slide and I like to use this
slide um I you know but right before the
talk or or the lecture someone told me
you know uh many of the other lectures
and maybe I'm counted with that uh you
know proudly but sort of are from sort
of large closed laps that don't publish
they're certainly not academics
certainly not anymore and they seem to
be leading all the progress and whatnot
and so so I really want to say that like
you know a big goal of dpy sort of a
meta goal is to enable open research to
again lead uh AI progress and open
research here has a lot of advantages
for us in terms of like you know uh why
we'd want that to be the case it's not
part of the scope of the stock um but
I'll tell you how this DSP really makes
a difference in this in this space uh
and it's to basically uh show that that
progress is really going to come through
modularity so we're not asking people to
sort of figure out sort of how to fund
you know billion dollar runs uh in
isolation or these ad hoc tricks that
sort of you apply and then you know two
weeks later the model changes and it's
not really very relevant anymore but
instead sort of we've sort of outlined
this space that I hope I convinced you
uh of is you know of basically how do
you Scope uh out your programs well how
do you develop General uh inference time
strategies that act as predictors that
anyone could apply to their signatures
and how we can devise new optimizers
that could allow to any could apply to
any of these programs that sort of uh
give us systems that are stronger than
the sort of the sum of their parts if
you will um and you know through that I
hope that a lot of open research and
optimizers predictors modules and
whatnot can sort of lead to the type of
progress we we saw with neuron networks
where people you know different people
developed attention uh Transformers
convolution and other things in a way
that is highly distributed and was
obviously incredibly successful uh as
opposed to a you know maybe the way in
which maybe we iterate on large language
models in a closed way now