um Hello thank you all for joining CS uh
25 Transformers today uh for today's
talk we have Ming ding a research
scientist at jeu AI based in Beijing he
obtained his bachelor's and doctoral
degrees at tingua University and he does
research on multimodal generative models
and pre-training Technologies um he has
LED or participated in the research work
Works about multimodal generative models
such as Cog View and Cog video and
multimodal understanding models such as
Cog uh VM and Cog agent uh for today's
attendance the attendance form is up on
the course website and if you have any
questions ask them through slido s l d o
and for the code you just have to input
cs25 um thank you Ming for today's talk
and I'm going to pass it off to
you thank you for the instructors of
cs25 to is very happy to gave a talk in
Stanford University about multimodality
in training and uh uh actually I have
checked the uh all the previous talks in
cs25 and uh they are really diverse
topics someone share the intuition in
their research about PR training someone
shared recent Works about maybe M Moe
and some other
technical uh actually I'm working in a
uh large language model company in China
and our company working on print
training and uh maybe there's lots of
different area uh from a large langage
model and
multi modality model and generative
model diffusion and uh tatto Speech
something like that so uh I Le all the
multimodality model research in J AI so
I will uh share lots of different topics
in in in this talk um some some of them
may be not very familiar to you so uh
yeah it's okay but you can uh get more
information of the the area uh
yeah I will talk about several aspects
of Transformers and I will generally
follow the history of large language
model and say why are we here it's about
large language model introduction and
history uh and how did we get here it's
about the some practical techniques for
training large lar langage models and
what are we working on it's about the
last one year uh the real language
models and other techniques in the uh
papers of all the uh V language model
community and finally I will talk about
the some possible and valuable direction
for research in multimodality
okay okay
well uh I will share three
moments uh I think the most important
three moments in the development of
language
model uh the first moment is called Bo
moment actually I get I got into the
area at this moment it's very uh honored
that I'm the first
among the first group of people who
publish paper on the next year ACL when
B came out and at that
time since is is we don't really know
what is language modeling
so at that time nearly all the people
talking
about uh how can we get a better
self-supervised method for an option
uh at that time a common opinion is mask
language model is just
for is is good at understanding the the
TX and GPT the auto regressive model is
better for tax generations and T5
maybe can U can do the B but is
redundant and that's true but uh uh
nowadays we are we will say that
gbt and has now uh nearly
uh s buet all the NP problem uh uh is
some sometimes the SC changes and we
will back from that time time point and
know how the language model change
and how we got more and more knowledge
about language model so at that time the
we I'm also among one of them who want
to develop a new self supervise my
learning method for
option we uh publish paper called glm
and we want to unify the board The Mask
language model and autoing model and uh
um T yeah uh in decoder only style the
actually the method is very simple we
just uh select a sequence a part of the
sequence and uh only do auto auto
regressive modeling during this sequence
so if this we select The Mask
area uh as all the sequence it become a
GPT and part of them it become board so
that's a method we F we found very
efficient and because we clean is like a
b is about 15% of mask area and they
perform better than b between TR as a
GPT perform as the same as GPT it's
quite um uh
pring but uh there's
a uh the the the second moment I think
is very important is the gpt3 movement
it tell us the scaling law is very
important
so you can design different
architectures Define different laws
different uh uh selfis task and
different method to schedule different
models but uh the
performance maybe uh has some upper
bound but if you add more compute you
can get a a guaranteed the performance
Improvement You can predict the result
uh complexity
uh based on
the based on the fitted Cur
so uh at that time the language modeling
has become more and more
engineering uh if if you have find a
very good points you train a language
model if you want to scale
it uh you and uh your boss give you uh
four times or Mons uh you can buy four
times the compute you just assign the uh
compute for more
parameters or uh training more tokens
this is this is uh called scaling low
and you they they tell you how how you
can assign different potential of of
your monies
so so uh at that time
uh you don't really the language model
don't really need some maybe uh
architecture Innovation
or as uh algorithm Innovation so has
become a engineering
scene and uh the third moment I think
which is more more important uh is
called Charing PPT moment at that moment
it tell us a very important fact is Task
adaptation is cheap and
what what is very important is the
knowledge from PR
training this is very B lesson so I have
told you that at that time we design
different
losses uh different architect PES but
the one some some of the pro the the aim
of design different losses is to perform
different tasks for example uh the
autographing model cannot fill in the
blank in the sequence but glm and BR can
so we uh use different point training
task but
uh uh currently we know that the task
adaptation is very cheap you just need
to F tune your language model as the
final as the final period what the the
only important thing is your PR train PR
training losss uh the the left figure is
uh from instruct GPT uh it's uh it's
actually the paper about chat gbt and
how can we align a PR model to a chat
model it told that uh the alignment can
give a very huge Improvement on human
preference compared to the original
printr language model and the right
figure is actually a recent paper in our
company uh it's is tell us a very
important uh fact and maybe it's
intuitive
uh the fact is the
downstream the performance of Downstream
task is only related to the
loss to the loss of tring yeah and it's
not directly relevant to the model size
which means if a large model
which uh uh where very high loss because
of leak of training and a small model we
train more and to reach the same level
of loss they performed exactly the same
in the downstream tasks so
the soall emergent ability and some
other maybe
uh uh ability uh strange rumors are not
true actually not the ability is not not
from the number of parameters of
language model is actually uh from uh
only relevant to the loss of your
language model so all the language model
become a game of curl feeding this is
actually the the the current uh the
current uh situation or language model
research so uh there's also some
technical details of lar Lang model uh
even way uh we know it's not cting but
there's a lot of important
things uh so we back from the some
Basics and uh talk about the Transformer
the Transformer
architecture uh a very interesting thing
is the most important
improvements nowadays are still from the
the the first author of the Transformer
paper the norm and maybe from his other
papers so uh actually the the real
innovation in
architectur is very small uh I can
summar summarize some
common uh adaptation on Transformer
currently first is decoder only the
original Transformer is a encoder
decoder architecture so um it's
redundant because the important the the
the encoder and the decoder uh should
learn the how to how to understand the
Tex from different parameters is
redundant and currently we only care
about decoder only decoder only
architectures the second one is pre
layer Norm in the original Transformer
layer the layer Norm is after the
residual residual connection is called a
postar norm and currently we usually use
PRM the rotary position in Bing is
something very special because in not
published from a paper it's not
published from a Chinese blog uh it's uh
but currently
[Music]
is is Prov and very
efficient and the group query attention
is actually from another people nor it
cance the inference
memory and GL warant is also from nor as
uh just a a replacement of the MLP and
mixure Export actually U also from Norms
paper and uh you can use the same flow
small parameter to get better
performance so this uh is what the the
current the most advanc open source
language model the architecture of most
Advan open source language model for
example
Lama okay we we know there tecture about
how to train the this Transformer is
also very
important uh this we need to uh prepare
very powerful code base to train the
large language model so the first choice
is deep speed is it's a library from
Microsoft uh and some of the most
important optimization method is from
the paper called Z in deep from Deep
speed
group uh if you several years ago some
of us uh not really know how to train a
very large model how to efficiently
trans them but z uh give us some advices
for example uh if we uh we can find the
most uh memory conception is actually
the Adam stat the optimizer St you must
keep it a for precision as a flood and
the m is also a FL the parameter and
gradient you can keep it half precision
and you you can have
a fast computation and save
memories
uh the Z1 can scatter the mass weight
and timer State into all the data
parallel ranks so if you have more uh uh
more ranks more GPU cards you just uh
use l
GPU memory
for for each
rank uh another important technique is
called activation check pointing is
actually recalls the IM
intermediate uh State and recompute when
backward so uh we don't really need
record all the computation flow graph we
just need to recall the some of of the
Hidden States it's reduce all the
activation many layers from into one
layers and there's other
methods to reduce the memory conception
for example Z2 CPU offload which means
you can offload some uh GPU memory to
CPU and Z three and also call fly shed
data
parallel you can just uh sh your model
into different cars and when you use the
parameter you gather this parameter from
the other R so all all this method is
very complic complicated but uh the Deep
speed Library have already give a very
clean API to use it uh it's so currently
it's not very hard to train very large L
remodal
efficiency and magron is another uh
framework to train large language models
it's and it is also the most valuable
framework to train a super large
language model more than 100 billion
parameters uh it's use another set of
optimization method uh the first is
called tensor parallel the tensor
parallel split the hidden
size and has into different ranks and it
ca additional or reduce for attention
and
mlc but um reduce the uh all the uh
parameters conception and the Computing
conception into different TP
ranks uh the pipeline parallel is a uh
to split the layers into different ranks
and uh uh it also uh in introduce
bubbles in peline and there's some
method for example inter and bubble to
remove this uh conception uh yeah maybe
if you are if you want to chain a very
large language model uh one day you need
to learn about all this kind of system
system SC because the current uh lar
Lang remote training is actually a
engineering work uh yeah LP is not very
important the the important is
mlc okay uh so and another very
important thing is long
Contex uh it's actually lossless long
contact which means we don't use SP
tension or other uh meod to change the
for attention
Behavior
Uh is the the current INF to tr long
context is beyond the imagination uh for
AI guys for five years ago uh the left
figure is actually my paper uh when I
yeah published them several years ago in
Europe it's um at that time there's no
such thing like uh gbt gbt 3 is only B
so um this paper is
actually uh very very complicated to
schedule the two schedule two different
boards to uh mimic the retrieval
rehearsal and
forget process in working memory or
human
to uh let the model to understand very
long Contex step by step but uh actually
we can see that we can use different
system level AR technical
to uh understand very very long context
for example more than
uh one more than
100,000 uh lens is full attention so
it's just different from several years
ago and the
anything uh is super simplified because
because of this Improvement uh a key
technique is called context parallel
which means we split the sequence into
different RS and use ring attention or
Uris and other technique called to uh uh
finish the attention uh
uh there's a library called Transformer
engy and all of this function is worked
in this library and uh uh we need to
hand out the load balance of the
attention um to make every R have the
same
computation so uh this is actually trans
change lots of different research
of and applications of op for example
with
uh we summary and uh uh extract some
facts from the documents several years
ago using uh like bm25 or other or and
other retrial method and currently we
can just use a Transformer and full
attention to get the information and
understand it it's quite quite important
uh Improvement
so using this very powerful infra we can
train very large language models and the
for the alignment the first period is
called sft and supervis find un it's
actually a very ordinary funing for
language model a high quality data and
the high quality data is usually from
Human notation the human this human
annotation is not not just CR sourcing
you need to hear export from different
domains to write this high quality
answers to train the model for example
if you want to uh want the model to
um uh write some code and explain the
code in a very formed way you need to uh
here a
very experienced programmer to write
some example to teach this language
model it's not just CR sourcing this is
quite different from the prous human
anotation and
the we can also extract the uh question
answer pairs from more powerful models
like gbt for turo to train our model but
uh this is actually not aled by open AI
uh so you cannot use this me to develop
uh their uh a model to competing with
them but uh you actually
uh uh if you for research you don't
worry about this using this method n
pass4
because there's a paper called way to
strong generalization and recall what I
said just now now uh what your what
what's really important is your PR loss
if your PR loss is lower than your
teacher math teacher model you can also
uh surpass your teacher model uh even
you use the SF uh data from your teacher
mode
yeah and another period of alignment is
called irf it use reinforcement learning
from Human feedback
to uh improve the model but actually the
most com open language model uh didn't
use this method the main reason is U uh
PO is very hard to um implement it could
be it it could be very powerful if your
reward model is good enough but not easy
to treat so uh that there
some more easy method uh and most open
source language model they use DPO
method it's from paper from stord and we
only need some PR PR reference Pairs and
use this uh formula to update your model
you don't need uh you don't rarely need
a reward model you uh you don't really
need a reward model you just need some
pairs uh maybe this pairs should some on
policy PS
but yeah uh but
it's much simp simple and also very
powerful
so this are basics of how to train a
language model currently uh and uh it
seem like it's nothing about NLP it's
actually the the a party of mlc SK so
what are the LM prer doing is actually
the most important things is data the
current
the data cleaning filtering Sy sizing is
the most important thing of all the
large language model company which is a
uh Open Secret so the training INF is
actually
uh B is basically what I said uh in the
last several slides maybe there's some
other more uh once me but the
Improvement is maybe 20% or something
like that but if you have a better uh a
better pring data and the performance of
your language model is quite uh uh quite
obvious
so and it's something like uh the
language model and some are are
told by the the media is um most one
thing and uh but but
actually most of
the M Engineering in large model company
is actually cleaning the data so is this
something a St for graduate student
should do maybe someone thing is very
it's very low I want to design some new
algorithm I
this is rare ml research but uh I have a
opinion that the data the algorithm and
architecture can transform transform to
each other
so the the the data is most most general
form but sometimes if you don't have
enough computer it could
be it could
be very
um hard to fed this kind of data and
algorithm is um very hard to implement
and not very general the
architecture uh is hard to perform what
you want you design new architecture
very hard uh I I will take um a multi
Health question answering task as an
example the right figure is is that from
the C is also one of my papers when I
was a p student uh it's actually about
uh a a a task
to we have very complex question and we
need to find the task the task find the
answer from several documents but you
need to uh you need to find the CH uh
reasoning between different document to
get the final answer so at that time I
proposed a
method invol BR and graph neuron network
is very
complicated um and uh finally I get I
got a very good performance and uh 10 10
points uh better than PR method but um
yeah there's a uh this is actually some
uh algorithm or
architecture uh Innovation it's very
fancy and get very high score uh in ACL
review but um there's some other current
work use MCTS M research and Bo and
something like that it looks like
algorithm level Innovation to solve this
problem but currently this problem can
be easily solved by a very long context
GPT and chain of s reasoning if you
include nearly all the documents into
your context you don't need any things
like graph neuron Network or MCTS to
jump between to jump between the the
documents you have all the context and
uh you can just finish using
sort it's a data level solution
so the data level solution is of course
most simple one
because uh you you just add the data
into your training training Corpus and
you you can just finish this task while
not uh affect other task so the the data
cleaning fing sizing is not a very easy
work and it actually very um
important uh view to to uh important to
do this
is uh it should we should transform our
view of data and algorithm architecture
to fit the current Uh current
air so uh yeah I have introduce some
knowledge about um uh the the about
language models so I will jump into the
second part which is a re language
models in the past one
year so uh the past one year we have
seen the we Lang
[Music]
models jump from nearly a very uh uh
very silly one to currently very
powerful ones so uh I will start from
bleep to which is U actually a uh the
maybe I think the first work to uh
Bridge the clip
and large language model to give the
language model ability to understand the
the
images actually if we if we have a image
encoder from clip and the large language
model uh from anywhere so you can just
insert
a a transformer called Q forer to
extract some important features from
image encoder and uh insert these
features into large L model to the uh
but the space of image features and text
featur is different so the Q form is
trainable uh you'll need the
lots
of text image Pairs and align the space
of image features and the language and
text features the space so uh yeah yeah
this the Q form uh is actually did this
but there's
a most
simple method called laa is it
actually actually uh don't you use a
simple projection withd to transform the
re encoder the feature from RE encoder
into the features in the Lang the
language model input
so uh it quickly become the most popular
architectures of your language models
Co m is a uh a work from our group
it the the motivation of c and is uh to
keep all the language Behavior while um
and we add an language uh image
understanding ability to the language
model uh for LA
and uh for for for for the previous
method
maybe uh you can you you actually can uh
change the language model and get a
better
performance but um the the uh but it's
about multimodality task the the
language model ability language ability
of the model will be reduced if you
change the language model during the tax
image alignment so we
first we first use a region
exports uh to uh add new parameters in
the backbone and uh the New Vision
exports only deal with the image
features and the original VDS in fit
forward layers and the qqv Matrix deal
with the original Tex features so so uh
the
original behavior of language model is
keeped and we add lots of new parameter
to train uh and get a better performance
of Lang of multimodality models uh the
CM
achieves state of art performance of
several benchmarks including image
captioning grounding and recu and some
other large model benchmarks and also
open source so you can download it from
our K have uh last last month I found
that uh C is
downloaded more than uh five
500,000 times uh in in in the last month
so I think it already helped lots of
people
and the code agent here another Works uh
from our group is use a different
architectures because we want high
resolution uh with cross attention why
is cross attention because we don't want
to um uh we just want want a high
resolution input and don't want to let
all the hidden size the same as the V
the language mod hidden size which is
very large so we use a cross attention
to deal with the low resolution the high
resolution channels uh it's uh slightly
complicated but uh the performance very
good we can find uh this this this model
actually trained to be a web agent and
uh it's just take a
screenshot as input and um it will uh
perform different operation on the uh
scream scream shot for example this is a
uh example for a search uh uh the last
year's best paper in C so uh we we ask
the model this question they told me you
need to uh type the best paper of cvpr
2023 in the box at this position and uh
step by step finally we GA the
information and we all we can also use
this method to uh book some tickets or
some other perform some other task yeah
this is Al also open resource open
source some other uh
popular architectures about uh we
language
modeling uh includes wies it's it's
actually different VAR featur that inut
and uh is largely improve the OCR
performance but what I want to stress is
uh we
actually the most uh in our most want
want uh re language model gm4 V we
actually use a more simple architecture
it's actually a small
adaptation uh upon lava we just replace
the uh projection weight of lava into a
stride convolution to suppose high
resolution input but keep the
computation in language model using this
architecture we can uh TR the V language
model mixed with the text and finally we
get a good performance we can say that
GM 4way Can U on the part of gbt 4way or
Germany or Cloud 3 and uh uh it's
performed better in OCR uh do OCR
benchmarks for example doc document qway
and uh it's perform much better at
Chinese
OA this is some this is example of our
most advanc
grm4 uh
model uh you can download
the uh uh our app from this Chad gm. CN
website uh this is actually
a very hard to recognize draft but and
it's it's also a mean uh the model can
analyze it
very accurately and can
translate what is
really what really right so uh yeah you
can experience our model is totally free
from this
website
okay we have some introduction about we
understanding it's more about
engineering but uh uh it's multi
modality but and another half of the we
language research about image generation
and is also relevant to Transformers so
I will also introduce this uh the the
the rule about image
generation
yeah uh for three
oh four years ago uh
aluto the we already know the gbt is
very powerful so we want to Auto
regressively modeling the X
Generation for uh using the
GPT so this is a uh uh the work of C
view uh it's also my work at 20 and uh
21 is uh it's very simple framework
because we know that GPT can only
predict multinomial distribution so we
we need to find some method to train uh
to train the image in a disc way there's
uh maybe
2020 uh there's paper called rgpt uh
from openi it's trained directly on the
pixel level uh for all modeling
but the
sequence is very long so you cannot
train a
very uh high resolution images so we can
train first train image tokenizer it's
actually a we way uh to
dis discs your image into uh several
tokens and you Pro prepare the
sequence of a text image as the for text
for image later and you can use gbt
to train this kind of sequence and
finally during the inference you first
inut the in the tax and then uh predict
token by token in the image token in the
image you can generate some uh image
yeah this is a a very simple idea and uh
a concar work called D and the most
powerful work called party is from the
the same idea
okay but
um yeah yeah we know that we can in we
can generate image you in GPT so a very
natural idea is can we achieve some
Universal modeling for re language tasks
so if if we just tokenize the
image just like the text we can generate
image we can uh generate text from the
image we can generate image from text
and only generate Tex so this is a very
neutal idea and um I also did this in C
to maybe two years ago
and yeah the
the the algorithm also very simple it's
just uh you you in in the sequence you
change different position or uh text and
image sequence if for first Tex then
image and you mask all the SC is T image
generation if first image then Tex it's
image captioning and you can also guess
other uh other um format like mask Auto
encoder or something like that but the
problem is
um when you compare this um Universal
modeling system to
diffusion of re language modeling re
language model you will find the image
generation it's it worse than the
diffusion and the very slow compared to
diffusion
for uh image understanding is perform
worse than with language model because
when your uh image uh is uh when you
when you transform your image into
uh dis disir tokens lot of information
is lost during this process so the
performance is worse than the V language
model
so using this method you can achieve
Universal modeling but the you you just
achieve Universal modeling and you
cannot achieve the best performance
on uh any task and
so uh the diffusion method actually wins
the game or image generation and not
Auto agressive alth the in in the NP
doain the auto method is dominant but in
image generation the vendor is diffusion
so what is diffusion uh diffusion
actually
another is a totally different
self-supervised learning method uh
compared to autoagressive meth it's uh
you can also think it's a autoregressive
on for doy or something like that so but
but
actually it's the ddpm is the
original uh paper of diffusion model is
still the most popular framework of
diffusion modeling we can uh Define lot
of steps is we gradually adding noise to
a clean image and uh we get different
inter medient state and the train model
to predict the noise the original image
or something like v as a velocity of the
of the angle is of the log actually
given the noise
important noisy noisy image
so uh it's it's totally different but um
uh the the the mo the most advantage of
diffusion model or autoing model is that
during sampling
we during sampling we
can uh during sampling we can use four
utility or gpus because in our
regressive model when we decode a token
we uh actually ER the power of the GPU
uh it is the utility of GPU is very low
if the batch size is small batch size
equal to one but um for diffusion model
we just input all the image into the in
in into the model so it can utilize the
GPU
and it can sampling much faster than
aive model
OKAY the Rel diffusion model is the Rel
diffusion model is our recent work about
uh is solve the problem in
diffusion uh about the no schedule
across different
resolution the first is
uh you can you can see the left image is
is actually three uh three images with
the same noise the a the A and B are two
images with different resolution and
with the same noise level but the a is
actually more
blurred for uh for us during the
observation the problem is um we add a
independent no and
[Music]
uh then and and and the actually
the original
signal the image not independent across
the space so
what what what we need to do is
U is a uh if we want to uh transform a
noise schedule from low resolution to
high resolution we need to use a block
noise to
uh find the
equivalence on the high resolution
images and finally we can
keep the S
SN in the frequency graph the same
so uh we uh uh using this method we can
disentangle the noisy schedule and the
actually uh Network we use for diffusion
use a noise schedule we don't care about
the resolution we just uh you a block
noise when we want to uh continue
diffusion on high resolution so the the
speed
can uh
improved uh because we don't need to uh
reimage generate the image from the high
resolution from the high condition on
the low resolution
image high resolution F
okay and we also scale up the Rel
diffusion to C after this uh after the
the paper yeah uh the cob 3 is actually
a large diffusion model and um after
disolution it could be very fast because
of the uh effect effectiveness of the
Rel diffus
okay uh finally we guess we get
something relevant to our topic
Transformer and actually the previous
Works about diffusion is on
units and uh using Transformer is not
trivial in the in diffusion uh the first
work I think maybe uh is is solid enough
is dit from
meta uh the author of this paper is also
the author
so the the most important most
difference between the original
Transformer and
this D is the ad
lome ome is predict uh scale and bias
for uh different lay know uh scale and
shift for different condition on the
time step it's actually needs a very
huge amount parameters is six times of
hidden hidden
size nearly equals to A QQ uh W per
layer but the the input is only one in
one in is actually very strange because
the input is only one in and you need a
millions of parameter to transform it so
uh there some method can reduce this
steam in
our pra
practice uh the St diffusion 3 released
recently use another architectures
called
MMD the St Defence three for use our
released C to caption of the model other
images and train L diffusion model using
this new architecture the new
architecture seem like very complicated
but uh the the most important thing
is um they use vision and TX exports
like hm instead of cross attention uh to
T5 features like the previous
ones so finally we will talk talk
shortly about radio generation because
Sor is uh currently very uh popular
uh we publish uh we do generation work
several years ago in and fin is
published on AAR so it's it's maybe the
first open S language model for test
video generation but the performance
much worse than the current Sora uh
because it's autoaggressive so using
diffusion we can get better we currently
also working for uh replication of Sor
like models and
our we we can summary that the the most
the the Improvement of Sora come from
this aspect the for is there no faking
in the videos and it's it can generate
high quality
images the first one Tod fleing can be
solved by the 3D latent 3D latent
encoder decoder and uh if you train a
diffusion decoder it could be better uh
the high
quality is s should s to the the scaling
up and um it requires a very high
resolution and uh this is something
related to the long contact Banking and
the Contex parallel techniques in uh the
language model infra which I
introduced at the beginning of this
course so um you the most important
thing is they use the infra the you use
infra in language model training into
the diffusion and uh make
it make it very easy to scale up and uh
scale up much much uh larger than the
other other companies yeah and finally
the most important thing is data
coverage it need a very heav DET
engineering and the video
recaption
okay
so this I have uh introduced many topics
our current multi modality print tring
and uh some problem in the the this
Transformer community so there are some
trads I think will happen in one or few
years in the multi modality
area in the next one or two years we can
easily
recognize uh grounding all the common s
attributes and human is is persons and
other lots of high level Vision scenes
and all these scenes will be very sheap
and be basically
sold
so this this will happen in one or two
years at that time the long tile problem
of Auto auto driving could be a littleit
not not so but largely a littleit and um
the second prediction is the the video
understanding will become very important
in the next one or two years because
it's very
useful we uh we have lots of video in
the internet and uh in our everyday life
but it's very hard and currently we
cannot understand video well and the
most powerful video understanding model
currently is
Germany 1.5 but it's it's basically uh
lots of hallucinations and uh wrong
counting and lots of weakness
so there's a very large room to
improve uh another thing is we have
enough compute to deal with the video
now
and especially in the next one or two
years because the uh Next Generation or
media GPU
and the requirements from the larg
language
model uh and another important thing is
inod ai inod ai will be more and more
important in the research and it will be
um very closely related to multimodality
research although it cannot uh impact
our real life in a few years because we
now have planning ability with L Lang
models we can recognize all the things
Lang models and there there will be some
chances to get some new ability and and
very very very astonishing demo of this
uh this embod AI
but the
the they may be they very expensive and
cannot be used for everyday life
so what should we do uh at that time at
that's that and
for me some some researcher like me in a
large langage model company we got
enough Computer Resources but for others
so I think if you are a senior
researcher so just follow your heart
time ignore me uh if you want to quickly
get some um sations papers
impact I think maybe you can consider
that the the the video understanding
models data sets benchmarks especially
data set and benchmarks is very
important and uh in great need of the
video understanding
Community yeah and for motive modality
and there's another topic I haven't uh
talk talked about in this lecture is uh
is a speech or audio um I
recently uh learn some knowledge about
audio and I lead the group of of
speech AI group in J AI so um I'm I'm
not a researcher about audio but I can
say that the speech AI is
underestimated it's
actually very important for uh the user
need and application but there's no
enough GPU and research researchers put
into this areas like in language
model yeah
finally if you want do some very useful
and impact a
research which is very risky you uh
advice is you need to make some system
PhD student Advance
because
the the best algorithm and must utilize
the current the
current uh GPU and other Hardware yeah
so you just need to know some system PhD
students and
there and there should be another is
more uh difficult but influential is
there's actually some room for new
architectures for self super
self-supervised learning and optimizers
because the next generation of Hardware
will be totally different so uh maybe
the Transformer will be uh have some
competitors and
the AL also the auto regressive modeling
method so there's some room but it's
very hard and need some computational
resourcing uh and finally the new ways
to transform campu to high quality data
is very important because the web data
is the high quality web data is actually
be Crow down um uh into uh almost every
large language model company and it's
currently not very enough so we need to
find some new ways to transform Compu to
high quality data for example how to how
to S sizing the new data using Code
execution result using uh maybe
MCTS reinforcement learning or some
other Master this very big area and uh
in in the next few years yeah I think I
will end this lecture here and thank you
for the instructors and audience and
thank you very much if you have some
question you can send email to this and
I will uh answer all the question thank
you very much
yeah thank you very much M for the
amazing talk and all the useful advice
um so we have some questions um I got
one through zoom and there's several
also on slido so um Emily are there any
in-person questions from your
[Music]
end okay if you if someone has some
question and you can type in the in the
chatting in in zoom zoom if you you are
using Zoom U let me
see okay yeah here are some questions on
slido that I'll ask um the first is that
the success of long context Windows must
come at a cost what what is this
cost the cost is a because is a very
[Music]
long the time com conception you just
need to run your run your uh inference
engine for a very long time actually the
current inference system of large
language model can be uh uh split into
two period one is profilling you need to
uh UT a very long contacts into your
engine and the another is decode and you
you generates the token by token so uh
most user case they actually not
generate a very long contest not
understand a long contest and generate a
very few uh
tokens about the question
so we can uh bear
maybe uh one
minutes uh to uh left the language model
to uh just round the long context
understanding and then begin to uh
answer your question so this is a course
you need to uh wait for maybe several
several seconds or one minute
yes right oops I was muted but yes
thanks that makes sense um so there's
two questions which are pretty similar
all uploaded on slido
um talking about the quality of data so
recently folks have been saying that the
quality of data is what really
determines final model performance
compared to anything else do you agree
and related to this do you think there's
still a lot of work to do around
improving the architecture of models or
has attention shifted to focus on
data yeah yeah I think I think this very
reason actually what what the the whole
community is doing is to improve the
data
uh I just talk talk about this opinion
in in the lecture is the architecture
the algorithm the data can transform to
each other if you have some idea you can
inject the inductive bias into
architecture you can design a new
algorithm and you can
Pro prepare some data to tell your model
to act like that so many of the the very
uh special cases you can you can you can
use data to solve the problem so the
high quality data is more important the
architecture of this to for many tasks
button I think if you can find a find a
a general update of Transformer is very
valuable if just increase the power of
the model to Feit in the the data is
very very valuable
yeah right great um here's a question um
why is auto regressive architecture
inferior to diffusion in image
generation
[Music]
uh uh yeah yeah the it's very
complicated this this this question is
very complicated actually so the
diffusion is has has is is totally
different in Auto regressive to some
extent but the most important thing I
have talk about in the in the lecture is
a the speed of generation for auto
regressive model if you use a very large
model you train it for a very long time
I I believe we can get
very good result we can also generate
high quality images using Auto
regressive Ms this is this is okay but
the time to
generate an image is very very long
because we need to predict the token by
token maybe a high resolution
image maybe thousands of thousand of
tokens
is but but for diffusion we use several
steps of um Fe forwarding all the all
the image we need we don't need to token
by token prediction it's it will be
thousands times faster than Auto resum
model if you are generating a high
resolution images so this is a very uh
obvious advantage and for for the
modeling power I think the most
important thing is the
maybe
some
uh some relation between the
the space is actually
not well not uh modeling well by Al
model because the left most pixel and
the right bottom pixel it's very far in
Auto regressive model but but uh uh in
in diffusion model is actually we can we
can see each other so it's not a problem
but for ring model is have position
problem so it's it's it's not easy
to uh modeling a very
complicated 2D special problems this is
also a a possible reason but I cannot
give a very
uh very uh good answer about this
question but yeah yeah yeah this should
be more research about that yeah thank
you right great thanks for that detailed
answer um so someone is asking how is
the Cog agent model different from the
Cog vlm
model oh yeah uh the Cog agent model is
actually fine tuned from the C model but
the C model they always high resolution
and and web scream cases because our
motivation is that the uh high
resolution input for web page is very
important because there's many words
many icons something very small and you
need to um use a very high resolution
model to deal with it but um if you just
extend
the the input resolution of CM the the
conception is very high so we need we
use a cross tension modu uh adding to
the C to get C agent so this module is a
much lightweight so we can uh deal with
the high resolution more easy
yeah great um here's a question about
video how do you think video
understanding will Aid ai's ability to
have a stronger physical understanding
of the
world okay okay that's a a very good
question I think yes I my answer is yes
but um it's uh actually a
BAL uh problem is because if you don't
have some dat Source Which con the
physical physical uh rules you cannot TR
a good uh video understanding model you
I I think using the current real
language model print Training Method
because we need the input the text image
or text video pairs to train and we did
we actually did not use any s supervised
learning uh in the image or video so we
cannot learn any knowledge from P video
or
image we
[Music]
actually we actually deal dealing with
the unnoted data from Human Side so if
you want
to understanding understand better of
the physical words using an noted videos
we need to uh find some new uh method
for self-supervised learning or PR
Training Method yeah this is a very good
a very good question this is a very good
question thank
you right okay a couple more questions
um someone is asking are there vqa tasks
that involve multiple terms of
conversation in a tree structure similar
to a tree of thoughts or beam search
style okay okay yeah
yeah maybe but uh I I still think it's
different and the three three Source V
could be better because it
can uh is a rare of other Mass
information for example the uh the wrong
pass the other
fa fa fail case something like that so
uh um my experence is uh if you you can
include all the contacts in your
input um you you always get better
results so yeah
maybe either tree of s or some other
different process process uh process
procedure and some other informations
you just included them into the content
uh the language model will learn to how
to deal with them and understand better
than the beam search which is actually a
hard code me to compare the top
probabilities uh it should be better if
you if you uh do it right yes right
thanks that's all all the time we have
your questions so thanks again to for
the great talk the detailed answers to
all the questions