Today we're going to be talking about
image classification with CNN's. So you
might be wondering who am I? Um I'm a
new face. You haven't seen me before in
this class. I'm Justin. I'm the fourth
mystery instructor in this class. I
think my picture's been on the website,
but it's my first time here today. Um
and a little about me. Um I did my PhD
here at Stanford from 2012 to 2018. uh
working with FE on deep learning,
computer vision, pretty much all tasks
in computer vision around that time. Um
during my time here at Stanford, I was
uh lucky enough to initiate CS231N with
Andre and Feay and others uh and teach
it you know quite a few times 2015, 16,
17 and 18 and 19 um at Stanford. After
that I spent time at uh Facebook AI
research doing all kinds of deep
learning computer vision stuff there. Um
and being I was a faculty member at
University of Michigan. Um and there I
taught basically the same class a couple
more times. So I've taught this class a
couple times but it's been a while since
I've been here. Um and most recently
I've been doing a startup called World
Labs with FE. Um and that's just a
little bit about me.
Now about where we are on this class. So
we're kind of at an interesting point in
the class right now. um where the class
is kind of divided up into these couple
different segments. Um and we basically
finished the first segment. The first
segment is basically around deep
learning basics. And this is really cool
because now all the stuff that you've
seen in like four lectures is basically
all the fundamentals of deep learning.
You basically know this whole pipeline
of what is the basic pieces that go into
building a deep learning system. So I
thought it's useful here at the
beginning of this inflection point to
just sort of step back and recap some of
the major themes that we've seen in the
first bit of the course. Um so the first
is this idea of image classification
with linear classifiers. Um and this was
kind of meant as a toy problem to give
you a sense of a kind of problem you
might solve with deep learning where
usually the first step in solving a deep
learning problem is to define your
problem in a way where it is um you take
input some grid of numbers some tensors.
You produce as output some tensors and
you want to formalize this problem as
some input output of tensors. Um, and we
kind of do that in the image
classification setting by saying that we
want to classify images into a bunch of
human understandable categories. The
inputs are going going to be these grids
of pixel values which are arranged in
threedimensional tensors. The outputs
are going to be scores giving us the
affinity or the the degree to which we
have one score per category. You define
a set of categories in advance and the
network is supposed to predict high
scores for categories that the image is
likely to be low scores for the
categories that the image is likely to
be not. Um and then we can define we can
set up a a problem to you know uh use a
weight matrix uh multiply that against
the the image pixels and predict these
scores. Um and we saw that there's a
couple different viewpoints a couple
different ways that we can interpret
these linear classifiers. Um and this
basically sets up a functional form
saying that we can predict scores for
images if only we have a weight matrix
W. So then the question is how do we
select a good weight matrix W? And for
that we go to loss functions. Right? So
loss functions are these things that
tell us you know given a particular
value of a weight matrix given a
particular data set how well does this
weight matrix fit the solve the problem
on this data set. Um and in particular
we saw some examples of loss functions
that are commonly used for
classification problems including the
softmax loss and probably the SVM loss
as well. Um and then now okay so now
we've kind of gotten a little bit
further along in our problem. We've set
up the problem of image classification.
um we have a model for solving that
problem using linear classifiers. We
have a way to tell if our solutions are
good using a loss function. But now we
actually need to search for a good
solution in that space. And that's where
optimization comes in. Right? So now
that we now you think of the now you
think of defining this optimization
landscape where on the x-axis or on the
on the horizontal plane are all the
different possible settings of your
weight matrix. And then the loss
function is basically a height of this
plane where a high loss function is bad
because losing things is bad. So you
want low loss. So the purpose of
optimization is to somehow traverse this
space, slide down this manifold and find
a point at the bottom of very low loss.
And now each point in this space
corresponds to a weight matrix. So by
sliding down that space, we're going to
find a good weight matrix that solves
our problem um and gives us a good
solution to our task. And in particular,
we saw a couple different commonly used
optimization algorithms that are used in
deep learning pipelines. uh stochastic
gradient descent usually with momentum
RMS prop atom um and one sort of
interesting uh topical note is that
right now um one of the biggest uh deep
learning research conferences is I clear
international conference on learning
representations um and just yesterday uh
iclear 2025 gave their test of time
award to the atom paper um because the
paper that introduced this atom
optimizer was published at iclear uh 10
years ago in 2015 um so at a lot of
academic conferences we'll they'll tend
to give test of time awards to some of
the most impactful papers from 10 years
ago. Um, and just yesterday the atom
optimizer that you guys have been learn
that you guys saw in this class got this
very prestigious test of time award at
iClar 2025. So I thought that was pretty
cool and a nice uh sort of way to
connect what you've been learning to
stuff that's happening right now in the
machine learning community.
Okay. So then now that we now we
basically at this point we've got we've
got our linear classifiers, we've got
our loss functions, we can optimize
them. Now we're almost good to go. Um
but we ran into a problem is that the
linear classifiers that we started with
are actually not very powerful. Um and
we saw this from we we saw two different
ways of attacking this this uh this
deficiency in linear classifiers. One
was from the visual viewpoint where you
can interpret a linear classifier by
thinking about by thinking of that
learned weight matrix as an image where
you learn one image template for each of
the categories that you're trying to
that you're trying to classify against.
Um, and if you think about it that way,
we realize that the weights of your
linear classifier, each row of that
weight matrix is one template. So the so
the linear classifier basically needs to
summarize all of its knowledge about
each category into just one template.
And that's kind of a difficult that's
just not a very powerful classifier. Um,
so then you can this kind of shows up in
these visualized templates of a learned
linear classifier where you can see that
for for categories like um the car, this
car kind of looks like a red blob, but
cars don't have to be red, right? What
if your car was blue or purple or green
or something else? There's just no good
way for a linear classifier to caption
this cap capture this notion of there
might be different appearances for an
object for each category. Um or from the
geometric viewpoint, if we imagine these
these each point of our data set as some
point in highdimensional space, then a
linear classifier is basically going in
and carving up that space with
hyperplanes. Um, so that's really good
if all your categories actually do lie
in linearly separable regions of your
space, but there's no reason to expect
that to be true in general. So these are
both two big deficiencies that we ran
into when looking at these linear
classifiers um as applied to image
classification problems.
And that led us in in that led us to
define this notion of neural networks
where we're going to generalize our
linear classifiers um to no longer just
have one weight matrix, but instead
stack two weight matrices on top of each
other um with a nonlinearity in between
them. And now this gives us a much more
powerful mechanism for predicting scores
from our inputs. Now the now basically
the problem is still the same. We have
our input pixels going through this uh
this computation spitting out scores.
But now rather than computing but we
just basically selected a different
functional form for this score function.
Um and this gave us and now you know the
algebra is pretty simple. You just need
to go from f= wx. You add an extra w2
add a little nonlinearity in between. So
the algebra doesn't change very much,
but in doing so, your classifiers get
much much more powerful than they were
before. Um, but now things get a little
bit complicated again because how does
this play into optimization, right? We
know that if we have a loss function, if
we have a model, then we want to find
values of those weight matrix that cause
the loss to go down. And and to do that,
we need to compute gradients. We need to
be able to compute gradients of the loss
with respect to all the parameters of
our model. And that's this notion of a
computational graph. So these
computational graphs are basically a
data structure to organize the
computation of a neural network where
each node in the graph is a little
functional primitive like a matrix
multiply or a ru or some other something
else like that and then data flows
forward in this graph from left to right
from our inputs and our weights on the
left flowing through all these
intermediate nodes in the graph to spit
out the loss function on the right. Um
and then once we compute the loss, you
you traverse this lo this uh this graph
backwards from right to left to compute
gradients of that loss with respect to
all the nodes of the of the of the of
the graph inside the network. Um, and
this is now really cool because it
basically means that we can write down
these arbitrarily complicated neural
networks, these arbitrarily complicated
expressions for computing our our
outputs from our inputs, but we now have
an automate a nearly automated algorithm
for computing whatever gradients we want
through arbitrarily complex neural
networks. Um, and the way that we do
that is this magic of back propagation.
Um, and back propagation is really cool.
I think it's one of the algorithms that
makes deep learning work because it
makes it takes this global problem of
how do we compute the loss through this
computational graph and converts it into
a local problem and now each of these
nodes don't doesn't need to know
anything about the larger context of
what is the graph I'm living in what is
the problem I'm trying to solve we just
need to be able to define these little
nodes inside of our computational graph
that on the forward pass know how know
how to compute outputs from their inputs
and then on the backwards pass can
receive gradients coming upstream. It
doesn't have to care where those
gradients come from. What what was what
was causing those gradients to happen.
And I just need to compute gradients
downstream gradients with respect to my
inputs given my upstream gradients. And
again, this is so powerful because now
it gives us this mechanism where we can
just define a bunch of different types
of nodes um that all just have follow
this local API of computing outputs,
computing local gradients. And if we as
long as we follow that API for all of
the nodes, then we can start to stitch
them together into these big complicated
computational graphs that can do
basically arbitrary computation. And the
gradients just come for free when we
turn the crank on the back propagation
algorithm.
Um and u you know this is this slide you
know that you guys saw last time is
basically back propagation on uh on
scalar values but we can generalize this
to work on vector value on vector valued
or matrix or tensor valued values as
well. Um but the basic thing to remember
is that your inputs are some tensors,
your outputs are some tensors. And now
your your upstream gradient that you get
is the gradient of the loss with respect
to your outputs. Um and that always has
the same shape as your outputs, right?
Because the loss is a scalar. A gradient
of a loss with respect to a tensor says
for each element in a tensor, if I were
to wiggle that element a little bit,
then how much does the loss wiggle,
right? And because the loss is a scalar,
we just need to wiggle each of those. we
just need to imagine wiggling each
element in our tensor independently. Um,
and that is the definition of our
gradient. So then that's very easy to
remember. Your upstream gradients always
have the exact same shape as your
outputs. Your downstream gradients,
those are the gradients with respect to
my inputs. Those also have the same
shape as my inputs. Right? So then the
back propagation algorithm is basically
just the chain rule where I need to
somehow compute my downstream gradients
as a function of my upstream gradients
and whatever function I was trying to
compute. um and you'll get some practice
on later assignments computing uh you
know writing down the gradient
expressions for different kinds of
operators uh in in your neural networks.
So basically this gives us our recipe
for solving pretty much any problem in
deep learning, right? Like this this was
intended to be quite a bit more general
than just image classification or just
linear classifiers or just fully
connected networks. Right now if you
have any kind of problem that you want
to solve, you just need to encode it as
tensors. Write down some computational
graph that computes your output tensors
from your input tensors. Collect a data
set of input output tensors. Write down
a loss function for the kind of problem
you want to solve. Now, and then
optimize that loss function using
gradient descent, using back
propagation. Um, and that's a really
powerful recipe that basically powers
all deep learning applications, whe
whether it's image classification, image
generation, large language models,
pretty much anything involving a neural
neural network is trained using this
using this formula or some slight
variant on top of this formula. So that
leads us to the second part of the
class, which is perceiving and
understanding the visual world. So here
is where we want to get a little bit
more specialized and start talking about
you know not the general framework of
deep learning but how does this apply to
to problems that we want to solve in
computer vision processing images doing
interesting stuff with images. Um and
today we'll take a step towards that by
talking about a bit more about
convolutional networks. Um so
convolutional networks actually are a
pretty small lift on top of this
framework that we've already already
defined. Right? So we've already talked
about two right we have this you have
this sort of general paradigm of
computational graphs of little operators
that can live inside of our
computational graphs but we so we have
this beautiful framework but we actually
haven't filled in a lot of the specifics
of that framework. We've actually only
seen like two or three different kinds
of nodes that can live inside of our
computational graphs. We've seen fully
connected layers which are which is
basically a matrix multiply. We've seen
activation functions like our ReLU and
we've seen our loss functions themselves
and um in you know now to build up from
what we've seen already into
convolutional networks basically all we
need to do is add a couple new types of
nodes um that can fit into our
computational graphs. Um, and in
particular, there's really only two
operators that we need to talk about to
build much more powerful networks, which
will be the convolution layer that we'll
spend most of today's lecture talking
about. Um, and then the pooling layer,
which is um, another thing that we often
use when processing images.
So, that's kind of the road map for
today. I want to talk a little bit about
convolutional networks in general. Then,
we'll talk about these two particular
um, computational primitives that we can
use to build convolutional networks in
our computational graphs.
Okay, so we've already talked about im
so then here we want to step back a
little bit and think about this problem
of image classification again. So we've
already talked about how image
classification is this super core
problem in computer vision where we want
to take an input image and then predict
you know from that input image what what
is in this image as a set of category uh
you know predict one of k category
labels basically um in this image
obviously is a cat so we want to predict
the cat classifier um and most of the
and you know we basically solved this
problem in some sense already by
building linear classifiers and by
building uh fully connected multi-layer
perceptron neural networks um but these
these uh these networks are basically
operating in pixel space um they their
inputs you know remember we said the
first way to the first step to solving a
deep learning problem is to formulate it
in terms of input output tensors well in
this case our input tensors were the raw
pixel values of our images um so when we
write f ofx= wx that x input that's just
the literal values of all of our pixels
um and then we go from those raw pixel
values to our class scores um but
there's another way to do it which was
common back in the dark ages before
neural networks came about and saved us
from all this tedium um maybe back in
the early 2000s sort of up until maybe
2010 2011-ish was this idea of feature
representations. So here the idea is we
could actually um you can actually
choose what is going to be your input to
your neural network. So you could have
said rather than feeding the raw pixel
values of the network of the image into
our neural network instead we could
define some other kind of function which
is going to extract features extract
some convert those pixel values of our
image into some other meaningful
representation that we as the
intelligent human designers of this
system believe represent or capture some
of the important facets of our input
image. Um so then when if you're doing
you know image classification on top of
a feature representation your step one
would be to define a feature
representation that converts your um
your raw image pixels into this higher
level representation. And now that
feature representation will now take the
will now be the X that feeds into your
linear classifier. Um, and there was a
ton of work in computer vision, uh, you
know, really in the 2000s to the late
2010s or to the early 2010sish that were
that used this idea of feature
representations for all kinds of CL for
all kinds of tasks. Um, and I don't
really think it's useful to go into
super great detail on any of these
particular feature representations
because spoiler alert, they got
deprecated like 10 years ago. Um, but
it's useful to have a a flavor for what
they might have looked like. So one
example of a kind of feature
representation that people sometimes
used is this notion of a color
histogram. So here what we could say is
divide the space. So maybe we we we
think that somehow the distribution of
colors in our image might be a useful
thing for a classifier to look at or
care about, right? Because maybe you're
building a fruit detector, apple
detector, and you want to know if it's
ripe or not. Maybe a maybe a red apple
from a green apple. you know how knowing
how much red or green is in the image
might be something that we as humans
think is useful for the network to know
for for making its classifications. So
here uh we could build we could try to
build a feature representation that
captures that intuition. So here what we
might do is take the space of all
possible colors, discretise that space
into some set of buckets and now for
every pixel in our image, we map that
pixel to one of the discrete buckets in
our color space and then basically our
feature representation becomes something
like a count of how many pixels in the
image fall into this color bucket. Um
and now you could and now this this is
kind of an interesting representation
because it destroys all the spatial
structure of the image and it only talks
about the color distributions. So now
you know if you had red in the corner
versus red on the other side they would
those two images would look the same to
this color histogram features um but
they would look very different from the
raw on the raw pixel perspective. So the
color histogram is a kind of one basic
kind of feature extractor or feature
representation that you can build on
images that basically looks only at
color and does not look at spatial
structure at all. Um another category of
um feature representations that people
used to look at is sort of the con is
sort of the sort of dual to that in
which are these histogram of oriented
gradients and I don't think it's useful
to talk too much about exactly how these
are computed but the intuition of these
is that they basically throw away the
color information and they only look at
the structure information they basically
want to look for every point in the
image what are like what direction like
what is the local direction of the edges
in the image around that local region so
here you can see that this frog you know
the leaves of the frog frog, it kind of
extracts diagonal type of features
because it corresponds to these diagonal
structures over here. Um, or around the
frog's eyes, you can see, oh, it sort of
captured those those those spherical
those circular structures. So, again,
it's not super useful to see how this is
computed, but it's useful to know that
these are the kinds of features that
people would uh designed for images
maybe a decade or decade and a half ago.
Um, and people combined these in all
kinds of complicated ways. So, people
would often you might wonder, oh, what's
the best feature representation? The
usual answer was just stack them all
together. So a pretty common approach
would be to have a bunch of different
feature representations um extract them
all from your image and then concatenate
them all into one big feature vector. Um
and that's kind of becomes your feature
representation for your image. Um and
now you could imagine once we have this
feature representation, we can basically
stick whatever kind of classifier we
want on top of it. Um and this and it's
interesting to then take a step back and
contrast that picture, that viewpoint of
that whole system, you know. So system A
is thinking about a feature feature
extractor plus learned network or
learned linear classifier on top of your
features. And then system B is endto-end
neural networks. And it's they actually
don't look that different if you take a
step back and think about it in the
right way. Both of these systems are
ultimately inputting the raw pixels of
the image and outputting some scores or
predictions about the image. Um the
difference is that the is the difference
is which part of the system is designed
by humans versus which part is learned
via gradient descent. In the feature
extraction plus linear classifier
paradigm the feature extraction portion
of the system is designed that could be
a bunch of really hairy C code or hairy
mat lab code. Um and you don't want to
think about the details of what's going
on inside of that. Um and then just the
part that you're learning via gradient
descent the part that you're learning
from your training data is just that
classifier on top of the feature
extractor. Whereas the neural network
approach is basically saying gradient
descent is probably a better programmer
than you and lots of data probably knows
more about your problem than you do. So
the then the intuition of these neural
network classifiers is there's still
ultimately going to be a system that
inputs the raw pixel values and spits
out your classification scores at the
end. But the difference is that all
parts of that system from the raw pixels
all the way to the final classification
scores will be tuned via gradient
descent and will be learned from your
training data set. So the intuition is
that you know there might be in this
feature extraction paradigm there might
be some bottlenecks. You as a human
might get something wrong. You might
have wrong intuition about what parts of
the problem are important what things
are not important or it might be really
hard for you to write down the right the
perfect feature extractor that solves
your problem. Um and this endto-end
learning approach of comnets and really
of deep learning more generally is just
saying that data and compute can likely
solve that problem better than you as a
human designer can. Um and this is and
this b this paradigm has basically won
over over the past decade and a half for
lots and lots of problems repeatedly.
Okay. So that that kind of gives an
intuition of so that so then the
question is like for the particular
problem of images um how should we
design these endto-end systems right
like it's not going to be a fully
connected network all the way that would
be a little bit silly. We do need to
still put a little bit of design into
the system, right? But the difference
about designing a neural network versus
designing a feature extractor is that in
designing a neural network, you're not
designing a particular function of a
feature extractor. You're kind of
defining a whole category of functions
where the category of functions is
defined by the structure of your
computational graph um by the by the
sequence of operators that get run. But
the but there's a little bit of but
there's some flexibility in that system
because you're leaving the weights of
the system free to be learned from data.
But the role of the human designer still
matters. You still need to decide what
is that architecture of your network.
What is that sequence of operators that
get stitched into a computational graph?
What are the sizes of all the matrices
involved at every stage of processing.
So there still is a lot of role for the
human to design parts of the problem um
in this deep learning era. Um but the
the that like what you're designing is a
little bit different.
So this is basically where we start to
see the deficiencies in the tools that
we have so far for solving this problem,
right? because we see that we've we
we've seen linear layers. We've seen
fully connected networks. Um and the
kind of only neural network architecture
that we've seen is to flatten our pixels
of our image into a big vector. Do
matrix multiply, do RLU, do more matrix
multiply, do more RLU, and that's about
it. That's all we know how to do at this
point. Um and one big problem with that
is that it destroys the spatial
structure of the images. Um there's this
big problem, right? Like it's sort of
like images are actually not
one-dimensional objects. Images are
two-dimensional. They have two
dimensional structure. That
two-dimensional structure matters for
the content of those images. And when
you build a linear classifier on raw
pixels by stretching it out into a big
vector, you're basically ignoring that
important factor of your input data in
the design of your neural network
architecture. So when we think about
designing neural network architectures
for images in particular, we want to
think what are other what are other
designs for our network? What are other
computational primitives we can slot
into our computational graphs that
better that better respect um that
two-dimensional structure of images?
And that leads us to convolutional
networks, right? So convolutional
networks are basically a category of
neural network architectures that are
built of linear layers, non
nonlinearities, convolution layers,
pooling layers, sometimes a couple
others um that stitch together into
these neural network architectures that
input raw pixel values and then output
some kind of prediction or scores for
our uh for our images. And the general
structure of these is that usually
they'll they'll have some prefix some
body of the network which is some
interled sequence of convolution layers
pooling layers and nonlinearities that
can be thought of of do as extracting
some useful feature representation for
the image. And then on top of that
there'll usually be some kind of fully
connected layers sometimes as few as one
um but sometimes more than one which you
can think of as a multi-layer perceptron
fully connected network classifier that
lives on top of and ingests the features
from the convolutional portion of the
network. But crucially this whole system
is tuned end to end um via gradient
descent by minimizing the loss on your
training data set. And these networks
actually have quite a bit of long
history. So um these this this image
this particular combinant architecture
that we've drawn on the screen actually
comes from a paper back in 1998 um with
Yan Lakun Leon Bau uh and others who
were at the time building these
convolutional neural networks all the
way back in 1998 to perform the task of
digit classification um and it actually
worked pretty well but it was really
expensive they didn't have GPUs they
didn't have TPUs they didn't have the
the kind of compute resources that we
did today but the underlying algorithm
the underlying network architecture
basically looks pretty similar in 1998
um to what things were you to to the
kinds of architectures that people were
using well into the 2010s
and then zooming forward from 1998 up
until 2012 um that's when the alexnet
architecture came out and this was kind
of a a big boom like giant explosion of
deep learning especially in computer
vision and I think we talked about this
in some earlier lectures um but the
alexnet architecture again like doesn't
look that different from this yanlun
lenat architecture from 1998 it's a
bunch of convolutional layers fully
connected layers. It's bigger. There's
more layers. The layers have more units
in them. Um but it's still trained end
to end with back propagation to minimize
some fairly simple loss functions. Um
but here like Alexet was when really
things started to take off and at this
time they were able to train on GPUs,
GPUs were available um there was more
data available because of internet
because of imageet. So that's the so
Alexet is when things really started to
take off. Um so then the era from I
think about 2012 to around 2020ish was
an era where convolutional networks were
basically dominating almost every
problem in computer vision. Um they were
sol like basically anything you any kind
of a problem that you wanted to do with
an image. Um in that era it was almost
certainly going to be a comnet that had
the best performance on that problem. So
this this included tasks like detection
on the left um which is the task of not
just classifying an image but drawing a
box around um all the objects in the
image and putting a category label on
the box. Segmentation is the task of
assigning labels not at the box level or
the image level but instead assigning
labels at the pixel level. So now we
want to assign a category label to every
pixel independently in our image. Um and
we'll talk more about architectures for
these problems in future lectures. But
you know these are sol these can be
solved very effectively using
convolutional networks.
People used comments for other kinds of
problems involving language as well. So
the task of image captioning where we
want to predict a a natural language
caption from an image. Uh the some of
the first widely successful approaches
to this problem also were built on
convolutional networks. Um and then even
for even for some more recent tasks of
generative modeling, right? So text to
image text to image uh sorry captioning
is basically the problem of image to
text where we input an image and then
want to output a natural language
sentence describing the image. We can
also think about the inverse problem of
text to image generation where we want
to in input a natural language
description of something that we're
imagining in our head and have the
system generate a new image from scratch
that you know hopefully matches our
input description. Um and some of the
really some of the first really widely
successful uh widely successful versions
of this problem also were built on
convolutional networks. So this uh this
particular figure is from the stable
diffusion paper that came out back in
2021. Um and this you know this has got
this technology has gotten a lot better
in the last couple years and we'll talk
more about that in some later lectures.
But it's useful to point out that this
basically the the first versions of this
that started to work really well were
also built on convolutional networks. So
basically convolutional networks were so
important for this history of computer
vision that the initial version of this
class that we started way back in 2015
was actually called um convolutional
neural networks for visual recognition
because at the time convolutional
networks was basically synonymous with
computer vision. Um and computer vision
was basically the the biggest the
biggest field that was benefiting from
deep learning at that time. So in in
setting out to teach a class about deep
learning, it actually made a lot of
sense to focus entirely on the problem
of convolutional networks for image
problems. Um and that's basically the
inception of this class 10 years ago. Um
but the field has actually evolved a lot
since then, right? Convolutional
networks have actually gotten replaced.
Visual recognition, there's a lot of
other interesting problems that we can
solve now. So you'll notice that the
name of the class changed at some point
along the way um and to no longer focus
so specifically on on neural on
convolutional networks. And the reason
for that is that you know I said this
was the era from 2012 to 2020. You might
be wondering what happened in 2020 other
than co that could have displaced
convolutional networks. Um it wasn't co
it was transformers. Right? So
transformers are this alternate neural
network architecture that we'll talk
about in a couple more lectures. Um but
basically they started off in natural
language processing for processing uh
documents for processing text strings.
Um, and the transformer architecture got
first published in 2017 and for a couple
years after that it mainly stayed in the
regime of processing text. But there was
a really important paper in 2021 that
basically applied nearly the exact same
transformer architecture that had been
getting used to process text to process
strings and instead used it to process
images in nearly the exact same way. Um,
and since then people have found that in
a for a lot of the previous problems
that we just talked about that were
previously solved using convolutional
networks. You could replace the CNN with
a transformer, keep everything else the
same and the problem and you tend to get
better performance on these problems.
They they scale up to more data, they
scale up to more compute. Um, and you
know this is a then we can get more we
can get more data, we can get more
compute. Um, so that so these are much
more commonly used for more and more
computer vision problems these days.
Um, and we'll talk much more about
transformers in lecture 8, but I thought
it would be weird to be pitching comnets
super hard when actually they don't get
used quite as much nowadays as they did
maybe 5 years ago. But I still think
it's really useful to talk about
convolutional networks. Um, one because
there is a lot of historical
significance. Two, these uh these these
algorithms still do get used quite a lot
in practice. Um, three, it helps you
build intuitions about what's important
for images. Um, and four, they're
actually not completely dead, right?
Like a lot of times we're actually
building hybrid systems. Sometimes we
use convolutions, sometimes we use
transformers, sometimes we mix them
together in various ways. So it's
actually super useful to still know
about this stuff.
So then basically um the rest of today
we're going to talk more about
convolutional networks. We said that we
already we said that a convolutional
network is just a computational graph
for processing images that's built from
a couple different primitives. We've
already met the fully connected layer
and the activation function. So we
basically need to walk through these two
more layers of the convolution layer and
the pooling layer. Quick recap of the
fully connected layer. This is what
we've already talked about in the
context of linear classifiers. So with
our fully connected layer, like we said,
basically what we do is we take our
pixels of our image. Our image is this
three-dimensional tensor. 3 32x 32x3.
32x 32 are these two spatial dimensions.
3 are three channel dimensions for your
RGB colors. So we take the that 32x 32x3
vector. You stretch it out into a long
vector of 3072 cuz that's you know if
you multiply those in your head, that's
the number you get. Um and then you have
this basically this vector of 372 3072
numbers. Um we have a weight matrix
that's 3072 by 10 in this case because
10 is the number of output classes that
we want. You do a matrix vector multiply
between those two you end up with with a
vector of 10 numbers giving us our class
score. Um and in particular it's
interest like in trying to generalize
this from fully connected layers to
convolutional layers. It's useful to
think a little bit more about the
structure of what this fully connected
layer is doing. Right? that fully
connected layer. Um the output vector
contains 10 elements. Each one of those
elements is a single number. Each one of
those numbers is predicted by computing
an inner product between one of the rows
of your weight matrix and the entire
input vector. Right? But each each entry
you should basically think of as a dot
productduct. And a dot productduct you
should basically think about as a
template match. Right? Because the dot
productduct between two vectors is high
when the two vectors point the same way
and it's zero when the two vectors are
orthogonal. So anything built on dot
productducts is basically a kind of
template matching. So what the way that
you should think about these fully
connected layers is that we have a set
of templates. Each of the templates has
the same size as our input. Um and then
the output is the template matching
score between each one of our templates
and the entire input. So then once we
think about it that way, there's
actually a nice way we can generalize
this from fully connected layers into
convolutional layers. And that's by
saying, you know, we're still going to
have this notion of template matching.
We're still going to have this notion of
learning a bank of filters, but what
we're going to change is that those
filters will those those templates are
no longer going to have the same shape
as the input. Instead, now our fil now
our filters will have a will only look
at a small subset of the input. So, more
concretely, um, rather than stretching
out our image into a big vector of 372
numbers, instead we're going to maintain
the 3D spatial structure of of our
image. It's going to now be a
three-dimensional tensor um of three
channels, sometimes called depth or
channels dimension. Um 32 width, 32
height. And now one of our filters is
going to be a tiny little sub image, a
tiny lowresolution image, in this case a
5x5 pixel image. Um and importantly that
that that small filter needs to have
three channels. The channels are always
going to span the same as the number of
channels in the input, but the spatial
size will be smaller. And now what we're
going to do is we're going to comput
dotproducts. We think about that small
filter as a little chunk of image
template and we're going to slide it
everywhere across the image and and say
for every point in the image, how much
does that sub portion subport subp part
of the image match this template that
we're learning in our convolutional
filter. So we'll plop that convolutional
filter down at some chunk of the image.
That 5x5x3 filter will line up with some
5x5x3 chunk of the image at that spatial
location. We'll comput an inner product
between those two. And that will give us
one single scalar number telling us how
much does that chunk of the image align
with our template. And now we'll repeat
that process and slide that template
everywhere in our image. And every place
that we plop down that template, it'll
give us we'll again compute this
template matching score that says how
much does that piece of image align with
that one template. And as we slide that
filter everywhere on the input image,
we're going to collect all of those
scores, all of those template matching
scores into a plane, right? And that
plane will now be a two-dimensional a
two-dimensional plane that says
basically for every point in the every
point in the plane now corresponds to
how much did that corresponding piece of
the input image align with our filter.
Um, but of course um this is deep
learning. We want a lot of compute and
how do we get more compute? we have more
filters. So now we'll we'll add a second
filter and we'll say rather we'll we'll
repeat the whole process again um with
another filter. So we'll have we we'll
go to go we had the a 5x5x3 filter that
we colored in blue. Um now let's imagine
a second filter that's now colored in
green. Our second filter will still be
5x 5x3 and we'll repeat the exact same
procedure of sliding that green filter
everywhere on the image. um compute
template matching scores between the
green filter and little sub pieces of
the image and then collect all of those
scores in a second plane telling us you
know for every point in the image how
much did it respond to the green filter
and now we can com and now we can
basically um iterate this and and add as
many filters as we want. Um so then in
this case we are drawing six filters um
each of them is going to be 3x 5x 5 or
3x so yeah 3x 5x 5. So then we can
actually collect all of those filters
into a single four-dimensional tensor.
Right? So that four-dimensional tensor
now has six as a leading dimension
because we have six filters. And then
that 3x 5x5 is that image template. It
is that chunk is that template um that
we're learning. And now the convolution
layer basically takes as input our
three-dimensional input our
three-dimensional image and our
four-dimensional bank of filters slides
slides all the filters everywhere in the
image and gives us these response
planes. So then once we collect all
those response planes and stack them up
in a third dimension then our output has
um has size 6x 28x 28 where 28x 28
should be interpreted as spatial
dimensions that and that six is a
channel dimension. Um and of course
we'll also uh you know just as we do
with linear layers we'll often add a
learnable bias vector as well to our
convolutional layers. So that then in
that sense is sort of in the in a linear
layer a bias is one scaler per row in
the in in the in the linear layer.
Correspondingly in a convolutional layer
we'll have typically one scalar bias
value for every filter in our
convolutional for every for every one of
our convolutional filters. So that means
that we'll have a sixdimensional bias
vector in this in this setting. Yeah the
question was clarifying three is the RGB
channels. Yeah that's correct. Question
is how do you get the filters back to
the miracle of gradient descent and back
propagation. Right. So the idea is that
we're defining this operator. This
operator is going to have an input image
and a and a set of filters, but we but
we no human is going to define what
those filters are going to be. Instead,
we're going to initialize those filters
randomly and then they'll be learned via
gradient descent um on whatever problem
you're trying to solve. So that that's
actually a really important thing to
keep in mind and that that that gives
these these layers their power is that
we're defining this fairly
computationally expensive layer but
we're expecting that it'll be filled in
with um with the data from our with the
data and compute from our training.
Question is how do you how do you set
the five? Um that's a hyperparameter. So
you know we talked about hyperparameters
and cross validation a couple lectures
ago. So these would be architectural
hyperparameters that you would typically
set via cross validation in some way.
Yeah good question. Does it make sense
to have different sizes of filters? So,
as we'll see in the CNN architectures
lecture next lecture, uh some actually I
think you're going to talk about
inception. Um sometimes you sometimes
you actually do have that but that
typically happens at the uh but um for
there there's kind of a nice API design
problem when you're designing what is
the what is a primitive in your
computational graph versus what is going
to be an emergent structure built out of
primitives. So in this case it's we
usually define a single convolutional
layer as having a fixed filter size
because that makes it easier to compute
and write efficient GPU kernels. But if
you you can effectively have multiple
multiply sized filters by stitching
together a computational graph that
combines convolution layers with
different filter sizes in a larger
network structure. So it's sort of yes
and no is the answer to your question.
The question is what are we learning? Um
and this is very important to
distinguish between a parameter versus a
hyperparameter. So a hyperparameter is
something that we set before we start
training the network. So in this case,
one one of the hyperparameters would be
the number of filters and the size of
those filters because those set the the
shapes of our tensor, right? So then and
a parameter is a value that we're going
to set and optimize over the course of
gradient descent. So in this case, the
number of filters, the number of output
channels, the size of those filters,
those will be hyperparameters. We set
those once before we start training. At
the beginning of training, we'll
randomly initialize the filters and then
the value that will that will give us a
fixed shape fixedsized tensor and then
the values inside of that tensor will
float around and change over the course
of optimization. So that's the so then
those are parameters because they get
set via grad via gradient descent. Yes,
the question is what gradient are we
computing? Whenever you whenever you do
back propagation, you're always
computing gradient of the loss with
respect to things inside the network. So
in this case we'll be computing gradient
of the loss with respect to the
individual scaler with respect to our
our convolutional filter weights. So
that's basically saying you know what is
a gradient that's saying for every
individual scalar inside of every one of
our filters if we wiggle that scaler a
little bit then how much is the loss
going to change. So then the gradient of
the loss with respect we're always
computing gradient of the loss with
respect to our our convolutional
filters. The question is basically like
what do we do with the bias? So, so
basically the bias would be added to
each of our inner products, right? So,
then we'll always compute like inner
product of one of our filters against a
chunk of the image and then add the
corresponding scaler from the bias. The
bias is is a is a vector, but the number
of entries in the vector is equal to the
number of filters. So then each each
entry in the bias gets basically
broadcast across the entire spatial
dimension in the output. Um, but each
bias only gets used for one bias gets
used for one filter. So conceptually you
basically one filter you slide
everywhere that gives us a
two-dimensional plane of activations
right and then if you have a second
filter you get a second plane of
activations those are independent
operators right like step one um slide
first filter everywhere step two slide
the second filter everywhere every
filter gives rise to a plane um a plane
of of a plane that we call an activation
map and then we stack all of those up um
and that's that's the operation of the
convolution layer question is yeah
basically after every gradient descent
every time we do gradient descent sent
um it's going to change the filters,
right? So whenever you whenever you
imagine training a neural network, it's
always this loop of like while true get
a batch of data, send your data through
the network, forward pass, compute loss,
um backward pass, compute gradient with
respect to loss, and now make a gradient
step using your optimizer. So then it's
always going to be data forward loss
backward step and then every time you do
a step, it's going to make a change to
the filters.
All right, so I I I swung the other way.
I said more questions. I got too many
questions. Um but that's good. We'll
we'll kind of equalize in here. Okay. So
then uh we talked about the convolution
layer. Um you know it's actually pretty
common in the convolution layer to work
on it in a batched mode. So rather than
working on one input image, we'll
actually work on a batch of input
images. So this this is kind of nice cuz
it makes everything four-dimensional.
Now we have a four-dimensional tensor of
inputs which is a set of input images.
We have a four-dimensional tensor of
filters which is a set of filters each
of which is a threedimensional chunk of
an image. And then the output is a
four-dimensional uh is a
four-dimensional tensor which is a set
of outputs. Each output one output per
image. Each images output is a
three-dimensional tensor giving a stack
of feature planes. Um you you have to
start to think in lots of dimensions
when you start to build neural networks.
And that's actually kind of fun. Um so
then here's kind of the general
formulation of a convolution layer. um
is that in general you're going to take
as input a fourdimensional tensor of n
by cn by h by w which is a set of n
images. Each of those n images has c
channels. Um for the case of an RGB
image that'll be three but we might in
general have more than c more than three
channels. This could be arbitrary. Um
and then h and w is the spatial size of
our input images. Our convolutional
filters will be a four-dimensional
tensor of shape C out by C in by KW by
KH. K C out is the number of filters.
the number of output channels. Um CN is
you know and then the rest of that are
threedimensional filters. So it's a set
of threedimensional filters. Um each
threedimensional filter has shape C in
by KW by KH. That's the kernel width and
kernel height. And then we have C out
such filters that could collect it into
a four-dimensional tensor. And then as
output we're going to produce a
four-dimensional tensor again where the
shape is N for the number of images one
output per image. C out. Each of those
outputs is going to consist of C out
feature planes um one per filter. And
then each of those planes is going to be
H prime by WP prime. Um and this is kind
of the general formulation of a con
layer.
And then a convolutional network is just
a network is just a computational graph
that includes a bunch of con layers. So
in practice we'll tend to stack up a
bunch of convolutional operators one
after another. Um and in stacking a
bunch of convolutional operators that
will be that will be a convolutional
network. Um so this was kind of a simple
connet. You know we start with an image
that's 3x 32x 32. Um then we have a con
layer that has six filters. Each filter
is 5x5x3. Then after we do the first
convolution that gives us a new
three-dimensional set of activations for
that one image where it we have six
channels that matches the six filters
28x 28 because the spatial size changed
a little bit through the convolution.
Then we have another convolution that
now has 10 filters which each of which
is 5x 5x 6. So the 10 is going to give
us the output dimen the output
dimensions in the next layer of the
convolution. Um and this six is going to
be the number of channels that needs to
match up the channel dimension here of
the input to the convolution. Um so you
can kind of see like you you can just
stack up a bunch of these convolution
layers and perform a lot of computation.
But there's actually a problem in
exactly this network archite
architecture design. And can anybody
spot it? sizing. Uh, that that's a
problem. Not the one I had in mind. Are
local. That's another good problem. Not
the one I had in mind. Uh, actually
those two we'll be able to fix pretty
easily in a couple slides, but I had a
different problem in mind. A lot of
memory. Uh, that is a problem, but not
one we can fix. You just got to buy a
bigger GPU.
Number of filters increases. Uh, I don't
think that's a problem necessarily.
That's okay. Ah, everything's linear.
Yes, that is a problem. Right. So, we
said that convolution was dot was
dotproducts. Dot product is a linear
operator. um composition of two linear
operators is still a linear operator. So
that means that if we have two
convolution layers stacked directly on
top of each other, they actually have
the same representational power as a
single convolution layer because because
of the linearity of the operator. Um
there's actually a very simple fix to
that. Add an activation function.
Exactly. So it's the same actually the
same bug that we saw in multi-layer
neural networks and the same fix. We
need to add a nonlinear activation
function in between our convolutional
layers if we want. This introduces
nonlinearity to the problem.
nonlinearity to the to the to the
network architecture and increases the
representational power of the network
that we're learning. So you know com in
general com nets are going to be some
stack of convolution layers
nonlinearities and other kinds of other
kinds of layers in our computational
graph. There was a question earlier
about what do the convolutional filters
learn. Um this is basically we can view
this by but by analogy with what we
already did in linear classifiers. So in
linear classifiers we have this
intuition where each row could be
visualized each row of the learned
weight matrix could be thought of as a
template that has the same shape as the
whole input image. Now with a
convolutional filter um you can you can
think of it the same way but now each
filter rather than extending over the
entire spatial size of the input image
is going to be just a small subpiece a
sub chunk of an image. So we can
actually visualize the first uh we can
actually visualize the first layer
convolution filters um of a trained
neural network. So these are some these
are the first layer convolution filters
that are learned by an alexn net
architecture that was trained for image
classification on imageet. Um and here
each of these are basically little
chunks of RGB images. These are the
little templates that get slid around
the input image in the first layer of
the alexnet architecture. Um, and you
know, the fact that this was AlexNet,
the fact that this was trained on
imageet, the fact that this was
classification, um, it turns out just
about all convolutional networks end up
learning filters that look something
like this, um, on almost all problems
and almost all data sets and tasks as
long as they're sort of reasonable
tasks. Um, and the the thing we see is
that we often learn two kinds of filters
in here. Um, one tends to be looking for
colors, especially opposing colors. So,
you'll see like this one is looking for
a contrast between green and red. We
also see colored blobs like pink and
green blobs. And the other category of
filter we tend to see are looking as
looking for somehow the spatial
structure of the images. So like this
one is looking for a vertical edge, a
horizontal edge. These are this one is
looking for a vertical edge. Some of
these are looking for a diagonal edg
edges. So they tend to look for colors
and edges um and like these little these
in these little local neighborhoods of
our input images. Um, so we can play
this trick on the first layer of the
convolutional filter and just visualize
them directly as images. It gets a
little bit trickier to visualize the
higher layers in the network. Um, and I
I'm not going to explain this figure.
I'm just going to present it without too
much too much explanation. But, um,
higher layers of the network tend to
learn larger spatial structures of our
input image. Um here the visualization
is like each row represents a filter in
in a learned network and each column
represents some piece of an input image
that that filter was responding strongly
to. So the the visualization here is is
a bit different than the previous slide.
Um so these are all basically chunks of
input images that a filter was
responding to. And here you can see that
this sixth layer convolution, one of
these filters feels like it's responding
maybe to eyes. This one looks like maybe
it's responding to pieces of text. Um,
this one looks like maybe it's
responding to wheels or or circles or
top halves of circles, something like
that. Um, and again like these this all
sort of gets driven via gradient descent
via training on your large scale data
sets via gradient descent. Uh, nobody's
sort of sitting down and designing these
filters by hand. Um, and like I said,
visualizing these higher layer filters
is a bit tricky and more involved.
Question was um, if you if you if you
look at all the responses to the
filters, can you reconstruct the
original image? Actually, it turns out
you can do that. And the trick that and
the way that you do that is also
gradient descent. Um gradient sense is
really powerful and that's something
that we'll talk about I think in a
couple more lectures on some some
mechanisms that do that. Oh that's a
good question. How do you how do the how
do the filters get differentiated? um
that actually comes down to the random
initialization, right? So then it's
really important that the way you
initialize your filters um is random and
and they have and and crucially that you
have a different initialization for each
filter when you start training your
network. Um because that's going to
break the symmetry between the filters,
right? Because if all the filters are
exactly the same, um the loss is the
same, then that gradient is going to
broadcast back and be the same on all
the filters. So if you initialize them
the same, they will stay the same. Um
but if you initialize them to be
different, then you'll break the
symmetry and they can learn different
features.
>> Yeah. Basically the the the human
designer of the network needs to write
down what is the sequence of operators
and the sequence of channels and that's
the question of neural network
architecture design that we'll talk a
little bit more about in the next
lecture.
Good question is how do we like why is
it the deeper layers visualize larger
structures that actually has a bit to do
with the receptive fields that we have a
slide on in a couple in a in a little
bit. So maybe maybe we'll get there and
I think a couple more some of these
questions will get answered. Um so one
thing that already came up is how do we
look at the spatial dimensions of these
convolutions? Um so I wanted to take a
take a look a closer look at exactly how
we compute the spatial dimensions of our
convolutions. Right? So in this case um
here we've taken this picture of a con
this picture of a convolution. We're
rotating at 90° and dropping the channel
dimension. So now the channel dimension
is going into the board. Um and then we
have our 7x7 spatial dimensions. So here
we're looking at an input that's 7 by 7
in spatial size and we have a 3x3 com
kernel. And then the question is how big
is our output going to be here?
Well, 1 2 3 4 5, right? So, our output
is going to be 5 by five because we can
slide that filter and plop it down in
five different spaces. Um, and then we
can generalize it, right? If our input
has has length w, our com filter has
length k, then our output is going to be
w minus k + one. And you can sit down
and convince yourself that that's the
right formula. Um, but there's kind of a
problem that actually a couple people
already pointed out is that your feature
maps are going to shrink in spatial size
as you go through this convolution. um
that's kind of annoying. Um it's
actually like you could actually work
with that and there are some neural
network architectures that deal with
that. But sometimes we're lazy and we
just want to keep the same size for
everything because that's just basically
simpler for human designers to think
about. Um and one trick that we do there
is something called padding. So here
it's common to add additional data like
virtual data around the input of your
around your true input data um that
you're going to like basically add extra
zeros um around before you compute the
convolution operator. Um and now in this
this basically lets us solve this
shrinking feature map problem because
now if we have um you know add padding
of P in this case we have padding P
equals 1. So we're adding one pixel of
zeros all around everywhere then we we
basically add 2 P to our output size. So
in particular if you have a three if you
have like a 3x3 con and you add padding
of one then your your feature map is
going to stay the same size and that's
convenient. Um now if you've taken
signal processing there actually are
some problems here right like this can
lead to weird weirdness in from a signal
processing perspective but we'll ignore
that and we'll just look at the sizes
sizes and shapes of the tensors because
that's that's a little bit easier to
comprehend but be aware like why are we
putting zeros is that going to cause
problems yes it is going to cause
problems on the borders but it seems to
be okay in a lot of cases
okay yeah so then like I said a pretty
common setting is to set p is to have
actually k be an odd number um and then
have P be k minus 1 /2 because that's
going to mean that your your your your
spatial size after convolution is the
same as the spatial size before the
convolution.
Okay. Then the next interesting thing to
think about is this notion of receptive
fields. Someone was asking a little bit
uh over here why do the deeper layers
learn larger structures? That's actually
sort of inherent in the way that
convolutions are built. Right? So in
thinking about a single convolution um
each output is looking at this local
region of an input. Right? So by design
the output of one convolution at the
first layer can only be looking at a
piece of the image which is the same
size as the convolutional kernel that
you're learning. But if we build a
convenant that's stacking multiple
convolutions on top of each other then
these receptive fields get magnified
through the network. So then you in this
case we're looking at a at a network
with three convolution layers and we see
that um in the in the final layer of
activations each entry here depends on a
local region in the in the in the layer
before it. But each one of those entries
depends in turn on a local region in the
layer before it which depends in turn on
a local region in the layer before it.
So when you have these convolutions,
even though each individual convolution
is looking at a local neighborhood in
the layer before it, as you stack up
convolutions in a bunch of layers, then
the effective size of the original input
that each of those convolutions is
looking at grows in the grows over the
course of the network. And in
particular, um this this uh this this we
call the effective receptive field. So
the effective receptive field of a
convolution is basically how many pixels
in the original image um had the
opportunity to influence um one one
activation of the network you know later
on downstream.
And you'll notice that the convolution
actually the this effective receptive
field basically grows linearly with the
number of convolution layers. Um, and
there's a potential problem here is
because ultimately when we make
classification decisions at the end of
our network, we would like our
classification decisions to basically
aggregate global information across the
entire image. Um, but you need a lot of
comp layers to do it. So a trick there
is um basically to add some kind of way
to increase effective receptive fields
more quickly. One way that we can do
this in convolution is by introducing
something called a stride. So here what
we're saying is that rather than placing
the filter everywhere in the image,
we're going to skip some. So we're going
to instead of moving the field moving
the receptive field with one, we're
going to stride it by two instead. So
now in this case, we go back to our 7x7
input 3x3 con do a stride two. Now
what's the output size? 1 2 3 3x3. Um
and then in general if we have our input
W filter size K padding of P stride S
then we get this kind of ugly formula
for the size of the output W minus K.
The uh bigger kernels shrink the input
plus 2 P um padding adds back some of
the missing size divided by the stride.
The stride you know divides the input
shape and then plus one because that's
how because of some fence post fence
post math.
Okay. So then the strided convolutions
are interesting because if you go back
to this picture now when we do a strided
convolution it's effectively
downsampling the image inside the neural
network. So then when we have a strided
convolution then each con layer is
effectively like dividing the the shape
of the feature map usually by two and
then when we stack these that means that
now you can get exponential growth in
the effective receptive field. So if you
stack you know a bunch of con players
and each of those con layers is actually
downsampling by a factor of two. Then if
you run through a similar exercise
you'll see that that the effective
receptive field is now growing
exponentially in the depth of the
network. So that means that with very
with relatively few layers we can build
up a very large effective receptive
field that looks at the entire input
image.
Um okay so here let's work through just
one one example to make sure that we all
are on the same page about convolution.
So here let's think about an input
volume 3x 32x32. Let's think about a
convolution layer with 10 filters. Each
of those filters is 5 x5 um with stride
one pad 2. What's the size of the
output? I color coded it because there's
a lot of numbers here to keep to keep
track of. Right? So here um it's 10 x
32x 32. This 32 is actually a different
32 than this 32. So that's why they're
different colors of blue. Um right, but
this 10 is the number of output
channels. Output channels has to match
the number of filters. Um and the
spatial size is computed using that
formula that we just saw. So then the
input spatial size comes down here. Um
plus two plus the padding comes down
here. Padding adds the spatial size. Um
five is the convolutional kernel that
divides the spatial size. Stride of one.
So that's trivial. And then add one. And
this just so happens to come out to 32.
Um so in this case this follows the same
pattern that we talked about a couple
slides ago where it's a five where it's
an oddshaped convolutional kernel. In
this case five, the padding is 2. So if
the kernel size is is 2k + one then
padding of k means we maintain the same
spatial size
number of learnable parameters here
maybe I'll just go through these cuz uh
we have a couple more slides to get
through um so here um in this case
number of learnable parameters is 760
because we have um each filter is
basically 3x5 x5 um and we have one for
the bias so we have 76 learnable
parameters per filter we have 10 filters
so it's 760 multiple 760 learnable
parameters here. We can also compute the
number of multiply ad operations. How
much compute does this convolution
kernel how much compute does this
convolution operator take? So here it's
it's a lot seven. Well, is it a lot? I
don't know. I don't have a lot. You may
not you may or may not have a lot of
intuition for what is a lot of
computation. But in this case, um the
way that I think about computing how
many flops, how much how much compute
does a convolution operator take. We
think about the output volume size is
10x 32x 32. And we know that each entry
in that output volume was computed via a
dot productduct. A dot productduct in
particular between one of our filters
and a chunk of our input. So in this
case we know the total flops because we
know the number of outputs is 10 x 32x
32 which is about 10,000. And then each
of those outputs is computed via a
dotproduct of a 3x5x5 um filter and a
3x5x5 chunk of the image. So that's 75
elements. So um multiplying those
together together means it takes about
768,000 floating point uh multiply ad
operations.
Okay. So then here's the kind of oneline
sum one one slide summary of
convolution. I'm not going to walk
through this. This is more for your for
you to look at later but this just
summarizes all the hyperparameters and
the formulas associated with convolution
layers. Um if you look in PyTorch,
PyTorch is the deep learning framework
that a lot of people use. Um there
you'll see um this convolution layer has
all these hyperparameters that we talked
about. There's a couple other
interesting hyperparameters that we
didn't talk about called group groups
and dilation. Um dilation isn't really
used so much anymore. Groups still get
used sometimes. Um and but maybe we'll
talk about those in a later lecture. Um
you can have other kind other kinds of
convolutions too. Um so we talked about
2D convolution. We can also do 1D
convolution. um where rather than having
a two-dimensional signal that we slide a
filter over, we now have a two like a
one-dimensional signal that we slide a
filter over in one with one degree of
freedom or a threedimensional
convolution where we have a
three-dimensional signal, a
three-dimensional filter and now you can
slide that filter everywhere in 3D space
to convolve with the input signal. So
this idea of a convolution really
extends beyond just two dimen two
dimensional images.
Okay, that's basically all about
convolution. Um and the last one is
pooling. Thankfully, pooling is pretty
simple. So, pooling layers are basically
another way to downsample inside of your
neural network. So, we saw that strided
convolution is one way that we can down
sample inside of a neural network. And
down sampling is useful because it lets
us build up receptive fields more
quickly as we go through the through the
depth of the network. Um, but
convolution actually still costs quite a
lot of computation. So, convolution, you
know, is where the most of the most of
the flops, most of the compute happens
in a convolutional network. And pooling
layers are basically a way to downsample
um that's very very cheap that doesn't
cost a lot of compute. And the idea in
in a pooling layer is given our
three-dimensional tensor um where in
this case 64x12 x112 you should think
about that as um a spat like a
threedimensional volume of features
where the spatial size is 112 x12 and we
have 64 planes 64 channels of
activation. So now what we're going to
and each one of those planes is a is a
112 x12 image. But then what we're going
to do is take each one of those
individual feature planes, pull it out
from our input tensor and down sample
them independently and then restack them
to compute the output. So then this uh
input 64x224 x 224, we're going to pull
out each of those 224 x24 planes
independently down sample it and then
restack them to give an same number of
channels um but change in the spatial
size. What is the method we use for
downsampling? Great question. Um so uh
the way there's actually that's actually
a hyperparameter. There's a couple
different mechanisms of downsampling
that we use. Um, one of the common one,
one of the most common ones to use is
actually max is called max pooling. Um,
so in max pooling, what we're going to
do is um take our single depth slice,
divide it up into non-over overlapping
regions. In this case, these are two uh
and and we often use and we use the same
terminology to talk about these as we do
with convolution. So this we this we
could say it's a kernel size 2x two with
stride of two um because that that then
that divides our inputs into these
non-over overlapping 2x2 tiles. Then
within each of those non-over
overlapping 2x two tiles, we'll take the
max entry. In this case, it's a 6, 8, 3,
4. So then you take the max entry inside
each of those. And then that and then
that that gives us our spatial
compression. Um, and there's a whole you
can imagine a whole set of
hyperparameters here. You could say what
is the kernel size? You could change the
kernel size. You can change the stride.
You can also change the function that we
use for downsampling. Um, max pooling is
pretty common. You'll also see average.
You'll also see anti-alias downpooling
sometimes. Um, so these are all just
ways that you can downsample these
feature maps one at a time. Uh, good
question. Do we make a use of padding?
Um, typically you do not use padding
inside of inside of pooling layers. Um,
there's nothing mathematically
preventing you from doing so. Um, but in
the case of max pooling, it would be
kind of silly. It's basically equivalent
to aru. Um, and when so whenever you're
using max pooling, if you're also using
aru, that would be redundant. Um, so
typically we don't use padding in in
pooling layers. I'm actually not sure if
PyTorch has a flag for pooling for
padding or not in in pooling layers.
Yeah. So the the stride would be another
one of these architectural
hyperparameters. Um but usually you
don't tune these things too much. Um
usually the intuition behind a pooling
layer like honestly the most common is I
want to down sample my I want to
downsample everything by a factor of two
is the mo is like by far the most common
operation. So then the most common thing
to do would be 2x two stride 2.
Sometimes you'll do like two 4x4 stride
two, but basically the most common
settings by far is I want to down sample
my everything by a factor of exactly
two. Oh, that's a very good question.
Uh, do images all have to be the same
input size? Um, in all the language that
we're talking about so far, yes. Um,
you're going to run into big problems if
your image if your input images are not
the same size. So then things that
you'll typically do to fix that would be
like one you either resize all your
images to the exact same size before you
batch them to feed to the network. Um
sometimes you'll also pad your images
out with zeros or some other value to
make them all the same size but now
padded rather than warped. Um or you
need to basically run these layers
independently for images of different
aspect ratios. Um so that's another
thing that you'll do sometimes um in
more sophisticated training setups is
that sometimes you'll do what's known as
like aspect ratio bucketing. So then
from your training data you'll bucket
them into different aspect ratios and
then each forward backward pass of the
network will be on a on a batch of
images of the same resolution and aspect
ratio but then each iteration you might
grab images with different resolutions
or aspect ratios but that's something
that you'll see in some of the more
common larger production systems. Yeah.
So the question is where do you put
these? Um these are usually interspersed
with the convolution layers. So a pretty
common architecture a pretty common
pattern for comn nets is to intersperse
the convolution and pooling. So for
example, you'll see like com pool comcom
pool comcom pool fully connected fully
connected is kind of a prototypical
convolutional network.
>> Yes, that's an extra excellent question.
Does this introduce nonlinearity? So it
depends on the type of pooling operation
that you're using. So if you're doing
max pooling that's a nonlinearity. So um
in some networks if you have a max
pooling you may you may not use a relu
around that convolution because a max
pooling is a nonlinearity itself. If
it's an average pooling, um, that's also
a linear operator. So then if you do
average pooling, it's linear. So then
you probably still would want a relu
there.
Okay. So then here's my my quick oneside
summary of pooling. Um, it's basically
the same hyperparameters as convolution.
Um, except you've got this extra pooling
function which is what is the mechanism
you're using to do the downsampling.
Um, then the last thing I wanted to
mention is this notion of translation
equivariance. What the hell is that? Um,
so I said at the beginning of the of the
beginning of the lecture that we wanted
operators that are respecting the
spatial structure of our images, right?
And that we have this notion that
flattening our images into big vectors
is somehow not respecting the spatial
structure of of our images. So there's a
really interesting property that is
shared by both convolution and pooling
which is one way to more for to
formalize this notion of them respecting
the 2D spatial structure of the images
and that's this notion of translation
equariance. So it sounds like it sounds
pretty crazy but the idea is we can
imagine two different operators uh two
different branches um along one branch
we can imagine taking our image doing a
convolution or pooling operator to get
an updated image and then translating
the result by shifting that feature map
to the side by for example then you
could imagine changing the order of
these two things instead. What we could
have done instead is first translate the
image and then do our convolution or
pool operator on top of the translated
image. And it and it just so happens
that in this case the order doesn't
matter. If you translate and then
convolution, you get the same result as
if you had done convolution and then
translate um subject to some boundary
conditions blah blah blah blah blah.
like in in sort of the limit of
infinitely large images and blah blah
blah blah blah ignoring this ignoring
some of these technical conditions. Um
it's really interesting that you can
actually swap the order of translation
in space versus performing these these
downsampling or convolution operators.
Um and that bakes in an important
intuition about images which is that
when we're processing images um pro we
the the features that we extract from an
image should only depend on the content
of the image and should not depend on
where in the image that where the
absolute location in the image that
content came from. So that means that
you know if I'm looking this way it
looks like people it looks like people
and benches. If I'm looking this way it
looks like people and benches. and the
fact that it's over here on my right and
the fact that it's over here on my left,
I want to process that data in the exact
same way. And that's an important um
intuition, an important structure of
that we want to of of images and of the
kind of 2D data that we're processing.
And the and this notion of translation
equariance basically is a way to
mathematically describe how that
structure is baked into these operators.
Um so this is kind of interesting um
that it's it's a way that we can build
in our intuition about how images ought
to be processed um through the design of
our operators not through the design of
our of our feature extraction methods as
we saw at the beginning. The question is
why do you do a translation? You you
don't like this is not something you're
actually going to do. Um this is
basically a mathematical cur curiosity,
right? To be clear that you should not
generally do this inside of your neural
networks. Um this is basically like it's
interesting to note that this happens to
be true but you would not do this inside
of your neural networks.
Um and if you if you were a
mathematician you call this a commutive
diagram and mathematicians love those
things.
Okay so that's basically the summary of
today. Um we talked about convolutional
networks. We talked about you know why
they're interesting. We talked about
these two new operators of convolution
and pooling. And then next lecture we'll
see how to stitch those together into
CNN architectures. Um and see you next
time for that.