So hopefully everyone's having
a good time with assignment one.
It's due tonight.
Let us know if you
need an extension.
Assignment two is
coming out soon.
We're putting on the
finishing touches
onto some of the Triton stuff.
Hopefully, you'll enjoy it.
You'll get to implement
FlashAttention two or parts
of FlashAttention two,
which I think will be nice.
So today we're going
to talk about GPUs.
GPUs are the thing that
makes our language models go.
So they're pretty
critical to get right.
And if you haven't
really studied
the hardware that
makes your models run,
they can seem pretty mysterious.
So my goal today is to try to
make CUDA and GPUs less magic.
And one of the things that
I want to demystify-- you
don't have to
understand the plot.
There's a lot on
the slide I know--
why do GPUs get slow.
And they get slow in
very mysterious ways.
I will try to talk through this
plot towards the end of lecture.
As you increase the size
of your matrix multiplies,
you might expect either gets
slower or faster or whatever.
You get these very unpredictable
looking wave like patterns
and you're like, why is my
GPU fast at certain multiples
of certain numbers
and slow at others.
It's very mysterious.
We'll try to understand that.
The other thing is we
would like to understand
how to make fast algorithms.
I think almost all of you
have heard of flash attention.
It's the thing that makes
much longer contexts possible
by very cleverly
computing the attention
operation inside a transformer.
And so maybe you
would like to come up
with new algorithms
or new implementations
like flash attention.
Like what primitives
and what components
do we need to understand in
order to be able to do that.
So those are the two
learning goals of today.
The first one is by
the end of the lecture,
you should feel
comfortable with GPUs.
You should understand
how they work.
And the second one is you should
feel comfortable accelerating
certain parts of
your algorithms.
You make a new architecture,
you should hopefully
feel like you can try to
accelerate that with CUDA.
And because hardware is not
necessarily the domain in which
I work.
There's special resources that
I have to give a lot of credit
to, especially Horace
He's blog, where
he's got a lot of fun GPU
facts that you can learn about.
For example, why are
matrix multiplies that
are filled with zeros
faster than ones
that are not filled
with zeros, you
can learn by going to his blog.
There's also other resources
that I've drawn from,
like the CUDA mode group and
the nice TPU book from Google.
If this topic interests you,
I'd encourage you to go and look
at those resources
to learn more,
because this is in some
ways like a shallow
but hopefully, complete
coverage of the hardware.
So today we're only going to
focus on non-parallel parts
of the hardware stack.
So we're going to study the
GPU, like a single accelerator
in depth how they work
in some important parts.
I'm also going to talk very,
very briefly about TPUs,
because in some ways, they're
very similar conceptually
to a GPU.
And so my discussion here
is going to carry over.
And then once we understand
the hardware and execution
model of the GPU,
then we're going
to try to understand
what makes GPUs go fast
on certain workloads,
what makes them slow.
We're going to understand
the performance.
And in the last
part, this is kind
of going to be almost
like a hands-on piece.
I'm going to try to walk
through FlashAttention.
I'm going to take all the
lessons that we've learned
and try to walk you through
FlashAttention saying, see,
here's how it all
comes together.
So that's the last part
of today's lecture.
So many of you have
taken an NLP course.
And these days in
an NLP course, I
think you teach some
amount of scaling laws.
And so you've probably
seen this, right?
And so this is just
setting the context.
We know that having
more compute is
helpful for training
large language models.
This is a pre-training
scaling chart.
But you could replace this
with an inference scaling chart
if you would like.
It's generally agreed upon
that the more compute you have,
the more processing you
can do on your data.
You can ingest more data.
You can train larger models.
All of those lead to
improved performance.
So you might think of
course, deep learning
is really important.
But what's really
driven performance
is faster hardware,
better utilization,
improved parallelization.
So that's setting the
stage of why hardware
is important to understand.
And of course, once you think
about compute scaling you ask,
OK, how do we get
compute scaling?
How do we get our
models to train faster?
So in the early days, of
semiconductor scaling,
if you were thinking
about, OK, CPUs,
how do they get faster, they
would scale under something
called Dennard scaling.
With Moore's law, you would
double the amount of transistors
on a chip every year.
And if you have this
doubling, what you end up
is Dennard scaling where smaller
and smaller transistors can
be driven at faster
and faster clock speeds
with lower and lower power,
which in turn give you
more performance.
And then in the 1980s to
2000, this tapped out.
You can see in this chart
here by Hennessy and Patterson
that single thread performance,
that's the blue dots here,
that basically
started to taper out.
Of course, the
number of transistors
didn't really start falling off.
You did have chips with higher
and higher transistor densities.
But that wasn't helpful.
It wasn't giving you higher
throughput on single threads.
And so, this means that we
can't just do computation faster
in absolute terms.
What we have to make up for
it with is parallel scaling.
So the story of scaling for deep
learning and neural networks
is going from single-thread
scaling, which is just
doing your computation
faster in absolute terms,
to parallel scaling where
you have a lot of workloads
that are all computed at once.
And this is one of my
favorite compute scaling
charts by Bill Dally
and his keynote
where he's showing the
super exponential increase
in the number of integer
operations per second,
going from the earliest
K20's to the H100.
And it's this really
remarkable exponential
or super exponential curve.
And so we have to
really understand
how to take advantage
of this curve
in order to really get the
most out of our language model.
So that's kind of
going to be our goal.
And so I've already
hinted at this kind
of important difference, right?
CPU is something
that I think everyone
is familiar with once you
start doing programming.
It's this execution model.
If you have a program,
it goes through.
And in a single thread,
it executes step
by step what's happening.
And in order to support that
kind of an execution model, what
do you need?
Well, you need
big control units.
You just need to generally
run these things very quickly
because you have
a lot of branching
and you have a lot of
conditional control logic.
So a CPU-- this is an
abstracted diagram--
is going to dedicate
a lot of its chip
towards large control
branch prediction.
And it's going to run these
very quickly because it
doesn't have that many threads.
There are CPUs with lots
and lots of cores now.
But compared to a GPU
it's almost nothing.
And so in contrast, the GPU
has really tons and tons
of compute units ALUs.
So those are the
little green boxes.
And there's much smaller
amounts of the chip dedicated
to control.
So there's a little bit of
control logic orchestrating
tons and tons of compute
units operating in parallel.
And I think
mentally-- so this is
the picture of what
is being emphasized
in a CPU versus a GPU.
But if you look at what's
the design goals are,
they designed for
very different goals.
So you can think about CPUs
as optimizing for latency.
I want to finish my tasks
as quickly as possible.
So if I have tasks T1 through
T4 here on the right side,
in a CPU, I'm going to
try to finish each task as
quickly as possible.
And so if you want
any one of these tasks
to be finished
quickly, T1 is going
to complete really quickly.
In GPU, you're optimizing
for high throughput.
I don't care about latency,
I just want all of my tasks
that I have in aggregate, to
complete as quickly as possible.
And to support that, maybe
you have lots of threads
and these threads can go to
sleep and wake up very quickly.
And in the end, you finish
all of your workload T1
through T4 before
the CPU 1 does,
even though individually all
of these have higher latency.
So they have different design
principles and design goals.
OK.
And so a GPU has a
pretty different anatomy.
And I don't know if you all have
ever looked at what a GPU layout
diagram looks like.
I'll actually show you the
chip figures in a moment here.
But the core idea, and this is
important conceptual concepts
behind a GPU, is that a GPU
executes many, many SM streaming
multiprocessors.
And a streaming
multiprocessor you
can think of as an atomic unit.
When you're programming
in something like Triton,
they're going to operate
at the level of an SM.
And within each SM,
they're going to--
it contains many SPs,
Streaming Processors,
and a streaming
processor is going
to execute a whole bunch
of threads in parallel.
So one way to think about it is
SM has a bunch of control logic.
It can decide what to execute.
It can do for
example, branching.
SPs are going to operate--
to take the same instruction
and apply it to many
different pieces of data.
And so you can do tons and
tons of parallel computation.
Under this model, an SM is
each granular unit of control.
SP can do a lot of
computation individually.
And if you look at an A100,
which is the previous generation
GPU, at this point
you've got 128 SMS.
That's a lot more than
most cores for CPUs.
And each of these
systems is going
to have a very
large number of SPs
and specialized matrix
multiply units inside them.
And so that's kind
of the compute model.
Was there a question?
Sorry.
Yeah.
[INAUDIBLE] back to the other
slide before Anatomy of GPUs.
So is this GPU the
same as that GPU?
So the question was, is this
GPU the same as that GPU?
Yes.
Like this is a kind of
cartoon version of this.
You can think of each
row as being an SM.
It's got its own control
units, and each green block
might be one of these
green blocks here,
like a FP32 processing
unit inside of it.
And each SM can
operate various pieces
that it owns, like the tensor
cores to do computation.
Cool.
OK.
And there's going to be
two important things.
You think of GPUs as computers.
They compute.
But actually computation is only
one of the two important things
we have to keep track of.
Memory is arguably more
important, at this point,
and it will continue to
be more important in terms
of the performance
profiles of how
we run our programs on the GPU.
And so to understand
memory, you have
to understand the physical
layout of the GPU and the chip,
because in some
sense, when you're
operating at such fast
speeds, the physical proximity
of the memory starts
to matter quite a bit.
And so I will show you
the physical proximity
of how things are
laid out and how
that relates to how you should
think about memory access
and performance.
So the closer a piece
of memory is to each SM,
the faster it's going to be.
So there's going to be certain
very, very, very fast kinds
of memory, like L1
and shared memory,
and that's going to
live inside of the SM.
And that's going
to be really fast.
Things like registers, things
you're reading and writing
very frequently, you're
going to want to put
into the L1 and shared memory.
L2 cache, as you
can see, there's
these green areas which are SMs.
And then there's
these blue areas.
This is on the GPU chip.
These are L2 memory that's
right next to the SMs.
So they're not inside
the SMs, but they're
physically still quite close.
And these are still pretty fast.
They're still a
factor of 10 slower,
but they're still
reasonably fast.
And then outside of
the chip itself, I
think this is like a 3090 card
or something like this, or maybe
a PCIe A100.
Oh, this is a PCIe A100.
You've got your GPU here,
and you've got actually
DRAM living next to the chip.
So it has to actually go
physically outside of the chip
and connect.
And you can see on
this chip diagram
here these yellow
connectors at the edges.
These are HBM connectors.
These are connecting
to the DRAM chips that
are outside of the actual GPU.
And you can see the speed that
it takes to access these, right?
The on SM memory is
much, much faster,
like 20 clock cycles to
access something from there,
whereas it's going to take
something like 200 or 300 clock
cycles to access something from
the L2 cache or global memory.
And this factor of 10 is
going to hurt you real bad.
So if you have a
piece of computation
that requires you to
access global memory,
it might mean that
you actually run out
of work to do on your SM.
You've multiplied
all the matrices.
You've run out.
Now you just have to idle.
So you utilization
won't be good.
And this will be a really
key theme, thinking
about memories in some sense.
The key to thinking
about how GPUs work.
And in assignment
two, you're going
to actually be writing high
performance code for a GPU.
So you have to actually think
about the execution model of how
a GPU actually executes things.
And this is somewhat
complicated, but not insanely
so.
There's three
granularities of things
that you need to think about.
There's blocks, there's
warps, and there's threads,
and that's the order in which
the granularity narrows down.
Blocks are these big
groups of threads.
And each block is going
to be assigned to a SM.
So think about this as each
SM is kind of a worker.
It's its own autonomous unit.
And a block is going to be
assigned to an SM to process.
So this is each granular unit.
Now then within these blocks
are a whole bunch of threads.
Each thread is a piece of
task that needs to be done.
And when these threads
execute, they're
going to execute in groups.
And this is a thing
called a warp.
So you take a block which
is a collection of threads.
And you're going to take
threads from that block,
and they're going to
execute in groups of 32
consecutively numbered
threads each time.
And that's of called warps.
And so you can see at this
diagram here what's happening.
You've got a bunch of blocks.
Each block is assigned
to a different SM.
And within each
block, there's going
to be many different warps.
And each warp is
going to consist
of a whole bunch of threads.
And all of these
threads are going
to execute the same
instruction on different data.
And so this is kind of
the execution model.
Right now it's going to it
seems probably mysterious.
What these blocks, and
warps and threads are.
They will have
important implications
for performance in how we design
things like CUDA kernels later.
So hopefully you
can remember this.
I'll refresh your
memory as we go.
Hopefully, that's clear.
So that was the kind of logical
execution model of a GPU.
And if you understand
that you understand
how GPUs execute things.
There's also a logical
memory model of a GPU.
So now I'm not showing
you the physical hardware.
This is just how you think
about the programming of a GPU.
And so there's registers.
So these are really
fast, storing
single numbers type storage.
You've got local memory,
you've got shared memory,
and you've got global memory.
And that increases in
the memory hierarchy.
You get slower and
slower and slower.
And your code can
write to global memory.
It can also write
the constant memory,
which is not something
that's used too often.
And so each thread can
access its own register
and shared memory.
But information that
goes across blocks
need to be written
to global memory.
And this is actually
quite important.
So now it means that whenever
you write a thread that
executes something,
ideally it's operating
on the same small
amount of data.
So you load that small amount
of data into shared memory.
All the threads are very happy
accessing that shared memory.
It terminates.
It's done.
That would be a great
execution model.
Instead, if you
have a thread that
needs to access data all
over the place, that's
going to have to access global
memory, that's very, very slow.
This theme will come back as
we talk about different ways
of operating on a GPU.
Hopefully that's clear.
That's kind of the
very high level,
four-slide overview of a GPU.
If you have questions about
how any of that works,
feel free to ask me as I go on.
OK, so here's a side thread.
Last year I didn't
cover this because I
think resources on
TPUs was a little thin,
but the nice TPU
book or internet
website that I mentioned at the
start of the lecture came out,
and that has actually
a lot of nice details.
And I talked to a few
Google people about the TPU.
And at a high level, it's
very, very similar to a GPU.
And so I want to just talk
for a moment about TPUs.
You may never operate
on a TPU, but I
think it's important
to understand
that these alternative
accelerators operate
in many ways, very similarly.
So here's a diagram of
what a TPU looks like.
There's kind of a-- so there's
something called a tensor core.
And mentally you can
think about a tensor core
as being similar to an SM
or streaming multiprocessor.
Each of these are kind
of its own atomic units
that can operate on data.
There's a scalar unit which
is basically a control unit.
And it can also do
CPU-like arbitrary things.
You've got a vector unit
that can operate on vectors.
So if you've got
a vector and you
want to operate entrywise on it,
that's a good place to do it.
And then it's got a very
big specialized part
of the chip dedicated to
just doing matrix multiply.
It's called the MXU.
And then it's got very fast
memory for vector memory and SM.
Both of these are very fast on
chip or on tensor core memory.
And then there's
high bandwidth memory
that lives outside of the chip.
So hopefully you see the
similarities to an SM.
There's slow memory outside
very fast memory inside.
And there's specialized hardware
to do matrix multiplication.
The core structure is
very much the same.
The difference is I'll talk
about this in the parallelism
lecture next week.
How the accelerators
are networked together
is a little bit different.
And then also mention
I didn't notice
I didn't talk about
warps, I didn't talk
about any of that other stuff.
Tensor cores are
in some ways very
simple because they're optimized
to just do matrix multiplies.
The tensor core, unlike
the GPU, doesn't attempt
to do anything but that.
And so in some ways
very, very simple,
much simpler in architecture,
but conceptually
doing the same thing.
Yes.
Is it called tensor
because it's also
in some ways optimized to
operate on general tensors
or this is just enough
to work on [INAUDIBLE]?
Yeah.
So the question was
is it called tensor
because it can operate
on arbitrary tensors.
So it can operate on
arbitrary tensors.
I can do the indexing.
The operations that MXU
performs is a matrix multiply.
And so it would always
be like a batch matrix
multiply operating on a tensor.
So it's kind of both a Yes and a
no answer, if that makes sense.
So they operate on tensors,
but the operations they always
perform are matrix multiply,
is not more complicated
tensor operations
that you can do.
Cool.
The reason why the GPU
has been so successful
is that it scales
up really easily.
If you want more processing
power, just add more SMs.
You don't have to
worry about driving
the clock faster and getting
more heat dissipation problems.
Programming-wise,
CUDA is intimidating,
but it's actually not as
horrendous to program because
of its programming model.
Like, the way it works
is within each SM right,
you have a thread, and it
executes the same instruction
on a bunch of different
pieces of data.
That's conceptually
easy to reason about.
You can think through
what that means.
And especially it's nice if
you're operating over a matrix
and you're doing very
simple operations.
It's exactly this
kind of simple model.
Finally, each of these
threads are very lightweight,
and they can be kind of stopped
and started at any time.
And so if you need to
wait for another thread
or if you need to evict
something and start
another process, all these
threads are very lightweight.
So this just kind of
means that there's not
much state associated
with the threads,
and they can be
stopped and started,
which allows GPUs to get high
utilization within each SM.
So GPUs, obviously
graphics processing units.
And for much of its
life, in the early days,
it was not used to do
scientific computing.
But people-- because
it was programmable,
researchers figured out how
to use early NVIDIA GPUs to do
fast matrix multiplies.
This is one of the early papers
on doing fast matrix multiplies
with graphics
hardware, and it shows
how you can hack kind of
things like the texture buffer.
And so on to get it to
do matrix multiplies.
And so even without specific
support for matmuls,
researchers figured
out how to do it.
But I think now, especially
in this day and age,
NVIDIA and others have realized
matrix multiplies are special.
If you're doing deep learning,
most of your workload
is matrix multiplies.
And so matrix multiplies are in
some sense blessed operations.
So this is a chart showing the
number of teraFLOPs per second
by different generations
of NVIDIA GPUs.
And the orange line
is your matmul FLOPs,
your performance you can
get if you're doing matmuls.
The blue line is your
non-matmul FLOPs.
And you see this
big, big gap at V100s
when they started putting
in tensor cores that
were specialized hardware
to do matrix multiplies.
And you see this gigantic gap in
the matrix multiply performance
relative to the
non-maximal performance.
And so if you're going to design
any a neural architecture,
I was saying this in the
architecture part as well.
You have to have most of your
workload be matrix multiplies
because that's the thing
that's orders of magnitude
faster than any other
operation that you're going
to be able to do on a GPU.
So if you make like a
non-matmul-based neural network,
you're going to be in
a big, big trouble.
And then kind of the
last thing that I
want you to understand
as just general facts.
Matmuls is fast is one thing.
But the other thing that's
important to remember
is kind of the relative scaling
of the different components
of the GPU.
So this is a very nice
chart that shows you
how quickly different
components of the GPU
or different components
of the let's call it like
LLM training stack are scaling.
So the blue line
is the connectivity
from the GPU to the host.
The server that
it's attached to.
So you can use PCIe,
you can use NVLink,
you can use all these
fancy interconnects.
They are growing, but they're
growing somewhat slowly.
So this chart is like
normalized scaling bandwidth
relative to when the first
generation of interconnects.
The green line, this is
the global memory speed.
So you go from GDDR to
HBM2E, and that's much,
much faster right.
This is log scale.
It's 100x faster.
But this is still
kind of slow scaling.
And the gray line here,
this is compute scaling.
This is the number of
floating point operations,
if you're considering
the matmul FLOPs.
This is how fast the
compute has been scaling.
And this is astoundingly fast.
It's 1 to 100,000 times faster.
And so in the early days
of this scaling, maybe
your problems were FLOPs based.
You just didn't have enough
FLOPs to do your matrix
multiplications.
But now all the way to the
right with the A100s, these
are astoundingly fast GPUs.
Your bottlenecks are probably
going to end up being memory,
because the memory is
not growing as fast.
And as we go into
the future, this
is not really going to change.
DRAM is very hard to scale.
You're going to keep getting
this bigger and bigger gap.
So if you're ever designing
hardware efficient algorithms,
you're going to have to think
more and more about memory.
And so we're going to
keep a lookout on that.
I'm going to keep
emphasizing this.
It's one of the
important themes in GPUs.
OK.
So I've been kind of throwing
lots of GPU facts at you,
especially if you haven't,
seen this recently.
It may be kind of new.
So just to recap, GPUs are these
massively parallel processing
systems.
They have same
instructions applied
across many different threads.
And they have
these things called
SMs, which are kind of cores
that there's many, many of them
in the GPUs.
Compute and matrix multiplies
have scaled really fast,
and they have scaled
faster than memory.
And that is an important
part of the characteristics
that you think
about, about GPUs.
But there is some fast memory.
It's not like
everything is slow,
so there's nothing we can do.
There's the memory hierarchy.
So some kinds of memory
are very, very fast.
Other kinds of
memories are slow.
And so if we exploit
this hierarchy maybe
we can get things that
are really, really fast.
So that's things to
remember about the GPU.
And if you remember
these facts, you're
going to be able to think pretty
cleanly about the performance
components that I'm
going to talk about next.
Any questions before I
move on to the next part?
OK, cool.
So now you all are GPU experts,
and what we would like to do
is we would like to make
machine learning workloads go
very fast on a GPU.
And so I'm going to
start with this chart.
And one of our goals
will be to understand
what this chart exactly is.
I think it'll be a good
puzzle to get us motivated.
And so here what we are
doing is we are multiplying
square matrices together.
So the x-axis is the size of
my square matrix multiplies.
And the y-axis here, this is the
number of operations per second
that I'm doing.
So you can think of this
as hardware utilization
on the y-axis.
And so as I get bigger
and bigger matrices,
I'm going to get better and
better hardware utilization
because I have more work to do.
So I don't-- that overwhelms
the overhead of launching jobs
and things like this.
But there's all these weird
things that are happening.
You see 1, 2, 3 different,
4 different lines.
And each of these lines
are kind of wavy in a way
that's looks very unpredictable.
And so we would like to
understand what exactly
is going on with these lines.
And by the end of this
section, my promise
is that you will
understand exactly each one
of these phenomena, and
you'll be able to say, yeah,
that plot looks totally normal.
That is a natural
thing for a GPU to do.
So the very first part, is
if you look at that plot,
you will notice that it
looks a little bit like this.
And if you've taken a
systems hardware course,
you should remember this as
kind of the roofline model.
The roofline model
basically says
if we're looking at throughput
or utilization, what we're going
to find is there's two regimes.
There's going to
be a regime that
is memory limited, that is on
the left side of this curve
on the green over here.
And then there's a
part that is throughput
limited on the right side.
In some sense, you can think
of it as, on the right side,
we are fully utilizing
our compute units.
All the matrix multiply units
are multiplying all the time.
And on the diagonal
here, we just
have some sort of
memory bottleneck.
And so our ability
to do computation
is limited by the amount
of intensity that we have,
the amount of FLOPs
per byte that we have.
So we want to avoid being in
this left side region where
we're memory bound.
And we would like to
be on this right side
where we're getting,
in some sense,
full utilization of all
of our compute units.
So that's, in some
sense, the goal.
And hopefully this roofline
model looks something like this.
We've got this diagonal part.
And then we've
got this flat part
all the way at the top here.
So that's one part
of the mystery.
And so this turns
out to be complex.
The simple way to
say this is-- let's
make sure that we're not
accessing memory unnecessarily.
We have as few memory
accesses to slow global memory
as possible.
But it turns out that
in order to do that,
we need a large array of tricks.
There's a lot of
different things
that you could do that
would mess you up,
that would make you very slow.
And the first one is
not a memory bottleneck.
I'll just mention it.
It doesn't come up too often.
We'll get it out of the way.
And then we'll talk
about the remaining five
items that in some
sense are really
core to thinking
about GPU performance.
OK, so the first thing
that I want to talk about
is conditionals.
So as I said before, GPUs,
their execution model
is something called SIMT,
Single Instruction Multi-Thread.
And so every thread
in a warp is going
to execute the same
instruction, and it's
going to do so on
different data.
And so what happens if
I write a piece of code
that looks like this.
I have an if statement.
And if the thread index is
less than 4, do something.
If the thread index is
greater than or equal to 4,
then do something else.
I have this very simple
conditional model.
If I run this on the GPU,
what's going to happen
is that I'm going to run
the A instruction on four
of my threads.
I will actually
pause my other four
threads, which are supposed
to be executing the else part.
And then these other four
threads will come alive
and they will execute x.
And these my original four
threads will go to sleep,
and I will just
alternate executing
each of these instructions.
Why is that?
I can't execute A and
x at the same time
on these different threads.
As I said again,
every thread has
to execute the same instruction.
So conditional statements
within a single warp
can be really, really
damaging because they
will force you to pause
any of the threads that
are not doing exactly the
main control flow execution.
OK, so that was the
only non-memory thing
that I wanted to mention, and
it should be kind of obvious
that you should probably
not be putting conditionals
into your massively
parallel compute unit,
but once we've gotten
that out of the way,
the other tricks that
we need to consider
are all kind of memory based.
The first thing I want to
mention is lower precision.
And this is a big trick.
This is an important trick.
You should do it all the time.
There's kind of a-- going back
to this plot of Bill Dally,
there's a sleight of hand here.
This looks really good because
the numbers are going up
and up and up.
But if you look at what's
driving GPU progress over all
these years, you
actually kind of see
that it's number
representations.
You go from FP32 to
FP16 to int8 to so on.
You get many orders
of magnitude gains
from just having lower and
lower precision in your GPU
operations.
And let me clarify why
that's so important.
If you have fewer bits
in all of the things
that you're computing and
your weights and so on,
you have much
fewer bits to move.
So even if you're accessing
these bits from global memory,
they become much, much
less of a concern.
So let's just give
a simple example.
And let's just think
about arithmetic intensity
of a simple
elementwise operation.
So I'm going to do it in ReLU.
So that's x equals max 0 and x.
And I'm going to do that
on a vector of size n.
Let's say naively I'm going
to do this on float 32.
So how many memory
accesses do I have?
I have to read my x.
I have to write the result
of if x less than 0.
And that's all in float 32.
So that's kind of 8 bytes.
And how many operations do I do?
Well, I have to
do x less than 0.
So that's one
comparison operation.
And I do one FLOP.
So I do 8 bytes per single
floating point operation.
If I do this in
float 16 now, well, I
haven't changed the
FLOPs intensity here,
but I have the memory access.
And so now I have
4 bytes per FLOP.
In some sense I've gotten double
the memory bandwidth for free,
assuming that I can
get away with FLOP 16.
And this is a key part of how
a lot of things are designed.
Part of the assignment
is going to be
you're going to try and play
with various mixed precision
or low precision training
and other kinds of things.
And a key part here is
that not all the parts
of your network and
your training algorithm
should be put into
low precision.
So let me give you an
example of matrix multiplies.
So in matrix multiplies
that are mixed precision,
what you would do is you would
have your inputs be 16-bit.
So these are low precision.
And then you're going to do your
multiplication in full 32-bit.
And that's useful because
the intermediate computations
as you're accumulating
partial sums,
you would like that to
be in high precision.
And so you're accumulating
this with FP32 accumulator.
And then your tensor core
will return a FP32 result,
which you can downcast if you
would like back into 16-bit.
And so we have our
inputs in 16-bit.
But things like the accumulation
we might want to do in 32.
So there's lots of
different things.
There's operations that
can use 16-bit storage.
might need more precision.
So you want to keep it
in either FP32 or FP16.
You might want to have
operations that need
more range, like exp functions.
If you don't have
the dynamic range
that might blow up or zero out.
And so you might want
to put those in bf16.
There's a lot of
careful engineering
that has to happen in order to
make sure that these models are
actually stable
when they're being
trained with lower precision.
But if you can do it,
that's really great
because you've basically
doubled the throughput
of your bottleneck
going from 32 to 16-bit,
if your memory is
your bottleneck.
The other one, and I think this
is kind of what a lot of people
think of when they say I'm
going to write a CUDA kernel
or something, operator
fusion is kind of both very
intuitive and both like a fun,
natural one to think about.
So one memory-- or sorry, one
mental model of how a GPU works
and how memory
works is this kind
of fun diagram of a
factory from Horus.
So imagine you have a
factory, and your factory
is your compute part.
And so it takes in
little box widgets
and then outputs little
triangle widgets.
And if you grow your compute
but your belt conveyor that
takes memory to compute
is finite bandwidth,
you're not going to be able
to use your second factory.
You're still capped by the speed
at which you can transfer things
from memory to compute.
And so you've got
this bottleneck.
Now, of course you
already knew that.
I've been hammering in the
memory bottleneck thing,
but I think one
insidious way in which
you can incur a ton of
overhead without really
realizing it is this
left-hand-side computation
pattern.
So imagine the left side of this
plot is where the memory is.
The right side is
your compute unit.
And so to do computation
I start with a square.
And I move my squares from
my memory to my compute.
I do some operation.
I turn them into triangles.
Now I shift my triangles
back to memory.
And then I realized I
need my triangles again.
So I ship them back
into the compute unit.
Now the triangles become
circles, and so on and so forth.
I send my compute back and
forth and back and forth,
back to memory.
And you might call this
a very naive approach.
And if you were just doing
operations naively on the GPU
and just shipping the results
straight back to global memory,
this is what you'd end up with.
And if you count the number
of times a piece of data
went back and forth,
this is pretty terrible.
You've incurred tons
of memory overhead.
Now, you should
be able to realize
that if you look at the right
side, will this compute?
Well, there's no
dependency, so I
should be able to go square to
triangle to circle to rectangle
and ship the rectangle back.
I can just keep everything in
the compute unit the whole time.
And that's the
right-hand-side diagram.
And this is the mental
model of a fused kernel.
You have a bunch
of operations that
are going to happen on a
piece of data in sequence.
Instead of writing it back into
storage, what I'm going to do
is I'm going to do all
the computation as much
as I can in one place,
and then only when I
have to ship it back to memory.
So that's this idea
of kernel fusion.
There's some very
simple examples
of how if you write
some naive code,
you might get of a
naive set of launches.
So here's an example
I wrote a little let's
say neural network module.
Let's say I write
a neural network
module that takes in
x and it produces sine
squared x and cosine squared x.
Simple code.
Now if I run this, the
computation graph in PyTorch
is going to look
something like this.
And it's going to launch a
whole bunch of CUDA kernels.
It's going to launch
take in the x,
and it'll launch a CUDA
kernel to compute sin x.
It'll launch one to
compute cosine x then
sine squared of x and
cosine squared of x and sine
squared x plus
cosine squared of x.
So there's a bunch
of back and forth
that has to happen in order
to do this computation.
It's exactly the left hand side
figure that I showed you before.
But if you were a little
smarter and you either
wrote your own CUDA
kernel or you use
something like
torch compile, well,
you can easily realize that
those five operations don't
really depend on very much, they
use only a little bit of memory.
And so you can fuse them
into a single operation that
does everything on
GPU on a single thread
without sending things
back to global memory.
So really easy fusion
operations like this
can be done automatically
by compilers.
I just mentioned torch compiler.
If you aren't already
doing this, you should.
You should consider strongly
thinking about using
torch compile everywhere.
We'll show you in the assignment
torch compile as well.
It's pretty nice.
OK, so I've gone through
precision and fusion.
If anyone has
questions, let me know
before I move on
to recomputation
and other kinds of tricks
that we can do on the GPU.
OK, good.
So another thing that we can
do is called recomputation.
And recomputation is
this idea of spending
more compute to avoid
having to do memory access.
So remember your original
back propagation lecture.
This one is actually from CS221.
What do we do?
Well, we take our inputs
at the very bottom.
These are the yellow ones.
And then we propagate
activations upwards.
Those are also the yellow
values on the tree.
And then we compute the
Jacobians backwards.
Those are the green
values on the edges.
And then to compute my gradients
I'm going to propagate.
You multiply.
So the Jacobian and
the activations I'm
a propagate the
gradients backward.
Well, if you think
about it, those yellow
values after the forward
pass have to be stored.
And then they're stored.
And then they have to be
taken from global memory
where I stored them and put
them into the compute units.
Mechanically, that's
how it has to happen.
But that might actually be a
ton of memory inputs and outputs
happening.
Instead you might actually
be able to avoid this.
So let me give you an example of
how computation can speed things
up.
Here's another silly
function that I might write.
I'm just going to stack three
sigmoids on top of each other.
You can look at the left.
That's the forward graph.
That should be exactly your
mental model of three sigmoids
on top of each other.
Now the computation
graph for this,
I'm going to compute
the sigmoids,
and I'm going to
store S1 and S2, which
are the activations
of the sigmoids.
And I have my outputs.
And then that's my forward pass.
Now, the backward pass in
this is kind of terrible.
When I do my backward graph, I
need to go and take S1 and S2,
and I need to take the gradients
coming backwards into this
out box and then push it into
this backwards computation.
And I'll get the gradient of x.
So I need to have three memory
reads one memory right in order
to compute the backwards pass.
And then for the forward pass I
need to do one memory read of x.
And I need to do three memory
writes for S1, S2, and out.
So hopefully that's clear.
This is a decent amount of
memory reads and writes.
I have to do eight of them.
And I have very low
arithmetic intensity
because I have no matrix
multiplies at all.
So the idea of
recomputation is to say
I don't want to store
those activations at all.
I'm not going to put
them into memory.
I'm just going to recompute them
on the fly in my backward pass.
So now in my new forward
pass, I don't store S1 and S2.
I take x as input, I compute my
sigmoids, and I get my output.
So now that's one memory read
for x, one memory write for out.
Now in my backward pass, I
don't have activations anymore.
So what I'm going to do is
I'm going to get both D out,
which is the backward
signal coming in from above.
And then x which is my input.
So I'm going to take two of
those, which is 2 memory reads.
And then on the fly in
my SM in my local memory,
I'm going to compute
each of these sigmoids,
and I'm going to put them
into the backward graph.
I'm going to recompute
S1, S2, and out
on the fly inside
my local memory.
And because I do that,
there's no global memory
reads happening here.
And then I have one
memory right which is dx.
So now if you compare the two
I have 5/8 of the memory access
for the exact same computation.
The price that we
paid is that I'm
going to have to recompute
these three sigmoids.
But if you were
running idle anyway
because you were memory capped,
this is a great trade off.
You would be very
happy with this
because now you've
traded compute,
which you have too much of
for memory bandwidth, which
you had too little of.
So this is one
great way of trading
one thing you need for
another thing that you have.
And of course,
this is different.
It's the same trick as gradient
checkpointing and recomputing
activations for memory savings.
But this is being done
for different reasons.
This is for execution speed,
not just because you're
running out of memory.
So it's the same technique
but for different goals.
And then this one
I think is actually
kind of a really
interesting one, and not one
that I knew until
I started really
looking into how the hardware
model of a GPU and DRAM works.
So the slow memory,
the global memory
called DRAM in a GPU, that's
actually very, very slow.
And in order to make
it faster, there
are certain optimizations
that are being
done at the hardware level.
And one of the
optimizations that's
done at a hardware
level for DRAM
is that when you go and
read a piece of memory,
you don't actually get
just that value back.
You actually get a whole
chunk of the memory back.
And this is called burst mode.
So let's say I went on and tried
to read the very first value
of this big memory block.
Instead of just the
memory giving me back a 0,
it would actually give
me back 0, 1, 2, 3.
It would give me back
four values at once.
It would be like, here you go.
I'm sure you'll need the 1,
2 and 3 too in the future.
And so each address
space is cut up
into what's called
burst sections.
And then you're given the
entire burst section rather
than just what you looked for.
And this might seem
very mystifying
why would the memory give you
three extra bytes for free when
you're just asking for one.
There's a very interesting
hardware reason,
which is that when you're
addressing into the memory,
in order to send the
signal out from the memory,
that those bytes have to
be moved to an amplifier,
that's the slow step.
And once you've done
that, you can get many,
many bytes bites for free.
And so that's why this
burst section thing exists.
It's kind of masking
this more expensive step
of actually moving
where the data is
stored to this amplifier.
But kind of regardless,
this kind of
means that we might be able
to significantly accelerate
our memory access if the pattern
of memory access is good.
So if I want to read this
entire block over here,
if I access it in
random order, then I'm
going to have to basically query
a number of times equal roughly
to the length of my query.
But if I go and I check
the very first value,
then I'm going to get all this
entire burst section at once.
And then if I go
and check number 4,
I'll get this burst section, the
second burst section at once.
And so I can basically get
four times the throughput
if I'm really clever
about my memory accesses
and only access just the bits
I need from each burst section.
So this is called
memory coalescing.
So if all the threads in a warp
fall within the same burst, then
basically the smart hardware
and programming model
will basically
group those queries.
Instead of querying 0, 1, 2,
3, it will group them and say,
just give me 0,
and then I will be
able to read out all
the 0, 1, 2, 3 at once
from this kind of
burst mode DRAM.
So remember that a warp
is 32 numbered threads.
And so memory accesses from
a warp happen together.
And so when these
warps are reading
in to these kind
of burst sections,
there's optimizations that
can be done so that you're
getting all 4 bytes at once
rather than getting one of them
at a time individually.
And so that will 4x the
throughput that you have
on your memory.
So these are very simple
things, but they're actually
very important.
Imagine I'm going to do
matrix multiplications, right?
This is a core thing that you're
going to have to do a ton.
If you were to implement, let's
say a neural network really
from scratch in CUDA.
In this case, imagine
I'm going to read
my matrices in one of two ways.
I can read it by
traversing the rows.
So each thread is going
to traverse the row.
Or I can read it
in column order.
So each thread is going
to go down a column.
Turns out that this
left one where you're
going across different rows.
So each thread is accessing
a different-- oh, sorry,
each thread is going
through columns.
This left model is
going to be quite slow
because the memory reads are
not going to be coalesced.
Whereas if you're going
to this right side
where each of the
threads are going down,
so they're incrementing in
rows, then these memory reads
will be coalesced.
And so you can think about it
for a moment why this is true.
When I first looked at
this diagram I was like,
isn't it reversed?
It's actually not.
This is the correct one.
And the way to think
about this is let's
say on this right-hand-side
diagram over here,
I'm going to have
a thread that's
trying to-- a series
of threads that's
trying to access left to right.
So each thread is going to try
to load the very first element.
And then in the next time
step I'm going to the load
the element from this column,
the second column and then
the third column and the
fourth column and so on.
So if that happens, what
happens at time step 1?
At time step 1, my first
thread loads at this point.
And then the second thread
loads at this point.
And then this point
and that point.
So those can't be
coalesced at all.
They're reading
different burst sections.
And so that means that I have to
read this entire chunk of memory
in order to perform
any an operation.
Instead, if I was going
in the column direction,
all the threads will be reading
within this single burst
section, and so
only one memory read
operation needs to
be performed, and you
get all of the memory at once.
This is a very low
level optimization,
but this is very important.
If your memory traversal
order is all wrong,
you will actually get much
slower memory accesses
than you really want.
OK.
So then that brings us to
the very last and big one.
And this is the idea of tiling.
And tiling is this idea that
you would like to group together
memory accesses in
order to minimize
the amount of global memory
access that we have to do.
And so to explain
this one, I'm going
to try to go through this
example of a matrix multiply.
And hopefully, I'll be
able to explain to you
why a naive algorithm
for doing matrix multiply
is going to be very problematic.
And then afterwards
I'm going to give you
a tiled version
of the same idea,
and hopefully you'll
be able to see
why that's going to reduce
the number of global memory
reads that you have to do.
So let's start with this
very simple matrix multiply
algorithm.
So I've got a matrix.
I've got this M matrix
on the left side.
I've got my N matrix on the top.
And in order to compute
the matrix product,
I'm going to have to
traverse over the rows of M
and the columns of N and
then take the inner product
and store that
into this P matrix.
Write the corresponding rows.
And I've written out
here each of the threads.
The thread 0
corresponding to where
they're storing their
outputs and the access
order in which they access each
of the individual elements.
Now notice here that
what's going to happen
is that the memory access
here is not coalesced.
Like, the row
matrices here, these
are going to be accessed
in a non-coalesced order.
And I have repeated
memory accesses.
So I've got M00 being accessed
in the first thread, M00
accessed here,
N10 being accessed
in two different threads.
So these values are being read
over and over from global memory
into many different threads.
So this is going to be
potentially very slow.
So there's a question
of can we avoid
having too many global
memory reads and writes what
I would ideally like to do.
So let me explain the
ideal outcome first,
and then I'll explain
the algorithm.
The ideal outcome
is that I would
like to spend one chunk
of time loading pieces
from global memory to shared
memory where things are fast.
I want to do a ton of
computation in shared memory,
and then I want to be done
with that piece of data.
That's the ideal outcome.
I've minimized my
global memory accesses.
So now how can I do in
this matrix multiply world?
So now what I'm
going to do is I'm
going to take my matrices, both
the M matrix and the N matrix.
And I'm going to cut
them up right into tiles.
So here I've cut this
up into 2 by 2 tiles.
So I've got a 2 by 2 m
tile and a 2 by 2n tile.
So I've got basically
smaller submatrices
within each of the matrix.
And now imagine that my
shared memory is big enough
to be able to fit these
submatrices within each
of these SMs.
So now this gives a very, very
simple algorithm with which
we can do computation.
So what I'm going to do is
I'm going to first load,
let's say this M00 tile
on the top left over here.
And I'm going to also load my
N00 tile into shared memory
here.
So now I have these partial
sums that I can compute.
I can take the row product
of M00, M01 with N00, N10.
And I can increment
that into P0.
I can do the same with all
of the different submatrices
that I can fill out over here.
Now then, once I'm completely
done processing these two tiles,
then I can load a
new tile over here.
And then I can repeat that
computation with my M tile
and my N 2.0 tile loaded
into shared memory.
And then I can increment
my partial sums in P.
So now I've really
consolidated and reduced
the amount of global
memory access I have to do.
I load as much memory as I can
at once into shared memory.
I do all of my
submatrix computations
on that tile that I can.
And then I move on
to the next one.
And of course, the
other nice thing
is that because I'm
loading an entire tile,
I can traverse these sub
matrices in whatever order
I want like column
major or row major.
And so I can coalesce all
of the memory accesses
whenever I'm loading a tile
from global to shared memory.
So there's wins all around
here when we tile our accesses.
So we can do a little
bit of tiling math.
So we've got let's say, a matrix
A, a matrix B, and a matrix C.
So let's say the
full matrix, these
are square matrices
are of size N.
And let's say I have a
tile of size T. Oh, yes.
Question.
Previous slide of
[INAUDIBLE] step three
we're loading and M00 again?
So in that case, I just
wrote it for completeness.
But M00 let's say is just
stored in the shared memory.
Let's just keep it cached.
I won't load it again.
Yeah, that's definitely
just there for completeness.
Not that you would actually
discard and reload the matrix
again.
That would be kind of insane.
Cool.
OK.
And so we can do very
simple tiling math
to think about what's happening.
So let's say I'm going to do an
N by N matrix multiply right.
So if I do a non-tiled
matrix multiply,
if I'm just going over rows
and columns, then every input
every time I process.
It has to come
from global memory.
So each input is read N
times from global memory.
So each of these
is read N times.
If I do a tiled matrix
multiply, well, the global reads
are operating over tile.
So I'm reading each input N
over T times from global memory.
And I'm reading T
times within each tile.
Of course, I'm doing
matrix, matrix multiplies.
So I can't reduce the
total number of reads.
I have to read all
the matrix elements,
but I can shift the reads into
basically fast shared memory.
So I do T times memory reads
into shared memory and N over T
times from global memory.
And that's great because if we
have a big shared memory that
can store big tiles, that's
a factor of T reduction
in the total amount of data that
has to come from global memory.
So tiling can be really,
really powerful of an idea
when you're operating
over matrices.
And you can move things
into shared memory.
Tiling is quite complex.
This is the source of
many, many confusing things
about GPU and matrix
multiply performance.
One thing that can happen.
Once we start tiling things,
you start asking things
about discretization.
So imagine I have
a tile size of 128.
That seems like a nice
good round tile size.
But then when I have a
full matrix of 256 size,
that's great.
That's a 2 by 2 tile,
things load nicely.
Now let's say I have a 257
size tile on the column side,
now this is a bad time because I
need to have six tiles in order
to cover this matrix, and
the two tiles on the right
are very, very sparse.
There's just not
much stuff in there.
And the problem with
this is that each tile is
going to be assigned to an SM.
So each of these tiles
is going to be a block.
And each thread is going to
be operating within each tile.
So those two tiles
on the right, they're
not going to be doing
very much at all.
Those SMs are going to be
basically be sitting idle.
And if you were kind
of compute capped,
you would have wanted to
more evenly distribute
the load between SMs.
So you have to basically
optimize your tile sizes
to try to avoid these
kinds of scenarios.
But in reality, there's
a lot of complex things
that go into setting
the tile size.
Remember, you have to
coalesce your memory accesses.
So you have to think
carefully about that.
You have to not exceed
your shared memory size.
So the tiles can't be too big.
And you have to divide the
matrix dimension, hopefully
evenly or as close to
evenly as possible.
So you don't end up with this
situation of an underutilized SM
the very end here.
Yes.
So if you had, say,
smaller sizes [INAUDIBLE]
would GPUs do something like
prefetching, where they can
fetch the next tile beforehand?
And so would that
happen [INAUDIBLE]?
Yeah.
So you're asking
about whether or not
you can overlap memory
reads and computation?
And yeah, that's
naturally done in GPUs.
They're always like trying to
use the available bandwidth.
As long as shared
memory is available,
they can go and
put things into it.
The issue is that whenever
you're effectively
utilizing your SMS,
you're basically maxed out
on your shared memory.
That's like the
bottleneck resource.
And so there is no place
to prefetch in some sense.
Cool.
OK.
And the other
thing that is very,
very, we're getting into
the weeds here, complex
is the interaction between
tiling and burst sections.
So imagine I have a
matrix layout that's
this, where I have my
nice burst sections,
and each burst section
lines up nicely with a tile.
So to read this tile,
all I have to do
is to get four different
burst sections.
And I've gotten
this entire tile.
Now imagine what happens
if I add one element extra
and the way the
matrix is laid out,
my tile start-- my burst
sections flow over.
So now what's happening
is when I load my tile,
I'm going to load
this first part.
And that's really great.
I get the entire first
row as a burst section.
Now in the second
row, this actually
belongs to two different
burst sections.
And so I have to do
two reads in order
to get this second row
and so on and so forth.
So I've essentially doubled
the number of memory accesses
because I've added a single
extra element at the very end
there that's kind of bumped
up the alignment of my burst
section and my align layout.
And so basically, if
tiles or your matrix sizes
aren't multiples of
your burst section,
you can easily end up
with situations like this
where the rows don't line
up with the burst section,
and you've doubled the
amount of memory access
that you have to do.
And the way to
get around this is
you have to do padding to be
able to get nice round matrix
sizes so that your
burst sections line up
with the size of your tiles.
So this is getting very
into the weeds here.
But if you really want to
squeeze out all the performance
from your matrix
multiplies, these
are the kinds of things
you have to think about.
And you will get bitten by this,
if you're not thinking about it.
And of course, I guess like
things like torch compile
and all the CUDA optimizations
for matrix multiplies,
they're doing exactly
the kinds of stuff
that I just talked about.
That's the way you get
better performance.
And so all of this
matrix complexity
ends up in situations like this
where I'm reading out Andres,
this tweet here, but the most
dramatic optimization to nanoGPT
is to increase the vocab
size from 5257 to 5304,
which is the nearest multiple
of 64, which gives you
much, much higher occupancy.
Careful with your powers of 2.
So that's a 25% speedup
from adding how many?
It's like 57, no, 47
dimensions to your vocab.
That's like-- how
does that happen?
And so that kind of brings
us back to the mystery.
I was dragging you through all
of the GPU details in the hopes
that you'll have a full
understanding of all
the performance characteristics.
But in some sense,
the payoff is I now
get to explain to you how
this chart comes to be,
and at the end you won't find
matrix multiply performance
to be so mysterious or
scary at the end here.
So the very first part
is very, very simple.
We understand compute intensity.
This is exactly the
roofline that I pointed out
at the very beginning.
So up until here,
which is about 1536,
there's just not enough
matrix multiply work to do.
Just loading the matrix
and doing very basic IO
that you have to do is becoming
a bottleneck below this point.
So throughput is going to
fall through to the ground
past this point.
You just don't have
enough memory bandwidth
to support your compute units.
Now on the right
side here, in theory,
if I draw the upper
envelope, this
is the kind of maximum
achievable performance.
So it's possible up here to
saturate all of my compute units
and get really
great performance.
But if you mess up
your matrix sizing,
you can end up in these
kind of really weird places.
And within each one of these you
can end up in a weird trough.
And so we're going to
think a little bit about,
why do you have all these
different places you can end up?
So the very first thing,
this first line here, this
is a tiling alignment issue.
So if you look at
the multiples here,
so I've now colored
each of these lines
based on the divisibility
of the matrix size.
And this is the size by
which it's divisible.
So if it's divisible by 32,
then you're in good shape.
You're in these
purple dots up here.
If you're divisible by 16,
you're actually still up here.
There's two colors.
And then if you're
green, your K equals 8.
You're up here.
If you're orange,
your K equals 2.
And if your K equals 1,
you're all the way down here.
If you're not divisible
by any number,
don't pick prime dimensions.
You're not going to get very
good throughput on your matrix
multiplies.
And a big part of this is going
to be once you get to K equals 2
and K equals 1,
you are basically
forcing this situation where
you can no longer read tiles
in this nicely aligned
way with your burst reads,
and that's going to lead
to some serious issues.
So that's kind of a problem.
But then, OK, so that's
one part of the mystery.
But I think another part
of the mystery remains.
Like, so within
this orange line,
I think if you zoom into
here, you see this giant drop
from this point all the
way down to this point
where you're just kind of
wondering what happened here.
How could I lose so
much performance,
increasing my dimension by 2?
And so let's just
look at these numbers.
And it's just I think
this is a fun puzzle.
So I'm just going to walk
you through the puzzle.
This is going to happen when
you transition from 1792 to 1790
I guess, 3 or 4 size,
let's say 4 here,
just so that it's a
factor of 2 still.
Well, why does that happen?
OK.
Well, let's say that we're
using a tile size of 256 by 128.
That's a pretty natural size.
As a fun fact, the matrix
multiply units in these GPUs.
There they are, naturally
operating on matrices
of roughly size 128.
So 256 by 128 is a
very nice tile size.
So that means how
many tiles are there?
Well, there's 7 times
14 tiles because we're
dividing the dimension of the
matrix by the size of our tiles.
That's a total of
98 different tiles.
And if we increase this
by one, well, we're
going to have to round up
each one of our coordinates.
And so we're going to have a
lot more tiles, 120 of them.
So we've increased the number
of tiles by quite a bit.
Well, you know,
what's going to happen
is not only did we
significantly increase the tiles
and some of them have
lower utilization,
which is bad, but
actually even worse.
An A100 has 108 SMs.
And if you go all the way back
to the GPU execution model,
SMs can execute in
parallel and they're
kind of the execution units.
And so when you have 98
SMs, they all go and run.
You can dispatch them all.
All the SMs stems are running.
You got great utilization.
Once you go to 120 tiles, now
you've got more tiles than SMs.
So 108 of those will execute.
And then you will go back
and you'll say, all right,
I've got some more SMs.
At very, very low
utilization, you're
going to execute
the remaining 12
and wait for those to complete.
And that's going
to be really bad.
So if you look at
your utilization,
you've got good
utilization for a while.
You'll drop off a cliff, and
then you'll finish up your job.
So this is something
called wave quantization.
And so ideally your tile
sizes are either much bigger
than the number of
SMS or they're not
this where you're just
like barely over the SMS
and you've caused this
quantization error additionally.
Cool.
All right.
I know this is low level
details, but in many ways,
I've been saying
through many classes
that language models and deep
learning is attention to detail.
And these kinds of
attention to detail
is the things that allow
people to scale up LLMs
to really, really large sizes
and get great performance.
So it's worth knowing,
even if you're not
a person that's going to
do systems engineering.
So what were the tricks right.
Key ideas here.
First one is you got to reduce
the amount of memory accesses.
So there's lots
of ways to do it.
You can do coalescing,
so that you're not--
you can reuse reads that
you're getting for free.
You can do fusion
so that you can
fuse multiple
operations together
and avoid unnecessary
reads and writes.
You can move memory
to shared memory.
So even if you're
going to do reads,
they're going to be
from much faster memory.
And that's going to be tiling
tricks that you can do.
And then finally, you can trade
memory for other resources
that you do have.
So you can trade it
for compute, which
is going to be recomputation.
Or you can trade it for
just numerical precision
or stability, which is
going to be quantization.
So there's lots
of bags of tricks
that you have in order
to get performance out.
So there's lots of
things you can do.
You just have to be
really mindful of the role
that memory plays in the
performance of a GPU.
That's kind of the key
thing to get the most out.
Cool.
Any questions on that before
I move to the final part
with flash attention?
OK, good.
All right.
So now I'm going to
put it all together.
I'm going to try to make it
so that all the tricks that I
taught you aren't these random
disconnected facts about GPUs.
They're kind part of
the standard performance
optimization toolkit.
And flash attention
and flash attention two
will hopefully teach you
how that all comes together
to build one of the
foundations, I guess,
of modern high
performance transformers.
So flash attention, we
know that it dramatically
accelerates attention.
And most of you probably
know that that's done
through some CUDA kernel magic.
But maybe you don't
know all the details.
So what the paper says
is, OK, so there's
one part that's happening,
which is do attention
on a unoptimized PyTorch
transformer implementation.
If you fuse the kernel
and you do some things,
you can get significant speed
ups. And from the paper,
they say we apply two
established techniques
tiling and recomputation, to
overcome the technical challenge
of computing exact attention
and subquadratic HBM accesses.
So it's not
subquadratic computation
because you can't do that.
You have to compute
attention in general,
but they're going to get
subquadratic accesses
to the high bandwidth
or global memory.
And so that's really the key.
If your memory is
the bottleneck,
you want to make
that not quadratic,
so that at least you can pay for
quadratic cost with your compute
rather than with your memory.
So just for a really
quick recap at this point,
you've implemented
attention many, many times
in many classes.
So it's going to be three
different matrix multiplies.
You've got a K, Q and V
with a softmax in between.
So the matrix multiplies
are pretty simple.
That can be done with tiling.
I've showed you
examples like that.
And what's different
about attention?
Well, there's this
softmax thing.
That's going to be
the real tricky bit.
And then once we can
deal with the softmax,
all of the matrix multiply
things I was talking about
will just come into play.
So the matrix multiply,
as I said before,
is exactly what I taught you.
So if you look at the figure 1
from the FlashAttention paper,
this is really just a simple
tiled matrix multiply.
You see the K
matrix, the Q matrix,
you see it cut up
into small blocks.
Small blocks of it are
being copied to SRAM,
they're being multiplied.
And then they're
being accumulate--
they're sent to the HBM
where you do softmaxes
and then you multiply with a V.
So this is all
just really simple
in terms of the K,
Q, V matrix multiply.
But now we have to
think about the softmax.
What's going on
with the softmax?
So the key thing
here is the softmax--
sorry, I'm going to
roll back one step.
So the issue with
the softmax, what's
the problem with the softmax?
It's a global operation.
The softmax in an attention
operates row by row.
You have to sum the
entire row right
to compute the sum normalizing
term of the softmax.
And that's very problematic.
If I have tiles, ideally
I want to do everything
within the tiles.
I don't ever want to have to
write back to the big matrix.
And so I need a softmax
that can be computed
online within each tile.
I want to do as much computation
within each tile as possible.
So the key thing
here is to use what's
called the online softmax.
And so what is that?
If you have a stream
of values, normally
the batch version of the
softmax, you take all of your x1
through x of and you would
exponentiate them, sum them,
and you would divide them.
That's what you would do
in your normal softmax.
And then you would maybe
compute the maximum value,
and you subtract
that in order to be
able to make this
numerically stable.
So this is the standard
numerically stable softmax
on the left side.
So the online softmax, I've
taken this from Mikailov
and Gimelshein in 2018.
Well, you can realize
that you can pull out
via telescoping some kind
of an argument, basically
the current running normalizer
term and the current top term
of e to the xi minus max of xk.
So what you're going
to do is you're
going to maintain your
current max that you've
seen over x1 through x of j,
which is my current iteration.
And then I'm also going to
maintain this correction term.
If my max updated, this is going
to basically correct my max.
And then I'm going to add
my new term over here.
So this d of j is going to
track online the top term
of this equation 2 over here.
And then at the end, I can also
then compute the normalizer
and then get the normalized
y of i that I want.
This d of v is itself the
normalization term that I need.
So the key thing here is
that this can be done online.
I don't need the x1
through x of n up front.
All I need is the
stream of x1 through xn.
And that's really key because
I can now compute the softmax
tile by tile.
Within each tile, can
run this algorithm,
and that will let me compute the
partial softmax for that tile.
And then I can write back if
I need to all the components
that I'm keeping track of.
And that's all that I need in
order to do this computation.
So I never have to materialize
the full n squared matrix
in order to compute the softmax.
And so that's basically it.
Once you have that,
you've put it all together
and you can get the forward
pass of flash attention.
And if you go and look at the
flash attention two paper,
which is going to be
a thing that we're
going to ask you to implement.
So you're going to be following
through these steps here.
You're going to see
exactly this idea.
So first, you're going to
have your KQ matrix multiply.
And this is going to be tiled.
So these are little tile chunks.
And they're going
to be multiplied.
And how am I going to
compute the softmax.
Well, I'm going to
maintain a running value
of these exponentiated sums.
And then I'm going to keep
incrementally updating
it and correcting for
the maximum terms.
And by doing that, I can compute
all of the necessary quantities
tile by tile going from
one tile to another,
and then just
multiply once again
with tiles with v in the end.
And that will give me
my full softmax output.
Yes.
So we won't be able to compute
that until we compute the QK
multiplication across
all of the tiles.
So we do have to double
back on each tile.
So the question was you
can't compute this until you
are done with all the tiles.
And so you have to double
back on all the tiles.
We'll talk about denominator
sum until we've seen every tile.
That's right.
So you will have to-- before
you can output your softmax,
you will have to go
through all the tiles.
This is correct, but let's
say I do all the tiles once.
I do all n square tiles.
At that point, I have
all the components
that I need in order
to directly output
the softmax at that point.
I don't have to do recomputation
because I have the normalizer
terms already.
By going through
each of these tiles,
at the end of going
through all these tiles,
I've built up L3
or L of n, which
is the sum of all of
the exponentiated terms.
So I already have
that in my shared
memory for this last tile.
And then that allows me
to exponentiate and divide
and then return all
of the components.
So the backward pass
I'm not going to cover.
You can do recomputation
tile by tile,
which will allow you to
avoid storing the softmax.
Remember, I always want
to avoid storing anything
that's of size n squared.
And so here I've been
clever with the tiles
so that I don't have to store
any of the n squared components
when I'm computing, for
example, the softmax.
But in the backwards pass,
if I store the activations,
that's already something
that's n squared size.
So I don't want to store
my n squared activations.
I'm going to have to recompute
it on the fly tile by tile
when I do the backwards pass.
So that's a really
key other trick
that they do in order to make
the backwards pass possible.
But otherwise, it's
fairly standard.
It's the same thing as computing
the gradients just tile by tile
and doing that computation.
So OK, that brings
us to the end here.
Hopefully you've seen
how all of the pieces
I talked about, about
tiling and coalescing
and recomputation, come together
to give you flash attention
and all these really cool things
that make your transformers
go much faster.
So to recap for
the whole lecture.
Hardware is the
thing that has really
powered all of the language
models that we have today.
And so if you really want
to leverage your hardware,
you have to understand
the low level details.
I think all the systems
advances really engage
with a lot of the concepts
that I taught today.
And the current GPU
scaling, that plot is really
the one you should
remember, really,
really incentivizes
and encourages you
to think about memory movement.
The memory movement is the
bottleneck in all of this.
And so you don't want
to just think about, oh,
how do I reduce the
number of FLOPs.
That's important to really, you
really have to think about, OK,
how do I make my memory
movements more efficient?
And then finally,
if you have to do
a certain amount of computation,
well, to optimize things,
the way to do it is to
optimize your data movement
to be able to avoid
as much movement
from the high bandwidth
memory or the global memory
as possible.
You want to reduce that and have
everything in the very, very
fast shared memory.
And that leads to
good performance
on things like flash attention.
Thanks, everyone.