hello everyone now let's get started for
the first lecture of this class Advanced
large language model
agents I'm s Chen I'm a research
scientist at Google d m and I'm in
sharting this course with Professor dson
here at UC Berkeley and CA from meta we
also have an amazing ta te who help us a
lot on S out course Logistics with the
head ta Alex and readers Tara ashin and
Jason last semester we launched the
first version of of this Aram agents
course both here at UC Berkeley and also
on
Mook last semester we had a very amazing
line of guest speakers talking about
very broad topics about AR agents so um
we discuss about the fundamental
reasoning techniques the agenty
workflows and different applications Etc
and we had around 15,000 people
registered on Mo we also launched a
hackos which attracted around 3,000
people participated globally and uh we
also we are very grateful for this
General sponsorship from our industry
Partners who gave us around
$200,000 support in prizes and resources
we will announce the hackerson winners
very soon so stay
tuned now let's go back to aarm agents
so the code of an large language model
based agent is that the the kind of the
Brin of this agent is a large language
model which is going to perform
reasoning and planning to take action at
each time step Lear with this action to
interact with the environment it will
receive the feedback and re revise its
internal memory so that it can better
plan for the next step to
take so with this agenty framework it
allows the AR to also utilize this
external feedback and tools whenever
available so it is can f expand its
capability and uh to give to get more
informed decision in its own like
decision- making process so some common
components in the agent framework
include tour use and
retrieval then why do you want to
empower these large range models with
the agent
framework because solving real world
tasks typically involves a trial and
error process and especially when we
deploy this arm agent in a like a new
environment it really needs to like um
interact with the environment to
understand some success and failure
modes in different action
so that it is able to like revise its
own internal
memory at the same time leverag external
tools and retrieving from external
knowledge for expans ARS
capabilities and with the more like with
this agent workflow design becomes more
mature it also fac facilitates the
accomplishment of complex tasks this
includes task decomposition allocation
of subtasks division of labor for
collaboration
between different specialized modules
and multi-agent
generation many people are saying that
this year 2025 will be the year of
Agents so nowadays we have already SE
explosion of AR agents for various
applications and in many domains
actually these AR agents transformed how
previous people are thinking about like
what this like AI models can how this AI
models can behave so like some very
successful demonstrations and also
practical use cases include code
generation computer use personal
assistant and Robotics and this list of
applications will keep like growing uh
in in the future as well and also there
are some like domain like education
Finance EXC where we already have seen
an emergence of a pretty nice AR based
agents another factor that further
drives this excitement about AR agent
development is about this like recent
rapid progress of reasoning models
starting from September last year with
the release of open air o1 and starting
from let a model we have also seen a lot
of like um great reasoning Pro progress
during the meantime for example last
month we saw the release of the Gemini
2.0 flash sing model and also the open
air 03 model and this month we saw the
release of DPS R1 and Kimi K 1.5 and
also within the same model series we can
can see a very just improvement from
different version of the model so for
example there is a rapid progress of
performance from open Air1 203 and also
if we compare the current Gemini
thinking model to our initial version
released last month there are also like
a lot of improvement we can see and if
we think about this like U progress in
reasoning the most impressive
performance we have seen so far are in
math and coding especially for solving
those very challenging problems
for example last year with the alpha
proof and Alpha geometry system
developed by my colleagues at Google
dine they received this silver medal or
nearly gold medal performance in IMO
last year and also with the more recent
open a O3 model it shows that it can be
ranked among top 200 among the human
participants on colde forces competitive
programming
contest if we think about these
Milestones probably they are even very
to imagine a couple of mon ago before
they actually happened so for this
semester our course is called Advanced
large language model agents so we will
do a deeper dive into the methodology
part especially on the reasoning
techniques so we will talk about
fundamental techniques for inference
time for inference time scaling training
techniques and also search and
planning and for the application site we
will focus more on software engineering
and math mathematics so we this includes
code generation and verification and
also Auto formalization and theor
improving after this deep dive on the
methodology we will talk about armm
agents use cases for real world
Enterprise application and also more
advanced agent agentic workflow design
and also topics about safety and ethics
for real world deployment of these AR
agents now I will hand over to our head
here Alex to talk about cost Logistics
okay so the course is pretty similar to
last week's the or last semester the
main difference is we are moving the lab
to a later due date so last year the lab
was a bit earlier and is so much shorter
this year the lab is going to be this
semester the lab is going to be more
involved and it will be uh due or it
will be released later and you'll have
more time to work on it the other main
thing apart from not having a hackathon
is we're also going to sort of open up
the project so last semester the project
was sort of open-ended this time we'll
have two tracks an applications track
and a research track um I think I wrote
about it here so the applications track
is pretty much the same content as last
semester the research track is new
basically if you want to or are
interested in uh submitting a conference
publication or a workshop publication
you can apply to the research track uh
we'll have a Google form out shortly and
if we select you then you can sort of
work with under the supervision of like
some of Don's postto and grad students
to basically try to submit a workshop
paper for this class um other than that
everything else is sort of the same as
last year I would just refer to um the
final like everything is on this master
website and we won't be having a
syllabus just keep track of the changes
on here and on Ed stem um so that's it
for
Logistics yeah and also like same as
last semester we will also invite like a
very great like speakers to talk about
different topics of Advan like um agent
SM Authority and applications so um we
will we are still finalizing the guest
speaker schedule so also check out this
course website for the most upto-date
information um in this lecture I will
talk about inference time techniques for
AR reasoning so in the inro of the Cross
we bu we really talk about this like
advancement of reasoning models which is
kind of one of the highlights of large L
model development in last year and so
here I will like go more into details
about what we can see from these
reasoning models so on the slides I'm
showing this U like a results which was
like quoted from the 01 block so from
here we can see that actually open1
model started to achieve pretty
impressive performance across very
various very challenging task where
previous models are really struggling
with so this includes the competition
level Mass problems like in the Emy
contest last year and also competitive
programming contest on code
forces and in the recent like o three
results they further show this that up
the performance can further improve with
more inference time compute for example
here I'm showing this that curves they
um demonstrated on a benchmark called
Arc AGI so this is a benchmark that
includes a bunch of puzzles to test how
well humans or AI models can learn some
reasoning part patterns given the
demonstration examples so this was a
very challenging task so for the most
existing models before 01 if we do not
apply any special inference time
techniques and just do the like very
regular inference then all models can
achieve um like a less than 25% accuracy
and even with the OM om model it can
only achieve around 30% accur
but with the recent 03 model if we set
the inference time budget to around $20
per task it can achieve a performance
that kind of matching the average human
annotators or mechanical turers and if
we further scale out this inference time
cost to a crazy number like $1,000 to
solve one problem then actually the
model can achieve 87.5% accuracy so uh
definitely this is a very expensive way
to solve this particular task but it um
shows how this model can perform in the
ideal case when we do not care so much
about inference time computer then here
on the slides I'm showing a a very
simple like open1 demo where basically I
called the model to solve a planning
problem so what is different for this om
model so the main difference is that for
the existing AR before the O model when
we enter a user query then the model
will directly generate this response
but in the our interface they include
this thought process so and basically
this process can take different amount
of time depending on the difficulty of
the task for example for the specific
question I asked the model it takes um
slightly more than one minute to
generate the final
solution and in the O interface they
didn't show the like a the RO s process
instead they show a summarized version
of the Hidden thought so from this
hidden s for this specific planning
program we can see that it summarizes
some key stages in the reasoning process
of including laying out initial plan
evaluate it in it based on the model's
internal belief and thenar like revise
the plan so that it can satisfy the
constraints and improve the
optimality learn with the Gemini 2.0
sying model we also like make these sort
tokens visible to users so on the slides
I'm showing a demo where actually this
pression includes an image input so this
question is um the mass part of this
question is pretty simple so basically
um there there are four BS in the image
and the question is asking the model to
take three out of the this St numbers to
so that the sum is uh 30 and so the
thought here as you can see is pretty
long so after the we enter the query the
model immediately generates this
thoughts and with don't need to read the
reasoning process token by token I know
it's pretty hard to read but the most
interesting step we can see from this
multimodal qu is that there is a so at
the beginning of the this like a image
there are there's a specific number
which is nine so at some point the model
figures out a very important step for
this question so Bas because if you want
to get the sum of 30 actually we need to
turn this nine into six by Rolling this
four so this is a very interesting like
a feature of this um of this query when
we put these numbers on on some b and um
also like the this like step itself um
is is not that like um kind of a
difficult mathematically but actually it
is an interesting trick and if we and
and earlier if we do not allow the model
to generate this long s this specific
step will be very hard to figure out and
also like um um besides the these models
from open a and and Google de mind there
are other like reasoning models out
there recently like at the beginning of
the lecture I mentioned there are also
models from the deick team and also the
Kimi team and out of all this like a
breakthrough in reasoning bot One Core
shared idea is that we need some way to
trigger the large language model to
generate long TR of thought before it
actually concludes with the final
solution in the literature there are
different approaches to trigger this
channel of s
generation like in original Channel Sal
paper they design a f short like fronty
scheme which basically demonstrates this
s process in
examplers and later on there are some
Works showing that we can apply an
instruction prompting to achieve this
like we can use the instruction letting
step by
step and for the reason that chat models
we can see that even if we do not give
any special instructions to the model
the model also tends to generate some
sorts before coming up with is the final
answer no matter whether the S is like a
short or long so there are different
ways to train the model to achieve this
like in for instruction tuning where we
actually put this Chanel of s data into
our supervised fine tuning mixture and
also like what we can see from RE recent
reasoning models we can apply
reinforcement learning to achieve this
goal in next lecture I will focus more
on inference time techniques for scaling
token budget and in in the future
lectures we will also deep uh dive
deeper into reasoning techniques and um
there will be some other guest speakers
who will come here to share their
thoughts so from this lecture I will
discuss like three parts about reasoning
techniques at inference time I will
first discuss the basic prompting
techniques and the common idea among
this prompting techniques is that we
want to allow the model to use more
token budget to generate a single
solution
then in the second part I will talk
about techniques to perform search and
selection from multiple
candidates and the common idea here is
that is want to increase the wi to
explore the solution
space in the last part I will talk about
iterative self improvement will allow
the model to increase its depth to reach
the final
solution after all these discussions of
different parts we will also see how we
can like uh best utilize different
combinations of these techniques to seek
the best uh like way to utilize the
inference time Compu to improve the AR
reasoning
performance so let's get started on the
first part about basic prompting
techniques before we talk about more
advanced prompting techniques let's
first reveiew the background about
standard
prompting so basically in standard
prompting let's say you want to solve a
mass problem at strong slides before the
line of work works on channel Sol
prompting the common practice is that we
just put some question answer pairs into
the prompt like here the question is the
math question and the answer is the
final
answer so before the advancement in post
training techniques if we directly apply
this standard prompting then the
performance is pretty Pro on reasoning
benchmarks the fundamental issue is that
if we look at these standard future
examplers they only provide information
on the final solution format but it
doesn't tell the model about the
rationale to derive the solution now we
can imagine that if we like uh if we are
taking a class and the teachers I'm B
basically just teaching you with the the
final like a official solution without
any more context then if you do not have
relative background knowledge yourself
then it will make your teaching a lot
more
difficult so for the child Sol prompting
the idea is that we will include this
like a f short exampl with SS again
let's let's take a look at this example
of solving maass problems so here
instead in examplers we will provide
this calculation steps to basically
demonstrate the model how we should like
like um how we should derive this like a
solution step by step to to achieve the
final answer then after giving these
exampl with try of s ralse then the
model is able to solve this problem
correctly
in practice how this how this like um
these models can benefit more from CH of
Sal prompting compared to standard
prompting is also dependent on the
model's fundamental capabilities so here
on the slides I'm showing the scaling
curves presented by the original TR of
salt papers and also some other related
papers about this like um train of salt
properties so we can see that among like
different model families one common
trend is that this CT performance
improves more significantly with the
increase of the model
size and in particular if we look at
this that gap of Channel s prompting
versus standard prompting learn better
models benefit more with CT generation
and there we suggest the Improvement on
reasoning performance once the model
reaches a certain
scale I also want to knowe that here for
all for this that curves they are from
papers in 2022 so these experiments are
done using brend only ARS so this is why
it is important to apply some prompting
so that the model can generate the this
Source
immediately and also with these like
recent post training techniques they
might show some different scaling curves
like we have seen some like um strong
but very lightweight ARS recently but
then the main conclusions will still
hold we will still see this overall
trend basically once the model becomes
better it will benefit more from this
like um this allowance of the CH of s
generation then in the followup work
called large language models are Z short
reasoners they further find that even
with cre only large range models we do
not have to provide a model with
examplers to elicit this CT generation
instead we can achieve this with an
instruction like in the paper they
demonstrate this instruction let's see
step by step then after we apply this in
before we ask the model to generally
answer the model can also Al generate
some sorts before generating the final
solution and empirically they
demonstrate that this Z short CT
significantly outperform Z short
performance especially on hard like mass
and symbolic reasoning tasks so Z short
C is more convenient than F short C in
the sense that we no longer need to
manually annotate Source ourselves as
exampl but if we compare their
performance Z cty performance is still
much worse than future
Cy then a very natural question I want
to ask is how can we get the best of the
both words how to improve C performance
without manually laboring
sampls so this is what we want to
achieve with our paper large language
models as analogical reasoners and this
paper was published at I clear last year
the idea is that instead of directly
providing the model with exampl we inser
the model model to First recall relevant
exampl to solve the test problem then
based on this like model generic
Samplers the the model will try to solve
the test problems as like just um
imagine that this self generated
Samplers are just um some CT examples
provided by external
sources the benefit of this design lies
in two folds first these exampl are
self-generated by the large models so
fulfill our original goal we don't need
to do any manual labeling
here on the other hand because this
instruction is applied to each test
question so basically for the for
different test question the model is
able to generate different examplars
which are more relevant to the concrete
topics covered in the test question so
these exampl are more tailored to
individual problems we call our approach
analogical prompting because the this
methodology is actually can be motiv by
human and logical
reasoning if we think about FAL
prompting it is not Supernatural if we
think about in a human reasoning way
because humans are not explicitly given
demonstrations every time for for each
single new problem and instead humans
also intrinsically recall from past
relevant
experience so in a classic recent
myology book called How to solve it from
poya they have a very nice description
about this reasoning method named do you
know a related problem so the idea is
that when solving a problem we look for
a pre formally solved problem which is
linked to our present one by
generalization specialization or analogy
and want to learn from this like um past
results or their methods so that we can
help us solve new test problems
better if we think about it from the
human reasoning perspective learn beside
examplers we can also install a model to
generate some high higher level
knowledge which can be like more like
better summary of what we need to solve
the new problems and this generated
knowledge can complement the problems
with broader insights so here let's take
the solving coding problems as an
example so given a new coding problem we
can first like inser a model to self
generate some knowledge which is a more
of like higher level tutorial about the
algorithms we need to solve the problem
and also the model needs to identify
what are the main algorithms we need so
that it can come up with related example
problems with their corresponding
code thenar after this instruction and
also once the model generate this
related like a background knowledge
including higher level tutorial and
examplers then the model goes back to
solve the initial test problem so in the
results we show that basically
analogical prompting not only
outperforms still short C but actually
all performs manual F short CT as well
and we show this performance Improvement
on in like um Mass problem solving code
generation and also like big bench
reasoning
tasks if you look at this results at the
first time you might be a bit surprised
because know that here all these example
problems or knowledge are generated by
the model so intuitively it might
contain more arrows than human annotated
exampl empirically we indeed observe
this trend we see that for example for
low St examples generated by the model
for Mass problems around 70% of them are
accurate and also they are relevant but
the rest can have some like um like
issues like they are completely
irrelevant or there are some actually
wrong calculation steps but even so
there are some noises in the
demonstrations the model still benefits
a lot from
it so given this like a finding you you
might imagine that this means at least
the model should be able to generate
some reasonable examplars or otherwise
it cannot learn from it at all so based
on this intuition we also conduct a like
pretty rough like a scaling like study
for this analogical prompting so here we
are comparing like models among like um
different among the GPT TX model
families and I know this models are all
shut down and deprecating now but um but
uh this trend will still hold so
basically we can see that weer large
range models benefit less from
analogical prompting although if we
compare the performance to zero short
chain of s it still U is on part or
still outperforms their
performance and with stronger larange
models like starting from tax D 002 in
the gbt family and logical prompting
starts to outperform chn S prompting
with manually designed examplars and
notice that actually this approach can
even outperform retriev examplers so for
retrieval method what we did is that
basically for each test problem we
Implement a retrieval approach so that
it will find those most relevant
problems in the in the this GSM AK Mass
corpos training
data so one explanation here is that
this generated chain of s by the model
can be more tailored to the underlying
reasoning style of this like P or
instruction tuned large Lang
models so this finding actually is also
in line with the reent trend like when
we are trying to develop the reasoning
models instead of like um putting like
in putting like um human written Source
we can have some training methods so
that the model is able to disc discover
the best like
reasoning strategies by
itself now let's go back to the
instuction that's see step by step so
why do we have to use this sentence is
there something special about it so in
the original Z CT paper they conducted
this ablation study of different
variants of this instructions to Cher
the channel of thir generation so some
of them do not make much sense so it is
kind of um um not surprising that they
do not perform well but if we look at
those different instructions in the top
category instructive if we mask out this
accuracy numbers it is it might be not
let intuitive to know which instruction
should be performed better and it can be
like kind of um not very good to see
that even if you just change a couple of
words the accuracy number can change
very dramatically so this shows that
current large range models are pretty
sensitive to prom
design and because um and also in many
cases there's no clear principle about
how to write Optimum PRS and this is why
nowadays there are still many people who
are try writing a lot of guidelines
about how to have have the best practice
to do PR
engineering so given this observation a
very natural question I want to ask next
is how we can reduce this manual work
for writing
prompts so one idea is that since our
larange models can solve like many like
um challenging reasoning problems and
also answering other queries so why
don't we also use it to help us do the
pr engineering or like PR design in
general so in iar 20 23 there is a paper
called large language models are human
level prom Engineers so the high level
idea is basically to apply a large Range
model to propose like prompts and so
that we hope this model Genera prompts
can also perform even better than human
return promps so here I'm showing the
complete diagram of their method so
there are two important stages the first
is this that proposal generation where
we can leverage this dark Range model to
generate initial instructions given our
task
description then once the model generate
different like proposed PRS we learn we
score each instruction based on the
prediction correctness on a small set of
problems so here basically we will hold
out a small validation set which can
tell us the quality of each prompt so
here the seta might be like more more
similar to the traditional machine
learning task where we have this like
separation of like training and test but
actually we do not need to include so
many like um examp examples here for
this validation purpose like in most
cases it is sufficient to include tens
of examples or just around 100
problems learning our work published at
iar last year we go further where we try
to use this lar Range model not only
just to propose some like some
instructions and do some kind of a
search and mutation we also want to
apply it as an Optimizer to creatively
improve the
prompt so so the idea of our approach is
that we want to inser AR to leverage the
past option trajectory represented as
sorted solution score pairs so that it
can learn to interally generate better
proms with more
steps so in this work we frame it as a
more General framework in the natural
language space but in this specific use
case of pro oranization basically this
means that we will have two a models as
optimizers and
evaluators so basically this Optimizer
is the L judge model which is
responsible for proposing a new
instruction given old ones and also the
task
exampl and the evaluator is the scolar
which will evaluate the accuracy or
performance of a given
instruction now let's take a look at how
we can design The Meta prom to achieve
this goal so on the slides I'm showing
an example meta prom for GSM AK to solve
the mass problems the problem itself
looks pretty long but basically are two
like a main components the first one is
this like trajectory including the
instructions we have like explored in
the past steps and with their
corresponding accuracies and in practice
we will sort them in the ascending order
and we can remove those older ones if
the mod if the contest L is not enough
to put all of them in
history and we also provide this exampl
to show what's the task we want to
optimize and um basically here for
example for M problems we only need to
include this that QA Pairs and with the
with the final answer so again there's
no need to annotate any chain of s or
any like explanation of how we can
derive this
solution learn for the results basically
again we are testing all these like
instructions on pre Trend only large
language models and we use like P to L
time and we also try using different
models as optimizers including P model
and the gbt
model so for all these like approaches
we are starting from the initial
instruction with let's solve the problem
which achieves an accuracy of around 61%
for this GSM AK task and this is a
pretty general purpose instruction it is
around like a 10% lower than the
instuction let's see step by step
and if we look at the best AR Genera PR
among this this we can see that actually
this instruction take a deep breath and
work on this problem step by step
achieves like um around like 8% like low
like higher than this leting stepbystep
instruction and actually if we compare
this performance to fure CT it matches
the performance like reported in the
Palm two paper where the chain of s
examplers are written by humans so there
are two things we can we can think about
here one is that basically here we are
seeing another way to basically achieve
very com competitive performance to
Future C without manually writing
examples ourselves another perspective
is that is that with this like AR um
based PR appliation it doesn't only save
us time to so that we do not need to
spend so much time to to like manually
tune the PRS ourselves but actually when
it comass with new proms it also
provides some sometimes surprising
different angle
like uh I can assume that for example
like turns take a deep breath um at
least for me um if I'm trying to like
revise the pr by myself I won't feel
that this phrase will be so so helpful
but um empirically the large Range model
um with this oranization Loop actually
it can some somehow come up with this
instruction that fits pretty well for
this
model no that in this like umm based
optimization process actually this is
not a real optimization in the sense
that we do not have any training here it
is completely prompting only so there's
no guarantee that the model can just
keep like um coming up with better and
better promps but in practice we find
that actually this like organization
curve of holds for different models so
we can see that basically this like um
with more oranization steps which which
is basically this it iterative prompting
steps the accuracy increases with more
steps and then prot so it looks pretty
like similar to the traditional
organization
graphs okay now let's go back to CH Sal
so from the methodology perspective what
does CH of Sal really bring into AR
reasoning why is it so
effective if we think about it Chanel of
prompting is basically giving us a way
so to perform this variable computation
of the S process which where this number
of tokens used for problem will be adapt
to TS of different difficulty levels so
if we think about standard prompting
basically it be for the same task if the
answer lar are the same then basically
if we just provide the final answer
directly it basically means that we are
forcing the model to use the same amount
of time same amount of inference time
budget to solve each problem regardless
of its difficulty but with this like a
CH of s basically it shows that for more
complex questions because um it also
require more reasoning steps um to solve
a problem like for Mass problems it
might require more calculation steps so
basically with this TR s idea it allows
the model to basically also perform more
reasoning steps in the token space so
that it can uh better solve the the test
problems and in the TR s paper they also
show that even if the the difficulty of
the problems is in examplars are pretty
simple Mass problems but actually the
same problem can also generalize to test
problems that require much more
reasoning
steps then if we think about the high
level reasoning strategies channel of s
also incorporates a lot of like um
reasoning process that are very
important for as humans to reason about
difficult task such as this
decomposition planning and
Etc so if we want to further improve the
model performance and especially if we
know what are some good guidelines on
the reasoning strategies we need to use
for a specific task we can also
explicitly insu the armm with the
desired reasoning strategies for problem
solving so one idea to further push this
that decomposition strategy is called
least to most prompting and the goal of
this approach is to achieve easy to hard
generalization by expliciting telling
the model what's the best practice to
decompose the original problem so on the
slides I'm showing this example for
solving maass problems and uh basically
in this original this to most prompting
paper from my colleagues at Google
demine it includes two stages so in the
first stage it performs a problem
reduction like given a mass problem it
first reduces the problems into simpler
sub problems so each each subm problem
can be easier to solve requires few
calculation steps then given L like sub
questions the model will be able to sub
to like sequentially solve these sub
problems and combine the solutions to
solve the original
problem the most impressive results from
this work is that actually with this
this to most prompting design it shows
for the first time that we do not need
to like like design the neuros symbolic
Frameworks or requiring any like um
program execution to but it can still
solve this like like composition or
transation benchmarks with a nearly
perfect accuracy so the results showing
in their paper is on this scan Benchmark
so scan is a synthtic data about like
translating programmatically generated
natural language commands into action
sequences the most challenging part of
this Benchmark is about this lens split
basically in there like um test splits
all the action sequences are longer than
the training samples so this makes it
very challenging for the traditional
like sequence to sequence learning if we
directly do this like a training on on
their training set and then on this lens
spit the test accuracy will be no no
more than 25% unless we apply some
neuros symbolic
techniques but then basically with this
to most prompting they show that if they
use the like the latest models at that
time uh which is a code event 002
they're able to achieve nearly perfect
test accuracy and at the same time they
only need to use like a 01 0.1% of the
training samples as exampl so it is like
both like more like test efficient uh
like like uh data efficient to adapt to
new tasks and while also the performance
is very competitive learning our
followup work published at I last year
we further show that we can extend this
Leist to most prompting idea to solve
like more complicated uh composition or
transition in the case of translating
text to more realistic uh programming
languages like here on the stes I'm
showing this example of translating
natural language questions to spar ques
so the main challenge here is that for
more real world languages including
natural language or programm languages
there are more complicated grammar rules
and also the vocabulary set is
larger this means that especially if we
want we do not have a model with a super
long context then a single PR will be no
longer enough to cover all the Gramma
rules needed to solve the
task so actually with this challenge it
shows one benefit of decom decomposition
by allowing the model to use different
proms for different reasoning stage it
also enables the model to use customized
proms for each sub progr or or each sub
task in the context of agent
development so here is an overview of of
our Dynamic Le to most prompting
approach so some details do not matter
too much here like how we do the
decomposition but the menual stage we
add is this like so-called Dynamic
selection of examplers for each sub
problem so basically here for each of
the like um test like a sentence we can
discover those example questions with
the most relevant grammar rules so like
so basically we can assure that for each
part of the sentence we can always
retrieve for the most most like useful
GR rules to solve the task so that the
model can have enough context to solve
the
problem so on this like U compositional
like um free based question Benchmark
the cfq data set again we show that
actually our Dynamic leads to most
prompting approach out performs all
these like baselines which where we need
to train a model on the complete
training
set and again if we compare list like
Dynamic list to both prompting with ch
of Sol prompting and other prompting
approaches
it also scales better when we increase
this example of pro to generate this
future
examples so far we have talked about how
we can install a model to solve the
problem in uh in some like a RIS with
some ring strategies indicated by the
future
examplers but if we think about it um we
can assume that for different reasoning
tasks they can require very different
reasoning structures like there will be
different ways to take compose the task
and plan for each stage at the same time
we might not want to annotate all these
that best practice for each type of task
like again we don't want to do this
manual labeling of of examples for every
single
problem so in our self-discover work we
published at new ribs last year we
basically insra the model to compose Tas
specific reasoning structures without
manually written demonstrations so in
practice how we do is that basically we
will list
L kind of tens of best practice of
reasoning strategies including like a
Chanel s reasoning doing decomposition
doing some self-reflection Etc then
given a different a new task the model
will think about how it can like utilize
the reasoning strategies that are best
of suit for the current task and compose
the reasoning structure follow it to
solve the
problem and for evaluation we also show
that with this self-discover methodology
it out performs train of Sol prompting
and also other base other baselines on
different benchmarks including big bench
hard reasoning task Mass Benchmark and
also some other benchmarks for social so
social agent
reasoning so to summarize in the first
part I talk about I first talk about
chain of s generation and the
fundamental idea of allowing the model
to perform variable computation to like
trigger the Sol process and this Sol
process can adapt to tasks of different
difficulty
levels and we talk about how to improve
the channel Sol performance at inference
time so in original chel of Sal paper we
talk about the fal prompting idea with
labeling of Sals we talk about
instruction prompting to trigger this
channel of s
generation and also we talk about how we
can insall lar model to automate the
prom design and discover better proms by
themselves
so notice that the this best practice of
interacting with lar models can evolve
over time like for example recently with
these post change larange models you do
not have to put examples for every
single task for the model to learn how
to do it and Al and in for some models
for example it is better for you to just
provide very clear guidelines and
instructions on what you want and then
hope the model can just follow your
instructions and some models prefer low
like a interactive discussion and some
models might prefer just a very long
detailed instruction at
once but the principles of how to
discover good prompting strategies for
reasoning still hold here like uh two
very important U criteria is that we
want this approach to encourage model to
generate longer CH of s for complex
tasks we want it to scale with different
task
difficulty and also we need this that
prompting technique to be able to
support reason strategies required for
the task so now let's start the second
part about perform search and selection
from multiple candidates and increasing
the ways to explore solution
space so after we talk about the first
part what is missing so far yeah I guess
this question is not so hard since I
already show the outline of this slides
so basically like basically from first
part we can see that we should not limit
the larange model to generate only one
solution per problem because the mo
because the model can just um have have
some mistakes in it single pass
solution instead we should allow the
model to explore multiple branches which
will allow the lar model to recover from
mistakes in a single generation and
there are two ways to basically increase
the width of this solution
exploration one is that we can generate
multiple candidate Solutions per problem
another is that at each step we can
allow the model to generate multiple
potential next reasoning
steps it is not that hard to think that
with this um like um multiple sample
generation then the upper bound of the
performance will be definitely higher
because we allow the model to like kind
of um select an alternative probably
better solution but the fundamental
challenge for Le for approaches along
this line is that how to select the best
response from multiple candidates
because in the real world use case we do
not have an oracle scoler at inference
time so surely for example in in a chat
interface we can just have the model
generate multiple like Solutions and the
user can pick whatever they want then
this is kind of a best of and like
selection case but it will be more ideal
if the model can just um do this kind of
process internally so that we do not
have to review like tons of um like
solutions by ourselves to select what we
want
so along the line of this like ideas I
want to first talk about this
self-consistency work from my colleagues
at Google demine so if we look at this
idea nowadays we will find that this is
an incredibly simple idea but it is
actually very effective and it is um is
it actually can up can improve
performance a lot with all the different
like
models so let's say we want to also a
maass problem and this time we allow the
model to generate multiple
responses so um basically after we have
all this responses we still do not know
which one is accurate but here we have
this consistency based selection
Criterium so basically let's say for
this that math problem with a single
number as the final answer we will look
at these three solutions two of them
have the answer 18 and one of them have
the answer 26 so basically 18 is the
both consistent answer so we pick the
response corresponding to this like a
most frequently appeared
answer and now that here one important
thing is that this selection is only
based on the final answer it is not
based on the reasoning passes the model
can like come up with whatever reasoning
passes it wants as long as they lead to
the same final answer we consider them
to be all good this is a pretty simple
idea but actually it Al it boosts the
performance across different models and
benchmarks and here we here in their
paper they also I evaluate all the
models um available at L time and
especially on mass prrs they show very
significant performance Improvement now
let's talk about the this scaling effect
again with the self-consistency
approach so for the base time here um in
the curves they compare with sample and
and rank Baseline this is actually a
pretty natural Baseline which says that
we can see response with the highest log
probability so here the assumption is
that if the model like gives like higher
probability to the current response it
should be more confident about it but
actually if we look at this curves we
can see that self-consistency
performance scales much better than
probability based ranking so it's more
and more responses like uh like up to
like 40 responses self-consistency
performance is still improving but this
like example and rank Baseline has
already stopped impr proving um with
with like U around 10 10 responses
already but there is an exception so the
exception is that if we train the model
to be a very good verifier for the task
we care about we might be able to kind
of um outperform this like a scaling
curve with self-consistency and we will
talk about it
later another very important factor that
contributes to self-consistency success
is that we need the model to like um
generate very diverse responses to
perform this consistency based
selection so here basically um in these
like U results they also compare with
different like baselines so the beam
search is actually a very classic search
algorithm like u in the NLP literature
before the AR um like era so basically
idea is that at each decoding step we
will keep the topk like a tokens with
the highest probabilities then in the
end we will we will use the like a
sentence with the highest overall
probability and then they also like um
compare with this ample baselines where
they apply gr decoding for like um among
like different variants of how you
formulate the prom because earlier we
mentioned that the ARs are sensitive to
different proms also they compare the
performance to different ways to permute
the examp orders in a
prompt so again they show their
self-consistency using sampling scales
better with more
samples so the important like um Factor
here is that basically for the sampling
method it needs to ensure that the
responses are very diverse so like we
can do we can do this sampling with a
high temperature or we can perform
nuclear s sampling with like by setting
the parameters in the right way to
enforce this diversity
Etc one analysis from this work is uh
actually pretty interesting it is
related to model calibration so this is
about like um actually how does s how
does this consistency based selection
like improve the model performance what
does it mean when the model is like um
Can for a given task the pro the model
can come up with a more consistent
response so here basically they show
this curve about to show the correlation
between like the accuracy and
consistency so here basically we can see
that um if if follow like a sample
responses if more of them lead to the
same final answer this means that this
consistency percentage is higher then
there are two like um conclusions we can
see from here one is that this dange
model is more certain with its final
predicted conclusion even if they are
like coming up with the same conclusion
with different reasoning passes and
empirically we see that this aggregated
solution for this like more consisten
like responses can be more likely to be
accurate the final solution can can just
be the the right one for the original
test problem so this can also explain
why this like consistency can be a very
simple but very powerful Criterion to
select the final solution so in a
self-consistency paper they demonstrate
this like um approach on those like a TX
based reasoning problems and actually
this consistency based selection
approach is also very powerful for code
generation and in our Alpha code work um
at Google at Google demite um basically
this Alpac Code system itself is a
pretty like a complicated one it
includes that model training and
inference time techniques but here I
will I will mainly focus on this like
inference stage called filtering and
clustering and especially this like
clustering is basically tries to like um
do this like a code selection based on
the consistency on execution
results so let's first briefly discuss
about the background the problem setting
of competitive programming so basically
in a competitive programming problem the
it uh in the problem description it will
includes a very long and complicated
text to tell about the background story
about what we want for the problem but
for for the corresponding code and then
also includes a few input pairs as test
cases thenar for the solution to be
considered correct the generated code
needs to pass both the given test cases
in the prompt and also us usually we
will have some her out test cases and
these test cases are typically like um
of larger scale and they will be more
diff more difficult Lear L like example
test cases and they will cover some
Corner cases so since we already have
some inov examples we can filter the
programs that fail the given test cases
already but for the remaining programs
they might still fail on the herout test
cases like for those of who of those of
you who have like participated in this
like um coding contest you might feel
the same way you feel like your code is
great but it just fa on some mysterious
holdown test cases and you didn't get
the score you want so basically for this
like for for the alpha Code system what
we do it is that we will change another
model to generate new test inputs U for
for this test
problems then we will execute those like
sample programs on all these like model
generated inputs and we cluster all
programs with the same outputs together
together
the Assumption here is basically if we
have the model to generate like enough
number of test inputs and also they are
diverse of and of higher quality then
actually we can assume that all programs
in the same cluster are semantically
equivalent because they lead to the same
execution
results and thenn finally we sample one
program from each of the 10 largest
cluster In our relation we show that LE
that clustering provides additional
performance scan compared to the filter
only method but clearly there is still a
gap from the Oracle selection because
there's still no guarantee that the
consistent response will be just the
best one out of the candidate
proofs now let's revisit this
self-consistency decoding pipeline so
one limitation here is that for the
original Self consistency we need an
answer extraction process so that we we
can do this aggregation among the
candidate
responses so if you want to like apply
is a consistency based decoding to like
um kind of um broader use cases the
nature next question is how we can do it
for free pH generation where it is not
like natural to have this aggregation
and answer extraction
process so this is what we want to
achieve with our work on universal
self-consistency the idea is that
instead of having this like answer
extraction process we ask the large
Range model to perform consistency based
selection so specifically we through an
instruction to the model asking it to
select the most consistent response
based on the majority consensus and also
it needs to take a look at all these
candidate
responses so the intuition here is that
clearly we know that it will be hard for
the motel to judge the answer
correctness by itself but consistency
should be a simpler criteria to
measure the empirically we also evaluate
this Universal self-consistency method
for different applications so for those
free phone generation problems like a
summarization and question answering
with with like a with like long factual
like um final answers we see that the
universal self consistency also still
can improve um over the baselines where
the original Self consistency is not
directly
applicable and on mass reasoning and
coding problems where we can apply this
original self-consistency idea actually
Universal self-consistency can match its
performance
without the requirement of Performing
this answer extion and code
execution and uh not L here clearly this
Universal selfconsistent performance is
bounded by the long Conta capability so
at the time we are using like a earlier
model which is not super great at long
contest reasoning so we can see that
when we include more responses in the in
in the prompt the performance might not
go like um up as like well as the
original Self consistency but we can see
that with the recent like development of
long context models this like will allow
such kind of a model based selection
approach to scale more with more
responses and also in practice for most
tasks it can be well solved within let's
say 10 responses in a candidate Pro so
this will still showcase the the this
usability of this modelbased consistency
selection previously we talk about like
a for the model based like a selection
you using the log probability from the
original model Le approach of ranking
doesn't scale better than the
consistency based selection so to
improve further over this consistency
based selection one idea is that we can
train a larg model as the ranker and we
hope that at least this ranker can
perform can perform better than this
like a simple consistency Criterion and
actually it can have some like um kind
of sense of which responses are more
likely to be
accurate so here on the slides I'm
showing this like um this like um kind
of diagram from the original open paper
which introduced the GSM AK data set and
also the and also they demonstrate this
like method of how to train a verifier
to show the to basically judge the
correctness of the mass solution and
also like later on they have they have
list like followup paper code let's
verify step by step so in total
basically for this like line of AR based
like ranking works there are two par
there are two ways to basically design
the ER based method to judge the answer
quality the first way is the most the
initial and the most standard approach
which is called outcome supervised
reward model basically it will verify
the correctness at the solution level
like given a mass problem the solution
the model will tell you whether the
solution is correct or
Not Another like um approach introduced
in this let's verified step-by-step
paper is called process supervised
reward model so the idea is that instead
of verifying at a solution space we can
also verify at a step level we can see
whether each step is
accurate so in their in their work
basically they show that this like a
process supervised reward model actually
scales better with more samples compared
to this outcome based reward model and
also this majority voting based time
but clearly here the performance will be
highly dependent on the verifier quality
and also the same verifier might not
like generalize across tasks because we
know that this consistency based
criteria is very simple and actually can
be directly applied to many tasks but
for this drer models you need to design
a good training like a strategy and also
design a good training data so that it
can really like a work across different
domains you care about so far we have
talked about response selection only at
the like solution level so we only
perform this section after the full
responses are
generated but assuming that we have a
very good stepwise scholar then actually
this like solution based response
slasher is kind of a waste of like um
using this step by scroller because
actually we can per we can do more with
such kind of a more powerful and more
frr
verifier so if we already have this a
good like stepwise scoler function then
actually we can perform this like a Tre
search with D model we basically instead
of waiting until this like solution
becomes complete during the search
process we can just um we can prioritize
those exploration of like partial
Solutions at the step level and we can
explore those more promising steps
before exploring other
passes so on the slides I'm showing this
like a like a this like um diagram from
the tray of solt prompting paper so from
this illustration you can clearly see
what's what are the differences of
different like um prompting methods like
Channel sub prompting is basically a
trend and this like self-consistency
method is like multiple parallel Trends
and then for this like TR of thought
basically at each step it can have
multiple branches to explore the next
step and you don't have to complete all
these passes until the
end so uh here I will show this like how
we can apply this like TR of s idea with
a simple example example of G of 24 so
basically at each step there are two
important like stages we want to do one
is called s generation basically this
step we try to we will Pro the lar Range
model to propose possible next thinking
steps like in the G of 24 these like
thinking steps are pretty like um simple
in format you just need to select the
two numbers to perform this
calculation then there's another stage
called s evaluation where again here we
can Pro the lar Range model to evaluate
how promising the current state is like
for for the G 24 you need to decide
whether it is possible to reach the
final number of 24 after the this all
the
multiplications so previously we show
that how we we can show how we can like
do this evaluation at the at like step
level so it will determine theu quality
of each individual step but um related
to our previous like cons consist based
selection discussion for this ex scoring
function we can also think about it as a
way to just select the best dat among
the candidates we don't need to just
have the model to make this like um
decision at the point level so idea is
that basically we can ask the L model to
like um select the best like responses
among all these like possible next like
um steps and learn basically we can also
do this voting multiple times since all
this like selection here is based on
larange model sampling then with all
these like different votes the model can
finally like SEL that the the majority
vote as the final choice to
proceed here for the results uh I'm
showing the this that g of 24 evaluation
and in the original paper they also show
some other benchmarks so we can see that
for with tra of s using breast first
search it scales better than the
standard prompting and CH of s with
respect to token budget
and going further clearly we can
integrate some more advanced search
algorithms like in this original TR of s
paper they just they use the most basic
B BFS and DFS algorithms but in the
later on we also see Le some like um
papers which are coming up with these
multicolor research methods and some
works are also trying to train a
separate evaluation function instead of
just prompting the
model again here the important
consideration is that we need to design
a good uh language model and prompting
scheme so that it can be effective for
self
evaluation so to summarize in this
second part I I saw that we can further
scale this inference time compute by
sampling multiple branches in the
solution
space and we talk about consistency
based selection which is a pretty simple
but effective and general
principle we talk about this
selfconsistent
where we can marginalize out reasoning
passes and do the selection based on the
final answer and for COD generation we
can also do this reranking based on
execution
consistency when this larange model self
evaluation works well so that it can
really judge the quality of partial
Solutions or structur quality at the
step level we can also apply this search
measure and in this case sometimes it
will scale better and also you can
reduce the token cost because it can
already eliminate those non-promising
passes during the meantime so finally I
will talk about iterative sell
improvements which will try to increase
the depth to reach the final
solution so even with the most recent
like um Advanced models including low
reasoning models we can see that they
can achieve pretty amazing like um
numbers on those competitive like um and
challenging bench marks for solving hard
mass and coding questions but L can
still sometimes make pretty obvious
mistakes and people are keeping
complaining about it but if we think
about us as humans we also tend to make
sometimes pretty Tri mistakes at first
thought so previously we talked about we
can sample multiple solutions to help us
reduce these mistakes from a single
prediction but if we think about again
it is actually a pretty suboptimal way
to do this error correction because all
these responses are generated in
parallel so we do not really learn from
the past mistakes we can just having the
model generally the same R um
predictions again and
again so basically in this part about
inference time self-improvement I will
talk about techniques using arange
models to iteratively improve its own
response for the given task and also
this will align better with as humans
like a arrow cor
process so the first papers about this
ideas include this like reflection and
self- refine so basically in this
process there are also like two
important steps after generating each
solution so basically after the model
generates the solution the model will
also generate some feedback based on
what it observes and in this step it can
use it those external evaluation when
available so for example in the original
reflection paper they focus more on this
agentic setup where basically the armm
as the agent will propose actions to the
environment and the environment will
basically like U put like gives the
model some kind of like um changes of
the observations so this will be
external signal to tell the model
whether the current step is
promising then based on this like a
model generating reflection feedback and
also this external observations then
this model will refine its like output
to revise this next uh predition step
given both this internal and external
signals in the in the this reflection
paper they basically show that this
self-reflection and self refinement
works pretty well especially when we can
have a scheme so that the mo so that
basically the model can utilize pretty
high quality evaluation or or when the
external signals are very
reliable so for example example in the
case of AF world it is basically a agent
like a navigation task so there will be
clear signals about observations at each
step and they also evaluate on the their
approach on hpk qway but they kind of
repurpose the this like a c task into an
agent environment in the sense that
after the model generates the solution
they assume that this environment will
give a signal about whether the current
solution is correct or not then this is
why you can keep keep seeing this like a
improvement with more trials and we will
revisit this assumption
later and if we think about this like
self-improvement Loop for applications
then code generation is actually a
pretty natural use case because of for
when we are writing code if for us for
example we also like debug our code
better within IDE and we do not just
write a code and we stop we actually
really rely on this like um interactive
Loop when we are trying to like like a
investigate all these code execution
results and see whether it makes sense
and also which parts we should Revis
data and this is also like Le a fun one
fundamental idea of the recent coding
agents so in our paper self debuging we
also like do a deeper dive into what
kind of feedback formats will be helpful
for the model to better correct its own
mistakes so for example the the most
like a simple um feedback
me message is basically a short
Universal um information about whether
current code is correct or not without
more
information L for unit test feedback
basically will also include the
execution results like uh whether the
current unit test has passed or whether
there are any roundtime
errors Lear for COD explanation
basically at each step we also ask the
model to self-generate some line by line
explanation of the implementation in
natureal language so this idea is like
kind of motivated by human robot du
debuging trying to ask the model to see
like what what is trying to do in a
code and finally in a trace feedback
basically it we ask the model to perform
some line by line simulation of the
execution Trace by itself this is also
one way of debugging by human
programmers empirically we evaluated the
like like um latest CH models at the
time of paper publication last year so
basically we can see that with this self
debuging Loop it consistency improves
performance across different larange
models of different capabilities and
also if we give more informative
feedback it can further improv the
debugging
performance now let's go back to list
like self correction for question
answering tasks previously we talk about
this results of hopo QA and also in some
other works it can it also show this
Improvement of self pression on other
reasoning task like um Mass problem
solving but all of this like signicant
significant Improvement comes from the
Assumption with an oracle
verifier but in practice this Oracle
verifier will not be available in in
many scenarios especially in the case of
solving reasoning problems you can
imagine that when you are taking a math
test you don't already have the official
solution at hand otherwise it will be
just trival for you to finish the exam
so basically the question here we want
to study is how do these L models
perform if we do not give the model such
very like um explicit and accurate
external feedback about the response
correctness so in our paper published
last year at I clear large Lage models
cannot self reasoning yet we actually
show some negative results from this
study so we compare with this Oracle
like Bas time where we basically utilize
the ground truth answer for CR and um
same as previous works we show this huge
Improvement then we study the case of
the real self question where basically
we do not allow the model to utilize any
Oracle feedback the model needs to judge
the response correctness by themselves
then this are the results we show in the
bottom table
we can see that the main issue here is
that because lar models can rly judge
the correctness of its predictions it
often turns an originally crash solution
into a r one so this is why actually in
this like self crash without external
evation this process can lead to worse
performance after each
round so with this study um one natural
question is um probably we didn't T the
feedback prompt where so this is why it
fails so to address this question we
also kind we also like um design like a
several variants of this feedback prompt
and notice that all these feedback
prompts are pretty General uh they are
not as specifically tuned for one task
so we can see that if we just have this
like simple general purpose feedback
prom if we do not have any more like of
the model training then uh editing this
feedback prom indeed can affect the self
crash Behavior but this is more about uh
adjusting the tendency for the model to
keep the initial response so in some
cases actually this like U feedback um
after the feedback prom update there's
no much regression on the reasoning
performance but then in this case this
also doesn't help the model to improve
over the initial performance so
previously we discussed about this uh
comparison if we just do this self
correction over One initial response and
we further like compare with another
method where basically we do this that
self correction among multiple responses
so for this we compare with the
multi-agent debate Baseline the idea is
that we will we will have the model
generate like several responses in
parallel ones then we prom the large
Range model to reval this multiple
responses and give an updated
one and for this multi-agent debate we
will compare with self consistency
recall of self consistency is just
competely generated Solutions in
parallel and select the response with
the most consist find common final
answer so in the previous multi- agent
debate papers they are showing some
improvement over self consistency but we
find that the major issue is that um
they do not like have a very Rous
comparison in terms of the token budget
so actually if we because in the multi-
agent debate each run um for this
specific experiment has like three
responses but uh basically if we keep
the same number of response on budgets
we will see that actually still like um
self-consistency scales better than the
multi-agent debate because at some point
like this again this multi agent depay
performance stops uh improving but with
more responses self-consistent
performance still like um improving on
this GSM AK Mass problem
Benchmark so given all this discussion
then the question here is that how we
can best utilize the token budget by
integrating all these different methods
together so the fundamental question is
here basically we need to understand how
to balance the inference budget for
generating multiple samples in parallel
or
sequentially so actually this is a
pretty difficult question because um it
really depends on the task and the model
and basically in essence it's about like
whether the model uh for your valuation
is good at self-reflection and corre for
your speci specific
task so here I'm showing an example
study from my colleagues at Google where
they're trying to like um basically in
this specific experiments they are
trying to find the optimal way to scale
this token budget to solve the mass
problems so actually here they train a
model which is um supposed to be more
specialized at uh correcting math
Solutions and also basically here for
for the different difficulty level of
problems they study what's the optimal
ratio
to like perform this parallel um
generation versus sequential generation
so I would say this that concrete
numbers will really vary a lot among
different like models but basically here
the overall conclusion is that um for
for simple problems it uh like like
actually the model can benefit more from
self CR because it knows more clear
about where the current solution is
wrong and how it should revise but for
harder problems actually there is a
better point in in like um in the middle
about how much you should perform par
generation and also this like sequential
refinement and along with this like um
kind of um compute Optimum like U factor
for different like T difficulty of
problems they show that least like a
compute optimal curve can also scale
better than this complete a parallel
generation and when we think about
inference time compute another Factor we
should consider is about the model sites
because intuitively with the same false
budget we can sample much more solutions
from a lighter model so if a if a like
more expensive model does not perform
much better than a cheaper model then it
will not be a very optimal way to do the
inference by calling the more expensive
model so basically uh from this like
empirical like a study from the paper
inference scaling loss so basically
again they will show that with the
optimal model with different inference
like different inference budget can be
like a different like when you have like
a smaller inference time budget maybe
you want to call rely more on the like
um lighter models but basically when you
have more budget probably you can
utilize the more expensive models which
can probably give you some boost on
those very challenging problems where
for with the smaller models it might
like um it will be very hard to come up
with the final solution
anyway so basically in this leure we
have covered like different ways to to
perform this like um inference time
scaling with like the more token budget
so we talk about the basic prompting
techniques about this like um search and
selection to increase the width of
exporting solution space Also we talk
about iterative s
Improvement and um again the best
practice to intergate with lar model
should be adapted according to its
capabilities so you need really need to
consider land Auto capability and also
the task in your hand about to think
about how you can best like combine all
these like different techniques and
design a more like um like um e
efficient and effective Paradigm for
your
task and finally I also want to talk
about the general principle of how to
design effective reasoning techniques
and this actually will be helpful for
both inference time techniques and
training time
techniques so I guess many of you might
have heard about Le that B lesson from
Richard ston but if not uh I highly
encourage you to read this like a web
page actually I would say this is a very
important guideline of for many of the
like um this like modern machine
learning works and especially with the
recent development of larange models and
reasoning techniques so this like
article itself has a lot of like text
but I will quote some most interesting
like U text in my opinion here so
basically what we really want to Dev
develop as a method is basically low
that can continue to scale with
increased
computation and when we want to like
improve the AI agents we want to like uh
basically teach the model to discover
like what we can't not which content
what we have discovered so it is more
about like um having some like a method
so that we can in we can kind of trickle
the model to know how it can like keep
improving itself and how to like uh have
the right way to perform the reasoning
so this is the end of this uh lecture
thanks for listening