so thanks faon for coming know it's a
really busy time in the quarter
everyone's busy with the homework
project and
midterms um yeah today I'm going to tell
you something I'm really passionate
about is uh the speech breing computer
interface uh my research so yeah before
that so I'm just s some self
introduction so I'm cha
um from the uh Stanford mptl lab our lab
uh trying to build speech Compu build
bre computer interfaces to help people
restore communication or like restore
movements um so today I think I'm just
going to really tell you guys how cool
this bre computer interface is given
that we have so many uh recent
development in the AI and the Machine
learning and I hope you guys will can
enjoy this talk
um all right so let me first start with
the video to give you some motivations
that why we want to build a uh green
computer
interface yeah I think what the story
tell is that we saw this teenager Howard
who's uh 21 at time of this video was
shot and he lost all his dreams because
of a severe stroke that also like made
him uh in this kind of a locking state
where he can't move and he talk about he
used to like going out and play football
uh making friends and just let her his
emotion out I think all this is lost to
him and I think the most important thing
is that he couldn't really speak to
express himself to let all the emotions
out so Howard just is just like one of
those individuals who suffer from this
kind of neurological disease disorder
such as brain stamp stroke or AOS that
can cause like severe speech and motor
impairment and even complete loss of
speech this individuals I think the life
is really challenging for them right
just think about it you cannot speak you
cannot move like you still have a fully
functioned brain but everything is lost
all all your dreams could be sh
other so I think for people like Howard
as you just saw in this video the way
they can still like communicate with the
outside world with their loved one is
through this assistive communication
devices such as the one we just saw in
the video which is this kind of lead
board that has the letters like
organized physically and for people like
Howard which may still like have there
some residual eye movement they can use
their like gaze to tell the his friend
that where he's looking at and then his
friend can use the Gaze to tell what
letter he's trying to say just imagine
how slow this process is if you want to
just say a sentence it might takes you a
few minutes to express like simple
things like how are you like I'm feeling
not comfortable today like an
alternative here is you can also use
like a it tracking device so that people
can you know use it tracking to uh
type on the computer on on virtual
keyboard but by you know just think
about it if you have to look at the
computer screen all the times all day
it's really tiring for for them and also
like these people are not like us they
probably even if they have still have
like a residual eye movement it's very
hard for them to move their eyes so it's
very tiring as
well
um maybe something different here is
that maybe it's some of you guys have
already seen this recently is uh some
videos published by a company called
neuralink for example here's one video
here let me see if I can play
them hopefully I can play
them all right so I think here is that
this company neur link is uh developing
this kind of like a
tiny uh implantable device that can be
actually placed inside your scale and
then rate the brain
signals um The Hope here is that because
for people like Hardward their brain is
still fully
functioning so we can the Hope here is
that maybe we can using this kind of
like a direct interface with their brain
so that they can still use their intact
brain to control like a computer or even
like a robots to help them to live like
a normal life and here is a quote from
this um their participants noan and he's
pretty excited about being able to uh
using
this very state of art BCI to be able to
connect with their families and then
being able to support himself I think
this kind of like PCI what I trying to
say here that for people like Hardward
are like a lot of people who has lost
their
uh control of their body and language I
think BCI can bring hope to them so
that's what I'm going
to motivate here today is that we're
trying to use BCI to really help these
people but I think before going into the
details about how this is how this works
I just want to First go through a brief
history of brain computer interface just
to help you guys understand how this
thing works like why we can put such
tiny devices into the brain and then
suddenly can interpret what the brain is
doing like there's a lot of interesting
stories here so let me start with a
brief history of
PCI so first uh back to the 19th century
here a British scientist called Richard
Kon uh started to do some experiments on
animals and one of the things he found
is that uh you can actually measure the
brain activity like measure electricity
is from the brain uh
moreover if you ask the animal not ask
but like let animals do do some task say
moving their heads then you can see that
they're like the electricity changes
somehow so I think this is the very
first early experiments that that
scientists do to show that okay actually
you can decode some signals from the
brain but we still don't know how
exactly what those exact like exactly
what those electric signals means
here so fast forward um to
1924 a German scientist called hansburg
invent this device called the yeah I
always forgot how to read that word but
anyway so it's show for EEG so it's
basically this kind of like on the right
you can see that's kind of like this uh
electrod that you can play place on the
outside of your basically on your scale
and then measure this kind of like a
wave like um signals so what the
scientist hburg find is
that uh first first so first he's the
first scientist to find that you you can
actually measure this kind of like wave
like like like signals uh from like just
this kind of like a electrod place on
the head and then he found that this
kind of signals has very different uh
safe frequency depending on how the user
how the patient is uh the fun like the
state of patient is for example if the
patient is in this kind of very calm
state that then it will have generate
this kind of slow alha wave around like
10 to maybe 20 HZ I don't I forgot the
exact range but if the patient is open
their eyes and then doing some like a
cognitive in tax then you'll see really
sharp beta waves so he's the first
scientist to discover that you can
actually know the using this kind of
like electrodes to measure the brain the
electricity electric signal of the brain
and also there's a funny story here is
that the hburg used to be a used to be a
soldier and then one day he was training
on the horse and then he fell from the
horse and I suffered from a concussion
he also has like a twin sister not a
twin but he has a he has yes he has a
twin sister and then the story is that
at the same day her sister felt like
there's a weird something weird and then
he just starting to worry about worry
about his brother so her sister his
sister sent a a telegraph to his his
father and telling his brother that is
his brother okay so this really intrig
hansberger that you know maybe there's
something called a telepathy that can
connect to uh to people through this
kind of like I know whatever this spring
wave so that's his motivation to start
to study uh Psychology and Neuroscience
and invent this EG which we are still
using today to diagn like things like a
epilepsy okay
um and then people starting to using the
this kind of eug devices to perform like
to use it to maybe since we can can
somehow detect this kind of wave like
things from the brain and then we can
also control the like the frequency of
the wave so someone started like a
musician here starting to use this EG
devices to um perform music right anyway
so I guess you guys already got the idea
that someone is controlling like doing
trying to perform some music with his
Brin wave I think this is a really cool
experiment it's done in I think in the
1950s and you can already see that
people starting to um get the idea that
you can actually uh bypass like the your
body you can actually use your brain
directly connect your brain to some like
external device and controlling that
device so I think the idea here that
what if we can also leverage the same
idea but to help people with like
Hardward you know you can help them to
maybe control robotic arm but like the
the problem with this kind of like a EG
or external measuring device is that the
signal you get is very weak just imagine
that uh your brain is generating you
know probably know that like the brain
has a lot of neurons right the neurons
actually generating a lot of like
signals and if you just put some
electrodes on your on the scalp on the
scalp and then what you are actually
measuring is like the average neuron
firings of like maybe millions of
neurons which is if you think about like
analogy is that um if you are trying to
see hear what people are saying in the
room next to us but we can only trying
to figure out like they what they saying
in this room what we are hearing is kind
of the mumbling of a lot of things we
can probably just tell maybe they are in
this kind of like a happy mood or maybe
they have reached a conclusion but not
exactly what they are trying to say so
the limitation here is that this kind of
EG device can only give us very uh low
Precision or like low resolution signal
we want to get barer signal so how I
think the answer is trying to go inside
the brain and then putting this kind of
electrodes next to a neuron and then
trying to directly measure the neuro
activities of this
neurons um and for the purpose of this
talk we're mostly going to focus on
uh the neurons in this region of the
brain called motor cortex so this brain
as some of of you may already know that
brain has different regions that's doing
different tasks so in the center of the
brain it's called motor cortex it's
basically controlling all your muscle
muscles or or your body muscles so the
Hope here that if we can understand the
neuron the coding of like the
information of neuron that's encoded
here then perhaps we can decode this
information and use this information to
help people like H to to be able to
control a external arm or being able to
uh speak
again um so here's a some very
basic neuroscience
uh so we know that there's a this kind
of cell called neurons right so this is
each one of this thing is called neuron
and this is the body of neuron called
soma and then this is the axon so this
is another neuron so neuron connects
through this uh tiny thing called
synapse so if neuron has want to
transfer some information to another
neuron just like in artificial neuron
Network you have some uh neurons and
then you want to send information to the
uh next layer you can basically this
neuron will generate some action
potential which is just some like a
electricity here to signal that another
neuron that there is some information
there so if you put a a chiny electrod
say on the uh Exon of this neuron here
and measure the uh membrane potential
which you will get is something like
this so you'll have like on the x axxis
is the time and on the y- axis is the
measure the uh uh electric potential and
then you will see this come like a
very uh sharp spikes spikes and then if
you zoom into this spikes you will see
this kind of like a typical firing
signature of the neuron which is like
the electric like if the voltage
suddenly goes up and then goes down so
basically what you can measure at the
neuron is that it's kind of very sharp
spikes that's what you will get by
putting electrodes next to neuron Okay
so
how do we figure out what like what kind
of information is encoded in this uh
what call a a spike
train um we can perform some Behavior
tasks here so for example here uh
suppose that we still lessen into a
single neuron and this neuron is let's
say we're using a monkey for this
experiment right so we are instructing
training a monkey to do two things uh
one thing is basically we're trying to
instruct the monkey to move his uh hands
either to the left or to the right and
then we measure the firing of the spikes
of that single neuron and then see
trying to get what kind of information
is encoded by that neuron so what you
see here is that each row here is
basically a spike train of that neuron
as you just saw here each vertical line
is just a spike of the
neuron uh each row is a trial a trial
means that the the mon he is try uh just
trying to move his hand in like One
Direction
um then the vertical if you see here
that because like you can see here that
the neuron seems to far slightly
different across trials so I think
that's one like fundamental properties
of a neuron is that it's very noisy it's
not like in artificial neuron network if
you put something you always get
something out whereas in a real neuron
Network in a neural real neural uh
things are really noisy so sometimes
they fire a little bit faster but
sometimes they fire a little bit slower
under the same experimental
conditions and so
here what we are trying to measure is
that if what kind of information is this
neuron encoding when the monkey has mov
his uh limb to the left or Lim to the
right and then one we can
also uh split the this information
encoding into two phases one is a
preparation and the other is the
execution so for preparation for
execution execution means that the
monkey is actually moving his his his uh
his arms where where is the prep
preparation means that the monkey is
preparing to move but he's holding his
arm fixed so he will actually move his
arm at this uh right this go time here
so what you can see here that it seems
like this neuron
um likes to firing a lot during the
execution when the monkey's hand is
moving to the right and it also fires a
little bit more when the monkey is
preparing to move to the left so this
means that maybe the neuron is encoding
some movement Direction
here uh so basically if you can repeat
this experiments for many different
neurons and then for a lot of different
directions and eventually what
scientists find is that the neurons like
if you fit like say for a single neuron
if you fit the the firing rates of that
neuron basically how many spikes it's
generating every seconds to different uh
movement directions you can fit this
kind of like a coign tuning curve to it
so what this tuning curve means that on
the Y AIS is the firing rate and then on
the horizontal axis is the movement
Direction so this neuron prefers to like
firing the most when the movement is say
180 degrees to some reference and then
the fireing gradually goes down um so
that's like one the first thing
scientists find like how the like single
neuron encoding like movement
information and then if you measure
multiple neurons like you will find that
each neuron could incode very different
informations for example this green
neuron here it's tuning curve is
slightly shifted to the right and then
the magnitude is shifted down so it's
preferred direction is around maybe
250 now with two neurons you can
actually decode out more actually decode
out what the the intended movement
direction is right so for example with a
single neuron like suppose right now I
measure the firing rate is around like
30 uh spikes per second then there could
be two movement Direction with 120 and
then 240 however with uh second neurons
here you can see that we can basically
eliminate the like suppose we measure
the second neuron is around five five
spikes per second then we can exactly
pinpoint that it's the actually the
movement direction is 120 instead of the
uh the other one
right
uh however we know that uh neurons has
uh some noises so we actually cannot
really exactly tell uh the movement
Direction by using two neurons here so
for example in the third part here right
due to the why the actual like suppose
the ground Cho like the the actual fire
rate is those gray lines but um due to
the noise the firing rate is slightly
shift to those Dash lines and you can
see that originally if we can decode the
movement direction is 120 but in this
case the possibility become that there's
four possibilities we cannot exactly we
cannot uniquely
Define um however you can see that maybe
it's still more likely that the the the
direction that monkey tries to move is
like around 120 rather than the one two
Lage is like around 50 and then the
other one is more like greater than 240
right so how do we deal with this kind
of like a noise in neuron like how can
we still uniqu more accurate like how
can we still accurately decide decoding
this um intended movements from this
kind of like a multiple uh neuron
recordings uh I
think we can basically use machine
learning here right so we can treat this
as a kind of like a classification
problem so here we are plotting each dot
here is basically a firing combination
of two neurons and the color here
basically represents the the intended
move movement Direction and then if you
like somehow train a machine learning
classifier here then you can basically
see we can draw some like decision
boundaries where say on the right side
where those uh if like on new
measurement that we get that the firing
rate somehow Drops Fall onto this here
then we probably know that it's going to
be the monkey is trying to move to the
left direction right uh so okay so I
guess here
like we know that okay we can do this
kind of single neural measurement we can
measure firing rates of multiple neurons
and then by training a machine learning
model
we can use this U machine learning
models with the neuro data to infer like
the what's the likely movement
directions so this is how we are going
to build up to uh actually build a uh
brain computer interface questions yeah
this for all these data you mentioned
like neuron one as a very like specific
number where how do you pinpoint which
neuron can start
measuring yeah so here neural one is
basically like we are taking so we here
make assumption that each tiny
electrode here you see is measuring like
exactly one neurons and then that
electrode will be fixed always be fixed
always measuring the fire of that
neurons
yeah but in the real case it's not it's
not always the case because like you
think about it the bra brain is this
kind of like a soft structure so if you
put electrodes there could move a little
bit and measure different neurons so
that's one of the challenging problems
of uh BC okay is that how you can deal
with this kind of neural change
recording change
yeah all right let's go back to here so
now we can basically know that we can
put some electrod into the brain into a
motor cortex measure some signals and
then we know how the neuron in encodes
those signals and then we can also build
a machine learning decoder to decode
those signals right so can basically
have some like methods to be able to
build a brain computer interface so that
we can interpret what the like a still
functioning fully functioning brain
trying to
do um one more thing is that so how we
can record this uh
signals so yeah this is a very
complicated figure but don't worry about
all the details what I'm trying to show
here that basically there's a lot of
different technologies that you can use
to uh record brain signals
but when you think about this technology
you can think about it as in this kind
of
two-dimensional two-dimensional way so
on the y axis is the think about as a
spatial resolution so the higher so the
higher up up you go on the y- axis that
means that you can basically measure you
you can basically measure like very
um the like basically shows like what's
the the region like what's the size of
the region of the brain that you can
measure so if you go really high up
there that means that you can only
measure say uh a very large like like
the average activ average brain
activities of a very large very large
Brain area whereas if you go down the Y
AIS that means that you can actually
measure two very fine green skilles like
such as a single
neurons whereas the Y the the horizontal
access here means like the the temporal
resolution that means that for
Technologies such as this kind of like a
single neuron recordings you can
basically measure like
exactly at each time point for example
like one milliseconds what's the like
electric potential is for that single
neuron whereas for technology Recording
Technology such as Mi which basically
measures like the blood flow in a small
brain region it can only measure on
average like around like like say 0 five
seconds or 1 seconds what's the blood
flow changes in that small brain area so
that's really like average of a lot of
information because we know that the
neuron fire is like this really like
fast speed right the
firing the electric potential change of
neuron is usually around order of one
milliseconds right if you can only
measure things
around like say one second you are
basically like averaging smoothing out a
lot of
informations so ideally we want to have
something both have like a high uh
spatial resolution and also uh temporal
R resolution here
um so what we will use in most of
this uh right now in a lot of like a
clinical trial in our lab is this kind
of like
a multi electrod array so each each
electrod here is like a tiny needle that
can measure maybe a signal of a few
neurons and then you put this needles
into a small tiny like a square on the
size of like a fingernail and then you
can measure maybe on order of hundreds
of
neurons all right so now we can have
this uh devices to measure neurons let's
go into a more like
a uh examples of how we do this
here so here's a let's take a example
for example
here so suppose someone has have a like
say SP spinal cord injury and then lost
the connection to his body so his mind
is still fully functioning so the
question here is that whether we can
still what kind of information we can
still decode from his motor cortex such
that we can decode those informations
and then use those informations to
either control his arm or like his own
arm or like artificial
[Music]
arm right what we going to do is uh
trying to put this kind of tiny
electrodes micro electrode arrays into
his motor
cortex really penetrating into his like
the surface of his motor
cortex and each electrod here as you see
here is this kind of tiny needle and
those uh gr triangle is the size of a
neuron so each electrod maybe is
measuring the firing potential of
multiple like local field potential of
multiple neurons around
it then we can pass all this information
in real time to a computer through this
kind of a wire right
now and then this what we get on the
computer here is that for example here
each block is basically the measurement
of that one
electrodes
and if we do some like Behavior
experiments as we just show now we can
probably figure out the tuning curve for
each electrod for example this one is
probably it's preferred direction is to
the left
right so we can repeat experiments
Behavior experiments for other for other
channels here and probably train a ml
decoder to figure out what this channel
each channel is encoding the preferred
direction for each channel so once we
have the decoder
trained and
then at test time we can basically ask
our participants who has the thing
implant his brain to trying to imagine
to move his hand to some directions and
then the decoder we're trying to figure
out the direction he's trying to move
right so that's the basic idea here
um let me go to a demo
here so this is one of the research
coming out of our lab in
2017 so here you see a
participant is typing on virtual
keyboard with uh with her mind right and
then on the bottom shows the typing
speed measured as the uh correct
characters per minute so it picks around
40 and then on average maybe it's around
like
20 I think this is really amazing like
think about like four people like
Hardward who used to have to um using
this kind of ladder board to
communicate now with this bring computer
interface he can fully uh communicate by
himself through a like say a computer so
that's a huge improvement over that the
board yeah does person open the ey or
close the uh he still opens his eyes I
mean she's still opens her eyes so is
there anything with eye tracking not for
this
experiment so even even she closed the
eye still work right yeah it will still
work but like she won't have the visual
feedback you know she won't know where
she's typing how about like if she came
up with a in a character in in the mind
e or R without looking at the keyboard
uh okay um that's something I'm going to
show next so
yeah how do you know whether it's the
person who mped or whether it's the
machine that's not capturing the correct
character like I'm confused by what do
you mean by correct
okay oh oh here so yeah that that's good
question so let me clarify here I think
the task here is uh maybe it's not
readable but I think the task here is
basically she is copying a sentence so
there we know the ground tro then we can
measure like the error
rate and
yeah ask how do you the clicking motion
or the like selection motion is is that
easy to distinguish or is there a
certain way of knowing that the user is
pressing down or does she visualize like
like a mouse or actually it that's
really good question so as I just
mentioned right so we can decode
movements and we can also decode like
say different gestures say like like say
you can use this kind of gestures or
like move his uh her elbows so you can
just imagine different uh modor
movements and then we can basically
match decode those modern movements and
map that to say a click signal or
different
signals so was it if the person look at
the keyboard and then remember the
keyboard in the in her and then she
close the eye and it does still
work
um I think that's really even like it's
that's even hard for me to do right I
can't like can you like remember the
keyboard and then just control like say
Mouse and I use keyboard every day so I
definitely remember the word Vis in my
mind and I just close my eye but this is
like a virtual keyboard so it's not like
a physical keyboard we can use your
muscle
memories yeah so yeah so maybe one thing
I have to clarify here that the mental
image for her is to say controlling like
a uh like what's the word I mean just
just like controlling a like a mouse
right so she's not actually doing the
touch typing but she is actually moving
like say a
mouse let's move
on all right so this is basically just a
showcase that
U building up on all the knowledge we
have uh learn about the brain so we can
basically decode uh some attempted
movements from people like uh like uh
this I forgot her name but like I think
it's T6 that code name T6 that we can
really help this kind of people to uh uh
regain communication through this kind
of PCI and I
think as I mentioned earlier you can
also use BCI to control robotics arms so
for example in this
case this is the participants in uh I
think
ctech
oops he's uh using his mind to control
this robotic s which grabs him a
[Applause]
drink all
right hey you finish that thing off
that's good
and
that's there you
go all right so and also you can do
things like a restore working
abilities um I think that's someone just
mentioned right now just now is that
maybe uh there's like we can try trying
to restore different modalities of
communication for example just now we're
just using the movements and then using
by restoring movements we can control
computer but like how about we directly
restore the abilities to do handwriting
right because handwriting is very um
natural ways to uh communicate so uh
Frank Frank wet uh research scientist
from our lab in 2021 published a paper
to show that you can actually do this
kind of uh handwriting BCI and he showed
that it's actually really really fast
compared to the previous one okay so now
we have seen that there's a different
ways to restore
communication
um here's just like a t a measurement of
different uh ways of communicating right
you can see on the very left is the uh
say Sip and puff interface it's very
slow basically that means that's for
someone who can not really move but can
still do uh some like a breathing they
can do the kind like a sip and a path to
say yes and no to communicate that's
really slow maybe around five words per
minute per minute for a normal person
I'm really surprised that on average a
normal person can write maybe like 13 or
14 words per minute that's really slow
but maybe that's just the average speed
and on the very far right side is the
natural communication which can reach up
to 150 and 60 words per minute for
minute just put everything into context
here so the 2D cursor I just show you
guys right now it can do eight minutes
for work per per minute eight words per
minute and the handwriting can do around
18 words per minute so compared to the
say uh Le board or like uh this kind of
ey tracking we are doing like we are
really uh make a lot of like advancement
here but still it's far way far from
like the natural conversation speed so
the next question basically is okay how
can we get there can we actually restore
natural uh can we actually restore
speech with a Brin computer
interface
um um to get there I think there's
a huge barrier here first is that um the
language processing in the brain is a
really complicated process so for
example here is sh all the braing areas
that's involved in the language and we
still don't know exactly how this
happens but this is just the our best
guess at the how language is uh
processed in the brain on the very right
you see that uh there's a lot of brain
regions that's involved with uh
knowledge and reasoning in the center is
uh maybe area that's involved with
semantics and uh syntax and on the very
left is about the perception of speech
and then the production of uh Speech
language is really complex so um maybe
the Hope here that we can start with Mod
cortex which modor planning of language
because things I've just shown you guys
that we already know how the model
cortex can incode movements right and we
can also know that in order to produce
language we need to speak and then maybe
we can put some electrodes into this
part of the modal cortex that actually
controls our oral facial muscles and
then trying to decode some information
there then see if we can actually
restore
speech
um to actually being able to restore
speech is uh I think it's more
complicated compared to the restoring
movements so what I'm trying to say here
is that this the production of speech is
really a a lot of a complicated
movements and it's really rapid it's
just more than just moving your hands to
like a certain
directions so restoring speech is much
harder than just the coding out the
those U uh like um movements of each
articulators so in instead of uh trying
to decode the movements of each
articulators because it's very hard
right so also like for people who has uh
like hard or people like uh has lost
speech it's basically it's very hard to
actually measure their uh Speech Artic
movements um instead maybe we can try to
decode out this kind of like a discrete
fums instead of like this kind of
continuous speech article Ms because we
know that all the languages has this can
be decomposed into this kind of basic
fonetic units for example for English we
know that there's different vows and
different consonants uh they are
correlated with how you place your towns
in your mouth and how you place your
different speech articulators so here
we're trying to instead of decoding the
actual articul movements we are trying
to decode this kind of like discrete
phic
tokens um and then there's a previous uh
work work showing that if you put some
electos on the modor cortex and then you
can
actually tell the differences by
measuring the tell the differences of
different fums by measuring the electric
activities in the motor cortex so
there's a hope of uh being able to
restore speech from by just putting elal
in the model cortex
here and inde so in
2021 uh researchers from UCSF actually
demonstrated that's actually feasible to
build this kind of like small vocabulary
speech PCI with this EOG Recording
Technology the difference between EOG
and then the micro electral array I just
show you guys is that uh whereas the
micro electral arrays actually
penetrates into the cortex but the Eco
stays on cortex so it doesn't actually
record single neuron firing still record
some uh average neuro activities over a
small region so compared to micro
electrod race they will have a slightly
lower resolution so that's why their
prototype is uh around this kind of like
a small vocabulary BC which can only
decode 50 words at around maybe 75%
accuracy but this is still very exciting
work that showcase that you can actually
achieve maybe achieve uh this kind of
like a speech decoding using uh uh by
putting some en actuals into M
cortex all right so I'll just right now
go into the research that's done in our
lab which is to build a high performance
speech neuroth neuro
prothesis so in
2022 so we recruited a uh participant
code named T12 who has uh AOS so T12 um
she used to be a very active person she
likes to write horse likes to jog
but uh because of AOS a couple years ago
she basically uh couldn't do all those
things that she used to enjoy and unlike
most Asos uh patients her symptom starts
with the artifcial movements first so
she still can move her hands a little
bit but she cannot really uh speak
intelligibly uh so we decided to put
four uh micro electrod arrays into her
brain two arrays into her modor cortex
and then two array into the part of the
Brokers area which is supposed to
involve with uh uh language planning so
the Hope here is that we want to PO
decode the the execution of uh of speech
the production of speech which is is you
can how you control your your like uh
Speech arcs and also maybe decode some
like high level uh planning about the
speech so that's why want to put arrays
into two different brain regions
here um so the first thing we do after
we put arrays in her brain is that we
did some like a Behavior test to see
what kind of information we can decode
from those arrays so here's a very uh
here's a result the first result we got
is that we're are trying to
classify different uh task here the
first plot is that we're trying to using
this four arrays to classify the auto
facial
movements um so this dash line is the
the cue that she's actually executing
those artificial movements and then
before this dash line she is trying to
prefer to do those artificial movements
so you can see that this two uh right
line here show that you
can classify you can classify You can
predict those movements much better
above chance using this two arrays in
the M cortex whereas this two are really
in the broadcast area you can basically
you can't really predict too much above
chance especially during the execution
of those more movements and for single
forums which we instruct our
participants to speak uh single English
fums you can also uh predict those
things much higher about like much
higher above chance using these two
arrays from the model cortex and also
for the words for single words right
so what this results tell us is that for
those two arrays we have put into t12's
mind these two arrays in the motor CeX
contains a lot of informations about the
the fumes being articulated and also the
the words being articulated but those
two AR in the broadcast area which is
supposed to uh help us to figure out the
planning of the speech production
doesn't contain too much information so
that's really intriguing to us and we're
still trying to figure out why why
that's true so for the rest of the uh
this talk here we mostly using only this
two arrays in the motor cortex
here so now we know that there's a
fanatic informations being encoded in
the those two arrays what we're going to
do next is actually trying to build a
real time spring to text
BCI here so what we're going to do is uh
let me just show you a video demo first
to
you know get a sense of what the the PC
trying to build so here this is our
participants so she's connect to uh our
decoding machines through this cable
here which transmits her neuros signals
in real time to decoding machine and
then on this screen you can see that
there's a sentence here that's we
instructed her to copy to basically to
read that out and then this once this uh
R square turn scen she will try to speak
and then what you will see below here is
what the machine is
[Music]
decoded I don't want to call for a
babysitter that would be good
[Music]
I did well in
school I don't see much pollution
turning
on all right so that's
the almost perfect decoding results from
her and you can tell from the video that
although she can vocalize but it's not
really intelligible because of her
limited um artificial muscle movements
but we can still decode out from her
brain signal that what she is trying to
say and this video is uh so the task I
just show is she's trying to copy a
sentence but this is trying to answer a
question here
I have a very good friend and
sister and we also try to different
modalities which is uh
because when she tries to uh attempting
to articulate it's very actually very
tiring for her to actually uh to
articulate those sounds so what we try
here is that only instructed her to move
her mouse or move her articulators but
not move but not vocalized so what we
call this a silent speech and we can
still decode pretty well using this kind
of like a silent speech
[Music]
modality I do not have much to compare
it
[Music]
to I as much as I would like to
either all right
okay okay so let's just move on more
technical details about how we uh build
this uh Speech V here so um as I just
mentioned right so the first thing we
need to do is to try to build a decoder
and before building that decoder we need
to do some data collection so here is
our research scientist Frank sitting
next to T12 and asking her to read that
sentence on the screen and then we'll
record the new activities of her seeing
that sentence so we'll have this kind of
a paired data collected paired data
where the input is the new activity and
the output is the targeted sentence we
want to decode so we basically have to
basically go to um where T12 Liv and
then we'll do some data collection
session there uh and then testing the
decoder the way we collect data is that
uh because um we only have very limited
time and we cannot ask T12 to to to
speak a lot of sentences so we'll divide
the our data collection into this kind
of a block structure where we can start
instructed her to speak 40 sentences
every block and then she take a break
and then we collect another block so the
data collection will last about 100
minutes for every research session and
then we Crea train a decoder maybe that
takes like uh 10 to 20 minutes it's
really quick after training a decoder
we'll start actually evaluating the
performance of decoder by asking our
participants to speak some new sentences
and then see how well we can decode on
those new set of
sentences so in total we did the
experiments sessions over maybe three
months of time and then we collect about
like 10,000 sentences from this T like a
switchboard uh tele telephone
conversation Corpus which really want to
emphasize that we want to decode this
kind of conversational
English um once we have the data then we
can try to see how we can design a
decoder that can best solve this task so
let's first Define the problem here so
we have some neuro features inputs right
so let's say we have some neuro features
which is a Time series you can think
about as a maybe similar to audio that
uh
at each time point we'll get some
feature
vectors um the output of this decoder is
a set of words right so we know that
she's trying to speak some sentence so
we are trying to decode the words from
this input neur features
here um as I say as I mentioned earlier
so instead of like directly decoding
words from the input sentences maybe we
want to have this inter media Target of
a PHS to decode the reason is that first
we know that um there's only 40 PHS in
English so that's much small set
compared to the number of words so if
you want to train decoder I can actually
decode words then you will have you need
to have much more data to cover all the
possible words whereas for PHS you
probably need way less data to cover all
the 40 fums here so we inide of decoding
directly decoding the words we decided
to decode a inter media representation
of PHS from the neuro input
features okay so basically there's a two
decoders we want to design one is the
first is a neural to volume decoder and
the second is volum to word decoder so
that's the two decoders that will have
to design this task let's focus on the
ne tonium decoder
first so basically that's I think at
this point of uh class we probably know
that we can treat this problem as a
sequence to sequence problem right so
the input is some feature sequence
output is a token sequence um and for
sequence two sequence problem we can
probably know that we can use some like
encoder and decoder models to to solve
this problem right
however for encod decod model it's
actually more powerful than we actually
need because um encod decod model allows
this kind of arbitary alignments between
inputs and outputs that's really helpful
for tasks such as the machine trans
ation whereas you know some languages
has like different word orders than
other Lang than other languages but here
we know that the the alignment is
actually is kind of like a more
monotonic compared to the like say
machine translation where the alignment
is arbitrary but monotonic I means that
you know that the probably like that the
say for example the first two neuro FES
probably like corresponds to the first
fores in out sentence rather than the
last volume in the output sentence right
so this is kind of a monotonic
alignment um so to solve this problems
of monotonic
alignments um we can actually borrow
idea that people have de developed
for machine learning tasks such as
handwriting recognition and speech
recognition where the task is also
trying to decode a say a ladder sequence
or like fum sequence also ladder
sequences from some like a uh
um Say speech Fe Fe features and the
techn we going to use is called
connection is temporal classification so
for people who have taken CS2 24s you
probably already know what this means
but I'm going to do some little bit
introduction about this thing I guess I
don't have too much time but I just
quickly go over it here so what um CDC
the connection tempis classification do
is that giving some input sequence right
the goal is that we want to decode some
output sequence but we don't know the
exact alignment between them and usually
the input output has some lens mismatch
for example in the case of like say
speech recognition um where the input is
uh could be have like a lens of like
several thousands of uh frames right
where each frame correspond to a very
like fine level like find high temporal
resolution featur such recorded at like
say 20 millisecond whereas the output
only has a few tokens so that's like a
huge lens mismatch
here what we can do is uh we can still
using like say a RN Transformer model to
predict what the output token is at each
time step right and then we somehow have
to figure out a way to fill in between
like fill in between the output tokens
some like spacers so that output token
can also have the same length as the
input
output sequence can have the same length
as the input sequence so what the CDC
loss does is introduce this additional
blank token as
output um with this blank token what you
can actually do is U for example here is
a a example output of the CTC classifier
it's trying to produce this kind of like
sequence here right what you can do is
first you merge repeated tokens and then
you're taking out that blank tokens so
what you get is a much shorter sequence
that's correspond to Output so what CDC
loss it does is it allows you to to do a
sequence to sequence problem that has a
different input and output length and
also have this kind of monotonic
alignment
property um let me just skip through
this detail here how you can train a CTC
loss
here uh just uh skip through this thing
so now let's suppose that we have this
uh CTC loss that can actually train be
used train to to to train our model
right the next problem is what kind of
decoder we want to use for this task
what kind of neural network decoders to
use for this task I think at this point
of class I think most of you guys are
convinced that Transformer is really
powerful right there's no no reason for
me to say more about it but in this case
we don't want to use Transformer the
reason is that
we don't have large data set as I
mentioned previous we only have 10,000
sentences right and also Transformer is
really good at dealing with long range
dependencies but here um for the speech
production the like there's no re really
required for long range dependency so
let's just go back to the very simple RN
we know that RN works for small data
sets and it can it can predict uh it can
deal with short range dependency pretty
well and another ni thing about RN is
that it can it's very efficient to run
in real time you can do like put a very
complicated R and even run very
efficiently on your on your mobile
phone
um one like one like the most popular uh
RN we have learn ISM right use this this
kind of like a memory State here's my
cursor uh use this memory state to
trying to store some long long-term like
long range informations and then use
this um different uh input and forget
gate input and output gates to control
how you can write read and write into
that memory state right um but LM is
also very complicated there's a variant
ofm called Gru Gator recurring unit it's
tries like I think the idea here that
just trying to combine this memory State
and hidden States into just one hidden
state by doing that you can also reduce
uh some gates so Gru is basically a more
simple version of lstm that's works
really well when you have a small small
data set so here we use Gru instead of L
lstm for our
task so now we know that how we can
decode PHS and then we have new network
models to decode PHS right we know how
to train the model so at inference Time
by inference time I mean that at testing
time you can pass in some new activities
into our decoders and then you will
decode out some like phum probabilities
right so there's a maybe at the first
time stamp the highest probability is I
uh the problem here is that how do I
figure out the most likely output
sequences giving this fun probabilties
right so basically the task is to find
the most likely output sequences here
um I think for this problem I think
since we have already did something
similar in the assignment three which is
that we can use beam search to figure
out the most likely sequence here
however this one caveat with the beam
search when you're applying it to the
CTC LW but I'm not going to expand it
too much here um yeah so let's just skip
over
that now suppose that we can use the
beam search to find the most likely fum
sequences how do we convert that fume
sequences into words right so that's CU
like we eventually want to decode uh a
sentences but not just like a a sequence
of vums so one thing you can modify the
beam search is that you can if you have
like a English dictionary where you can
map each words into its pronunciations
then while doing the beam search we can
basically see if you de some fum
sequences that correspond to words and
can basically replace that fum sequence
with that words right
um however you can actually do better by
using a language model for example here
uh that's the the
thing that's the the decoding equation
what I want to do here is that uh here
the x is the input the Y is decoded the
word sequences and then because not all
word sequences
are have the same likelihood right so
some word sequences say suppose I decode
a sentence say called I can spoke that
doesn't that doesn't seem like a
syntactically correct so we can use
maybe use the language model to evaluate
the probabilities of each decoded hypo
this and then using that as some sort of
weight on the final um decoding
probabilities so we're adding this extra
term here called the probabilities of a
sentence here that's actually you can
just decompose that into um the
probability of each token giving its
previous tokens and you can basically
measure this things using any language
models
right now another thing we want to add
here is another term is a word insertion
bonus so one problem about
this language model this probability of
sentences that actually longer sentences
will have smaller probabilities than
shorter senten that's just like the
properties of this how you decompose
that how you decompose the this
probability here so we want to actually
to balance the length of the uh decoded
sequence here by adding some word
insertion bonus so what we eventually
trying to optimize is this equation here
using um both the probabilities
generated by the RN decoder and then
using some sort of language model like
weights and then we insertion bonus and
also some ways here you can
optimize okay just start trying to put
everything together so suppose that you
have a neuro feature inputs here which
is you get this neuro features every 20
milliseconds you pass that through Gru
and now you got some phing probabilities
right this is all happens in real time
so everything has to be happen under
like all computation needs to be down
within 20 milliseconds you do a really
quick beam search and then you find okay
maybe this this pH corresponds to the
word I or the word I um and then here we
want to use the angram language model
instead of like a more powerful
Transformer language model the reason is
that we want to really do a lot of like
evaluation really quickly under 20
milliseconds so if so suppose that you
have like say 100 hypothesis right and
then you want to all evaluate the
possibility of them if you use a
Transformer language model such as gpt3
which is really powerful but you cannot
really like do really fast inferences
under 20 milliseconds right so whereas
the angram language model you can just
load everything into memory and all the
evaluation is just a memory lookup so
it's really
quick after that you can get some
probabilities out and then you'll just
keep say the top K hypothesis for the
next uh step next step of a beam search
here so that's how we use the angram
language model in the real time uh
decoding after that we'll use a
Transformer language model so
to uh rerank all the hypothesis
generated by the engram language model
so this actually happens when you
actually decoded out the entire sentence
say what I can keep the most likely 100
sentences and then I can at this time I
can use the Transformer language model
which can quickly evaluate the
probabilities say only 100 hypothesis
under the time of maybe half a second
right and then can get a better
probability measurement of other the
sentences
here yeah so putting everything together
this is how the entire system works when
I show you the previous video is
that is that we can right now using uh
this complicated not comp like
multi-stage uh machine learning model to
accurately decode what the person is
trying to see and build this high
performance uh neural uh speech Pro NE
speech
PCI right we almost time here so I just
uh skip the evaluation part evaluation
is how we measure the performance is
basically measur in the world a rate um
it also have a all the data open to as a
competition so if you guys are trying
really want to curious about this thing
you can try to play around with it I
think here's uh I think the most
exciting thing about doing this research
is that
actually see how your research can
impact people here so this is a quote
from our participant T12 and then this
is how she reacts when this thing first
worked for her it's really exciting that
uh she can speak after so many years of
uh uh
silence okay so in the last five minutes
maybe I can just go a little bit into
what I think is the future of uh bcis
here so I think what I've just shown you
guys is that using BC we can help people
to either restore movements or um
restore
communication
um one exciting Direction I think is
this kind of multimodal BCI here is a a
work published by group at UCS UCSF is
that they are trying to decode not only
the phes but also uh Speech I mean the
actual speech and then also some articul
adjures so that you can actually um move
3D avatars here and also as I just
mentioned is that the
um uh the the the the final goal of this
P PCI is you want to actually deploy it
for people to be able to use it every
day just as we use our phones right
so um so here's a more recent
development of speech PCI by our
collaborators at UC Davis what they do
is they actually p put four arrays into
the motor cortex meaning that they can
actually have better uh signals than we
do so what they I can actually show is
that so for here just for reference
because I previous I just forgot to
mention that the the final performance
of our system is that we can get maybe
around
25% word arate means that for every 100
W the participant says uh 25 of them
maybe is wrong uh so for this latest to
work at the USA d
they show that you can actually get
close to zero word error rate in uh a
few sessions by training the system more
and more continously so it's actually
being very close to being actually a
usable system right now and here's a
video of their participants using the
system to type to to speak it's very
accurate she's he's actually using the
system
to every day right now to uh for
communicating with his family and the
full
work that really cannot be understated
how important that
is all right so I think the most
exciting Direction I think happen at
least like personally I think is
happening in our lab is that um we're
trying to maybe trying to restore more
effortless and natural communication by
decoding this kind of inner speech
so previously all the speech PC just
show you I think the maximum speed we
can do is maybe to at 60 to 7 70 words
per minute but that's still far slower
compared to Natural competition which
happens at 150 words per minute so one
of the reason is that for all this
participants if we ask them to trying to
attempt to speak because they have been
lost speak speech so many years it's
very hard for them to speak at a normal
rate however we know that we know that a
lot of people have this kind of inner
speech right we're kind of like talking
to our s self in our mind I think the
research question here is whether we can
decode this sort of like inner
speech um so that is like some like a
prelim preliminary work from uh one
collaborators in our lab show that you
can actually do so so for example here
she's our the result show that by if you
decode attempted speech which is why I
just show you that you can do maybe at
the for a small set of work you can do
say at the 90% accuracy but if you ask
the participants to imagining moving her
mouth or imagining like a voice in her
head you can pretty do pretty well right
so it's not as good as um the a template
speech but still much better than much
higher than chance so I think this
showing that it's possible in the future
that we can decode this sort of like a
inner speech to fully uh restore like
natural communication to people like
Hardward and
T12 but I think there's a more a
controversial issue regarding this kind
of inner speech because what if like you
can decode something that's your like
your private thoughts or private
memories that you don't want to express
right that's a very difficult question
here and
also as I just mentioned not everyone
has UN speech and also someone maybe
like when you think about it's kind of
like speech right speech is just a
external One external representation of
your internal thoughts it's just like a
linear representation that you want to
put out through this kind of like a med
like medium of speech whereas your in
your thoughts could be more complex more
multi-dimensional so it's very hard to
decide where you want to put arrays and
you where you want to decode all those
inner but I think that's also very
exciting opportunities to for us to
learn more about like the speech
processing in the brain um and I just
mentioned like if you want to decode
this kind of inner speech then you also
coming to this uh facing a lot of new
ethical questions um that's really I
think thought provoking for example like
suppose should we allow bcis to decod
read in the memories right like what if
like we de something you don't want to
say right that's how can we deal with
that on the other hand like what if we
can actually use this things to help
people who has lost their memories due
to like a Alzheimer disease right or
we can read out some like subconscious
fear that can help people to do their
psycho therapies are this like how
should we decide whether we want to
allow this kind of in decoding or not or
you know memory decoding or lot or not
and
also I think a more like deeper question
is like what if like one day we could do
this kind of like a cognitive
enhancement with BCI such as you know
what if you can move a robotic arm much
faster than your real arm is that
allowed
or like can you actually purchase a
memory so that you can skip this CS2 24n
class um yeah I think that's really a
hard question to answer but it's just
like to throw this question out so that
you know we're not like it's not like
only a PCI problem but we're also facing
this problem right now right there's a
lot of ways you can do enhancement of
yourself so I guess what I'm trying to
say here is that b will raise a lot of
new a lot of new uh ethical questions
so this is I'm taking this quote from uh
this textbook here what it's trying to
say is that I think this question is um
we're not really looking for answer here
but I think the point here that maybe we
just want to keep this in discussion
with Scientists with Engineers with uh
with policy makers and just to make sure
that
everything know well we we can use BCI
to help people that's really need them
and and also be aware that there could
be some a lot of like potential issues
here um yeah I think the just to give a
summary here so I think I've I hope I
can convince you guys that BCI is a
really cool new research directions it's
uh at the intersection of uh AI machine
learning neuroscience and
neuroengineering uh we'll soon have this
kind of like systems that can really
help people to be able to communicate
again and also it's a really cool
opportunity days to understand how the
brain process the process languages I
think I think the most important thing
is that we are bringing hope to people
like horard and
T12 all right thank you everyone and
special thanks to the people in my last