okay cool uh let's just get started uh
welcome everyone to lecture
12 um so you know so far we've learned a
lot about how uh like you know we
convert words into vectors how we
convert sentences into vectors and you
know uh basically uh take actions in the
real world using that so like classify
documents uh we learned about uh you
know Transformers we learned about
pre-training today is going to be a
little bit different uh I'm going to be
talking about how you can train large
models on gpus and a few Basics about
how you know these ml systems work and
it's it has nothing to do with natural
language at all but hopefully it's going
to be useful for final
projects um so I'm going to spend some
time on mixed Precision training uh some
time on multi-gpu training with DDP and
Fs DP and hopefully by the end of the
lecture these terms will make sense and
sometime on parameter efficient
fine-tuning uh but before we get into
the lecture uh just some
announcements uh proposal grades are
going to be coming out shortly uh
hopefully by the end of the day uh thank
you so much for all the hard work I know
you know it's kind of getting a little
bit crammed with you know a lot of
deadlines for assignment 4 and the
project proposal so thank you so much
for for all your hard work uh the other
thing is the project Milestone uh
details should be out shortly if not
already out on the website um so it's
worth 5% of the overall grade uh it's
due 12 days from now and it's a maximum
of two pages and really the way to think
about the Milestone is to use this as a
forcing function to get work done for
your final project um and yeah uh with
that out of the way let's just jump into
into the material uh so I'm going to
start by thinking about how parameters
and gradients and generally numbers are
represented in computers uh and I
promise it's going to be relevant to to
deep learning pretty soon so let's start
with uh floating Point uh how many
people here are familiar with this
cartoon depiction of fp32 can you just
get okay so some of you so yeah let's
let's kind of recap how floating points
are represented in computers uh so so
firstly fp32 that's like 32 bytes so the
memory requirement is it's 32 bits so
the memory requirement is 4 bytes okay
and so if you're thinking about neural
networks then for every single neural
net parameters you need four bytes of
GPU memory and the way to convert this
cartoon into a real number is something
like this uh so the first bit there is
the sign and then the stuff in green
represents the range and then the stuff
in blue represents Precision okay um and
and yeah and and so for fp32 you know
there's like uh you can represent like a
pretty large range and it's fairly
precise right um and so the larger the
stuff in green is the more numbers you
can represent which means more smaller
numbers and also like larger numbers and
the more stuff in green uh the more
stuff in blue we have the greater appr
Precision in representing actual numbers
okay um so another popular data type
that takes half the memory of fp32 is
fp16 and uh the way we reduce memory is
we're going to reduce uh the stuff in
green so there's going to be less range
less dynamic range and also the stuff in
blue which means it's going to be uh
less Precision okay but the good uh
thing is that we can save memory so you
know we slash memory requirements in
half so uh let's think of a scenario
where you know you're trying to train a
big neural network and your model
parameters and gradients are represented
in fp32 you start training and suddenly
you get uh an out of memory Cuda error
okay and so just based on you know what
we've seen so far one possible solution
is you cast everything into
fp16 okay and if you do that you reduce
memory usage by
half um so let's kind of work through
what are some possible problems with
doing something like that uh so you know
like I said uh because there's less
stuff in green there's going to be less
range and so that means uh a lot of uh
very small numbers will get uh converted
to zero and a lot of really large
numbers will get converted into n okay
and there's also less Precision because
you have less bits in in in blue which
means you're going to get rounding
errors um for example uh 1.1
gets converted to one uh in half
Precision uh and I have a little uh
screenshot of how you can test uh
various properties of data types right
so um basically the things to to to to
look at are the Epsilon the Epsilon is
like the smallest number such that if
you add that to one you don't lose any
Precision if you add a number that's
smaller than Epsilon to one that gets
just round rounded down to one and the
smallest normal is the smallest number
that can be presented in uh uh fp16
anything smaller than that it goes
straight to zero okay and uh for neural
network training if a lot of small
numbers get rounded down to zero uh
that's actually not good so here's a
diagram that I took from uh an Nvidia
blog post that's just showing um just
sort of some gradients during the course
of training and more than half of these
gradients will literally just get set to
zero in in fp16 uh which is kind of a
problem um and uh that has to do with
the range of fb16 and the second problem
is uh with Precision right so we have
basically uh less precision and so our
updates are not going to be
precise
okay so uh the solution here's one
possible solution right so uh we're
going to use fp16 but we also going to
use fp32 okay so that's that's sort of
the high level idea uh and what we're
going to do is we're going to maintain
uh a copy of the model in fp32 and let's
call those Master weights and then uh
you get a little bit of data you run a
forward pass um and then when you run
your forward pass you run it by uh
converting from fp32 into fp16 okay and
then uh you get a gradient run a
backward pass and then get your gradient
in fp16 okay so everything so far has
happened in fp16 then you take your
gradients upcast them into
fp32 and then update your master weights
and then once you update your master
weights you copy them into the fp16
version of the neural network okay so
this seems like a reasonable scheme you
know I'm using fp16 on my GPU but I have
the full sort of uh 32-bit Precision
also lying around somewhere so I can
have more precise updates okay uh can
someone tell me why this is still
problematic any
guesses yeah uh one would be like really
slow because you have to copy like the
32 bit versions from like GPU into like
some yeah so so that's a good point so
you can often like overlap uh IO with
like forward and backward passes so
practically this is not a problem but
yeah that's a good point potentially if
your network is very very small this
would be a
problem yeah gradients are usually
fairly small like individual gradients
are usually Fair small and when you copy
the fp6 computed Radiance onto fp32 you
may be sending your network somewhere
else where you don't want it
to so yeah so that's that's pretty much
pretty much the right answer so you know
let's kind of uh go back to this diagram
that we had uh so this shows gradients
in the backward pass and you know I said
that we're going to compute all our
gradients in fp16 what's going to happen
like most of them will just get
converted to zero okay which is which is
something that we really would like to
avoid okay so here's a possible solution
so what you can do is you can you get
your batch of data you run your forward
pass in fp16 you compute your gradient
uh but then when you have the uh sorry
so we here um so you get a batch of data
you compute a forward pass in fp16 you
get your loss you scale the loss by some
large value okay let's say 100 let's say
a th000 and then you compute gradients
and now you just like scale your
gradient by a large number and so
everything that we had on the left hand
side of this red line just gets shifted
to the right and hopefully there's less
stuff that will uh get rounded down to
zero
okay and then compute your gradient in
fp16 copy it into fp32 and then divided
by the scaling factor and then you
update your master widths okay uh so
this will solve uh both the problems
that we talked about okay and so this is
basically uh what we call Precision
training okay and it's relatively simple
to implement this in pytorch uh all you
have to do is uh you need to instantiate
this grad scalar uh uh object and then
um within the context of like this
AutoCast you want to run your forward
and backward passes and then um scale
down your gradient uh and then uh update
your model parameters
okay uh but then this seems a little
complex you know we have to deal with
sort of scaling the loss uh and then
scaling it back down what if you
multiplied it by 10,000 and that leads
to nans and so then you have to kind of
scale uh you have to update your scaler
you have to like in the next iteration
multiply by th000 you know and you have
to kind of adjust to to sort of network
Dynamics okay so we'd like to not do
gradient scaling um so can we do
something better okay so uh the reason
we why we have to do the scaling is you
know just recall uh sort of the role of
uh of sort of the bits in green that
kind of tells you what is the dynamic
range of the data type and we needed
scaling because fp16 has a small much
smaller range compared to fp32
right um and so because of that fp16
cannot represent very small numbers okay
so how do we solve this any ideas
yeah so uh here's the problem right so
in fp16 because you have fewer bits for
the exponent you can't represent very
small numbers so if you have something
that's smaller than I don't know 6 e
minus 5 it gets uh down uh sort of uh uh
rounded down to zero and that's because
of the dynamic range of fp16 so how do
you solve that sacrifice Precision so
have more
green absolutely yeah so that's that's
the right answer uh so what we're going
to do is we're going to sacrifice uh
Precision so uh that's the idea for B
float 16 which stands for brain float 16
um so you're going to have exactly the
same number of bits for representing the
range so that's going to be eight bits
so has the same dynamic range as
fp32 but a lot less precision and it
turns out that this this is okay for
neural network training okay
and now if you use B float 16 you don't
need to use uh grad scalers anymore it's
it's as simple as wrapping your model
forward pass and backward pass uh within
the right uh
context uh the one caveat about B flat
16 is that it's not available on all
gpus so you need to have the latest sort
of ampere uh Nvidia architectures which
the h100s the a100 the a6000 have uh but
if you have like a older GPU then you
might not be able to utilize B FL 16
sorry can you why having less Precision
but the same amount of eits um yeah so
it's B 6 and oh never mind sorry
I'm uh so here are some um kind of
results um so someone uh find you in
dist bir for sentiment classification on
a single a 100 um at the very top is
float 64 which is like you know really
really rich 64bit representation of
floating points it takes about 25
minutes um and you get a pretty high
accuracy but it also takes a lot more
memory okay and all the way down we're
using mixed Precision training with B
float 16 and now we have reduced
staining Time by roughly a third um more
or less have the same accuracy a little
bit better actually because there's some
regularizing effect from U the you know
half bit uh the half Precision
representation and then a lot less
memory
okay uh and the reason we see speedups
for training is because Matrix
multiplies tend to be faster when you
are multiplying in half
Precision okay so uh before we move on
are there any questions about about
this Okay cool so uh let's let's keep
going and uh let's sort of change the
setting right so now now we have more
than one GPU now we have multiple gpus
and we want to train a network or all of
the multiple gpus that we have Okay so
let's start with some Basics okay so uh
here's a cartoon
showing uh basically a model and an
Optimizer uh receiving some data from a
data set okay and let's kind of work
through what's stored on GPU vram okay
and this is going to be some what of a
lie and I will I I will point out what
my lie is soon uh but you know just to
keep things simple uh we have the neural
net parameters okay so let's say we're
doing mixed procure training and so it's
stored in
fp16 and then we have an Optimizer okay
and uh you know when I first saw this uh
you know few years back I was very
surprised to see that optimizers also
need memory but uh if you're using
something like Adam uh then you need to
store the adom momentum term and the
adom variance and every time you get a
gradient you have to update adom
momentum and variance and that's what
you use uh for updating your parameters
and because you're using mixed Precision
training these have to be represented in
sort of um fp32 okay uh so so that's
that that's that's what the picture
looks like if you have a single GPU now
let's say we have multiple gpus okay and
what we'd like to do is is uh first
divide our data set into let's say we
have four GPS right so we'll divide our
data set into four parts and we'll
maintain a synchronized copy of the
model uh and every model receives its
own slice of the data set
okay um in the beginning we have a
synchronized model and everyone has
their own copy we run a forward pass
okay so this forward pass receives
different data points and so every model
is going to have different activations
and correspondingly every model is going
to have different gradients okay so you
run a backward pass every model has a
different gradient because there's
different data points and then we're
going to run a synchronization step and
what synchronization is going to do is
communicate gradients between between
different workers okay and so I'm going
to introduce the first sort of uh MPI
primitive in this lecture and that
primitive is called the all reduce
operation what all ruse does is it takes
um four pieces of uh information on in
this example on four different gpus it
sort of merges everything together and
then uh distributes it to all of the
gpus okay and the communication overhead
of doing that is two bytes per parameter
because remember we have uh fp16
gradients okay so two bytes per gradient
and then uh this needs to be
communicated um and so the overhead is 2
bytes per
parameter okay so that's the all reduce
operation uh and then once gradients
have been communicated so they have to
be communicated by you know sort of
gathering on one worker and just sort of
Distributing the cumulative gradient at
that point uh every Optimizer has the
full gradient and then the optimizer can
you know update the model so that you
maintain
synchronization okay so that's the basic
that's uh that's known as distributed
data parallel okay um that's good uh but
turns out that it has really poor memory
scaling so let's kind of go through our
math for how many uh how much memory is
needed right so uh we have the model
parameters that's fp16 because we're
doing mixed Precision training and then
for the gradient we also have the
gradient in fp16 right so two bytes uh
for the gradient and then we have the
stuff in green the stuff in green is
let's say we're doing adom so we need to
well we need to store the master waste
regardless of whether we're doing adom
or not and then we need to store the
momentum and the variance okay so that's
12 extra bytes uh per parameter okay and
this needs to be stored on every single
GPU okay um and so the question is can
we do better than this okay and so now
uh things are going to get a little bit
more tricky so if you have questions
just stop me um and you know we can we
can go from there so um the way we're
going to improve uh our memory sort of
scaling is we are a set of techniques uh
that are together known as zero that
stands for zero redundancy Optimizer so
this was uh you know a set of techniques
released by Microsoft as part of their
deep speed project okay and the idea is
going to be that we are going to instead
instead of having every GPU contain all
of this state so by the state I mean the
stuff in blue the stuff in Orange and
the stuff in green you're going to sort
of Shard it okay so there's there's
there's going to be uh shards so that
not every GPU has all of the parameters
or all of the gradient but by
communication they can sort of
synchronize okay so that's pretty much
what uh the the the uh sketch for this
is going to look like okay so let's look
at stage one so like zero has like
multiple stages so there's stage one 1
two and three in stage one we're going
to Shard uh the stuff in green so stuff
in green was the optimizer State um and
so the way we're going to Shard and
still maintain synchronization is
something like this okay so every GPU
has um you know uh the full set of
parameters in
fp16 and every GPU has its its gradient
for its data okay but it only has a
sharded copy of the full Optimizer State
and the the the other requirement is
that every GPU is responsible for
updating the parameters corresponding to
its own Shard okay so if you go step by
step this is what it looks like uh every
every GPU has its own
data uh every GPU gets a gradient on its
subset of the data okay then we perform
a reduced scatter so now this is the
second uh MPI operation of the lecture
so we've we've done all reduce this is
the second one this is called reduce
scatter
uh what A reduced scatter does is every
GPU
has uh the full gradient on its data and
what you want to do is you want to take
the chunk corresponding to let's say GPU
1 so let's say your GPU 0 and you've
computed the full gradient for all the
parameters and you want to
communicate uh your uh the chunk for GPU
1 to GPU 1 okay and same for GPU 2 and
three okay so what you're going to do is
from the full gradient just communicate
the bits that a different worker wants
to that worker okay and every GPU has to
do that so that's called a reduced
scatter okay and then once every worker
gets uh the gradient corresponding to
its Shard they're going to update its
parameters and then once they have
updated their Shard they're going to
sort of perform an all gather so what
that means is let's say you have a
neural network with just let's say eight
parameters uh two parameters on each GPU
at the end of this uh each GPU has
updated their subset of parameters and
then they're going to sort of do an all
gather to just sort of maintain
synchronization so every GPU gets the
full set of parameters that are all
updated yeah is maintaining this and
you're not merging them together in that
way um what is what makes this more
efficient um sorry could you repeat your
question can you go over why this is
better than doing the prion right so uh
what we're going to do is uh Shard the
optimizer state right so let's say in a
running example we have a neural network
with eight parameters okay earlier uh we
needed the optimizer state for all of
the eight parameters now every GPU has
to maintain Optimizer state for only two
parameters okay so after the reduced
scatters are done you have the full uh
gradient corresponding to just two
parameters okay so the optimizer state
is just uh the gradient for two
parameters the model is going to update
only two
parameters using the partial uh uh sort
of Optimizer state but you have to have
the entire set of parameters to run so
you'll eventually get the rest of the
parameters back so you have the entire
set of parameters you have all the stuff
in blue and you have the full grad for
your subset but you don't have the full
Optimizer state so what you can do is
you can only update the parameters for
the bits of Optimizer State you have
okay so in a running example that I just
made up uh you know gp0 updates two
parameters gpu1 updates two parameters
and so on okay and then they communicate
updated parameters to maintain
synchronization okay more questions
about this
okay so let's keep going so so so far we
have looked at three MPI operations we
looked at um all gather we looked at
reduce scatter and we looked at all
reduce okay so turns out that um all
reduce is actually equivalent to running
a reduced scatter followed by an all
gather
operation and just recall that like for
DD P all we had to do was this all
reduce operation and we commun we we
computed what's the communication
overhead of that and turns out that when
you're doing this Optimizer State
sharding you have to do exactly the same
amount of communication overhead just
because an all reduce is equivalent to a
reduce scatter followed by an all gather
okay and so we basically saved memory
for free okay so just I mean you should
just always use this okay um because you
going to get memory savings and you
don't have any additional communication
overhead okay so we happy we saved
memory and now you know we want to Shard
even more things okay so let's let's
start doing zero stage two uh and now
along with sharding the stuff in green
which was my Optimizer state I'm also
going to Shard gradients okay and now
this is going to be a little bit more
complex because um we kind of still need
need the full gradient
for the workers's data slice okay but
each GPU only has enough memory for um
instantiating the gradient for a small
subset of parameters so how are we going
to deal with
that so we are actually never going to
instantiate the full gradient vector and
then whenever a GPU gets um a gradient
in the backward pass you instantiate uh
a vector sort of temporarily for the
parameter for which you just received a
gradient and then compute the gradient
and then just send it to the right
worker and then you destroy the memory
that you just created okay that's kind
kind of the sketch and let's kind of go
through this step by step
okay so um we have four workers okay
each worker performs a backward pass and
the backward pass happens layer by layer
right so uh recall the lecture on uh
Auto diff so you have the loss and then
you have this back backward passw layer
by layer you compute gradients okay so
now let's say you're at layer J you take
the Upstream gradient you compute
gradient for the parameters at ler okay
immediately the moment you compute those
gradients send it to the right worker
okay so there exists some worker that is
responsible for ler okay and what's
going to happen is every GPU that's just
computed uh the gradient for layer J for
its data slice sends it to the right
worker okay uh and then the moment
you've done that you deallocate this
memory that you just created okay uh and
so uh this is kind of uh a fourth MPI
operation but really not very different
from a reduce CER this is just a reduce
so there are four gpus uh that have a
gradient and then they just have to
communicate it to whoever is responsible
for maintaining gradient for that layer
okay um
and then yeah so there exists some
worker that is responsible for a given
layer they're going to
update uh its parameter Shard using uh
the full gradient that it received via
this communication along with the
optimizer State okay and then at the end
to synchronize everything you have to
perform in all gather as
before okay uh any any questions about
about uh this like high level sketch
okay so so let's keep moving um okay so
recall that uh for zero stage one um it
was basically free because uh turns out
that an all reduce is equivalent to a
reduce scatter plus an all gather and
we're kind of doing the same thing here
we have a reduce followed by an all
gather so this is practically also for
free Okay so
we've gotten away with saving memory
without any communication overhead
compared to DDP so far okay so let's
keep going let's let's try and see if we
can Shard even more things
okay uh and I think someone sort of
alluded to this in the audience early on
so what happens if you Shard even your
model parameters okay so let's say you
run into a situation where uh you know
forget about the optimizer State even
your model wouldn't fit on a single GPU
and so in that that case what you do is
you split up your model so you split up
your model across all the different gpus
so you Shard your model parameters which
is the stuff in blue um uh but the
caveat is that now we're not going to
get uh this for free we're not going to
get memory savings for free there's
going to be some communication overhead
okay and uh this is zero stage three
this is the final stage of zero this is
also known as fsdp fully shoted data
parallel for uh anyone who's heard that
term before
um and here's sort of the high level
sketch okay and I feel like uh this is
kind of the easiest to understand
compared to zero stage one and two um
just because there needs to be
communication at every step of the way
right you can't get away uh without
communicating so the first thing we're
going to do is we're going to take our
model and we're going to convert the
entire model into fsdp units Okay so
here's a sketch um a simple deep neural
network I'm going to convert that into
multiple fsdp units uh three fsdp units
here okay so that's that's just a data
structure an fsdp unit okay we've not
done anything so far uh and then I have
this fsdp unit I'm going to convert this
into another data structure called a
flat parameter and then I'm going to uh
assign a subset of these parameters to
every single GP okay so here we have 16
gpus and a flat parameter consisting of
14 parameters plus some extra padding so
that uh things divide properly and I'm
going to assign each parameter to uh a
distinct GPU okay and so that's
basically just a complex way of saying
that we created some data structures and
we just like divided up model parameters
uh to every GPU okay so every GPU gets a
subset of model
parameters um okay now let's start
thinking about what my forward pass
would look like so there's no GPU that
has the full set of parameters okay so
you're running a forward pass let's say
you're at layer 4 now there's no GPU
that has all of layer 4 so you have to
communicate uh so we need to do an all
gathered operation that's the operation
that we did to um you know uh cumulate
multiple things that are on multiple
gpus uh so that every GPU has the full
thing uh so you perform an all gather so
that all so you have all pieces of layer
four you run a forward pass okay and now
you don't need layer four so you now
discard your parameter shards
okay and now you have to run your
backward pass right so you computed your
loss and now you have to do a backward
pass uh again uh let's say you are back
at layer four you have your Upstream
gradient uh you don't have layer four so
you need to do another all gather so you
get all the parameters of layer four
um and then you uh run a backward pass
for layer Force you compute the gradient
for your subset of parameters so recall
that every GPU has different data points
right so there's going to be different
gradients for every GPU okay so then for
layer four uh you do an all gather get
all parameters computer gradient every
GPU has different gradients and then you
have to do a reduce scatter so that uh
you can send the full gradient to the
GPU that's responsible for whatever
parts of layer 4 uh that that that
you're sending okay
so yeah so so that's basically uh full
fsdp um and then once you uh once you
sort of run the forward and backward
pass then each GPU will update its own
parameter Shard using the full gradient
that it received just now um and then
you do a synchronization
right so let's kind of do a quick review
of everything we've looked at so far um
so there was
DDP um which was you don't shot anything
you have the full model full gradient
the full Optimizer State on every single
GPU and all you're going to divide up is
the full data set right so you have a
big data set of 1,000 examples every GPU
gets 250 examples okay and then you
compute a forward pass and a backward
pass every GPU has a different gradient
you need to communicate that gradient
and then you synchronize okay and so
that was called an all reduce operation
uh in MPI terms and then we looked at
zero which is now we want to save some
memory we don't want uh the full sort of
memory requirements of models gradients
and Optimizer State on every single GPU
and in zero stage one we shouted the
optimizer state so that there is uh you
know so that you don't have to maintain
the full Optimizer state for every GPU
you kind of break that down between all
the different gpus that you have and we
saw that the communication overhead of
maintaining synchronization in zero
stage one boiled down to basically just
doing an all reduce through this uh
identity that says that an all reduce is
a reduce scatter plus an all gather okay
and we save memory for free with zero
stage one and two so you should just do
it uh you know um and then with zero
stage three things got a little bit more
complex uh because you have to divide up
your model parameters the optimizer
State and the gradient and so while
you're running your forward pass you
kind of have to do some communication to
get the full parameters for for any
layer for layer four uh in in our
example and then also have to do an all
Gather in the backward pass so you get
the full gradient and then you have to
do a reduce scatter so that you can send
the full gradient for whatever chunk of
the parameter to the right GPU and uh
over overall that's like two all gathers
plus a reduced scatter so that's a lot
more overhead uh than stages one and two
but if you don't uh have enough GPU vram
so that you can even load your model
onto a GPU then this is kind of what you
have to do um all right uh any questions
about MPI Primitives or stages of of
zero or fsdp
okay cool um so I'm going to fix the lie
that uh that I said earlier about the
GPU vram calculation um so I said that
there's just like model parameters and
gradients uh and the optimizer state but
there's this thing there this like final
thing the model Activation so like you
know we've all seen that uh as you keep
you know you you want to increase the
bat size uh and there's a point when the
GPU say says that it can't fit more
stuff and that's because you also need
to store model activations in the
backward pass right uh and that scales
linearly with the bath size okay so the
larger the bath size the more the number
of model activations that need to be
stored uh and by the way if you're doing
mixed Precision this is in fp16 or bf16
but it scales with the bat size okay and
so uh that's sort of the other thing
that you have to think about and you
know you uh none of the techniques that
we've looked at so far
help with uh kind of Shing model
activations um so okay so we looked at a
bunch of like um you know basics of like
multi-gpu uh training and you know like
floating point but it kind of boils down
to this very simple flowchart which you
can use for your final projects when
you're fine tuning models so the first
thing is always use mixed Precision
training you know you barely ever see a
a hit in performance
uh by performance I mean like
generalization or like you know F1 or
accuracy and if you're using the newer
ampere architectures the the h100s or
the A1 100s or the a6000 always use BF
float 16 uh it's just better um and you
can check that with with that torch
command um okay so always use mixed
Precision training now uh ask yourself
this question does bat size one fit on a
a single GPU okay if it fits and try a
larger bat size okay bat size one is too
small uh try a larger bat size and or
use zero stage two okay zero stage two
is for free just use a zero stage two
and increase your bat size if you can't
fit even bat size one uh then you have
to see if zero stage three fixes your
out of memory issues cuz now you're
going to Shard your model
parameters okay and all of this is is in
the context of full fine tuning right so
I'm fine tuning all of my model
parameters
okay sometimes the answer to that
question is also no so you can't full
fine tune your model on four whatever A1
100s or you know
a6000 um and you've tried zero stage
three you've start you've tried mixed
Precision training uh you have a bat
size of one maybe you did gradient
checkpoint pointing activation
checkpointing and nothing works and so
now uh basically you can't do full fine
tuning and so the thing to do is to try
parameter efficient fine-tuning okay and
that's going to give you a lot more uh
memory savings
okay so let's talk about parameter
efficient fine tuning
okay um so why is it called parameter
refer in fine tuning so in full fine
tuning uh you know you run a forward
pass and a backward pass and you update
every single model parameter and in
parameter efficient fine-tuning you're
only going to update a small subset of
the full uh set of parameters
okay and uh why would you want to do
that so uh you know maybe you're in a
setting where you cannot full fine tune
even with bat size one you've tried all
the tricks possible uh it just wouldn't
fit uh and so maybe you have to do
parameter efficient fine tuning um maybe
the other possible reason why you want
to do it is kind of slightly more
scientific uh you know these like models
these days are heavily
overparameterized uh and you have a
small data set and you you believe that
if you do parameter efficient F tuning
uh then you can get a better like
generalization
okay um or you believe that you know
it's going to match for fine tuning okay
uh sort of a second reason for wanting
to do f
adaptation um so uh the plot on the
right here shows uh in in red it's sort
of the estimated growth uh in training
compute for training the largest AI
models and uh the line in blue is the
global compute capacity so very soon we
are going to overshoot the global
compute capacity and going to need a lot
more compute than you know the global
capacity and so this is kind of not
sustainable
um and you know there's there there are
arguments to be made about how uh if we
keep going down this route then you know
AI development becomes concentrated in
only the hands of a few well-funded
organizations and you know as students
we can't do it um and so that's a
problem and then also like if there's
only a small number of players that are
training and fine-tuning models then
they may bias the model in specific ways
that reflect their value systems and not
sort of the the broader uh public um and
so that's another reason to do full uh
to to think about efficient adaptation
um and there's sort of this Paradigm in
in in machine learning in general and
NLP uh specifically to focus uh a lot on
on accuracy instead of efficiency and so
the pro on the right here shows um the
percentage of papers where where the
main contribution is a method that
produces just you know more accurate
models versus methods that produce same
accuracy for more efficiency um and so
we can see that for most
conferences the vast majority of papers
are about accuracy there's very few
papers about efficiency okay um and and
so maybe this is kind of leading to this
like monoculture and maybe that's why we
want to focus on efficiency
uh the second maybe bigger sort of
concern is that there's this huge uh
hidden environmental cost of of training
and fine-tuning large language models uh
so I was just reading some report where
where they said that the cost of
training gpt3 was equivalent to 1.1
million tons of carbon emission or some
some some some some such number and they
they kind of estimated that that's the
cost of running a Coal Power Plant for
10 hours straight okay um
all right uh and and uh for an example
closer to home um in in in the
reinforcement learning class um there
was like uh you know the final project
no not the final project a homework
assignment and um you know a lot of
students implemented uh kind of a common
algorithm uh one uh one or two
algorithms that sort of outperformed
everything else it used a lot more power
okay and someone did this calculation
that if everyone had used the most
efficient algorithm that would have uh
uh sorry if everyone had used the more
efficient algorithm that would have
reduced the power consumption of the
Class by about 880 kilowatt hours which
is what an American household uses in a
month okay so so there's another like
the you know these are all reasons to
think about like efficiency and like how
you can um like fine tune your models
with like uh less resources okay uh so
let's let's kind of jump back into like
parameter efficient fine tuning okay and
let's let's start by recapping what full
fine tuning
is um any questions so far about any of
this okay um so yeah so let's recap full
fine tuning so let's say we have some
large uh pre-trained Auto regressive
language model um let's say it's a
GPT um and maybe we want to to use it
for summarization maybe we want it for
semantic parsing so like converting
natural language to SQL commands or
maybe we want it to answer questions
about paragraphs okay and what do we do
we collect a data set of XY Pairs and
then we do full fine tuning in full fine
tuning we are going to update all of the
model parameters based on the gradient
for some loss function okay um and maybe
that's not feasible uh GPD 3 has 175
billion parameters and so there's just
like lot more parameters to learn and
even once you have done full fine tuning
uh you kind of have to store all of the
parameters and if you're doing like
several tasks you have to store
parameters for every task okay uh so can
we do better
um okay so the main idea is instead of
updating all of the parameters I am
going to update
um a much smaller number of parameters
okay uh and and then instead of uh
finding sort of a Delta Theta which is
the same size as the entire set of
parameters I have to search over a much
smaller
space uh and then the added benefit is
uh I can store this much smaller Delta
uh pretty easily on disk and hopefully
it's going to require less compute and
hopefully it's going to generalize
almost as well as full fine tuning
okay um so there's many different ways
of um kind of operationalizing this high
level idea of of parameter efficient
fine tuning uh the one I'm going to talk
about today is Laura okay so that stands
for uh low rank
adaptation and uh that basically comes
from this observation that when you have
uh big language models that you fine
tune often times when you look at sort
of the um the like geometric structure
of the gradients they tend to have a low
intrinsic rank okay um do people
remember Rank and
SD all right okay so um so these
parameters uh so the the gradients tend
to have a low intrinsic rank okay and so
what the authors real realized is
instead of uh fine-tuning the entire set
of parameters you could instead
fine-tune a much smaller let's say rank
R Matrix for every uh full rank Matrix
that exists in the model okay so let's
say we have uh some pre-trained weight
Matrix W
KN and what I'm going to do is instead
of applying some kind of arbitrary
update I'm going to make sure that the
update it has this following form okay
so it's going to be the product of two
low rank matrices b and a okay so a is
in R uh in R is is an R cross K uh
Matrix and B is a d cross R Matrix okay
and R is is the rank much much smaller
than either the um the uh sort of uh
incoming Dimension and much much smaller
than the outgoing Dimension okay and the
term Alpha you can think of that as some
kind of trade-off between uh the
knowledge that's already stored in the
pre-rain model versus some additional
knowledge that you want to add into the
model okay so if Alpha is zero then
you're not doing anything if Alpha is
something really really small then you
don't really want to change your model
parameters all that much and you want to
add some really small task specific
knowledge um and then additionally the
only trainable parameter s here are
going to be a and b
okay
um
okay um and then uh sort of the other
thing to note about this is uh since I'm
representing updates as this product u b
* a as I increase R that's going to
converge towards full fine tuning right
so you kind of have the slider that you
can use to control how much fine tuning
you want to do is essentially
um and then uh the other important thing
is uh inference latency so what you can
do is uh you can just store these
learned matrices for every task and
whenever you switch to a different task
uh you can just uh you can just remove
the extra term that you've added to
every Matrix for that task and add in
sort of the task specific terms for the
new task that you want to run inference
on okay and and the cost of like storing
these like much smaller matrices is also
way lower than storing uh sort of the
full Delta
okay um and we'll kind of see where you
should apply Laura but like generally
you want to apply it to uh the weight
matrixes in self attention okay so um in
code it actually looks fairly simple um
so what you're going to do is uh when
you're running uh the regular forward
pass then you sort of uh you know just
like compute the hidden State as let's
say the product of uh The Matrix and the
incoming feature uh Vector now with
Laura what you're going to do is you're
going to freeze your model parameters
you're going to compute the H as before
and then to that you're going to add
this additional offset term and that's
the only thing that's going to be uh
trainable okay and that's pretty much
all you have to do we have to do it for
every single like weight Matrix uh for
every single layer okay
um but yeah so there's like an alpha
term in the second to last line where do
you define Alpha in the rest or do you
just like put it
somewhere uh so you so so yeah so you
define the somewhere uh if you set it to
one that's like saying that uh I kind of
want um uh like an equal trade-off
between pre-trained knowledge and the
new task specific knowledge typically
people set it to one you could set it to
something larger than one if you believe
your task is something that the model uh
the pre- model has no idea about uh or
something smaller than one if you don't
want to change the model too
much
um so so that's basically Laura um in
practice so I said there's a bunch of
different uh parameter efficient fine
Heering methods right so uh I'm not even
going to name all of these uh there's
adapters some of you might have heard
about
adapters uh there is uh bitfit which is
not here um and so there's like lots of
different like ptuning um but it turns
out that like compared to a lot of these
different uh methods it's it's kind of
like uh you know pretty high high
performing uh on a bunch of different
tasks uh for these like relatively
smaller models okay um and then if we
try and look at uh some of the bigger
like we're trying to fine tune some of
the bigger models like GPD 3 uh and then
compare it with other parameter
efficient fine tuning methods um so full
fine tuning is is is at the is at the
way top then we have bit fit uh which is
you only fine tune the bias terms um and
and adapters compared to that uh firstly
Laura requires a lot fewer additional
parameters that you need to store uh and
it kind of gives you a good tradeoff for
accuracy compared to full fine tuning
and sometimes there's a regularizing
effect uh from fine tuning only small
subset of your model
parameters
um
okay so uh you know the question is like
for every uh Matrix you can apply Laura
and I said that you want to apply it to
the various um learned uh bit matrices
in site self attention the question is
what uh what parameters uh you want to
apply Lura to and uh generally the rule
of the thumb is that if you apply it to
the Matrix that takes your hidden State
and converts that into queries and the
Matrix that converts your hidden State
into values apply Lura to those and
that's pretty much going to give you the
best performance overall um the other
hyperparameter for Laura is the optimal
rank so recall that these like two
matrices b and a that are both like low
rank and turns out that like already
with a a really small uh rank you can
get a pretty high performance okay and
this is much much smaller than um sort
of the Hidden State dimensions of most
of the matrices for most models these
days okay all right so uh we covered a
bunch of things uh we talked about uh
you know floating points and mixed
Precision training uh multi-gpu training
DDP
fsdp uh Laura
uh kind of boils down to a very simple
flowchart that you can just like use for
your project so if you were sleeping
through the entire lecture maybe now
it's the time to wake up and just like
look at this uh this flowchart
um so always use mixed Precision
training okay if you have the newer
Amper architectures use B float 16 try
with the bat size one okay if bat size
one fits try a larger bat size and then
always just use zero stage two
okay bad size one doesn't fit uh try
zero stage three uh maybe try gradient
checkpointing activation checkpointing
uh sorry there's a question this is
assuming we have more than one GPU
because doesn't help
us oh yeah so all of this applies only
if you have more than one GPU yeah if
you have a single
GPU yeah you have to do other things
maybe have to like heavily uh quantize
the model and even then I don't think
you can uh fine tune some of the bigger
bigger models yeah um so assuming you
have multiple gpus uh you can try zero
stage three if you have uh out of memory
errors with a bat size of one if that
doesn't work you can try Laura okay and
the main hyperparameters in Laura are
the alpha the rank and what uh weight
matrices to apply Lura to apply that to
the query Matrix apply that to the value
Matrix set rank to eight okay that's a
good starting point set Alpha to one
okay just do that and you should be good
to go okay so you can find tun your
models and things should be reasonably
good okay so uh I'm going to end now
unless there's
questions um oh there's one question in
the
back
diamides I was wondering if you just
like go back to it and walk through it a
little bit on step uh sorry on slide 48
yeah this diagram from the last right uh
okay um so let's go through this diagram
so basically uh what this diagram shows
is how the communication overhead is
really not that bad if you have a fairly
big model such that the the time it
takes to do a forward pass you can
already sort of prefetch uh all of the
parameters for the next layer okay so
that's pretty much the idea so that's
kind of like a standard idea that I
guess everyone should already be using
like you want to make sure and pyos does
this by default by the way like you want
to make sure that you know um you sort
of fully saturate your GPU uh and then
sort of make sure that you uh kind of
overlay that with any additional compute
you're doing and that's pretty much
what's going on here but let's sort of
go through this kind of Step by Step
okay and so the starting point here is
uh fsdp units so 0o one and two are
different fsdp units okay so um what you
start by doing is um you want to run a
forward pass on the first layer you
don't have the first layer okay so let's
say you are gpuk you don't have the
first layer so you have to do an all
gather to get all of the parameters for
the first layer so that's
ag0 okay at the end of ag0 every GPU has
the full set of parameters for uh the
layers corresponding to fsdp unit Zer
let's just say that's layer that's layer
one okay or let's just say that's layer
zero okay so you have the full
parameters for layer zero you run a
forward pass so that's the stuff in
blue and while you're running a forward
pass through the first layer you're
going to be smart about uh communication
overheads and while you're running that
you're going to prefetch uh the
parameters for the next fsdp unit okay
so let's say Layer Two is a different
fsdp unit so that's a G1 okay and so you
can see that there is like a little bit
of overlap between um between F zero and
ag1 okay at the end of getting all of
the parameters for layer one uh you're
going to do a forward pass okay and so
on and then you're going to do AG uh
ag2 uh and at the same time uh now let's
say you just have way tooo many uh
parameters on your GPU okay so you're
going to do a little bit of uh like
memory free uh you're going to free up
some memory okay so that's the stuff in
uh in yellow okay and so that's how that
goes so you know you basically overlay
all gather operations with the forward
pass okay and that's how you run the
forward pass okay so the communication
overhead is really not that bad if you
have like a really big uh deep neural
network uh and uh assuming that you have
uh um kind of shoted everything properly
okay um and then you start the backward
pass so in the backward pass uh uh I
guess it's a little bit tricky uh cuz
you know you want to do these uh all
gather operations to get the full
gradient so let's say it's a 10 layer
neural network okay so you want to
compute the full gradient at layer 10
you need to do an all gather operation
to get all of the gradients or to get
all of the parameters at layer 10 and
then you have to do a reduced scatter
okay so you have four gpus everyone has
the full set of parameters at layer 10
they have different gradients and so
they have to kind of merge their
gradients and then sort of split them up
to the right GPU and so that's the
reduced scatter uh but that's not too
bad because you can still like overlay
uh reduce scatter operations with the
backward pass okay and so that's what
you see happening in the backward pass
there okay um and then like along with
these forward and backward path
uh at sort of um you know regular
intervals you have to make sure that you
kind of free up GPU memory so for
example once you have run a forward pass
through layer one now you're on to Layer
Two you don't need anything in layer one
so you just like free up uh the memory
in layer one okay that's pretty much the
idea of behind this diagram um so
there's a few details here um one of the
details is like in fsdp uh unit zero is
sort of treated differently so you'll
see that unit zero is never freed up uh
that's just sort of an implementation
detail in fsdp I'll just quickly say one
more thing about fsdp and take a
question okay so uh the presentation
here makes it seem like it's so simple
and that it can be applied to any any
neural network right but uh turns out
that that's not the full picture so you
need to do this kind of uh like you need
to kind of divide up your neural network
into fsdp units okay and depending on
how you uh depending on what policy you
use for dividing up your parameters into
fsdp units there's different
communication overheads okay so for
example it makes sense to kind of uh
have like multiple like consecutive
layers in the same fsdp unit and so on
and so this is like very architecture
specific so when you start to use this
in pytorch you'll see that the
fsdp uh wrapper requires a sort of a
sharding policy uh and that is like very
architecture specific so because
everyone uses Transformers now they're
like very sort of you know handcrafted
fine-tuned policies for Transformer like
for for creating fsdp units and and
shotting strategies for Transformers but
let's say you want to you know for your
final project you came up with a new
architecture sub quadratic attention
whatever maybe it's not going to be as
efficient just because you don't have
the right shot policy okay so that's
like one detail about fsdp uh that that
maybe you want to keep in mind okay uh
you have a question just a clarification
when you mentioned uh you can throw away
the weights that you don't need after
each layer forward FS but then when you
compute backward FS you stream them back
in each time uh or do you sort of cash
some or cash recent or is there any
cashing going on or do you throw them
all way and streaming all back uh so
there might be some caching but uh uh in
in the system but uh the idea is that
you just sort of throw them away or at
least to the user it it seems like
you've thrown it all away in terms of
like uh GPU Ram utilization and then we
stream them each layer
again and so that's why it's important
to like Shard it properly right so for
example if like every consecutive layer
is you know is like shoted such that
it's on multiple gpus then you kind of
always are communicating right as
opposed to you know you kind of did like
uh all gather and then all of the sort
of next three layers are loaded in okay
so that's why like you know how you
Shard and this like Shing policy becomes
important
okay okay so if there's no more
questions uh let's uh let's end early uh
thank you so much
[Applause]