okay thank you um okay so I will first
start with some introduction and then
we'll get the actual content um of this
class
started okay so first uh so my name is
dong I'm a professor in computer science
here at y Berkley and also a co-director
of a campus wise Center called the
center on responsible decentralized
intelligence uh so I'm the instructor
for this class and also we have uh guest
co-instructor
s from Google who is also alarm she my
former student here teaching his class
together and also we have our great Alex
and cun and also we have our great reers
Tara uh and
as um okay uh so this is the teaching
staff uh who will be working together
with you uh this semester
okay great so everyone's here uh
everyone has been seeing the
exciting uh growth of large language
models uh the speed of advancement is
just Adon
astonishing uh however these large
language models they operate in a fairly
simple manner they take tax input and
produce tax output so what we will cover
in this semester in this class is the
next Frontier large language model
agents so instead of just taking tax uh
as input and produce tax as output here
we use a large Lang model as the key
brain for reasoning and planning for the
agents and enable the agents to interact
with external environments observe uh uh
the environments and take actions in the
environments and the Agents will uh be
using um external tools and also
external database and knowledge base uh
and so on uh for retrieval uh to help uh
the agents to perform these
tasks and the reach capabilities of um
these large ener bottles makes these LM
agents very flexible uh and they can
easily operate in diverse environments
without uh much uh particular training
and these uh our agents they can uh
interact with different types of
environments uh including for example
suring the web uh through different apis
online and they can also be embodied
even in a robot and operating in a
physical
world and they can inter sense the
environments through different types uh
of inputs uh even in the multi model
setting even including very sensory uh
inputs and taking actions in these
diverse uh environments and through this
interaction with the complex and diverse
environments uh they can uh update their
memory they can learn to do to use they
can interact with humans and uh they
obtain grounding through this uh uh
interactions as
well and these agents not only just
interact with the environments they can
interact with other agents through
multi-agent uh interactions and
collaboration including humans as well
and this multi-agent uh collaboration
can help agents together to solve even
more complex
tasks so why is our agent the next front
here why do we need to empower ours with
the agent framework for a number of
reasons solving real real world Tas is
never just uh in one goal with tax
inputs produce tax outputs often times
it involves a trial error process and
leveraging external tools and the
retrieval from external knowledge can
help expand lm's
capabilities and more
importantly uh this Dynamic uh agents uh
agentic flow uh this agent workflow can
facilitate solving complex tasks through
enabling task decomposition allocation
of self tasks to specialized modules
division of labor for project
collaboration and throughout the course
we also see that multi-agent generation
can help inspire better
responses even though um agents has has
been a fairly recent development we have
already seen um agents uh helping
transform different uh education domains
uh through wide ranging including
education law Finance Health Care cyber
security you name
it and the development is really
exciting and is fast improving there are
many different leaderboards for
different agent uh uh benchmarks that
you can see online and you can see the
really fast improvements on all these
different agent
Frameworks so overall to better enable
um engine deployment there are a number
of key challenges that we still need to
address so first we need to improve the
reasoning and planning capabilities of
Agents agents tend to make mistakes when
performing complex tax and to end and
it's important to improve the reasoning
and pl uh and planning capabilities
and also when to improve embodiment and
the learning uh from feed uh environment
feedback for these uh LM agents LM
agents are still not efficient of at
recovering from mistakes for long
Horizon tasks we need to further develop
uh methods and capabilities for
continuous learning and
self-improvements for this L agents and
also improve multimod understanding
gring and world the capabilities of
these
agents and also as I mentioned multi
agent can really help uh agents to uh
provides a better solutions for tasks
and developing threeory of Mind helps uh
multi agents to better develop as
well and safety and privacy these issues
are also very important for um agents
LMS are susceptible to ADV attacks can
emit harmful messages or Le private data
and so on solving these challenges are
also really important for deploying
agent safely in the real
world uh and also enabling human AG
interactions and uh ethics uh how to
effectively control our agent behaviors
and design interaction mode between
humans and our agents to best in Nal our
emissions to serve human needs is also
really important
so to help students learn and uh better
develop uh methods to address these
challenges uh the course uh is has been
designed to cover a broad spectrum of
topics uh actually throughout the
different uh layers uh of the agent
framework uh and also the
domains so first in the class we'll
cover uh key model uh capabilities
including reasoning planning multimodel
understanding we are also cover um
popular real world agent Frameworks to
enable students to learn how to better
design uh agent applications and use
various agentic flows
easily and this will help uh students to
also learn and to use uh our asan
Frameworks for workflow design to use uh
retrieval arguments the generation rack
and multi-agent
systems and we'll also cover a number of
exciting application domains using these
our agents including software code
development workflow automation
multimodel applications and Enterprise
applications um and finally we'll also
cover important topics on our agents
safety and ethics
to cover this wide ranging topics we
have assembled an amazing team of guest
speakers uh and researchers to cover
these topics so the class will be L by
me and shin and we have this amazing a
crew of uh guest speakers to help uh
cover these important topics in
class before the talk um I want to ask
one question for
everyone so what do you expect
for let me take seconds about
it so I can imagine many different
answers like solve the hardest math
problems that humans Cann solve for
example you can car cannot solve right
or discover new scientific
the or even South
AI um my background is machine learning
I don't know in the current days still
many people study ma C or not because
it's like transform is always need
right as a m person I have a little
impation about AI AI should be a perform
from just few
examples like what humans usually
do in the past DEC
case the mamic community spend great
efforts to develop data efficient
methods like Sam supp learning Active
Learning
Ma and
you know if you look at newspaper in the
past decade the people always excited
about one point two point games in the
as over
Pap so in practice actually I never saw
data efficient approaches I would like
to
say Miss and
failed you know don't feel bad about
that I de back I started almost
I actually that Mo me to s a different
problem what's missing ma
learning so I sort of T them for years
and
finally I found out the answer reason
me in the C days in particular for
people in the course today the so
obvious right this lecture about
reasoning humans can learn from just few
examples because humans can
reason not because of data
statistics s Street
for let's start from a to problem in my
research I us prefer a very simple
problem but it Con all the detail all
the challenge
places so this problem is called last
letter if you are familiar with neur
symbolic literature you'll find similar
problems so for this problem given a
people
name as input the output will be the
conation of the first of the last letter
of the first name and last name for
example like you
mask and the last letter of is n the
last letter of M is K so output is n
ke it's so
simple and if you have this
problem few years ago you probably will
try to solve it by Machine learning
model for example you could use
transformal model is why is decoder is
encod why is encoder is
decoder and then you will find that okay
you probably
need penc label examples to train the
model and finally you get accuracy like
85% or 9%
something now it's interesting about in
uh methods you know for such a simple
task I mean simple for humans okay and
if the method requires a vast amount of
label data to learn and would you like
to call it as AI or not AI means
artificial
intelligence right as I suppose a
intelligent model should be able to
learn this part just using one or two
grp examples
now let's see how this problem can be
solved by using uh lar Lo
models um I suppose most
people know lar models but Professor
told me
to uh explain what LM are okay LM is a
Transformer model train to predict next
world for example given the Tex AI is
the
future where mask future just AI as the
as the input well that model predict
what will be the next
word if the next prediction is not the
world future we need to adjust
parameters to make produce in
correct you one that's called back
probation
of course here you can change your model
with many sentences for example you can
use all text from the
internet if you don't want to go to
details you can simply think of training
LS as training pars to mimic human
language actually um I cre this sentence
and one guy me he said he he's very fous
about CH par has look for
job um why we CH this model
okay and then we can just minic the
process of the training the training is
about PR NE toen we can use whatever as
input and to see what will be the output
the just PR that token and then you can
inut the the generated token as you can
use the input token and the next token
as how to get answer
from and for this problem we can simply
contaminate all the examples we have had
as the input and also concate with Test
example Barack Obama here
we can try this has use any LM and see
what happened and probably see you get a
wrong answer
here is c k of course it's not correct
right because K is a last letter of
bread and and a is the last of Obama the
output should be a
k so it's wrong right the problem this
called f short PR it's just mimic of
machine learning process
instead of training model we just use
the examples at input that's the only
difference in the C days we know how to
fix this uh this prompting
idea we just need to add reing process
before
answer like we just add the exclusive
press here the last L is n the last of M
is k n k n k like that it's called reing
process and similarly for
bases and now we the this as the new
input and you will
see okay we get a perfect response from
the large models
so even like a humans one demonstration
is enough to get accuracy
100% that's exactly what I looked
for we cannot imagine any machine
learning
method can achieve this perfect
generation here this no
way but by the way don't overrate what I
said about machon maon is just so useful
and important for doing research in the
C days I saw many naive mistakes from
social media news even from the the
papers
conferences all the native mistakes
mostly from people who have no AC on
machine
learning they just random different
ideas
it's interestingly you know this kind of
idea of adding intermediate
steps has been uh propos many years um
in the
literature so this is the amazing
paper we know um by researchers mind
published Ino
2017 so in their paper
they uh use natural Lang re nail to
solve Mass
problems in their paper the even Road
derive The Final Answer through a series
of small
steps and then they trained a a s six
model from
scratch if you know Channel work you'll
be so surprising about the paper right
the authors are just like Time
Travelers they know how to make a
different
approach in
2021 a team in the
OPI published an amazing data set called
GSM K they are followed the idea in t
paper in
2017 in this set every
problem uh followed by intimidate steps
as solution and also final
answer
and this team created this amazing data
set and they use that to F tune gp3
model they are greatly scale up the work
by good demand in 2017
even in the same year 2021 a group of
researchers in Google brain now part of
Google mind part the work like show work
s path for intermediate competition with
logal models they
discovered the similar ideas
independently but in the domain of
program
synthesis that's why they used um Abra
symbols here instead of using natural
language in the country probably many
people know our work CH of s property
and the chain of s actually literally CH
of s is not a term way invented it's
just common English phrase it means M St
reasoning so in this work we extensively
evaluated from individ steps and show
amazing results on almost every NLP Tass
so that's all the pap here together in
2017 who demand publishing paper
training with inmedia
steps in
2021 and the few poty
papers LS with intermediate
steps in 20 21
and promting with intermediate
steps I will see okay which part is more
important you can see
here actually it doesn't
matter if you are CH or F or
model what really matter appear
here intermediate steps
that's the
key so let me summarize here regardless
of training funing or
promting when provided with examples
that include intermediate
steps L will generate responses that
also include intermediate steps
Okay g the mid St when ask question is
it helpful to introduce reason
strategies in those examples for humans
they when they solve a problem they
could have a strategy for
solving so this um so here's I work from
our team is this most PR team in this
work we enable easy to hard Generation
by the
composition probably many people saw
this famous
book how to solve it by Pia a classic
book for Mass
education so there's a chapter about de
composition so if you just if you go
details you may loss yourself in
details
yeah now let's see what is difference by
um by DEC computation so given this uh
Mass problem
here so by the way so um in this talk
the mass is keep at a elementary level
so every time I a par um before actually
my daughter also came my par
and make she could understand she's at
the fifth grade
now and U you say es has three apples
Anna has two more apples than Isa how
many apples do they have together okay
we see the difference is that okay we
first show light models how to break
down this problem to Sol problems and
then solve one by
one and that's why could least most from
least to most complex
problems is
very simple idea but surprisingly awful
so I suest is how to De compose complex
task into simple tasks so this is a um
scan task for composition or
generalization you can look at examples
here give a naturally natural language
uh command and we need to translate to a
sequence of
accents and that could be executed by
robots something like
that so if you use list most promp we
get accuracy
99.7 so we just use1 % demonstration
examples so I wonder why I chose this
task actually um I knew this T from sh
she's here today and she invented a
beautiful approach to solve this task
many years
ago when I looked at this task I was
really surprised because it look so
straightforward for
humans why could be so difficult for
Maes finally we can make it by
LS and this is another task with save
here test to code again a compositional
generation part I don't know if
anyone knows the concept compositional
generation roughly speaking the test
examples are more difficult than
then training examples or or prompting
examples so for example uh for the for
the for the T code
problems the T problems we need uh
longer
snipp here where approach is a little
bit Chang littleit called Dynamic L most
PR and we just use one person data and
achieve the proper great results way
better than uh the solar results in the
literature and the solar result in
actually are by
specialized architecture design and the
training and they use of course all the
train data
set yeah so far any question here
otherwise I'll go to the next section
yeah okay I suppose this part is quite a
familiar for
everyone um I have two Cas my daughter
is
uh um 10 years old and my my son is 7
years old um actually when the CH pring
paper came out I uh heard a very
interesting conversation between my
daughter and my my son and my daughter
asked uh her little brother
so was 11 17 *
three um the little brother said I don't
know and then she asked was 10 times St
30 was 7 time 3 21 so what's the 17 3 oh
yeah I know
51 and the funny say is my daughter
shouted to me Daddy CH pring also works
my little brother bra
okay now uh okay why may see okay why
intermediate steps are
helpful so why me say okay that's so
natural for
humans but if we are doing research we
have to S it deeper you know that's just
something similar that LS are just
models while understand what
happened and this year we have work
published at 2024 and I collaborated
with Bren s from
Stanford and in that work we are give
rigorous mathematical
analysis okay so um here are the key
results Transformer generating
intermediate steps can solve any in
currently seral problem as long as it
deps
exceeds a constant sh colde after
emphasiz get constant that means
independent for your
input however if a
Transformer generating direct
answers either requires a huge deps to
solve or canot solve at all
yeah please check the statements again
then I'm moving to the next
slide probably can see tons of practical
implications of this
Theory yeah if you are couldn't Sol a
problem you may think about generating
more in
STS and also probably you could have
um call some external tools that search
to help intermed
steps right so I think in in this LM
agent um course many people talk about
how to use exal
force and you could think about how to
diing L fures and limitations yeah so I
have one of my big fun
is to find
problems my daughter can solve in
settings
by fail
yeah okay so far we have talked about
how to use
examples to trickle
LS uh to generate step by step
re so one one is possible to triggle
with you without
using it's an amazing work actually when
this paper came out I thought it was a
joke it turn out not and then I was
inspired a lot by this work it's called
let thing step by
step so given this question okay we
don't need any examples we just need to
see Lessing step by
step and the motel can generate buiness
steps yeah it's really cool but usually
you know the Z short approach that mean
z short there's Nostra examples um it's
worse than F
sh so we wonder okay if we have approach
is still to short but can do much better
work so this these two our another work
is called L as analogical
reasoners so again this beautiful book
how to solve it and
bolia you um so in book say okay how to
do analog reasoning in s Mass problems
so we see in new problem you first ask
your a question do you know a related
problem or methods or strategies
here so after how you're going toy find
this and provide another
paper
um so this I really like the code from B
yeah if you started fun analysis you
will know
space
and I was really Amazed by that last
sentence the ultimate mathematic is one
who can see analogies between
analogies of course I I show the here to
let you know how far from
a um so given this simple problem okay
of course can see okay lesson step by
step but now we can see different way
okay we call a related problem and then
solve the one Sol this one okay you can
see that actually indeed we c um
relevant examples and the knowledge is
here but those problem are exactly the
same problem but they are use for that's
amazing
you and uh we found that actually which
of course we try to bench marks and see
it works really well so you can see that
um the last R is from analogical
Reasoner by prompt of course you can
optimize the prompts by yourself get
better results the most important thing
here see that um it's much better than
just see that's thing step by step
that's step step here means Z short z t
yeah and even this approach uh out
performs manual so
here as the main Reas is that you know
we use this approach the model
automatically generate related questions
each different
problem this uh results on big bench
yeah was great
performance and uh
the result on
fores competive
programming yeah if you are interested
in competive programming you could try
this approach so what we didn't do here
is about
scaling you can U you can search the web
from all the related problems
knowledges uh for for the problem you
will
solve so the key idea here you know
thatly generate relevant examples and
the knowledge for each given
problem instead of using a big set
examples as a manual genal
prompting okay now we can see that okay
we can use few short examples to show
the model how to do step by step
reason what can do zero
short without using any examples just
see that's step by
step now I could ask another question is
it possible to trigger step by step
reing even without using any problem
that's step by
step you could say okay all the models
in the count are just like that right
you're right but they
did or something that means they already
used many examples in the data mixture
for training or
training so yeah we found the answer is
yes this in our or World CH of s
reasoning without
problem without problem that without
saying anything just give problem to the
model even
for for L not
so um let's look example
here I have three app my dad has two
more app than me and how many appers do
we have
together for this example is
see the approach actually is very
simple um at decoding at the first step
we look at all the pass tokens here at
Le to the file tokens here okay so we
started the first file tokens and then
continue gr decoding okay for the first
one is say file app okay the first is a
file and the next was
F and if use um to to can is I then the
four generation will be I have three app
my dad has two more appers than me and
Sil has five app yeah it's correct yeah
and I see that so that's that's very
interesting right so we didn't see
anything about reason here but the model
can do some you started from different
tokens here is another example you say
okay with Nu close cage Bor in even or
all
year um the first one say Okay cage was
B in all year Nu was the first token and
second one that even and then period
third one is all then period
okay now probably say okay if the you
know the
model could have had CH SW in their
responds the promise how to F it
I say okay you can take a longer
sentences longer senten means the model
could do some readon
steps actually a surprising s that to
look the
probability of the of the token
of if you look at the probability on the
first roow here a nichos cage was born
in order in year and the is quite
low and however if you see if there Rec
past like the last one uh K was born in
1964 and an even year this a reason
process here and then probability
finally jump
to
98 that's amazing right it seems that
the model is so well calibrated at I was
really surprised at seeing those
probabilities see that like two the
street if say even or old the
probabilities are really
low so key
observ and
pre have had responses with step by step
reasoning and generations started with
the top ke to
Cas we don't need use any PRS here not
needed and have confidence in decoding
the final answer when a step by step
reasoning pass is
present so here is a compressing between
gr decoding and the chn decoding we see
that the de coding performance much
better yeah so far any question
here now let's uh move to the next topic
right generating intermediate steps are
helpful even really helpful you know
but any can on Genera sets instead of
direct
answers any concerns
[Music]
yeah so probably all say depends on your
problem your need
yeah so actually in the C days you know
we need to always keep in
mind that LMS are PR mods of generating
next
tokens they are not
humans no matter if I use a key examples
or not keep this in
mind so it's a PR model so that's see
what LM does in deod
so it's actually
ARX
probability of reasoning pass and The
Final Answer here the
problem however what we want is
ARX probability Final Answer given
problem right that's what we learned in
machine
learning this doesn't mean WR pass is
not
important but I just say final answer we
have to make sure final answer is
correct and then look at the Reas
pass they are not aligned right the two
different
objective
okay now let's look one step further
okay
the probability of find answer given the
problem for the
computer which should sum over all
possible reason
parts that's uh that's how is computed
from our
course will learn right so given Mass
problem you could found different
solutions which lead to the same answer
yeah we need that we need to do the
summation
here and then okay how to compute
side if you started machine learning you
know answer here right simply so simple
okay now uh this du to our work self
consy probably many people have no self
consy but my talk here is I really want
to let you see the underly
motivation how we approach this problem
from the first principle you
learning so let's look the question here
okay give this math problem and you
could sample the answer multiple times
yeah again and then finally you see okay
the most frequent answer is
18 okay what will give one here is not
most frequent reason
pass we choose most frequent
answer that's huge
difference Rec pass here is lat
varable this idea is so
simple by by using
self consistency we simply Crush solar
results in the literature that
time and see that in doing
research we don't
need we we can you know it's really just
about your idea you don't have to have
to know a lot of
sense and of course you know give our
explanation on self consistency is about
probability it's about samp so imagine
that more consistent results more likely
to be crack when you look at the curves
here if the consistency is more than
80% then the I the uh accuracy is nearly
100%
here okay
so when the outputs a direct answer
without intermediate
steps we use the sample several times
and then choose the most common
answer anyone like answer
here yeah
okay great yeah one token okay that's
already the the the token with maximum
probability yeah
Al and for the second
question
and change S consen by La LM generate
multiple
responses instead of sampling multiple
ttimes and then choosing the most common
answer does this make
sense yeah
no great yeah that is
no and for both answers we just need to
follow this principle I Max probability
to find answer given problem that's all
you need to understand self consistency
is a very very simple principle was the
first one of the first principles in
machine if you know more probably know
okay this this maximum marginal
inference okay so one okay how about
free form
answers um
is uh Universal s
see here
so this idea is a little bit different
uh but relation I put here and given
this problem where do people drink less
coffee than they do in Mexico now if you
look the
answers and each answer is different
from others but the most common response
is to here Japan China and India
um any question otherwise we could move
to the next section
okay
yeah self consy oh sample your answer
multiple times and then chose the most
um frequent answer
as yeah
and next I'm going talk about
limitations the first one I talk about
LS can be easily distracted by
context from psychology studies you know
um re
information May significantly decrease
some children and even adults problem
solving
accuracy so I want to check if this
observation code
for so this is a simple problem
here
um the highlighted
text is manually added so Mario's M
which is
$10 is Rel for the original problem
but I see after that the the model made
a wrong uh solution
here so
um actually interes that
okay if we add a PR like ignore EV
context and the model immedately notice
that and make a correct
one but it's still hard to take back if
we make the problem make contents op big
so even we can simply just add
development synes like the sky is blue
and the the grass is green or something
you know those mountains you can make
this uh input up along you will see a
significant performance draw across or
L the next limitation I'm going to talk
about LMS cannot self correct Reon
yet let's start from a math problem
again and actually this problem is a
little bit tricky you look
at and uh you see that the model um give
a wrong
answer and then we uh from to the model
with review your previous answer and
found
problems with your answer okay and
interestingly after reviewing the model
re recognize the
mistake and uh proactive
design this looks something right you
see and then we see another problem
based on the problem you find improve
your
answer and The Final Answer here is
correct if the or is correct we do the
same
prompt the mod could have made mistake
that's the
problem
so overall when allowing a to review
their generated response can help
correct inacurate
answers it may also risk changing
correct answers into incorrect
ones we run extensive studies on um on
some benchmarks like GSM commiss QA and
QA and we didn't notice any
improvements from self- correction
methods they just makes sense
worse um prob you supp some improvement
from the literature you know they they
said at Improvement
reasoning and actually they use
Oracle answers you can see the Oracle
here Oracle means you only prompt LMS to
correct the answer when the answer is
wrong the problem is the model doesn't
know if the answer is correct or wrong
your
wrong and also this Rel to multi agent
debate the Y could could use multiple a
debate each other and to uh to achieve
agreement or
consensus and also with try this
approach know we uh we find out actually
the trick is how many response are
generated for example if we have
three and if let everyone generate a
response that will be three if let
debate that that re on that will be n
response together so how part just to S
consistency with n response and see what
happened we find that those approaches
cannot outperform self consistency self
is might simple simple times and take
the most frequent answer as final
prediction so the lesson we learn here
is oral feedback is needed for a to self
correct if so that we our work is self
depar self depar naturally leverage unit
test as Oracle you coding problems you
can natur have unit test
track actually we started this work
quite early and we didn't make make a
and then finally we move to the
and the last lastation I want talk about
the premise order matters in
reging so um you know in the C B where
every time we show T reports from
archive or to somewhere and the people
will show great results for example
recently model could be FL and result
onk and I I have to tr those
numbers in the C the model Trend was all
data from internet there already some
problems so one of
um working on my team is to generate
different Evol tasks so to to test the
models so that here here we just did a
simple check we are given this original
gsmk problem
we U
reorder the
sentence a little bit and see if the
model can solve it so here know in this
in the OR problem he loses 10 beers
while getting
home and we could you know just
uh move this sentence to to the to the
end and see what
happened we just did some change for
some JK
problems and we notice that there are
about 10 points drop on solving R across
all from
TM so here the response here can look
compare response for the problem for or
problem and theorder the
problem so
um you see that the model actually just
the model just know how to solve the
problem sequentially they couldn't go
back and
forth and one could say okay that may
related to some semantic understanding
about reason okay then we design another
another task logical
inference is is more pure than the mass
problems
yes say B if if then if then if then
right even even we don't use real real
words we just use a random uh random um
tokens
here and given the rules and the
facts and then model inference logical
inference in the
query and the rules for the original
problem the rules are order according to
the use in the inference
process but I I uh point out not all
rules are necessary for the
query and another way you know we could
just
randomly order those
rules okay I only only random order
rules relevant for query if not relevant
for query
they just keep
the
positions and surprising was then we saw
City Plus points per draw across all
[Music]
Frontier
um from my personal experience I think
it's really important
to design
experiments when doing a own research so
this just like a
depart
okay now uh let me summarize the talk
here so um the first thing I talk about
is generating intermediate steps
improves
performance lot and you can do training
F PR with intermediate
steps but you can do also do Z SH
analogical reson or some kind of special
decoding like 7 deing I presented
today and also self consistency great
improves step by step reasoning no
matter
your from from F model or from
F and I also a lot of limitations you
know like you have context self
correction and the prise order all those
are matters for Reon
performance so when
I next what problem right
[Music]
and I the most important here is you
know I see we work on something we put
work on ai ai that's not problem the
problem is Define a right problem work
on and solve it from first principles
not
just from principles why is super
important
here and actually I'm organizing a
conference called conference modeling
with a of amazing people and this the
first ever companies dedicated to
langage modeling and welcome to
yeah that's it SS