Last time on on Tuesday this week, we
had a lecture on GPUs and how to train
and how to use them and how to use
multiple GPUs for training larger scale
scaling your trainings and so on. an
exciting um a new topic that we've added
to this uh class this this year which is
I think timely and very important with
the increase of model sizes and and
applications
uh that you see the AI models have these
days.
And [sighs] before that we talked about
we covered all of the key tasks in
computer vision from classification,
semantic segmentation, object detection,
instance segmentation and so on. And uh
we're going to revisit some of these
topics, some of the results of the
models we talked about today. But so
that's that's those tasks are uh still
quite important.
And then we talked about visualizing and
understanding the
models and and seeing what the models
are learning. One of the things that
we've discussed was
for example using just
in the in the early sessions we talked
about nearest neighbor and and in the
pixel space and how we can actually do
find the class of um we can find the
class of images based on only pixel
space distances and we discussed how
it's actually not efficient and one of
the things that we talked about was
if we use the embedding layers or the
feature space feature layers, what one
of those fully connected layers in
the the feature maps there from a
convolutional neural network or any
other network architecture that we use
there that could actually be a good
representation of images. And we talked
about the L2 distance if if we use that
as the metric for nearest neighbor in
the feature space feature of these
models. Right? So these uh this means
that these features are quite meaningful
for the specific task that we had at
hand. And this means that specifically
okay if we run a neural network a CNN a
resnet or even uh the transformer models
and look at the
representations the learned
representations in different context you
may uh see these as uh referred to with
with different names large
representations features embeddings uh
latent space and so on but These
learned representations or features are
very good representatives of the images.
And if we can if we have a way to to
extract those, we can always get the
class labels out of those features as
well by a simple linear model as you can
see at the end here. But the major
challenge that exists is
training or building these networks at
large scale is always um challenging and
can you tell me why there's a challenge
here?
So the thing is that at large scale we
need a lot of labeled data because this
network is trained starting from an
image and at the end we have class
labels. If we train this network, yes,
these features are going to be very
useful for getting those uh class labels
out, right? But at scale, we need a lot
of manual labeling efforts uh to to sit
down and label the images one by one. If
the task is segmentation, you have to
label the pixels one by one in every
image. And that is going to be very
challenging.
So the question is is there a way we can
train neural networks without the need
for huge manually labeled data sets. So
these manual labels are um the the
challenge and we want to see if we can
bypass them in a way to train any neuron
network that gets us very good features.
And with that the topic of
self-supervised learning uh comes in
light and that's what we are going to
cover today. So
having a a large data set of say images
without any labels
our hypothesis is that we can train a
neural network using an objective
function a pretext task that gets us
good features
from images. And then when it comes to
learning on a specific data set with a
smaller uh set of data points which have
labels, we we can basically train uh we
can transfer this trained encoder and
use that to extract features for a
downstream task or downstream objective.
So here we want to define a pretext
task, a task that is general enough to
be able to uh learn some good features
from the images and then use that
encoder. Let's call it encoder
to
uh to to solve another problem what we
call downstream task downstream
objective which is the application that
you care about. Like for example, we
have a lot of natural images
downloaded from in the internet. We can
we can train something out of it and
then we have a small data set of for
example one of these industrial
applications or medical applications
that we have few labeled images on and
we can now use that transfer of
knowledge to extract features and then
classify or or perform the task that we
are interested in.
So we want to delve into this topic and
go a little bit deeper in uh
understanding the different components.
In a nutshell, what self revised
learning is, as I said, defining this
preex task on the data set with no
labels. encoder often
uh gets us some learned representations
and then another module of the the same
neural network generates or or does um
transfer the learned representations
into the output space which could be
labels or outputs that automatically are
generated from the data. They are not
manual annotations. So if we can do this
then um we have an an objective function
a loss function and a neural network uh
to be trained with that loss function.
I'm as as you can see here we call the
second part sometimes decoder a
classifier a regressor depending on how
we define our pre-text task. I will give
you some examples but there are this
could be any form of framework but when
when it's encoder and then a decoder
this is more of an autoenccoding
framework that I'll I'll talk briefly
about okay
so after we we do this uh training with
the pretext task now we can um use the
encoder and the learn representations
for a downstream task which we just need
to add uh one layer or even a fully
connected neural network, a linear
function or a fully connected neural
network that you that predicts the
labels and these labels are coming now
from the data set. So that's that's the
major that's the main concept of
self-supervised
learning that the pretext version of it
portion of it doesn't require any
labeled data to do the training. But how
to define the pretext task itself is not
that uh straightforward.
There are many different ways of
defining those. For example,
just keep in mind that we want to define
um
the pretext task in a way that it's
first general enough that can get us
good features and doesn't require manual
labeling. So the labels should come from
the data itself, right? So one one
example would be image completion where
we mask half of the image or parts of
the image and we define a task to given
the parts that are unmasked predict the
parts that are masked. Or for example,
we rotate the image with a specific u
angle and the task is to take the image
as input and predict what's the rotation
angle that it's gone through. And the
other one could be a jigsaw puzzle where
we have patches of the image that are
not ordered but the the the the task is
to output the correct order of these
patches. and colorization is one of the
popular ones that these are the four
that we'll be covering uh very quickly
today. But uh given the um blackout and
white version of the image predict the
colors for each of the uh pixels. So
solving the pretext task allows the
model to learn good features. That's
what we wanted. And we can automatically
generate labels for the pretext task. So
the two points that I mentioned we we
need for a task that could be qualified
as a good pretext task for
self-supervised learning. Some uh quick
considerations to to always keep in mind
how to evaluate a self-supervised
learning framework. There are many
different pieces and and areas that you
can actually look into the pretext task
itself because we are generating the
labels and so on. It gives us the power
to do some evaluation of how good the
model is able to solve that pretext
task. So that's one of the
uh factors. Then representation quality
itself is sometimes very important
looking at um for example
only representations without any
fine-tuning or anything that I'll I'll
be talking about or even clustering the
the representations to see do we see a
pattern in the representations and
sometimes there are some good
dimensionality reduction algorithms uh
I'm I'm referring to TSN testing here
which we didn't very much talk about but
this is a dimensionality reduction
framework that you can reduce the
dimensionality of the lens
representations and then visualize it in
2D or 3D and see if there is a pattern
that you can find in your
representations. So robustness,
generalization and computational
efficiency I these are all quite
important but the most important thing
the most important um aspect that we are
after is
the performance on the downstream task
because we are doing the entire
self-supervised learning and and define
the tasks pre text tasks and so on to be
able to improve results for a task of
interest or something that we are we
care about. Let's see some quick
examples of how this could be done. Um
this is an example of let's rotate the
images and then predict the degree of
rotation in as the output. So we can
train this in a self-supervised manner
without the need for labels of the
objects in the in the image. And we have
a bunch of convolution layers in this
example and then a fully connected uh
neural network at the end to do this
either regression or classification
task. And this means that this is giving
us some sort of uh a set of good
features uh good feature extractor which
we can at the end remove this these
task pretext task specific parts the FC
layers and puts
one layer or in some cases multiple
layers uh to to classify the features
into the object label. So this time we
use the object labels to do the
prediction and train these uh this
linear uh function itself. So we often
look for a shallow network because if
the features are good enough then we
don't need to um do a lot of training um
on um on on getting the class labels
out. So
this is self-supervised learning in in
general and um although we are talking
about um the computer vision
applications but this this paradigm of
self-supervised learning was actually
what enabled all of these large language
models uh GPT4 and all of these
frameworks are trained with mostly raw
data without any manual ual labeling and
um not just in language models in speech
and these days quite a lot in robot and
um robotics and reinforcement learning
because when we don't need any labeling
data, we can start capturing data
raw data without any manual labeling and
use those for training. And that's why
you see so many self-driving uh cars in
the Bay Area collecting data because
that's that's getting them the data and
they don't have to really annotate the
data but they can still train models
based on.
So with that um today's agenda we'll
we'll cover some of these pre-text tasks
from image transformations and then I
will talk a little bit about
a set of algorithms that are around
contrastive representation learning that
um
are slightly different from these image
transformation based pre-text tasks but
have shown promise. So let's start with
the with the first part and there we
will cover the tasks one by one.
So I talked quite uh a lot about
rotation predicting rotations. Let's see
if we can actually u rotate the images
with random or or arbitrary
degrees and predict the rotation uh
angle with with a model. And our
hypothesis here is that the model a
model could recognize the correct
rotation of an object only if it has the
common sense visual common sense of what
the object should look like u
unperturbed.
So these models mostly uh are are
designed around this concept of uh
visual common sense and um and then if
if the model is able to to capture that
it means that it is also able to
summarize the image the entire image
into a a useful
um set of features good features.
This paper published in 2018
um
implemented this with with just
exploring four different angles of 0,
19, 90, 180 and uh 270. rotating th
those into with with one of these
rotating images with one of these angles
and then using the convolutional neural
network to basically predict what which
which of these rotations the output is.
And because they only created four
different outputs, this is a
classification task because it only has
four different cases, right? It doesn't
have to predict the exact value of the
angle the degrees but it's um
it's actually um just predicting one of
these four
uh classes of 0 1 2 or three
why 0 1 2 [sighs] or three. So with that
um the authors were able to
learn good representations
and um with those representations they
they started training the neural network
at a downstream application basically
fine-tuning the neural network
based on um fine-tuning the encoders and
also the
um the and the classifier actually we in
this case they they froze
first and second layers and then they
fine-tuned uh the last convolution layer
and the linear layer. So it's not
entirely
um fine-tuning the entire network but
[clears throat] they were able to get
very good results. This is on C410 data
set, one of the data sets that we've
talked about earlier. You see that when
when the model is pre-trained, it starts
with a good accuracy to start with. So
it means that it it it already is in a
good shape and it's it's having a good
understanding of the the objects even in
the very uh first iterations. But if the
task is simple enough, CR10 is actually
not too hard to um to train a model for.
If the task is simple enough, the
supervised version, the fully supervised
version and the one that starts with
pre-training often converge to the same
number, same same accuracy. But again,
if the task is simple enough in a very
hard application, much harder
applications, often the supervised
learning frameworks, if we don't do any
pre-training, larger scale pre-training,
we don't get as good results. Okay.
Um [sighs]
so
um they've they've done also some uh
applica some some um experiments on this
POS Pascal VOCC 2017
data set which involves a number of
tasks including classification,
detection and uh segmentation.
And these all these three uh sets of
tasks they've used different setups of
just pre-train just training a few fully
connected layers or all of the layers
for for the classification detection and
segmentation tasks. If you look at the
imageet labels like if we have a huge
labeled data set and we pre-train on
that uh data set we already get a very
high accuracy but but again have this in
mind that this is imageet with all of
the labels involved for for the
pre-training but if we don't do any
supervised pre-training and the
pre-training is all based on
self-supervised it's it's showing that
this rot ation uh framework is doing a
much better job than many of the other
counterparts any of the other examples
that are um other other methods that's
we don't actually go into many of the
detail of many of those but the it's
showing efficacy for this rotation
pretext task and see how it's different
how much better it is if you start with
a random
um initialization of the weights. So the
random initialization versus um
pre-training with rotation um pretext
task the the difference is huge and the
the this rotation pretext task is not
equal but it's close to pre-training on
the entire imageet. So
one of the thing that
they've they've looked into in this
paper was looking at the features and
how um how how the learned features are
meaningful. I mentioned earlier that one
of the ways of evaluating the pretext
tasks generally self-supervised learning
frameworks is to look at the features
right and and you can always go from the
features from the fully connected
layers. We talked about grat cam and all
of those other attention based
frameworks how we can go from the
features back to the image space. So
this evaluation involves projecting
those into the image space and seeing
what the model is looking at. If you
look at the attention maps for the
supervised model often the supervised
model has more focused uh maps because
it's it's only trying to solve one
single task of classification. So if I
if it captures the eye and and the shape
around it doesn't care about the other
other parts very much. But in cases of
self-supervised learning often more
features more areas are covered because
it has to have a more holistic
understanding of the image because we
don't know what the downstream task is.
But it's that the the goal is to perform
equally well in many of those. So that's
one of the tasks. Um, if you do have any
questions, skip it. I'll I'll stop after
uh going over some of the tasks and if
your answer your question was not
answered, then I would be happy to to
answer that. Okay. Um
another one another popular um pretext
task was to to basically create this 3x3
grid and then use networks to predict
the location of each of the given
patches with respect to the sensor
patch. So for for this patch which is
around here the output should be three
because we only have um uh eight
this is 3x3 and the center patch is the
the reference. So this also turns out to
be an eightway classification task. It's
getting any of these patches and yeah,
it's trying to output what the location
of that given patch it is with respect
to the input uh with respect to the
sensor [clears throat]
patch. Sorry.
So
uh so this is this was another another
example but the um this other follow-up
paper paper publication which uh turned
this into a jigsaw puzzle framework was
instead of saying to to uh asking the
model to just predict which of these
eight patches it is it tried to predict
the exact permutation the right
permutation. So what they've done was
they used the same 3x3 um grid took all
of the patches shuffled them randomly
and then ask the neural network to say
which of the
correct permuta which one should be the
correct permutation.
So they they basically predict the the
correct permutations. Can you tell me
what is the number of permutations you
can you can have for um
this setup? Say again.
>> Nine factorial. Yes, exactly. So, it's
it's a huge number, right? 300,000
something, I think. Uh but what they've
done was they've they've created this
lookup table with only four 64 um
plausible possible uh rotation uh sorry
uh permutations and then only only they
consider 64 permutations and when when
they're shuffling shuffling that they do
the shuffling based on one of these 64
and then the output will also be just a
6064 uh sized vector. So again, this
turns out to be a just a simple
classification task with 64 output
classes and they've shown this is also a
great idea for
um solving to to define as a pretext
task and on the same data set with
similar type of
tasks that I talked about and and how
the supervision is is done. they've
shown their method was um outperforming
some of the
more
uh previous models, previous frameworks
and uh again remember that this is this
was published in 2016. So
next pretext task is just in painting
predicting what is missing. So
[clears throat] what they uh have done
here was a simple masking strategy. You
mask parts of the image and then you ask
the model to impose those parts that are
masked. So how it was done simple
masking um on the input image but
because we have the all of the images we
actually have the desired output. So an
encoder turns this into a feature space
and then that feature space is also
there are some uh fully connected layers
in the middle and then there is a
decoder that decodes the parts that is
missing and the loss function is
comparing the output
with what um the ground truth was.
And this is basically learning to
reconstruct the missing pixels.
Again, um we've talked about
autoenccoders a couple of times before.
And um and this is also some form of an
autoenccoder that it encodes the input
image um into a representation that you
want to decode the output. But this
autoenccoder is trained with a masking
strategy. masking uh objective. So
[sighs] just to show you some examples,
the impainting
evaluations
um are a little bit interesting and
tricky because when you want to impsing
this this image, right? And it's um we
can't say it's it's it's it's
there are there is just one um output to
to do um in this case here
reconstructionbased frameworks earlier
reconstruction based frameworks we're
actually creating a lot of uh fuzzy uh
and and very
um
a smooth outputs And
that's why
this this paper that I'm uh referring to
here was actually using
an an additional adversarial objective
function which I'm not going to go into
details because this is a topic of
discussion for the next lecture
generative models. But generally how um
these uh frameworks work, we have a
reconstruction loss and the
reconstruction loss is basically
calculating the difference between the
patch uh between the image X and the
image after it's passed through the
uh the encoder.
So um
and then uh these this is element wise
multiplication and we also have this
mask here because we want to only
calculate the loss function the
objective function only on the masked
area. So we do an element wise mask um
multiplication with the mask as well.
And this basically gives us the
reconstruction loss for that part of the
mask that um we had. So as I said the
it's also supplemented with an
adversarial objective adversarial
learning uh loss function which
ensures the images that are generated
are real looking right. So with with
that um they have been able to improve
the the parts that are
uh reconstructed to look a little bit uh
better but again details will be um
discussed in the next lecture.
So this reconstruction uh framework was
actually able to again provide and this
ours is the same provide additional
benefits when it's run on the same
classification detection and
segmentation task on uh same set of data
sets.
I will come back to this reconstruction
based frameworks and and masking in a
bit because it's one of the most uh used
models or pretext tasks that these days
are used for for pre-training. Uh so
I'll I'll I'll come back to this but
before that let me introduce this this
um other
pretext task of image coloring.
And this is another very simple
framework setup that we turn a colored
image because our data set is mostly
colored colored images, right? We turn
that colored image into its components
or channels that that separate the
lightness, the illumination from the
color itself. There are several color
spaces. If you've taken uh courses like
computer graphics or CS131 other uh
computer vision class, you know that
there are so many different color
spaces. Mostly in computer vision we use
RGB.
But if you want to separate lightness
illumination from color, there are some
other color spaces. For example, lab
color space L A B is one of those color
spaces that separates lightness from
color. So we have one channel for
lightness and two channels for defining
the the actual color. And if we add
these two all together, L A and B all
three channels together we can actually
get the colored image. So the pretext
task here is simple. Given the L
channel, predict the A and B channels.
Right? So again, we don't need to do any
manual annotation. It's already in the
data. [snorts]
And this was extended into uh other
frameworks. Why why should we only look
at like given L predict A and B? We can
also do the reverse, right? And that um
led us to split something that we call a
split brain autoenccoder where the input
image is split um is basically turned
into one the the L channel lightness
channel and the color channels uh these
two images. This is one channel. This is
two channels of color. And we train two
functions, two neural networks, sets of
layers to predict the other one. And
then at the end in order to calculate
the loss function uh and um back prop we
just merge these two to generate the
actual image and a loss uh an L2 loss
any distance function can help with
training this neural network in a more
generic uh framework um or or
formulation. The idea is
given one channel or a set of channels,
predict the others and do the same uh
for X2. So sets of channels X1, sets of
channels X2. So given one, we can
predict the other one. And these are the
neural networks for those. Merging them,
we'll get u the value
the image and then loss function would
be simple. So if we have such a
framework, we can run it on everything,
not just u color and illumination,
right? We can have um data from some of
these
RGBD sensors, those that have um RGB
channels and and depth channels like for
example connect and and other sensors
that they use in robotics. And given the
RGB channel, predict the depth and vice
versa. And this was a very successful
downstream task that was used for
different applications. And as you can
see this this uh this model and uh this
paper that I just um the split brain and
uh the papers that um the the model that
predicts colorizes the images is those
those features themselves. they do have
actually a very good level of accuracy
for
um predicting the class labels and you
can see there are many different other
frameworks that are used also
um in terms of uh comparisons again this
is not as good as supervised learning
because there is no label involved uh
here and and it's just based on the the
learned features with concatenated
features out of f_sub_1 and f_sub_2.
Okay, so uh the image coloring pre-text
tax was actually very interesting
because now we could um not only use it
for pre-training neural networks, but it
was also itself useful somehow because
now we could colorize images that we
don't have a colored version. So we
could colorize images that and then
videos that we don't have a colored
version of those.
And not only that, uh one of the other
interesting results that they they
they've shown in the paper was uh this
image of yuseimmed
and the halfdme that um they colorized.
The interesting thing that is
is seen in this image is the consistency
between the actual object the halfd dome
or trees or the bridge and its
reflection in the in the water. So the
model was was also able to understand
that this reflection should also somehow
preserve uh the color based on how it
was trained on vast amounts of data.
Again,
keep in mind that these models are all
pre-large language large vision models
and they have been trained on specific
tasks. So they're not trained for
solving everything.
So this could be actually extended into
video settings because now if we have a
video, we can have a reference frame
that has the color and do the coloring
for the follow-up frames. And how this
is done. This is very simple because uh
with with uh I mean this is also very
useful because with uh colorizing future
frames in the video what we are doing is
we basically try to uh track pixels and
objects in the video and the model
implicitly learns how these uh tracks
should be formed. So the hypothesis is
learning to color video frames should
allow model to learn to track regions or
objects without labels.
Um
and learning to color videos because
there are a lot of correspondences is an
interesting task by itself. I would um
suggest taking a look at the the
details. I'll um very briefly talk to
them talk about them. So if we have a
reference frame, what we need to do is
for coloring the input frame, we need to
find the pointers of where that uh
specific object or pixel is and then
based on that see what the color is and
copy what the color is u as as the color
for that pixel as the output at the as
the target color. And how this is done
is very much similar to the same topic
of attention uh that we talked about. So
it's it's about forming attention uh for
each of the pixels for each input frame
sorry reference frame and target frame.
We often run a CNN to see what features
around those pixels should be used. And
using those fe features now we can
calculate for each of the target pixels
we can calculate the attention or the
distance to all of the frames all of the
pixels in the reference frame. And then
after defining this attention with
respect to the
uh the the pixel of interest in the in
the target frame with all of the frame
all of the pixels in the
reference frame. Now we can do an
average color um of all of based on
those attention modules. So attention is
basically just similarity between the
the two. So anyways with that um what we
can do is we can just get the output
color as an average with with that
tension and then ultimately
um calculate the loss function because
we have the the the values of the colors
the right colors of those pixels in our
data [clears throat] and this was able
to with this reference frame colorize
the images. You see how consistent this
this becomes in terms of uh coloring if
we color them separately without this
consistency over time. You often uh see
like for example the person uh person's
shirts or or clothing changes color
because uh because there's no
uh constraint to keep it consistent. And
then there has been also very
interesting um applications because now
that you're calculating attention to a
reference frame, you're actually able to
track objects, track segments in in
videos and even identify key points in
the videos. That's a good question.
You're you're asking the qu your your
question is about this slide basically
and and how the encoder knows about the
data to begin with and um gets us good
learned representations. So all of these
tasks that I presented and and defined
are trying to do something here either
decoding
uh classifying or using regression to
generate some outputs to be able to
train this encoder. So if your original
images, if these are all natural images
taken off of internet or imageet or
whatever, then you are learning an
encoder that can extract features from
those types of images, right? With the
pretext task and then when you remove
the enc decoder and add this this
classifier to the end, you only need to
uh train this this part because this
encoder was already trained with all of
these pre-training tasks that I just uh
talked about.
You're asking if the labels are coming
from the decoder for pre-training the
encoder. And the the answer to that is
yes. That's that's why we define the
pre-text tasks because we want to have
some sort of labels, some outputs,
right? And then based on those outputs,
we try to um train this entire network
and the
on on the way of predicting the right
labels. This this encoder is also
trained. Good question. You're asking if
encoder and decoder of one big neural
network or there's differences in
different um papers in different works.
It has uh been completely different in
some cases your encoder and not just
decoder that's why I'm calling it
classifier in the example that I showed
you about um predicting the degree. This
is just a simple neural network right
the decoder is these FC layers. So this
could be one entire network and then you
you're replacing it with something for
your downstream task. But in some cases,
for example, when I talked about
autoenccoding,
encoding an image and then decoding
another image, you have you often have
two neural networks that are trained end
to end because you have you want to make
use of that representation space in the
middle. And in the next um thing that I
want to talk about mascato encoders even
there is no symmetry between encoders
and decoders. They can be just two
different um frameworks two different
neural networks even without any
symmetry to
um to to train the task. So this this is
very much task dependent pretext task
dependent but they could be belonging to
the same architecture that we we know
about say CNN or ResNet or they could be
two different architectures even without
any symmetry.
Remember that these are the very first
um methods for self-supervised learning.
So they're not supposed to be solving
everything. Uh that's just a a quick
disclaimer but the idea is the
hypothesis here is if the model is able
to say this is 90° rotated it means that
implicitly it's understanding the right
rotation right sorry right uh right uh
orientation and direction right and then
u it will be able to if if given a right
um an an unrotated image it's able to
recognize what it is in it Right. So,
but this is a limited task by itself. I
agree with that. The question that you
have is why why here they use 64. Right.
Um that's a good question but that's
also an arbitrary choice almost
arbitrary choice. As I said there are
many different types of different number
of uh permutations here 9 factorial. So
it's a very big number. it doesn't make
sense for us to be predicting all of
those. What the authors did here, they
decided to select a few of those
perurbations that there is enough
variation because many of those uh
perturbations is just like one uh patch
like switched only, right? So they
selected 64 of those that they have the
largest difference between them and they
just selected 64 because they wanted to
solve a classification problem instead
of um other types of tasks.
Okay. So I've been talking about these
um
frameworks that often do some transport
transformation on uh the image or the
videos and so on. And this brings us to
this newer framework which is um
published in 2021 and then there has
been so many uh follow-ups on this and
um it's been a great framework for
pre-training for many tasks even if uh
these days when we want to pre-train on
a um data set uh on raw data sets we
often use this uh MAE framework it's
called masked out encoders it is also a
reconstruction-based framework similar
to that masking strategy in painting
that I mentioned but this is far more um
uh detailed and as you can see this uh
framework is is not just selecting one
mask. There are so many different uh
patches and and places that they do
masking with even more aggressive um
sampling rates. 50% masking or 75 uh
masking rates and ratios. And through
training in large scale, they have shown
that not only they are able to
reconstruct all of those masked areas,
they are also
getting very good encoders that can
summarize the images into good features.
And how this was done was through
defining a dec encoder and a decoder.
And that's one of the examples that I
said this is not these are not symmetric
and encoders and decoder. So a large
portion of the input masks uh input uh
patches are masked and the ones that are
not masked they are
um given to the encoder to encode in to
features that are then passed through
the coder to generate the the complete
image. But let's let's go a little bit
into details of uh what this means. I do
have some of the details and and and how
these models are trained here. But
um I um very briefly just explain to you
how these models often work. The encoder
um here is very much similar to vit all
of the them are are based on
transformers. The vit that we've talked
about uh similar to the vits the images
are uh split into patches. The patches
are then uh sampled.
So uniform sampling is what they've done
in and they've shown 75% sampling is um
was was quite efficient in in uh the
experiments and um they use a mask a
high masking ratio and then this makes
the prediction task very challenging and
challenging in the set of pre uh pretext
for pretext tasks in self-supervised
learning means the task is meaningful,
the task is is very good because the the
model has to learn uh good features to
be able to reconstruct it. So uh with
that high sampling um high ratio of
sampling what what it uh it can do is
they can actually augment the data by a
lot too because each time you mask 75%
of the data. So you can reuse the same
image multiple and multiple times during
training. So you you will have so much
of data to train this uh encoder for
with and then that's why they use a huge
encoder a large um vit in as as their
encoder. So this encoder uh itself only
sees 25% of the samples the the patches
embeds those two with a first linear
projection to some embedding spaces then
positional embeddings are um added
exactly same as what uh what we
mentioned for vits and all of these are
transformer blocks and um
the encoder is is very large that's what
uh I just mentioned and then when it
comes to the decoding uh part. So we
have the embeddings of all of those
patches that were present for the
patches that were masked or or were
missing for those. There is a trainable
uh parameter very much similar to that
class token that we had a shared masked
mask token that is um basically in some
sort of average uh we can consider that
as as an average patch an average
representation that is put for the ones
that that are missing are masked and
then the decoder has to transfer those
them to the uh image patches of the
entire image. And then the entire last
one the entire image is the the target
the is the output target is the output.
So how we train this this is a simple
MSE based uh mean squared uh error loss
function for um the
between the image and the reconstructed
image. The loss function is only
computed for the masked patches similar
to the the previous one that I I just
talked about. And then what it has is um
when we do the training, they've shown
in the paper that you can do either
linear probing or full fine-tuning
to train your uh to to to to use it for
your downstream tasks for any of the
applications that you have in mind. And
um in linear probing what happens is you
often have your encoder frozen and then
use the learn representations and only
learn a linear function for the for
[snorts] the final task. And this this
mark is it's it means that it's being
trained. But in full fine tuning in
fine-tuning the pre-trained encoders are
also fine-tuned either either all of
them or just few um transformer blocks.
And that's uh that's the fine-tuning uh
framework. The linear probing provides a
measure of representation quality. How
the those representations features are
um and fine-tuning always exploits
models near potential to adopt for new
tasks. Okay.
So uh I if you're interested in this
topic and if you're planning to use this
this paper I highly advise looking at
the paper in his follow-ups. There are
so many uh discussions around different
aspects model choices hyperparameters
masking ratio is one thing they've
they've shown with the masking ratio
that the 75% is actually giving is
giving them a very high accuracy. So 75%
that's that's the reason that it was
chosen uh decoder depth decoder width um
mask tokens uh reconstruction targets
data augmentation how it's it's u
helpful and mask sampling method I'm I'm
showing the results here again mask
sampling method is uh mostly around
should should they use um some uh random
masking blocks or grid type of masking
you see the examples here and they've
they've um came to the conclusion that
this random masking was was the best uh
choice
and um finally they've been able to to
show that MAE is um doing a
much better job compared to many of the
other methods that were used. So some of
the other state-of-the-art methods were
actually Dynino and Moco V3. If you have
time, I will briefly go over them. But
um this framework was actually
outperforming those that are more um
[clears throat]
um at the time advanced frameworks of
contrastive learning. [clears throat]
So uh I'll stop for a few questions if
you have any after. Let me just
summarize the the
what we've talked about. pretext tasks
uh were actually very important and as
as I said their focus is on
understanding the visual common sense
and um one of the things that also
related to some of the questions that
were asked we can see is coming up with
an individual pretext task is often
challenging because the learn
representations may not be general
enough because of the type of task that
you you define Right? Uh for example,
um if you're using completion rotation
prediction or or jigsaw puzzle or
colorization,
your learn representations are good for
solving those specific tasks and they
may not be very good for uh general
pretext um tasks. So the question is in
split brain autoenccoder how does the
model knows know um how to predict the
other channel given the for example L
channel the illumination channel
lightness channel so your question let
me ask answer your question with a
question when you're training a model to
predict classes of objects in the image
how does the encoder know what features
to extract to predict them the
um the class of models labeled data
because you have what you're doing is
you're back propagating a loss value
that is calculated around those labels.
Right? It's the same story here. We
define a network that takes the one of
the channels and outputs the other
channel. How this was trained was by
back propagating what the output should
be. The output was the other other
channel. we do have the other channel in
the data. So instead of defining the
task being a classification of
predicting the class of the objects here
we define the task to be predicting the
color of the pixels
and the color of the pixels we already
have them in the data set. So the loss
function still can be calculated and
back propagated.
So the question is how they these
outputs are used as input to the
decoder. So this is again a vit
transformer uh style uh framework the
encoder that turns every uh every input
to a token at the as the output that is
representation of that specific uh input
patch. Right? So we've talked about this
but then we know that this is not this
is not the list of all patches. There
are some of the patches that are masked.
for those that are masked. We also train
this encoder outputs um shared mask
token. A token that is basically an an
average token for example. It's it's a
learnable parameter. We can't
necessarily interpret it, but we can say
just it's probably something that is
similar to mask like an average token.
So that that shared mask token is put in
the place of those that are missing and
then this long vector long long sequence
is created. Decoder another transformer
framework takes these long this long uh
set of tokens and outputs those that are
projected as the output pixel value.
Perfect.
So, we only have 15 minutes
and um
and a lot of things to cover.
But, uh I think what I wanted to to to
get out of this uh this um session was
for you to understand what pretext tasks
are and how we define them. and and one
of the most um used frameworks right now
is the masked autoenccoder which we
actually covered um uh to some good
extent. But anyways um I was here that
um we we did look at these
transformations and then we know that
all of these transformations are
representing are actually the same
object as the original image just in a
different uh form. Right? But then we
also have the knowledge that in the data
set we have other objects that look
completely different right. So if I
define a task that can say these that
belong to the same object, same pixel,
try to bring them close in the
representation space. Basically attract
them to each other in the representation
space and those that are not um the that
they do not belong to the same object
uh kind of put them try to maximize the
distance between them in the latent
space. basically repel the
representation of of these two images.
Then this is another task that is often
referred to as contrastive learning,
contrastive representation learning. And
there are quite a number of very uh
interesting methods to look at. We have
sampled there are so many papers um uh
in this space especially around uh 2018s
to 2020s u and uh and so on in around
those those years Sinclair Moco CPC and
then ultimately Dino which is actually
borrows concepts from contrastive
learning but it's not necessarily
contrastive learning framework
um
and uh what we do there is in order to
define, attract and repel functions u
characteristics or or uh regularize the
model based on those. We define the
reference image as X and then all of
those that are transformations of the
same as positive samples and all of the
other objects in the data set or in the
batch as negative samples. And these
positive and negative samples will
basically define a way for us to
calculate the loss function. How can we
do that? Assume we have a scoring
function. We want to get a scoring
function that says the score for the
reference image encoded version features
of the reference image and the features
of a positive sample should be larger
than the score that is comparing
the reference image and the
uh negative samples.
So with this type of um
scoring function if we uh so basically
to define uh this type of scoring
function we define a loss function based
on that after training the scoring
function uh s you can see this s is the
same as a score in the previous slide.
Um so if we have that scoring function
now in order to attract and repel we can
use this uh framework of uh turn them
the softmax uh setup with the exp that
turn those scores into probability
values and then in the denominator you
see all of the other negative samples
that are um used um are are considered
are are In order to implement actually
we use this we use the batch learning
framework. All of the other negative
samples that belong to other objects in
um in the batch are are taken as
negative samples and one of the
transformers as as the positive sample.
So we define the loss function like this
and um a score for the positive pair
score for all of the other negative
pairs.
And this function is very similar to
what we've actually discussed before.
Any ideas? This is the cross entropy for
multiclasses.
So if we have n samples, sorry, n um uh
samples. Yes.
Then um in this case we have n samples.
So the softmax is
if you have multiple classes, if you
have 10 classes as the output, it wants
to maximize the score for one of those
10 and minimize for the rest of it.
Right? It's the same story here. We want
to maximize this score but kind of
minimize the score between negative and
reference. Right? So it's it's the same
concept that we discussed about
multiclass uh classification but put in
the form of um formulation of
contrastive uh for this loss function as
contra contrastive learning. This
function is called info NCE or the
information noise contrastive estimation
loss which was proposed in uh this paper
and there are a lot of theoretical uh
discussions in in in the paper that this
uh objective this loss function measures
the dependencies
uh sorry that uh it's it's a lower bound
on mutual uh information and what in
mutual Mutual information is uh when you
have two images and you calculate the
mutual information between them, it's
basically measuring the dependencies or
shared information between these two
images. Right? So what we want to do is
we want to maximize shared information
between X and X plus but minimize the
shared information for X and X minuses.
Right? So the paper says um and again
this will itself take half an hour to to
go into. So you should definitely take a
look at uh the paper if you're
interested that
this the negative of this loss function
influenc is a lower bound on mutual
information between X and X plus. So a
lower bound on mutual information if um
the negative of it is a lower bound on
mutual information if I minimize the
influenc I'm basically maximizing the
mutual information between X and X plus.
So this is what I really want. So that's
why we take this as a as the loss
function and start minimizing
the uh that value. There is also another
theoretical aspect in the info inc paper
that says the larger this this the
number of negative samples the tighter
the bound. So they it tightens the bound
based on the number of negative samples.
So that's why for training a loss
function neural network with this type
of loss function we need a huge batch
size.
ute a larger number of negative samples
we'll get better um
and more much faster training
convergence
and then this loss function was used in
a number of different frameworks and in
the next few minutes I'm just going to
tell you what those u frameworks are for
example Sinclair is a simple uh
framework for contrastive learning
learning is basically taking each image
do the two transformation of the same
image transfer it into the
representation space and what it does is
it calculates the the cosine similarity
between um embeddings representations
but before doing that it does a linear
or nonlinear projection into a set of
features Z that calculates the the uh
the distance between those in this
space. And um this is this is the way
that they uh they do this generating
this positive samples and uh for
generating positive samples all sorts of
transformations would uh make sense. The
details are are basically uh covered
here. Uh generate a a positive pair by
sampling data uh augmentation functions.
So we sample a few of those then we
calculate the info NC loss on uh the
pairs and this is what we iterate
because each each sample has two n uh to
multiply by n uh samples that we have
created. So what happens is we take a
list of um
images in the in the mini batch in the
batch that we have and um pass them
through encoder for both variations of
the same image. So each of the images
basically will have a version of it
transformed version of it next. So we
have two n um subject two n samples in
the batch now.
And then this means that for each of the
samples the next one these two are
positive samples and everything else is
negative. So for the first one the
second uh image is positive everything
is else is negative. For the second one
the first is positive and everything
else is negative. And this repeats for
all of the samples there. So this is a
highle implement uh high level
definition of Sinclair.
Please note that we have in assignment
three a question related to Sinclair
that you will be uh exploring this
framework a little bit more but be
careful that the definition is slightly
different from what the standard
definition that I presented here and and
make sure you follow the instructions in
the assignment. So Sinclair was actually
very successful. it was able to without
the use of labels or or um and then
training a linear classifier on top of
the features. It was able to to surpass
all of the previous works and even be as
uh basically generate results comparable
to the supervised learning fully
supervised uh learning frameworks.
Although we need a larger neural network
because now we are learning more generic
features but in terms of accuracies it
was not as uh it was comparable to what
we had for supervised learning.
So um the interesting thing um with
Sinclair and and u some of the results
around it was
um that there are a few choices actually
let me uh spend time on on the the main
main choices. You may have this question
of why did we project the features into
a new variable instead of using the same
representations.
So this this was a design choice that
they made in Sinclair because they
rightly so assumed that when we have an
objective function that does this
contrast between samples, you often lose
some more information, some extra
information that do not help with the
contrastive learning framework. Right?
So in order to preserve all of those uh
extra
features representations are defined as
edge but then there is this linear or
nonlinear projection in their paper they
use nonlinear projection to to get the
uh z values that they can calculate
influency on. So that's one important uh
design choice and the other one is I
mentioned earlier large batch sizes. You
need huge batch sizes, larger batch
sizes to be able to get better Sinclair
performance. And we talked about it how
and and why this is the case. But we
can't always do large batch sizes for
many of the tasks that we have at hand
because um of
constraints in memory and so on. And
that was why a number of follow-ups for
example Moco was um proposed momentum
contrastive learning instead of using
the samples all of the negative samples
in the batch. What it does it it creates
a queue and and keeps a history of the
negative samples across patches over
time in the model. So it doesn't only
depend on the negative samples in the
batch. It has a separate queue that is
defined and and um keeps a number of
negative samples and changes it updates
it over time to train the u to to do the
info
uh loss with the contrastive loss here.
But because we have this Q, we cannot
back propagate because those samples are
not in the batch anymore. Right? So we
cannot back propagate for the negative
uh samples. And that's why it had to
separate the encoder for positive
samples which are now called query and
the negative samples which are now
called key in this um architecture. So
the training only impacts encoder and
over time the [clears throat]
Q encoder
using a momentum
m it updates the key encoder the
momentum encoder right so this is a
framework that is actually been very
successful in terms of implementation
and and followup versions of it there is
a lot of uh interest interesting results
But then what they've done was basically
uh tried hybrid versions of using some
nonlinear projection heads and data
augmentation from Sinclair and using
this mini batch style the the decoupling
of the mini batch and negative samples
from Moco. And they've shown that
actually if you if you do this together
version moco version two it um improves
the performance by a lot. So I will uh
stop here but there was some notions of
CPC the contrastive predictive coding uh
as another example that you can look at
in the slides and then a better version
of Moco Moo version 3 and Dino is also
one of the widely used frameworks which
actually has a similar type of
architecture as
uh as Moco but it's not necessarily uh
contrastive learning because now we have
student and teacher networks. So I'll
leave that for a separate discussion and
if if uh if uh you're interested we can
discuss maybe in the future uh slides in
future lectures. But anyways uh this is
also one of the widely used frameworks
for extracting features from images and
also videos sometimes.