all right well it's fantastic to have
everyone here my name is Ava I'm also an
instructor for the course and this is
now lecture two of 6s one91 on deep
sequence modeling and as Alexander kind
of alluded to at the end of his lecture
deep sequence modeling is a very very
powerful concept that especially as of
late has gone a lot of interest and a
lot of excitement around it due to the
Advent of large language models and
actually excitingly in the course this
year we're going to have two two and a
half uh lectures guest lectures on large
language models on Thursday and Friday
and Our intention with this lecture is
to really give you the foundations of
what sequence modeling is all about so
that you could be ready when we go into
these lectures on these Cutting Edge New
Frontier topics to really grasp them
from the fundamentals and Foundations
up okay so with that in mind in the
first lecture Alexander introduced the
very Basics the essentials of neural
networks how we train them using back
propagation what it means to define a
feedforward model and so in this next
talk we're going to turn our attention
to now applying these neural networks to
problems that involve sequential
processing or sequential modeling of
data and what we'll do is we'll try to
walk through this problem formulation
and the models step by step side by side
building up our intuition about how we
can build these networks up starting
right where we left off in the end of
last
lecture so to first set the stage what I
always like to do is to motivate this
notion of sequence modeling and
sequential data with a very very
intuitive example super simple one let's
say we have this image of a ball in 2D
space and our goal is to predict where
the ball is going to travel to next now
if I didn't give you any prior
information about the ball's history its
motion in this 2D space any guess you
place on the next position of the ball
will be a random
guess now instead if in addition to the
current location of the ball I gave you
some information about its history say
its prior locations now your problem
becomes much easier and effectively the
task is reduced to given this past
history about the ball predict where
it's going to go to next and I think we
can all agree that in this example right
the ball is appearing that it's moving
from left to
right so this is this notion of what we
mean when we think think about sequence
modeling and Beyond this simple example
as we'll see throughout the course
sequential data and sequence modeling is
really really all around us for example
the audio from my voice talking can be
split up into a sequence of sound waves
effectively chunked and processed in a
sequence we can do this similarly with
words and texts and natural language
where we can chunk or split up text into
a sequence of individual character
characters individual words and process
that in that manner Beyond this there's
many many more cases in which sequential
processing becomes Apparent from medical
signals like ECGs to stock prices in
financial markets to biological
sequences like nucleic acids or protein
sequences to weather to motion video and
more and so really this P this Paradigm
of sequence modeling unlocks a great
potential of applications and real world
use cases for deep learning in the
wild so what are some concrete problem
formulations or tasks we can think about
when we start to think about sequence
modeling in the first lecture we learned
about kind of the very basic prediction
problem like a classification problem of
will I pass this class yes or no
binary now instead of being able to go
from a single input to a single output
like a class label with sequence
modeling we want to process a sequence
of inputs such as the text the words in
an individual sentence and produce a
output at the end which may be similarly
a classification label like does a
sentence have a positive or negative
sentiment or feeling associated with it
it could also be a sequential output
like taking an image and now producing
or generating text that captions that
image or similarly we can think about
many to many generative or predictive
tasks where maybe we have sequences in
one language in English and we want to
translate that into sequences of another
language so these These are kind of the
the fundamental problem definitions or
problem setups that we can start to
think about when we have the capability
to process sequential
data so now with that in hand the
question becomes okay how do we actually
build up a neural network model to be
able to process and handle this unique
type of sequential
data and today we'll spend the about
half the time in the lecture talking
about where kind of the history of the
field got started with a new type of
neural network architecture that kicked
off our our real abilities to model
sequences and then in the second half
we'll talk about a powerful mechanism
that is being used today in the most
state-of-the-art um sequence models that
we see all around
us in both cases my goal is really to
convey the fundamentals of how we
actually do this and so we're going to
build up from the perceptron that
Alexander introduced and go step by step
to develop an understanding of these
models
okay so let's do exactly that let's go
back to the perceptron which we studied
in lecture one right we saw a diagram
like this where we have a set of inputs
X1 through XM and these are numbers
right they're represented numerically
and what we do in a perceptron is we
take these inputs we multiply it by a
corresponding weight value add them all
together to get this state Z and take
this Z and pass it through a function
that's nonlinear also called an
activation function and that leads us to
our predicted output
YH while we can have multiple inputs
coming in here you can think of these
inputs as a single slice or as a single
time step in a
sequence we we also saw that we are able
to stack these individual perceptrons
together to comprise a layer of a neural
network and here we can also extend to
go from a set of uh inputs to a set of
multiple outputs in purple but still
right in this example we're still
operating on a static single step right
there's no notion of sequence or no
notion of time these inputs are all
these individual inputs at just one
slice of a Time
step we can simplify our diagram further
and all I'm doing here in the middle is
that I've collapsed that visual of the
Hidden layer down to just this
abstracted green box still we have the
same operation of mapping an input to an
output some vectors of length M two
output vectors of length
n what can we do now to try to apply a
network like this to time series data or
sequential
data well maybe let's start off with
something perhaps a bit naive as a first
pass let's take this same model all I've
done here is I've just rotate it so it's
instead of left to right it's down to up
input to
output and what if we repeat this
multiple times we have our input Vector
at some time step T here t0 we feed it
into our neural network and we generate
an output
prediction and maybe we do this over
multiple time steps because in
sequential data we don't have just a
single time step we have multiple
individual time steps from t0 to T1 T2
and so on in the
sequence we could do this in isolation
right we take the inputs at these
individual time steps pass them in
through the model and generate an output
and here again it's a simple function
where we're applying this function
defined by our neural network to the
input at a time step T to generate a
prediction y hat of
T but what's the problem here
right we know that our output Vector y
hat at a particular time step is just
going to be a function of the input at
that time step and if this is inherently
sequential data it's probably in
sequence for a reason because there's
some sort of inherent dependence on time
steps within that sequence relative to
each other and in this way we're
completely ignoring the inputs at the
previous time steps to make a prediction
at a later time step right these are all
treated in
isolation to predict a Time Step at say
time an output at say time two we could
probably benefit aot lot from taking the
information from time Step Zero time
step
one how do we circumvent this how could
we possibly relate these time steps to
each
other well fundamentally what we're
trying to do is to relate the Network's
internal computations at these
individual time steps to Prior history
of the computations from those prior
previously observed time steps and we
want to pass this information on forward
through time to maintain that
information as we move through the
sequence so maybe we can try that out
what if we were able to define a way to
link the neuron's internal state from a
previous time step to the computation at
a later time
step maybe we can make this concrete we
can define a variable
we'll call it an internal State h of T
that's maintained by the neurons in this
network and we pass this stay on time
step to time step across time and our
goal is to maybe embibe this this
internal state with some notion of
memory right some record of the prior
computations that the network has
made and what this means a little more
concretely is now our prediction why hat
of T at a particular time step should
depend not only on the input at that
time step but also this state that's
been carried on from the prior time step
this past history and the current
input and so what's really powerful here
is now we're starting to Define more
formally a relation between these output
predictions that depends not only on the
input observed but also the this past
memory and as you can kind of see and
hopefully start to get intuition for
that past memory is dependent on the
prior inputs right so we have this idea
of some sort of recurrence something
that's repeated and maintained over time
as the network makes these
computations and because this output
that we're producing is a function of
not only the current input but also this
past State we can describe this type of
network via what we call a recurrence
relation and we can visualize this in a
couple of different ways here on the
right I'm showing these time steps kind
of unrolled in slices over time where
we've made these links kind of
visualized by this variable H but we can
also represent this on the left via this
cycle this Loop which tells us this
concept of the state maintaining this
recurrent log effectively of the
Network's internal computations that
gets updated with each time
step and so this is this notion of a
Time series model that has a sense of
recurrence and really this is a very
very foundational Concept in all of
sequence modeling this notion of what we
call recurrent neural networks and
hopefully this example and this buildup
from where we started with the
perceptron gives you this intuition
about how we can start to model
sequential data using these time series
models called recurrent neural
networks so let's keep going right let's
continue to build from this foundation
and now start to get a little bit more
formal about the operations that go into
the internals of these recurrent neural
networks or
rnns as we started to see right the key
idea is that we have this internal State
h h of T and that state is going to be
updated at each time step as we process
the
sequence we can do this by defining what
we call this recurrence relation right
it's a way to process a sequence time
step by time
step and what we want is our internal
CLE State H to to be a function of not
only the input but also the prior state
so that there's some notion of memory
that's carried through to formalize this
the cell State h of T is defined by some
function parameterized by a set of
Weights W that depends not only on the
input at that time step but also the
prior state from the previous time
step and we can recur currently apply
the same function time step by time step
updating the weights so that we get this
uh recurrent update to our cell State as
the sequence is
processed an additional way to build up
this intuition about rnns is to think
about this kind of in pseudo code right
so here we're going to walk through a
python pseudo code example that helps
build up this
intuition so let's say we want to convey
and and build up the uh RNN from scratch
we're going to Define some RNN my RNN
and we're going to initialize it with a
hidden State set to zero and now our
input is this little fragment of a
sentence I love recurrent neural and our
task is to use the individual words in
this sentence to predict the next word
that comes next in that sequence
what we do is we Loop through for each
word in this sentence we use our RNN to
take that word take the last hidden
State predict some output and update the
hidden State and do this iteratively
right through this iterative procedure
such that at the end we can generate a
prediction for the next word that comes
after we've processed these inputs
this is the fundamental of this notion
of aate update and output that is the
core of the RNN so again walking through
this from the from the bottom up given
our input Vector we Define a function to
update the hidden State and now we've
just introduced a little bit more
formality that makes these weight
definitions and functions uh explicit
but just again this is the update to the
hidden state is a function of both the
input at that time step and the prior
hidden state from the previous time
step that updates our hidden State and
now we can actually generate a
prediction an output vector by taking
that hidden State and applying awaited
transformation to it right so this is
the core of both how the RNN can update
its internal memory its hidden State and
also produce a prediction and output at
each individual time
step so by seeing this and visualizing
this rnm as sort of this recurrent
cyclic visual here I mentioned that we
can also represent it by kind of taking
these individual time slices and
separating them out on a Time axis
unrolling them across time and if we do
that I think the intuition becomes
perhaps even more clear where again
starting from the the first time step we
can unroll step by step T1 T2 all the
way to T where you can see this internal
state is being passed on time step to
time step we're generating the
predictions we can also bring back that
formal math to this diagram where now
you can see we have one weight Matrix
that transforms the input to the
computation of the Hidden State we have
a weight Matrix that defines how the
hidden state gets get updated and
finally one that transforms the hidden
state to the output
prediction importantly right these are
the same weight matrices at each
individual time step right there's this
this and this and they're reused at each
time step in the
sequence so now this tells us okay how
do we actually make these updates how do
we predict the outputs
but what we need to know to actually
train this network and learn it is how
do we Define a loss right as Alexander
introduced in order to learn a neural
network or train it you need to Define
some sort of function that tells you how
close the predictions are actually
getting to the desired behavior that you
seek out and with rnns that concept that
exact same concept still applies the
only difference is that we can compute a
loss at each slice at each of these
individual time steps in the sequence
and get a total loss by summing over all
the time steps in our
sequence so in total right this defines
what we call our forward path how we
make predictions time step by time step
and how we use those predictions to
compute a
loss we can walk through an example of
how you can actually Implement an RN
yourself bottom up from scratch in a
library like tensorflow where we try to
Define an RNN as a layer per uh
initializing the weight
matrices as attributes of our RNN class
and we Define importantly in this
function call how we do that exact
forward operation that forward pass that
I introduced in the prior slide and as
you can see right it consists of these
two key lines
the first being the update of the Hidden
State according to the input and the
prior hidden State and the second being
the prediction of the output which is a
transformation of the Hidden State at
that time
step and we return both of these the
prediction and that hidden State
value and as you'll see right this is a
really good way to move now thinking in
code from that pseudo code into inition
we showed earlier to now kind of how you
can define an RNN class yourself from
scratch and moving forward one more step
you can build from this intuition to now
learn and understand how to
operationalize an RNN through uh layers
and modules that are already implemented
in these common machine learning
Frameworks like tensor flow and P
torch and in the first lab of this
course using uh rnns for sequence
modeling you'll get hands-on experience
in working um with these these functions
and classes in either of these
libraries
okay so hopefully now right that gives
you this intuition of how we've built up
from this first example of static input
static output to to these diverse types
of tasks and new sorts of problems we
can tackle when we start to be able to
process and handle sequential data
whether that's taking a sequence
producing a class label or actually
being able to do something like next
word prediction or next character
prediction to actually generate and
produce out a sequence as
output and in this latter example
forecasting a bit not only is this what
get hands-on experience with in our
software lab but really this notion of
many to many sequence modeling is the
backbone of how language models actually
work and you've just you know kind of
understood some of that intuition um
starting today and and now Building
forward all right
so let's now think about how do we
operationalize this in the real world
yeah go ahead
uh every node in the hidden first hidden
connected by tode in the second is that
how the AR
looks yeah so the question is what
defines the connection between the
hidden layers the important thing is
that one of these individual green
blocks that can have many layers itself
right it doesn't necessarily have to be
one it could be many the important thing
is that that's you can think of that as
a unit and that unit contains some
number of layers within that unit but
that operation is basically applied for
all the individual time steps in that um
sequence using the same set of layers
and weights in that unit you compute the
loss at each of those steps and then as
we'll see when you actually update the
weights that is done by taking the loss
from all the individual time steps and
then updating after you've processed all
the time steps
individually just just in the same in
the same way as with feed forward
networks where you can have weights that
connect layer to layer in RNN that has
multiple layers within one unit there is
weights there are weights that define
those
connections any additional questions
before we transition
otherwise
okay okay
so now now let's think about how we
actually operationalize and bring this
this notion of sequence modeling to a
real world
example sequences are rich and sequences
are interesting for a few reasons one is
because they're tremendously variable
right it's not like an image where you
try to have you know a height and a
width of the image and for all your
images in your data set those height and
width are fixed in something like
language sequences can be short they can
be long they can be in between so we
need to be able to handle this
variability the other richness and
Nuance is that inherently with things
that depend on time
you could have instances where there's a
really short range interaction or
dependency or you can have instances in
a sequence where something at the very
beginning dictates the meaning or uh the
value at something at the very end so
this notion of spread or long-term
dependency and kind of fundamentally
right there's this notion of order and
our model needs to be able to do a good
job of representing and reasoning about
this order um
through through the approach that we
take so we'll use these kind of criteria
to to motivate how rnn's can do well at
doing this but also what are some
shortcomings of rnns when it comes to
these kind of real world operational
criteria that our sequence model needs
to meet so to do that we're going to
walk through a very very concrete
example which is really maybe now has
become the quintessential sequence
modeling problem out there and that's
this idea of predict the next word given
a sequence of words predict the word
that comes next and this to underscore
this this is a very important task
because not only is it beautiful and
simple and intuitive but it turns out
it's incredibly powerful to build up the
very very powerful language models that
we see today are trained on this exact
task of being able to predict the next
word so let's say we have this example
sentence this morning I took my cat for
a walk our task is given this set of
words we want to be able to predict the
next word and let's say we want to build
a sequence model like an RNN to do this
task what is our very first
step any ideas
breaking breaking the words into chunks
yeah let's say now we've done we've
broken the sentence into chunks or words
what do we how can we actually build a
neural network model to do
this vectorize them exactly so the core
consideration after we've broken this
text up into words is we need a way to
actually represent it to to a model
right because remember all neural
networks are are their
function actuators or function
approximators that operate on numbers
right vectors and matrices and ways of
representing numbers so that's exactly
what we need to do if we want to have a
model that takes a word in and predicts
the next word out we can't just uh pass
that in as words we need to ual way to
represent these words as numbers in a
numerical representation to be able to
operate on them using a neural network
and this is this notion of vectorizing
the input or encoding the language for a
neural network to to operate on and this
is really really a core Concept in
language modeling and uh neural network
and machine learning modeling in general
and so the solution that we're going to
introduce right now is this notion of
embedding which is an idea of taking an
input that can be in some form like
words and then transforming it into
first an index that then can map to a
vector of some fixed size so to break
this down step by step how do we
actually do this let's say we have our
VOC our body of all possible words we
could see in all sentences we could
encounter
we call this a vocabulary right a corpus
of words that covers all the possible
words that we could
encounter and this vocabulary has to
have some fixed size right what we can
then do is take the individual words in
this vocabulary and map them to a number
an index let's say a maps to one cat
maps to two so on and so forth
then now these indices give us a way to
transform that index that slot to a
vector and look up a vector that
represents that word based on the index
and I'll show you exactly what I mean by
this the last step is to do this
embedding operation which means mapping
an index to a vector of fixed size one
way we could do this is what we call a
one hot or binary encoding or embedding
and what I've done here is we've defined
a vector of a sparse Vector of a fixed
size and all it has is zeros and a one
in the index that corresponds to that
word and So based on that index value I
can effectively encode the identity of
the word and look up and backtrack what
the word was based on on that
index the other thing I could do is to
actually use a neural network layer to
learn an embedding of those words in
some fixed length lower dimensional
space and this is very similar we've
just done this operation of mapping that
index to an encoding such that similar
words end up in a similar space of this
embedding space but we are still able to
retrieve our Vector representation of
the word using that index so I think a
really good way of thinking about these
vectorization or um embedding operations
is to think about indexing to look up a
fixed representation a numerical
representation for these
words and this is a really really
important
concept so now we can do that for our
sequences we can transform our words
into this vector
representation and to now think about
okay why why sequence modeling is
difficult and complex we can think and
see some examples of how that really
comes to life right we can have the the
um complexities that arise when we think
about variable sequence lengths so maybe
we could have short sequences medium
length sequences longer sequences and in
all cases we want our neural network
model to be able to track these
dependencies consistently to still be
able to do a good job of PR of
predicting the next word at the end and
that relates as well to a good ability
to track and store these long-term
dependencies in these sequences where in
many cases we may need information from
very very beginning of the sentence to
predict the next word at the very end of
the sentence
that's important because depending on
how we Shuffle the words around right
this notion of sequence can convey very
different semantic meanings in our
prediction
task and so hopefully this example of
language modeling and next word
prediction gives you a sense of why
sequence modeling can be very rich and
very complex as as a neural network deep
learning
task so okay that gives us away
concretely in the real world some some
understanding of why sequence modeling
uh is Rich and challenging to actually
train a sequence model like an RNN
though we need some special
considerations we're still going to use
that fundamental algorithm that
Alexander introduced of back propagation
but now we need to introduce something
to be able to handle that time
dependence
so like we've been doing throughout this
lecture let's build up from the first
principles that we started with let's go
back to how we train our feed forward
models right we first take our inputs we
make a forward pass through the network
going from input to Output to actually
train the model and compute loss and
back propagate gradients we do this
backwards through the back propagation
algorithm by taking the derivative of
the loss with respect to each of the
parameters and each of the model weights
in our Network and then we adjust and
move those parameters in the direction
that will minimize the loss right we
take a
step in rnns right we saw this preview
of how the loss is actually computed
time step by time step now when we uh
when we want to go to train rnns we not
only need to consider consider an
individual loss but actually the
aggregate loss through all these
individual time steps what that means is
that instead of back propagating these
loss values through a single feedforward
Network we need to back propagate errors
across these individual time steps and
then uh such that we can carry through
errors from late time steps all the way
back to the
beginning and the algorithm for doing
this is what we call back propagation
Through Time such that errors flow from
all the way back late in this in the
sequence to the very
beginning what this means practically is
that you can have this chain of very
repeated computations multiplying a
weight Matrix uh uh multiple times
repeated with each other as well as
repeated use of the derivative of the
activation functions in these
networks that can pose some very
practical challenges which for the sake
of time we're not going to go too deep
into but the important thing that to
keep in mind is that these standard rnns
can be somewhat difficult to train
stably because you could get many values
that are larger than one you multiply
them together and then the the gradient
explodes right conversely you could have
many values that are very small you
multiply them together and then the
gradient vanishes and it goes down to
very very close to
zero this actually has real practical
implications because what it
means is that it makes it really really
hard to be able to track these long-term
dependencies that we care about in our
sequence if our gradients are unstable
either blowing up or shrinking down to
nothing we can't effectively take those
gradients from late time steps and pass
them through to the earlier time steps
to be able to uh promote our model to
retain that
information and so in the literature and
in the sequence modeling Community
there's been a lot of active research to
come up with improved architectures
based on the RNN to try to solve this
problem and the real core concept is
that they add some complexity to that
RNN unit itself
effectively adding um additional
functions to try to selectively control
the amount of information that's passed
to the update of the Hidden
State one very very prominent way of
doing this is a network called an lstm
or long short-term memory Network and
this was introduced now um quite some
time ago but has been very foundational
to a lot of the sequence modeling work
that's gone on
since so to give you one quick look at
some of the applications of rnns that
you'll actually get Hands-On with today
I want to highlight this particular
example of Music
generation and this is a problem that
really lends naturally to sequence
modeling and to an recurrent neural
network architecture because what we're
doing is let's say we want to try to
predict and generate a new piece of
music one way we could do this is by
taking the individual notes in a piece
of music and very similar to how we saw
with the task of predicting the next
word build a model that given the past
history of musical notes learns to
predict the most likely next musical
note in the
sequence and this is exactly what you
will do today in our soft sofware Labs
where you'll be able to train a RNN
model to generate brand new music that's
never existed before and in fact you
know you're you're not the only ones who
have had a go at this this is an example
from a few years
ago of a startup that was trying to seek
to do a music
generation and they trained a neural
network model on um classical music and
tested to finish a work by the composer
France Schubert uh the famous unfinished
Symphony where they gave two movements
of the symphony and tasked the model to
generate the music corresponding to the
third third movement so let's see if we
can play this
[Music]
so it's it's pretty good maybe some
there are some classical music officios
in the audience who are familiar with
this work but I always appreciate it
because it kind of gets at some of these
themes that we're talking about in terms
of the um capabilities of these sequence
models so so far we've talked
exclusively about this sequence modeling
architecture called recurrent neural
networks but and I want to take a moment
to kind of appreciate that it's very
very remarkable that we're able to
understand the fundamentals of sequence
modeling and build up to some of these
capabilities using
rnns but like any technology and any
method right rnns have some core
limitations and in fact
those limitations have motivated new
development of new architectures and
approaches in sequence modeling as well
as improved versions of rnns that have
done better and uh solved some of these
limitations couple things that are
important to keep in mind when thinking
about
rnns one is that the core concept as we
talked about is this notion of the state
hftt remember right the Concepts in all
that we're talking about these neural
networks operate on vectors and matrices
of numbers just like that the state of
an RNN is a fixed length Vector right
there's only so much information that
can be encapsulated into something of
fixed size and so that presents what we
think of as a bottleneck to the amount
of information that the RNN State can
hold
additionally because rnn's process
information time step by time step this
can make them very difficult to
parallelize such that things can be
processed simultaneously right we have
this inherent sequence
dependence and finally related to both
these points that encoding bottleneck of
the state can prevent the long-term
memory capacity of some of these types
of recurrent
architectures so to think about now how
we can try to overcome this let's go
back to our fundamental goal of sequence
modeling which is to take a sequence of
inputs use a neural network to compute
some features or States representing
those inputs and now be able to generate
predictions according to that sequence
with RNN we said we are going to process
this time step by time step use
recurrence but we also saw that
inherently ly this notion of sequence
time step by time step processing places
some real limitations on the
capabilities of
RNN ultimately and ideally we want to be
able to process our sequence very
efficiently in parallel perhaps so that
we can generalize uh to Long sequences
and do so efficiently and also have this
desired attribute of being able to track
these important dependencies in the
sequence
effectively and so a question that was
posed a few years ago is what if we
could try to tackle the sequence
modeling problem without having to deal
with the data time step by time step
maybe we can eliminate the need for
recurrence maybe we could do this by
squashing everything together right
ignore this notion of these individual
time steps and let's say concatenate all
our inputs together right into one
vector and we feed it into something
like a feed forward model and generate
an output at the end and hope that it
makes
sense while we if we do this in this
naive first approach right yes we've
eliminated the need for recurrence so we
don't have to process our data step by
step that's good but this doesn't seem
really scalable because now let's say
we're just trying to use a dense Network
that's not going to be very
efficient also we've destroyed all
information about order we've squashed
the inputs into a concatenated vector
and by doing so we've destroyed any hope
to remember things that appeared earlier
or later and relate them to each
other so this has has motivated a
different way of thinking about sequence
modeling
which is this idea of trying to take a
representation of sequential data and
Define a mechanism that can on its own
pick out and look at the parts of that
information that are important relative
to other uh parts of that thinking about
this in other words can we Define a way
to be able to given a sequence identify
and attend to the important
parts of that sequence and moreover
model the dependencies in that sequence
that relate to each
other and this is the core idea of a
very powerful mechanism called attention
and in 2017 there was a paper introduced
called attention is all you need that
introduced this mechanism and so if
you've heard of a model like chat GPT or
GPT the T T in that acronym stands for a
Transformer and a Transformer is a type
of neural network architecture that can
be applied not only to you know language
data but other types of sequential
data and the foundational mechanism of a
Transformer what makes it different is
this operation of attention and so we're
going to in this lecture talk about that
attention mechanism and in later
lectures you will learn more about how
these Transformers are actually being
applied as language models and in other
applications as
well so we're going to break down the
core concept of attention really step by
step all
right let's do that okay attention
itself is a very informative word right
what it means is we have this inherent
ability as humans to to think about an
input and automatically zoom in and pick
out the things that are Salient the
important
features so let's build up our intuition
starting with an
image how do we figure out what's
important in this
image one way we could do it naively is
we could go pixel by pixel left to right
back and forth and scan this to try to
compute some value about how important
these individual pixels are
but of course our brains don't operate
like that we're able to automatically
look at this and pick out to and attend
to the important
parts and the first part of this problem
is this notion of being able to identify
which parts are are important in some
input and then ultimately we want to use
that identification to extract the
features the components of the input
that correspond to these high attention
values
right and to think about this more
concretely this notion of identifying
the parts to attend to is really similar
to search right so when we do something
like a search we present a question and
we're trying to seek an answer let's say
you came to this class right and you had
the question how can I learn more about
neurl Networks and deep learning and
AI maybe one thing you could do besides
coming to this class would be to go to
the Internet have all the videos all the
materials available on the Internet and
try to do a search to find something
that matches your
query let's say you go to a giant video
database like YouTube and you put in
your query your ask deep
learning that's your search topic and
now what search does is through let's
say we go through every video in this
database and we ex extract some
informative nugget of information a key
that represents the core element of that
video a descriptor of that video and now
we have our query and we have a set of
keys now our task is okay to actually do
the search how could I go about this
well I want to see how close the match
is between my query what I searched for
and those keys those key indicators in
the
database and I want to see how similar
they
are so I'll do this step by step ask how
similar is my query to these
Keys first instance a beautiful video
about elegant sea turtles not
similar a video of from our past lecture
on deep learning yes similar a key
related to Kobe Bryant's fadeaway not
similar so now we've identified the key
that's important we want to attend to
this our last task is to actually
extract the value that's associated with
this similar uh match that we found we
want to extract the features that we
want to pay attention to the video
itself and we'll call this the value and
because our search was implemented with
a good attention mechanism we've
identified the best deep learning course
out there for you and your
query this concept is really the core
intuition behind
attention and that's very very closely
related to how this attention operation
Works in neural networks like
Transformers so now let's go back to our
sequence modeling problem where we have
a series of words and we want to predict
the next word with this
sentence if we break this down step by
step first remember we don't want to
process the information time step by
time step we've broken down that need
for recurrence we're going to feed in
the data all at once and still we need a
way to encode some notion about order so
what we're going to do is we're going to
put in an embedding called a positional
embedding that effectively gives us a
way to encapsulate that relative
position of these elements in that
sequence we're not going to go into
great detail about positional embeddings
but you can think of it as an encoding
that gives us some representation of
position in the
sequence now we take those position
aware
encodings and we do that search
operation and we operationalize that
search operation to extract three sets
of matrices that we call the query the
key and the value just like I introduced
before the way we do that is we take the
positional embedding and think about
that as representing our sequence in a
positionally aware way and we use a
neural network layer to produ uce each
of these individual matrices the query
the key and the value the important
thing to keep in mind is that it's that
same positional embedding that's
repeated in this mechanism of self
attention but these are different neural
network layers that yield different
values for each of the query key and
value
matrices that means is that they can
effectively capture different
information as well
see now again our next step in the
search operation was to figure out okay
how similar is the query to the key and
that's exactly what we're going to do
next with attention to do that right
remember these are um numeric vectors or
matrices and so we need a mathematical
way to compute that similarity between
two sets of numerical features so let's
say we have two vectors our query Vector
our key vector and what we can do
mathematically using linear algebra is
measure the similarity of those vectors
in space using the dot product that
tells us how close they are to each
other we can scale it and this gives us
a very concrete similarity metric that
captures that similarity between the qu
query and the
key that same principle can apply now to
matrices as well do product and scaling
that gives us a similarity
metric now let's think about what this
similarity computation actually means
remember right we're trying to
understand how these components of the
input relate to each other what parts of
the sentence are important to each other
and uh important to convey the semantic
meaning of the sentence as a whole so if
we have this examp example he tossed the
tennis ball to serve let's say we have a
we've computed our querying key matrices
applied a scaling we can then apply a
function called a softmax to basically
squish these values between zero and one
and now this gives us a matrix that
gives us a relative waiting of how those
individual components in the sequence
relate to one
another intuitively you can think about
things that that are more similar as
having higher attention weights more
related as having higher attention
weights things that are less related as
having lower attention
weights so here right in this example
toss and ball have a high score tennis
and ball have a high score and so on
this gives us our attention waiting or
attention Matrix the final step is to
now use that relative waiting to
actually pull out those important Fe
features that we care about what we do
here is we take our value Matrix
multiply it by our attention weight and
this gives us an output of a feature set
over that input space that reflects the
relative elements of the sequence that
are interrelated relative to each
other that's really the core of how
attention
works and that's really really be it's
really really beautiful and striking to
me because this mechanism gives us a
very natural way to pull out and attend
to features that are quite important
relative to each other in an input and
architecturally now how do we actually
build this out into something like a
Transformer
well one second please um we can go
again by taking our input Computing
these positional encodings we Define
these neural network layers that compute
the query key and
value then we can compute this relative
waiting between the query and the key
that's a matrix multiply representing
the dot product a scaling and a softmax
and then ex use the value Matrix to
extract features that have high
attention
scores and these are the core operations
that now Define these attention heads
which can be which are really the core
component of architectures uh like the
transformer so as as we've mentioned and
realized right this is really the the
foundational attention is the
foundational building block of of
Transformers and as I think kind of some
questions got to as well right a
Transformer architecture does not need
to be defined by just a single attention
block you can actually stack multiple
attention heads uh together to now be
able to
uh basically increase the capacity of
your network and pull out different sets
of features and more complex sets of
features so again in this very intuitive
example maybe you have a Network that
has three attention heads and if you go
in and inspect again this is a intuitive
um example let's say you were to go in
and inspect the values of each of these
attention heads maybe you could get some
interpretability out with respect ECT to
the different features or parts of the
input that the network was attending
to so what are some real world use cases
and what has attention really enabled
and transformed over the recent years
it's not only in language processing
that Transformers and self- attention
have really led to tremendous
advances while that's the case right the
mechanism and the architecture behind
attention Transformers is very
generalizable and so as you'll see right
natural language is one tremendous area
that Transformers have really taken off
and you'll get hands-on experience with
this not only um in the lectures but in
a brand new software lab on llms we'll
also see a bit about how attention and
sequence modeling has been extended to
biological sequences in one of our guest
lectures and in fact in something that
may not appear sequential like images or
computer vision there are a class of
models called Vision Transformers that
have now also become very very powerful
um in processing image data as
well so to summarize and and close
hopefully you've gotten a sense of how
rich sequence modeling is as a set of
problems and things we can consider we
saw how rnn's work we saw how we can
build up intuition for rnns through this
notion of recurrence how they can be
trained through back propagation you'll
be able to get a hands-on experience
building rnn's for music generation and
finally we closed with talking about
self- atttention and Transformers as a
way to model sequences uh without
needing to handle time steps
individually and
recurrently and stay tuned for more on
llms both Hands-On and in more lectures
so with that that closes the lecture
portion for
today we now can use the remaining time
for open Office hours and discussion
about any lingering questions you have
or comments uh related to the discussion
we also want to draw your attention to
the software Labs which are now
available on the GitHub linked on the
course website the instructions for
completing the software labs are all
there we have options in both tensorflow
and pytorch so hopefully you'll get um a
fun chance to go through those and work
with those and finally I think um our
gracious host reception host John
stepped out but immediately uh after
this there will be a in-person reception
to kick off the uh the course just down
the street at One Kendall Square um with
food provided and many special thanks to
John Werner and Link Venture oh he's
still there back at the top thank you
John for for graciously hosting