hi everyone welcome back to day two of
MIT intro deep learning thank you all
for coming back for day number two hope
everyone enjoyed day one today we're
going to be talking about one of my
personal favorite topics in this entire
course which is how we're going to give
computers the ability to have a you know
an ability that many of us have you know
which is the ability of sight and the
ability to sense Vision so some
background first of all so what is
Vision vision is you know one of the
most important human senses that we all
have it allows us to uh do everything
from you know detect and interpret human
emotion and facial expressions to
navigate the world to manipulate objects
and manipulate our world around us and
today you know what we're going to do in
the class uh today is just understand
fundamentally how we can give computers
this exact same sense as well the
ability to understand you know what is
what is in the physical world around it
just from raw visual inputs and I like
to think of this you know very super
simple definition of dis ability just by
uh this quote right here this is the
ability to know what is where by looking
and today's class will basically be
focused on what we look at will be
images but in general this is the you
know broad sense of ability that we'll
be focusing on but you know vision is
actually so much more than just
understanding what is where but it's
also understanding you know a sense of
planning as well right it's not a static
sense only but when I show you this
image here for instance right what you
see is you know first you see the static
things you see the things like the cars
on the side of the road you see the
people but then most importantly you
start to as you look closer at this
image immediately what you'll feel
yourself doing is also getting a sense
of Dynamics as well you know not only
understanding what is where but also how
things are moving you understand that
even though these two uh cars are on the
road one of them probably is uh
completely static right the white van on
the left is probably completely static
because it's parked on the side of the
road and even though these are both cars
you can detect them as cars they are
perceived very differently right when we
look at this image same as you know
these people on the side of the the the
the side of the road versus these people
actually actively moving right and
vision is actually all about not just
understanding what these things are in
this image but actually understanding
and interpreting the image holistically
in terms of how things are moving how
things are changing temporally as well
and it accounts for all of these details
in the scene we take this for granted
right when we look at all these things
even minor things like the traffic
lights in the background right very very
Minor Details that Define you know like
the movement of even these future cars
right we can infer a lot of things about
this image the closer we look at them
and deep learning is really starting to
bring about a huge revolution in uh
computer vision algorithms and their
applications you know this has changed
changing everything from robotics
manipulation autonomy to mobile
Computing everyone in your pockets you
have uh a lot of computer vision models
running on these embedded
Hardwares uh biology Healthcare right
making sure that we can detect things
the way that humans detect things from
from live or from from raw imagery and
raw medical
imagery to autonomous driving and
accessibility applications as well the
real theme that you'll see throughout
this class is how pervasive these
algorithms especially today today's
lectures are going to be focused on the
pervasiveness of these computer vision
algorithms because they are truly
everywhere you know the one one example
that you'll get some exposure with in
today's lab is going to be on facial
detection right this is one of the
original computer vision applications
that was extremely impactful in the
community it just basically allows us to
detect not just if there is a face there
but you know also features about the
face understanding micro emotions about
the face that are extremely hard to
detect and extremely hard to interpret
and of course we've all heard a lot of
Buzz and a lot of hype around
self-driving cars this is a classic
computer vision problem right what we're
doing here is taking as input imagery
you can actually see the image that
comes in on the bottom right hand side
of this uh video right this is the raw
camera image that's coming into the the
network and this is an endtoend Network
this is a single model this is very
different actually than how most
autonomous cars operate it's a pipeline
of mini models and predefined maps
actually this was work that we did here
at MIT where we created an autonomous
vehicle it's actually located in the
garage of this building uh to drive
fully autonomously on brand new seen
brand new never seen before roads purely
from visual input
data and of course uh we already have
have talked about this a little bit but
we'll see some applications of of what
you'll learn about today in biology
Healthcare medicine and so on so I'd
like to you know now start to dive into
some of the technical basis of today's
class and I'll I'll just preface all of
this by saying that you know all of the
amazing things that I showed in the
previous slide that today's class will
be one of the classes where what we'll
be training these computer vision
algorithms to do are going to a lot of
times be uh tasks that we as humans take
for granted we do these things without
even thinking about them and we do them
with such ease and I think the the
question that will really boil down to
today's lecture is how we can take
something that all of us take so for
granted and distill that also into
computers as well so in order to
understand this first we're just going
to start with the base most simple case
which is understanding just how a
computer can process an image right not
even just uh not even process it but
let's say even just represent an image
well to a computer images are just
numbers right actually images are a lot
easier than language because images are
already repres presented as a array or a
list a two-dimensional list of numbers
so if we had for example this image of
Abraham Lincoln that you can see on this
slide here it's just made up of pixels
right what is a pixel a pixel is a
single number and since this is a
grayscale image uh every pixel is going
to be represented by just one number if
this was a color image every pixel would
be represented by three numbers it's a
composition of red green and blue uh
values instead of just a single gray
intensity value so we can represent this
image nothing more than a
two-dimensional array of numbers right
one for one number for every pixel in
this image and this answers our first
question of how a computer can see an
image so if we have you know like I said
a color image this is going to not be a
two-dimensional array but rather a
three-dimensional array it will be two
Dimensions by a third dimension which is
going to be this color axis which will
always be of length three for most
images and this is how we'll we'll
proceed for the rest of the class today
this is how we'll represent our images
and there are two types of common
machine learning or deep learning tasks
that we'll be focusing on actually
throughout this entire course but
especially for the purpose of today and
this is going to be the top the the
tasks of regression and the tasks of
classification so let's start with both
of these tasks so number one for
regression what is regression regression
allows us to Output a continuous value
in our system
right and classification on the other
hand allows us to Output a class label
so for example the the image that you
see here could be mapped into a
classification problem let's say we want
to detect which US president is this
image coming from and the answer can be
one of K or n different classes right
these are discrete classes and you can
be one of those n
classes so in order to correctly
classify images like you see on the left
hand side what does our model need to be
able to do or what do we need to be able
to do in order to do this ourselves as
humans well what we need is we need to
understand well what is unique about
every one of those classes on the right
right what is unique about a picture of
Abraham Lincoln that makes it different
than a picture of George Washington
right if we understand those unique
features again then those are the things
that we can look for on the image on the
left but the first step is actually we
need to extract
right and Define what are we looking for
in each of those different classes right
and that's this this task of feature
detection right feature detection means
nothing more than understanding what
makes up one class different than
another class right so another way to
think about this is high level you know
imagine classification is is just done
by a two-step process number one
defining what you're detecting in your
images and then detecting those things
and if you detect enough of them then
you classify it as that object so for
example let's say for detecting you know
an image of a face you may look for
features like eyes o noses and ears if
you detect enough of those in an image
then you can have some confidence that
you're probably looking at a face on the
other hand things like houses are
defined by features of doors windows and
you know steps right if you if you look
for those things in images you can have
some confidence that you have identified
that if you successfully them so if
you're building an image classifier it
really boils down to nothing more than
this right you want to First Define your
features know what you're looking for
and then you look for those things and
if you find them then you can
successfully classify your image now
this is easier said than done right
because one way to solve this problem of
you know knowing what you want to detect
this is a big problem right because
knowing that you want to detect let's
say uh you know a face by Looking For
Eyes
now how do you detect eyes right it's a
recursive problem now you have the same
problem for detecting eyes that you had
for detecting faces and it's a
hierarchical problem and beyond that
it's also a problem where there are so
many different variations and so many
different adaptations so you can imagine
that you know faces look completely
different depending on your Viewpoint it
depends on your scale it depends on your
uh you know occlusions and and things
that are on different lighting and
illuminations and so on there's so many
different variations of a single image
in the in the pixel space right even
that same object taken with two
different cameras can appear very very
differently and this is why computer
vision is so difficult for computers
even though we take it all for granted
so our classification algorithms our
models that we build in this class they
have to be able to be invariant to all
of these different changes and all of
these different you know modifications
in our feature space in the things that
we're looking for in our image in order
to build a very robust pipeline if we
don't have that level of of adaptability
or uh invariance to these features then
we will not be able to be very robust in
our
detection so it all really actually
boils down to this last bullet here
right so the detection of these features
in order to classify is usually where
machine learning breaks down and deep
learning kicks in right so the machine
learning world makes it very very
difficult to detect these features Fe
because defining the features in machine
learning is a human process whereas in
deep learning we're going to say okay
we're going to Define these features
using data now what does that look like
using a neural network we can actually
start to say okay instead of me defining
as a human saying that I want to detect
Faces by looking for ears and eyes and
noses and then defining you know
recursively one more step how would I
find an error I would look for you know
like vertical lines followed by like a
circle underneath the line something
like this I'm not going to Define any of
that as a human I'm going to show my
image show my model a lot of images of
faces and it should be able to extract
what is unique about all of these images
of faces to help me disentangle all of
those images of faces from pictures of
cars let's say for example what are the
unique features the unique styles of
pixels that really differentiate these
two things and let's do that in a
hierarchical fashion the hierarchy here
comes from the layers in my model so the
depth of my model curates hierarchy and
every layer of depth that is composed on
top of each other allows us to inject
yet another layer of complexity or
expressivity like we saw yesterday
right now neural networks all they do is
allow us to learn this
hierarchy implicitly as opposed to
explicit definition instead of you know
by constructing them manually by humans
so in lecture one we learned about how
we could use fully connected networks to
do this type of task actually right this
shouldn't sound so new so far because
what we've been talking about is you
know simply just a composition of a
multi-layer network where every layer is
composed from the outputs of the prior
layer and every neuron in every get
every given layer is going to be simply
just connected to every input in that
prior layer so let's say we wanted to
use what we learned from lecture one in
this problem definition of what we're
seeing right now with computer vision
how could we do this let's actually try
it out so in our case right now unlike
lecture one now we have a
two-dimensional input previously in
lecture one we just had one-dimensional
inputs of features coming in to our
model but now we have two Dimensions
because we have an image so let's feed
that two-dimensional input into our
fully connected Network what would this
look like so already you know we we to a
problem right because what we have to do
here is we have to flatten our image our
two-dimensional image into a
one-dimensional input because all our
fully connected networks can handle are
one-dimensional inputs that's what we
learned about in lecture one so the only
way to you know use a fully connected
Network for an image processing task
would be to you know conform the images
into a shape that these fully connected
networks are capable of processing now
automatically hopefully everyone in the
audience you can all understand and
appreciate that absolutely 100% of the
spatial information that was previously
stored in this like very
rich uh very rich data type of an image
is now completely gone we've destroyed
100% of that spatial information by
flattening it and additionally we also
have a lot of parameters in this model
because every single Pixel in my input
layer is going to be connected to every
single neuron in my hidden layer and
that's only one layer and then you have
that you know depthwise many many times
so what we have is a extremely expensive
model for a actually a suboptimal
solution where we've thrown out a lot of
very valuable spatial information so
instead what we want to do here is you
know ask us ask this question on the
bottom right we want to ask this
question of how can we preserve and
leverage all of this really really rich
and unique spatial information present
in our data natively this is just part
of the data just to inform our Network
architecture we don't want to throw all
of this out for no reason we want to
leverage it and amplify our capabilities
with it so to do this let's actually
represent our two-dimensional image as
its true form right let's represent it
as a two dimensional array of pixel
values and one way that we want to use
now the spatial structure inherent in
our input is just to connect the input
pixels in patches to our neurons so
previous we had connected everything to
everything but in reality what we're
going to change now is say okay we'll
keep the two-dimensional structure but
we will only connect things in our input
pixel space to Output neurons that are
locally connected to each other in a
patchwise fashion so for example this
one neuron here will only see inputs
from a local connectivity structure of
patches of pixels from this patch here
on the left likewise you know this is
actually repeated across the entire
image this one patch that you see on
this top left hand corner will give rise
to this one output neuron but the very
next output neuron right next to it will
be defined or Guided by the next patch
shifted one layer over so everything is
not connected to everything now there is
still a lot of overlap in information
because you'll see that this neuron does
share a lot of input pixels with this
neuron right there is overlap there but
there's not complete uh you know fully
connectedness of the entire model and we
have successfully preserved a lot of
spatial information we have you know
enforced basically by definition that
you know the neurons close to each other
in the output layer will be derived from
pixels that are close to each other and
the input layer right and this is how we
preserve spatial
information now in practice what I what
we just talked about is nothing more
than an operation a mathematical
operation called a convolution so what
is a convolution let's first actually
think of this at a high level and
suppose we have what's here represented
as a 4x4 filter I'll use that word now
so a filter is just you can see this red
box that's going to be I'm going to call
that filter this is going to be
consisting of 16 so 4x4 pixel weights
right so you'll have the 4x4 pixels that
come from the image you will also have
four 4 by4
weights that are coming from the filter
and then this thing will slide over my
image step by step and apply the same
operation that we saw in lecture one
right element wise multiplication out a
bias apply a nonlinearity right no
difference here except everything is not
connected to everything you'll only do
this on the filter level right not for
everything but just for these 4x4
filters as you move across the image and
we're going to then just shift our
filter after every time that we do this
operation we'll shift it over and over
and over again let's say by one pixel or
two pixels over so that we can scan
across the entire
image so probably you're already
wondering right the next layer of
complexity on top of this would be to
really understand you know how the
convolution operation actually allows us
to extract these features so far I've
only defined how the convolution
operation works but how is it allowing
us to Define what we started D lecture
talking about is we want to Define you
know the the things that we should look
for in our image and how does a
convolution operation allow us to
extract that information so let's make
this concrete by just walking through a
couple examples so suppose we want to
classify or detect X's from a set of
black and white pixels uh so these are
just you know images they're
two-dimensional arrays of numbers in
this case they're not going to be gray
they will only be black and white so
everything must be either a plus one or
a minus one and I want to build a model
that can determine does the left side
equal the the right side right so I have
I have some examples of x's and I see
this new example on the right that is a
bit of a skewed rotated X it's not a
perfect X so I cannot simply just
compare the pixels on top of each other
I have to detect them more
intelligently right so what we want to
do is actually classify things on the
right if they are X's or not even if
they are shifted they're scaled they're
shrunk rotated deformed whatever the
case may be we want to be able to still
have a very reliable detection so let's
think about this so how can we do this
using the same principles that we just
saw we can do this by you know having
our model compare the X's not globally
but what if we did it on patchwise so if
we looked at for example the patches of
key interest the things that define an X
what defines an X actually there's only
a few things that define an X there's
the you know the diag is this way the
diagonal is this way and then a Crossing
between the two right so here you can
see three features that we're looking
for we're looking for a diagonal going
from left to right we're looking for a
diagonal going right to left and we're
looking for a crossing right and if we
do this comparison patchwise actually
you can see that even though these
features these things that we're
detecting they may be in different
places so the green diagonal is not in
the exact same place but it's very close
but we are able to detect those features
right and if our model can find rough
matches on the patch level then again
we've successfully detected you know the
things that define an X that allow us to
confidently say okay this is probably an
X at a global level as well if I can
find enough of these
patterns so each feature basically is
nothing more than like a mini image
right it's a miniature image it's a
small again two-dimensional array of
numbers no different than the Big Image
as well but what we're going to use is
or what we're going to do is use these
filters these convolutional filters to
detect and to define those patches right
so in this case the the patches or the
filters you know represent like we saw
diagonal lines and crossings of lines
these are all the important
characteristics of what make up an X but
in practice you know probably we're
going to want to capture these these
features for any type of new X that come
in right not just for this one X and
they will be robust to those types of
peration
so let's uh let I mean okay so this is
again like this is no different than
convolution but I'm going to keep kind
of hammering the point
home and start to actually introduce
some of the mathematical terminology as
well so that you can start to
familiarize yourself and how that
translates from the intuition that
you've seen on the past few slides to
the mathematics on the next few so what
does convolution do so the operation
that does exactly what we seen
illustratively in the past few slides is
convolution but what does it do it
preserves the spatial information that
is present within the images by breaking
the image the Big Image down into
smaller sub images and then searching
for key pieces of information across
those sub images and to do
this it does this by basically doing an
elementwise multiplication between what
it's looking for and the original image
at every point along the image so let's
say it's looking for this uh uh this
diagonal going from left to right right
so the filter is going to be the
following 3x3 miniature image that you
see on the top left this is a
threedimensional matrix or sorry a 3X3
Matrix a 2d Matrix but it's 3x3 and in
this case all of the entries uh here or
actually excuse me all of the entries
are minus one except for the diagonal
which is positive one this is because
we're looking for this diagonal line and
we element wise multiply this filter
this is what we're looking for we
multiply it with every patch in the
image so we'll start right here this is
the actual true patch right we'll look
right there we element wise multiply the
patch on the top left with the patch of
pixels coming right here and what we get
when we multiply every number on the top
left with every number in this green box
we'll get another 3x3 Matrix with
everything inside of it equal to one
because there's a perfect match between
every pixel in the top left filter with
every pixel in our bottom or our image
patch okay now that we have this element
the result of our element wise
multiplication we'll do exactly what we
saw in lecture one we take the result of
element wise multiply we add them all up
and we pass them through a nonlinearity
which we'll see
soon let's consider one more example
before moving on so suppose we want to
compute the convolution of this 5x5
image in green with this 3x3 filter so
to do this we need to convert uh or we
need to cover the entirety of our image
with this filter so we can do this by
sliding our filter not just one time
like we saw in the previous slide but
across the entire image step by step in
piece by piece and then at each step
doing the same operation element wise
multiplication and addition so let's see
what this looks like right so first off
we start with the top left corner we
place that yellow filter on on top of
the top left corner of our image we
element wise multiply that 3x3 patch
with all of the pixels in that 3x3
location and the entries of all of those
things and then we add up all the
entries after the element wi multiply
and we get the answer of four okay and
we're going to put that at this neuron
location so this is the output of our
top left neuron of the first layer of
our
Network then we slide over one step over
and we do this exact same process again
now there's a little bit less of an
overlap with this filter so what we're
going to see is that the output of this
neuron right next to it is three and we
can keep repeating this over and over
and over again until we slide over the
entire image and fill over the entire uh
all of the patches right and that's it
right so now what we have done is we've
defined an operation that can go
entirely from the input image on the
left given an input image and given a
patch or excuse me given a filter in the
middle Define what is the output layer
on the far right
yes what what's your choice of
filter
yep
exactly exactly so so far we haven't
talked about this at all right so all
we've said is we're defining an
operation given an image given a filter
how to compute the output answer and
you're completely right that the next
step is to say okay we want to learn
those filters because the filters
actually dictate how good of an output
answer you you get right that's actually
the tunable knob that will dictate this
entire process so we'll get to that in
the next part of the lecture yes great
question and actually to motivate this I
mean there's a couple things that you
can do you for a long time people have
hand engineered these filters you don't
even have to learn them right so if you
want to detect lines actually there's
like very good filter you don't need to
learn them it's like easy to design a
filter that can detect edges right this
is a filter that detects something going
from you know a very high brightness
value to a very low brightness value
it's a it's a type of derivative filter
right um and in fact people for many
years have hand engineered filters to
serve different types of purposes here
you can see some examples of different
filters so given an input image on the
left you can see you know these are hand
engineered filters for sharpening images
right hand engineered filters for
detecting edges or even stronger Edge
detection in the filters right if you
look at these filters you can actually
interpret them meaningfully right the
sharpening filter amplifies the the
center and then minimizes the edges
right and it's when it slides over the
patches you get that sharpening effect
the edge filter is again a form of a
derivative right kind of the opposite
effect so simply by changing the weights
of the filter as the question you know
uh implied you change entirely the
output of the of the next layer so the
filter has a lot of importance and
defining your filter can have a lot of
impact on looking for the things that
you really care about in your image so
hopefully now there's very clear
understanding not just like on how we
can compute the output of your
convolution but the importance of
preserving all of this spatial structure
and maintaining this through the
convolution
operation now now that we've gotten all
of this about you know the convolution
operation under our belts I think now
it's time for us to kind of transition
and say okay how can we yes go ahead
what does the overlap with the zero mean
because with one and minus one it made
sense the multiplication and then we get
one but when we have zero in the filter
and zero in the image what does that
comparison mean it's still a comparison
right so if we're looking for zero in
the image and zero so it would be Zer
times zero so it's like a it's like a
null passive information that you're
you're not looking for anything in this
location right so a zero in your filter
is almost saying that you're you it's a
it's a null piece of information in this
detection
right okay
so let's transition now to say okay how
can we understand not just what the
convolution operation does but how we
can start to define the inputs of the
convolution operation we already saw
obviously the input image is well
defined right we give this as as an
input to the model but what about the
the filters themselves and to do this
you know we can zoom out a little bit
and see where we're going to end up with
the entire convolutional neural network
let's consider you know a simple CNN a
CNN stands for a convolutional neural
network designed for image
classification so the goal here is to
learn these filters or these features
they're the same thing same the same
word two words just different same
meaning uh we want to learn those
features from image data so given a
bunch of images on the left hand side we
want to learn what are the filter or the
features that can disambiguate the
different classes that can come out on
the right hand side and there are three
main operations to cnns we already saw
one of them right so the first one is
convolutions Right convolutions define
this processing of patchwise operation
scanning across our images the second we
also have hinted at already it's the
nonlinearities that come after each of
our convolutions and then finally the
third piece is going to be pooling which
is just a down sampling operation that
allows us to you know grow our receptive
field right because if we're doing this
thing patchwise over the image we also
need to have different layers of you
know depth like how big our patches are
so by down sampling the image we're
effectively upsampling our patches in
the same
way so we can train our model on a set
of images and in training them what
we're going to do here is learn those
filters right right now we'll go into
more depth on this but when we Define
the model with this framework you know
all we're doing here is you know via
back propagation you define all the
operations you show the data and then
you can compute the optimal set of
weights or the optimal set of filters
that will optimally solve this task and
you do this through optimization so
let's go through each one of these
operations just to break this down even
further and see how this looks even more
concretely so let's dig even deeper into
the operation in the CNN and as we saw
before each neuron in our hidden layer
so the output of the first layer of our
model this is just going to be uh
computed with this weighted sum of our
inputs with our filters we apply a bias
we add up everything and we uh apply our
nonlinearity right now what's special
here is really I want to highlight this
point about the local connectivity the
local connectivity allows every neuron
in the hidden layer on the right to only
see this patch of input pixels on the
left right that's really important
because now we can really Define this
computation in math Right Moving from
all of the illustrations that we saw
before for a neuron in the hidden layer
its inputs are the neurons in the
patches in the previous layer so what
does that look like we can apply this
Matrix of Weights also we've been
calling them filters or features this is
a 4x4 Matrix in this case to do this
element wise multiplication we add the
outputs apply the bias and apply our
nonlinearity same stories before but
remember that our elementwise
multiplication and addition is nothing
more than convolution this is literally
just convolution that we talked about
earlier so this defines how neurons can
operate in this forward pass right but
within a convolution operate within the
convolutional layer we don't do this for
only one filter right every layer does
this for a whole set of filters so you
may say one layer is looking for a wide
variety of different types of edges it
may learn to look for those filters in a
you know a huge variety of edges and
then use that in the next layer in the
detection of those many different types
of edges so what you'll see is actually
in this slide you're not outputting just
one two-dimensional image of your filter
output you're outputting an entire
volume and the volume is derived from
not just one filter but now an entire
depth wise of filters and again this is
just one layer of your convolutional
neural network so one layer in your
network takes as
input again a volume but let's just call
it an image on the first layer it takes
as input your image and it detects n
different filters across that image it
gives you back a new volume which is
that image convolved with those nend
filters now the next step after we have
that volume as we saw before is we
compute or pass them all through our
nonlinearity this gives us our nonlinear
uh capacity and our expressivity that we
saw about and we care about in the first
two lectures we've been talking about
this um now a common application for
images in
particular is to use nonlinearities like
the reu activation the rectified linear
unit that you can see here why may you
want to do this is because uh the reu
the relu activation is basically a form
of a thresholding function right it gets
rid of all negative values it squashes
all negatives to zero and it keeps
everything positive as what it is so you
can you can kind of think of this as a
very intuitive meaning in computer
vision as a thresholding function right
so you just want to get rid of
everything and squash it all to be uh to
be positive
yes is to prepare the is that correct
but you don't do any fions
show last yes so the convolutional step
is to detect features within the input
and then the nonlinearities is to
increase the expressivity of those
detections right to make them nonlinear
detections now you don't do any more
convolutions in that first step but you
do have a deep network with many of
those layers so each layer does one
convolutional operation but then you
stack them
sequentially in depthwise
yes
so I
see no no so actually convolutions will
not necessarily change the spatial
resolution of the image at all right so
as you can see here right so I mean you
you it shouldn't need to change the
spatial resolution you can Implement
convolution in different ways right but
let's say in the example here right if
you pass over your filter typically
filters are much smaller than the size
of your image right so you'll have a
output size resolution that is roughly
the same size as your input image so
spatial resolution does not change as a
function convolution there's different
ways to implement it where that may not
be true we don't have to get into that
now but generally let's let's say it
like this uh you change the spatial
resolution to do this like let's say
multiscale operation of detection of
features so you do it one time and
you're detecting features at one scale
then you downscale this volume and then
you repeat it again the next time you
repeat it you're now detecting features
at a bigger scale because you've now
downscaled your volume right and this
this repeated process is what allows you
to detect features not just at the
original size but repeatedly across many
sizes right and and to also have those
features Compound on each other right
you may want your features to be
hierarchical so you want to say okay I
don't want to also only detect edges
very basic features but I want to
compose okay this Edge combined with
this Edge that can only be possible if I
take it from the output of the second
convolution not the first convolution
because you want compositions of
detections not just original
detections
yes so filters will always be different
because filters are learned they're not
defined by human right so filter So
within a single layer and across layers
filters will you know always be
different because they are going to be
randomly initialized and then optimized
by data so you'll always have a set of
filters when everything is said and done
you'll have a set of filters that will
have very little overlap with each other
throughout your network unless you have
a huge Network and you'll must have
overlap
basically exactly yes yes we'll see some
examples so actually let me let me go
forward a couple slides because this
will this will become much more parent
very
soon now we we touched on this already
but why do we do something after
convolutions we do this pooling
operation pooling is nothing more than
downscaling our dimensionality so after
every convolution we get an output set
of features that are detected we
downscale those features and then we
repeat the convolution again because the
next time we do the convolution we will
have now a larger receptive field
because our input image is now smaller a
common technique here to do this down
pooling is something called Max pooling
this is basically just saying okay
you'll take a a patch on the left hand
side and you'll pick the maximum value
from that patch and you'll put it in
this 2 by two and from a 2 x two you'll
put it in a 1 by one single maximum
value there's many ways to do uh pooling
and dimensionality reduction Max pooling
is only one way you can think of you
know ways that are less uh for example
uh harsh on derivatives Max pooling is
actually quite harsh because derivatives
don't pass through through you know 3/4
of the pixels by doing it like this
you'll only have a derivative through
the one pixel that activates the the
maximum imagine for example if you did
mean pooling instead you would have
stable gradients throughout the entire
patch instead so you can think of clever
ways to do other forms of down pooing as
well this is a it's a very open uh an
open Point okay but getting back to this
point of you know how do we interpret
and how do we see the filters that are
being learned actually you can as the
model trains or after the model trains
also you can visualize those filters
right so you can actually look at what
the convolution neural network what the
convolutional layers are optimizing
themselves to detect in this image so
here's an example of a convolutional
neural network uh learning to detect
faces and you see basically three
different levels of activations of
filters that are being activated by this
network in the beginning it's looking
for basically these edges like changes
in intensity value with different
directions As you move up in the model
you start to combine those filters and
those features together that are being
extract hierarchically and you start to
see actually facial features start to
emerge things like eyes noses and ears
like we were talking about before and
then you move up even more than this and
you start to see full structures start
to emerge right now with cnns the key
Point here that are different than
machine learning is that we didn't
Define any of these filters ourselves
we've learned these filters by showing
the model a lot of data and asking the
model hey what are the filters that
would be best for you to use in order to
get your accuracy of detecting faces as
high as possible right we only penalize
it when it's not able to detect faces
and we say hey keep changing your
filters until you're able to detect
faces better and this is what it comes
up with these are the filters of things
that it it's learned to detect in order
to do this task most
accurately so roughly actually now this
whole process is just broken down into
two parts right part number one is
extracting these features using those
learned filters and part number two is
going to be using those features to do
some form of detection right in this
case we're we're talking about facial
detection right so there are these two
pieces right how can we take the
features that are learned from phase one
on the model to inform our
classification phase right we can do
this with a function called a softmax
function what is a softmax function this
is just a function that takes our n
outputs at the last layer and squashes
them to have a sum to one why do we do
this because we're caring about
classification in this case and if you
want to classify something you have to
have a probability distribution what is
a probability distribution you have to
have mass that sums to
one okay so now let's put all of this
together in code to build our first
endtoend convolutional neural network we
can start by defining those two parts of
the network that we saw in the previous
slide first part is going to be the
feature extraction part this is the part
with all of the filters this is going to
have 32 feature maps you can see right
here so the first volume that comes out
of this first layer will have a volume a
depth of 32 features corresponding to 32
filters that have been learned in this
first layer we will downo the spatial
information and then we'll pass it onto
yet another convolutional layer that
takes those 32 features and learns
another 64 features on top of them at a
smaller Dimension we're going to then
flatten all of this now we can remove
our spatial information we go into a
one-dimensional space because now we're
actually wanting to make a
one-dimensional prediction on the
classification so we flatten everything
because we've already learned our
spatial information
and then we project to a softmax
function that allows us to predict our
probability distribution and allows us
to Output our final let's say 10 classes
right if we're trying to predict numbers
we would have zero to nine different
classes that's 10 total
classes in pytorch you'll see a very
similar uh very similar uh version of
this code right almost identically
mirroring what you saw before right
again we defined the convolutional
layers 32 followed by 64 features a
flattening operation that allows us to
enter the one-dimensional space and then
pass into our final output
dimensionality yes you say a few words
about how you choose that there's three
the patch is a size three and there's 32
feature Ms and layers te me that might
be more of an art than a
science yes yeah it it's an art but it's
also uh it can be guided by a lot of uh
uh intuition I guess so some intuition
that I'll provide is that typically you
want your features especially depending
on the task you want to start out quite
small but you want to preserve you want
to uh upsample spatial information as
you go deeper into the model so you want
to make sure that you understand first
of all what are the based on your image
based on your data set you want to
understand what you know looking at this
as a human what are the scale of the
features that this model should be
looking at to detect in the beginning
and at the end and those will define
basically those two resolutions right if
you're saying okay this is a massive
image that's let's say 2,00 by 2,000
pixels wide starting with 3x3 will be
too small right probably for most images
right it doesn't make sense to look at
that small scale if your image is 2,000
pixels wide but then there could be
other applications you know it's very
small and even 3x3 is is already like a
significant resolution in that image
right so it's very problem dependent as
well
yes yeah sorry you TR your your
allow not if it wasn't trained on faces
that were sideways this is a great
question so the question was uh you know
you train it on upright faces and then
you test it on faces that are turned
sideways and no it it we would not
expect it to do well in this case
because it has learned to detect
features of faces that were always
upright if it showed if it was shown
faces of both orientations then we would
expect it to do this successfully right
because we would expect that then it
should learn that faces can be in either
orientation so it should learn to you
know pick out those features in both
cases yes how would this approach work
for
projectable object for example if we
have a a gun bear or if we have a flue
simulation like how uh is it a at all or
um it's it's very problem dependent but
again we'd want to make sure that we can
learn it from data right so in even in
these more Dynamic cases right we'll see
some examples later in the in the deck
right of of these types of situations as
well but really we want to make sure
that these are all learnable from data
okay I'll I'll continue on just because
we we have a lot more to get through so
so far we've talked about cnns only for
classification tasks but in reality this
architecture extends far beyond
classification as well remember this
picture I showed you before I think this
is a really helpful picture because it
decomposes all cnns into two pieces
right a feature extractor and what we
previously saw was a classifier but
actually the second piece can be really
anything you could take a feature
extractor and use it with an object DET
tecture a classifier a segmentation
Model A probabilistic control model a
regressor model or so on right so in
this portion we're actually going to
look at what are all of the different
types of models that you can create just
by keeping this left side static use the
same feature extractor but now let's see
if we change the right hand side how can
we achieve a lot of very different
things and different types of model that
look very different but in reality
they're actually not so different at all
so in the case of classification we saw
this already right that that right hand
part of the network is nothing more than
a flattening operation over all of our
features and then we classify Over N
different classes right so here for
example um you you see an example
basically classifying binary right uh
diagnosis or not diagnosis this is the
case a paper that came out a few years
ago that basically demonstrated that CNN
can outperform Radiologists for these
types of diagnosis tasks uh for mamogram
images classification is an extension of
you know or classification let me say it
like this classification is a binary
problem typically or or a k set problem
it doesn't have to be two classes but it
could be K classes let's go one layer
deeper right so this is an image of a
taxi classification would be me saying
okay I input this image and I predict
taxi right how about object detection
object detection would be not just
predicting the Class Taxi but it would
be predicting a couple more things it
would be predicting a location of that
object a class for that object and an an
exact bounding box as well so it's not
just a location of the center of the
object it's a location of the entire
bounding box of that object and the
neural network has to tell us for not
just this one object but actually for
every object in this scene where it is
and also the class of that object so our
model needs to be extremely flexible in
order to do this type of task because
now it's not outputting just a you know
n sets of different outputs or k sets of
classes it will output if the scene has
only one taxi it will output one
bounding box but on the other hand if
the image has many objects right it
should be flexible enough to have many
outputs as well right so potentially
even these outputs could have different
classes obviously different locations
different uh you know uh different
numbers and ordinals as
well so how can we how can we accomplish
something like this this is very
complicated because number one those
boxes that we saw they can be anywhere
in the image they can be of any size and
they can be of any ordinality you can
have many many of them or you could have
no boxes actually in your image so let's
consider a very naive way first right
let's take our let's take our image on
the left hand side and let's start by
placing one random box over the image
right we'll just place a r we'll pick a
random box we'll put it over that image
and we will take that one random box and
we will pass it through a CNN that we
trained before right the feature
extractor and then we'll use that
feature extractor in the old way we'll
use it as a classification model even
though we talked all of this stuff about
you know making this very flexible we'll
just do this in the the old way first
but we will do this repeatedly we'll
keep picking random boxes and we'll say
okay is there anything in this box no
okay go to the next block and we'll keep
doing this over and over and over again
for enough boxes in the image we'll fill
up our entire image with a bunch of
classifications uh and simply discard
the box if there was no class detected
right now the there's a lot of problems
with this but the main one is that uh
there's way too many inputs here it
would be way too computationally
expensive and even for any practical
image you would never completely have
coverage over this image for all of the
types of boxes as well there's a
exponential explosion of number of boxes
with respect to resolution so you can't
simply do this type of naive method but
it gives us a good starting place so
instead of picking random boxes what if
we were a bit more intelligent and we
used aisti method so actually there was
pretty simple istics that we could build
that you know pick boxes around things
that look like they they have stuff
happening in that part of the image
right you don't have to know anything
about the image but just looking for
like blobs in the image you can create a
pretty decent heris that I just
identifies okay here's a here's a
potentially interesting piece of the
image I'll draw a box around it and pass
it through my classifier but still
actually this is still very slow because
I need to draw a lot of boxes for this
to work well and we have to feed in each
box independently to to our
classification model so it's very
brittle because now also we've
completely disconnected these two parts
of the problem we talked also a lot
about you know this end to-end model
that goes from feature detection to
classification but now I've broken that
model I've said okay I'm going to have a
proposer a box proposer model over here
that will propose boxes for me and I'll
have another classification model which
takes the boxes and processes them but
if uh you know ideally we want those two
models to share information in order to
predict good boxes it should know what
it's looking for at a high level
right so how can we solve this uh this
is one way that that you'll see and and
hear a lot about I'll I'll present it
very briefly so everyone is familiar
with it it's called a rcnn method right
so this is a regional CNN convolutional
neural network method what it attempts
to do is actually learn those regions
those boxes it attempts to learn it
within the same network as the model uh
you know that that classifies those
boxes so what does this mean this means
that we can start from the bottom we
start from our original image and we
have this you know region proposal
Network the region proposal Network
takes us input the image and it proposes
regions right it learns to extract
features of where are high important
highly or or importance uh or excuse me
high importance regions within the image
and this is used to define the boxes
that I use for the classification model
so I take those those regions I draw
boxes around them and then I pass them
through the same classifier using the
same features that were learned to
predict those regions so now there's
good alignment end to endend in this
entire process this requires only a
single forward pass to do this entire
model now so it's very efficient
compared to the models that we saw
before and it's very accurate because
it's actually sharing features along
this process
okay so in classification we saw that we
went One Step Beyond uh sorry we we
started classification then we went to
object detection goes One Step Beyond
classification we're go one step even
now Beyond object detection to
segmentation so instead of just
predicting boxes in the image what if we
predicted for every single Pixel in our
image a classification so now given an
image on the left hand side we want to
predict another image on the right hand
side with a classification value for
every single Pixel in that image right
so one example of this this is just
shown here this is a semantic
segmentation model semantic means that
we're learning the semantics right the
the the classes of every pixel in our
RGB image on the left hand side so here
you can see basically an image of a a
cow on the leand side being semantically
segmented into you know a few different
categories grass cow looks like trees
and sky in the in the background as well
so how is this done the first part of
this network on the left this is the
same feature extractor that you saw
before it's composed of convolutions
down pooling and nonlinearities the
second half is no longer a
classification model in the in the
one-dimensional case but now it keeps
everything in two Dimensions but it
upsample convolutions now so instead of
going convolution followed by down
sampling we do a convolution followed by
upsampling and again we learn the output
on the far right to be just a
classification of all of this so this is
nothing more than another classification
problem where we didn't down sample to
one Dimensions we just kept everything
in two dimensions and we uh used
upsampling instead of down
sampling let's see one final example so
let's say we want to learn a neural
network for autonomous navigation like
we saw in the beginning part of the
class for self-driving cars and let's
specifically say we want to learn a
model model that can go from raw
perception camera data uh to and and as
well as you know noisy Street View maps
let's say like what you would get on
your you know Google Maps on your phone
for instance right these are like bird's
eye view pictures of where the car is at
this point in time uh but they're just
pictures right and you want to feed both
of these into a neural network and allow
the neural network to learn how to drive
based on these two pieces of information
if you think about it actually this is
all that humans need to drive as well
right we only use two
and we use Google Maps if we go to a new
city we need some layer of navigation
information to drive through that city
and what we want is we want to directly
infer not just one steering wheel angle
where the steering wheel should be but
we want to infer a full probability
distribution again it's a it's a form of
a classification problem but now we're
not just predicting over K discrete
classes we're going to learn a
continuous probability distribution
because steering wheel angles are
continuous they can be anything from
what let's say like negative 180° to
positive 180° it's a continuous
value so this entire model can be
trained using exactly the same
techniques that we learned about today
we can pass through each of those uh
images on the left hand side through the
same types of modules that we've learned
about these are convolutional uh
convolutional layers followed by
nonlinearities followed by down sampling
right all of that gives us
features that come from each of those
images at the output we combine all of
those features in one dimension and then
we use that to learn the control
parameters of the vehicle and then we
regress on that with back propagation we
learn the features and we learn the
filters that are optimal for this type
of task by watching a lot of driving
data and learning okay what are the good
features that I should learn in order to
do this task successfully
right and you know in the end the the
result here is that you know this is a
autonomous car that uh has never driven
through this road before it can actually
drive brand new roads never seen before
without Maps this is something that's
actually very different than how you'll
see like whmo cars Google cars are quite
different than this because they require
to drive through a city once human
driven before they can drive autonomous
right humans don't operate like this
right we can be put in a brand new city
for the first time and we can
successfully drive in that City without
ever seeing it before right and this
type of model is also able to exhibit
that type of
behavior so the the impact I'll I'll
just conclude briefly right because the
impact of cnns has been very wide
reaching Beyond these examples that
we've talked about today but hopefully
what you can appreciate is that in all
of the examples actually they all come
from these exact same fundamental
techniques right it's Evolutions the
operation itself its feature learning to
to learn those filters and then some
amount of some combination of either up
sampling down sampling to to preserve or
modulate spatial resolution so I'd like
to basically you know summarize now all
of this so first we considered uh you
know a lot of the origins of computer
vision we took a you know uh we took
some some history back through how
images are represented they're
represented as these two-dimensional
arrays of values we we you know went one
layer beyond that to say okay how could
we learn from those two dimensional
arrays using convolutions to extract
meaningful pieces of data and then
formulate that into full networks not
just a single convolution operation and
then many applications with that
backbone of convolutional layers many
applications that can be spun off very
easily of different types of models from
that point anything from classification
to detection to segmentation and know
many others as well I'll pause there and
uh I'll transition to Ava who will be
talking about uh generative deep
learning as well which is actually how
we can there a brand new uh thing that
we haven't talked at all about in this
class is not just how we can learn from
data but to learn from data to generate
more data right it's a it's a very
different it's not only a different type
of model but completely different
Paradigm than everything that we've seen
so far in the class so we'll take a
couple minutes we'll do a transition and
then we'll continue in probably 2
minutes thank you