Okay, then let's uh get started. Uh so
from the week uh from the last week we
are discussing some kind of the ideas in
terms of like how we can apply some kind
of the pre-trained uh diffusion and the
flow models for some kind of the really
broader the applications especially in
terms of like injecting some kind of the
guidance uh in the generation the the
the period. So those are some kind of
the some techniques that we discussed
the last time
and for the discussion of the infrance
time degeneration like one thing that I
briefly mentioned uh was about basically
this technique that I called the uh
division the synchronization which was
basically the case that we are making uh
some kind of the data in the other forms
like this like the some 3D things or
some kind of panoramic images and many
other things like those things and the
panorama images we also have seen those
kind of the any examples for the
synchronization in terms of that uh
these are basically all the examples
that we are making some kind of a data
uh in the form that know we didn't have
the data in the training of the
diffusion model right uh so those are
all the cases that uh we are basically
making some kind of the data not the
form that has been used for the training
of the diffusion models but the data
that can be actually mapped to the the
data that we have seen during the
training uh in a way that we are
basically performing the den noising the
process from the multiple perspectives
like the simultaneously in a way that
the these are basically integrated uh in
the canical space that we defined last
time. So this was kind of the
interesting the idea in terms of that uh
if you have some kind of the any print
pre-trained the model then this kind of
the pre-trained model can be used not
only to generate the data that we have
seen during the the training time but
also for the other data that can be
mapped to the data that we have seen
during the training. Uh so this is also
kind of the one specific kind of example
in terms like you know uh widening kind
of the the range of the applications of
the pre-trained and the division and the
flow models and speaking to uh this
direction we are also going to briefly
discuss some kind of the uh some very
practical and the simple idea which is
called the core distillation dampling
and this idea also can be applied to the
many other cases as well.
So here the basic kind of thing is that
as we uh also discussed from the
beginning of like this class uh the
diffusion models can be applied not only
to generate the images and the videos
but into the uh to generate some kind of
the many uh the diversity type of the
data like the audio or the molecular
structure for the weather forecasting
for the many other things. But here the
basic question is that the how much data
do we need to produce some kind of the
realistic the data.
Actually this is really very practical
question that I also received multiple
times when I also basically uh discuss
like making some kind of models for the
many the people especially in the
industry. uh they typically they easily
very ask like so how much data do we
need uh to make some kind of the good uh
the diffusion model or some kind of
other model
and obviously there's no clear answer
right uh can you see like so you also uh
train your own the diffusion pool model
right for the alo for the image the
generation challenge did you feel that
the amount of the data uh was like
sufficient to make some kind of the good
quality of This
did you get any sense of like how many
that you need uh to train some diffusion
model for some specific type of data?
I mean if you really try to apply those
kind of the ideas for the uh the
generative models to produce like many
other the types of data then this is
really some practical problem that you
will face like let's say like we want to
make some kind of the diffusion model
for some kind of the medical imaging uh
some kind of the images like that are
having some kind of indication of some
kind of the disease for example uh for
some kind of the to train some other the
the AI models for some diagnosis for
something then how many how much the
data do you need?
Uh so this is really kind of the
uh non-trivial the question in terms of
like how much kind of the amount of the
data will basically guarantee uh the
quality of the outputs.
So I'm not going to say any kind of
answer for that. Uh but obviously uh
more is better right in all the cases if
we have some kind of more amount of data
uh that would be much better to in terms
of improving the quality of the outputs.
The problem is that for many cases for
many many applications uh we would not
have some kind of the that kind of the
big scale of the data uh for the images.
The reason why we are seeing some kind
of the really good quality of the
outputs would be not only because of
some kind of the advances of the generic
models that we are seeing but also
because of the scale of the data right
uh for the images we have seen that
there are like billions of the images.
Uh for the videos we also might have
some kind of the another billions of the
data but how about the other things for
the audio or some kind of molecular
structure or some motions here for many
other things. uh will we have some kind
of such kind of big scale of the data.
So that's kind of the motivation in
terms of like how we are going to uh
best leverage some kind of apply the
knowledge that has been learned from
some kind of the pre-trained uh image
models for the video models in terms of
like using this information to produce
the many other things because for the
image generation the video generation
for those like the diffusion models we
know that like billions of the data have
been used
uh and these models basically can
produce like very high quality of
outpost and also in the very wide rev
diversity. So here the question is that
how can he reverse those kind of the
information uh to produce any other
things as well. So that's kind of the
the basic the idea.
So for example like how about those kind
of like 3D kind of shapes. So basically
we can find those kind of 3D shape in
some kind of the online repositories for
those kind of data. But obviously it
would be very hard to basically uh
collect some kind of good quality of
like such kind of 3D models in the scale
of the billions right. So if we really
see some kind of a skill of the public
data set both for the 2D data and for
the 3D data then we can see that for the
2D images as we as I mentioned before we
have some kind of skills of the five
billions of the images
but if we see the scale of the uh 3D in
the public 3D the biggest one is still
kind of the 10 million. So you can see
the kind of the difference of the scale
like the five or six billion uh is kind
of like corresponding to the like
similar to the population in the world
right uh compared to that the 10
millions uh it's kind of similar to the
population the people in the soul for
example so very small scale so given
this kind of the why I mean 10 million
is not very small right but compared to
this scale with the 10 million of deer
uh can we also produce like really high
quality of the outputs and also in kind
of the big the the the the range of the
diversity.
So here the question is then uh how can
you still produce those kind of the 3D
the models uh using some kind of the
diffusion and the flow models. So if we
consider making those kind of the images
uh using the like whatever some kind of
the image design models these days using
the nano banana whatever then you can
really try this whether the image
diffusion model can produce like those
kind of images and typically it works
quite well right because of the fact
that they basically have been trained
with the really intra scale of images.
So from the images in the inter skill uh
maybe there will not be exactly this
image but basically much more the
diversity and this kind of the diversity
of the samples that we have uh in the
distribution are basically giving us the
giving the model to the sense of like
how those kind of images can be
degenerated right but even with the kind
of the 10 millions of the shapes can he
still also make some this kind of the
imageable some 3D shapes so So that's
kind of the questions.
So what we are going to briefly discuss
for today is that how can you reverse
the power of the pre-trint the image
diffusion model or some kind of otherly
the diffusion flow models in a way that
they can be also used to produce like
many other things like making this kind
of some imageable some 3D shapes not
using some kind of the exactly the
direct some 3D samples but using the 2D
samples that have been used uh to train
the diffusion and the flow models
and this kind of technique It can be
applied to the many other things not
only for this 3D but also let's think
about some kind of the vector images for
example what are some kind of some some
CAD format
is there anyone who major is in the
industry of design
or
other field or mechanical engineering uh
for the people in the the the design
field and also some CAD committee uh
they would want to make some kind of
some those kind of the 2D or the 3D data
not represented as some kind of the
pixels and the points but you know like
more the structural way with some kind
of the some stroke information or the
many other things but obviously for
those kind of the more the some
structural data it's really hard to
basically expect to have the the data in
this scale be billions. Uh so here the
question is that how can you also
produce those kind of data with the very
large diversity uh not exactly just like
using the samples in the this the uh the
data domain but based on the the priors
uh that know we could learn from using
the uh that has been learned from the uh
the image and the uh the diffusion flow
models.
So this is kind of the basic question
here. So what we are going to briefly
discuss for today is that you know some
kind of the techniques in terms of like
leveraging the uh the some knowledge uh
from the image division models that has
been trained with the uh with the
intrakill the the image data set to
produce like many other some kind of
visual of the contents and this idea
also basically can be applied uh to not
only to gen some kind of the visual
content uh but for the many other things
so I didn't bring some kind of examples
here but you can also find some examples
in the internet basically using this
kind of the idea to produce some kind of
the audio or some kind of the motion or
many other things.
So basically the problem setup here is
that uh we assume that we are making
some kind of a data that has some kind
of a rendering function and here
basically the meaning of the rendering
is that uh is basically any kind of some
predefined function uh that can be that
is basically mapping the data that we
want to generate uh into the form of the
image. So let's say this like set theta
represents some kind of the visual the
contents it doesn't need to be visual
things but I mean for the given the
pre-trained uh image diffusion model
let's say we want to make some kind of
the dual representation data here uh
which can be mapped to the some kind of
the images from the specific viewpoint
of the scene. So let's say we have any
kind of those kind of the rendering
function right so this is something that
we want to generate and when you choose
some kind of the perspective like seeing
this kind of the content we can map the
content into a form of the image using
this pre defined function G so for any
case that we can define those kind of
rendering function uh how can you
basically produce the the setup using
the pre-trend image diffusion model
and as kind of the some off topic I'd
like to briefly introduce this idea of
the neural rendering. How many of you
are familiar with the neuro rendering?
Heard about this? Uh yeah and this is
also quite uh interesting idea that has
been uh uh quite popular in the area of
the graphics and the vision but you
don't need to know any details for this
but here the basic idea is that uh we
want to somehow produce those kind of
some 3D output uh from the collection of
the images from the all different views.
So the input is the collection of the
images and here the question is that how
can you basically generate uh something
that is representing the 3D uh the kind
of the object we're seeing here uh in a
way that we can basically render those
kind of reconstructed output from the
any arbitary view
and this is like very classical problem
in the graphics and division. Uh but the
interesting the point in the new
rendering is that those kind of
reconstruction can be done by the neuron
net. Uh so that's kind of the the
reconstructing using the neuronet
network means that actually we are
having the the neuron network as the
representation of like those kind of 3D
things in a way that this can be like
rendered into the form of the image.
So without like any having any any kind
of details uh so this is kind of the
basic kind of the setup of the rendering
and there also bunch of the technique in
terms like achieving those kind of the
goal. uh you can see actually quite
interesting results like this. So this
is like one example. Uh this would look
like a video but actually this is not a
video. Uh this is basically generated
the the the images uh in the the the in
the sequence. So basically here the idea
is that we are having lots of images of
this scene and doing some kind of 3D
construction and as we basically play a
game we are basically navigating this
kind of some virtual this 3D space. Uh
so yeah this is really just like
randomly basically navigating this space
in a way that we are seeing some kind of
the uh some of the details here and you
can see that uh the reconstruction is
not perfect here uh because of the lack
of the information. So as you can see
here we are seeing some kind of the
black the sky. Uh the reason why we are
seeing the black sky there is that we
don't have the the images there right.
uh so that's kind of thing but this is
kind of the examples in terms of that uh
we are having some kind of the loss of
the images with some kind of the known
the viewpoint information
and based on that we want to basically
uh reconstruct the 3D representation the
data here
and without like know I mean knowing
some kind of the details here especially
in how we define the rendering function
and how we also have some kind of
representation for this uh the basic
idea of the the reconstruction. The
reconstruction is that uh basically we
are performing the gradient descent with
this specific gradient. Uh so basically
we do have some kind of the
representation and also the rendering
function and what we want to do is that
we want to basically update the data
here uh in a way that basically
minimizing the L2 loss here.
very basic idea right uh nothing but
basically minimizing the L to loss for
the all the perspectives where basically
we have some kind of the given images
so this is like very high level the idea
for the neural rendering so many other
kind of things then uh what be the
question here so if we have this kind of
the technique that we can reconstruct
some kind of 3D things then which
questions that are going to ask
especially if you want to apply apply
those kind of technique for some kind of
real applications.
For example, like uh how fast the
reconstruction, how much the computation
that we will need uh to reconstruct
this, right? And also how fast the
rendering would be those are some kind
of questions that we can ask, right? And
how much kind of the big scale of some
kind of 3D things that we can
reconstruct based on this technique. Can
you just like reconstruct a single
object or some kind of scene or like the
skill of the city or something? Uh the
skill might be also interesting factor
and how can you deal with some kind of
the some moving object. uh if some
objects are basically moving while
basically taking those kind of images
then can you also uh handle those kind
of some kind of movement of the object
in the scene those are some kind of
questions right do you have any other
questions
actually this idea has been uh
considered for a while uh to apply this
for some kind of the online shopping
mall uh in a way that for some kind of
products that know the people we're
selling we can basically put not only
the images but some something like a 3D
in a way that the customer basically can
see the object by rotating it uh in the
web browser right so these kind of
things has been discussed for many
applications
uh one of the kind of the big the
bottleneck uh in terms like you know
applying this technique for the many
application is that actually we need
quite many number of images. So that's
also the one question I mean how many
images should we have to make some kind
of the good quality uh of the some kind
of 3D here.
So that that's kind of the some real
question
and typically for those kind of 3D
reconstruction if we reconstruct a small
object and more or less like 100 images
would be okay for the techniques that we
can typically use some kind of code uh
in the internet but let's say like if we
want to basically apply those kind of
techniques uh for the online shopping
mall then people would want to basically
quickly do this kind of 3D construction
obviously the computation should be
super fast and also these recon
reconstruction should be done with some
very some like few number of images. So
when you just like take some kind of
photos like 10 photos of the object then
you should be able to still get some
kind of good quality of the outputs
right then can you also go some kind get
some kind of good 3D the outputs or only
from the 10 images
or the five images or three images
uh so this is kind of the question so
what's the kind of the limit in terms of
the know reducing the number of the uh
required the input images. So can he
also make this kind of the technique in
a way that uh we can produce those kind
of 3D outputs only from the very few
number of images. So this was kind of
the the very basic demotivation
and for that uh one of the kind of the
early the idea uh relatively early idea
in the 2021 uh was that uh we are also
reing some kind of the priority
knowledge from some kind of the
foundation model uh especially this like
the clip model. Uh
does everyone know the clip model here?
Everyone should know right. So clip is
like the most popular model that is
basically about uh some kind of the the
the relationship between the text and
the image right. So if I briefly
introduce the clip for some of you who
are not familiar with this uh is
basically some kind of the uh some
embedding some kind of the function in
terms of that we can uh basically map
both the image and the text into some
kind of certainty embedding space. Uh so
the role of the embedding space is that
now we can measure some kind of the the
degree of the alignment of the image and
the text uh in this specific embedding
space. So it's basically very highly
measured the embedding space and if we
measure the distance over this kind of
the high measure embedding space after
mapping both the image and the text then
we can see how close how much they are
basically aligned each other how much
the image this input image here can be
basically described with the given the
input text. So it's basically some kind
of the measure of the uh the alignment
between the image and the text.
Then how can you use this kind of the
information uh to do some kind of the
few shot the reconstruction uh to do
some kind of reconstruction with few
images.
This is like all some very practical the
idea theory here.
So here the kind of simple the idea is
that um so let's see this kind of the
example that we are reconstructing this
like the bulldozer the image here uh but
let's say like we only have like five
images or the three images but the thing
is that for the bulldozer image uh here
uh from whatever the perspective uh we
see the object this object will be
bulldozer right consistently bull from
the any perspective So basically what we
can do is that uh for those like the
perspective that we have the images only
three or the five for those cases uh we
can still use the L2 loss uh basically
for the back propagation basically
matching the rendered image uh with the
basically image that we have. uh but
from the many other the perspectives
basically what we can do is that uh we
can basically simply uh check the
alignment between the rendered image and
also the text prompt that we have
because we know that the the object will
be user right so now we basically define
the uh the gradient not as kind of the
alto loss between the two images but as
kind of the gradient of the distance uh
in the embedding space. So that's kind
of very practical the idea in terms of
that we are liberating some kind of the
prior knowledge of the pre-trained the
click model in a way that we can do some
kind of view shot the rec construction
make sense
like just like very simple the idea
then here the question might be is that
then how many how how much we can reduce
the number of the the images that we can
be that are basically required for this
3D construction using this kind of
technique.
So with some kind of the engineering
actually the thing is that uh when we
start to use this kind of the clip the
the priority knowledge then we can
reduce the number of images to the 10 or
the five even to the three uh even to
the single image uh it's possible that
we only have the one single image and
basically for all the perspective we are
using the clip loss for the back
propation
but then even the extreme case is that
what if we do not have any images. What
if we only use the uh the clip loss uh
for the reconstruction?
So this is kind of the the first kind of
the example in terms of like doing some
kind of the zeot reconstruction.
So zeot reconstruction sounds quite
weird in terms of that we don't actually
have any images. We only have the text
prompt. Uh so that's kind of thing. So
without having any kind of images what
we are going to do is that here we are
doing some kind of like 3D uh
reconstruction now actually it becomes
not the reconstruction because there's
no images but it's more about the
generation right uh only from the text
prompt what we are going to do is that
we perform the same thing in terms of
reconing this but now the back
propagation is done with this kind of
the distance in the embedding space and
the question is that would this still
work
and this works in some extent but
obviously the quality is not very good.
So these are basically some quality of
the the outputs that we could see uh
some very early version of the 3D
generation. Uh
so now we are seeing lots of the many
good quality some 3D models. So this
quality looks really really bad. uh but
at the time of the 2022 I think it looks
quite interesting in terms of that we
are seeing some kind of the uh some
armchair uh with the shape of the
avocado or some kind of pumpkin or
something Pikachu. Uh so there those are
some kind of the examples in terms like
doing some 3D not the reconstruction
anymore but it's more about like 3D
generation uh using only the text pump.
So this was kind of the first case of
like seeing some kind of 3D generation
uh using some kind of only the 2D prior.
So this was kind of the interesting
example in terms of that. Now we can
also produce some kind of something like
a 3D uh not having any kind of 3D data
as some kind of training the data that
we have uh but only using some kind of a
2D prior uh that are also learned from
the uh pre-trained model.
So this is kind of the interesting the
examples for that.
But here the question is that but
instead of like using the clip
uh can we use some kind of a pre-trained
uh image diffusion models uh to
basically do the kind of the same thing.
So this is kind of the some the the
basic question here
and can you guess how we can basically
use the pre-trained uh image division
models instead of click for the 3D
construction in this case.
So as I said uh while I just show some
kind of examples of the 3D
reconstruction actually you can see that
this is quite the general idea that can
be applied to the many other cases
right. So basically we want to make some
kind of data that can be mapped to the
other form of the data that have been
used for the training uh some foundation
model. So without really having some
kind of the some data samples uh for the
format that we want to generate uh using
some kind of the priors of the data some
kind some sort of the mapping from those
kind of the the data and also the prior
that have been learned from the uh some
pre-trained the foundation the models
how can it produced those kind of
things. So this is kind of the basic the
setup
and now we want to use not the clip uh
but the pre-trained image diffusion
model uh for doing doing this kind of
thing. Any ethos how we can do this?
>> Denoing projection as the ground tring
process.
that moving through that.
uh so the couple of the issues would
that that direction might be is that so
if we try to perform the denoing process
with some kind of the random the the
projection from the some random output
would be is that we don't know whether
that's so basically the projection of
some kind of the the data that we want
to generate should be is some kind of
intermediate data points that have been
seen in the training of like this model
right but would this be true for most of
the cases it do not right. So that's the
thing but that's kind of good try. You
can really try that. uh that might
actually uh that's kind of like worth
trying but for most of cases it would
not work because like if you try to
basically uh map some kind of some data
points into the some kind of images
uh for any kind of randomly the output
then this kind of the projection would
not be some kind of intermediate data
points that the our neuron net has been
seen has seen during the training. So
basically the XT that we are talking in
the division model should be something
that is really coming some coming from
the realistic data point with the
forward process right if the XT is not
something that look like the kind of
some noisy version of the clean data
that we have then the the noise
prediction will not work uh so that's
kind of one thing
any other
I mean actually there's no kind of a
clear answer for this. So this is really
kind of the
uh the case that we want to use the
generator as kind of a discriminator.
So basically for the generator basically
what we want to do is that for example
for the text to image generation we want
to take the text as the input and make
some kind of image as the output right.
So that's basically some kind of
blackbox kind of things for the digital
model. But the thing is that now what we
need is basically having some kind of
discriminator discriminator is taking
the both the text image and kind of the
input and basically checking their kind
of the alignment between these two and
giving this score for that or some kind
of a distance. So the clip model can be
easily used as some kind of
discriminator. But here the question is
that how we can use the pre-trained the
gent model as kind of discriminator as
well. If we had a GAN uh instead of
diffusion model then it could be much
easier because you already have some
kind of discriminator. Uh but for the
diffusion model we don't have the
discriminator right.
So the
very basic idea some kind of practical
the idea uh without having any kind of
some good theoretical explanation like
in terms like why it works uh is that
the simple idea in terms of using the
preision model for this case is that so
if we recall the loss function of the
diffusion model the loss function is
basically defined as basically the
matching the noise the here right uh so
if we have some kind of pre-train in the
future model. Uh this will be the the
case that this loss has been converged
right. So which means that for whatever
some kind of the clean the data point of
the XO uh we going to we can expect that
these loss will be close to uh some kind
of some small number right some
something very small.
So actually the basic idea is that we
are directly reversing the loss function
of diffusion model. So what basically
this mean is that uh let me go to the
yeah so that's good thing so if the
training has converged the loss for the
realistic the data point xj will be
close to some small value so actually we
are going to use this loss function as
the measurement of the alignment uh so
that's kind of some very basic the idea
so in the pre previous case the previous
cases uh if use the the alto loss as
kind of the uh the loss function or some
kind of the clip distance as kind of
loss function. Uh now we are going to
directly use the loss function of the
diffusion model while basically putting
the render the output as some kind of
the uh the x the zero the point here.
So
like more the procedurally basically
what we are going to do is that uh for
any kind of the given the random the the
data point from the the perspective uh
we first render uh the 3D representation
uh into the the data point here
and then uh what you do is that if you
recall how we train the diffusion model
uh we basically perform the forward
process basically adding some kind of a
noise basically making the intermediate
point of the XT here and predict the
noise
using our pre-trained noise predictor
and you know measure some kind of
difference with the noise that we added
in the board process and basically
computing the L2 loss and performing the
back propagation.
Uh that's kind of the basic idea. So
what you can see is that uh we changed
basically nothing but we only changed
the loss function that we are using
here. So in the 3D reconstruction we use
the L2 to loss with the given images for
the clip based reconstruction we use the
clip loss for the uh yeah clip distance
as loss function here and now we are
using the loss function of the diffusion
model directly as kind of the measure of
the alignment here. So that's kind of
the very practical and some kind of the
some some simple the idea.
So again uh there are basically the four
steps. We basically run render the
visual contents uh and then basically
performing the fourth uh the process and
the predicting the noise using the noise
predictor and the back prop uh you know
way to basically minimize kind of the
the alto difference of the noise here.
So here basically one thing is that uh
since we have some kind of the
differentiable the rendering function g
here the back propagation of like this
also can go all the way uh to the clean
data point and also into the uh the
visual content here. So that's kind of
key thing. So which means that our
rendering function obviously should be
differentiable in this case.
it is clear.
So this is kind of the basic idea like
one small thing is that uh if we try to
perform the back propagation for the L2
difference between the prediction noise
and the noise here then using the chain
rule actually uh this gradient can be
decomposed into these three parts right.
So the difference between the the noise
here and the the jacobian uh to the
noise predictor with respect to the XT
here and also the XT uh and also the the
data of the XT with respect to the uh
the final individual content the the
data here. Basically there are the three
parts right. Uh which competition will
be most expensive here?
to perform that.
Should we fix the parameter of error
predictor?
>> Fix the parameter of the uh this. Oh
yes. Oh yeah. Obviously this is the case
that we are uh not basically changing
the parameters of the noise predictor
using the pre-trained uh diffusion model
we perform this. So the back prop yeah
that's al kind of thing uh here the
thing is that uh sorry I think there are
some kind of the some notation issue so
because I'm using the setup for the
older places sorry uh so actually this
back propagation should not be to the
the parameters of the noise predictor
but to the actually the visual content
here so I'm going to fix the notation
here
but you can also see that this becomes
basically taking the derivative uh for
the rendering function in this case and
also taking the derivative with respect
for the the noise predictor for the all
the parameters of the the the neural
network of the noise prediction right so
actually this is the kind of the most
expensive the part in terms of the
computation in terms of performing the
back propagation
some also without any kind of a theory
some kind of very practical the idea is
that uh even when you do not perform uh
the the compute to the Jacobian here
basically assuming this jacobian is kind
of the one uh still it basically works
some extent so that's kind of this
practical the idea so we can somehow
ignore the jacobian the part here in
terms of computing the gradient and also
running the back propagation
and the reason like we want to omit this
is that this is the most expensive part
in terms of the computation because we
need to compute the uh gradient for the
all the parameters of the the new
network right so we want to skip this in
terms speeding up the computation.
So this becomes up the the final
gradient for the the bure content the
data here and based on that uh we can uh
make some kind of some 3D the outputs
and actually either we have the Jacobian
parts or we do have the uh do have the
jacobian or do not have the jacobian the
parts actually the quality is not very
different. So this is some kind of the
quality of the output the three
generation without the jacobian the part
and also this is the output with the
jacobian part. So you can see that
actually the quality is kind of similar.
The only difference is that uh without
basically skipping while skipping the
jacobian part we can speed up uh the
computation and also we can actually the
computation is also kind of similar. The
good thing is that we can save the the
memory uh in terms of the computation.
So that that's kind of the the things.
So now you can see why this technique is
called this core distillation. So
basically the thing is that uh we want
to distill the knowledge learned by the
pre-trained uh diffusion model in a way
that we can produce like many other
things while the knowledge is basically
distilled in the form of the the noise
of the score. So that's basically why
this is called the score disting
sampling and this idea can be applied.
So actually these are all the 3D the
outputs. I don't have the videos for
this but you can see that actually these
are all the outputs and actually this is
quite interesting to see right I mean
can you imagine to have like those kind
of 3D model in the internet
uh flock wearing sweater and ghost
eating a hamburger. So those are really
some uh some very um interesting some
imaginable some 3D outputs but it's
really hard to expect to have some 3D
models for those kind of things right
but still we can produce like those
things uh because we are leveraging the
uh the strong prior pre-trained uh image
models that has been trained with the
billions of images
and more examples
uh with the
Some Yeah,
something like Yeah. Many kind of weird
in the output, right?
Playing some games with some dogs here.
Whatever. Yeah. So many interesting
outputs.
So this is basically the technique that
can be applied to the any data type the
type that can be basically mapped into
the data space of the pre-trained
individual model. So maybe you can think
about some kind of the other the
applications not only for the
pre-trained uh image diffusion model but
also for the molecular for the many
other things there might be also some
kind of interesting the applications for
the this kind of technique.
So as I also briefly mentioned at the
beginning uh some of the applications
for this is that this can be also
applied to the uh to generate some kind
of the vector images for those kind of
the some uh some stroke informations of
the the vector images. Uh it's really
also hard to make some kind of the
billion scale of the data set and we can
use this technique to produce like those
kind of things and we also seeing many
of the some 4D examples as well. Uh so
these are also some examples that we are
now using the pre-trained uh video
diffusion model not the image diffusion
model uh to produce many kind of some
interesting the for the outputs as well
and also for many kind of some visual
content editing not only for the
generation uh given those kind of the
already generate some kind of the some
uh 3D content if we want to make some
kind of the some uh some modification uh
if you just strictly use some kind of
the physical the priors In terms of
making those kind of deformation then we
might get some kind of the some
artifacts like this
and by using some kind of the priors of
the image different model we can also
fix this kind of some artifacts and
making some more realistic the outputs.
So this is kind of like very easy idea
and there are lots of the code in the
internet. So I recommend you to try to
run those kind of things and see what
you can generate and also I recommend
you to try not only for the generation
but also for the editing. uh we can also
try those kind of things and also this
idea can be applied not only for some
visual content and also many other types
of the data as well and but when it
comes to basically you know uh
speaking to like the making some 3D
using the 2D prior uh what would be some
kind of the some failure cases if you
only have the 2D information to make
some 3D.
So this is basically the case that we
want to make some kind of some full like
3D output while the information the
prior knowledge that we have is some
kind of the partial observation right
not the full observation. So if we want
to generate some kind of the full the
outputs or using some partial
observation what's would be some typical
the failure cases
can you imagine some failure cases
actually this is also kind of the case
that we going to face for many
applications right uh while we might
want to make some kind of some like some
entirely outputs the information that we
have might be some kind of some partial
observations for many of the cases.
So one specific I mean the the inverse
problem was also such kind of the case
uh but not only for like the training
the model but only for the generation
some single outputs uh that was also the
case that we only have some kind of the
partial observation. So how can he
producing some like the entire the
outputs that can match the the pos
observation right but in terms of like
uh producing some full outputs with the
priors of the some pos observation the
typical ferotic cases would be something
like this.
Let me play this.
Can can you see the value here?
Did you check how many faces those
characters have?
Obviously not one, right? Multiple
really faces.
So this was some kind of the very
typical defailure cases in terms of that
the rendering of those kind of the 3D
outputs from the specific perspective
might look okay uh from some
perspectives but if we see the full
structure that doesn't look like some
kind of realistic data point right
basically having some multiple de faces
uh this is some kind of a better the
quality of the outputs with some kind of
more autoy technique but you can still
see that there are some failure cases
this uh with the two masses here and
also yeah some part of the face is kind
of weird right the occlusion is
basically not correct. So this is kind
of the issue in terms like you know we
are making some poor outputs maybe some
partial the priors. So this basically
means that uh while we can somehow
leverage the prior of the image
diffusion models to produce like many
other things then we might still need to
have some the prior of the data itself
for that specific domain in terms of
giving some kind of the some information
about the some global structure of the
data. So still there are some kind of
limitations for that
and also one practical kind of thing is
that uh if we want to produce some kind
of the realistic the outputs then those
are all the cases that we are doing
still like some text condition some kind
of generation
and if we want to get some kind of the
clean the outputs then you can play with
those kind of things typically you need
to have some very high the CFG weight
the classified free guidance the weight
uh basically increasing is basically is
that we are basically narrowing down
into some kind of the very uh small
scope of kind of the the the
distribution of the data that is really
perfectly aligned with some kind of a
given the uh the text prompt uh which
means that uh if you need to increase
the safety rate that means that you're
going to lose some kind of diversity uh
in the outputs. So how we can also
achieve some kind of the bigger
diversity while maintain the good
quality uh using this kind of technique
is also kind of some remaining kind of
the questions here.
Any questions on this?
Okay.
Yeah. So this is the last topic uh for
this class. So so far we discussed the
lots of topics uh in this class uh from
the so especially for this semester uh
we intended to basically cover some kind
of a more theoretic background of the
defian flow models the first in a way
that we are first discussing the some
basic idea for the models and see how
this idea has been evolved uh in the so
the DDPM the DDIM and also into the
continuously time deformation
and how we can also do the SD and the OD
the conversion and how this also can be
connected into the flow models as well.
So those are also some kind of some uh
some foundational the ideas for the
different flow models and also for the
last parts of this course we discussed
some kind of the uh some the ideas in
terms like how we can also broaden the
applications of the different flow
models with some kind of techniques for
the uh inference time the guidance and
also with this core distillation.
So the thing is that uh we haven't
discussed some like many more
applications for the different flow
models and also the this is aling the
topic how we can also apply the idea of
the diffusion models not only for the
continuous data but also for the
discrete data. So that's basically why
we are going to have the two uh the
death structures. So for the first gas
structure uh the human will cover some
kind of the basics of the disk
diffusion. How the diffusion models also
can be applied to the discator and also
one of the interesting the applications
of the uh diffusion deflow models would
be basically uh video models and also
the world models. uh especially world
models might be quite interesting topic
in a way that uh many kind of some
rendering the pipelines that we
discussed there uh would not be uh you
know used many for the many future
applications. So those kind of some many
future applications also will be
discussed in the uh in the second guest
le actually and before we wrap up the
course uh the here the question might be
is that so at the very beginning of like
this class uh I said this actually there
are basically two big types of the some
models that we are using in the many the
foundation the models these days
basically for the text generation uh for
many of the cases we are still using the
author of the models
It's basically very standard thing to
use the auto list model for the text
generation for many kind of sequential
and the discrete data and diffusion and
the flow models would be the best for
the many kind of the continuous data and
also in the some kind of the high
dimens.
But is this really true?
So this is actually very interesting the
question that now we are seeing uh for
now because uh recently uh we are also
seeing many kind of cases uh using the
autourist models for the image
generation and also with some kind of
really good quality.
Uh so can you guess how we can also
apply the autourist model for the image
generation?
So as we know like it's the matter of
like know that the autist model is
basically good for the sequential the
disk data which means that uh it's the
matter of like how we are going to
represent the images as the sequential
discrete kind of things. So which means
that we somehow need to discretize
some elements of the images here and
make some kind like you know as the
sequence of those kind of the some
discretized the elements. So there are
also lots of the the ideas in terms like
applying the uh author models into the
image generation
and the uh kind of the uh good and bad
things for the like the image generation
the model for now is that uh still the
quality is not the best if we only care
about the quality of the output uh for
now it is still the best to use the
diffus and the flow the models and also
for the finetuning for the many
applications like some training free
some kind of like guided generation. Uh
we know that the diffusion flow models
might be kind of be better. The reason
like why people want to still like use
the autoresist model for the image
generation is that uh we are now seeing
some kind of really good quality of the
uh language models. So here the question
is that how we are going to combine like
all the things in a way to make some
kind of multimodel the models that can
produce both the text and the images and
we already are seeing some the GPT
models and the gemline models for the
many things. So if you want to make some
like one single model that can produce
both the text and images uh what would
be kind of the best way to answer that.
So this is now kind of very important
question and uh regarding that uh still
kind of the best option for now is to
use the author model that can basically
produce the both the tax token and the
image tokens
and we don't know exactly how the GP2
models basically uh designed but many
people are basically assuming that
they're going to basically use the
models for that right if you want to
generate both the text and images and
also pretty many open source models like
this one so let Let me uh play this.
Well,
good morning.
Okay.
Oh.
So yeah this is a open model that can
take both the text and the image as the
input and also produce text images as
kind of the output. Uh so really the
multim model the model right for those
kind of the models uh still the best
option is to use the autourist model not
the flow models. So you can really check
out how exactly those models are
basically developed. Uh you can check
some more details there. So it sounds
like then yeah for the the cases that we
if we aim to make some kind of the
multimodel the model then the solution
still would be basically the models then
we don't need to really uh you know
study the different for models right uh
but also the interesting thing is that
uh we are also seeing the opposite as
well. I think I also briefly mentioned
in the beginning of this class but also
there are many kind of some development
in terms of how we are going to do the
language modeling uh with the diffusion
models and also the what people say for
now is that the benefit of like using
the diffusion model for the text
generation is that uh it can be way
faster like this. So you can see that
like the the comparison between the
diffusion LM and the LM and this is like
all the sequential generation like one
by one the all these tokens are
basically generated like at each step.
But if we use the D model
mimicking the denoising the process then
what we can do is that we can den
noiseise like all the tokens at the same
time in a way that we can produce the uh
this clear the outputs with the much
fewer number of the iterations. So these
are also some examples in terms of like
know adapting the idea of the diffusion
the den noing the process to produce
some kind of the some discrete data and
which means that we are basically seeing
some kind of the advances of like also
applying diffusion model for the
discrete data as well and also there is
the gemini the diffusion model which is
also another example this is not a yeah
uh yeah another example applying the
diffusion models for the language
modeling so very interesting uh The
situation for now is that we are seeing
some more cases like applying the
automation modeling to the image and the
video generation typically known as kind
of the the cases that we need to use the
diffusion and the flow models right and
also there are more more cases like
doing some language modeling and the
discrete and flow models and we'll see
how these are basically being evolved uh
over time and this is also one kind of
the some the paper uh from the Nvidia
which was actually released last week.
Uh so you can see some kind of the uh
many recent advances here. Uh think in
diffusion and token autoation. So some
parts of the text generation is done at
the especially in the beginning with the
diffusion and also the final the output
is basically generated in the like more
auto way. So you can see many kind of
some hybrid version in terms like you
know combine these two. So uh so
actually this is not just kind of the
the case that we are seeing some kind of
the competition between these two
there's also some more the cases in
terms of how we are going to combine
these two and especially when it comes
to the not only for the text and the
image and the videos uh if we go with
some kind of the more some complex the
types of data uh for example the graphs
like know for those kind of the not the
regular structure kind of the data what
kind of the best way to design the
basically can make some kind of the the
the genetic model. Should he use some
kind of the typical the model or the
typical models or can you consider some
kind of the combination between these
two? Uh so there are many kind of the
research going on uh into this direction
and also for the video generation for
many kind of cases like making the
videos like this actually videos might
be interesting the example in terms of
that if we see every single frame these
are basically the images right. So we
know know that diffusion deploy models
might be basically the best uh but
actually this is the sequence of the
images. So which means that actually if
we consider the sequence of images still
we might need to basically produce like
all the things you know like the more
the auto way like frame by frame right
so this is might be also the good target
in terms of like how we are going to
combine the idea of the auto relic
generation and also the diffusion models
as well. So many uh interesting kind of
discussions going on for those kind of
cases
and also for the more the applications
actually uh we haven't discussed that
much kind of the some the applications
in this class but actually the diffusion
the flow models can be applied to the
many other things for the some molecular
structure or some DNA or some other some
kind of biological and the chemical data
they might also have some kind of some
non-regular based specialty structures
for those kind of the cases is we can
also come up with some kind of the new
type of the directed models and also
diffusion the flow models are also
widely used for those types of the data
and also for the robot the manipulation
to basically for the loy plaining for
the many cases diffusion the flow models
also widely used but this is also
interesting case that we need to produce
some some kind of the sequence of the
some data points right so this might
also the good target to consider making
some kind of hybrid version of the the
autores ressive and also the difficulty
models
and also there are many other examples
uh even the division models uh can play
chess uh you can also check out many
interesting examples in terms of how the
discrete diffusion can do all those kind
of cases and also solving the sudoku as
well. So this is a very recent outputs
in terms of solving the uh the sudoku
using the diffusion mods.
So lots of the uh applications and lots
of the some interesting types of the
data. So here the question is that uh so
in the future what would be kind of the
ultimate legend model. So at the end
basically we would going to want to see
some kind of the one big foundation
model that can take all the types of
data as the input like all the text
image and the audio like many other
things as the input and also producing
all the things as the output as well.
Right for those kind of some ultimate
design model what we kind of the best
way to design this.
So the future might be is that actually
the diffusion flow models may not be
necessary like autois like the models
might be kind of the best way to handle
all the things or even the text would be
like the next GPT might be released with
the diffusion models right so we don't
know the future so there are many kind
of questions remaining here and I hope
that uh this was helpful for you in
terms of like not just getting some kind
of details of this some theory for
different and the flow models but also
getting the sense of like how those kind
of the uh the techniques are basically
being uh evolved for now. Okay. So this
is the end of the class and thank you
for the participation.
So as I said uh uh so this stops