So today I'm um it's my pleasure to
welcome Joshua Batson from Anthropic. Um
so he'll be talking about on the biology
of a large language model um which
should be a very interesting talk. Um so
Josh leads the circuits effort of the
anthropic mech um inter mechanistic
interpretability team. Um before
anthropic he worked on viogenomics and
computational microscopy at the Chan
Zuckerberg Biohub and his academic
training is in pure mathematics um which
is very cool and impressive. Um and just
another thing which is um some um more
recordings for this quarter have
released like Karina and Div's talks. Um
so feel free to check those out on our
YouTube playlist. Um, and um, for the
folks on Zoom, feel free to ask
questions um, either on the Zoom or the
Slido um, with the code CS25. And
without further ado, I'll hand it off
um, to Josh.
Thank you. Uh, clap, come on, we're
getting started. Okay.
Um, it's it's a pleasure to be here. Um,
it's crazy to me that there was a class
on transformers now, which I think, you
know, were invented rather recently. Um,
we've got like an hour for the class I
guess and then like 15 20 minutes for
questions. Feel free to just like
interrupt me with questions like I as um
as you said like my training is in pure
mathematics and like people just
interrupt each other all the time very
rudely and it's um totally fine. And so
if I'm if I want to just cut you off and
move on to something I will. But you
know this can kind of be as interactive
as you guys would uh would like it to
be. And that's true for the people on on
Zoom too. Um, okay. So, uh, this talk is
is titled on the biology of a large
language model, which is also the title
of a of a paper, um, which is what we
call our like 100page interactive blog
posts. Uh, that that went out a few a
few weeks ago. Um, and if you're here,
you probably know something about large
language models. Um, the biology word is
like, you know, was our our sort of
choice here. And maybe you should
contrast it to like you know a series of
papers called on the physics of large
language models where you're sort of
thinking of them as like dynamical
systems over the course of training. Um
but we sort of think of you know
interpretability um being in
relationship to neural networks as um
which are trained by gradient descent
right as biology is to living systems
that are developed through evolution. So
you have some process that gives rise to
complexity and you can just study the
objects that are produced for for like
how they do the kind of miraculous
things that they
do. So um models do lots of cool things.
I don't need to tell you guys this. This
is an example um oh I don't know when
it's from now maybe 6 months ago which
is like 10 years in AI time. Um but I I
quite enjoyed this. This was just
somebody um who was working on natural
language processing for sarcasian which
is like a very low resource language.
Not many people speak it. There's not
many documents. Um and he'd been sort of
tracking the state-of-the-art and NLP
for many years like you know using the
best models at the time to try to like
just help um translate into this
language, translate from this language,
you know, help help preserve it. um and
um tried it with a version of Claude
where I think this was probably sauna
3.5 um where he just shoved um this
master list of of Russian circadian
translations into the context window. So
just like painstakingly gathered over
years rather than train a model just put
it in the context window and then just
ask the model to do like um other
translations and it could not only
translate it successfully but also kind
of like break down the the the grammar
right and so just in context learning
with these models was sort of enough to
beat um the state-of-the-art for the NLP
specific models that he'd been working
on for a while. So like that's cool. Um
would be my my
summary of that. Um but models are also
weird. So
um this was also clawed.
Um and someone asked it what day is
tomorrow on leap
day and um it's just like got in a big
fight you know uh if today is February
29th 2024 then tomorrow would be March
1st however 2024 is not a leap year
which is untrue. So February 29th is not
a valid date in the Gregorian calendar.
Okay, now it starts looking at the
rules. Following this ship, 2000 was a
leap year. 2100 will not be like fine.
Um, and then it says the next leap year
after 2024 will be
2028, which is true. And then so if we
assume you meant February 28th, 2024,
the last valid date in February, then it
gives it this just like what is going
on, right? There's like some smorgesborg
of like correct recollection of facts,
correct reasoning from the facts, and
then like disregarding them out of
consistency with this like initial. It's
just pretty weird for it to be leap day.
It's like that's odd, right? I mean, if
a person were doing this, you would
wonder like what was in the brownies
they had consumed. There's just this
like now children are are sort of like
this. So maybe that's an interesting
topic. And then I just
love this
uh AI art will make designers obsolete.
AI accepting the job. And it's got so
many fingers. Um this is like now out of
date, right? like people figured out how
to keep the finger count down to at most
five per hand. Um, you know, the new uh
ChachiP model, right? Can do like
extremely realistic people and they all
have five fingers now. But like that
wasn't exactly solved by figuring out
like why are there so many fingers on
these, you know, just sort of like other
other methods got through it. But like
presumably you you kind of bat down some
of this weirdness and now it's just the
weirdness is more sophisticated. So as
the models get better, you need to get
better at understanding just where like
the craziness has sort of gone. Um so as
the frontier moves forward, like maybe
it's not five fingers, but there might
be subtly other other things that are
wrong. Um and when I think about
interpretability, which is sort of like
what did the model learn exactly? How is
it represented inside the model? How
does it manifest in behaviors? Um I am
sort of thinking ahead to when you know
most of the simple interactions seem to
go well and then it's like are these
going well because fundamentally the
model learned something like deep and
true or because you've managed to kind
of beat this down like the finger
problem but but like if you went out to
the edge of the model's capabilities it
would all be seven fingers again but you
can't tell and also because it seems
pretty reliable you've delegated a lot
of decision-m and trust to these models
and it's in the corner you can no longer
verify where things get weird. So for
that reason I we kind of want to
understand you know what's what's going
on with these
capabilities. All right. So so um this
will be a bit of a review at the
beginning of like why models are hard to
understand. Um some strategies for for
picking them apart and then and then
three main lessons I think we've learned
about about how models work inside that
like aren't obvious from a blackbox way
of engaging with them.
Um so so here are sort of three three
statements that are like somewhere
between myths or things that are out ofd
or like true if you interpret them in
one way philosophically but missing the
point. And so these statements are that
models just pattern match to similar
training data examples. Um that they use
only like shallow and simple heruristics
and reasoning. Um and that they just
kind of work one word at a time. you
know, just kind of like gutting out the
next thing and some like eruption of
spontaneity. And I think, you know, we
find that that models learn and can
compose pretty abstract representations
inside. Um that they perform rather
complex and often heavily parallel
computations. It's not serial, so
they're doing a bunch of things at once
at the same time. Um and also that they
plan many tokens into the future. So
even though they say one word at a time,
they're often thinking ahead quite far
to be able to make something coherent.
um which will which will work for
that. Okay. Um this is probably review
for this class but we made these nice
slides and I think it's nice to go
through anyway. So you have a chatbot
which is hello, how can I assist you is
an answer. How does this actually
happen, right? You know it's it is
saying one word at a time um by just
predicting the next word. So how goes
through claude and predicts can and how
can goes to I and how can I goes to
assist and how can I assist goes to you.
So you can reduce the problem to the um
computation that gives you the next
word.
Um and that is a neural network. Here
I've drawn like a fully connected
network. Um to turn language into
language passing through numbers, you
have to turn things into vectors first.
So there's an embedding. So every word
or token in the vocabulary has an
embedding, which is a list of numbers or
a vector. Um, morally speaking, you
basically just concatenate those
together and run them through, you know,
a massive, you know, neural network with
a lot of weights. Out comes a score for
every word in the vocabulary and the
model says the highest scoring word
modulosum temperature to introduce
randomness. Um, transformer
architectures are more complex. access
these residual connections alternating
attention and MLP blocks um which you
could think of as like baking in a
really strong prior into a massive
MLP but um in some sense that's just
about efficiency.
So um a metaphor we found useful which
also biological is that language models
should be thought of as grown not built
like you kind of start with this
randomly initialized thing an
architecture which is like a scaffold
you like give it some data maybe that's
like a nutrients and then the loss is
like the sun and it grows towards that
and so you get this kind of organic
thing which has been made by the end of
it. Um and you know but but but the the
way that it grew you don't really have
any access to um it the scaffold you
have access to um but that's like
looking at a model at a net which tends
not to be that interesting okay
so of course like we have the models and
so and so there is a tautological answer
to what are they doing which I already
told you which is they turn the words
into numbers they do a bunch of matt
moles they apply like simple functions
it's just math all the way through and
then you get something out and it's like
that's it. That's what the model does.
Um, and I think that's an unsatisfying
answer because you can't reason about
it, right? Like that answer to how do
models work like doesn't tell you about
what behaviors they should or shouldn't
be able to do or kind of any of those
things. So, um, the first thing you
might hope is that the neurons inside
the neural network might have
interpretable roles. Um, you know,
people were hoping this going back to
the first networks in the 80s. Um, and
um, there was a bit of a resurgence in
deep learning, a kind of small one.
Chris Ola, who leads the team at
Anthropic, got really into this 10 years
ago. You just like look at a neuron and
you ask when does this fire? For what
inputs is this neuron active? And then
you just sort of see like do those form
a coherent class, right? This is the car
detector neuron in a vision model or
this is the eye detector. This is like
the edge detector if it's early in the
model, you know? um they found like the
Donald Trump neuron um in a clip model
um for example. Uh but it turns out that
in language models um when you do this
you just say which sentences cause this
neuron to activate. Um the answer
doesn't make that much sense. Um so here
here's a visualization of a bunch of
example text for which a neuron and a
model activates. And
um there's just a lot of stuff. There's
like code and
um some Chinese and some math and
hemlock for
Socrates. Um it's not especially clear
and like of course there's no reason it
would need to be right like it's just
learned to function and so asking for a
neuron to be interpretable is like a bit
of a hail mary. Um, and it's pretty cool
that that like works sometimes, but it's
like not not particularly systematic.
Um,
so there's a a prior though, a prior
from neuroscience is that like maybe
maybe while there's a whole bunch of
neurons going on or something that in
any given moment, maybe the model's like
not thinking of that many things at
once. Maybe there's some sparsity here
where if there were a map of the
concepts the model is using or the sub
routines it's using or something um that
that on any given token it's only using
a few at a time. Um and that's just you
know maybe a slightly better guess than
maybe the neurons are interpretable.
It's like not necessarily a great prior
but it's something you can work with.
And so you can fit
um linear combinations of neurons such
that each activation vector is a sum
sparse combination of these dictionary
elements. This is called dictionary
learning classical ML. Um and we just
did it. So you just like gather a bunch
of activations from the model and you
put through the trillion texts or
something and then you take those
vectors you look for dictionaries and
then you look at when are those
dictionary components active and lo and
behold it's way better. So you know we
had a paper last year which was just
like here's a bunch of them where we fit
about 30 million features on claude 3
sonnet on the middle layer of the model.
So you just say you know what are the
atoms of computation or representation
inside that model. Um this was one of my
favorites um where this linear
combination is present or it's like a
dotproduct but the vector is large um
when when the input is about the Golden
Gate Bridge and that is true if it is
like an explicit mention of the Golden
Gate Bridge in in English on the left.
Also true if it's translated into
another language
um also true if it's an image of the
Golden Gate Bridge also true it turns
out if it's an indirect mention so
you're like I was driving from San
Francisco
to
Marin right which you know you cross the
bridge to do and the same feature is
active there right so it's like some
relatively general concept also in like
San Francisco landmarks etc um these
combinations of neurons are
interpretable we were happy with this
there's things that are more abstract
you know notions of inner conflict there
was um a feature for like bugs in code
that like fired on kind of kind of small
bugs like division by zero or typos or
something um in many different
programming languages. If you suppressed
it, the model would act like there
wasn't a bug. If you activated it, the
model would give you a trace back as if
there were a bug. And so, you know, it
sort of had this general general um
properties. But there was something very
unsatisfying about this, which is
like how does it know it's the Golden
Gate Bridge and um and so what you know,
what does it do with that information,
right? So even if you manage to like
piece apart the representations that
that's just a cross-section. It kind of
doesn't give you the why and the how. It
just gives you the what. Um and so um we
wanted to find ways of connecting these
features together. So you start from the
input words and you're going to process
these to higher order representations
and eventually it'll say something and
trying to trace that through
um through optimization. So very
concretely you have a matrix which is
like you take a billion examples and you
of of of activation vectors and then
you've got D model here that's a
matrix and you um try to factoriize that
matrix into a product of a fixed
dictionary of atoms times a sparse
matrix of which atoms are present in
which example and you have just have an
objective function which is this should
reconstruct the data and some L1 penalty
to encourage sparsity.
Through it's a joint optimization
problem. Yeah, that's right. That's
right.
Um, we tried being clever about this.
There's like a beautiful rich literature
on dictionary learning. Um but but after
a few months of that the bitter lesson
got us and it um turned out that you
could just use like a one layer sparse
autoenccoder which you can like put in
torch and then just like train on your
GPUs and like that scaling was more
important than being clever yet again.
Um so that's what it is. It's a sort of
sparse
autoenccoder. All right. So
um here's a prompt. Okay. So the capital
of the state containing Dallas is
Austin. This is true. Um, that's because
the state containing Dallas is
Texas. Good. Um, did the model do that?
Was it like Texas, so Austin, or is it
like I don't know. It seemed a lot of
training data like was this just in it
and it's just like reciting the answer,
you know, people there's a lot of eval
contamination like a lot of emloo made
it into people's training sets so you
get high scores. Well, just knew the
answer to that literally because it had
seen it. Did it literally see this
before or is it kind of thinking Texas
like you did?
Um, it's thinking about Texas. So, I'll
I'll tell you this is this is like a a
cartoon and we can slowly through this
like pick, you
know, break away these abstractions to
like literally what we did. But I'll
sort of start by saying that you should
think of each of these
um as sort of bundles of features which
are again atoms we sort of learned
through a through an optimization
process. We label the role of each
feature by looking at when it's active
and trying to see if we can describe
kind of in language, you know, what that
feature is doing. And then the
connections between them are actually
direct causal connections as the model,
you know, processes this in a forward
pass. And so what we do is we break
apart the model into into pieces. We ask
you know which pieces are active. Can we
interpret them separately? And then how
does the how does it flow? And so in
this case we found you know a bunch of
features related to capitals, a bunch
related to states in the abstract, a
bunch related to Dallas. We found some
features that were like you can think of
as like motor neurons. They make the
model do something. In this case they
make it say the name of a capital like
they make it say a bunch of state
capitals or country capitals or
something. So that's a start. Um, but
also it has to get it right. And so, you
know, there's some mapping from Dallas
into Texas. Um, and there's a pile of
features there. Some are like, you know,
um, discussions of like Texas politics.
Some are like phrases like everything's
bigger in Texas. Um, and once you have
Texas in a capital, you get saying
Austin in
particular. And you know, if you're
saying a state capital and also you're
saying Austin, what you get is like
Austin coming out. There's some
interesting straight lines though, you
know, so like Texas also feeds into
Austin directly, right? Um, if you're
thinking about Texas, you might just be
thinking about
Austin.
Um, and so, you know, I'll get into more
of how we how we build this. Um, but but
you know, this gives you a sort of a
picture in terms of these atoms or
dictionary elements we've learned. Um,
and you might want to check that they
make sense. So then you can do
interventions on the model deleting
pieces of this like in neuroscience
these would be ablations of neurons or
something and then you see if the output
of the model changes as you would
expect.
Someone on Zoom asked words like Austin
frequently appear together in internet
text suggesting simple statistical
corrections. So isn't this a way of over
complicating things?
I think that people have found that
transformers have outperformed back then
for most tasks. So um you know Houston
also occurs you know with Dallas and the
training data and the model doesn't say
Houston so it must be using the capital
and and Dallas in this case I think you
could say you know maybe if you just had
capital and Dallas then it would it
would um it would say Austin and that's
actually true. I think some of this
edges were pretty weak and it turns out
you could just say the
capital you it makes something un
grammatical just like you know the
capital of Dallas is and it will say
Austin um and that's an interesting
thing where I think you look at the
graph and this edge is weak and it
indicates that actually maybe it is just
like if you have capital in Dallas in
proximity you might get Austin which is
then causally true. Uh yes
layer layer layer
that's you want to do the layer and the
bottom layer. Yeah, I understand this
correct. Yeah. So this is the this is
the flow through layers of the model.
Okay. Upstairs. And we've done some
grouping here. So
um uh I will show in more detail. Um let
me actually see when we're going to get
to that. Yeah. So I'm gonna give you a
lot more detail in just about a slide on
the the technical side. Yes.
per size for a dictionary or for the
dictionary. Um we did a scan where we
trained dictionaries of different sizes
and we
um you know you get some tradeoff um of
just the compute you spend and the
amount
um or the accuracy of the approximation
like you know these are supposed to
reconstruct the activations. How well
does that happen? The bigger the
dictionary the better it does. Also, the
the denser it is, the less sparse it is,
the better that does, but you pay some
price on forability at some point. So,
we did a bunch of sweeps and then we
picked something that seems good enough.
There's still a bunch of errors and you
know, I'll show you later how those show
up to, you know, mean that we can't
explain, you know, a lot of things.
Okay, I'm going to go on.
Um,
so yeah, literally what we do
here is train this sparse replacement
model. So the basic idea if you have a
model of residual stream goes through
LPS we're going to forget about
attention right now um and we're going
to try to approximate that with these
cross-layer transcoders and so what do I
mean by that so transcoder is something
that like you know moves information so
it emulates the MLPS but the cross layer
is this ensemble of them emulates all
the MLPS there's an architecture called
densenet from a few years ago right
where every layer writes to every
subsequent layer and this is like that
so the basic idea is that this ensem
ensemble of of CLTs have to take in the
inputs of all the MLPS stacked together
and produce the vector of all of their
outputs at once. Um, and a reason to do
this is like there's no particular
reason to think that like the atomic
units of computation have to live in one
layer. If there's two consecutive layers
in a deep model, those neurons are
almost interchangeable. People have done
experiments. You can actually swap the
order of transformer layers without
damaging performance that much, which
means that like indexing that hard on
the existing layer is maybe unwise. So
we just say okay you know these can skip
to the end. Um this ends up making the
interpretability easier because
sometimes it's just biogram statistics.
I see this word I say that word that's
evident at layer 1 but you have to keep
propagating it all the way through to
get it out. And so here we could make
that be one feature instead of you know
dozens of features and consecutive
layers interacting. Um and then we just
train that optimization. You've got a
loss on accuracy and a loss on sparity.
Um okay. And so here we replace the
neurons with these these
features. Um we use just the attention
from the base model. So we do not try to
explain attention. We just flow through
it. But we try to explain what the MLPS
are doing. Um and now instead of the
neurons which are sort of
uninterpretable like on the left here we
have stuff that makes more sense. On the
right this is a say a capital feature.
Um, and I think it's probably more
specific. So, this is like in, you
know, these like literal state to
capital mappings. Um, yeah.
our company.
So I don't know reasonable I'd say it's
expedient. Um um it it loses a lot. Um I
think that from a practical perspective
though if you want to model the action
of the attention layer
um or anything that moves information
between tokens then the input would have
to be the activations at all of the
token positions.
Um, and uh, here we only can do one
token position at a time. So you can
learn something much simpler. Um, and
the I think the learning problem is just
like a lot a lot easier. Um, it's also
like slightly less clear what the thing
to replace the attention layer is that
would be interpretable because it needs
to be a system for both transforming
information and moving it. Um, and
sparsity isn't a good priority there.
You've got like a four tensor instead of
a two tensor and we aren't sure what the
right answer is. So we just did this for
now.
You are embibing your information of
what the relevant features are.
[Music]
Right? So there's two questions there.
One is like what do you lose by doing a
replacement and the other is like you
know
um how much are you leaning on your
interpretations of the components you
get and what is a relevant feature.
Yeah. Something that you
Yeah. Um well so the sparks autocoder
just produces a bunch of these right and
then but we do have to interpret what
comes out and so um for any particular
graph you know we can go we have now the
attention is frozen um we have a forward
pass of the model sort of through the
replacement where we've got a bunch of
the features we've got these triangles
represent these diamonds are the heirs
so like these don't perfectly
reconstruct the base model so you have
to include an air term and then you can
you know, track the influence directly.
These are just linear
maps um until you get to the end. Um and
you know, there'll be a lot of these
active, fewer than there are neurons,
but you know, order order order hundreds
per token. Um but they don't all matter
for the model's output. So then you can
sort of go from the output like Austin
here backwards and say which features
were directly causally relevant for
saying Austin and then which features
were causally relevant for those being
active and then which are causally
relevant for those being active. And in
that way you get a much smaller thing
something you could actually look at um
to try to understand why it said this
literal thing here. Um and now you're in
but this is all still math right now you
have this graph but if you want to
interpret this then you need to look at
you know these individual components and
see if you can make sense of them. And
now you're back to like looking at when
was this active in which examples hoping
that's kind of interpretable and that
you know that the connections between
them make any sense. Um, you know, often
often these will be in some rough
categories. So, here's like one Texas
feature is like again the like
everything's bigger in Texas. Texas is a
big state known for its cowboys and cowg
girls. Um, and this other one is about,
you know, politics in the judicial
system. Um, and it, you know, I'm not
saying that like these are like the
right way to break apart the network,
but they are a way to break apart the
network. And if you look at the flow in
here, you know, these Texas features
feed into the say Austin ones, right?
There is a path here. And so we sort of
will manually group some of these based
on at this point human interpretation um
to get a map of what's going on. Yeah,
just a zoom question. Um in CLT
architecture, we freeze attention blocks
and replace um MLPS with transcoders
that speak to each other. Um this is
complex, right? So won't this be adding
unnecessary interpretability when the
underlying connections could be a lot
simpler? Also, do you mind repeating the
question so the folks on Zoom can hear?
Yes. Um the question is, boy, this seems
like a lot of extra work. Um you know,
there's a lot of connections between
these features, right? They're mediated
by attention. Um and I would agree. Um
but we couldn't find a way of doing less
work and have the units be
interpretable, right? One way to think
about this is the base components of the
model aren't that interpretable. So if
you want to interpret things as
interactions of components like if you
want to use like the great reductionist
strategy that's been quite effective and
you know break organs into you know uh
cells and understand how the cells
interact. You like have to break it
apart in some way. You lose a lot when
you do that but you you gain something
which is you can talk about how those
parts work. And so this was our best
guess today as like parts to to
study. Um okay so um we're still in
schematic land here. Um once we have
group things to make a graph like this
we can do interventions. So
um and this these interventions are in
the base model not in our complicated
replacement model. They amount to
basically adding in vectors that are the
feature outputs to another one. Um, and
you can see if if the perturbations make
sense. So, if we swap out the Texas by
muting those and add in the California
features from another prompt, then the
model will say
Sacramento. Um, if you put in Georgia,
it will say
Atlanta. Um, if you put in the Byzantine
Empire, it will say
Constantinople. Um, and so here it's a
sign that like we did capture like an
abstract thing in a manipulable way,
right? you don't put it in and get
gibberish, right? And um you know, if
you're just doing biogram statistics or
something, it's not clear how you would
how you would get this
separability.
Um okay, so I'm going to get into these
three kind
of motifs that we see a lot, the
abstract representations in a medical
context and a multilingual context. um
parallel processing motifs um which is
about arithmetic some jailbreaks and
hallucinations
um and then also some elements of
planning. Yeah.
Yeah. So this this approach of like
training a replacement model of an
analyzing an attribution graph is just
math. So you can do whatever you want.
Um and then it's like are they
interpretable you know as a we do this
on a small 18 layer model um in one of
the papers which can't do very much and
find pretty interpretable things. So I
think this this works at at all scales.
I know people who are doing these on
like you know sort of now how
interesting is it if your model can't do
anything maybe it's not that interesting
but but I think if your model's narrow
purpose and small this would still be
useful since you're talking about
biology here and this all seems like
something that maybe in a different
field has been kind of human brains and
human rights do you know is there any
kind of overlap on literature that
you're relying on from the real like
medicine side of things for for some
inspiration um I think in particular as
like you know the the idea of doing the
perturbations the causal perturbations
and seeing what happens is like a very
neuroscience on the geneneticsy thing to
do.
Um fortunately or unfortunately like our
experimental setup is so much better
than theirs. So I think we we're now
like well past what people can do in
neuroscience. Um because we have like
one brain and we can study it a billion
times and we can intervene on everything
and measure everything and they're in
there like trying to capture like.1% of
neurons like at a time resolution a
thousand times worse than the actual
activity. So um
maybe the other way around. Yeah.
Yeah. Yeah.
Um, okay. I want to give you, you know,
just I think it's it's it's good to like
be able to like actually
um see some of these. So this is in the
in the paper itself. This is
like what we make these cartoons from.
Okay. So each of these nodes is like a
feature and an edge is like a causal
influence. Um here's um you know uh one
whose direct effect on the output is
saying Austin mostly and also some Texas
things. Um it's getting inputs from
things related to Texas and from states
and um you know these like the the art
of this is like now you're doing the
interpretation. You're like bouncing
around looking at these components
looking at when they're active looking
at what they connect to um and trying to
figure out what's going on. Um and so
the cartoons I'll show you are given by
grouping sets of these based on
common properties. So I said these were
say a capital and you can see that these
are different from each other but they
all do involve the models you know
saying capitals in some context and so
we just sort
of piled those on top of each other and
this is what like I don't you know how
many features should you have I don't
know there's obviously no right answer
here I think um it's not a perfect
approximation but you sort of break it
into 30 million pieces then you put the
pieces back together in ways that make a
bit of sense and then you do
interventions to check that like what
you learned is real.
Um okay. So now
we
always systems and emergent properties.
Uh and then maybe this is the biggest
difficulty in studying this kind of
systems and clearly LLMs they kind of
start displaying this kind of behavior.
So if you start breaking it down at the
same time you end up losing those
emergent properties. So how can you
balance that uh you know and having
losing all these this properties that
just emerge when everything is together?
It's a good question.
So I think one thing that makes LLMs
kind of different is this flow of
information from the input to the
output. um in which it seems like the
the like latent spaces work at a higher
level of of of representation or
complexity as you move through it. And
so, you know, like all cells are somehow
like the same size. They communicate
with each other, but it's all like
lateral communication. Um and um you
know I think you do see this some in the
brain as you go from like you know the
the first um light sensitive cells
through the visual cortex where um you
will get you know ultimately like a cell
which is sensitive to a particular
face. Um but that comes from things
sensitive to less specific things and
ultimately things that like just detect
like edges and shapes and those kinds of
structures. And so I think as you move
through that um you you do get these
higher levels of abstraction. And so um
you know when I say okay there's a
feature that seems to correspond to
errors in code. Um this is one of our
atomic units. You know it's like one of
the things we're getting when we shatter
this is like sensitive to errors in code
but like in in a very general way. Um,
and so to some extent I think that that
like the these are built up
hierarchically but that it's just maybe
they're still units. There's another
thing that I think we don't have any
traction on which is like if it's doing
some like in context like dynamical
systems stuff um that I think that will
be much harder to to understand um and
you might need like much larger
ensembles of these
um
okay let's slideshow again okay
So, here's like a medical exam style
differential diagnosis question. Uh,
32-year-old female at 30 weeks,
gestation, presents with severe right
upper quadrant pain,
etc. Given this context, um, if we could
only ask for one other symptom, what
should it be?
Um, does anybody is there a doctor in
the house?
Does anybody know what the what the
medical condition is
here? Uh yeah. So ask about visual
disturbances and the reason is because
this is like the most likely diagnosis
is is
preeacclampsia
here.
Um which is a se severe complication of
pregnancy. Um, and you know, we're sort
of able to trace through by like looking
at these features and how they're sort
of grouping together and how it flows.
You know, that is pulling things from
pregnancy from, you know, that that
region, the headache, the high blood
pressure, the liver tests, um, to to
preeclampsia. Um, and then from that to
other symptoms of preeacclampsia and
then from those, you know, ultimately,
um, there's actually two complete visual
disturbances. Um and you know there's a
tiny box here showing like you know what
do we mean by that those are the this
component is also active on training
examples discussing you know causing
vision loss um floaters you know in the
eye which is another visual disturbance
lead to loss of vision um the other
answer would be protonuria and so you
know it is it is in the same way
thinking about Texas it's thinking about
preeacclampsia in some way before like
saying what these what these are and we
can see that intermediate state um it is
thinking about other potential diagnoses
like uh biliary system disorders and if
we suppress the preeacclampsia
um then um it will say instead of visual
disturbances with a rationale because
this presentation suggests
preeacclampsia it will say decreased
appetite because the scenario suggests
um biliary disease right and so it is
thinking of these options when you turn
one off then you get like a coherent
answer consistent with the other one. So
what does this mean? The fact that you
can intervene so clearly that this is
only represented in exactly one location
in the in the network and that by
intervening they are you know you don't
need to intervene in multiple times.
Well, so so no. Um um because two
reasons, three reasons. Okay, the three
reasons are one, you know, this node is
a group of them, right? It's a few of
these features um that are all related
to preeacclampsia. The second is because
it's a cross layer transcoder. Each of
them writes to many layers.
Um and then the third is we're creaming
it. So here we're turning it off double
the amount that it was on. Um you know,
we overorrect. We overcorrect. And you
often need to do that to get the full
effect probably because there's
redundant mechanisms and stuff. And so I
don't think this is the only place it is
necessarily but but it's enough. Yeah.
Um earlier in your talk you talked a bit
about polymatricity of neurons. Yeah. So
for example if you do one of these
interventions like the what is it
pre-exam right? um and let's say I
deploy the model for some other would
you expect like um like what is the
distribution of things that this will
also hit if if you can um sort of give
some sense of but like what would be the
other not what would be other types of
yeah um that's a great question we
didn't dig into that as much here we did
a little more with our last paper um you
know I think that you push too hard and
the model goes off the rails like in a
big way. Um I you know here this is less
for the purpose of shaping model
behavior and more for the purpose of
validating our hypothesis in this one
example. Um so we we were not like and
now let's take a model we've deleted
this everywhere. It's like no the
model's going through answering this
question right here. We're turning off
this part of its brain you know and then
we're seeing what happens.
Couple uh questions on Zoom. One is uh
in practice when you trace backwards
through these features do you see a kind
of explosion of relevant features as you
go earlier in the model or is it some
function of distance from the output?
Um yeah the question is like um as you
go backwards through the model you know
is the number of relevant features go
up? Uh
yes. Um
uh sometimes you know sometimes you do
get convergence um you know like the
early features right might be about that
you know a few symptoms or something and
and those are quite important um and
um I don't think we've made a good plot
to answer that question. I am going to
push onwards a little bit and I'll come
back to questions soon. Gotcha. Uh just
one more. How much are these examples
carefully selected or crafted? Does this
work for most sentences?
Um, you learn
something about most things you try. So,
I'd say like 40% of the prompts that we
try, we can we can see some non-trivial
part of what's going on. It's not the
whole picture and it like sometimes
doesn't work. But, um, it also just
takes, you
know, 60 seconds of user time to kick
one of these off. Um, and then you wait
and then it's done and it comes back and
then you get to learn something about
the model rather than having to like
construct a whole bunch of a priori
hypothesis of what's going on. You just
sort of get it once you've built the
machine you get it for free but this
doesn't tell you
everything. Okay, so
um here's a question like what language
are models thinking
in? Um if there's a you know is it a
universal language? Is it English? Is it
like it just like there's a French
claude and a Chinese claude inside of
Claude and like who gets gated to is
kind of depends on the question. Um and
so to answer this we looked at three
sentences which are the same um sentence
in three languages. So the opposite of
small is big the
the and I can't speak Mandarin. But
maybe someone here can say what what
someone surely is a Mandarin speaker in
this room. Like there's no chance.
Thank you.
I came to What? What's the final
character?
I I came to see it because we were doing
these like this part of the paper like
so many times that like it's the only
character I can recognize now.
Um so so this is like even more
cartoony, right, than the last one. And
I'll get into the the more detailed
version later, but
basically what we see is at the
beginning there are some of these like
um
opposites um in in specific languages,
right? Contra in French, opposite in
English. Um and the the quotation it's
like uh this is like an open quote in
the language I'm speaking, right? So the
quote that follows will probably be in
the same language. Um but then there's
this like complex of features
um about you know antonyms in many
languages saying large in many languages
um smallness in many languages that that
go together and then you spit it back
out in the language of interest. So the
claim is that this this is a sort of
multilingual core here where smallness
goes with oppositeness to give you
largeness and then largeness plus you
know this quote is in English gives you
the word largeness plus this quote is in
French gives you
um give you and
um we did a bunch of these like kind of
patching experiments Um
uh you could say instead of the
opposite, you know, you could say a
synonym of um and just like drop that
in. So the same thing in all of them and
now you'll get um little
um or minuscule in French. Um and so
sort of like patching in a different
state, you know, you can you can you can
it's the same feature you're putting in
in these three places and you get the
same change in behavior later. Um, and
we sort of looked at this does have a
big effect with scale. So you can look
like how many features overlap between a
pair of sentences that are this just
translations of each other as you move
through the model. And at the beginning
it's just the like the tokens in that
language. There's no
overlap. Um the you know uh Mandarin
when it's tokenized has nothing in
common with English when it's tokenized.
So at the beginning and the end there's
nothing. Um but uh as you move through
the model you see a pretty large portion
of the components that are active are
the same regardless of the language that
it was that it was put in. Um and so
this is English Chinese French Chinese
and English French.
Um this is like a random baseline if the
sentences are unrelated. So it's not
just like the middle's more common. But
when you compare pairs that are
translations, this is in a 18 layer
model and this is in our like small
production model. Hik um so this
generalization is kind of increasing
with scale.
Yes.
It's almost like it can kind of
interpret concepts in like a Yes. Have
you ever tried um doing prompts that are
metaphors that are kind of like specific
to that language that don't really have
translation?
Um, no. If you have some examples of
that, I'd love to try it. Um, I think
that would be fun.
Yes.
Yes. I would be happy for collaboration.
[Music]
Yes. So, would you say this kind of
implies that in the center of the
network is the most abstract
representation of any given concept
because the I would basically agree with
this plot which is like a little to the
right of the center. Yeah. At which
point you start to have to figure out
what to do with it because in the end
the model has to say a thing. Have you
seen have a harder time finding auto
semantic features in the in the middle
of the network where it's very abstract
rather than towards the end where it's
very concrete?
It's I if anything it's actually the
opposite. Um because the like if you'll
permit me to be philosophical like the
point of a good abstraction is that it
applies in many
situations. Um and so um in the middle
there should actually be these like
common abstractions. It's like dealing
with the very particulars of this
phrasing or this grammarical scenario
that it's quite bespoke and so you would
need way more features to unpack it.
Yeah.
One more question. Uh yes. Um is the
same like operation stored redundantly
across multiple layers? Like do you find
that uh like for example if you need
five reasoning steps to to get something
done for like like in one example but
then in another example you need eight
reasoning steps to get something done.
Um do you redundantly have to store the
like follow-up operation on both of
those layers?
Yeah, I think this is like a very deep
question. Um so to repeat it for the the
audience it's like do we see redundancy
of the same operation in many places?
And of course this kind of it's like a a
thing people complain about with these
models. Um right which is like well if
it knows A and it knows B why can't it
do them in a row in its head? It like
might just literally be that A is after
B in its head and have to do a forward
pass. And so unless it gets to like
think out loud it literally can't
compose those operations. Um, and you
can see this quite easily, you know, if
you just ask, you know, like who is the
what's the birthday of the father of the
star of the movie from 1921 starring,
you know, like it might be able to do
all of those, but like it can't actually
do all those lookups consecutively.
That's like the first thing. So there is
there has to be redundancy. And then we
do see this. It was one of the reasons
for the crosscoder setup is to try to
zip up some of that redundancy. Um, I
think one of my one of my favorite plots
is not from the so-called biology paper,
but is from the um sister paper
uh here. Uh, let's find Copenhagen.
Okay. So like on the left is if you do
sort of you do this decomposition per
layer on the right is you do the cross
layer thing and like basically you know
it's just like bouncing back around you
know it's like the Copenhagen is like
propagated is talking to Denmark and
it's just like happens in like many many
places in the model. They all perform
you know like small improvements to it.
Um, you know, there's another
perspective here which is like the the
like neural OD like gradient flow
perspective where it's like all tiny
adjustments in the same direction all
the time and I think the real models are
somewhere in between.
Okay. With the overlap of the features
here as the models get larger uh you
found like if you change like data set
very significantly or also like ordering
in parts of the data set you end up with
very different representations.
We haven't done systematic studies of
like you know data set ordering
effects but
sometimes I guess I'm curious if you're
around the other
um no I don't like like we've maybe been
lucky you could have a plot where it's
like how how compelling was science
hypothesis from the attribution graph
and then like how well did it work when
you intervened and the best ones did
work. Um but there there are some small
failure cases we we talk about. Okay, I
want to dive into the parallel motif
because I think it's actually super
interesting and it's a unique feature of
the transformer architecture, right?
It's massively parallel. So, um, to give
a to give a really simple example of
this,
um, imagine that you want to
add 100
numbers. So, the easiest way to do is
you start with one, you add the next,
you add the next to the sum, you add the
next to the sum, and you do 100 serial
steps. Um, to do that with a
transformer, it would need to be 100
layers deep.
But there's another thing you can do
which is you could add
um pairs consecutively in one layer and
then add the pairs of pairs
consecutively in the next and then the
pairs of those pairs in the next. And so
in login depth you could you could add
up the 100 numbers. Um and you know
given the depth constraints here and the
sophistication of what we ask these
models to do you know it makes sense
that they would attempt to do many
things at once. premp compute things you
might need kind of slap them all
together and I'll give you a few
examples of this. So
um if you ask the model to add 36 and 59
it will say 95. If you ask it how it did
that it will say it used the standard
carrying algorithm which is not true. Um
what happens is somewhat more like this.
So, first it parses out each number into
like there's some component where it's
like literally 59, but there's also
something for all numbers ending in nine
and something which is like that number
range and the same up there. And then
you kind of have two streams. One where
it's um getting the last digit,
right? And then another on top where
it's getting the magnitude, right? And
even inside the magnitude, there's sort
of like like a narrow band magnitude and
a really wide band magnitude. Um and
then um those give you a sort of median
band and then if the sum is in this
range and it ends in a five then it's
actually 95. That narrows it down and
then it gives you the answer.
Um which is cool. It's not how I would
do it.
Um but but then again it wasn't trained
by like a teacher being like here's
something to do. It just got like
whacked every time it got it wrong. um
or like rewarded every time I got it.
Right. Right. In training. Um and you
know, I don't think we're going to have
this next in here. So, I want to show
you one of my favorite things
from the addition section. Um which is
like, okay, so you know, there's a
feature in here. Okay. Like, like if
anybody here like feel like this is like
a word cell shape rotator test. So for
the shape rotators who like kind of
mathematical thinking like I love this
section. So this is like this is the
graphs we make to visualize on the
arithmetic prompts. Um uh this is like
is it active on the prompt a plus b for
a and b and 1 to 100. That's a grid. And
so vertical lines mean like when the
second operand is in a range it's active
you know. Um these dots is like is it a
six and a nine? You know so there's a
grid. this bands, you know, a band here
is a line x plus y equals constant,
right? And so those are where the sum
is. So we were looking at this to sort
of figure out what these did. Um, but
this feature here I really like. So
everything in the graph you can hover
over, which is kind of neat and see the
feature. Um, and we looked at cases in
the data set when this thing was active.
Okay, so so on this narrow domain is
active when when things ending in six
get added to things ending in nine, but
on the data set it's active in like all
these other cases. So this is like um
thymus organ fragments federal
proceedings volume
35. It's like okay so in some sense that
has to
be a 9 plus a 6 is the volume 35
supposedly if this interpretation is
correct. Here's just like a list of
numbers. Um there's more
journals. Uh there's like these
coordinates. Um and so and so the claim
here if our method is working is that
there's one component that in this
context means ends in 6 plus ends in 9
but it's also active in these. So like
this is really working if secretly every
one of these examples is the model
adding a six to a 9 and it's getting to
reuse the module for doing that across
those examples. Um and so we dug
in and um I couldn't really understand
these. So, so here's one example
um where this is the token where where
you know that feature was active
um and uh
I just put it in claw and I was like
what is this and it's like ah this is a
table of astronomical
measurements and it spit it out in like
a nicely formatted table and the first
two columns are the start and end time
of an observation period. Um and
um this is the minutes of an end
time that it's predicting. And if you
read down the table, the start to end
interval is like 38 minutes, 37 minutes,
but it creeps up over the course of the
experiment to be like just under 39
minutes. And this measurement interval
started
um at a minute with a
six and the six plus the
9 equals ending in a five. And so the
model was just like gutting out, you
know, next token predictions for like
arbitrary sequences of data was trained
on and um learned in that, you know, of
course to recognize what controll
supposed to do. But then it needs a bit
where it has like the arithmetic table,
right? like 6 plus 9. You just got to
look it up. So, it has that somewhere
and it's using that same lookup in this
like very different context where it
needs to add those things. Um, this was
another one where it turned out this was
a table and it's predicting this amount
and these are um arithmetic sequences.
This is I guess the um
total cost that's going up. Um and so
um the amount that it's going up by, you
know, is this where you're carrying
that's about 9,000 plus 26,000 is
35,000. This was maybe my favorite where
like why is it firing here to predict
the year? And the answer is because it's
volume 36. This journal was founded in
um first edition was in 19 um 60. So the
zeroth would have been in 1959. 9 + 59 +
36 uh is 95. And so it's using the same
little bit to do the addition there,
right? Um and so I think when we talk
about generalization like you know you
know and abstraction this is was for me
like a pretty moving example where I was
like okay like did learn this little
thing but then using it all over the
place.
Um okay that's maybe like not the most
like mission critical thing in the
world. So let's talk about
hallucinations. Um so so models they're
great. They'll always answer your
question. Um, but sometimes they're
wrong. And that is that is just because
of like pre-training. Like they're meant
to just predict a plausible next thing.
Okay. Um, great. Like it should say
something. If it knows nothing, it
should just give a name. If it knows
like anything, it should give like, you
know, a name in the correct language,
right? If it knows more, maybe like a
common name from the era or like just
some basketball player or whatever,
right? And so that's what it's trained
to do. And then you're like, you go to
fine-tuning and you're like, "No, like I
want you to be an assistant character,
not just a generic simulator." And when
you simulate the assistant, I want the
assistant to say, "I don't know." Like
when the base model certainty is
somehow, you know, low. And that's like
a big switch to try to make. And so we
were curious like how does that happen,
right? How does this like, you know,
refusal to speculate get fine-tuned in?
And then when
um why does that fail?
Um, and
so here's here's sort of two prompts
that get at this. One is, "What sport
does Michael Jordan play?" Answer in one
word. It says basketball. The other is,
"What sport does Michael Batkin play?"
Um, which just the person we made up.
Um, answer in one word. And it says, "I
apologize. I can't find a definitive
record of a sports figure named Michael
Bin." Okay.
Um, so, um, here these graphs are a
little bit different. They've got
suppressive edges highlighted here. You
know, this is common in neuroscience,
like inhibition. Um, and we've drawn
some features that aren't active on this
prompt, but are on this one and vice
versa. So, if they're in gray, it means
it's inactive here. But part of the
reason it's inactive in particular is
it's being suppressed by something that
is active. And what we found was sort of
this cluster of four features in the
middle.
Um, you know, uh, Michael Jordan and
then we have like a feature for like
it's active when the models recognizes,
you know, um answers to questions.
There's another feature for like unknown
names. Um and then there's a generic
feature for like I can't answer that.
And that generic feature I can't answer
is just fueled by the assistant which is
always on when the model's answering. So
it's just like there's just an always I
don't know to any question and then that
gets down modulated when it recalls
something about a person. So when
Michael Jordan is there that suppresses
the unknown name, boosts the known
answer. Both of those suppress the can't
answer and that leaves room for the path
of actually recalling the answer to come
through and it can say
basketball. Um, so that's a cool
strategy, but getting back to model
depth, there's an interesting problem
which is that like it might take a while
for the model to come up with an answer,
but it also would have to like at some
point decide to refuse and like get that
going and those are happening in
parallel. you could have a little bit of
a mismatch where like by the you know it
has to decide now whether or not it's
going to answer or not but it hasn't
like done all that it can do to get a
good answer right and so you can get
some divergence where for very hard
questions for example but it still might
know it has to be like okay do I think
I'm going to get
there and that's like a little bit of a
tricky knob it can't fully self-reflect
on the answer before saying it um and so
okay this is just the intervention you
you you known answer and it will
hallucinate that Michael that can play
chess. Um
uh so so this is a fun one. So if you
ask for a paper by Andre Carpathy um
formerly of Stanford um it gives a very
famous paper that he didn't write
um why is that? Well, it's like trust
me, I've heard of Andre Carpathy like
from the name, but then there's the part
which is trying to like recall the paper
and then it uh gives that answer, right?
But like and then actually it says that
and then you know I think it's covered
up here but then it then then like if
you're like are you sure it's like no I
don't really think he wrote that because
at that point then the model as an input
gets both the person and the paper and
can like do calculation earlier in the
network again. Um now we can juice this.
We can we can
um suppress the the known answer bit and
um eventually um it
will apologize and refuse. Um there's a
fun one in the paper where the model
hasn't heard of
me. I didn't write that section. Jack
wrote that section and um it refuses to
speculate about papers I've written. And
then if you if you turn off the like
unknown entity and you like give the
known answer, then it says I'm famous
for inventing the bats in principle,
which I hope to one day do.
Um, okay. So, um, there's a lot more we
could talk about here. I'm just going to
like speedrun these for vibes and you
can like read the paper where we do a
lot more. There's a jailbreaks trying to
understand how they work. And you know,
some of it is like you get the model to
say something without yet recognizing
what it's saying. And then once it's
said it, it's kind of like on that track
and it has to balance being coherent
verbally with like I shouldn't say that.
It takes a while for it to cut itself
off. Um, and we find that if we suppress
punctuation, which would be an
appropriate grammatical time to cut
yourself off, you can get it to like
keep doing more of the jailbreak. Um,
and that's a competing mechanism thing,
right? There's a part which is
recognizing what am I talking about?
What should I do? And then there's a
part which is completing it and they're
fighting for who's going to win.
Um okay. Um do you know the process for
the models like
um Cool. Let's talk about Yeah. Okay. So
So I think Mike would be very
disappointed if I didn't talk about this
one. So this is a poem um a rhyming
couplet written by Claude. Um he saw a
carrot and had to grab it. His hunger
was like a starving
rabbit. It's like kind of good.
Um,
so how does it do this, right? It's like
kind of tricky, right? Because to write
a rhyming thing, you better end with a
word that rhymes, right? But you also
need to like have it kind of make
semantic sense. And if you wait to the
very end, you can back yourself into a
corner where there's no next word that
would be like metrically correct and
rhyme that would make sense. You kind
of, you know, logically should be
thinking ahead a little bit of like
where you're trying to go. Um, and we do
see this. So, actually, um, he saw a
carrot and had to grab it. New line. And
so, on that new line token, it's
actually there's there's a feature for
like,
um, you know, things um, rhyming with
it. So this is like after words ending
in it or eaten poems and those feed into
rabbit and habit features. And then the
rabbit feature is sort of being used to
to get starving and then ultimately
rabbit and we can
[Music]
um we can suppress these. So, if we
suppress the rhyming with it thing, we
get
um blabber
grabber salad bar. And that's because of
the ab sound is still there. So, it'll
just like rhyme with the ab part. Um if
we um inject
green, you know, it will now write a
line ending or rhyming with green
sometimes ending with it. Um if we put
in a rhyme with a different thing, it'll
sort of go with e. I think I don't know
if we have it here, but if you just
literally suppress the rabbit, it will
make something ending in habit when it
rhymes. Um, and this was pretty neat.
This is like the smoking gun. This is
like, oh, okay, like literally here is
here's a model component. When we look
at the data set examples when this is
active, it's literal instances of the
word rabbit and
bunny. A forward pass on this model,
that feature is active on the new line
at the end of the sentence. And the
model writes a rhyme ending in rabid.
And if we turn this off, then it like
doesn't do that anymore. So it's like
very definitely thinking about like that
is a place to take this. Um and then
that influences the line that's coming
out. And so that's a place where even
though it's saying one token at a time,
it's like has done some planning in some
sense, right? Here's a target
destination and then like writing
something to writing something to get
there. Um there's equivalent things.
There's a incredible thing with
unfaithfulness. I'll just say sometimes
the model is lying to you and if you
look at how it got to its answer, you
can tell um in this case it's using a
hint and working backwards from the hint
so that its math answer will agree with
you and you can tell because you can
literally see
like you can see it taking your hint
which is the number four working
backwards to divide by five to give you
a point 8. So when you multiply by five
you will get four and it will agree with
you which is not what you want. What you
would want is something like this where
it is only using information from the
question to give you the answer to the
question. Um, but if you just look at
the explanations, they look the same.
They look like it's doing math, right?
And so here there's a competing thing of
like, should I use the hint, which would
would have made sense in pre-training.
It'd let you guess the answer better,
and you're rewarded if you say the next
token. Well, so maybe the human's right,
and you should use the hint. Should I do
the math actually? And um, these are
competing strategies. They're happening
kind of at the same time. um on the
right, you know, um this one wins.
How does that work?
They're both available. Yes. How does it
come into this like obviously there's no
time constraint?
Is there some incentive or motivation
driving that?
I think like that's the question. So I
think you know I think in this paper we
really did we were able to say like
which strategies were used when it got
to this answer but the why I don't think
we've really nailed down. Um you know I
think that to some extent it could be we
could look at some of this more
carefully. I think in the hallucination
case we had a bit of a hint right it was
like recognizing the entity so I'm going
to do the refusal thing or let it
through. Um here though um my strong
suspicion is that that like it's just
doing both but in a case where um it's
more confident in one answer that shouts
louder. So it doesn't know what the
cosign of this is. So all that's left is
following the hint. Um but I think a big
caveat is that like we're not modeling
attention at all and attention is very
good at selecting right we've got this
QK gating right that's like a bilinear
you know bilinear thing. um you could
really pick with that and we're not
modeling how those choices are made. So
I wouldn't be surprised if for a lot of
these attention is crucially involved in
choosing which strategy to use while the
MLPs are heavily involved in executing
on those strategies and in that case
we'd be totally blind um to to what's
going on here.
I've been modeling this idea for a
while. Um, how would we prepare?
I mean, that's like a billion dollar
question. If I literally knew the answer
to that and it would worked really well,
I couldn't tell you. I would just like
go make Claude the best model in the
world cuz it's always accurate. But, but
I don't know the answer, so I can
speculate. I mean, I think I think like
it is in some sense an impossible
problem for exactly this reason. And so
um I think I think like you could try to
train better have the models be better
calibrated on their self-nowledge. You
could you know I think with the thinking
tags basically with like the reasoning
models is a straightforward way where
you do let the model check things and I
think models are much better on
reflection than they are on the forward
pass because I think the one forward
pass is just limited for like these
physical reasons. Um I think as an
effective strategy that might that might
be more the way um than than like not
allowing like how do you keep the
creativity in another possibility is you
could make the model dumber somehow. So
maybe you could make a model which
doesn't hallucinate but it's just dumber
because it uses a bunch more capacity
just for like checking itself in the
forward pass. Um and it could be when
models are smart enough people might
take that trade-off. Do you think that
the underlining architecture the
transform architecture?
Yeah, I think that's one of the sins
here. It's possible that like with a
recurrent thing, you could just give it
a few more loops to to check stuff. I
mean the other if you could fully
adaptive compute, you could just have it
go until it's some level of confident,
right? And get variable compute per
token um and then sort of sort of fail
if it's not. I think there is a tricky
thing about hallucination is like people
think of it as being like a well-
definfined thing but like you know it's
producing like reams of text like which
word is the one that went wrong you know
um and there are some very factual
questions where that's true but I think
if you think more generally like what
would make a given token a hallucination
it's like a little bit less clear
um I want to just see was if there's
anything yeah okay so there's nothing
else here other than like if you want
more read the stuff Um and um I get this
probably this ends formally in like 2 or
3 minutes. Is that Yeah. So I will just
be done now and then people can clap and
people can leave if they want but I will
just stay for questions for a while and
I'm happy to like continue doing
questions as long as people want. So
thank you.
[Applause]