This is CS231N
and uh I'm professor Falei from computer
science department. I will be co-eing
this uh quarter with professor Isan
Adelli and uh my graduate student Zay.
So you'll meet them as well as our
wonderful uh TA team that you will meet
later. So I just want to uh get started.
Yeah. So this is what excites me that um
AI has become such an interdisciplinary
um field that what you're going to learn
in this class of course it's very
technical it's about computer vision and
deep learning but I really do hope that
you take it to whichever discipline you
work in and are passionate about and
apply it. So we hear a lot about the
field of AI. So how do we position uh
computer vision and the scope of this
class? If you consider AI as this big
bubble, um computer vision is very much
a integral part of AI. Uh some of you
have heard me saying that not only
vision is part of intelligence, it's a
cornerstone to intelligence. Unlocking
the mystery of visual intelligence is
unlocking the mystery of intelligence.
But one of the most important tools,
mathematical tools to uh to solving AI
is uh machine learning or some people
call statistical machine learning. And
this is exactly um you know what we will
be talking about within the field of
machine learning. Uh in the past 10 plus
years, we have seen a major revolution
called deep learning. And I'll explain a
little bit of what deep learning is.
Deep learning is a set of uh uh
algorithmic techniques that is built
around uh a family of algorithms called
neuronet networks. And uh so if you ask
me to pinpoint the the scope of this
class, we'll not be able to cover the
entirety of computer vision. We'll not
be able to cover the entirety of machine
learning or deep learning, but we're
going to cover the core intersection of
these two fields. And of course um just
like the entirety of AI, computer vision
is becoming more and more a uh
interdisciplinary field. A lot of the
techniques we use as well as the
problems we work with intersect with
many different other fields like natural
language processing, speech recognition,
robotics and AI as a whole is a field
that intersects with mathematics,
neuroscience, computer science,
psychology, physics, biology and many
application areas from medicine to law
to education uh and business and so on.
So what you will get for this lecture,
our first lecture is I'll give a very
brief history of computer vision and
deep learning and then uh professor
Delhi will uh go over the overview of
this course and lay the groundwork of
how this course is set up and what our
expectations are.
So you know the history of vision did
not begin when you were born or humanity
was born. The history of vision began
540 million years ago. You might you
might ask what happened 540 million
years ago? Why are we pinpointing a
relatively specific date or year in
evolution? Well, it's because a lot of
fossil studies have shown us there is a
mystery period called um Cambrian
explosion. It is the fossil studies
showed about 10 million years in
evolution. During that time, which is a
very short period of time for evolution,
we see the explosion of animal species
in the fossil study. Which means before
Cambrian explosion, life on Earth was
pretty chill. It was actually in the
water. There's no land yet. No animals
on the land yet. And animals just float
around around. So what caused this
explosion in animal speciation? There
were many theories from climate to
chemical composition of the ocean water.
But the most uh compelling one of the
most compelling theories was the onset
of ice. uh the first animal a trilobyte
um they gained photosensitive cells. So
the eyes we were talking about were not
sophisticated lenses and retinas and
nerve cells. It was literally a very
simple pinghole and that pinhole
collected light. Once you collected
light
is completely different without senses
life is metabolism. It's very passive.
It is just metabolism and you come and
go. With senses, you become an integral
part of the environment that you might
want to change. You might want to
actually uh survive in it. Some some
animals becomes your or plants become
your dinner and you become someone
else's dinner. So evolutionary forces
drives
um um intelligence to evolve because of
the onset of senses because of the onset
of vision along with uh haptics or or
tactile sensing those are the two most
uh the oldest uh senses for for animals.
So that entire course of 540 million
years of evolution of vision is the
evolution of intelligence. Vision as one
of the primary senses of animals drove
the development of nervous system. The
development of intelligence. Almost all
animals on earth today we know of have
vision or use vision as one of the
primary senses. Humans are especially
visual animals. More than half of our
cortical cells are involved in uh visual
processing and we have a very complex
and convoluted visual system. So this is
what excites me to enter the field of
vision and I hope it excites you. So um
now let's just fast forward from uh u
fast forward from uh Cambrian explosion
to actually human civilization. Um
humans does innovate and not only we see
we want to build machines that see. So
here is a a drawing by a couple of
drawings by of course Leonardo Davinci
who was just forever um curious about
everything. He he studied um camera
obscura for uh how to make seeing
machines. in fact that uh even way
before him in ancient Greece and in
ancient China, we have seen documents
about uh you know thinkers, philosophers
thinking about how to make uh how to
project objects through pinholes and to
to uh create images of objects. And of
course in our modern life cameras have
truly exploded. But uh but cameras are
not enough for seeing just like eyes are
not enough for seeing. These are
apparatus. We need to understand how
visual intelligence happens and that's
really the crux of this course. So let's
let's just talk about the a little bit
of the history that brought us to this
intersection of deep learning and
computer vision. So um so let me go back
to the 1950s. Um the 1950s a set of very
critical critically important uh
experiments happened in neuroscience and
that was the study of the visual
pathways of mammals especially the
seinal work by Hubo and Viso. They used
uh electrodes to put into live cats
anesthesized and then they study the
receptive field of neurons that are in
the primary visual cortex. What they
have learned to their surprise are two
very important things. One is that um
vis uh uh neurons that are responsible
for seeing in the primary visual cortex
have their own individual receptive
fields. Receptive fields means that for
every neuron there's a part of space it
actually sees. It's not all the space.
It's not very big. It tends to be a very
uh uh confined patch of the space and
within that space it sees uh uh
specialized patterns simple patterns
when the the the when you're measuring
from the early uh early part of the uh
uh visual pathway and by and large in
the primary visual cortex which is
around here in the back of the head not
near your eyes um it's oriented edges or
moving oriented edges. So every neuron
some neuron will be seeing the edge like
this, some will be seeing an edge like
this or this. And uh that's how vision
the computation in the brain begins. The
second thing they learned is that uh
visual pathway is hierarchical. As you
move beyond the the visual pathway, the
neurons feed into other neurons and
these the neurons in the higher uh
layers or deeper layers of the visual
hierarchy have more complex receptive
field. So if you begin with
oriented edges, you might feed into a
corner receptor, you might feed into a
an object receptor. I'm overly
simplifying but that's the concept is
that neurons feed into each other and
then they create this big network of um
uh of uh computation. Of course most of
you sitting here are already thinking
the way I've been describing this will
have a profound impact on the modeling
the neuronet network modeling of uh
visual algorithms. Let's keep going.
That's year
1959. It's very early studies of uh
scene. By the way, um about 30 years
later uh maybe not quite 20 something
years later, Huba Visel won the Nobel uh
Nobel Prize in medicine for studying
this uh uncovering the the uh principles
of visual processing.
Another um milestone in the early
history of computer vision was the first
PhD thesis of computer vision. Most
people attribute Larry Roberts in 1963
writing the the first PhD thesis just
studying shape and this is a very very
character uh representation of the world
and the idea is that can we take a shape
like this and understand the the
surfaces and the the corners and
features of this shape um it's intuitive
that humans do. So an entire PhD thesis
is developed uh is devoted to this and
that's the beginning of computer vision
and uh and around that time in 1966
um uh as an MIT professor uh created a
summer project in MIT and asked to hire
a few undergrads very smart ones um to
study uh vision And the goal was pretty
much solve computer vision or solve
vision for one summer. Of course, just
like the rest of the history of AI, we
tend to be over optimistic of what we
can do in a short period of time. So
vision did not get solved in in that
summer. In fact, it has blossomed into
an incredible computer science field. If
you go to our annual conferences every
year now it has more than 10,000 people
attending but 1960s is where you know
between Larry Robert's uh PhD thesis as
well as uh as well as this kind of
project we in our field consider that
the beginning of the field of computer
vision.
A seminal book was written in the 1970s
by David Barah who um unfortunately died
too early. He wanted to study vision
systematically and start to consider how
visual processing happens. Even though
this is not explicitly stated but there
is a lot of inspiration from you know
neuroscience and cognitive science. He
was thinking about you know if you look
at if if a um if you take a input image
how do we visually process and
understand the image maybe the first
layer is more like edges just like we
saw uh he calls it primal sketch and
then there is a 2 and 1 halfd sketch
which uh uh uh you know separates
different uh uh depth um u of the the
objects in the image. So the ball is the
foreground object and then the the the
grass here. Oh no, not grass. The floor
ground here is the background. So he
does these two and a halfD sketch and
then finally he he believes David Mar
believes the the the grand holy grail
victory of solving vision is to know the
entire full 3D representation. And that
is actually a um the hardest thing of
vision. Let me digress for 20 seconds
because um if you think about vision
right for all animals it's a illposed
problem. Since the early trilobytes who
collected light from underwater
light the world through photons is
projected on something on a surface more
or less 2D at that time it was just I
don't know some patch in the in the
animal but right now for us it's a it's
a retina um but the actual world is 3D
so recovering
3D information the entire entire 3D
world
from 2D images is the fundamental
problem nature had to solve and computer
vision has to solve and mathematically
that's a illpose problem. So what did
linker do? Anybody have a wild guess?
>> Yes, nature the trick that nature did is
develop mult multiple eyes mostly too.
Some animals have more than uh more than
two and that's and then you triangulate
information but two eyes are not enough.
You actually have to understand
correspondences and all that. We'll
touch on some of these topics but there
are other computer vision classes in uh
in Stanford offers that also
specifically talk about 3D vision. But
the point is it's a very hard problem
and and we have to solve it. Nature has
solved it. humans have solved it but not
to extreme uh precision. In fact, humans
are not that precise. You know, I
roughly know the 3D shapes but I don't
have you know geometric precision of all
the shapes. So that's that's one thing
to consider and appreciate how hard this
problem is. Another thing that is very
different for uh computer vision and and
language is actually something
philosophically subtle. Language doesn't
exist in nature. You cannot point to
something and say there's language.
Language is a purely generated
thing. I don't even know what word to
use, right? It comes through our brain.
It's generated. It's 1D. It's
sequential.
So this actually has profound
implication in the latest wave of Gen AI
algorithms is this is why these LLMs
which is outside of the scope of this
class is so powerful because the the we
can model language that way but vision
is not generated. There is actually a
physical world out there respecting the
laws of physics and materials and all
that. So vision has very different
tasks. So I just want you to appreciate
uh the difference between language and
vision and and actually frankly
appreciate nature how how it solved this
problem. Okay let's keep going. 1970s.
Um the early pioneers of computer vision
without data, without really much of uh
powerful computers, without um the
mathematical advances we have seen today
are already beginning to solve some of
the harder problem of computer vision.
For example, recognition of objects here
in um in Stanford. One of the pioneering
work is called uh generalized cylinders
by Rodney Brookke and Tom Binford. And
ironically Rodney Brooks uh today is on
campus actually some part over there
giving uh giving a talk at the robotics
conference and he went on to become one
of the greatest roboticists of our time
and was founder of uh uh Roomba and many
other robots. And then uh not very far
from us in another part of Palo Alto uh
researchers have worked on these uh also
compositional uh compositional um um u
models of uh human body and and objects.
And then in the 1980s
um digital photos start to appear. At
least photos start to appear and people
can digitize that a little bit. And then
um there are some great work in edge
detection. You look at all this and um
it probably feels a sense of
disappointment, right? Like I mean it's
kind of trivial to get some sketches and
edges and it's not really going anywhere
if that's how that's how vision you know
uh works at that time. And in fact,
you're not so wrong. That was around the
time um before many of you were born
that we entered AI winter. The field a
entered AI winter because the enthusiasm
and hence funding for AI research has
really dwindled. A lot of things didn't
deliver. Computer vision didn't deliver,
expert systems didn't deliver, robotics
didn't deliver. But under the hood of
this winter, a lot of things uh a lot of
research start to grow uh from different
fields like computer vision, NLP,
robotics. So let's also look at another
strand of research that had a profound
implication in computer vision is that
cognitive and neuroscience continue to
blossom. And what is really important
especially for the field of computer
vision is cognitive and neuroscience is
starting to point to us the northstar
problems we should work on. For example,
psychologists have told us there's
something special about seeing nature,
seeing uh seeing real world. Uh this is
a uh this is a study by uh Vidderman who
shows that the detection of bicycles on
two images differ depending on if the
images are scrambled or not. Think about
it from a photon point of view. These
two bicycles land in the same location
on your retina, but somehow the rest of
the image impacts uh the the the
viewer seeing the the objects in in
um in in in the target object. So there
is something telling us that seeing the
entire forest or entire world uh impacts
the way we see objects. It also tells us
visual processing is very fast. Here's
another direct measure of how fast we we
uh we detect objects. This is an early
1970s uh experiment um showing people uh
a video and uh and the the task for the
human uh the subject is to detect the
human in one of the frames. I suppose
every one of you have seen that human in
one of the uh frames. But think about
how remarkable your eyes are or your
brain is because uh you've never seen
this video. I didn't tell you which
frame the the the target object would
appear. I did not tell you what the
target target object would look like,
where it is and gestures and all that.
Yet you have no problem detecting the
humans. So that is and on top of that
these uh frames are played at 10 hertz
which means you're seeing every frame
for only 100 milliseconds. And this is
how remarkable our visual system is. In
fact, uh, Simon Thorp, another, uh, uh,
uh, cognitive neuroscientist, have
measured the speed. If you hook people
up in EG caps and show them complex
natural things and ask human subjects to
categorize things from animals without
uh, versus things without animals,
hundreds of them, and then you measure
the brain wave. It turned out after 150
milliseconds of seeing a photo uh your
brain already has a signal of a
differential signal that categorizes.
You might not be so impressed because
compared to today's GPUs and modern
chips 150 milliseconds is really orders
of magnitude slower. But you got to
admire our wet wear. our brain, our
neurons don't work as fast as
transistors. 150 millisecond is actually
really fast. Uh it's only a few hops in
the brain in terms of neuroprocessing.
So yet again, this is telling us humans
are really good at um um seeing objects
and categorizing them. In fact, not only
were so good at seeing objects and
categorizing them, we even developed
specialized brain areas that have expert
ability in recognizing faces or places
or body parts. And these are discoveries
by MIT uh neurohysiologists in the 1990s
and early 21st century. So all these
studies tell us well we should not just
be studying these kind of character
shapes or the sketches of images. We
really should go after uh important
fundamental problems that drives visual
intelligence. And one of those problem
that everything has been telling us is
object recognition. is object
recognition in natural setting. There's
a lot of objects out out there in the
world and studying this is going to
unlock is going to be part of the
unlocking of visual intelligence. And
that's what we did as a field. We
started by uh looking at how we can
separate foreground objects from
background objects. This is called uh
recognition by grouping. in the 1990s.
Keep in mind we're still in AI winter,
but research is actually happening and
progressing. And then there is uh um you
know studies of features and and this is
some of you might still remember like
sift features and matching and when I
enter grad school the most exciting
thing was face detection. I remember
that first year in my grad school this
paper was published and five years later
the first digital camera used this
paper's algorithm and delivered uh
automatic face focus because of uh face
detection. So things start to work and
be taken into industry and then around
the early 21st century a very important
thing start to happen is internet start
to happen. when internet start to happen
um data start to proliferate and the
combination of digital cameras and
internet start to give the field of
computer vision some data to work with.
So in that early days we're working with
thousands of d uh images or tens of
thousands of images to study the visual
recognition problem or the object
recognition problem. So you've got uh
data sets like Pascal Visual Object
Challenge or Caltech 101. So that was
I'm going to pause here. Um and uh and
and this is where the the the first
thread of computer vision start to
progress and you might be wondering why
is she proing uh pausing because I'm
going to come back and talk about deep
learning. So while
you know this field of vision was
progressing through neurohysiology
to computer vision to cognitive neur uh
neuroscience to computer vision again a
separate effort is going on in parallel
and that eventually became deep
learning. It started from these early
studies of uh neuronet network things
like perception and uh and people like
Ramart started to you know work and of
course Jeff Hinton in his early days
start to work with a small number of
artificial neurons and look at how that
can can process information and learn.
Um and you've heard uh people like uh
the great minds like Marvin Minsky uh
and his colleagues uh working on on
different aspects of these uh
perception. But he also did Marvin
Minsky did say that uh perceptuals
cannot um cannot learn these X or logic
functions and that caused a little bit
of a setback in neuronet network. Well,
things continue to progress despite the
setback. And one of the most important
work
before the inflection point, first
inflection point is this neocognitron
work by Fukushima in Japan. Fukushima
handdesigned
a neuronet network that looks like this.
So it has about six or seven or five or
six layers and then he kind of he kind
of designed the different functions
across the layers which you will learn
more that more or less was inspired by
the the visual pathway that I was
describing. Remember the CAD experiment
from simple receptive field to more
complicated receptive field and he was
doing that here. you know the early
layers have simple functions and then
the later layers have more complex
functions um and and the simple ones he
call it convolution or he uses the
convolution function and the more
complex one he was pulling the
information from the convolution layers
so Neocognitron
was really a engineering fee because
every parameter was handdesigned he has
there are hundreds of parameters he has
to just meticulously put them together
so that this small neuronet network can
recognize digits or letters.
So the real breakthrough came around
that time in 1986 is a learning rule.
That learning rule is called back
propagation. It's going to be one of our
first classes to show you that Ramahar,
Jeff Hinton and they they they
took neuronet network um um um
architecture and introduced a error
correcting objective function so that if
you put in some input and know what the
correct output is, how do you take the
difference between what the neuronet
network outputs versus the actual
correct answer and then propagate the uh
the information back so that you can uh
um improve the parameters along the
neuronet network and that propagation
from the output back to the entire
neuronet network is called back
propagation. it follows some of these
basic calculus chain rules and uh that
was a watershed moment for a neuronet
network algorithm. So one of the most
and of course we're still smack in the
middle of AI winter all these work was
uh was happening without public fanfare
but of course in in the world of
research these are very important
milestones. One of the most earliest
applications of this uh neuronet network
with back propagation is Yamakun's
convolutional neuronet network made in
the 1990s when he was working in the
Bell labs and uh what he did is just
created a slightly bigger network about
seven layersish and uh and made it good
enough with great engineering uh
capability to recognize letters and it
was actually shipped to uh some part of
the US postal offices and banks to to
read digits and letters. So that was a
um application of early neuronet
network. And then um uh Jeff Hinton and
Yan Lun continue to work on your
network. It didn't go very far because
um despite these um improvements and
tweaks of these neuronet network things
more or less just stalled. you know, we
uh they collected a big data set of
digits and letters and digits and
letters kind of was quasy soft in terms
of recognition. But if you put the
system through, you know, the kind of uh
uh digital photos that the
neuroscientists were using to recognize
cats and dogs and microwaves and chairs
and flowers, it just didn't work. And uh
uh a huge part of this problem is the
lack of data. And uh lack of data is not
just an inconvenience. It's actually a
mathematical problem because these uh
these algorithms are high-capacity uh
algorithms that actually needs to be
driven by lots of data in order to to
learn to generalize. And there is some
deep mathematical principles behind this
rules of generalization and model
overfitting. And data was
underappreciated was underlooked because
most people are just looking at these
architectures. They did not realize that
data is part of the first class citizen
for for uh machine learning and deep
learning. So this is part of the work
that my lab uh my students and I did in
the early 2000s um that we recognize
this importance of data. We hypothesized
that the whole field was uh was actually
missing this underappreciating the
importance of data. So we went about and
collected a huge data set called image
net that has 15 million images after
cleaning a billion images. And this uh
15 million images were sorted across
22,000 categories of objects. We
actually studied a lot of the cognitive
and psychology literature to to
appreciate that 22,000
um uh images uh were uh oh sorry 22,000
categories were roughly in the order of
the number of categories that uh humans
learn to recognize in the early years of
their life. And then we open sourced
this data set and created a imageet
challenge called the large scale visual
recognition challenge. We curated a
subset of image net of a million images,
a million plus images and a thousand
object classes and then ran an
international uh object recognition um
challenge for for many years. And the
goal is that we ask uh researchers to
participate and their goal is to create
algorithms. It doesn't matter which kind
of algorithms. And then we'll test you
on your algorithm's ability to recognize
photos and see if you can call out these
a thousand uh object classes in as
correctly as possible. And here are the
errors, right? Like first year we run
this uh uh we run this uh um uh
competition, the the error the algorithm
the best performing algorithms error was
nearly 30%. And it's really pretty
abysmal because humans can perform under
like say 3% error and then 2011 it
wasn't that exciting but something
happened in 2012 that was the most
exciting year. That year
um Jeff Hinton and his students
participated in this challenge using
convolutional neuronet network and they
reduce the error almost by half and uh
and truly showed the power of deep
learning algorithms. And so the
participating algorithm in 2012 image
challenge was called Alex Net. And uh
the funny thing is if you look at Alex
net um it's not that different from the
Fukushima's neo cognitron 32 years ago
but two two major things happened over
between these two one is that back
propagation happened it's a principled
mathematically rigorous learning rule so
that you don't have to ever use hand to
tune parameters and that was a major
breakthrough theoretically. Another
breakthrough was uh was u um was data.
The recognition of data and uh the
understanding of data driving these
highcapacity models which eventually
will have trillion parameters but at
that time was millions of parameters was
critical for for uh for setting off the
deep learning uh uh you know the the the
to for for this to work. And really many
people consider the year of 2012 the and
the Alex net algorithm that won the
image net challenge the historical
moment of the birth of or rebirth of
modern AI or the birth of deep learning
revolution.
And of course the reason many of you are
here is since then we are in the era of
deep learning explosion. If you look at
computer vision's um uh main annual
research conference called CVPR uh the
number of papers have exploded and arc
paper has exploded and many new
algorithms since then have been invented
uh to participate in the image that
challenge in the following years. We're
going to study some of these algorithms
but the the the point is that some of
these algorithms uh beyond Alex that
have had a profound impact in the
progress of uh of the field of computer
vision and into the applications of
computer vision. So um so a lot of
things have happened that we're going to
cover some of these. Not only the field
of computer vision made a major progress
in the in creating algorithms to
recognize everyday objects like cats and
dogs and chairs. We also quickly right
after uh image that challenge uh the
2012 uh moment. We've got algorithms
that can recognize uh um uh you know
much more uh much more complicated uh
images, can retrieve images or can do
multiple object detections, can do image
uh uh segmentation. These are all
different tasks in visual recognition
that you'll find yourself getting
familiar with throughout this course
because vision is not just calling out
cats and dogs. There's so much in in the
nuanced ability of visual recognition
and uh and of course vision is not just
static images. So their work in video
classification, human activity
recognition. I'm showing you this
overview. You will learn some of these.
It's uh these are all um you don't have
to understand exactly all what's going
on here but I want you to appreciate uh
the the the different the variety of
vision tasks. medical imaging. Those of
you who come from a medical uh field is
you know whether it's radiology or
pathology or or even other aspects of
medicine is deeply visual and this has a
profound impact. Um you know scientific
discovery even the uh the seinal uh
picture you probably remember of the
first photography of black hole is uh
uses a lot of computer vision. um and
computational photography techniques. Of
course uh you know applications in the
sustainability and environment is also
um you know computer vision contributed
a lot of that and uh and uh we also have
made a lot of progress in image
captioning uh right after the image that
uh 2012 moment this is actually work by
Andre Capathy when he was my student his
uh thesis work um then we uh also worked
on you know relationship ship
understanding. So not only uh not only
visual intelligence is about seeing
what's on the pixel, you also see what's
beyond pixels including relationships of
uh of objects. Um and also style
transfer. Um a lot of this work you will
actually Justin Johnson who will come to
guest lecture this course will tell you
all about his seminar work in uh in
style transfer. Um and of course in
generative AI eras we get these really
incredible results like you know face
generation and uh uh this is the very
early days of image generation of Dolly
that I think this is the early Dali of
course now midjourney and everything has
gone beyond these avocado and peach
chairs but uh but really we are squarely
in the most exciting modern era of AI
explosion. The the the um combination
the three converging forces of
computation, algorithms and data have uh
have uh taken this field just to a whole
different level where we're now totally
out of AI winter. I would say we're in
an AI global warming period
and I don't I don't see any of this
slowing down. So um for both good and
bad reasons and also you know just a
word because we are in the Silicon
Valley we're in the very building of uh
Juan building and Nvidia uh lecture hall
so we cannot ignore also the progress of
uh hardware and what that played. So
here is just the the um the the the flop
per dollar graph for Nvidia's GPUs. And
before 2020, you know, the progress was
steady. But as soon as deep learning
started to drive these um these uh GPUs
and chips, you can just see the the the
the G-flops have just completely taken
off. And uh we're just by alien measure
we are in this accelerated curve of uh
of lots of compute as well as lots of
AI. And these are just different graphs
showing you conference attendance,
startups and enterprise applications in
AI all across not just computer vision
but also NLP and others have um have uh
just exploded. Okay. So quickly, last
but not the least, it's been exciting.
There has been a lot of successes, but
there is still a lot to be done in
computer vision. So this problem is
still not totally solved and with great
tools comes with great consequences as
well, right? So um um computer vision
can do a lot of good, but it also can do
harm. For example, human bias.
Every single AI algorithm today, the
large ones are driven by data. And data
is an artifact of human activities on
earth and in history. And a lot of the
data carry our bias. And uh this gets
carried in AI systems. We have seen a
lot of face recognition algorithms
having the same kind of bias that humans
have. And we do have to really recognize
that we can also use AI to impact human
lives. Some for the good, think about
medical imaging. But some are
questionable. What if AI is solely
behind deciding your job or deciding
your financial loans? So um again,
is it totally bad? Is it totally good?
These are very complicated issues. This
is also why I always get so excited when
students from HNS or law school or
education school or business school
attend my class because not all AI
issues are engineering issues. We have a
lot of human factors and societal issues
to to solve. I'm also particularly
excited by AI's medicine and healthc
care use. And this is something really
dear to my heart that uh professor Delhi
and Zay who are also co-instructors of
this course. We three of us work on AI
for aging population as well as uh
patients and to try to use computer
vision to deliver um you know care to to
people. So this is a good use and also
even in terms of technology human vision
is remarkable. I want you to come out of
not only today's class but also this
entire course to appreciate despite how
much computer vision can do there's just
so much more nuance subtlety richness
complexity and also emotion in human
vision you know look at these kids
studying whatever that their curiosity
lead them or the humor in this image
there's still a lot more that computer
vision cannot do so I hope that continue
to entice you to study uh computer
vision. At this point, I'm going to give
the podium to uh professor Delhi to go
over the rest of the class. Thank you.
>> Awesome. Thank you, Fay. Uh
great start of the quarter and I hope my
microphone is working um right now.
Okay, good. I'm seeing some uh nodding
of heads. All right. Uh so
very excited to be here with you all and
um I'm hoping that um you will have a
fun and challenging course with an
amazing list of co-instructors that we
have and and great TAs.
So
in this class we are going to cover a
wide variety of topics around computer
vision use of deep learning in this
space categorized into four different
topics. We'll start with deep learning
basics and and let's start actually with
a simple question of what is computer
vision really. So at its core it's about
enabling machines
to see and understand images and
uh basically this is the most
fundamental task uh in the space uh in
this space is is image classification.
You give the model an image say of a cat
and the model should output a label cat
and that's it.
But it's uh this deceptively simple task
um is the foundation for much of more
complex applications from self-driving
to medical diagnosis and so on. So how
do we teach a machine to do this? One of
the simplest approaches is to use linear
classification as you can see in this
slide. So
imagine each of the images in our data
set is shown with a dot in that uh space
and each axis shows some sort of feature
uh which was driven from the image
itself. Here we are showing a 2D space
but uh for simplicity but the task of a
linear classifier is to find the hyper
plane or the linear function that
separates these two say cats from dogs.
But we all know that these linear models
often go just uh only so far. Um they
struggle when the data isn't cleanly
separable with a straight line. So the
question is what's next? We'll get into
uh the the topics of how to model more
complex patterns and um if if we do so
we often face challenges of overfeeding
and underfeeding which um are the topics
we will cover in the early lectures of
the the class and to strike a right
balance. the right balance.
We use techniques like regularization
uh to control model complexity and
optimization
to find the best fit parameters.
So these are the nuts and bolts of of
deep learning and and creating these u
uh models training models that not only
fits the data but also generalizes to
unseen and and new data as well. And now
comes the the fun part. Neural networks,
we've been talking about them uh quite a
lot. And what neural networks do unlike
the linear classifiers they they stack
multiple layers of um operations
to model nonlinear
um
functions to be able to either classify
to to solve the same problem of uh image
classification and so on. Um
these are the models powering uh
everything from uh Google photos and
then now everybody's familiar with chat
GPD chat GPTs vision models and so on.
Uh in this course we will uh go deep
into the
uh details of how they work, how they
are trained and we will be looking into
how to debugging and improving them.
After looking at the deep learning
basics, we will cover the topics of
perceiving and understanding the visual
world, which is a complex process that
involves interpreting a vast array of
visual information. And to do so, we
often first define tasks
that refer to specific challenges or
problems we aim to solve. Some of the
examples are object detection, scene
understanding, motion detection and so
on. And to solve um these tasks, we use
uh different models which are
computational and theoretical
frameworks we develop to mimic or
explain how our visual system
accomplishes these tasks. Uh one of the
examples of the these types of models is
uh neural networks.
So by aligning models and uh with with
tasks, we can create systems that can
see and interpret the world around us.
Speaking of tasks, let's uh go back to
the topic of image uh classification,
predicting a single label for an entire
image.
Um but we know that real world computer
vision is much richer than this and
let's walk through some of the tasks
that go beyond classification. First
semantic segmentation
um where we
we are not just labeling the
uh the object or the entire image as cat
or tree or whatever. Here we are looking
for labels for every single pixel in the
image. So every pixel is is a grass,
cat, tree or sky. But we don't uh
distinguish between individual uh
objects. And next we have object
detection
where um we now want to not only say
what is the what is in the image but
also pinpoint the location. And that's
why we create bounding boxes around the
objects and associate them with specific
labels. And finally we have instance
segmentation. We will uh review we'll go
into instance segmentation which is the
most granular of them all. It combines
the ideas of detection and segmentation
together and every object instance gets
its own mask.
So these tasks uh require you know much
deeper understanding special
understanding in images and they push
the models to do more than just
recognizing
categories.
The complexity doesn't stop with with
static images. Let's let's look at some
uh temporal dimensions. So there's the
task of video classification as Fe
talked about where we want to understand
what's happening in the in the video is
the is is there someone running jumping
or or dancing.
There is the topic of multimodal video
understanding which is combining vision
and sound and other modalities. uh for
example in this uh this this example the
person is playing a vibrophone to really
understand what's happening here we have
to create a blend of visual features and
audio features to be able to understand
what's happening and finally there is
the topic of visualization and
understanding that we we will be
covering in this class where we want to
interpret what's being learned uh by the
models and and um see an attention uh
frame or attention map of what the model
is is attending to to do a correct
classification and so on.
And then uh we have models beyond tasks.
we we look into models and uh there the
very first topic let me introduce to you
uh that we'll be covering is uh
convolutional neural networks or CNN's
there are a number of operations we will
be going over the details um in the
class starting from an image a number of
convolution sampling and fully connected
operations and finally uh creating the
output and beyond convolutional neural
networks we will
study uh recurrent neural networks for
sequential data and even newer
architectures such as
transformers and attention based uh
frameworks.
So next we will be covering some large
scale distributed training topics which
is kind of new uh this quarter. I'm sure
you've all heard about large language
models, large vision models and so on.
And uh we will be briefly discussing how
these models are actually trained. We
know that data and data sets are
expanding models and and large models
are are models models are becoming
larger and larger. And in order to train
such models, there are some strategies
for example data parallelization, model
paralization that we'll cover in this
class. But beyond that, there will be so
many challenges such as synchronization
between these models and workers and so
on.
as well as several other um aspects that
we'll be covering in one of the lectures
this uh quarter and and we will go also
some uh over some of the trends um for
training these large models. After
completing this topic, what we'll do
next is looking into
generative and interactive visual
intelligence
where we will first start with u with
self-supervised learning.
Self-supervised learning is a branch of
machine learning in which models learn
to understand and represent data by
getting some training signals from the
data itself. We will cover this this
topic. It's a it's um uh one of the
approaches that has enabled training of
large scale models using vast amounts of
data that do not require labels,
unlabeled data.
And they have played a key role in
recent breakthroughs in in computer
vision in general.
And we will talk a little bit about
generative models. They go beyond
recognition. They actually generate.
This is an example of the content of a
Stanford campus photo uh which is
reimagined in the style of Van Go's uh
star night. This is known as style
transfer. A classic application of neuro
generative uh techniques.
Generative models can now translate
language into images given a prompt. A
model like Dolly Dolly 2 generates an
entirely novel image.
This showcases how generative vision
models blend understanding, creativity,
and control in in their generations.
And you've probably heard recently about
the topic of diffusion models in in
general. That's another thing that we'll
be covering in u this quarter.
They basically learn to reverse a
gradual uh noising process to generate
uh images. And interestingly, in
assignment three, you will actually be
implementing a generative model that
generates emojis from
text u inputs from prompts. For example,
a face with a cowboy hat, which is den
noiseis from pure noise.
Vision language models are the next
topic uh topic of interest we will be
covering.
Um they connect text and images in a
shared representation space and given a
caption or or uh or image the model
retrieves or generates its corresponding
pair as you can see. So there are a lot
of advances in this area that we'll be
covering some of the key examples.
Again this is a key task for
uh crossmodel retrieval or understanding
and visual question answering and so on.
So we'll get get to that in the class
too. Moving beyond 2D, models can now
reconstruct and generate 3D
representations from images. And uh here
you can see uh some waxel based
reconstructions,
shape completion and even 3D object
detection for uh from single view
uh images. So 3D vision enables more
especially grounded understanding which
is crucial for robotics and AI ARVR
applications. And finally vision uh
powers empowers embodied agents
that act in the physical world. So these
models often must uh perceive, plan and
execute whether it's cleaning um up a
messy room or generalizing from human
demonstrations. So with with all of
these we will be covering different
topics around generative and interactive
visual intelligence and finally we will
cover some human- centered applications
and implications and as as um very
nicely explained. So there is um
computer vision and generally AI have
been um having a lot of impact in the in
the past years and it's very important
to to understand the human- centered
aspects and applications and some of
these impacts are reflected by these
awards that are um going to researchers
in in this space. Um it was first
recognized by the uh touring award 2018
which is the most prestigious technical
award given to major contributions for
of lasting importance for computing.
Jeff, Antonio, Benjio, and Yan Lon
um received the award for conceptual
engineering breakthroughs that have made
deep neural networks a critical
component of computing. Beyond that,
last year in in in 2024,
uh Jeffrey Inon was jointly awarded the
Nobel Prize in in physics
alongside John Hopfield for for their
foundational contributions to uh neural
networks. And finally, I want to very
briefly mention the learning objectives
for this class will be
formalizing computer vision applications
into tasks. As you can um see some of
the details here, we want to develop and
train vision models, models that operate
on on images and visual data, images,
videos and so on. Gain an understanding
of where the field is and where it is
headed. That's why we have some new new
topics also covered specifically in this
uh this year.
So the four topics that I mentioned
earlier, we will be going over the
basics in the very first very first few
weeks. Bear with us because these are
important topics and you need to
understand the the details first. How to
build the models from scratch and then
we'll get to more interesting exciting
topics of the day. um computer vision
and and finally we will have one uh big
lecture on human centered AI and and
computer vision. I want to just leave
you with what we'll be covering next
session that's that's going to be image
classification and linear classifiers
which will get us started with the world
of CS231. Thank you.