okay we'll look at the transer that
enterprises I think today's lesson I
look at the briefly the first three
lessons that you have it's going to be
less about going really deep in
algorithms although we will do a little
bit especially when we talk about the
key blocks for building agents but it's
more about what we're seeing um in the
in the market today I'll also give you a
few hints like if you're looking into
the Masters PhD some of the ideas that
you might track or if you want to do a
startup again some of the interesting
ideas that you might uh we might pursue
as well so let's start with some of the
trends that we that we seeing and I'll
maybe go very quickly on some of the
things that You' already seen and and
you know I'll try to keep it uh quick so
uh maybe if you look at a little bit of
the history and if I even go to my time
of of PhD and and um all of my peers my
my friends U my classmates were talking
about wow why is neural networks even in
these text books at the time support
reing Machines of decision trees more
less all the regation algorithms were uh
working you know quite better and um we
were thinking well neural networks would
just be odds like it's it was really
performing
horribly and actually my my um
officemate uh who used to play lots
of Chess By the way and if you're
looking intoing your Masters and PhD in
a in a limited amount of time don't play
chess all the time that's maybe the The
Lesson 12 today um he and I were talking
about okay we should really take this
this take this out but we were both
wrong at the end of the day and what is
it that changed and how come new
networks became so much better than
anything else one I think from
architecture point of view it's much
more easily paralyzable compared to many
of the other algorithms that we've we've
been working at the at the
time
second beyond beyond that you need the
training set right like to be able to
paralyze things you need lots of lots of
data to be able to make paralyzable
really know something something useful
to give context at the time I was
looking at detecting some cancer from
various CT images and I believe I had
access to about know 50 patients data
set so every time I I I I did the
training it was taking roughly 42
seconds and I was like oh my God it's
it's taking so much time every time I
click on you know restart 42 seconds of
wait time now it's pretty crazy right
like if you look at some of the large
models and how much they are taking
today it's uh you know sometimes it's
taking days sometimes weeks and
sometimes months depending on the size
of the of the model by the way as a side
note one of my worries is that we're not
learning fast enough like there was
something good about that 42 seconds
every 42 seconds I was changing
something I was learning what it did to
the training and it was at the time most
of support Vector machines everyone was
using support Vector machines okay if
you change this parameter this happens
if you change that parameter okay this
other thing happens you get intu very
very fast imagine being a researcher
working on large language models and
then you change something click on start
training and you get back to results
about four weeks from today so of course
that's one of my worries sometimes many
of us don't know why it works we're
getting intuition faster and faster but
uh as a side note like of everything
that's happening in the world like our
pace of getting intuition is much slower
than what it used to be now let's talk
about the data sets I said okay neural
networks are very paralyzable so that's
great but what about these data sets now
imagine getting it's not really all the
books but you know taking that aside for
a second all the books in the world or
all the websites in the world that's a
lot of data right but how do you create
the training set and you've probably
seen seen this in some of the prior
classes as well this technique called
masking which is you take a sentence I
love running or or you know any sentence
and you start masking the words and
you're trying to predict those words now
if you have the web and or or the books
all the books in the world this can
create lots and lots of training data so
now we solve the training data problem
we do not need to deal with only 50 know
patient data sets anymore we can we can
work with you know a huge amount of data
set and combine it with you know really
great improvements in gpus in tpus and
like especially in hardware and
all a sudden neural networks uh have
started and with the Transformer stru of
course you know there is lot of
improvement in some of the algorithms as
well but with the with the Transformer
structures all of a sudden it start
working really great and you're getting
all those all those uh awesome results
now now again looking at history I think
one of the moments that really
especially with
Enterprises um change the moment was um
when chat GPT launched in November 202
to um after that everyone realized oh my
God AI actually works better than we
thought it does I believe lots of
companies including Google had lots of
internal uh tools that showed know chat
GPT like you know chat experiences and
other experiences you know internally
but making it public a was a brave move
but but B I think uh it changed the
mindset with with everyone in the world
now going through you know some of these
other other things that we are seeing
and you've seen some of these problems
right like you give an image and you you
detect a label out of an image or you
give some speech and and you recognize
what that what that speech is
translation lots of AI problems we're
seeing lots of improvements especially
in the last one
decade and more than that with
generative AI you can actually go the
other way around as well like now
what used to be output you can give
input and it generates you know all
these images or or speech um Etc videos
you see you see all of that or or some
text you know poets
Etc so just to again give more context
so this is image classification on image
net and you see when it started in 2011
like this grap at least starts in 2011
um about 50% accuracy rate in in some of
the
algorithms and this graph at least is is
showing until 2022 and we've already
reached you know almost 91% and actually
it's Advanced even more with the you
know large models uh in general this is
huge amount of advancement inde when I
look at the time when me and my
classmates were doing our masters or
phds we were making some predictions
about where AI would be and I think we
where we
are
um we thought we would be here about in
100 years or so whereas we arrived there
in 15 years or or so something like that
so it's moved so much faster and and and
the last few years that acceleration has
even increased uh further you see it
everywhere speech recognition um so in
this uh in this uh data set it moved
from 13% in 2016 to it's a measurement
in 21 2 and a half% and and nowaday it's
actually much better but uh you know
open II's products Google's products
anthropic like when you look at some of
their their systems they're they're
working so much better than than some of
some of this but compared to you know
what we started with and this is only
2016 only eight years ago it's a day and
night
difference now I think I mentioned about
this it's it's neural networks a
Transformer structure of course um
there's lots of advancement in in
algorithm as well and I mentioned this
uh okay how do you uh generate the lot
of training sets this concept of next
token prediction um you take any
sentence and you start masking the
masking the keywords and that's how you
generate lots and lots of uh keywords
and uh at the end I think uh what
happens is you get something that's
versatile and effecting effective in
handling lots of different use cases
anywhere from a technical discussion or
kind of a friendto friend conversation
they're very versatile in their
capabilities and I don't need to tell
you because you've been trying this you
know all over I'm assuming and now when
you look at some of the uh main
algorithms or approaches to be able to
either build the base models or start
improving on them and I think you know
agents is a is an overloaded term but uh
like building an application or agent
that's specific to your use case what
you would usually want to do is get lots
of know expert responses like give a
prompt and he's the here is the output
from from an
expert you do this many times actually
many many times the issue is
that well first of all let's talk talk
about the good part it actually works
like once to do it many times tens of
thousands of times it works the is is
getting an expert to be able to give you
that much training set is not easy so
although the supervised fine tuning is
very effective it requires lots of
training set but also it requires like
finding those experts and being be able
to spend lots of time on them as well so
the more practical approach that we've
seen is you know usual reinforcement
learning from Human feedback essentially
you can have the your your base
algorithm generate multiple
options and let them in front of a a
human that says and hopefully an expert
that says thumbs up and thumbs down
giving a thumbs up and thumbs down is
significantly faster you know process
than providing a very expert opion
sometimes know you can do both of both
of those um and then you can feed these
inputs into your loss function for
optimization um of your of your uh large
language models so these are some of the
main approaches we we're seeing I'm
going fast in here because I know in
some of the other classes you you've
seen this and uh at least on Google S
you've seen uh
Gemini and um this is a project and I'll
go very fast on this one and this is all
public data but this was released in
December
and I think February there was another
another version that's already released
I think a few interesting things it's
it's multi model from day one and second
it's uh it has the ability to be able to
provide a very large context uh indeed
internally we're trying 10 million and
and um and we're getting really
interesting results and and good results
as well now maybe one interesting idea
for if for you as a PhD thesis or or
Master thesis or a
startup um you know search is very
fundamental to our lives and the search
algorithms are very fundamental to our
lives indeed you will see even to make a
large language model work well search is
fundamental to that as
well one question is is the input
context is
growing with a large language model with
a huge amount of input context be able
to replace search like the search
algorithms traditional search algorithms
either keyboard matching or embeddings
matching or deep retrial techniques will
it be able to replace essentially
traditional search algorithms in in
future so I think that's you know
something as a a food for thought
um but uh this is I think an very
interesting interesting problem and lots
of interesting research is going to
continue happening in that in that area
so as I said it's multimodel from from
start you can input images text audio
video and uh we actually get really
interesting interesting results and
here's one example uh in this example
you see um a physics problem and then
you give actually an image um and then
you you continue with your text and it's
able to provide a a pretty good uh
pretty good response and you can try on
AI Studio or many of many of this and as
I said large context is really
interesting and um if you want to try
with you know videos or what or with
very large amount of text I think it's
it's very interesting to to experiment
with those uh it's again available at
this link in in AI
studio um and I think this was one of
the reading materials that I that I
mentioned it's um a needle in TCH test
uh for any retrieval algorithm or for
large language models with with a larger
context let's drop a piece of sentence
or a or a piece of a video or or piece
of an image or or or or something which
is called the needle in a large amount
of text and see if the large language
model is able to extract extract that so
if you especially want to do more
research search on that idea about okay
how do I build a search engine using
just large language models this test
becomes really relevant for you but also
to be able to test all these large
language models as their input context
increases um this test is is a very
interesting test and then in the case of
Gemini I think green means it it's it's
it P the needle and red means it's it's
missed it um the results were very very
promising and I think in in some of the
reading material that I sent there are
results from from other uh other LMS as
well it's less about the specifics of
those results it's more about this test
and and learning it and uh and using it
in your research when
appropriate um and then this is a limb's
leaderboard I think Gemini made it to to
number one in August now it's not um
then it became number two then then it
changed again it's constantly changing
and that's maybe one of the artifacts of
what's happening in the world right now
if you look at 18 months ago but first
of all there was more or less one model
that was available to to anyone uh
through open AI um or at least one
really high performance model nowadays
that's changing quite uh quite a lot and
I think that's actually going to be
bringing some of the trends that we're
seeing in Enterprises as well and you
will see that uh in a
second all right so let let's look at
some of the Enterprise uh Trends now now
the very first one and maybe the obvious
one is that AI is moving so much faster
it's not a surprise right but all the
Enterprises are all about AI right now
so I've been doing this job you know for
for for a while now let's say two and a
half years ago or three years ago when
we have a new product in AI we would
usually you know barely be able to find
one or two customer know Enterprise
customer to Pilot it and we'll be like
wow this is
great that has completely changed now
for every feature that we're putting
immediately thousands if not tens of
thousands of Enterprises are like
calling us and wanting wanting to try
and and this is probably correct for any
of these any of these companies so
that's a big Trend change and a mindset
change when comes to Enterprises and how
they're looking but there's also like I
think theoretical reasons as well I mean
one of them as I said people understood
well AI could work but another one is
the amount of data needed to get
started has come down very very
significantly so before large models and
large language models a typical
Enterprise needed to collect some
training set and then need need to you
know clean it up and then usually
something went wrong they would go back
and redo it again and then it would take
months and and I've seen cases of taking
it years for them to be able to collect
all the training set and then feed it
into you know their you know training
algorithm or or machine learning
algorithm of their choice now that has
changed because all these large models
and large language models are already
trained with a huge amount of data where
the amount of
data so what it means is many
Enterprises just can take one of the
base models and can use it in their in
their
application or if
not like they can just add like let's
say you have a very custom application
that you want to work on the amount of
additional data that you need that you
need to provide is very significantly
less than what it used to be
before so this I think is really exper
things now people can you know start
things and and try things within days as
opposed to sometimes within years now
second and I think this is also a big
culture change in the world as well it
used to be that to be able to develop
any AI algorithm or
application you need to be an AI expert
a data
scientist someone who's trained like
either a master's PhD or lots of courses
in AI
that has completely changed
nowadays any developer and we see you
know lots of middle school students high
school students are doing this can start
building AI applications using large
language models and also reading a
little bit about okay how do I what do I
do to fine tune these
models so that's a big change and indeed
there a big culture change for uh for
all these companies who have been
working on AI as well indeed one thing
that I tell to my teams is that because
all of all of our team members were were
essentially producing or developing
products for AI
experts so that's a culture shift that I
think is happening in the world for the
producers of of these large language
models they're also trying to focus much
more on developers you see that's why
like open AI anthropic you know Google
Microsoft everyone is doing developer
events because any developer can provide
and produce AI applications nowadays and
and that was much less the case a few
years ago now if you think for a second
the number of AI experts or data
scientists versus number of developers
in the world maybe there's more than 100
100 scale that's also partially why we
are saying
an exponential growth everywhere like
all companies that's working on AI
nowadays is is seeing a big exponential
growth and this is one of the reasons
now literally anyone can go there and
start producing
AI now a few other technical
Trends um and I was partially wrong on
this one I thought we would have a
separate model
for um different let's say at least
domains like like for healthcare you
would have a different model and and for
finance you would have a different model
etc etc what is happening is the pace of
improvement in the Bas large
models H is is so large that you can
produce a base model A a domain specific
model and by the time the new uh you
know base model comes it's usually
already better than that domain specific
model so we've seen that a couple of
times
iteratively and the approach I think
many of the at least larger companies
are taking right now is produce um a
large
model that is very good in
reasoning now again another idea for you
is there is a master student PhD student
as a teases work undergrad project or a
startup how do you get you know these
large language models and and be able to
customize it perfectly for a specific
use case and you know potential domain
as well inde just Healthcare model is
nothing enough you need to like
healthcare has thousands of different
use cases and you might need a a
different model for different use cases
but uh if you're looking for another
idea to go pursue I think uh the world
can use more research in that area right
now I think many many people are already
have already started but that's at least
another another idea for for you to to
look at
into um another trend is it started with
all dance models and essentially which
means that uh during inference time
during running your know large language
model that that you trained and you
learned you would go and execute you
know every Noe of of your of your trans
Transformer that's also changing now
we're going more and more into efficient
sparse models so you do not maybe
necessarily need to go through every
note you can you can be much more
efficient about it and maybe you know
execute 10% of the paths or
Pathways and uh this uh you know is has
is is showing a transformative effect
because that means a your latency could
be much less and B your cost also much
much less as well so I think at least
that's a trend that we're that we're
seeing among other
things and I think I mentioned this I
personally thought there would be single
modality models there will be one for
image one for video it's all getting
combined into into one thing we're
seeing models that are able to
understand all kind of modalities and
and probably they'll be able to produce
all kind of modalities as
well now this is an interesting Trend
again 18 months ago especially for
Enterprises it was all about
okay which model do I use what is the
latest model what is the largest
model and that was the main you know
parameter for choosing what to use and
we're seeing that change now we're
seeing that it's really the choice of
the platform rather than than the model
one of the reasons is that every other
week there is a new model right so
um regardless from which whichever
company but but you you you you start
now you expect to to see another model
every few weeks every
month and especially Enterprises are
seeing that and uh for that they they
really want to be in a place where they
can try many models Al together in that
and again this is uhis and um you can
see you know this is different this is
more recent it's not yesterday but I
think it's a few weeks ago
you see there are several companies that
are producing really great large
language models they head-to-head again
very different from 18 months ago what
it meant is when you talk to Enterprises
and we did talk to maybe thousands of
them um and some of these attributes
like accessing a broader set of models
became very important and then ail to
customize these models on top of these
base models has become very important
and similarly choice and flexibility at
every level is very important I'll show
a diagram of how visited in verx AI I
think you would see similar kind of
diagrams everywhere but a typical
architecture or architecture whatever
you want to call it where you build on
some of these uh success models for uh
success factors for generative Ai and of
course especially for Enterprises being
able to manage these models is very
important so it needs to be able to
return results not 98% of the time it
needs to be able to return
99.9999% of the time so of course that
becomes very important as well if you're
building an actual production um
algorithm an application another Trend I
think the cost of API cost is
approaching zero which is also very
interesting um I think I mentioned some
of the reasons like dance models versus
sparse models there are many reasons
beyond that there lots of improvement in
the chip space gpus are getting better
tpus are getting better and you I'm not
sure how much more you will see this
trend probably you would like it to
continue to see one interesting fact is
for instance the the flash model
uh running that versus some of the open
source models we've done lots of
calculations it was cheaper to run a
flash model which is supposed to be not
free than an open source model because
you still need to figure out the
hardware and chips yourself and you need
to have some cost of management so maybe
the trend might slow down a little bit
because it's come to a a place where
running open source actually is almost
more expensive than than some of these
uh paid models uh but at least that's a
trend that we that we've seen um I think
the prices have come down uh at least
probably one and a half order of
magnitude since how things get get
started now good news is usually the
latency went down with it as well and
that's very important because the
smaller the latencies the the the
broader the set of applications you can
do that fits that latency requirements
of your applications so uh we are seeing
the scale also go up as the
latency of of these models are going
down that
means you can build know more lat see
sensitive applications as a as a
result okay another huge huge huge trend
is search
and we see I I think every other
customer that I meet and probably every
other use case uh is starting to use
large language models and search
together some of them just make a call
to large language models and search
separately some of them they you like
they use grounding to be able to do it
but this is a big Trend that that that
wasn't there a year
ago so there are multiple reasons for it
um if you think about it large language
models are are great but they're
typically trained in the
past sometimes it's two weeks in the
past sometimes it's two months sometimes
it's six months but sometime in the past
so if you're asking the score for the
game last night you're not going to have
much success with large language models
another one is I think you all know this
but large language models hallucinate
even the best of the best ones still
hasate several percent of the time so
essentially they're they're lying to
your face but they're very confident
about it because they don't know they're
lying and for many of the applications
where factuality has become more
important we see people are going more
and more into okay I need to also
retrieve some data through search and
triangulate between what large language
model is doing and what search is
doing and third large language models I
think you all know this they're great in
reasoning they're able to they're great
in answering you know questions and that
is coming and maybe
combine 100 different sources and and be
able to design an answer for you the
issue is they cannot tell you which
exact
source that answer is coming from from
and again search has been pretty great
uh in citations and that creates for
many applications the level of authority
that the application needs to be able to
say hey I'm saying this because here is
the exact blur from exact this document
that's saying this and uh I think uh
especially Enterprises in many of their
use cases have been have been using the
so this is a huge Trend every other
application and use case as I said uh
seems to be know somewhere on it
especially Health Care Finance any kind
of know customer service how much is my
bill okay let me hallucinate about that
like things like that so it's a like you
really need search to be able to um you
know make the large language modes much
more factual and another maybe last
trend is we see that um many Enterprises
are interested in also their own
employee productivity
so we see lots of companies coming out
there with tools that are specifically
targeting employees of of a company and
and the companies are very interested in
those tools as well I think Google is
coming up with with something as well
but other examples gleen we've seen chat
GP Enterprise all about making you know
the employees more productive U as
well now uh I think we we summarize some
of this but uh um we've talked to many
many companies to be able to uh come up
with know with some of these Trends and
I mentioned the like success factors for
generative AI now has has really come
along these other factors like accessing
to broader set of models choice and
flexibility uh and ability to customize
now with that as I mentioned let's look
at you know one possible architecture
you know of course vertex AI is is the
one that my teams are building so I'm
most familiar with but I think many
companies have similar architectures so
choice and flexibility at every level I
think that's very important to provide
to to Enterprises like that's uh
probably all the way to chips um that's
why for in the case of vertex AI can use
GPU or or TPU and it's very important
because um at this time there is a huge
chip shortage in the world I would say
probably the the demand is 100 to supply
uh right now so being able to have a
choice is there is is quite important
again models like being able to provide
models from you know whatever company
you are the first party of your models
your own models other companies models
as well as open source models in one
place uh to to your customers to to the
Enterprises I think becomes very
important and then model builder and
agent Builder which are really the tools
to be able to customize based on these
base uh base models as I said um like at
least on vert.x I lots and lots of
different models including Gemini models
um you know Gemini pro at Le now
actually with two million context
window and all kind of models you know
not just for text generation but image
Generation Um speech to text and text to
speech as well as embeddings generation
as well but the key is uh you need to
provide the the
choice and then I think um especially in
vertex Ai and I see it in in other
platforms as well being able to provide
the uh open source models as well at the
same place because depending on the use
case I think different Enterprises is
looking for something else and being
able to compare them and evaluate them
by the evaluation tools become really
really important as well um becomes very
valuable to the to the Enterprises
same and now actually we have three and
a half sonets on on verx AI as well um
actually providing other other uh
providers other other companies models
as well uh so that again your customers
can
compare so and then I think uh once you
have these base models and then the
choice model builder and agent
Builder is how you get into to
customization and how you get into
building successful agents and and and
applications and then maybe like in the
next part of this uh lesson I'll focus
more on on these which is tuning and
distillation grounding extension and
function uh function calling as well but
if I were to give an overview because I
think uh given time will'll probably you
know go fast in the next section and uh
you know have time for question
questions as
well tuning is as you might s you know
guess you get your own use case you get
your own data with it how do I get the
base model be able to perform
specifically for your use case
distillation is um usually these base
model are are are super large and uh and
they're able to answer all the questions
in the world right and for many use
cases especially use cases of the
application you do not need that
indeed you'd rather have a smaller model
that is great in in your exact specific
use case and this solation essentially
is the is the concept of going from
large language models or generating
smaller models that
are as good as a large model in that in
your specific use case or and and and
and test
data grounding essentially I mentioned
it a little bit combining it with search
and and uh making your large language
models much more factual and you might
want to do it with the web search or web
data or you might want to do it with
with your own Enterprise data as well
but uh essentially combining with search
like that's what you should remember
when it comes to grounding and then
function calling or or
extensions and I sometimes call this as
I think you probably have watched this
show Who Wants To Be A Millionaire but I
think one of the things is okay you need
to call a call a like you have an option
to call a friend to ask a question and
it's there there are two things that are
pretty tricky here one you need to know
that oh okay that's a question that I do
not know and I need to call a friend and
second you need to be able to choose the
right friend to call when you know you
do not know the answer so I think uh
function calling is is like that a large
language model for instance is not going
to be able to book a flight ticket for
you or look up flight
schedules um but with a function calling
like let's say xedia has a has an
extension for that uh you you might have
your large language model be
successfully be able to do uh do that
again It's tricky because it needs to
still know that oh I can't do this I
need to call an extension and second
like for the case of the flight booking
it needs to call the xedia extension not
for instance the math extension which is
great in math but um no not necessarily
in Flight booking so I think uh this
next section which we will go a little
bit faster is going to really look into
these four uh areas fine tuning
distillation grounding and function
calling and then you look at fine tuning
I think you see lots of different
algorithms here and and as you go from
left to right um for anywhere from
prompt design which is not really a
training by the way it's essentially
you're just changing your prompt
to all the way to full fine tuning and
maybe this table shows some of them a
little bit
better in the case of full fine tuning
um you're changing the weights of you
know all of your notes in your in your
Transformer um in the case of uh prompt
design but for that you also need lots
and lots of training set in the case of
prompt design you're typically just
adding one or two or up to 10 examples
on what you would expect from the large
model or large language model in the
case of uh prompt tuning so there was
prompt design in the case of prompt
tuning you can give much more inputs as
a okay let's say it's a it's a
classification task let's say it's a
classification task of finding the brand
from a description of a product and then
you would give maybe thousand examples
and instead of giving them one by one um
the algorithm would learn an embedding
space and an embedding Vector that it
can prepend the large language model
almost as an instruction uh to be able
to do that uh one thing to my surprise I
would say I would I would have expected
that to to work much more you know
broadly uh not many people are using it
because prompt design is just like you
give a few examples much more easier
much more practical we're seeing people
just doing prompt design uh in in
practice and we'll talk about
distillation in the next section uh
actually but um again conventional find
tuning you get a a pre-trained model
checkpoint any one of them um and uh you
have a new data set a new task and uh
you know you're with your loss function
you're you're updating all of the all of
the weights or most of the weights it
requires lots of computes um so in
practice especially for Enterprises
we're not seeing many customers doing
this actually we're seeing much more of
the customers doing other types of
training which I will I will talk in a
second I think I mentioned conventional
prompt tuning from many examples you
learn an embedding Vector to be able to
prepend your your large language models
I don't see much of the use right now in
practice and that was a surprise to me
now I think this is what I see many
people are doing you probably have done
it as well you have a question that you
want to know give to your large model or
large language model and you provide you
know one two five uh examples uh you can
provide no example which is called zero
shot or or one shot is you providing
exactly one example of a similar
question and answer you were getting and
then large language models typically get
so much better in answering the
questions as you give even a few
questions about your about your use case
we see lots of people going this
path and then I think one thing that you
should uh you know know about is
parameter efficient fine tuning so when
I was talking about the conventional uh
fine tuning we talked about updating all
of the parameters of your neural network
uh here you would be updating you know
certain set of parameters or you might
even be adding a layer of a network on
top uh as well so we're seeing this
becoming uh much more effective and much
more commonly used in in practice and I
think there are many reasons for it I
think you see some pros and and and cons
in in general but uh it works with uh
much less no uh amount of computes
because you're not trying to uh update
all of your neural networks but select
parts of it and uh typically might
require a bit less data as well and uh
we're seeing lots of customers you know
choosing to go this path and uh of
course uh ER low rank adaptation or Lowa
tuning is is one of the most common ways
of uh ways of doing it um I think you
can you can read the paper to you know
for the details as well but uh in
general maybe a few things to to
remember here it's it's quite efficient
because it's holding the base model and
then almost having an addition component
to it and learning just that uh
component which is mentioned by BNA a
matrices and as you will see in the
paper because of the way it uh you know
handles the BNA matrices it also becomes
pretty efficient from Storage Point of
View as well and that's something that
uh
many Enterprises care about when they
have a fine tuning they want to be able
to store it all you need to do here is
you're not changing the base model
you're only changing just a set of
matrices and you you need to just store
that part which is called an adapter and
that becomes very effective for many
reasons like less data to store so very
storage efficient but also because of
that security privacy everything just
follows and Enterprises have been really
liking that and of course uh both in
terms of inference as well as in terms
of performance uh it's it's worked
really well many many many research
papers show that Laura and then and then
Q Laura which is a quanti version of of
Laura uh have worked very well um You
probably have read those papers if you
haven't please go and go back and and
and and read those we'll now move on to
know other topics but uh at least that's
a you know as a trend in Enterprises we
see a lot of usage of of Laura and I and
I know other platforms um also see the
same distillation um I think uh as I
mentioned for many of the use cases you
do not need these you know huge models
and the huge models usually mean higher
cost and higher latency so for many
applications actually you want less
latency so dation usually comes to your
uh help here and uh we look at one
algorithm here I'm not going to go into
like some of the you know historical
other
advancements but uh a typical approach
that uh people use here is a teacher and
a student model and the teacher is
trying to give you you know answers on a
set of training data that you have and
and the student model is is learning
from from that the alternative would
have been let's say you have a
classification task and you
have millions of data
samples you probably would have needed
to label them which we call hard labels
a human usually would would need to do
that and then you can probably train a
student model based on that and it could
be a small small model as well as you
might guess it's actually uh pretty just
to just to label instead a typical
approach is you might still label a few
or some but you would typically give
that training data to a teacher model a
very large model which is great in
reasoning assume it's good and and it
essentially helps generating
labels and there are various techniques
for it and I will mention just a few
talks about that as well it could be
even soft labels and then you get your
prediction from a smaller model you
start with a smaller model and you start
tuning or changing the weights of that
smaller model based on your loss
function of how much you're able to
guess the answers from the teachers
teachers answers but when I describe it
like you realize immediately oh I do not
need to create lots of labels the
teacher model is doing that for me so
that's why we see many people uh use
this technique when it comes to when it
comes to you know distillation or or
generating much smaller
models and
um I think one approach let's say this
is a you know similarity problem or
classification problem let's say it
could be an image
similarity and um with the soft Max uh
activation function you you turn uh the
output layers outputs of potentially
similarity between between in this case
images into probabilities
now this function is very common the
issue is that as you see in this example
it put almost all of the probility into
the you know first one so many people
have used various techniques and and one
of them is a temperature and in this
function as you increase the te
temperature uh you would actually
smoothen out that probability more and
more and the idea is you're really
create creating soft labels and if I go
back to the Alor that I was verbally
explaining um is that the teacher model
is getting the soft labels uh the
student model is getting these soft
predictions which is again a vector of
you know potential matching and the loss
function uh put them back propagate into
changing the weights you could also do
that with the heart predictions by the
way it's just that you need to get the
get the labels you need to get the heart
uh are predictions which is which is a
timely process and sometimes you do both
all right so uh let's maybe look at a
little bit on grounding too I think I
mentioned this why grounding is needed
LS being trained in the past
hallucination and can site sources and
uh we've seen many approaches being
taken taken here so first of all making
sure you provide the right context to
the large language models and through a
retrial algorithm you could for instance
use the web search to be able to in
parall to the LM to be able to get the
data and then you can potentially use a
search engine with your with the
Enterprises private data as well and
then and then combine the combine the
two um with hallucination and and and
and factuality another approach that we
see many people take and we certain to
take that at Google as well is looking
to generating better models that are
getting better in
factuality and this comes in a little
bit expans of reason capability as well
um but I think many Enterprises would
prefer prefer
that and then user experience actually
becomes important as well you want your
results to be authoritative you want to
be able to show um where the sources of
of the data is for the results that
you're
generating so and the right context as I
said could be anything anywhere from
private documents anywhere from fresh
content of in the on web uh or other
auor authoritative uh documents as well
and this could be from thirdparty
sources that are making their their
their data uh
available and then a
typical of course people refer to some
of this as rack uh as well a typical uh
way to do it is you would get a query or
a prompt and then you would convert that
into a query that you can feed it into a
retrieval engine or a search engine you
would get the results and then you would
tell your large language model hey here
is the result that I'm getting when I
ask a search engine about this and
here's the query now taking also this
results into account what would you say
so that's a typical approach that we
we're saying of course lots of details
like how do you take a prompt and
convert it into a query like uh cury to
a retrieval engine or a search engine
and then once we get the results how
exactly create a new prompt to be able
to give to uh to the to the large
language models as
well and I'm not going to go into the
details of this uh as we as we running
out of uh uh time but uh you might also
want to get the results and do another
post processing to really check the
citations one you know again and and uh
be able to like you know really be sure
about your your answers as well um as
you're combining search and and large
language
models I mentioned uh about better
models
um very typical people would to use
reinforcement learning with human uh uh
feedback and and potential AI feedback
as well like you could use a very large
model to do the PS and thumbs down uh as
well designing a reward model to highly
punish you know
responses um and and creating a loss
function to be able to feed feedb and I
will I think I'm guessing a big trend
from any large language model um
producers to go more and more into
factuality in in the next few months
maybe six months 12 months because many
use cases um you definitely want to be
in the you know more on the factual
factual side than a reasoning or
creative side there is usually a little
bit of a a cost or or or tradeoff
between the between the
two all right and then I think uh user
experience depending on the use case we
see lots of uh customers using the
various tools all the way from okay like
in a response looking at the sources how
many supporting sources there are how
many you know know contradicting sources
there are and based on that maybe
refining the refining the answer uh as
well but in general being able to site
the
sources um has been something that many
Enterprises have been asking for again
and
again and I think even on vertex AI we
took this approach where you have
grounding with Google search grounding
on on on emperis data grounding on you
know moodies or Thompson Reuters like
third party data and having a model
that's uh like we call it grounding with
High Fidelity which is uh it's actually
a model not even combining with a surge
but much more factuality train and and
of course on top of all of that and this
is an you know interesting concept
remember I mentioned the cost of LMS are
going down we do not see that Trend as
much in search in general like there are
lots of search engines out there where
the cost of an API call has been
constant for for a while for years so
this requires a concept of dynamic
retrieval being able to really
understand intelligently when you want
to combine with a search engine versus
not so that's also another Trend that
we're seeing again if you're looking
into Ted work
startups um this is also another another
idea being able to intelligently
understand what to do based of based on
llm response like a dynamically
understand you need to call a search
engine but as we will see in the next
section on function calling um being
able to call a
function all right um You probably have
all used large language models you come
across many things where you're not
getting the the results that you want or
especially do if you want the large
language models to do
something give the schedule of trains
give like maybe buy a
product there are many things that you
just cannot do change something in an
you know health record of a of for
patient change something in a in an
employee record those are the type of
things a large language model cannot do
large language model is great in getting
information but it's not great in taking
actions we call it real world actions
with them I would say function calling
um as well as grounding combined like
helps with many many of
those um but
uh some of these limitations we've seen
when it comes to function calling I
think the biggest uh limitation I would
say of large language models is is being
able to take these actions and for many
applications you would need to be able
to take these
actions and uh I think you've got into
some issues and and you've done lots of
work arounds but uh maybe in this slide
I'm I'm going fast now because I want to
have some time for questions as
well I think there are multiple steps
like three easy steps I would say um
defining your functions uh first of all
like let's say you're a travel company
creating an extension or a function that
does you know looks at flight schedules
looks at flight bookings hotel bookings
Etc and you have a different function
for each one of them and then you like
either gemini or or you know an
anthropic model or an open AI
model uh there's lots of work going on
to make large language models understand
that okay I cannot do
this and and then be able to choose from
the functions the available
functions to be able to call them when
needed and then I think in the inference
time that's exactly what the what the
large GL model would do here is
something that I cannot do I cannot book
a flight oh I need to find an extension
here's here's my extension library with
100 different extensions okay Expedia is
the right one to call to be able to do
this and I think uh this roughly
describes uh what I what I said in a bit
more technical technical terms
um but uh um like this is also how it
works with with Gemini as well I think
as a tool provider it's important to be
able to provide the ER the ability to
your customers to provide your
extensions and functions so that your
library of extensions are constantly
growing but at the same time you need to
constantly put on work on on your large
language models as well to be able to
get better in understanding when it
needs to call an extension and and
also you know which extension to call it
only becomes more challenging over time
because as people are adding more and
more
extensions that means now the library of
extensions is extending and you need to
be even smarter to be able to choose the
right extension uh for the things that
you want to
do all right I think with that you can
do lots of things all of a sudden like
uh you could say get structured outputs
know real time information
retrieval um
you can you can get for instance if
you're a customer agent you can you can
get your customers's data you can get a
customer bill you can uh have you know
tools for your
employees uh you can book a hotel or a
flight or buy a product you can do lots
of things once you have function uh
calling enabled essentially function
calling extensions make large language
Bots be able to do many more things
things in in in life and in applications
rather than just being able to provide
you the data and and
information all right now I mentioned
many tools but there are many other
tools that you really need to be able to
build successful agents and applications
like you need to be able to have a great
pumpt management system like store them
have a revision history even being able
to convert a prompt from one large
language model potential to another
language model uh as well and uh I think
I mentioned as you give more choice and
availability to these large language
models U something very important is
evoluation and I will mention a very
important Trend that we're seeing here
as well which is um providing evoluation
tools for uh
for large language models or or other
other tasks and uh in in vertx AI we
have multiple of them but I think the
auto side by side is a really important
concept and you will see a a a growing
Trend and this might be another idea for
you again for your teis work etc to use
larger models like the the largest model
possible um for rating uh
purposes indeed there is a shortage of
human in the world right now for all the
rating classification work that needs to
happen and and uh we're definitely
seeing a trend towards doing some of it
with you know actual large language
models that that are that are large and
have have very good reasoning
capabilities The Other Side by Side tool
that that we also have has exactly that
um you can run multiple large language
models and then you you ask a very large
model U to rate them and and decide
which one is better interestingly enough
you're seeing a a significant
correlation and I think there's there's
lots of work going on across many
companies as well with these large
models assessing these tasks and a human
assessing these tasks as
well so with that uh maybe I these are
some of the announcements that we've
done actually last week these are all
public announcements and I think
different companies are seeing a very
similar Trend maybe one thing to
remember is that we're seeing a huge
exponential growth everywhere in AI in
the world right now just a few numbers
that we published last week is um just
this year in Enterprise world only just
for for
companies um I think from January to
August uh about 30 time 36 times
growth uh on the API call for a business
it usually takes between five and 10
years to get this this type of a growth
this is not even one year half a year
and uh and then you would say wow this
was very successful business so the
amount of growth that I think all of
these AI companies are seeing is just
something that no one has seen before I
think if you want to remember one thing
a you're in the right place right now
because you have a huge interest in in
this um and and B I think this trend is
gonna is going to
continue and um like try to be as
involved with AI as as possible but also
add uh like many students come to me
okay what should I study in addition to
AI maybe add components of you know
other Sciences or Humanity art something
also that brings in some creativity as
well to your mind too I think that's
going to be really important even how we
program uh a few years from now uh is
going to be very different than than how
we are doing it how we are doing it
today and and and creativity and forcing
your creative part of your your part of
your brain is going to be super valuable
for you as well