[Music]
Uh hi everyone uh thank you thank you
for being here and um yeah in this talk
we're going to talk about LM post
training. So we're going to see all the
different steps uh in the LM push
training world. We're going to talk
about the data set generation. We're
going to talk about the training
algorithms and finally we're going to
talk about the evaluation which is very
very important and on top of that I want
to also talk a bit about future trends
and a bit about test time comput
scaling. So um bit about me uh indeed
I'm um I do post questioning at liquid
AI um I'm also the author of the LM
engineers handbook if you're interested
and I done a few contributions on the
open source side uh with blog post with
uh models fine tunes and uh some tools
that could be uh useful if you want to
do things like model merging or
evaluation. So uh first of all let's
define post training. Push training is
what happens after pre-training. Uh so
it's quite easy during pre-training you
have a lot of row text. You have huge
volume of row text and the goal is to
predict the next token in a sequence. So
you do this to create a base model. This
is cool. But this base model is only
able to predict the next token in a
sequence and it's not able to answer
questions. it's not able to follow
instructions which is why we have
pre-raining. This is the goal of
pre-raining turning a base model into a
useful assistance. So to do that we have
two main steps. The first one is
supervised fine tuning. And during
supervised fine tuning what we do is
that we give instructions and answers to
the model as input and we ask it a
question and we teach the model to
answer the question and we do it a lot.
We teach the model a structure, a chat
template that we're going to talk about
later. And this is what the model
learned during this stage. Then it's a
model that is able to follow
instructions. It's a model that is able
to answer questions, but we can do a bit
better because if you use it, it might
not give you the kind of answers that
you want. So the next stage is called uh
preference alignment. And during
preference alignment, we give
preferences to the model. We give not
only one question and one answer. We
give two answers. One is the chosen
answer. This is how we want the model to
behave. And the other one is the
rejected answer. And this is contrastive
example to tell the model do not output
this kind of text. So this is what we do
in terms of training uh doing post
training and we will see uh the
algorithms a bit later.
Um so in terms of data set as you might
have uh noticed um during the
pre-training phase we have a lot of
samples we have uh trillions of tokens
and the data set are really really large
this is not the case with pre-raining
the data sets are a lot smaller and we
focus more on quality so here I wanted
to give you different types of
finetuning um that you might encounter.
The first type in green is general
purpose. With general purpose
fine-tuning, the goal is to create a
general assistant, a chatbot that is
able to answer any type of questions.
So, this is typically what you have if
you use GPT. Um, Chpt is like a very
general purpose assistant and it's
capable of doing pretty much everything.
But you might want to take a model, for
example, open source model and fine-tune
it for a specific use case. you might
want to do it for a specific domain like
medical domain, legal domain, financial
domain or language specific uh finetune.
So here the idea is that we're going to
embed include more knowledge into the
model. So it's able to perform better on
this specific domain. So if you do that,
you don't need 1 million or over 1
million samples to do it. You probably
need a data set that is not as um as
big. uh and there's a third type which
is task specific fine-tuning and with
task specific fine-tuning the goal is to
really learn one function. So it's a
very type very narrow type of
fine-tuning where you want to learn for
example how to become better at
summarization. How to become better at
being a spell checker. Um and in this
case you need even fewer samples. So
it's a lot easier to do. Note that all
these um estimates like rough estimates
because it depends on multiple
dimensions. For example, the model size
is very important. The bigger the model
uh the fewer samples that you need and
it depends on also on the complexity of
the task that you want to achieve uh for
some domain. For example, if you do not
know a language at all with the base
model, if the base model hasn't been
trained on language, fine-tuning will
probably not help you a lot because you
don't have enough tokens to properly
train the model in this
language. Okay. So when should we
fine-tune a model? So here I'm talking
about domain specific and test specific
fine tuning. So there are four main
areas, four main points where it might
make sense for you to fine-tune a model.
First of all, I would say always start
with in context learning with uh right
pipelines because it's just a lot easier
to test and if it doesn't provide enough
value if it's not uh good enough for you
in terms of quality of the answer but it
can also be in terms of latency in terms
of inference speed there are a lot of
different dimensions that you can uh
consider. Then there are uh finetuning
can be an option. The first type is when
you want to change the tone or the
format of the answer. For example, if
you are trying to make um an assistant
to write emails, maybe you do not like
the tone that the model has. In fact, I
I really dislike the tone that uh GPD
has when you try to write an email with
it. So, this is something that you might
want to change through
finetuning. Then you might want to add
knowledge for example with domain
specific uh finetunes. This is what we
talked about. Uh here I'm saying that
it's superficial because you cannot
learn an entire language with it. But
you can for example learn um teach the
model facts about yourself or about your
company. Um so there's still potential
in adding knowledge um during the
finetuning process. You can also try to
distill a very large model like GPT4
into a much smaller one to reduce the
cost and also to in uh to reduce the
latency can also increase the inference
speed. And finally in terms of output
quality you might want to have a very
specific narrow um model for example to
make diagrams. And with that when you
have like such a super specific um task
it's possible to really outperform
Frontier models because uh they haven't
been trained specifically on your task.
When this is done um I'm talking here
about evaluation. Um it's very important
to always evaluate uh your fine-tune.
make sure that what you try to do
actually works and also to be able to
iterate because probably the first model
that you fine-tune will not be the last
one and you might want to enter in a
kind of training loop where you can uh
evaluate uh get information about what
works, what doesn't work. Uh fix your
data, train it again.
Uh there are other reasons why you might
want to fine-tune a model. Um besides
this technical stuff um if you look at
um why companies care about like open
source and finetuning you see that it's
mostly about control and
customizability. So control is because
they might not want to just send data um
through APIs to to the cloud. um and
customers ability. It's because they
might want to change the tone, the
format of the answers, create their own
model. So there are a lot of different
reasons why you might want to fine-tune
even though um maybe a frontier model is
all you need. Maybe you already have um
llama and it works well for you.
Actually, there are also like more
political reasons why you might want to
fine-tune your own
model. Okay, let's talk about data sets.
So the most important uh question when
we talk about data set is what is good
data and I think this is uh kind of the
main question uh through the entire post
training uh process is what is good data
and good data is actually can be
summarized into three dimensions. First
you have accuracy. Accuracy is quite
easy. It's is my answer relevant to the
question? am I giving the correct
answer? So most of the time it's quite
easy to to check and to see okay my
answer is correct. Uh but if you have
very complex questions it can be a lot
harder. Um so for for example if you uh
are dealing with code you might want to
run unit test to make sure that your
answer is correct. If you are answering
complex math questions you might want to
use a solver to double check that the
answer is correct. So there are all
these different ways of ensuring the
accuracy of the data that you can use
when you generate your data. The second
dimension is diversity. Diversity is
something that is not as simple um to to
pin down uh because it's really
about having um samples that are uh very
different from each other um and that
try to cover like the entire possible
interaction that you users will have
with the model. So you really want to
have um covered as much as possible. And
the problem that was mentioned with
synthetic data for example is that when
you use too much synthetic data your
diversity will collapse and this is why
um it's good to have a bit of synthetic
data because just a bit can actually
improve the diversity but too much of it
and you collapse in terms of diversity
and it makes the data lower quality.
Finally, you have complexity. And
complexity is really about challenging
the models to answer tough questions.
It's about giving answers that are long
and detailed with chain of thoughts,
stepbystep reasoning and all that kind
of things. So, this summarizes what is
um a good data set and um yeah, this
might be like the most important thing
to remember. Um it's those three
dimensions because they can be applied
like throughout the entire pipeline. For
example, with diversity you see here
real life conversations. Real life
conversations are really varied because
people ask questions about anything
really. Uh so you see here with um 2D uh
representation of the embeddings of a
data set that these three data sets on
top are really varied and cover pretty
much the entire spectrum. But this is
not the case if you zoom on a math data
set or the two code data sets here. You
see that they're really um in a single
region. So if you want to create a math
LLM then okay maybe math is all you
need. But if you want to create a
general purpose LLM then you cannot just
have math and code. You will need more
to increase the
diversity. Then there's the complexity.
Here's a simple example I made. Um, so
low complexity. My prompt was how tall
is the Eiffel Tower? Very simple
question. Um, you can just write the
answer with a few words. So the
complexity is like really really low.
Um, but then I evolved it and this is
actually something pretty neat because I
evolved it using a framework called auto
evil. And basically you just ask an LLM
to rephrase uh your prompt to increase
the complexity. And this is what it
produced. So here the complexity is not
crazy high either, but it's definitely
higher because you see that it has
different layers. It has a lot more
details and we asking for several
answers and not just a single one. So
this is a good way to increase the
complexity of your samples.
in terms of data formats. So I mentioned
earlier that um with instruction data
sets you have questions and answers,
instructions and outputs. You can also
have a system prompt to guide um the
model into um adopting the style that
you want. For example, uh you are a
mathematician from MIT. Um but with
preference data, we have a chosen and a
rejected answer. And the goal is really
to teach the model to maximize the the
margin the the probabilities of the
token uh between the uh chosen answer
and the rejected answer. We really want
to maximize this gap. So this is what
it's trained at uh during preference
alignment. Here's an example of a simple
data generation pipeline. So you can see
uh that we use seat data as input. The
seat data can be pretty much anything.
It can be row text. It can be uh
instruction and answers. It can be just
um questions from users and then you can
refine it by generating instructions by
generating answers um by generating both
of them. Uh there are a lot of different
techniques to do that. For example, if
you have row text, the problem is that
you do not have questions with it. You
just have the answers. So you can use
back translation to ask a language model
to please write the question that
corresponds to this text. Then you have
scoring and filtering. Here you can use
different techniques to uh like
curistics but you can also use other
LLMs as judges to measure the quality of
your answers and filter out the bad
samples. And on top of that you have
classic data duplication decontamination
to make sure that you're not training on
the test set and data filtering because
for example you want to exclude some
keywords. An example that of that is for
instruction following. So instruction
following is this category uh that is
focused on actually following
constraints. So we have an example here
where my constraint is your entire
response should be in English and all
lowercase. So we have two constraints
here and we want the model to really
follow these constraints in its answer.
So to create a data set uh to teach the
model this kind of behavior, what we do
is that we start with some prompts and
some constraints and we can just append
the constraints um after the prompt like
here and then we can query an LLM and
ask it an answer but we're not sure that
the LLM will actually follow the
constraints very well. So we can run
some tests. It's very easy to make sure
that the answer is in English. You can
use a library like lang detect to make
sure that it's in the language that you
want and you can also really easily
check that it's all lower case. So you
can run this unit test to make sure that
the constraints are really followed.
Then you can do decontamination. There's
a um evaluation set that is called if
eval. Uh so you want to make sure that
you're not by mistake generating samples
that are too close to if and finally you
can do some keyword exclusion um to
remove some part of it. Another example
is ultra feedback. So the first one was
for instruction um data sets. This one
is for preference data sets and with
preference data sets we want to generate
not one answer but two answers. So to do
that we have prompts once again but
instead of quering a single LLM we query
a lot of different LLMs and we are going
to use a judge LLM to rate them. We're
going to score each um each answer. We
take the top one as the chosen answer
and we take the worst one as the
rejected answer. Then you can remove the
duplicate duplicates, you can remove
short answers, but this is like the idea
behind it. And this is a really good way
of creating uh preference data
sets. As a case study, um here's open
perfect blend. This is a open source
version of the perfect blend uh data
set. Um this is something I've made by
combining uh different data sets that
are available um on hugging face. And
you can see here I think the most uh
interesting part is about the categories
uh to give you an idea of the mixture
that you want. Here you have a lot of
math, a lot of code and also a bit of uh
chat data plus the instruction following
uh data sets that we talked about. And
you can also see on the right a
breakdown with all the individual data
sets that compose um this uh open
perfect blend data set. So here we're
talking about general purpose
fine-tuning. We want the model that is
able to do a lot of stuff and this is
the kind of mixtures. This is the kind
of proportions that you are targeting in
this
case. When this is all done, you have
your data set, you've done like your
mixture and you're quite happy with it.
Um the final step is to apply a chat
template to it. So on the left you can
see a storage format. Um here it's
called alpaca. doesn't really matter but
it's a way of storing the data the
instructions and the outputs and what we
are going to do is that we're going to
map a structure to it so the model knows
who's speaking so here it's very simple
you see you have a special token called
I am start that says start of the
message the rule of the the speaker is
system so it's going to be like a system
instruction and then it stops at im end
and we start again with the user that
will give the user prompt and finally
with the assistant that will give the
response uh from the LLM and if you're
doing a entire conversation then you can
repeat user assistant user assistant
user assistant so this is exactly what
the model is going to be trained on and
we do that especially during um
supervised fine tuning to make sure that
we learn this template the structure is
really really important and this is what
makes the difference between the base
model that is only able to uh
autocomplete text and with the post
train model that is able to actually
follow instructions and um have entire
conversations. Okay. Uh that's it for
data. Now we can talk about the training
algorithms uh that we use during post
training. First of all, I want to
recommend uh three libraries to do
finetuning. The first one is TRL. It's
from hugging phase. It's built on top of
transformers. Um it's a very good
library. It will give you a lot of
different algorithms. Um it's always
very up to date with the research. So
you can have very fancy um algorithms.
Um there are a lot of them that are
published um every week almost. So um
they keep it up to date. Then you have
axelottal. Axel is built on top of the
and it offers some nice features. for
example, it can pre-process your data
sets uh for you and abstracts a lot of
different things uh for you. So, it's um
more user friendly. Uh what I really
like about it is that everything uh your
training run is a YAML configuration
file. So, it's very easy to just share
your configuration files with other
people and also like spy on what other
people do to get like the right
parameters and um get inspired by their
work. Um, so it's a really cool one. And
finally, you have Unsloth. Uh, you might
be familiar with it. Um, and this one is
really, really good if you want to do uh
fine-tuning uh with only one GPU. It's
super efficient. It's really good. It
also has a lot of nice utilities. Uh,
for example, it can handle quantization
for you. So, that's really really
nice. In terms of techniques, we have
three main techniques uh with SFT. Um
the first one is full fine-tuning. Full
finetuning is basically like
pre-training. Uh we are loading the
model in full precision and we are
retraining every parameter on the
fine-tuning data set on the instruction
data set. So this is really good if you
want to maximize the quality of the
model. Um but it requires a lot of VRAM
because you are loading the entire model
and then that you're training the entire
model. So if you calculate all the
optimizer states, all the activations
plus the the size of the model, it will
require probably like an entire node,
entire cluster to do it. Um so this is
nice but also very costly. Um so a more
approachable um solution is to use
parameter efficient um techniques like
lower. Laura is really nice because
instead of retraining the entire model,
you will just load the model, but you
will add adapters. So these matrices A
and B and instead of training the model,
you only train these mat matrices. Uh
what's really nice about it is instead
of retraining 100% of the parameters,
you only train something like 0.5% of
the entirety of it. So, it's a lot
faster and it's a lot less costly in
terms of VRM and in terms of hardware in
general. The only issue is that you
still need to load the entire model in
memory. Uh, and if it's a big model,
it's going to be very very costly. So,
if you are really hardware constrained
and you don't have like enough GPUs to
really do um the lower uh finetuning,
you can use CQA. Kilawa is a variant of
Laura where you don't load the model in
full precision but you you you load a
quantized version of it in 4bit
precision then you apply the adapters
and the law fine tuning but the idea is
that okay now loading the model is not
as costly um so it's really good if you
cannot do lower the problem is that it
also it's also slower and it will
degrade uh performance performance a
little bit like a few%. So it's not
really recommended and if you can afford
doing lower finetuning I would recommend
lower finetuning and most of the time
full fine tuning is actually a bit too
much. You probably don't need it unless
you are really training models because
you're an LM
company. Then you have preference
alignment techniques. So this is the
second stage of post training and with
preference alignment techniques um there
are a lot of them there are really
really a lot of them there like over 100
different techniques um in this uh
umbrella u so I want you to only
remember two of them the first one is PO
the proximal policy
optimization this is kind of the
traditional and original version of
preference alignment uh this is kind of
the original algorithm to do it the
problem with PO And you might see it on
the diagram here is that you need three
different models. So we complain earlier
about loading one model but here you
need to load three. You need to load the
frozen model, the train model and the
reward model. And the idea is that you
are going to get uh some text into the
train model. A question is going to
generate an answer. The answer is going
to be uh scored by the reward model. And
to make sure that your uh train model is
not deviating too much from the initial
policy, so from the model before it
started training, you also have KL
divergence um to make sure that yeah,
you're not diverging too much. Um so
this is good in terms of quality. It
will maximize quality, but it's very
complex. It is very costly to run and so
it's not really recommended. Instead,
what I would recommend is direct
reference optimization or DPO. And here
it's less costly because you only have
two models to load. Actually, if you use
a lower, you can um load only one model
and just adapters for each of them. Um
so it's faster, it's cheaper to use, uh
but the quality is slightly lower. In
practice, this is not really a problem
and I would recommend using DPO over PPO
unless you are open AI or you are like
in a very precise configuration where
you have like unlimited resources. Um
plus DPO is a lot more user friendly.
It's a lot easier to tune the
parameters.
And in terms of training parameters, um
here is a list of the main ones, the
main training parameters that you might
want to tweak um during fine-tuning. The
first one is the most important one
really is the learning rates. The
learning rate corresponds to like how
much the parameters are updated during
training. And I give you like some
common values uh to give you an
estimate. The two next parameters are
really connected the batch size and the
max length because they directly impact
the VRAM that you are going to use
because they determine the size of the
input that you feed to the model. The
batch size is the number of example that
you're going to feed in in one pass. Uh
so the more you feed obviously um the
more VRAM you consume and the max length
is the length of every each of these
samples. So once again if the length is
high obviously you're going to consume
more uh VRM. So those parameters are
really hardware constrainted with the
batch size you can do something a bit
tricky um um by just having a loop and
instead of updating the parameters after
one pass you you accumulate like several
um forward passes and then you can u
update your weights. Um so this is why
we make the difference between effective
batch size and the real batch size.
After that we have epochs. Epoch
correspond to the number of passes
through the entire training this set.
This is quite easy to do probably
between three and five. Um and you can
monitor that. We're going to see how to
monitor the experiments afterwards.
And the two uh final ones are also very
very easy to select uh the optimizer. So
it's the algorithm to update the
parameters and I would just recommend
AdamW. Um you can explore a bit more but
AdamW is really good. So uh this is a
very strong baseline and about the
attention mechanism flash attention is
pretty much all you need. Flash tension
is a very efficient implementation of
the attention mechanism in the transform
architecture and that makes it a lot
faster especially to process long uh
sequence length. Um so this is the one
that I would recommend always if you can
to monitor experiments here um here's an
example with uh the learning rate. So
you can see a bad learning rate and a
good learning rate. The bad learning
rate is the one with the loss spike. So
we start with a smooth descent and then
immediately after that uh we see that's
the loss u spike. So this is probably a
problem with the learning rate. I would
say it's too high and if you reduce it a
bit it's probably going to give you
something more like uh the curve on the
right where it's a lot smoother. You see
that there's a little bump at the
beginning, but it's not too important
and I wouldn't mind it too much. There
are other metrics that you can also
monitor during training. Uh you can see
on top there's like the training loss,
but in the middle at the bottom there's
also the validation loss. If you have a
validation data set, you can also
monitor that and make sure that uh
you're not overfitting. And there's also
the gradient norm. So the gradient norm
is really the magnitude of the updates
that you receive. Um and you don't want
to see uh too many spikes because this
might be a problem with your data for
example. You don't want it to also um
raise too much. So here migraine norm is
is okay. I don't think it's a problem
because the eva loss and the training
loss good. Uh but if you see this kind
of behavior it might be a sign that the
training is not going too well.
what?
So you can have a training data set uh
that is just for training and you can uh
save a small part small data set just
for validation purposes. So it's the
same
yeah you can just split it as you would
do in traditional machine learning. So
here we're not going to do like a 80 20
split like we would do in traditional
machine learning because the training
set is so large that it wouldn't make
sense but you can save like 1% 2% of it
for
validation. Now that we have trained our
model um you can have different
scenarios. For example, you've trained a
lot of different checkpoints and now you
have like 10 models that you've trained
or you have one model but for example
it's a llama model and there are lot of
llama fine tunes available in the open
source and hugging face. What can you do
with that? Um an answer to this question
is model merging. Model merging is the
idea that you can simply average, fuse,
combine the parameters of different
models together to make an even stronger
model. So this was a bit of a joke at
the beginning and now everybody uses it.
Um, every LLM company applies model
merging. Um, so yeah,
um, I guess I shouldn't make fun of it
now, but um, it's still a funny idea
that you can just take kind of random
models and uh, it makes a stronger one
uh, in the end. I really like uh, model
merging and it's a really neat
techniques that is maybe a bit
underrated still. Uh, but as I said like
everybody uh, applies it now.
So yes, question.
more than two models. Yes, exactly.
We're going to see that in this um in
this slide. Um here you can just like
add more models and average them all
together. Uh but there are techniques
that are a bit more advanced uh in model
merging. And for example, one is slurp.
So slurp stands for spherical linear
interpolation. So instead of doing just
a normal interpolation um you do this
one by moving along a sphere instead of
a straight line. And we see that it's
generally better. It produces better uh
merges. It's very popular in the open
source community. It's quite reliable.
Uh but the issue is that you can only
merge two models together. Uh you can
see on the right one that I've made
using using this technique. And the
second uh technique that I find more
interesting is uh de ties or de linear.
So dear is a technique that uh randomly
prunes and rescales the parameters of
your source models. Ties is a technique
that keeps the most significant
parameters uh in your your source models
and add a sign consensus because it
happens that um if you take the
parameter of model one and parameter of
model two one is positive and the other
one is negative. So if you combine them
you get zero and that's actually not
really good. That's not the best way of
combining them. So this sign consensus
uh addresses this issue. I think I saw
other question. Yes.
Yeah. So the question is like do we need
models with the same size or um can we
merge models with different sizes? Um in
theory you could try to merge models
with different sizes. Um but in practice
it doesn't work. So all the merging
techniques that I'm talking about are
with the same models and the same
architectures too. This is very
important. So for example, we only merge
like llamas together and not llama 2 and
lama 3. It would only be llama 2 with
lama 2, lama 3 with lama 3, right? Yes.
The two models are in different
position. For example, the first one is
precision and the second one is the
high models that actually have lower
quality. Yeah. So the question is like
can we uh what what happens if we merge
a model in full precision and a model
uh a quantized model. Um I would not
recommend doing that uh because of
course you will have more quality if you
only merge models in full precision. I
don't think I've tried doing that uh to
be honest but yeah obviously the
quantized model uh has some performance
degradation so the merge model would
also suffer from it. It's better to only
try to do it with full
precision. All right. Yes.
Yep. We're going to see that with an
example. But yes indeed. Um so if you
have different models, you can assign
different weights to them. And a common
way of doing it is for example you have
one model that is really good. you know
it's very good because you've run some
evals and you know the scores and you
have other models that might not be as
good so you want to prioritize the first
one compared to the other ones and this
is something that I've done to create um
the second model like Daredevil um if
you look at the family tree of the model
so I was talking about like merging
models together but you can also merge
merges together and you can iteratively
obtain crazy family trees with models
merge with each further. Uh so here you
see um the family tree of the devil 8b
and indeed to make that um you see the
configuration that I've used on the left
there are different models. This is a
configuration using like yaml uh with
merge kit and you have parameters like
density and weight. density will um tune
the parameters that you retain um
because you want to with ties you don't
want to keep all of them. Um and weight
is really about like the weight of the
combination of the different models. Um
so with their this is a bit of a science
or um more like an alchemy uh kind of
thing like choosing the right weights
and the right parameters to obtain the
best models. This is something that you
learn if you do model merging quite a
lot. You get ideas about like what is
going to work. Uh but there's no real
science uh behind it. Uh there are
papers I've published one um about how
to do it automatically that are a bit
more uh scientific. Uh but yeah, if you
use these methods, I would recommend
using like different parameters, testing
a few different uh merges and running
evaluation on them uh to see if it
works. But uh on the right you can see
that um we have a few benchmarks
um and what's really funny is that their
devil also the merge model is better
than the source models on these
benchmarks. So the merger was really
successful. it's really better than the
source models and this is what model
merging is about right
um and to apply that in a more concrete
example um let's say you want to do a
language specific uh model by language
specific here I mean something that is
not too close to English uh for example
German is too close and models are
already good in German so it doesn't
make sense but uh for example something
like Finnish um models are not really
good in Finnish in general. Um, so let's
say you want to do this Finnish
model. A recipe that you can use is
doing continuous or continual
pre-training on Finnish row text. So you
do it for billions of um tokens. It's
between like five and 100 billion
tokens. It really depends on how much
your base model knows about um finish.
Then you do supervised fine tetuning and
preference alignment like we talked
about um once again in finish. And if
you run evals, what you're going to see
is that your model is now really good in
Finnish. Good job, but it's really bad
at everything else. U so this is a
problem and this is a common problem
when people try to do uh language
specific models. They end up being a
model that is just good in the language.
So to fix that model merging can really
help you because you can take the model
that you have trained in Finnish and
merge it with the instruct general
purpose model. For example, if you took
lama 3 as a base model, you can take
lama 3 instruct as the um instruct
model. And by merging them together,
you're going to get a model that is not
only good in finish but also good at
everything else. This is one of the
powers of model merging is that it
allows you to kind of add these
different skills together without
compromising the rest. Uh so yeah, this
is a case study where it really
works.
Yes. Before
what does this mean
for regular machine? Let's say you
doing your own
can do that task very well.
Uh sorry, you talking about a large
language model should a CNN task? No,
I'm saying for you can merge
model for a bunch of task then
what I I guess what's the role of like
other machine learning techniques at
that point you can use for example for
object detection or any other problems.
Okay. I don't think that you can use
large language model for object
detection because like this is like
another modality and here we're talking
about um like the same architecture the
same size of models so this is really
uniquely for text you can do the same
thing with VLMs for example and it will
provide like better um performance for
vision language models but you would
still need to have like the core skills
like it's not a magical technique it
will not give you like complete new
abilities. It's about combining
abilities from different models with the
same architecture
together. All right, let's talk about
evaluation. So, evaluation is the main
problem uh in the LLM world. Um it
doesn't work very well. Um and uh we
don't really know what we're doing.
Um but it's really important actually. I
want to convince you that despite all
the flows, it's it's like really really
important because all this training and
all this post training is about like
optimizing something. It's about
optimizing models to become better. And
evaluation is really measuring if it's
better or not. So if we don't have the
right evaluation, we optimizing for the
wrong thing. And maybe we don't have
perfect evaluations. For sure we don't.
uh but we have something and we will see
how to combine them together to get a
good idea of how good the models really
are. So the first time of the first type
of evaluation is automated benchmarks.
So with automated benchmarks if you know
about NMLU this is a classic example if
you know about the open LLM leaderboard
it also uses automated benchmarks. The
idea is that you have a data set like
you have samples and you have a metric.
So for example with MMLU the prompts the
samples are questions about anything can
be biology can be English can be math
and you have four different options A B
C and D and the metric is just the
accuracy. Um so if the right answer was
A and the model said B well zero um and
we measure the performance of the model
based on the accuracy over the entire
data set. So this has really good
properties. It's really scalable. It's
really um cost- effective. It has also
you can design benchmarks for very
precise task like math or it can be like
algebra. It can be very very precise. Um
it's also reproducible which is really
really nice u because people can make
sure that your evaluations were correct.
But the issue I have the main issue is
that this is not how models are used at
all. like we chat with models, we do not
check um if they output the right letter
uh when we ask them a question and it
might be difficult to um
evaluate questions that are more free
form that are more complex than just
four options. So because of that
automated benchmarks give you an idea of
how the model perform in math in code
but this is really uh not connected with
how people use it in the real world.
You can also use more focused benchmarks
um because I talked about MMLU and very
generic uh benchmarks that are really
general purpose but you also have um t
specific benchmarks like enterprise
scenarios. Um but you also have domain
specific benchmarks for example finish
we could create our own uh benchmark uh
evaluation suite for for finish uh for
code for medical domain all that kind of
stuff. Another way of evaluating models
is just to ask humans to rate the
answers. So a popular way um is to use a
an arena. If you know the chatbot arena,
you have a prompt. So you tap your
prompt and then you have two answers
from two anonymous models and you just
decide which one was better. So you
really rate the answers of the two
models and we keep doing that with a ton
of models and you can use this uh
comparisons as um a way to calculate an
score and this is how the chatbot works.
So this is nice because you can be very
precise in um how you want humans to
rate the models. You can ask them to
just focus on toxicity for example. This
is a popular way of doing it with red
teaming. Um, it has a lot of flexibility
because of that. Uh, there's also a lot
less risk of data contamination which
exists with automated benchmarks. And on
top of that, it's directly human
preferences. So you if you use um these
scores, you're really optimizing for
human preferences, which is kind of the
goal of post training. Um, the problem
is it's really difficult to scale. It's
obviously very costly. It's very time
consuming and humans are incredibly
biased too. Uh we we like to think that
we are kind of the ultimate evaluation
but we're really not. Um it's it's very
easy to u make humans like a model of
another. you just need longer answers
for example and they like it better or
you need models that are very confident
in um what they say and the answer can
be completely wrong but because it's
said so confidently people will like it
better um so it's definitely not the
ultimate evaluation but it's also
something that is very important very
important tool in
general and this this is like the main
thing about evaluation is that human
preferences are not correlated with
automated benchmarks. And here you have
a comparison with a ton of different
benchmarks. The first one on top is the
chatbot arena. And um all the others are
more or less automated benchmarks. You
have MMLU for example. Uh GSM8K is a
math uh evaluation. You have math which
is a math evaluation and human eval
which is a code evaluation. And you see
that the correlation is like pretty poor
in general. And this is something that
you observe if you um really try models.
Um you can be really good on MMLU and
really bad in terms of human preferences
and vice versa. So this is why these two
approaches are kind of complimentary. Uh
you really need both if you want to
produce the best model and you cannot
just like focus on automated benchmarks
or just focus on um human
preferences. And a way to um scale it a
bit more um is to just get rid of humans
and replace them with LLMs. So now we
have LLMs generating answers and LLM
judging other LLMs. Um and this is
really um much better to scale and to be
able to uh get a lot more uh samples.
You can also not use one LM as a judge
but multiple LLMs as a jury. And this
tends to also produce more reliable and
more robust
evaluations. Uh what's good is that yeah
this is how models are used. We uh rate
the answers. Um the models also now can
handle very complex tasks. So you can
really automate the free form stuff. It
provides direct feedback. Okay, it's not
human preferences but it's very close.
It's very correlated actually. Um but
unfortunately these um judge LLMs also
have their own biases and they're
actually very close to human biases. Um
so you kind of run into the same issues.
Um and there's some quality validation
that is needed on top of everything. So
you might still want to have some human
evaluation to make sure that your LLM
judges still are very correlated with
how humans would rate it. But it's a
very nice way to to scale uh this this
thing even though it's not as scalable
as automated benchmarks because you
still need to run a ton of different
comparisons to to get meaningful
results. And finally, you can create
your own evaluation. Um so I would say
the the main um thing is to start early
like before finetuning even. Uh it's
it's like test-driven development a bit.
Uh you need to know what you want to
optimize. Um so you create the data set
that will optimize this thing and based
on that you will probably iterate a lot.
Don't think that your data set is the
final version of this data set. It will
probably evolve because after um seeing
answers from your model you will
understand that oh um I forgot this part
or like the model is hacking a bit uh
these questions. So you will probably
need to iterate and have several
versions of the evaluation data set. You
can combine different types of eval as I
said automated benchmarks and human or
LLM judges uh together. This is a nice
way of doing it. And finally, don't
forget to compare your models with
others. Uh not just your fine tunes, but
also like other models, other
architectures can be really nice um to
be able to get a good picture of how you
score, how you compare uh with other
models. Okay, future trends.
So um the biggest trend right now and I
think in early 2025 is called test time
compute scaling and it's a very simple
idea. It's the idea that okay during
training we can train on a ton of data
and like throw a lot of compute at the
problem to get better at it. It works
very well. But what if we try to throw
compute at the problem during inference?
Um, and a very easy way of doing it is I
have a question, for example, a math
question. I ask my LLM not one solution
but multiple solutions. And I take the
one that is the most
frequent. And if you do that, well, well
done. It works. Um, you actually get
better results at this um at this math
uh question. Um, so this is a technique
called majority voting and it works, but
it's very naive. So there are better
versions of it. Uh one of them is best
of n. In best of n what you do is you
still generate different solutions but
instead of just picking the most
frequent one you will use a reward model
or a judge LLM to score every answer.
And here you can see different scores we
take the one uh with the highest score.
And good job. This is probably in most
cases even better than majority voting.
Uh so that also works but as you can see
now we have two models uh that need to
be run together to produce an answer. So
we throw more computer at the problem.
You can do even better and this one uses
um process reward models or PRM and
process reward models they do not just
score the final solution the entire
answer they score steps in the answer.
So if you have a math question, if you
want to do a calculation, you probably
need to solve it with multiple steps.
Process rule models allow you to score
each step independently and the score
that you get is pretty much the
probability that this step will give you
the right answer in the end. So you can
do that with an LLM and generate partial
solutions. You can then score the the
steps in your partial solutions with a
process reward model. Select the best
steps and expand them and you can do
that iteratively and you get better and
better scores. I'm not going to detail
like all the variants of it. There are
more complex solution that you can get
but you get the idea. We can just use
more large language models and do more
steps to produce better answers.
So an example of that um is this
question. What is the product of 6 * 7
when both numbers are in base 8? Give
your answer in base 8. Here you see the
first step was correct in attempt one.
Let's multiply them together. The second
is wrong because um it's in base 10 and
not in base 8 whatever. So the attempt
is wrong. We skip to attempt two. So now
it has an extra correct step but it has
the same issue. It's also rejected by
the process reward model. And finally we
have attempt four. I skip the third one.
Um where it's all correct and the answer
is good. So you see this mechanism we
iteratively um improve the quality and
iteratively we get better and better
steps. Yes.
Reward model is something that happens
during uh preference alignment. If you
remember the uh diagram with uh
PO, you see here that during training,
we actually have a reward model and this
reward model is specifically trained to
take u text as input and produce a
number between zero and one uh to give
you a score. So you can reuse the reward
model that you've made for preference
alignment in your test time compute
scaling. Um this is a way of doing it.
There are other ways you can just use a
judge LLM. Um you can just prompt a
model to um to give like a measure of
the quality. Um but this is a nice way
of reusing something that you've trained
uh before. So thank you for this
question. And finally here. Oh sorry.
Yeah. For example, if you do it infinite
number of times, you want to recover the
original model. Sorry, if you do it in,
let's say you generate an infinite
number of
answers. The thing is when you do
majority voting is that you're probably
going to use different sampling
parameters. So, it's not greedy
decoding. It's something that is more
like top P decoding. It has like you
will see that the model can sometimes
fail. This is also something that you
see with hallucinations. For example,
sometimes because of the non-greedy
decoding because there's some randomness
introduced in your decoding. The model
will just pick the wrong token and the
entire reasoning will be derailed
because it picked the wrong token. And
this is kind of the intrusion behind
majority voting is that we want to
recover the performance that are lost
through this um decoding process.
If you use a temperature of zero, you
will have the same answer every time.
Did you answer that?
Uh,
no. So, no, you like we do non-greedy
decoding because it actually improve the
performance of the mall in general. For
math and code like reasoning task, you
want to use a temperature that is very
low. So, this is like closer to what you
you're talking about. But, uh, for
majority voting, I would set a higher
temperature because I want diverse
answers. And because I have diverse
answers, then it makes sense that if an
if an outcome um is frequent, it's
probably the right one. It's not
foolproof for sure. Um this is not the
best method to do it, but this gives you
give the intuition of like how we can uh
do
it. All right. Then results. Um so this
is some work made by uh people at
hugging face and you can see that they
used llama 3.2 to 1B and 3B and they
manage by having like more and more uh
generations per problem to outperform
much bigger models like lama 3.18B and
LMA
3.170B. So this really shows that you
can transfer you can exchange inference
speed for output quality and this
scaling test time compute ID is really
about that. It's about if I have a lot
of inference it means that I can
generate a lot of uh different answers
and because I have that I can directly
um transform it into output
quality. Okay, that's it for me. Uh this
is the conclusion of this talk. It's um
the post- training loop is really about
creating a data set. So really spending
a lot of time on data. it's a third of
your time. Then training models using
all the techniques that we've seen,
supervised fine-tuning, uh preference
alignment techniques, maybe a bit of
model merging, uh if you can, and
finally evaluating it. Evaluation is
another third of your time. Um and
evaluation, as you've seen, it's it's a
bit messy. Um there are a lot of
different ways of doing it but you can
try to combine different techniques,
different families to have a good
representation, a good overview of the
performance of your model and based on
that it will probably give you feedback
about areas of improvement. You can see
that the model maybe is bad in math um
on the automated benchmarks which means
that you should probably generate more
math data and train it on it and you see
that it's a loop every time when you
evaluate the model you do not only
evaluate the fine-tuning process. What
you evaluate the most is actually the
data and the quality of the data that
you have the mixture the diversity
complexity and the accuracy of your
training data. So yeah, that's the
training loop and that's an iterative
process until you get better and better
and better
models. Thank you. Uh thank you
[Applause]
everyone. Awesome. Thank you Maxim. Is
there any questions? I can bring up
microphones just so we can uh go through
them with captions.
[Music]
You can
uh from the profit profitability
perspective from LM providers uh which
one has a better chance B2C generalized
models or B2B uh fine-tuned models thank
you
okay is your question is in terms what's
the metric is it in terms of uh which
one had a better chance in terms of
profitability of provider okay so it's a
it's a business question uh okay so uh
is it better to have like general B2C
models versus uh B2B finetune B2B model.
Uh I think that the B2C model um the
business model is really saturated right
now. So it's really going to be very
difficult to compete against um against
Google against OpenAI against Anthropic.
So I would say that it's probably better
to do some fine-tuning and targeting
business customers and you can like the
best case scenario you can use that as
leverage to then um become a B2C
company.
One of your earlier slide had um rag on
top uh in context learning rag and then
four branches and then eval. So I had
question about that second option which
was train on add
knowledge. We could add knowledge. So my
this is my intuition I'm trying to
portray. If we add knowledge in the
fine-tuning process it get the model
gets frozen at that point of time right
and the knowledge as we know will keep
evolving. Okay. So how does rag and that
adding of knowledge during fine-tuning a
compare or should we after adding the
knowledge still keep doing rag for
future refresh of the knowledge? Yep.
Yeah. Exactly. So uh the question is the
knowledge that we add here during
finetuning is frozen in time uh while
rag allows you to dynamically like
retrieve uh up to-date context and I
think that there is never like fine
tuning versus rag it's rag or fine
tuning plus rag basically uh so yeah I
would always recommend using both uh if
retrieval augmentation um makes sense.
It's better to do it with a fine tune
model.
Hi, typically when you have to train
with parametric in finetuning or
fine-tuning a large language model, you
use like input output pairs. But if you
don't have data and you want to maybe do
a reinforcement
learning a use of weights of the model,
which type of algorithm do you usually
use at first?
Sorry I didn't get the the beginning of
your question. I was looking for you
here. Can you repeat it please? Okay. If
you don't have like input output pairs
and you have to do reinforcement
learning which type of algorithm you use
like proximal policy optimization others
or which type of library for example if
you don't have input output maybe you
want to uh use your large language model
to made
uh more knife or um have like a type of
personality and you can use for example
a bird or another language for
classificate. So you have a policy. What
type of algorithm do you we lose? Yeah,
I would recommend like to to change
maybe the tone. It depends on the use
case that you you want to do. But if
it's really about like something like
changing the tone of the model, I would
definitely recommend doing preference
alignment. and within preference
alignment direct preference optimization
DPO is like the algorithm that will work
out of the box for you. Um then the
question is how to get the the data and
to do that yeah this is like data
pipeline um that we we talked about
ultra feedback is a good example of how
to generate this kind of data. Okay
thank you. Thank you.
[Music]
Uh it seems to me that the techniques
that you presented focus on single turn
interactions. So for example, we have an
instruction and then we have an answer.
Uh can we also do some multi-turn
optimization or preference alignment?
Sorry, preference alignment with
multi-turn.
Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Absolutely.
Absolutely. Um this can be completely um
expanded to multi-turn conversation and
actually it's a good way of doing it
because we we see often that uh what
works with a single turn. For example,
instruction following doesn't work with
multi-turn. Um there's like an entire
evaluation set uh dedicated to
multi-turn instruction following and it
shows that models that are good with
single turn might not be with
multi-turn. So yeah, I would recommend
um when possible always trying to get
some multi-turn data instead of single
turn.
A number of people want to know if
you'll do autographs at the end of
today.
Thank you. Thank you. Yes. Yeah. Yeah.
Um, I have a question about
the example with the model merging where
you uh you you average the Finnish model
and the English model. Yeah. So, I'm
just trying to get a sense of
um well, first of all, when you have
these two different languages, like the
the input and output space are very
different. So do you like train a
separate tokenizer per language or how
and like just the trunk is shared or how
does it usually work when you do this
cross language training? Yeah, so it's a
good question. Um tokenizers are really
created on a calibration data set and
this calibration data set most of the
time has a ton of English. So yeah, the
tokenizer of the model for example llama
is mostly dedicated to English and you
can have special tokens. You can also
have like some Chinese for example,
Japanese, Korean, Arabic, Finnish uh to
get other um special characters. Um but
in general and here in this example, I
would say this is kind of out of scope a
bit. We are going to use the same model
with the same tokenizer in the base and
the instruct version. And changing the
tokenizer at this point is too late. We
need to do it um before pre-training. Uh
and if you try to change the tokenizer
during post training, you're going to
absolutely uh drop in term of
performance. uh because the model has to
relearn the entire mapping between the
token ids and the embeddings. Uh so
that's kind of like a costly uh
solution. But I agree that in general
it's a lot better if your tokenizer is
designed for a specific language and
you're going to really struggle if you
have a small voc vocabulary size. a
tokenizer with like 20 uh,000 um
different tokens, it's going to be very
difficult to learn uh languages with
completely different uh characters like
Chinese.
Great. Let's do one more.
I thank
you. Um with the techniques like the
best of end and majority vote can we
give a sense of uncertainty to the end
user for like security or safety
critical applications?
Yeah. So you do you want to to use these
techniques not for math but for other
domains?
um like the so if you're using majority
voting or um best of end with the scores
there can be a widespread or a smaller
spread and that could give a sense of
like how certain the model is about a
technique or is that the case and can
then we then feed it to the user um when
like a regulatory agency is asking for
like yes safety or security critical
issues. Yeah, definitely definitely you
can use it as a measure of uncertainty,
but in your precise use case, you could
also use a reward model that is
dedicated for this task. Um, it doesn't
have to be general purpose. It can also
be really dedicated to measure toxicity
for example and provide scores only uh
on this metric. So this is a nice way of
customizing the best of end technique uh
to tailor it for specific use
cases. Excellent. Okay, let's all thanks
Maxim one more time.