[Music]
Hi everyone. Welcome back to lecture
five of MIT deep learning. Today we're
going to learn about how we can marry
these two very long-standing fields of
deep learning like we've been learning
about in this entire course together
with this other field of reinforcement
learning. And the combination of the two
is going to be the focus of today's
lecture. So deep reinforcement learning
is is quite an amazing intersection of
two fields because it moves actually
beyond everything that we've seen in the
course so far uh that we've that that
we've learned right so specifically it
moves away from this paradigm of trying
to learn on you know data that we've
seen in the world to make predictions or
or you know inferences uh that mimic
that piece th those pieces of data.
Instead, you know, the the movement in
reinforcement learning and deep learning
together focuses at building this
interaction between a model and its
environment and its data. Right? This is
not about just taking a data set that is
pre-colcted and training a deep learning
model on it, but actually having a
dynamic environment where the model will
interact with that environment in order
to learn. And the goal is that we want
to ideally try and do this without uh
any supervision, without any human
labels or as ideally with as few human
labels as possible. Now this has a lot
of obvious implications in the world. It
it basically we see applications of this
type of technology and everything from
autonomy and robotics all the way to
gameplay, right? In fact, a lot of the
original uh breakthroughs in deep
reinforcement learning have come from
gameplay. And we'll see some exa some
strategies or some some uh some recent
works that have really driven forward
the field starting in this field in this
uh realm as well.
Now I want to start by just setting a
little bit of groundwork uh and laying
the groundwork for everything that we're
going to see in the rest of the class
today and just taking a step back first
of all and trying to understand how
reinforcement learning fits into this
bigger paradigm of all of the different
types of learning algorithms that we've
seen in the class so far. We've seen two
types of things, right? We've seen
architectures, right? Lecture one, we
talked about fully connected networks.
Lectures two was re recurrent neural
neural networks. Lecture three was
convolutional neural networks. These are
all architectures. And then we started
talking about learning algorithms.
Supervised learning, unsupervised
learning and today is reinforcement
learning. Algorithms are agnostic to
architectures. Right? So one the first
algorithm that we saw was supervised
learning. Supervised learning focuses on
problems like this where we are given
X's and Y's. X's are our inputs, Y's are
desired outputs. And our goal here is to
learn a model that given an X will learn
how to predict a Y from a lot of
examples of X's and Y's, I can try to
learn that mapping concretely. So for
example, an analog or you know intuitive
de example here with this apple, right?
If I show a lot of pictures of apples to
a model and I say this is an apple, this
is an apple. If I showed a new apple
that looks slightly different, it should
still be able to recognize that this is
yet another
apple. Next, we discussed unsupervised
learning, right? This was the lecture
number four that we saw yesterday where
we only have access to the data. We only
have access to the x's, but we do not
have access to the y's. So, there are no
labels in unsupervised learning. But now
for example this this apple example is
trying to say okay if I just show you a
lot of these similar things I don't have
to tell you that they are apples but if
I show you another thing in that
category it should be able to detect
that you know even if you don't know
that this is an apple or what an apple
means you should be able to detect
similarities in the features just by
observing many of these
X's. And finally in today's class,
reinforcement learning is the third
category of algorithms that we'll be
covering in this class. And this is
going to focus on, you know, moving away
from X's and Y's. Now we're going to be
given what are called pairs between
states and actions. Okay, so states are
simply the observations that our model
will see while it interacts with the
environments. And the actions is how it
can interact with that environment. how
it can, you know, make decisions to
receive new observations, right? We'll
make this more concrete in the next few
slides, but really the goal of
reinforcement learning is to take all of
these state action pairs. So instead of
XY pairs, just like data and label
pairs, now we're going to take state
action pairs. And the goal of
reinforcement learning is to learn how
to, you know, take actions in this
environment such that we see desirable
states, right? And we'll talk about how
to measure desiraability. These are
rewards that we'll give to these models
over time. But a good example of this is
you know again in the apple scenario we
don't have to say you know this is an
apple or this is not an apple. But just
by interacting with these items you know
a model should be able to learn that it
needs to eat apples for nutrition in
order to survive for instance.
So today's lecture we're going to be
focusing on this third category of
algorithms and seeing how we can build
models in this type of world as well. So
before we go any further I want to dig
into all of the terminology that I just
introduced on the previous slide. Right?
And I'll I'll just start by introducing
the the vocabulary first of all that
we're going to be building on throughout
the entire lecture today. So this part
is actually a really important part of
the lecture because uh it the entire
rest of the course will will build on
this part here. So we're going to start
with this this uh piece of the
reinforcement learning pipeline on the
left hand side. This is the agent. This
is the main actor in the environment. So
this is the thing that is taking the
decisions. It's taking the actions, you
know. So this could be, you know, Mario
in Super Mario. It could be a drone in a
navigation or a delivery setting. You
know, in life, we are all the agents,
right? We're the ones acting in our
environment and making
decisions. Then we have the environment.
This is simply just the place, the world
in which the agent exists and makes its
decisions. And of course, the
interaction between these two things is
that the agent can send actions to the
environment, right? actions correspond
to, you know, different sets of possible
things that this agent could do. So, for
example, we could imagine a a simple
two-dimensional world, a two-dimensional
environment where our agent can move in
just one of four directions, up, down,
left, or right. And you can basically
imagine actions being living within this
discrete space. So, you can imagine a
very simplified world where you have
just four possible actions that you
could ever take, up, down, left, or
right. Or you can imagine a much more
continuous space, right? Like like all
of our lives where we have many a
continuous and infinite amount of
actions that can define our
future. And finally, this feedback loop
closes on the other side as well by the
environment sending back observations to
the agent. Right? Based on an action
that the agent takes, the obs the the
environment will send back and reply.
You can think of it like this with a new
observation of how the world has changed
by them taking this action. And there's
one more step here is that not only does
the agent or sorry, not only does the
environment reply with an observation,
the environment also replies with a form
of reward signal, right? So this is how
it it's it's demonstrating how desirable
of a
state the the agent has now entered
into, right?
So this is a reward. We'll call this R
at time
t. And finally,
ultimately what we really care about is
not just the reward at one time t, but
we're looking at, you know, a total
reward that this agent is able to
accumulate throughout an entire
lifetime, right? So the agent will live
from, let's say, time one all the way to
time capital T. and it accumulates
rewards over time which is simply just
the sum of all of these rewards from one
to capital T.
But often times it's actually useful I
want to highlight this that it's
actually useful to not only think about
the sum of all rewards you know just the
aggregate sum of every reward that you
accumulate over time because not all
rewards are created equally right for
example future rewards are oftent times
much less valuable than current rewards
right you can imagine this for example
if I offered you to give you $5 today or
$5 in 10 years from today the $5 is not
worth the same amount in that time, even
if without inflation or anything, you
would still prefer the $5 today because
it's $5 that you could spend today and
choose what you can do with it. So,
oftentimes what we'll think about when
we develop these reward functions is not
just a total sum of all rewards, but we
actually discount future rewards more
heavily the farther they are into the
future. This enforces, you know, some
form of basically short-term uh, you
know, feedback for the model to be able
to prioritize the rewards that come
sooner and discourage the rewards that
come a bit later into the
future. Now, finally, there's this very
important function in reinforcement
learning called the Q function. So let's
look at how the Q function is defined,
what it is, and you know, especially
putting it into the context of all of
these definitions and vocabulary that
we've learned so far. So remember this
equation. So the reward function capital
R of T is just going to be the total
discounted sum of rewards that happens
from time t all the way into the future.
So starting from this current time up
into the up until the the maximum time
into the future. Now the Q function that
I mentioned earlier, this is just going
to be a function that takes us input two
things. It's going to take us input the
current state that the that the agent is
in and the action that it will take in
this state. And the Q function is just
going to return the expected total
future reward that this agent will see
by taking this action from this current
state. So if the agent executes this
action a of t at time t given the state
that it's currently in s of t, what is
the total future expected reward that
this agent could ever receive, you know,
by taking this
action? Now the question is you know if
we are given
this you know actually magical Q
function I'm not going to tell you how
we are given it but I'm just going to
tell you that you are given this Q
function. So given a function that if
you if you give it a state and an action
pair it will tell you how much reward
that you can expect to receive. Let me
ask a question to everyone here. If you
if you had access to this type of
function and I asked you, you know, how
would what action would you pick? Given
a current state, what action would you
pick? How would you use this Q function
to determine your best next action?
Right? So, you find yourself in a state
and I give you a Q function. Can you use
that Q function to determine what is
your next best action?
Exactly. Yes. So what you would do is
ultimately you know what you want is to
identify what is the best action that
you can take in this state. You can use
the Q function to basically say okay let
me evaluate my Q function as you
suggested over all of these different
actions and for each action I will
compute what is the what is the expected
reward that I would receive and I'll
take the maximum of all of those. I'll
take the the action that gives me back
the maximal expected reward based on all
of those possible
actions. Okay. Now remember though what
we really care about is not just uh you
know observing all of these. We really
want to choose the action that maximizes
this future reward. So what does that
look like? As we said, we can formulate
that as the optimal action for any given
state is just going to be computed by
basically plugging in all of our actions
to this Q function, evaluating the Q
function across all of these actions,
and then picking the action that gives
us back the best
reward. Okay.
Yes,
this
is for example offer
now. So is this kind of getting this.
Yes. Yes. Yeah. So the question is
basically about like how can you not
just optimize based on the reward right
now but the reward into the future as
well. And that's actually a really good
question because you know why I wanted
to highlight this is because remember
the Q function is optimizing over
capital R of T which is the return. And
this is not little R of T which is the
reward at time T. Right? So capital R of
T. Let me go back one slide because this
is a really good point. capital R oft
the relationship between the return and
the reward is that the return is the sum
the discounted sum of all future
rewards. So this would also account for
cases where you take potentially a
suboptimal action now for less reward
but this sets you up for a better
success in the future. This would be
captured in capital R but would be lost
in little R. But remember in in Q
functions you actually capture the
entire future return that you would
expect to take by taking this action.
You assume that if you take this action
and all optimal future actions after
that what would be the expected return
that you could possibly achieve and this
would be how you determine the action.
So now in this function in this lecture
what we're going to do is basically
focus on two different ways that we can
learn this you know action maker right
if you will right given then there's
basically two two different ways that
I'll I'll tell you about so number one
is ways that we we do this by first of
all trying to get access to this Q
function we already saw that if we had
access to the Q function we could have a
good action maker right we know how to
take actions based on that Q function
The secret is basically you have to find
the Q function. This is a magical
function and we'll talk about basically
one way to do it is basically by trying
to learn the value of that Q function.
This is called value learning. So you
try to find Q and then you use Q in
exactly the way that we saw just by
taking the argmax over the actions. And
then you have another side of learning
which we'll also cover today which folks
is instead of you know trying to learn Q
and then use Q what if you just directly
tried to learn this policy function
because ultimately your policy function
is a function that doesn't you know get
evaluated over all the actions it just
gets evaluated over your states and this
is actually the function that you really
care about you want this function pi pi
of s that takes as input your state and
tells you the action
There shouldn't be a need to necessarily
say I want to evaluate my Q function
over
every
sly tell me the action right and then
how would I use this you know I can just
sample optimal actions from that policy
right in order to achieve we'll talk
more about this but I want to dig into
first of all the first part of the
lecture which is just going to focus on
this first technique that we saw trying
defined a Q function and then leverage
that Q function to find the optimal
action. Let's dig into this a little bit
more because I think a lot of the
questions will start to get answered as
we see an example here. First, I'll
introduce you know this this game of
Atari on the left right now. For those
of you who are not familiar with uh you
know Atari Breakout, this is a game
where the actor is this paddle on the
bottom, right? So this is a horizontal
paddle that can move only in one of two
directions, right? Only left or right,
only two actions. And its objective is
to basically make sure that it moves in
a direction that it can hit this
oncoming ball that's approaching it and
bounce off of its paddle in order to hit
and break off the colored blocks at the
top. Now, the objective is basically to
break off as many of those blocks at the
top before it misses the ball and it
passes by. If the ball passes without
the paddle hitting it, it loses the
game. So it wants to actually basically
keep hitting the the blocks or keeps
hitting the ball. So it breaks off the
blocks. Now let me let me present
basically a you know a interesting
scenario to to the audience.
So I want to highlight that you know
estimating or even getting intuition
about Q functions can be sometimes very
difficult for humans and actually often
times humans are not very good at
estimating what are optimal Q functions.
So let me give an example here. So
here's two different scenarios state
action pairs. There are two different
state action pairs. So here's on the A
category. This is a category where the
ball is coming right to the paddle and
the paddle is going to decide to not
move and just hit the ball back and
break off some of the colored in the
background. And then we'll have another
scenario on B where the ball is actually
approaching to the side and the paddle
has to try to move towards it just to
catch up to the to the ball. Does anyone
have an idea of you know which state
action pair you would think has a higher
Q value if you estimated the Q value for
both of these?
I think it would probably be option B
because the reward would be higher
although there is more of a chance
because bouncing to the side.
Okay. How about any other answers for
maybe for a
Yeah, go ahead. Yeah, because I played
this game before.
[Laughter]
Yeah, regardless how how old that that
was, but I think the problem with B is
that as you go to the side, this thing
gets kind of slow for some reason. So, I
think Mhm. Okay. Okay. How about we do a
show of hands? So, uh, people that think
A will be better, you can raise your
hand. Yeah. And how about
B? Okay. Yeah, I'd say probably 60 60%
for B. Uh, okay. So, let's let's take a
look at it. So, actually, let's take a
look at A first, right? And we'll look
at actually a policy that implements
both of these strategies. Uh, just so we
can compare them qualitatively, right?
So, these are A is basically uh defined
by very conservative actions. It tries
to hit the ball straight on to the
center of the paddle. Right now, what
does this look like? Here we can see an
example of this strategy executed in
practice. Right? It's very conservative.
It usually tries to hit the ball right
in the center of the paddle and it's
been trained to do that. But as a
result, you see it really starting to
break off a lot of the balls also in the
center of the game. Right now, let's
take a look at strategy B where it
actually you'll see something
interesting here that the paddle
actually tries to move away from the
ball purposely just so it can come back
and hit it at the side and at an angle.
Now, why does it do this? It moves away
from it. You see, it's hiding actually
on the left hand side just so it can
come back and hit it from a corner and
try to break out the top and and get
this cheat code basically, you know, at
the top of the game. and it's learned
that, you know, there's kind of this
cheat code. If it breaks into a corner,
it gets like all of these free
blocks. Now, this is just one example,
right, of of trying to demonstrate how,
you know, it's it's oftentimes very
difficult to build intuition about what
Q functions or Q values are are good at
in order to determine the best actions
that we could take at a particular
state. And this is why it requires so
many examples to to play with these
systems in order to encounter just one
scenario that looks like that and and
try to reinforce it as part of learning.
So now let's ask ourselves this
question, right? How can we train our
model to learn a Q function like we just
saw on the previous slide, right?
Because that's ultimately the the
objective here is, you know, given the
two things that we see on the left,
given a state and an action pair. Our
state is just a current frame of our of
our game where we currently are at this
exact moment. And given an action that
we want, let's evaluate how good of an
action that is.
Right? Okay. So now what what we can do
is create a network in two different
forms. We could have a network that
takes as input a single action that we
call it multiple times for every action
to evaluate its Q value for each of
those actions. Or we can have something
like on the right hand side where we
just you know basically shift the action
onto the other side onto the output side
and basically say okay for a single
state I'm going to output the Q value
for every possible action. Right? These
two sides are identical. There's no
difference here. The only difference is
actually you're changing the
parameterization of how you know you're
you're calling this model. Instead of
the calling the model you know uh n
times where n is the number of actions
on the left hand side you call the model
one time and you get n outputs. So
you're basically sh you know re
redefining the model to say okay instead
of calling the model n times I'm going
to just output n times instead. It's
actually the same the same situation.
But what we'll focus on is actually the
side on the right because usually
calling the model is is very expensive,
right? So we want to minimize the number
of calls that we have to the model and
we want to say okay, how many times can
we get an can we get all of our answers
at once basically from a single call of
the
model. Yep.
So, so the state has to capture not only
the state of the paddle but of the ball
and the angle of the ball and where it
is. So, it's so the state captures a lot
more than just where the par is captur.
Yeah. Yeah. The state captures the
environment, right? So, the state
captures let's say it's like an entire
picture of uh of the screen. Exactly.
Yes. So, and basically this means that
you know what you're trying to do here
is that you're you're trying to train a
network that given you know a picture of
the screen which is basically exactly
what we as humans would see if we played
this game right how would how would what
action would result in the highest
return. Now what would happen here if if
we made an agent that you know took all
of the best actions right what would
that look like? Well, what this would h
what this would amount to is basically
maximizing the target return for any
given state, right? So given a state, we
always want to maximize the target
return. So given all of these outputs of
possible returns, the Q values, we want
to maximize those Q values at every
possible step, right? Which actually
also means that all we really want to do
is just take all of the best actions in
order to produce that target return.
Now to do this we can formulate this
expected return as if we were going to
take all of those best actions which is
just going to be combined you know two
things combined it's first it's going to
be the initial reward that we get at
this exact uh you know instance r oft
combined with the expected maximum
future return that we get in all future
steps from this point on. And of course,
we also have to apply the discounting
factor so that we discount for all of
the future returns because those are not
as valuable as our current returns. And
this is our target, right? This is our
target value that we're trying to
optimize
for. We also have the predicted value
because we can call our network and ask
our network, you know, what did you
think the predicted Q value would be?
And that's going to be our predicted
value. Now automatically you should look
at these two things and this should look
very similar to what we've seen in other
parts of the class right we have a
predicted value we have a target value
we can now subtract these two and
compute a norm between them let's say an
absolute value or a squared value
between these two values and then this
gives us exactly the the term that we
are describing as the loss right this is
our loss that we can use for back
propagating so that on the next step
when we call this Q value hopefully the
prediction is going to be closer to the
target return that we would have
achieved. And this is exactly the Q
loss, right? This is what is known as
the Q loss. Let me just summarize this
and then I'll I'll pause for questions
before we go on to the next uh section.
Right? So let's summarize this whole
process end to end. Right? This is our
deep neural network that is our Q
network. Right? This is going to take as
input our state and it's going to output
a Q value for every possible action that
this agent could see. We're assuming
there are discrete actions here. So
there's let's say K different actions
that the agent could take and it's going
to output K different you know Q values.
These are just K different numbers. So
here are the actions that that this
model could take. Let's say again in the
game of in the game of breakout we have
three actions left right or stay
constant for each of those actions we
can have our model predict the Q value.
So let's say for example in this given
state on the left the Q value for going
left is going to be 20. The Q value for
going uh you know staying in the same
place is three and the Q value for going
right is zero. Why is this the case is
because as you can see the ball is
traveling to the left and the paddle is
already to the right. So if it goes to
the right it knows it's definitely gonna
you know not get any more future
returns. If it stays in the same it's
also very unlikely that maybe it has a
few more time steps to pick up those
returns and move to the left but it's
running out of time. Now with all of
those you know let's revisit what we
talked about earlier in the class. Given
all of those Q values we have three
numbers. Now, how do you determine
what's the best action to take? Well,
you'd look at those three numbers. You'd
say 20 is the return, expected return of
going left, three is the expected return
of staying still, and zero is the
expected return of going right. I should
go to the left, right? Because I want to
maximize my chances at getting future
returns. And then I take that action. I
actually go to the left. I send that to
the game. The game gives me back a new
state based on my one movement to the
left. The state changes of the game and
this whole process repeats over and over
again. You know this this uh exact
paradigm, this exact algorithm has been
you know used in practice extensively
with many different uh you know
examples. One example was with Google
DeepMind how they use these networks
called Q networks uh to apply to solve
you know a variety of different types of
these breakout Atari games. Uh so
basically on the left hand side you can
see the state always coming in as input
but now not three outputs coming out but
a very wide range of actions that this
agent could see at any or could make at
any point in time. And you see this very
big network in the middle that tries to
determine for this action you know what
are all of the Q values for all of these
states and you know actually a really
really elegant and really simple you
know at its core type of algorithm. It's
actually amazing how well this works
because they tested on so many of these
Atari games. And here you can see the
performance of those games, over 50% of
the games with this basic method, right?
No no extra, you know, tips and tricks
involved here. This is really just the
the method that they used and 50 over
50% of the games surpassed human level
performance just with this basic
technique. Um, other games obviously on
the far right hand side you see this
tail end that were obviously there's
plenty of games where these are way more
challenging than what a simple technique
like this would be able to handle. But
still it's to me it's it's amazing how
how simple and clean this algorithm is
to uh uh you know to work at this scale
you know for this many for this many you
know complex behaviors as well. Okay,
one more thing and then I'll pause for
questions on Q-learning. So I want to
comment on the downsides the
disadvantages of Q-learning and this
will help motivate you know the next
section uh in in our transition. So
number one you know we only talked about
these discrete action spaces right
discrete action spaces means where your
actions are one of n different actions
but you have to choose one of those
actions. So this can only model what
we've talked about so far. We've only
seen how we can model those types of
spaces, right? That's obviously a very
big disadvantage and we're going to talk
about how we can alleviate that uh in
the future so that we can move more
towards these continuous action spaces.
That's number one. Number two is going
to be on the flexibility of these
algorithms. If I gave it the uh the same
state twice, it would give me the same
answer twice. No matter how many times I
gave it the state, I could give the
state same state a 100 times, it would
always tell me the next action is the
same because this is a deterministic
algorithm. There's no stochasticity
involved in this algorithm. We'll also
see why this is problematic because it
doesn't allow us to deal with stoastic
environments as well, right? Our
environments are not always
deterministic. So we need, you know,
policies and action networks that are
capable of being stocastic as well.
So to address these basically the these
two considerations are going to be the
ones that drive forward the next part of
the lecture which will focus on policy
learning. Not trying to learn the Q
network to derive a policy but directly
learning our policy from the model. I'll
pause there uh and just take a couple
questions before we go on to the next
slide. Uh yes you're
go
ahead. Firstly, there is an assumption
that all future actions are also
correct. Next,
yes, we'll we'll see some examples of of
how these will extend beyond to like
very large action spaces. It's
definitely problematic where you have
very large action spaces. I would say in
some like for example, chess, right?
Chess has, you know, the the space of
trajectories or space of like solutions
is is massive, but the space of actions
is actually not as massive as one would
think, right? At any moment in time,
there's a relatively manageable set of
possible actions that could be taken,
right? But if you think of like let's
say even just building out a tree of
actions three steps in the future, this
grows massively, right? Then it's
problematic. But remember your Q network
only needs to manage you know one like
just given a state right now actions
that are taken at this step right. So
your action space is defined by actions
at every step not actions you know uh
you know jointly over the entire
trajectory of all futures.
Exactly. So you want constraints. So the
question is about do you have uh rules
on the game imposing on your action
spaces and yes right you want to make
sure that you only allow for actions
when you select an action that are valid
actions. Okay, one more question.
Um, yeah, you've been waiting actually,
sorry, you've been waiting a long time
for the rewards. Are there scenarios
where the reward could be contextual and
subjective? So, in this case, our
example
[Music]
objectives that consequence. Exactly.
So, the question is about like how do
you define success basically, right? So
this is the yeah we didn't touch on this
at all but actually the the the
underlying assumption to all of this is
that you have a uh an a reward model
that is uh calibrated with what you
believe is true reward. Right? So if if
something says that okay you receive a
reward of you know whatever of 100
points it actually calibrates to 100
units of of reward for that for that
individual. Right? Defining that
calibration metric is a is a very
difficult problem. We completely glanced
over this, right? But who defines this
is the game maker, right? It is the
person designing the game. This is not a
learned uh thing, right? Whoever sets up
the game defines what the rewards are
because it's part of the rules of the
game. Excellent. Okay. So let's for the
sake of time let's keep pushing forward
and uh I'll zoom back out to these two
parts of the reinforcement learning
algorithms that we've been talking about
so far. So so far we've only talked on
this left side, right? We've focusing on
cases where we want to learn the Q
function. Use that Q function to to
determine the optimal action by picking
the you know maximum the the action that
gives us the maximum future Q or the
maximum future return. Now let's focus
on policy learning algorithms which
don't aim to do this intermediate learn
this intermediate Q function. They aim
to directly learn the policy. So the
policy is again this function that takes
us input the state such that if you
sample from this policy function you
directly get an action does not need to
necessarily be an optimal action but it
should be one of good one of the good
actions. If you sample from it enough it
should be on expectation the best
action. We'll talk about this more
detail in this next section. So one
quick recap now. So what did we just see
with Q networks? We're going to build
off of all of that to go into the policy
networks as well. So what did we just
see? Deep Q networks take as input the
state the output all of the Q values for
all of the actions. Then we pick the
argmax over those actions. For policy
networks, the only difference that we're
going to make now is that we're going to
directly output not the Q value, but for
each of those actions, we're going to
output a probability that that action
would have been the best action from our
Q value. Okay, so let's break that down
a little bit more. So let's go back to
this example with Atari. Instead of
outputting the Q value for each of those
actions, I'm now going to output this
probability score. Okay, so the
probability that me going to the left
hand side given this state, we'll see
we'll see when we evaluate our policy
network is 0.9. With 90% probability, we
believe given this network that the left
action is the best action. With 10%
probability, we see that staying still
is probably the best action. And with 0%
probability, we see that going right is
the best action. So we've changed the
definition of kind of what is the
output. Why do we do this? Well, it's
because if we have a probability
function over our output space, it means
that now we can pick our best action not
just by taking the maximum of these
numbers, but we can sample from that
probability distribution, right? In
order to determine what is our next
action to take, we can take all of those
probabilities and sample from them. So
that you know 90% of the time we would
get the action going left, but 10% of
the time we would still get this action
staying
still. We have to enforce of course that
you know because we're now dealing with
probabilities we have more constraints
on the model on the model's output.
Right? So now number one the the biggest
constraint is that you know
probabilities have to add up to one. So
we have to enforce that the output of
our model uh respects that constraint
first of all we can do this for example
with softmax. Basically we're we're
dealing with a classification problem
almost at this point right we're trying
to classify you know given a state what
is the optimal next action that we want
to take from this
state. Now I want to open up a little
bit for some ideas. Maybe we can get
like two people in the room can can tell
me what are the main advantages that you
see with this formulation so far even
without going into much depth. Yes.
With this approach you would take
that times.
Good. Yep. So sometimes we would get
some exploration right of of maybe less
you know optimal or less maximal
actions. Yep. Yep. Because you're
sampling you could also see which
direction you're going to go based on
this action like what is the next
action? Is that a positive or a
negative? Right. Right. So yeah it gets
back at a similar point. Right. So
exploration as well. Yep. One more. you
reduce time complexity because now
you're not computing
um each of the
well you still have to compute each of
them because it's still uh you're you're
outputting all all of the probabilities
right so the time complexity of this
network is still going to be the same
let's see try and call in someone new uh
yes we no longer have to wait for the
evaluation like we have to use earlier
right so evaluation time gets kind of
reduced I
Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Go ahead. The main
advantages here is where where obtaining
the Q function might be very hard to
calculate and estimate over over the
time period that Exactly. Yeah. Exactly.
Exactly. So like you're the point is
that you're you're you're getting a more
direct function to the to the thing that
you're desiring, right? Um which which
is exactly the point. And we'll see
actually we'll make that more concrete.
it'll be more clear like why you would
want to do that in a second. So, one
advantage here actually tied if you if
you combine all of those pieces
together. Actually, an implicit thing
that hasn't been said is that you can
now deal with both discrete and
continuous actions. Right? Before we
could only deal with discrete actions
because it only allowed us to estimate
uh you know Q values for a finite set of
different actions. How could we do this
for continuous actions as well? So for
example here's a discrete action space
left right or stay in the middle and we
can see that basically okay we can have
a probability of doing that doing each
of those actions is the best action
that's a probability over a discrete
space but what if for example we wanted
to change this into a continuous space
like instead of saying left right or
stay if I said how fast to the left or
how fast to the right do I want to move
now all of a sudden we're not having a
you know three different actions This is
now an infinite action space that can be
any number on this real number line on
the x-axis. How could we you know
generalize this approach to deal with
that? Q networks would not be able to do
this. But with policy networks we can do
this because now we can actually model
you know a continuous probability
function over the output and say okay
for you know this probability mass can
we estimate this with our model and then
can we sample from that mass to produce
our best
action. So now what we want to say is
okay the probability or let me say it
like this the best action that I should
take at any point in time is just going
to be a sample from this estimated
probability distribution that I can
predict with my
network. So let's take a look at how we
could actually model these continuous
action spaces with a policy grade with a
policy network type of method. So
instead of predicting the probability
for each of those three different
classes like we saw before or let me say
like instead of predicting the
probability for every possible action
that could
exist which of course we cannot do this
for an infinite number of actions even
if we just have one number like the
speed it's an infinite number of speeds
that that this model could take. Uh so
we can't do that already. We've thrown
that approach out. Now, how would we do
this for output distributions that are
basically having an infinite number of
actions? Well, we could do this by
parameterizing our action space by a
distribution, right? So, a distribution
like you can see here, this is a
Gaussian distribution. How many numbers
do you need to generate a Gausian
distribution? Any Gausian
distribution? Yeah, just two numbers.
So, two numbers would describe this
entire probability mass, right? You need
a mean. This tells you at the center of
your gausian and you also need a
variance which tells you the width or
the the spread of the gausian. So now
you just have a prediction of instead of
an infinite number of actions you just
predict two numbers. You predict a mean
and you predict a variance. And this
tells you your probability score for
every
possible speed that this model could
take.
So if we want to then sample you know
and and you know say okay what is the
speed that that my model should act on
well I could just look at my mean and my
variance and I could sample from that
distribution and that distribution will
tell me exactly right that my optimal
you know mean and variance would be at
this point right close to the mean or
but maybe with some spread and of course
you know again just like before we have
to have this constraint of probabilities
summing to one, right? Which we can do
because we actually explicitly
parameterize our model using this
gausian
formulation. Okay, so now let's look at,
you know, let's tie all of this together
with a concrete example of policy
gradients in in practice, right? Let's
think of how we could take this method
and use it to train an autonomous
vehicle in a kind of simplified
environment using reinforcement learning
and this policy uh policy method. Right?
So here the agent is going to be a
vehicle that we want to navigate in
world. Actually let's simplify it even
further and just say not let's just say
stay in your lane and don't crash. This
is the the criteria. Uh the environment
is going to be you know where it is on
the lane right how far from the center
line it is and so on and it's and its
movement in that world. Its actions that
it can take will be just the steering
wheel angle right at any moment in time
it can execute a steering wheel angle.
Steering wheel angles are continuous
right you could be any angle within a
wide range of
angles. And finally the reward. Let's
keep it simple. You won't get a reward
on every single time step. you'll just
get a penalty if you crash and you want
to maximize the time before you crash.
This is the the the
reward. So, okay, let's let's uh let's
pull all of this together and let's see
how we can train this network uh in this
context. So, we're going to start by
firstly initializing our agent. We
initialize the car in this environment
and we're going to run our policy. So at
every moment, at every step, how did we
run this policy? At every step, we
computed our policy probabilities. We
sampled from those probabilities to
compute the action that the car thinks
that it should execute at that time. And
then it executes that action and it
repeats this in a loop. Of course, in
the beginning, it was never trained. So
the policies are really bad. The
probabilities are very uncorrelated with
what is safe. So it it travels very uh
you doesn't travel very far. and it
ultimately crashes. What we're going to
do though is for each one of those
steps, we will record every state and
every action pair that it executed and
it saw. And as well, we will also
uh record the rewards that it saw in
each one of those stages as well. So at
each one of those steps, we will have a
triplet of three numbers, a state, an
action, and a reward
pair. And then finally what we'll do is
we'll take we'll go back to our policy
network and we will just do two things.
We will discourage we will decrease the
probability of every action that
happened in the lowreward parts of this
sequence which will be the things close
to the the crash. Right? So roughly
we'll have two parts of the sequence.
The parts close to the crash and the
parts far from the crash. parts close to
the crash, we will decrease the
probability of everything that happened
close to that part and we will increase
the probability of repeating all the
actions that happened and everything far
away from that uh from that
crash. Then we will repeat this entire
loop again from scratch. We will
reinitialize the agent. We will start
it, rerun the policy. We will re-record
new state action reward triplets and
again we will do the same thing right we
will decrease the probability of the
things that came later and increase the
probability of things that came sooner.
Don't get caught up on later versus
sooner. The point is actually we're
decreasing the probability of the
penalized actions and we're increasing
the probability of the good actions. The
fact that the good actions were actually
earlier and the bad actions were later
is just a consequence of this particular
example. It doesn't necessarily need to
be the case.
Now we keep repeating this over and over
again and eventually you'll learn that
the agent you know can can you know keep
learning from all of its mistakes keep
increasing the things that went good and
decrease the things that went bad and
eventually it starts to kind of follow
these lanes without crashing.
Now this is really amazing because
number one we never showed this model
any information about uh the
environment. We never taught it the
rules of driving or you know that it has
to stay in its lanes. We only gave it an
extremely sparse reward signal that we
penalized it when it crashed, when it
exited its lanes. We never told it
anything explicit. We never gave it any
examples of humans driving in order for
it to learn this task. But it's able to
learn this task just by interacting with
the environment and receiving those
reward signals iteratively.
Now I think the the nuance here of
course is in this part of the uh of the
of the algorithm, right? So these last
two steps especially this is where the
nuance really starts to drive home how
did we increase the probability of the
good things happening and how did we
decrease the probability of the bad
things happening because this is how we
trained our model. Step four and five is
the training and the back propagation
that we haven't talked about. Everything
else is actually just forward
propagation through our network and
collecting information. So how do we do
this? Let's actually walk through this
part and you know there's two parts to
any training. There's the loss function
and then it's how you back propagate
after this. So we have to understand
what is our loss for this type of you
know step four and five that we see
here.
So the loss consists of two terms,
right? Number one is going to be the log
likelihood, right, of selecting an
action based on what was currently
chosen. And then second, we're going to
multiply this by our
discounted return R. Okay, so let's
let's pause on this a little bit and
let's step through it step by step,
right? So first of all, this is the
first part. This is the log likelihood
of seeing that action of selecting the
action that was selected. And then part
two is the reward, the return, right?
Let's assume that we got a lot of reward
for an action that had high likelihood.
Okay, this loss would be very large
because you multiply two large numbers
together and you would negate it. Note
the negative sign in the beginning which
would mean that you have a very negative
loss in the end. It's a very desirable
state, right? You did a high likelihood
action for something that returned a lot
of reward. So you want to keep doing
that. That was really good. Let's take
the opposite case. Let's say that you
had, you know, a reward that was very
low for an action that was very high
probability. So, you took an action that
looked really confident to you, but it
it resulted in a really bad reward. You
multiply those two numbers together,
you're going to have a much smaller
number. You negate it, it's going to be
a bigger number. Okay? When you plug all
of this together, you get this loss
function that now you can back propagate
through, right? You plug those two
numbers in, you compute that loss, and
you can back propagate to update your
network in order to find, you know, and
to update the likelihoods because
ultimately, let's say in that case where
you had a high likelihood action that
resulted in a bad reward. The next time
you run that network, you don't want the
the likelihood to be high anymore. The
next time you run it, you want the back
propagation signal to say, okay, I
wanted to lower this because now the
loss told me that I should be penalized.
So when I back propagate, I'm going to
update all my weights. So the likelihood
on the next time is going to be much
smaller. And that's exactly what what we
do. And if you actually plug this in,
you get this this equation which looks
like this. Uh this is a gradient descent
equation. Hopefully it's familiar to
everyone. But the key point here is this
policy uh gradient, right? So the reason
why this algorithm is called policy
gradients is because you're computing
the gradient over your policy uh which
is this likelihood function. Right? This
is just where the name comes from. Now I
want to go back to this this uh you know
algorithm the pseudo code for this
algorithm and talk about this a little
bit not in this toy world synthetic
world that we saw in the you know the 2D
driving example but what if we wanted to
do RL in the real world right how would
this story change what would we need to
consider how would we have to deal with
some of the shortcomings here so I want
to actually open this as a question
right what does everybody in the
audience think is
the is the limitation, right? Which step
which step here is going to be the
problem if we wanted to do exactly the
same process that we saw in the 2D
driving world. If we want to do that in
real driving, right? Which step of the
five steps here is going to be the one
that really is not so good. There are
many more states than what you will see.
You're not going to see all the states.
Yes, true. But depending on your
simulator, it could also be true, right?
You could have a very, you know, big
simulator with a bunch of states as
well. And they could also have a a wide
action space. What else? Yep.
Exactly. Exactly. So yeah, step two.
Yeah, this is the this is the problem
because termination is as the name
implies it's not a good you don't want
to run a policy until termination
because in the real world this is uh you
know like basically you don't want to
you don't want to reach termination in
the real world uh you can do this in
simulation it's not a problem but in the
real world basically the in order to do
everything that we talked about so far
we need to run until termination so this
is not going to work out so well now of
course people have tried to solve this
by really advancing photo realism and
and simulation to the point where you
know termination is is safe. You know
you don't need to run to termination and
and deal with consequences in the real
world. So actually one really cool
result that we created here at MIT was
you know this uh the lab that actually
uh I'm part of just upstairs uh we do a
lot of work with autonomy and robotics
and we created this extremely
photorealistic simulator. This was now a
few years ago but you can see actually
images from this simulation engine. Uh
these are uh images or excuse me videos
of an autonomous vehicle running the
same reinforcement learning policy that
you just saw on the previous slide
through the simulator with extremely
photorealistic scenes uh and and
actually training end to end entirely in
simulation in a way that we can then
deploy this model directly into reality
as well. And we did that actually. So
this was the the model that's just
located one layer uh one level below
where you're sitting today in the garage
of this building. We have a car that we
took to our test track, trained it in
exactly the same way with the algorithms
that you learned about in today's class
and then deployed it in in real world uh
roads, right? Directly from simulation
using the same algorithms uh but done in
a very safe way because it's all with
photo realism, right? and able to
directly translate into into
reality. So now I I think we've we've
covered a really strong foundation of
you know both Q-learning as well as
policy learning so that you can
understand you know given you know
actions and environments or agents and
environments how we can optimize our
agents to perform actions in those
environments. But I think you know one
really exciting thing that you know when
I was learning about all of these
algorithms was was really intriguing to
me was trying to understand how we could
translate similar to the autonomy and
the robotic situations how we could
translate a lot of these from you know
not just the the toy cases that a lot of
reinforcement learning literature has
covered for many decades into some of
the real world use cases. So one of the
big advances and the breakthroughs of
reinforcement learning came uh several
years ago with the game of Go, right? So
reinforcement learning agents were put
to the test on this game because Go is a
game with uh you know extremely large
action spaces and very complex
behaviors. At the time you know these
reinforcement learning agents were put
to the test against human grand masters
and you know that brought a lot of
really exciting results. The game of Go
is really interesting and maybe I'll
just give a quick background very quick
to the game. So this is a 19 by19 grid.
It's a two-dimensional game and you can
either hold white pieces or black
pieces. The thing that's special about
Go is that
uh well okay what do you want to do? You
want to just occupy more of the board
than your opponent. So you want to take
up more board pieces than your opponent.
Though the grid and the game are
actually relatively simple. This is a
two-dimensional world, two players,
black or white. Uh, sounds actually
really simple, but the thing is that
because of the 19 by19, there's a
explosion of possible actions that you
can take. And even more than that, it's
the explosion of possible steps of
actions that you can take if you go out
a few steps into the future. So in fact
in the full-size game of go there are a
greater number of legal board positions
than you know atoms in the entire
universe right so the objective here is
to train an AI that can not just
interpret those board positions but
given a board position find an optimal
policy what's a probability of every
action being the optimal action that it
could take in order to beat those
current world or current or past world
champions of uh of the game right So how
did how did uh Google deep mind solve
this? So they developed actually a very
similar pipeline to the ones that you
learned about today. uh it still is you
know not that different actually is it's
very hard to beat these algorithms is
basically the idea starting from the
left hand side is going to be first you
know train this neural network that
watches human go players and learns
given a board state an optimal action
for that board state just predict the
next state right this is not
reinforcement learning this is
supervised learning so given examples of
state one and the next state that a
human would take predict the next state
supervised learning
only but then use that network as a
beginning network to train your
reinforcement learning network. So now
you should have kind of a you know kind
of a early version of a beginning Go
player just by watching a lot of these
go uh you know games that have occurred.
You can learn some of the dynamics, some
of the behaviors that are happening and
you can, you know, predict the next
state in some way, but then use
reinforcement learning to play against
itself and get rewards based on when it
wins and when it doesn't win. So, it can
actually continuously improve. Not just
be limited based on what the human games
were being shown, but actually extract
more meaningful feedback and more
meaningful signal through its own
reinforcement and its own reward
signals. Now one of the thick one of the
tricks that really brought this idea to
the next level was this third layer
right was the ability to say okay let's
not just do the learning with ourself
right playing against ourselves and
trying to extract that uh reward but
actually try to at every stage evaluate
what the value or what the what the
score at that point in the board was
because you can imagine go like chess
for example is a game where the signal
is not seen until the very end, right?
And if you only have one signal at the
very very end of the game, you then it's
very hard to say, okay, did this one
move that I make much earlier in the
game, was that the move that caused me
to lose this game or win this game? So
that the signal, this is another way to
say the signal is very sparse. You only
have one signal and it has to sply
travel all the way back through time.
And the challenge here is that you don't
only want this sparse signal. The trick
that was employed here is saying okay
can I create a value for every possible
board state that could have. So as I see
board states can I can I evaluate how
good of a state that was at this time
already at this time and having a good
measure and actually human players do
this in chess for example they can look
at a board without seeing any past or
any future moves and they can say this
is a good state this is a bad state like
which side would I rather be on if I
just look at this board and I can pick
up this board would I rather be black or
white and that's basically this question
here and you can plug in all of these
pieces together to basically say Okay,
I'm going to train this end to end and
self optimize this reward model. Now,
the one limitation actually the one
thing people really didn't like was that
first stage where you had to show it to
human games first, right? Because this
actually seems very unnecessary. You
shouldn't have to do this and in fact
you don't have to do this. So you could
start and this is what was later shown
is that you could start from scratch
selfplay from scratch using both
reinforcement learning from playing
against yourself with the AI against the
AI and having this value understanding
of every board state in the game to not
even pre-train these systems based on
the human
feedback. Okay, I will summarize all of
this very briefly. So we covered a lot
in today's lecture. We covered a lot of
the foundations, a lot of the
terminology and the background to
reinforcement learning. We brought that
up and we basically covered two
different sides of reinforcement
learning. Both the uh Q-learning side as
well as the policy learning side. And
then we transition to cover some of the
applications of how these systems are
used, you know, in in a variety of
different both autonomy applications but
also gameplay applications. There's a
ton of different areas that people are
covering here.
That's it for the reinforcement learning
part. We will transition to Ava's
lecture for the day. And maybe just
while we while we do the transition,
I'll highlight that, you know, tomorrow
we're doing t-shirts and guest lectures.
I'll keep this up on on the on the
screen while we do the transition just
for some information. Uh but but yeah,
please uh please come back tomorrow
because I think tomorrow's lectures are
going to be some of the you know the
newest content that we're showing today
and it's going to be brought by you know
some of our leading industry speakers.
So uh really looking forward to
tomorrow's lecture and also giving you
guys some some course swag as well.
Okay, thank you.