um okay welcome everyone um to week four
we're into now um so for today what I
want to do is first of all um well a
couple more bits on machine translation
especially just talking a little bit
about evaluating machine translation
then I want to spend a while on
attention so attention is a very um fun
mental concept and of newal networks
which was originally developed in the
context of machine translation there
also then a very um Central concept when
we're talking about Transformers which
we then start talking about on
Thursday okay so um getting straight
into it um so this is the picture that
we saw towards the end of last time that
this is how we were baking uh machine
translation system where we are using um
a multi-layer lstm where we're feeding
in a source sent sentence and then we
were flipping um to um then turning the
model into a decoder with different
parameters which would generate one word
at a time to generate the translated
sentence um so um here I've got an
German sentence and it's produced an
English translation that looks a pretty
good one and but you know we're going to
want to have a way of deciding well are
we um producing good translations or not
um and so we need some way to evaluate
machine translation now this is a
complex area because you know if you
start poking around in the literature um
people have proposed literally hundreds
of different measures that could be used
to evaluate machine translation systems
I'm of writing a couple of papers on it
myself so I'm contributed to the problem
um but you know by far the most commonly
common measure that you see to this day
was essentially the first measure
proposed to automatically evaluate
machine translation which was the blue
measure um which was um proposed to
understand for bilingual evaluation
underst study though it went along with
the fact that was proposed by IBM
probably not coincidence um so until
this point um the only way that people
had really used for evaluating
translations was getting human beings to
look at them and say how good of a
translation this is and you know that's
still a gold standard measure that is
widely used um for evaluating
translations because you know many of
the automatic measures have various
kinds of um biases and problems that
make human evaluation
useful but on the other hand um a lot of
the time we'd like to you know iterate
quickly on evaluations we'd like to use
evaluations and training loops and
things like that and I the IBM people
with the blue paper suggests well maybe
we can come up with a halfway decent
automatic method of um doing
translations and the idea of what they
proposed was this that we're going to
have one or more reference translations
for a piece of text so these are human
written translations and then we can
score any automatic translation mainly
on how often they have overlapping one 2
three and four grams uh the number four
isn't special you could have only gone
up to three or five but four we seen as
a reasonable length um overlapping um n
gs with one of the reference
translations and the more overlap you
have the better um and we we this
discussion of this evaluation in the
assignment so you can think about it a
bit more and I won't go actually through
all the formulas right now um but you
know that's most of it um and so here's
um a picture of how that looks so the
original idea was what we should do is
you know have several reference
translations and then we'd get a machine
translation and then we'd look at this
machine translation and try and find
pieces of it in the reference
translation so we can certainly find the
unigram the um we can't find American at
all but we can find International
Airport and its in the second reference
translation so we're going to get a 4 g
match for that um we can find that again
that's easy office all receives one call
Self the sand Arab I'm not of very good
translation this right so that all
misses but then you start to find other
pieces um that do overlap and you use
those to work out a score um the
original idea was you should always have
multiple reference translations so that
you can sample the space of possible
translations and have reasonable
coverage in practice for what's been
done more recently it's not so uncommon
that people do this with one reference
translation and the argument then is
still on a kind of a probabilistic basis
the more often you have a good
translation the more often you'll get
matches and therefore your score will be
better yeah so um
why you know why did people come up with
this and why is it still imperfect well
the problem with translation is that
there isn't one right answer it's not
like the kind of classification things
you see in machine learning where you
show people a picture and the right
answer is to say this the class of this
object um is whatever labut or right dog
breeds or something right that for any
sentence there are many different ways
to translate it and you know translators
can sit around and argue that oh this
phrasing is a little bit nicer than this
phrasing blah blah blah but to a first
approximation you can translate sentence
in lots of ways um and those different
ways of translation can involve
different word orders so you can't
really sort of check the words off as
you come down in the sentence and that's
what motivated this idea of sort of
matching engrams anywhere so you can get
reasonable credit um for having the
right matches but you know nevertheless
it's a pretty crude version of it right
um you know you can still get a poor
blue score for good translation just
because the words you chose didn't
happen to match a reference translation
and also you can get points for things
without really having a good translation
at all right if you just have words that
match even if they're having completely
the wrong role in the sentence you will
get some points but it's harder to get
engram matches unless you're um for
larger n unless you're using words the
right way um there's one other tricken
the blue measure that there's a penalty
for two short system translations CU
otherwise you could leave out everything
difficult and only translate the easy
part of the sentence and then for the
bits you have translated um you could
then be getting a high score for the
Precision of those
pieces okay so we'll use when you're
developing your Mt systems for
assignment three um we'll use them with
blue um so so um now we have a
evaluation measure um we can um start
looking at how well
um how well do systems do on a blue
score and blue scores are theoretically
between zero and 100 but you're never
going to get to 100 because of the
variations of how you can translate
things um and so typically if you can
start to get to the 20s uh translations
uh you can sort of understand what the
source document was about um once you
get into the 30s and 40s the
translations are getting much much
better
um yeah so um statistical phrase-based
translation was pioneered um by IBM in
the late 90s actually and was sort of
redeveloped in the 2000's decade and was
what Google launched as Google Translate
in the 2000th decade and it continued to
be worked on for sort of the following
decade but there was basically a strong
sense um that progress in Translation
had doing statistical phrase based
systems had basically stalled that it
got a little bit better each year as
people could build traditional Ingram
language models with more data every
year and things like that but the
numbers were barely going upwards um so
in the years from about 2005
to 15 or maybe 14 the dominant idea in
the machine translation Community was
the way we were going to get um better
machine translation is doing
syntax-based machine translation if we
actually knew the structure of sentences
and we'd pass them up then we'd know
what the role of words was in sentences
and then we'd be able to translate much
better and this was particularly invoked
by looking at languages where trans
worked terribly so in those days
translation worked sort of okay for
languages like French to English um or
Spanish to English which are kind of
sort of similar European languages um
but the results worked way worse for
Chinese to English or German to English
and even though English is a Germanic
language German has a very different
word order um to English with commonly
verbs at the end of a clause and
different elements being fronted and so
there was it wasn't so people tried to
work on um um grammar-based syntax based
methods of statistical machine
translation and I was one of those who
worked on those in the late 2000s decade
but you know the truth is it sort of
didn't really work right if the rate of
progress in um syntax-based
um machine translation was had slightly
more slope um than phrase based machine
translation over these years the amount
of slope um wasn't very much so things
were completely then thrown on their
head um when neural machine translation
got invented because as I explained you
know the first attempts were in
2014 the first cases in which it was
evaluated and boff evaluations was
2015 and so in 2015 it wasn't as good as
the best other machine translation
methods but by 2016 it was and it was
just on this much much steeper slope of
getting way way better and that this
graph only goes up to
2019 um but it's continued to go up and
so it's not that uncommon these days
that you see blue numbers in the 50s and
60s um for new or machine translation
systems so that's a good news story um
so after this I want to go on and sort
of introduced this um idea of attention
um which is now a very fundamental
important idea in neural systems it's
also interesting because it's actually
something novel that was invented kind
of recently so for everything that we've
done in new networks up until now really
it had all been invented before the turn
of the Millennium right so um basic feed
Ford neural networks recurrent neural
networks
lstms other things that we haven't yet
haven't talked about like convolutional
newal networks they were all invented
last Millennium it was really a waiting
game at that point until there was
sufficient data and computational power
for them really to show that how good
they were um but attention was something
that actually got invented in 2014 in
the origins of neural machine
translation and it proved to be a very
transformative idea for making neural
networks more powerful um so the idea of
what motivated attention was looking at
exactly this kind of machine translation
problem so we're running our lstm over
the source sentence and then we were
using this hidden State as the previous
hidden state that we're feeding into the
generator lstm for the T Target sentence
and what that means is everything useful
about this sentence has to be stuffed
into that one vector and well that's
maybe not so hard if you've got a
four-word sentence but you know maybe
you've got a 40w sentence out here and
it seems to be kind of implausible that
it' be a good idea to be trying to fit
everything about that sentence into this
one hidden State and well obviously
there are crude solutions to this you
make the hidden state bigger and then
you've got more representational space
you use a multi-layer lstm you've got
more representational space but it still
seems a very questionable thing to do
and it's certainly not like what a human
being does right like if a human being
is translating a sentence they read the
sentence and they've got some idea of
its meaning but as they start to
translate they look back at the earlier
parts of the sentence and make use of
that in their translation and so that
doesn't seem like it's a very plausible
model so the idea should be that our new
network should be able to attend to
different things in the source um so
that they can get information as needed
looking back in the sentence and so this
is the idea of attention so on each step
of the decoder we're going to insert
direct connections to the encoder so we
can look at particular words in the
sentence um so I've got a bunch of
diagram sentences that go through what
we do and then after that I'll present
the equations that go along with this
okay so once we're starting to translate
um we've got a hidden State at the start
of our generator and then we're going to
use this hidden State as our key to look
back into the encoder to try and find
useful stuff
so we're going to compare in a way I'll
make precise later the hidden state with
the hidden State at every position um in
the source
sentence and based on our comparisons
we're going to work out an attention
score where where should we be looking
at in the source sentence while
generating the here the first word of
the translation
and So based on these attention scores
we'll stick them into a soft Max as we
commonly do and we'll then get a
probability distribution or a waiting
over the different positions in the
sentence and then we will use this
waiting to compute a representation
based on the
encoder um which is then going to be a
weighted average of the encoder St dates
so in this particular case it'll be
nearly entirely the representation above
the first word eel which means he in
French um so then we'll take that
attention
output um and we'll combine it um with
the hidden state of our decoder and
we'll use both of them together to
generate an output Vector which we stick
through our soft Max and generate a word
as the first word of the translation y
one and so then at that point we just
repeat this over
um so we then go on to generating the
second word um well you know we copy
down the first word generator start to
generate the second word we work out
attention at every position um it gives
us um an oh sorry there's a little note
there which little fine point which
maybe I won't deal with but it points
out sometimes you um also do things like
stick the previous time steps attention
output into the next step as an extra
input and we actually do that in it
should say assignment three there that's
buggy um so there are other ways to use
things but I'll sort of gloss over that
um
so um we generate another word and we
sort of repeat over and at each time
step we're looking at different words in
the source and they will help us to
translate the
sentence
yeah wait wait say again why is it bring
bring point the green okay the so the
the green Vector the hidden Vector of
the coder is going to be used together
with the hidden States the hidden
vectors of the encoder one at a time to
calculate the attention scores so the
attention score at a position is going
to be a function of the Hidden state of
the encoder at that position and the
current hidden state of the
decoder and I'll explain exactly how in
a moment thank you any other
questions okay um well so here it is in
math okay so we have um encod of hidden
states which we're going to call
H um so we have decoder hidden states
which we're going to call S so there're
something different um and we're going
to at each point being some particular
time step T so we'll be dealing with
st um so to calculate the attention
scores um for
generating uh then word for time step T
we're going to calculate an attention
score for each position in the
encoder okay um I'll discuss
alternatives for this in a moment but
the very easiest way to calculate an
attention score which is shown here is
to take a DOT product between the hidden
state of the
encoder and the current hidden state of
the decoder and so that's what we're
showing here so that will give us some
dot product score which is just any
number at
all um then the next thing we do is we
stick those ET scores into our softmax
distribution and that gives us our
probability distribution as to how much
weight to put on each position in the
encoder and so then we are calculating
the weighted average of the encoder
hidden States um which we're just doing
with the obvious equation that we're
taking the weighted sum of the Hidden
states of the encoder based on the
attention weights and then what we want
to do is concatenate our our our tension
output and the hidden state of the
decoder and we're going to which is
giving us then a double length vector
and then we're going to feed that into
um producing the next word from the
decoder so typically that means we're
multiplying that vector by another
Matrix and then putting it through a
soft Max um to get a probability
distribution over um words to output and
choosing the highest probability
word okay um that make sense I hope yeah
um okay so attention is great so
inventing this idea was completely
transformative um so the very first
modern neural machine translation system
was done at Google in
2014 and they used a pure but very large
very deep
um lstm so was an eight layer deep lstm
with a very large Hidden State for the
time um and they were able to get good
results um but very shortly thereafter
um people at the University of Montreal
dimma bad now K huno and Yoshua Benjo um
did a second version of machine
translation um using attention and with
a much more modest compute budget of the
kind that you can afford in universities
um they were able to get better results
because attention was their secret um
thing so attention significantly
improved nmt performance and essentially
every new machine
translation um System since has used
attention like we've just seen um you
know it's more human like as I was
indicating because it's sort of what a
human would do you'd look back in the
sentence to see what you need to
translate um and it solves this
bottleneck problem you now no longer
have to stuff all the information about
the source sentence into one hidden
State you can have the whole of your
representational space from your entire
encoding and use it as you need it um it
also helps with the vanishing gradient
problem this is connected to what I was
saying NE last time when talking about
res ual connection so of a way out of
the banishing gradient problem is to
direct connect things and this provides
shortcut connections to all of the
Hidden states of the
encoder and another nice thing that
attention does is it gives you some
interpretability so by looking at where
the model is um attending you can
basically see what it's translating at
different time steps and so that can be
um really useful
and so it's kind of like we can see what
We're translating where without
explicitly having trained A system that
does that so for my little toy sentence
here if he hit me with a pie you know at
the first position um it's you know it
was looking at the first word eel he
which it translates um then there's in
French this there's this sort of verb on
T to sort of pie somebody I guess in
English as well you can use pie as a
verb right so so um the a is a is a sort
of perfect past um exiler so sort of
like he has me pied is what the French
words are one at a time and so the hit
is already looking at the pi then the me
is attending to the m which means me and
then all the with with the piie is
attending still to Anar which is
basically the right kind of alignment
that you want for words of a sentence so
that's pretty cool um
too okay um so I presented up until this
point um just this
um said oh we could do a DOT product but
you know in general there's more to it
than that so what we have is we have
some values H1 to hn and we have a query
vector and we want to work out how to do
a tension based on these things so
attention always involves Computing some
attention scores and taking the soft Max
to get an attention distribution and
then getting an attention output but the
part where there's variation is how do
you compute these attention scores and a
number of different ways have been done
for that and I just want to go through
that a little bit um so the simplest way
that I just presented is this dot
product attention we just take the
hidden States and Dot product the whole
of them um
and that sort of works um but it doesn't
actually work great and I sort of
discussed this a bit when talking about
lstms last time right that you know the
the hidden state of an lstm is its
complete memory right so it has to
variously store lots of things in that
memory it's got to be storing
information that'll help it output the
right word it has to be storing
information about the future about other
things that you'll want to say given the
kind of sentence context grammar and
previous words you've said right you
sort of got all kinds of memory and so
it sort of makes sense that some of it
would be useful for linking up for
looking back and some of it would be
less useful you sort of want to find the
parts that are related to what you want
to say immediately not all the parts
that um do all of the rest of the
future um so that suggested um maybe you
could do a more general form of um
attention and so tanglong and me in 201
2015 suggested maybe we could introduce
um what we called by linear attention
which um I still think is a better name
but the rest of the world came to call
multiplicative attention um where what
we're doing is between these two vectors
um we're sticking a matrix um and so
we're then learning the parameters of
this Matrix just like everything else in
our neural network and so effectively
this Matrix can
learn which parts of the um generator
hidden State you should be looking to
find where in the hidden states of the
encoder in particular it no longer
requires that things have to match up
Dimension by Dimension you know it could
be the case that the encoder is storing
information about word meaning here and
the and the decoder is storing
by learning appropriate parameters in
this Matrix
um we can sort of match those together
and work out the right place to pay
attention so that seemed
um kind of a cool approach to us um yeah
why don't go all in with Even build like
a neural network that's GNA H input and
output um you can do that I was going to
get to that on the next slide um
actually that's in a way sort of going
backwards but I I will get to it on the
next slide but before I do that um I
will
uh um show you um these other versions
so the the dis the one thing you might
wonder about um doing it this way is you
know there's a lot of parameters that
you have to learn in The Matrix W you
know there aren't that many in my
example because they're only 36 but
that's because my hidden states are only
of length six right and if your hidden
states are of length a thousand say then
you've got a million parameters in that
um W Matrix and that seems like it might
be kind of problematic and so the way to
get beyond that which was fairly quickly
suggested thereafter is well maybe
rather than having that whole big Matrix
in the middle instead what we could do
is form it as a low rank Matrix and the
easy way to make a low rank Matrix is
you take two skinny matrices like this
where this is the rank of these of the
pieces and multiply them together which
would give us the big Matrix that I
showed on the last slide and so this
gives you a low parameter um version of
um the um bilinear attention Matrix from
the last slide but at that point if you
just do a teeny bit of linear algebra
this computation
is exactly the same as saying well what
I'm going to do is I'm going to take
each of these two vectors and project
them to a lower dimensional space using
this low rank transformation matrix and
then I'm going to take the dot product
in this low dimensional space
um and uh on Thursday when you get to
Transformers um what you will see that
Transformers do is this that they're
taking um the big vector and they're
projecting it to a low dimensional space
and then taking dot product um attention
in that low dimensional
space okay um back to the question um
yeah you're totally right and you know
at this point I'm going um sort of you
know in an ahistorical manner because
yeah actually the first form of
attention that was proposed in the B
hour Al paper um was hey um let's just
stick a little new net there to
calculate attention scores so um we take
the the S and the H we multiply them
both by a matrix add them put them
through a tan H multiply that by a
vector um and we get a number you know
this looks just like the kind of comput
ations we've use everywhere else in an
lstm so there's a little neural net
that's calculating the attention scores
and then they go into a softmax as
useful usual um in most of the
literature this is called additive
attention which also seems to be a
really weird name I mean I think kind of
saying you've got a little new net um
makes more sense um for that one
um so but anyway so this is what they
proposed and used um and and you know at
this point it's a little bit um complex
to be honest I mean you know
um so like when we wrote our paper the
next year we had found that the um
bilinear attention worked better for us
um but there was subsequent work
especially this massive exploration of
new machine translation architectures
that argued that actually um with the
right kinds of
uh good hyperparameter optimization
actually this is the best kind this is
better than the bilinear tension but you
know this is a lot more complex and a
lot slower um than doing what you're
doing in the upper part of the chart so
regardless of whether it's better or not
in practice what's completely one is
doing this and this is what Transformers
use and just about all other new Nets
that are used these
days okay um questions on attention will
be found in assignment three um yeah so
um I won't say much more about this now
and you know we'll see more of it just
next lecture um but attention is a very
general technique right it was a great
way to improve machine translation and
that was how it was first invented but
you know for all kinds of new
architectures for all kinds of purposes
you can stick attention to into them and
the general finding was that always
improved results so in general anywhere
where you have a a vector of values a
vector query and you can use attention
to then sort of get a weighted average
of the values which finds relevant
information that you can use to improve
your
performance um and so maybe maybe I
won't try and even give examples of that
now um but you'll sort of see another
example of attention immediately when we
do things on T on Thursday where um we
then sort of start doing self attention
inside transformers yes in the you also
try
nonlinearity um no we did
not ah
I mean it didn't seem especially
necessary I don't know but no we did not
okay um well this is the end of um the
part with attention are there any other
questions yes um for the RNN attention
stuff is there a need for positional
information or is that not required to
solve the for positional
information um
so so there was none and it seemed like
it wasn't very required I mean you
could yeah I mean you could make some
inform you could make some argument that
maybe position information um might have
been useful but there's also a good
argument that it wasn't necess Neary and
the sort of
recent everywhere usage of positional
information only becomes necessary when
you get to a Transformer and the reason
for that is you know going back to the
pictures
um for these encoder States they're
being calculated with respect to the
previous encoded estate right because
it's a current newal Network and
therefore the representation here knows
something about the past so it kind of
knows what position it's in basically
and so that you know that's giving a lot
of that information or another way to
think about it is this final
representation will give a certain
overall sense of the semantics of the
sentence and so to the extent that
you're looking backwards the more sort
of associative matching of similar
semantic content that's needed seems
sufficient you don't really need
additional positional
information okay I will go on okay um so
that's the um that's the new Network's
content for today um and so for the
remaining 39 minutes um I want to talk
final projects but also a bit about um
data experiments and things like that
okay so this is a reminder on the class
so um we've got the four assignments
which are
48% and then the big other part of what
you need to do um is the final project
which is
49% almost completing things out except
for the
participation um and um let me just give
one note back to um collaboration the
honor code I mean for final projects
it's quite use usual that people use all
sorts of stuff that were written by
other people that's completely fine we
don't expect you to implement everything
from scratch um but you must document
what you're using you know give
references or URLs if you're using other
people's code rather than writing your
own we do not want to know what code you
wrote yourself and what things you
downloaded from pie um and in particular
in thinking about final projects um the
question of interest for us is what
value add did you provide right so you
haven't done something great if you've
downloaded a really good neural network
and run it on some data and it produces
really good results that's not much
value ad um so if you want to have value
ad in that context you at least want to
be doing something interesting about
understanding um why it works so well
what kind of examples it doesn't work
well on doing some thorough experimental
analysis
um yeah a couple of other points there
um okay so for the final project um for
this class um there's a binary um choice
you can either do our default final
project which I'll talk about more a bit
later or you can come up with your own
final project and I'll talk about that a
bit too um so um we allow team size of 1
to three um the complicated thing that
comes up
um oh actually sorry I should say the
other point first um yeah so if you do
um we we generally encourage people to
form teams it means that you can do
something more interesting it's more
motivational you can make friends
whatever um so teams are good um on
expectations for teams um our expect for
teams is that a bigger team should be
able to do proportionately more work now
and so when we're grading things we
expect to see more work from larger
teams um now how this works out is kind
of I will admit a little bit complicated
because you know there's sort of a
quality issue that's separate from the
amount of work um so you know the
reality is that it's just always the
case that several of the very best
projects are one person efforts because
they're just somebody who has a good
idea and knows what they want to do and
does it by themselves and it is great um
but you know they're also great
multi-person projects as well but um the
point I'm meaning is well if you know it
kind of doesn't work if you're a
oneperson project and you try and
attempt a huge amount of stuff and you
can only get onethird of the way through
it um that's not a good recipe for doing
well in the final project um for any
project um you really need to sort of be
completing something and showing
something but you know nevertheless if
you're one person and you can show
something kind of interesting even if
our reaction is oh well this would have
been much better if they' shown it was
better than this other kind of model or
it would have been really nice if they'
run ablations to work things out well if
you're one person will give you a buy
and say oh but it was only one person um
whereas if you're a three-person team
and it seems like you obviously should
have compared it to some other models
and you obviously could have run it on
some other data sets um then we'll feel
like well as a three-person team um they
obviously should have done that and
therefore we should give them um a less
good score and that's how that is a
worked out um the complication comes um
with other things people are doing at
the same time we allow people to do
final projects um that are shared with
multiple classes um but you know
expectation is again that you'll do more
work so if there are two of you who are
using one project for both this class
and cs231 and say then it's sort of like
it's a four-person project and you
should be doing a lot of work for it um
there are other cases sometimes people
have ra ships or their PHD rotation
students or other things if you're doing
it for other things we'd like you to
tell us and we expect you to be um doing
um more work for it
um okay um I'm very happy to talk to
people about final projects and have
been talking to people about final
projects but unfortunately there's only
one of me so I definitely can't talk to
500 people about final projects so I do
also encourage you to um talk to all of
the Tas about final projects so on the
um office hours page under all of the
Tas there's some information about
things that they know about um so if you
know what your projects is about you
could at least try and find one of the
most useful Tas or just find a TA with a
friendly face um whatever mechanism you
use talk to Tas about um final
projects yeah so default final project
so what it's going to be um is so Bert
was a famous early um Transformer and
we're going to be sort of building and
experimenting with a minimal bir
implementation so if you do this um
there's part of a a part of an
implementation of bird and you're meant
to finish it off and you're meant to
fine-tune it and get some data results
um for doing sentiment analysis and then
basically um we want the even the
default final project to be an
open-ended project where people can do
different things and so then there's
lots of other ideas or you can come up
with your own of ways you could extend
um this system and make it better which
might be with paraphrasing contrast of
learning low rank adaptation something
and you can do something and that is
your final project
um so why choose the final project so if
you haven't had much experience with
research um you don't have any real idea
of what you want to do for a final
project um or you'd like something with
clear guidance and a goal and a
leaderboard because we provide a
leaderboard for people doing the default
final project of how good your
performance is on the tasks we provide
then you can do the final project and I
mean honestly I think for many people
the best option um is to do the final
project um for sort of past performance
typically about half the students do the
final project including some Pro people
who um start off thinking I'll do a
custom final project then after a couple
of weeks they decide H this makes no
sense what I was suggesting it's not
working at all I'm just going to abandon
and flip to the default final project um
okay but we also allow custom final
projects and there are good reasons to
do custom final projects so if you have
some um topic or research idea that
you're excited about maybe you're
already even working on it or you want
to try something different on your own
um or You' just like to have more of the
experience of trying to come up with a
research goal finding the necessary data
and tools and starting from scratch
which is actually very educational if
considerably harder um well then the
custom final project um is fine for you
um restriction on topics I think we'd
already sort of signal this on AED um we
insist for um cs224n final projects that
they have to substantively involve both
human language and new networks you know
because this is the NLP class um so we'd
like people to know and learn something
about human language um I'm totally
aware of the fact that you can use these
same models for bioinformatic
sequences um or music or um uh radar
whatever but we'd like you to do
something with human language for this
class um that doesn't mean it has to be
only about human language so people have
done things like visual language models
um or music and language um so it can
have a combination of modalities um but
it has to you know substantively not
completely trivially involve human
language if You' got any questions about
that ask and it also has to
substantively involve neural networks
though again it doesn't have to be holy
about neural networks if you've got some
ideas thinking oh I think I could show
using kernel machines that they work
just as well as having multiannual
networks or something like that that's
of course fine to do as
well um
gamesmanship um yeah the default final
project is more guided but it's not
meant to be a complete Slackers ride
we're um hoping that people do the same
amount of work for either kind of
project but on the other hand it does
kind of give you sort of a clearer focus
and course of things to do but it is
still an open-ended project um so you
know for both um default final projects
and custom final projects there are
great projects and there are not so
great projects um you know if anything
there's a bit more variance in the
custom final project so you know the
path of success is not to do some try
and do something for a custom final
project um that just looks really weak
compared to people's default final
projects um okay um you can get good
grades either way um we get give best
project Awards um to both kinds of
projects so yeah it's really not that
there's some secret one you have to pick
um Computing um yeah so
um to be honest with the confessions
right at the beginning we're actually in
a less good position um for computing
than we've been in recent years and it's
all open AI fault no that
part um but you know up until and
including last year um we were actually
had invariably managed to get um very
generous um cloud computing giveaways
from one or other cloud computing
provider which really um provided a lot
of um Computing support but you know
there's the great GPU shortage on at the
moment due to the Great success of large
language models and it turns out that um
Cloud compute providers just aren't
being as generous as they used to be and
gee I guess the AWS rep was pointing out
um that my course was their single
largest Grant of free GPU last year so
it's getting harder to do um so um so um
really people will have to um patch
things together more in many cases and
so we'll be relying on the Ingenuity of
students to be able to find free and
cheap stuff um so um Google is giving
$50 credit per person on gcp which can
be used for assignments 34 and the final
project um on all the clouds if you
haven't used a cloud with an account
before you can usually get some free
starter credits um which can be a useful
thing um there are um the sort of jup
notebooks in the cloud so um the most
used one is Google collab um which
allows limited GPU use um it often tends
to get tighter later in the quarter um
so you might find it a good investment
to not have a couple of lattes and pay
10 bucks a month to get collab Pro which
gives you much better access to G um
gpus um but there are alternatives to
that which you might also want to look
at so AWS provid provides a Jupiter
notebook environment s maker studio lab
um and you know also owned by Google
kegle separately provides kegle
notebooks um which actually commonly
give you better GPU access than Google
collab provides even though um you know
they're otherwise not as
nice kegle notebooks are sort of just um
Bare Bones Jupiter notebooks whereas
collab has some fancier um UI stuff
grafted on it um so other possibilities
um modal is a low price GPU provider and
allows and a a certain amount of free
GPU usage a month so that could be handy
um there are other lower cost GPU
providers like vast AI which could be of
relevance um and then the other thing
that I'll say more about in a minute is
you know the way things have changed
with large language models there are
lots of projects that you might want to
do where you're not actually building
models at all yourself but you're
wanting to you know do experiments on
large language models or you're wanting
to do in context learning with large
language models um or other things of
that sort um and then what you want is
to have access to large language models
and in particular you probably want to
use have API access so you can automate
things so another thing that we have
been able to get um is through the
generosity of together AI that together
AI is providing $50 of API access to um
large language models which can actually
be a lot um how much of a lot it is
depends on how bigger model you're using
so something you should um think about
is how big a model do you really need to
use to um show something because if you
can run a 7 billion parameter language
model um on together you know you can
put a huge huge number of tokens through
it for 50 bucks whereas if you want to
run a much bigger model um then you know
the number of tokens start you can get
through it goes down by orders of
magnitude um so that's good um and I
mentioned some other ones so we've
already put a whole bunch of documents
um up on Ed that talk about these
different um GPU options so do look at
those okay um jumping ahead so the first
thing you have to do as a project
proposal um so it's one per team so I
guess the first step is to work out who
your team is um and so for the project
proposal part of it is actually giving
us the details of your project but
there's another major part of it which
is writing a review of a key research
paper for your topic so what um for the
default final project we provide some
suggestions so you can find something
else if you've got another idea for how
to extend the project um for your custom
project you're finding your own but what
we want you to do is get some practice
at looking at a research paper
understanding what it's doing
understanding what's convincing what it
didn't consider what it failed to do and
so we want you to write a two-page
summary of a research paper and the goal
is for you to be thinking critically
about this re search paper you know of
what did it do that was exciting versus
what did it claim was exciting but was
really obvious or perhaps even wrong
Etc okay um and then right so then a so
um after that you know we want you to
say what you're planning to do that may
be very straightforward for a default
final project but it's really important
um for a custom final project um and in
particular um you know tell us about you
know the literature you're going to use
if any and the kind of models you're
going to explore but you know it turns
out that when we're unhappy with custom
final projects the two commonest
complaints about um what you tell us
about custom final projects is you don't
make clear what data you're going to use
because we're sort of worried already if
you haven't worked out by the project
proposal deadline what data you can use
for your final project and if you don't
tell us how you're going to evaluate
your system we want to know how you're
going to measure whether you're getting
any success um as a new thing this year
um we'd like you to include an ethical
considerations paragraph outlining
potential ethical challenges of your
work if it were deployed in the real
world and how that might be mitigated
um this is something that now a lot of
conferences are requiring and a lot of
Grants are requiring um so w't give you
a little bit of practice on that by
writing a paragraph of that um how much
there is to talk about various somewhat
on what you're trying to do and whether
it has a lot of ethical problems or
whether it's a fairly straightforward
question answering system but in all
cases you might think about what are the
possible ethical consider ations of this
piece of work okay the whole thing is
maximum four
pages um okay so for the um research
paper summary yeah do think critically
right I mean the
worst the the worst um summaries are
essentially people that just paraphrase
what's in the abstract and introduction
of the paper and we want you to think a
bit harder about this you know what were
the novel contributions of the paper um
is it something that you could use for
different kinds of problems and
different ways or was it really
exploiting a trick of one data set um
are there things that it seemed like
they missed or could have done
differently or you weren't convinced
were done properly um is it similar or
distinctive to other papers that are
dealing with the same topic
does it suggest perhaps something that
you could try that extends beyond the
paper
um okay and for grading these final
project proposals most of the points are
on that paper review and so do pay
attention to it um there are some points
on the project plan but you know really
we're wanting to mainly give you
formative feedback on the project plan
and comments as to how we think it's
realistic or unrealistic um but
nevertheless um we're expecting you to
sort of have an idea have thought
through how you can investigate it
thought through how you can evaluate it
data sets baselines things like that oh
yeah I should emphasize this do have an
appropriate Baseline so for anything
that you're doing you should have
something you can compare it against so
sometimes it's a previous system that
did exactly the same thing but if you're
doing something more novel and
interesting you should be thinking of
some seat of the pants obvious way to do
things and proving that you can do it
better and what that is depends a lot on
what your project is but you know if
you're building some complex new net um
that's going to be used to work out
textural similarity between two pieces
of text well a simple way of working out
textual similarity between two pie
pieces of text is to look up the word
vectors for every word in the text and
average them together and work out um
the dot product between those average
vectors and unless your complex newal
network is significantly better than
that it doesn't seem like it's a very
good system so you should always attempt
to have some baselines um after um the
project proposal we also have a project
Milestone Stuck in the Middle to make
sure everybody um has making some
progress this is just to help make sure
people um do get through things and keep
working on it so we'll have good final
projects um for
most final projects I'll say more about
this in a minute we The crucial thing we
expect for the Milestone is that you
know you've kind of got set up and you
can run something it might just be your
Baseline of looking up the word vectors
but means you've kind of got the data
and the framework and something that you
can run and produce a number from
it um and then there's the final project
um we have people submit their code for
the final projects but final projects
are um
evaluated almost entirely unless there's
some major worries or concerns based on
your project report so make sure you put
time into the project report which is
essentially a research paper like a
conference paper and they can be up to
eight pages and it varies on what you're
doing but you know this is the kind of
picture typically of what um Pap will
look like will'll have an abstract and
introduction it'll talk about other
related work it'll present the model
you're using the data you're using and
your experiments and their results and
have some insightful comments in its
analysis and conclusion at the end
okay um finding research topics um for
custom projects um all kinds of things
you can do you know basic philosophy of
science you're normally either starting
off with here's some problem I want to
make some progress on or here's this
cool idea for a theoretical technique um
or change in something and I want to
show it's better than other ways of
doing it and you're working from that um
we allow different kinds of projects um
you know one common type of project is
you've got some task of interest and
you're going to try and solve it or make
progress on it somehow that you want to
you know get information out of state
department documents um and you're going
to see how well you can do it with
neural NP a second kind is you got some
ideas of doing something different with
newal networks and then you going to see
how well it works um or maybe given
there are large language models these
days you're going to see how using large
language models you can do something
interesting by in context learning or
building a larger language model program
so NE you know nearly all um 224n
projects are in those first three types
where at the end of the day you've got
some kind of system and you've got some
kind of data and you're going to
evaluate it um but that's not a 100%
requirement there are different kinds of
projects you can do and a few people do
so you can do an analysis
interpretability project um you could be
interested in something like how could
these Transformer models possibly
understand what I say to them and give
the right answers to my statements let
me try and look inside the neural
networks and see what they're Computing
how recently there's been a lot of work
on this topic often under um titles like
mechanistic
interpretability um circuit training and
things like that so you can do some kind
of analysis or interpretability project
or you could even just do it um looking
at the behavior of models of some task
so you could take some linguistic task
like
metaphor interpretation and see which
neural networks can interpret them
correctly and which can't or which kinds
of ones they can interpret correctly or
not and do things like that um another
kind is a theoretical um project
occasionally people have done things um
looking at the behavior
of well what's a good example um
somewhere that's in the math so an
example that was actually done a few
years ago and turned into a conference
paper was looking at in the estimation
of word vectors the stability of um the
word vectors that were computed by
different algorithms word Toc versus
glove um and um deriving results with
proofs about the stability um of the um
um vectors that were calculated um so
that's loud but we don't see many of
those um here very quickly um it's sort
of just sort of random things so a lot
of past projects you can find on the
224n web page you can just find
different past year reports um and you
can look at them to get ideas as you
wish um so deep poetry um was a gated
lstm where the idea was as well as sort
a language model that generated success
of words they had extra stuff in it to
make it um rhyme in a um poetry like
pattern that was kind of fun um you can
do a
reimplementation of a paper um that has
been done previously this is actually
kind of an old one but I remember it
well so back in the days before
Transformers um deep minded these kind
of interesting papers on newal chur
machines and differentiable neural
computers um and um but they didn't
release implementations of them um and
so Carol set about writing her own
implementation of a differentiable
neural computer which in a way was a a
little bit crazy um and a few days
before the deadline she still hadn't
gone at working so it could have been a
complete disaster um but she did get it
working before the deadline and got it
to run producing some interesting
results um so that was kind of cool so
it if it's something interesting it
doesn't have to be original it can be
sort of reimplementing something
interesting um okay
um sometimes um papers do get published
later as interesting ones this was a
paper that was sort of again from the
early days and was sort of fairly simple
but you know it was a novel thing that
gave progress so the way we've sort of
presented these rnm you have sort of
word vectors at the bottom and then you
kind of compute the soft Max at the top
but if you think about the sort of
multiplying by the output Matrix and
then putting that into the softmax that
output Matrix is also like a set of word
vectors because you have a column for
each word and then you put it to you get
a score for each output word and then
you're putting a soft Max over that um
and so their idea was well maybe you
could sort of share those two um sets of
vectors and you'd be able to get
improvements from that and you could
um okay maybe I won't talk about that
one um sometimes people have worked on
quantized models that's sort of more of
a um a sort of a general new network
technique but providing you show you can
do useful things with it like have good
language modeling results even with
quantize vectors we'll count that as
using language um so in recent times um
these two last tour from
2024 um you know a lot of the time
people are doing projects with
pre-trained large language models which
we will be talking about in the next
three models three lectures and then
doing things with them and so you can do
lightweight parameter efficient
fine-tuning methods you can do in
context learning methods and things like
this and I suspect that probably quite a
few of you will do projects um of um
this kind so you know here's an example
so lots of work has been done on
producing um code language models
um and so um these people um decided to
improve um the generation of Fortran
maybe they are physicist I don't
know and um so um they were able to show
that they could um use parameter
efficient fine-tuning to improve code
llama for producing for now where was
the natural language um code has natural
language comments in it and the comments
can be useful for explaining what you
want the code to do and so it was
effectively doing um translation from
human language um explanation of what
the code code was meant to do into
pieces of code
um here was another one um which um was
um doing AI fashion driven cataloging um
transforming images into textual
descriptions which again was starting
off with an existing visual language
model and looking at how to fine-tune
it okay um other places to look for
stuff um so you know you can get kind of
lots of ideas of areas and things people
do by looking at past papers they you're
also welcome to have your own original
ideas thinking about anything you know
or work on in the world so for NLP
papers there's a site called the ACL
Anthology that's good for them for there
are lots of papers on language that also
appear in machine learning conferences
so you can look at the neurs or I clear
proceedings you can look at past 2 24n
projects and then um the archive
pre-print servers got tons of papers on
everything including NLP and you can
look there but I do actually think it's
you know some of the funnest best
projects are actually people that find
their own problem which is an
interesting problem in their world you
know if there's anything about a cool
website that has text on it and you
think you could kind of get information
out of automatically by using a language
model or something there's probably
something interesting and different you
can do there um another place to look is
that there are various leaderboards for
the state-ofthe-art on different
problems and you can start looking
through leaderboards for stuff and see
what you find there um but you know on
the other hand the disadvantage of
looking at things like leaderboards and
past conferences is you sort of uh tend
to be trying to do a bit better on a
problem someone else has done and that's
part of um why you know really often in
research it's a clever thing to think of
something different perhaps not too far
from things that other people have done
but somehow different so you'll be able
to do something a bit more original and
different for what you're doing
um yeah I mean I do just want to go
through this a bit quickly um
that you know um for sort of decade that
I've been doing natural language
processing with deep learning there's
sort of been a sea change in what's
possible um so in the early days of the
deep learning um Revival you know most
of the work in people's papers were
trying to find better deep learning
architectures so that would be here is
some question answering system I've got
an idea of how I could add attention in
some new place or I could add a new um
layer into the new network and the the
numbers will go up um and um there were
lots of papers like that and it was a
lot of fun and that's what a lot of good
CS2 224n projects did too and people
were often able to build systems from
scratch that were close to the
state-of-the-art um but you know in the
last five years your chances of doing
this have been become pretty slim
frankly um you know you can if you
really got a good idea and it's
something different than original by all
means but it's kind of hard so most work
these days even for people who are
professional
researchers that you know they're making
use of existing large pre-trained models
in some way and then once you're doing
that that actually sort of fixes a lot
of your architectural choices because
your large pre- chain neural network has
a certain AR architecture and you kind
of have to live with it you know you
might be able to do interesting things
by adapting it with something like low
rank adaptation around the side or
something but nevertheless there's sort
of constraints on what you want to do so
you know for just about any practical
project like you've got some data set
and you want to understand it and get
facts out of it or something like that
essentially the only sensible choice is
to say I am going to use hugging face um
Transformers um which we have a tutorial
on coming up ahead and I will load some
pre-trained model and I will be running
it over the text and then I'll be
working out some other stuff I can do on
a top and around that so you know
building your own architecture is really
only a sensible choice if you can do
something in the small which is more a
sort of exploring architectures project
if you've kind of got an idea of hey
I've got an idea for different
nonlinearity that I think will work
better than using a re let me
investigate kind of thing because then
you can do small
experiments um yeah maybe I won't read
out all of this list but um there are
lists of sort of some of the ideas of
what's more interesting um now um but
you know do be cognizant of the world
we're in in terms of scale I mean one of
the problems we now have is that people
have um seen the latest paper that was
being pushed by Deep Mind or whoever um
doing some cool graph structured um
reasoning search to do things and they
turn up and say I want to um do this for
my project but a lot of the time if you
um read further into the paper you'll
find that they were doing it on 32 A1
100s for a month and that's not the
scale of computer
that you're going to have available to
you in almost any all circumstances
maybe they're one or two industry
students for the industry students that
you can do that if so go for it but for
the vast majority of people not likely
um so you do have to um do something um
that um is practical but you know that
practicality is true for vast majority
of the people in the world and if you
look around in blogs and so on you find
lots of people um doing stuff in
lightweight ways um and describing how
to do that and that's why methods like
parameter efficient fine tuning are
really popular because you can do them
in lightweight ways um the question
related to that and I'll end on this is
you know I just want to sort of
um sort of mention again you know if you
want to you're welcome to use gp4 or
Gemini Pro or Claude Opus or any of
these models in your project um but you
know it has to be then API usage you
can't possibly train your own big models
I mean even for the models that are
available open source and like those you
know for big models you can't even load
them into the kind of gpus you have so
you know probably you can load a llama
7B model but you can't just load into
your G CPU llama 70b model um
so you have to be um realistic on that
size but you know there's actually now
lots of interesting things you can do
with API access doing things like in
context learning and prompting and
exploring that or building larger
language model programs around these
language model components and you're
certainly encouraged to do that um lots
of other things you can do such as
analysis projects which look at are
these models sexist and racist still or
do they have good understanding of
analogies or can they interpret love
letters or whatever is your topic of
Interest lots of things you can do and
that's totally allowed um but again you
know remember that we'll be trying to
evaluate us on what interesting stuff
you did um so your project shouldn't be
I ran this stuff through gp4 and It
produced great summaries of the
documents I am done the question is um
what did you do in addition to that to
have an interesting research project
okay I'll stop there thanks a lot