As you can see on this slide, today
we're going to talk about neural
networks and back
propagation which is actually the
process
early years I was I was studying this. I
was often referring to it as the magical
process that um lets the neural networks
learn from their own mistakes
pretty much like humans but in a more
organized fashion and also uh using a
little bit more math. So let's let's
dive into the topic. I'm I'm sure this
is going to be uh exciting and this is a
found is is laying a foundation for the
rest of the quarter. Every single
algorithm that we'll be discussing in
the future without even mentioning is is
using a form of back propagation and um
so that's why understanding this this
lecture and the topics are
uh is is very important. Okay. in
keeping us with the uh tradition. Let's
cover what we've talked about so far.
So,
I'm sure you now remember uh what we
talked about last time.
We we said how we can form the
objective functions or loss functions
what we call here and then um we talked
about regularization.
But to do that
uh we formulated everything through the
XY
uh defining the pairs and and scoring
function which in this case we are using
a linear scoring function as you can see
and also
uh defining ultimately this this loss
function. So this graph that you see on
the right is what we
uh we drew showing all the process the
entire process of learning. There has
been some questions um
the questions last
last le in the last lecture and also
even before that that why we only using
the soft max function. I wanted to uh
reiterate that it's not the only loss
function that we have and we use it's
it's um it's one of the most widely used
in deep learning and and building
especially for the task of
classification but there are so many
other options that we use for for other
task for different tasks even for the
task of classification
if you've looked at the slides that
we've shared on the website I I included
this hinge loss loss or um used to be
called SVM loss in the reading
assignments on le in lecture two. So in
the slides we had uh examples and and
everything around
the topic of
um hinge loss. It is also one of those
widely used um loss functions especially
in the early years of uh neural
networks. And um just to give you a high
level understanding of what it is uh
this is a loss
function that unlike soft max does not
turn the scores into probabilities. So
turning them into probabilities is not
is not the only option. Right? So we can
uh use other forms. This this function
encourages the score of uh let me
highlight here the score um
of the correct items uh which is defined
by s yi to be higher than the scores of
all other items sj. You can see the the
condition here creating a
value of zero.
if the condition is is true and
otherwise
what it does is um so as as I said it it
encourages the score of the the correct
item uh to be higher than the scores of
all other items um by at least a margin
that number one that you see there is
the margin that it creates and then if
the condition is violated the loss
increases proportionally
um from the margin and this is the
visualization. So creating the
uh this um
visualization of of the function. So
this promotes correct scores by
penalizing cases where irrelevant items
are scored too highly. So again refer to
assignment reading assignment in lecture
two for examples and uh and to get
better understanding of that. Next we
have talked about uh general
optimization how to find the the best
parameters w for
for uh the neural network. And in doing
so, we talked a little bit about this
lost landscape
uh being as a large valley um as as as
shown in this um image. And every point
on that valley is a different set of
weight parameters
and we wanted to find the set of
parameters W that minimizes that loss
landscape.
We talked about the fact that the key is
is being able to take the gradient of
the loss function L with respect to W
and use the gradient for optimization in
a stepbystep
manner which gave us the gradient
descent algorithm. Right? So the weights
are basically updated. Although it's
very hard for me to see from from this
distance what I'm pointing to, but I
guess I
uh I can guess. So um anyways,
in order to walk down the loss landscape
towards the minimum value, a step size
is defined. and we often uh get
take one step
with respect to a step step size in the
negative direction of the uh gradient.
So this was the gradient descent
algorithm and in order to optimize we
talked about uh two different approaches
of numerical gradient and analytical
gradient both of which having pros and
cons and we discussed in practice to
drive analytical gradients.
In practice, we drive analytical
gradients and often if it's if it's hard
to do the implementation and the math
and everything, we check our
implementations with neural numerical
gradients.
And one of the other challenges we
talked about was the use of um um
incorporating the loss function and its
gradient on the entire data set. So if
you have a large data set, it's it's
very expensive to
um to run the loss function and the the
der derivative on the entire data set.
And that's why we talked about the idea
of mini batches using a number of
examples sampled from the data set often
32 um
often maybe uh 3264
uh 128 or 256.
And that subsampled
data is used for
identifying the gradients and then
taking the steps towards the
the minimal.
And beyond SGD and a stochastic um
gradient descent, we talked about some
optimizations of SD SGD with momentum
um RMS prom uh prop and and atom
optimizer.
And um there were a lot of details that
I would refer you to the lecture
um the third lecture if you have um any
specific
uh questions about those. So
and then one of the other things that we
talked about was the importance of the
learning rate and and scheduling the
learning rate. And in some of the
optimizers we often try to start with a
larger value of the learning rate and
then start using different types of um
decaying the learning rate or or
reducing its its value by a factor. Um
this is normally uh needed in many
uh optimizers but but in in some of the
more recent ones uh atom and it's its
variance we often do not need to uh
manually or explicitly decrease that
because they that that is kind of
encoded into the optimizer itself.
So with that I uh want us to get uh to
the topic of neural networks
and and see how we can actually build um
neural networks and and solve more
exciting and and harder problems.
So uh
we've so far talked about this this
function linear function of w multiplied
by x and that is um is is the most basic
neural network that could be defined.
It's just one u layer. We will be
talking about the layers.
And um what I want you to pay attention
to here is are these dimensions D and C
which are the dimensionality of the
input um data input X or or the uh
number of features and C is the number
of classes basically the number of
output uh nodes or or neurons whatever
number of outputs we need.
And um in order to create a neural
network at a second layer, we can define
a new set of weights uh referred to as
W2 here. And we apply those to the the
previous layer of W1 uh multiplied by X.
Again pay attention to the
dimensionalities here that we have the C
number of outputs and D as the number of
uh input features. But then we also
define H and and uh that defines
uh the number of neurons the number of
hidden layer nodes or neurons.
That's one point. The second point is
this max function that um we'll be
coming back to and we'll explain what it
it is and what it means. What um the max
operation is doing here is to create a
nonlinearity between the linear
transformations done by W1 and W2. And
this is actually a very very important
um
part of um the the process. I will talk
a little bit about the nonlinearity but
also uh look at this this last part
before I forget in practice that's right
that we are only including w and x we we
as we talked about this in the first and
second lecture we also
uh incorporate a bias just to have a a
complete framework so so in practice we
also have bias but we don't write it
here for the sake of simplicity anyways
the max operation is creating the
nonlinearity and it's actually very
important because as we talked about um
the
linear classifiers last in the last few
lectures we we said we mentioned that
there are so many different problems
that we can't uh separate the samples
with just one single line right this was
one of the examples that um in order to
be able to solve this problem with
neural networks with linear functions.
we need some sort of nonlinear
transformation from the original space
to a new space and now in the new space
you see that it's they are separable
using a a line right so with um in this
case it's it's a nonlinear u
transformation between the input and
then the second space which is mapping
the x and y to their polar polar
coordinates r and theta but again Um
this is just one example. There are so
many other um examples too.
So um with
this example, let's go back to oops uh
let's go back to our uh definition of
the two layer neural network.
As you've probably seen in the
literature and outside uh this class,
these types of networks which only
depend on weights and u inputs and
layers and so on. There are no other
operations than multiplication are often
referred to as fully connected networks
or multilayer perceptrons MLPS. So
that's that's one um thing and we can
actually stack more and more layers to
create better um more um larger networks
and in this case again uh pay attention
to the dimensionalities and the hidden
layers that we have in u in in in the
middle and the dimensionalities that do
uh match one after the other. So um
back to this visual representation of
what the neural network is doing. Um
we talked about this when when we had
the linear representations that often
what happens is the network through the
weights is learning some sort of
templates.
If you remember last uh last week we
were talking about these templates that
are being learned. So again I'm saying
templates they're they're not I mean
they are some representatives of the
images but from the data
uh depending on what data it was trained
on. So these templates in in um what we
discussed last week were kind of
generated by by these um 10 outputs by
applying the W's on top of the input
neurons right so um with that
now that we have multiple layers more
layers now we can actually create some
more templates now now we have a layer
in the middle that can actually create
100 templates lets um as opposed to just
just 10 for a linear classifier although
we still have those 10 as well and this
again uh in a very high from a very high
level understanding point of view I'm
I'm telling you what this means when um
we have these 100 neurons in the in the
middle we are giving the network the
power to create templates for not entire
objects but maybe parts of the object
for example the classes that you see
here We had bird, cat, um, deer, dog,
frog, horse, they all have eyes, right?
So one of those 10 templates, 100
templates could probably be a part of
the objects that is that could be shared
between all of the classes. So from a
high level point of view and
understanding this um these can form
templates and when we come back to the
topics of visualization and what we
learn from the neural networks this uh
this topic will we'll uncover more
details about what I I'm talking about
right now. So um
back to the function max we talked about
max uh function the nonlinearity that is
created here and in neural network
terminology we call that an activation
function right it and it's actually
playing a very very important role a
pivotal role in in building the model uh
building a neural network let's answer
this question that we have on the slide
what happens if we try to build a neural
network without uh one of these
activation functions let's say the the
max function this will be our function
if I remove the the max right so it
would be w2 * w1 by x what would happen
here yes exactly so as u you can guess
and and correctly you mentioned the
multiplication of w2 by w1 could
actually be replaced easily with another
matrix W3 and then your function becomes
just a linear function. So everything
could be lumped uh together. So we need
some sort of nonlinearity in the middle
to be able to give us the uh the power
to solve nonlinear
uh problems. The function that we just
talked uh about is uh ReLU. It's the
rectified linear unit. It's a very
popular function activation function
used in neural networks while there are
so many other variants that have have
been tested in many uh many other
architectures and and even in the more
modern architectures. One of the
problems that ReLU has it it sometimes
creates dead neurons because it it's
it's it's making everything equal to
zero if it's uh not positive. Right? So
in order to avoid the dead uh neurons
leaky relu with this uh type of modeling
or uh elu the exponential linear unit
are other options. ELU is a little bit
better because it has a better zero
centered uh function and then there are
some newer variations
um jello uh gshian error uh linear units
or I don't know I've I've heard both
variation jello and yellow so um could
be could be used they are often used
more often in neuro architecture in in
transformers and Um we also have
silo
or or swish. Uh it's the sigmoid linear
unit that um uh that one is is also used
in some of the modern CNN architectures.
Google was using this for uh efficient
some of the variations of their uh
models and also in efficient net.
Other than these there are um functions
like simmoid and uh ten or or tanh that
are often also used for
as as activation functions although they
do have a few problems
because they do squash values in a
narrow range and that uh sometimes
results in vanishing vanishing
gradients. So we often do not use
sigmoid or or tang in the middle of the
neural networks. They are often used in
the later layers where um we want to for
example binarize the outputs and and uh
things like that. So as I said ReLU is
often a good default choice. It's it's
very much used in many
architectures and there are so many
variations of the same function that we
talked uh about.
I want to summarize what what we've
talked about and then answer some
questions. So um we did talk about
different uh adding layers and and so
on. But I want to highlight that
activation functions are often functions
that are operating in the
layers. And you also have W's which
define the weights mapping between the
previous layer and the and the next
layer. Again, these are fully connected
neural networks with very simple
uh implementations.
What we only need is to be able to
define an activation function. And in
this example, if you look at the
example, we have um the sigmoid uh
function defined as the activation
function. And very easily using that
activation. The first and the second
layers of the hidden values, hidden
neurons are
uh calculated by applying w1 by x and
then also the uh the bias and then
applying it um applying the function the
the activation function and then same
for h2 and the output will be very
simply the the dot product for the uh
between the with w3 and the last layer
of hidden values creating the output
layer. I'll stop here to answer some
questions if there are any and then I
would love to continue it. That is a
great question and the question is how
would we choose for a new problem which
of these activation functions to use? Um
the short answer to your question is uh
is yes. It's it's empir empirical in
most cases. Um but we often start with
with Reu or we go with um standard
activation functions being used for
those specific architectures. Uh as I
mentioned there are um activation
functions that are often commonly used
in um CNN's or in transformers and and
uh different architectures. So we often
uh go with the with the ones that are
tested before. But yes, it's it's mostly
empirical. If you're if you're designing
a new network for a new problem, then uh
that's one of your choices that you have
to make very much similar to other
hyperparameters.
So the question here uh is is uh what is
the attribute that is is is basically
common between all of these activation
functions and uh what it it really does.
I will uh give you some examples and
I'll I'll go into some of the details of
what these activation functions are
doing. Uh basically the uh main and and
the most important common characteristic
here is to create nonlinearity and we're
not using a linear function as as the
activation. Right? So creating some sort
of nonlinearity is is something that is
makes makes it very important. And why
do we have so many variations? I told
you a little bit about the problems with
v vanishing gradients. I told you uh a
little bit about
uh differentiability of the the
functions. They should be uh
differentiable because we are using them
in neural network. and uh and and uh
sometimes having a a proper zero
centered value and a smooth function
makes it uh much faster to to get
converging networks. So there are so
many different uh factors these are the
the main ones that I uh told you and
talked about which play an important
role for defining or designing these uh
functions.
I'll talk a little bit more about that
when I uh go into details of the
functions too. In all of the layers we
often use um same activation functions
but as I said sometimes in the later
layers or the output layer we use like a
sigmoid activation sigmoid uh function
and or tangent function. So um but but
commonly yes and uh
the question was if we use the same uh
across the networks
uh the the entire network same function
for all of the neurons.
Okay. Um continuing uh to
what we were talking about which um is
the implementation of these um
models these um a neural network. So
there is a very simple way um I mean
that building a neural network a two
layer neuron network in Python is just
less than or or 20 lines of code very
simple define our network as I talked
about the dimensionalities n is the
number of samples dn d in is the
dimensionality of the input and d out is
the dimension of the out the output and
h the number of neurons in the
uh hidden layer and we talked about this
is just creating X and Y and randomize u
randomly init uh initializing W's. Then
we have the forward forward pass which
means applying W's to the inputs
layer by layer and ultimately creating
the output the prediction wise predicted
wise and then al and and and finally
calculating the loss function and
outputting that loss value
after the forward As we need an
optimization pro process, a way to
calculate the analytical gradients and
use those gradients that are created to
run gradient descent to optimize W1 and
W2. Basically taking one step towards
the optimal value of the network.
But this part calculating the analytical
gradient is is the most important um
part in in here that we haven't very
much uh gone into. So this is the the
almost the rest of this lecture is about
making this work and scale in um
different settings. So um
after training and building such a
neural network depending on on how many
nodes we use in the hidden layer you see
that we can we can identify we can get
different patterns uh of separation
between the two classes and more neurons
often means more capacity to learn more
complex functions and better separation.
of the
uh the nodes the the
points
if you take a look at this this is this
is very much similar to this this
pattern I'm showing here is is similar
to the one that I showed in the second
lecture where we were talking about k
nearest neighbor and and when we had
only k equal to one the the one nearest
neighbor framework
it was very much similar to using more
neurons right so same type of arguments
happen here that that if we give a lot
of capacity to the network then we will
have some overfeeding problems uh we
won't be able to generalize to unseen
data but uh there are many different
solutions for
this as well and one thing that I as a
rule of thumb what I want to highlight
here for you is to not use the size of
neural network as a regularizer. We
don't often use that as a hyperparameter
to fine-tune this this network size
although we experiment with different um
values of uh the network size and um
related hyperparameters. But what we
often do is we we go with a a little bit
of a um bigger network that we need and
then we use the regularization
um and then this regularizer and
specifically this regular regularization
um hyperparameter
to to do a different to check the
different setups. So what we often tune
is the regularization and regularization
hyperparameter not necessarily the
network size itself.
Okay. Um
this is the concept of neural networks
in a nutshell. But we
have heard about neural networks and how
they could be related to uh the
biological there are some biological
inspirations. Uh so I'll I'll talk a
little bit about it but there's a
question basically your question is uh
why is the model
more underfeeding when we increase the
value of lambda here? Yes. So um just to
quickly answer that question, the value
of lambda is controlling how much
contribution the regularizer should have
in the overall loss, right? And the
larger contribution that you have um on
the regularizer and remember that
regularizer was defined on W's. So it's
constraining the W's. It's giving less
freedom to the values on W's, right? So
less freedom equals a little bit of like
u
more generic boundaries not not
necessarily giving you those uh like
detailed values detailed um uh parts of
the the boundaries right so if you
constrain the model too much even with
regularizer you're also going to get uh
values like that decision boundaries
like that yes the right regularizer
always overfeeds uh prevents
overfeeding.
Again you you are creating a compromise
a balance between the loss like
predicting the actual the right output.
So the first part of the loss is
predicting the right output. The second
part is only playing with the values of
the weights doesn't doesn't care about
the outputs anymore. If you overweight
this you're not going to get very good
uh classifiers right. So creating a
balance regularizer is always good but
nothing is good if you use too much of
it. Right.
[Music]
>> Um could you go over again why we would
want to change the regularization rather
than the size?
>> So um there are many different reasons.
One of them is size of the network.
You're building networks. If you're
going to build networks that sometimes
that you have to run them for few days
to to to get some results, right? So
networks um we often what we what we
often do is we start increasing the
quality the number of parameters in
networks until we see some levels of
overfeeding.
So that's that's the time that we know
that the network is is actually
understanding the patterns in the data
and is trying is is is now able to
memorize the data and that's the time
that we try to minimize the overfeitting
by regularizing the the network. So
regularization plays an important factor
there. So if we if we go too high on the
uh on the number of parameters number of
complexity of the network then that's
going to be causing a problem. We never
never often do that. We often for a new
problem start with smaller u networks
and and increase that um after with
correct that with the regularizer for a
given problem.
How do we know how many neurons we need
to solve the problem? that's based on uh
empirical um research work and and
looking at other uh similar type of
there is no one prescription for all
like you have to look at um other
counterparts other other types of
networks that were trained in sim on
similar data. start from that range and
then um often you do a number of
experiments yourself to balance and
increase or decrease the complexity of
the network. So it's it's often and
always pretty much bound to uh
exploration.
So your question is are there any
theoretical and and foundational work uh
done to see um which ones to use, which
activation functions to use and how many
layers to use. There are so many uh
research and and and uh papers out
analyzing these and and also some
methods for optimizing all of these um
meta or hyperparameters of of the
networks. We're not going to get into uh
them in in detail because again a big
part of it is based on very much
dependent on the data set the problem
you're solving and um so
uh the best answer to your question is
yes there are some works out there but
um but again each of those make
assumptions that may not be necessarily
true to your uh for your application or
problem. So um what what happens is um
there are some biological inspirations.
Again these inspirations are very much
very loose. If there is a neuroscientist
sitting here or is watching online um
it's uh do not take all of the examples
that I'm um giving you or talking about
as u
the ground truth. But
generally what happens in in neurons and
you know this this is a a
visualization of a neuron. It does have
a cell body that often uh aggregates the
impulses carried through dendrites to
the cell um
body itself cell uh body and then using
axons those impulses are carried away to
other uh neurons. This is very much
similar to what we are doing in our
neural networks. We often have a
function that captures the
uh the the the the signals all of the
previous impulses activations from the
previous layers and in the cell body
that function
is operated on the um on the inputs and
outputs the out the the activations and
passes them to the next layer. here next
neuron. And that's basically why we need
some sort of activation function here to
to create the impulses to to to increase
or decrease the the values. Um, so with
that again, uh, that there are many
differences between biological neurons
and how they could actually be way more
complex than what
neural networks we build look like. But
um, but generally there are common
concepts.
Often the neural networks that we build
are organized into regular patterns and
those patterns are because we want to
have better computational efficiency
when we be we implement the uh neural
networks. Although there has been
research creating these complex neural
networks and and trying to optimize but
um again in terms of results they are
almost comparable with the regular
functions regular neuron networks that
we often build and we'll be talking
about in this class.
I can't uh warn you enough on on on on
being careful with your brain analogies
and um and how this could uh be
interpreted. So there are so many
differences and um I'll I'll just uh
stop here and would be happy to discuss
if if anybody was interested in the
neuroscience aspect of things as well.
So um plugging everything in we did have
a scoring function.
This scoring function
turns the inputs through some W's, some
weight vectors or weight matrices into
scores. And um
what we often use as the loss function
for the network is using those scores
either through hinge loss or soft max or
other variations.
And uh and and in addition to that we
defined regularizers
which ultimately give us the total loss
of a the data loss plus regularizer.
And um we talked about this fact that in
order to be able to optimize W1 and W2,
what we need is to be able to take the
derivative of the partial derivative of
L with respect to W1 and W2. Uh partial
A by W1 and W2. There are so many
different um details that we have to be
aware of.
First, uh building these functions and
then taking the derivatives and and
writing them down is often tedious.
There are lots of matrix calculations
and need a lot of uh work on the paper
before you can actually implement a
neural network. The other challenge, the
other problem is what if you want to
change the loss slightly different from
what we we've we've done the paper all
of the calculations
um over. So in that case again we have
to um
redo the entire thing and finally um
this becomes intractable and sometimes
invisible if the loss function is
complex. So with complex functions
that's going to be even
harder.
But there is a better idea, something
that is often used um in our
implementations and I'm going to go into
a few examples today just to make sure
everybody is on the same page and
understands these uh topics.
So and and that is computational graphs
and the idea of back propagation.
computational graphs are are
putting together all of the operations
in the neural network and um creating
that stepbystep thing and and and start
from the inputs and all of the
parameters that are uh basically needed
and get the loss as the final um output
final layer. So in this case we had a
loss function which could be a softmax
function or a hinge loss function
whatever it is it's the loss function
which is added to the regularizer the
the function rw
and r has the has w as the input. So
these two added together calculate or or
create the loss and before doing the um
or or having the loss calculated we
often also need to aggregate X and W and
create the score. This is a
multiplication function.
This is um actually very useful because
most of the neural networks that you
build are also they have graphical
representations and all of these complex
functions could be could be shown with
the same uh framework and then we can
use this and uh and build their
computation graph starting from input
image or input data. There are a bunch
of weights throughout the network. And
finally, there is the loss function.
And again, this is useful because um
there are some complex neural networks
like this um neural touring machine and
uh that is actually used for temporal
and sequential data. So there's a lot of
unrolling of this this machine. And if
we have to do all of the work manually
by hand, this is going to be un um
intractable and and not uh feasible. So
and that's why
when we build this this computational
graph, the solution to that is back
propagation.
And I want to start with a very simple
example. So we start with a function um
f of x y and z which is x + y * z. And
if I draw the computational graph for
for this function, you see we have an
operation
which is uh the the the addition
operation between x and y and then we
have a multiplication between x uh
between the
that that addition of x1 and y
multiplied by z.
So given an input setup of x = -2, y = 5
and z = -4.
Now actually we can make all of the
calculations for and and do this uh the
forward
pass the uh for stepping forward in the
the neural network. The first step is
adding x and y which gives us three. And
in order to be able to to understand the
steps and step by step, I'm I'm giving
the name to it. So Q= X + Y. And if I
want to calculate the partial
derivatives of Q with respect to both X
and Y, it's very simple because we have
the formulation here between X and um Q
and X and Y. The the formulation is
there. the derivatives the partial
partial q by x = 1 and partial q by y =
1 as well. So so this is this is a
simple setup we know it exists so just
keep it in the back of our minds. Then u
the second operation is f= q *
z. Again, since we have this function,
it's very easy to calculate to to write
the partial derivatives, right?
Uh partial f by q= z and f by z equals u
q. So, it's kind of swap between z and
q.
I'm hoping that everybody knows all of
these from linear algebra. So, and if
you don't, you should definitely check
it out and remind yourself because these
are actually very very important
um algebra in general and uh for the
rest of the quarter. what we want and
what we need uh in this setup and and to
complete this example of back
propagation, we need the partial
derivative of f with respect to x, y and
z.
How we start and how back propagation
implements this is to start at the front
of the network at the end of the network
and we start going back back propagating
all of the gradients and um this is
basically a recursive process that will
be u running. So
derivative of f with respect to f
is what? It's the thing with respect to
itself, right? So it's always the the
the the last part the derivative of loss
function with respect to itself is is
always one. If I want to back prop the
first the most immediate one is z. You
can see here that
um we have z and and for this one if I
calculate the derivative of f with
respect to z we already have it right f
with respect to z is equal to q. So
whatever the value of q is goes to
this um as as the gradient as well. Next
we have um q q is the the next one. next
one that is directly connected to f. So
this is also easy to compute because we
have um derivative of f with respect to
q. We have also already uh calculated
that it's equal to z whatever z is
that's the value of derivative here
minus 4.
Next we have
y which is directly before q and we know
that y and f although we need derivative
of f with respect to y but y and f are
not directly connected and that's where
we use the chain rule
where
we split the the
uh calculation of derivatives with
respect to the variable in in the
middle. So partial f by y equals to
partial f by q q by y. Right? So this is
the
this is how the chain rule could be
could be written in this case. And now I
want to introduce you to two important
new terms. Local gradient and upstream
gradient. up string gradient is often
the gradient that comes from the end of
the network to this this um
current node that we are in and then uh
the local gradient is the gradient of
the the the note what the input of the
note is with u
gradient of of its output with respect
to its input. So it's the local
gradient. So defining these is actually
not too hard because f by q we already
have the value q by y we also already
have the value. So it's 1 multiplied by
z and the value will become minus 4.
Same story when it it's the
for the other uh variable x here the
local gradient upstream could again be
written uh down with this chain rule and
it also results in minus 4 and and um
gives us because because in both cases
the
gradient with respect to x or y was
already one. So both of them get the
same value. So with this computational
setup and the computational graph, it
becomes very easy to modularize what we
want to do for every single node in the
neural network
having X and Y as input or whatever else
and Z as the output.
What we need
are first the local gradients
which we can always we have the function
f it's a function of x and y. So the
output gradient of output with respect
to the each of the inputs it's easy to
calculate for every single node and what
we need to be able to back propagate is
the upstream gradient right and the back
propagation process is giving us the
power to get this upstream gradient step
by step. So we when we are at this node
we also have the upstream gradient
already uh calculated from the future
nodes and um
that's what we need. What we can do
after this is just to multiply the
upstream gradient with the local
gradient and create what now we call
downstream gradients. So the downstream
gradients are going to be upstream
gradients for the previous layers.
Right? So that's how we calculate that
for X. Same story when it comes to Y.
So this this whole process gives us the
the power to create and and calculate
all of these completely locally and step
by step go backwards and give it to the
previous nodes so they can continue the
process. So again this is one of the
most um fundamental operations in all of
neural networks and many optimization
uh processes involving multiple layers
of uh information.
If I understand the question correctly,
you're saying how can we understand this
intuitively what the gradients are
doing, right? So let's take one step
back and and see why we why we are here
to begin with. What we needed was to
identify to calculate the gradient of
the loss function with respect to w1 and
w2 and w's in general to be able to take
a step to uh in the negative u direction
of in the opposite direction of the
gradients to be able to find the the
optimal value right optimal loss. So in
order to do that we need gradient of l
loss with respect to everything. So what
we are doing is we are just moving
gradient of L with respect to all
variables in the network back to every
single value of the network without
sitting down and writing the function
for the entire network. If the network
has um 100 layers, we're not going to be
sitting down and writing the function
for all of the 100 layers separately.
This is how we back propagate step by
step to to get the values that we need
for that optimization process of every
single weight that is going to be
incorporated in the network.
Okay. Um
example uh another example
um
so this is a little bit more complex
function uh function of weights and x
and we have 1 / 1 + e ^ of a linear
combination of x and um w.
So
there are a bunch of multiplications,
additions,
negation and and the exp function and
and ultimately the one over whatever we
calculated function. So with with with
all of those let's look at this example
that we have specific values for w0 x0
w1 x1 and w2 with these given values we
can do the forward pass calculate every
single value that we have in uh this
process and just to remind you we do
have some of the details some of the we
we know um For an exp function e ^ of x
what its derivative is with respect to x
constant
uh multiplication always the derivative
is the constant value itself 1 /x has a
derivative of -1 / x2
uh these are again what we know from
algebra. So and and if it's a constant
addition it's always the derivative is
equal to one. So as I said always in the
very beginning at the at at the end of
the network the derivative of L with
respect to L is always equal to one. So
that's where we start using this uh rule
the derivative of function 1 /x. Now we
can calculate upstream I said it's it's
one always at the end. The local
gradient could be one min -1 / x 2. What
is the value of x that whatever the
input is? So this calculation results in
minus uh.53.
So.53 is the downstream gradient which
defines the upstream gradient for the
next one. And in the next again the
function here is just a constant
addition where we know that the local
gradient equals to one. So one
multiplied by upstream gradient same
value goes back
uh next step is the exp function. So for
that again the lo the upstream we
already have the value for the local
gradient it's e to the power of x what
is x the input of to the of this uh step
minus one. So calculating this will give
us minus.2
and this goes back to the next step.
Here we again have a multiplication with
a constant number which defines the
local gradient equal to that um number
that that uh constant value and
defining the new gradient downstream
gradient and going back now here we have
an addition function where we are
getting some um data some some
information sorry two inputs
um of the different values here. And
again, if you want to calculate the
upstream gradient, it's 02 already. We
have it. The downstream at the local
gradients will be equal to
uh one because it's just an addition
between two values and an addition. The
derivative of x + y with respect to both
x and y is always one. So both inputs
will be the same. Then we have
multiplication operations with
multiplication.
Uh upstream gradient again we have the
values and the local gradients with
respect to a multiplication val is if we
always have say for example a multiplied
by x. The derivative of this with
respect to x is always a the other
variable. Right? So here for the first
one it's minus one which is the value of
x and for the second one it's two which
is the value of w. So the other other
variable whatever the value it has. So
with that we can calculate everything
and then then also calculate the the
ones with respect to w1 and x1. Again,
we made all of these calculations so we
can identify how much W should be
changed in order to step towards the
optimal point in the neural in the
network.
So this was another example. There are
so many different ways to
draw a computational graph. This was not
the only one that I I explained. So we
can actually lump all of the function
together and define a sigmoid sigmoid
because this is basically sigmoid of a
linear function. Right? So the linear
function could be here and then all of
these operations could be defined as
sigmoid. And actually sigmoid is
interesting and very useful to um to use
because the local gradient using sigmoid
is dependent on sigmoid itself. So the
local gradient of sigmoid with respect
to the variable x if we do the
calculations and simplify it's 1 minus
sigmoid multiplied by the sigmoid of the
same x. So it's actually a very very uh
useful uh framework. So anyways uh
useful function and easy and in order to
calculate the upstream um the the the
downstream gradient again what the
upstream gradient was was value one and
if I calculate the local gradient which
is this function replacing x with what
the input was which is one
it's it's how this will be calculated
multiplied by one will be 2 which is
actually the exact same value that we
had from before doing it um separately.
I want to summarize and and say that um
there are few patterns in in the data
often um very much in for the for the
for the nodes that um we can actually
kind of memorize. uh there is AD gate
for the AD gate it's always a gradient
distributor because of the the the
properties of addition that I explained
the gradients will uh remain the same as
whatever its input is for the
multiplication gate it's the it's a swap
function again I told you gradient of xy
with respect to x is y with respect to Y
is X. So it's kind of a swap and then
um there is copy gate in the copy gate.
copy gate it the operation that happens
is is just an addition of what is coming
uh to the network and to the node or
gate the gate and then ultimately
there's a max gate which is actually
something that we use quite often very
much similar to the relu function max um
gate has the gradient of because it's
it's up it's taking a max between its
inputs so whichever the max value was
you just relay the or route the gradient
towards that um direction.
So with that um it's it's very simple to
now implement a neural network forward
pass compute all of the steps and then
in the backward pass we start computing
the gradients and step by step I explain
that the gradient of the uh fun the loss
function with respect to itself is
always one and then we start from the
end of the network and go up. You can
see here that we are going uh up. So
this is the sigmoid function
calculating the gradients. Then going up
that was the add gate. We had another
add gate and then we had two multiply
gates which basically very simply um
gives us the implementations.
And with this type of formulation, what
we can do is just do some implement
modular modularize every um function in
the in neural network and create the
forward and backward APIs for every
single function that we need in the
neural network. So in this case this is
a multiplication gate that because for
multiplication we need to access the
inputs for use in the backward pass we
often save them memorize them but then
calculate the forward pass values and
then the backward pass calculate the
gradients. So this means we can write
our functions and put the forward and
backward passes all in. And this is how
PyTorch operators right now look like.
If you look at the sigmoid layer for
example, it's just the forward pass.
Although
um in this very function, it's not
implemented. It's it's somewhere else in
the C++ code in the C code um that it's
actually implemented in PyTorch. But
then the backward pass of sigmoid is
also calculating the same function that
we just uh talked about.
So with this um
the so far what we've what we've said uh
and I actually covered most of the
examples that I wanted to cover in um
using the scholar values. All of the
examples were were were just scholar
values. But we know that um all of these
operations could actually be implemented
in vector or matrix uh forms. Just
expanding on that um piece here. Um we
talked about this that with the scholar
to scholar setting so far what we've
talked about uh for any input x and y
being scholars. So um the derivative
will also be a scholar which means if we
change x by a small amount how much the
value of y uh will change if it's now
vectorzed and and there are vectors if
if x is a vector of n elements and y is
a scalar a vector to a scalar uh
derivative then in this case the
derivative will also be a vector. vector
and every single element in that vector
means if we change x by a small value
that that value then how much the amount
of y changes then the entire amount of y
because it's just one single value and
then there are also vector to vector uh
frameworks where x and y both of them
are vectors of arbitrary size n and m in
those cases the derivatives will form a
matrix or what we call Jacobians
and and there
uh for each of the elements in X if it
changes by a small amount then uh this
derivative tells us how much each
element of Y will be changed again look
at the sub u scripts here they are not
um completely they're not the They could
be different for every single element in
this jubian. There has a there's a clear
meaning. And then how we can do or or um
see it and visualize it in here is that
if you want to backrop uh with vectors
say xy and z are vectors of size dx, dy
and dz. Again the loss
derivative um L is the loss itself is
always scholar because that's always one
value we want to uh minimize but then
calculating the upstream gradient will
result in also a vector DZ same size as
its u
um variable Z and same story happens
when it comes to downstream gradient in
in downstream gradients. U actually
before going to downstream gradients let
me tell you a little bit about the local
gradients where we have
uh
gradient of Z with respect to X and uh Y
and in this case that's the part that I
said there will be Jacobians because now
the matrix the the gradients will turn
into matrices. So we have two Jacobian
matrices here um defined by the size of
their input by multiplied by the size of
the output and um and then this results
in downstream gradients that are
multiplication of upstream and the um
local gradient and there we get same
size as the inputs. X itself. So the
we will have a vector again here because
the input was a vector same size in
terms of the
gradients. Um
I just mentioned that gradients of
variables with respect to loss always
have the same dimensionality as the
original variable itself as also shown
in this um slide. So um
back prop with vectors was that's just
one uh one example here. Let's say we
have a function which is the max of zero
and x. That's that's the relu function.
So this is an elementwise function that
takes the input takes a max between zero
and if it's non zero if it's uh non-
negative it passes through otherwise
replaces it with a zero. Assume you get
some upstream gradients and there now we
need to build a Jacobian matrix here and
this Jacobian matrix in this case
because this is an elementwise operation
it doesn't have any dependence on any of
the other inputs only the dependence is
on the value itself. This is a very
sparse matrix only has value on the main
diagonal. And those values are actually
either zero or one depending on if the
max was actually um taken or a zero was
if the the value was passed through or
or just the zero was replaced um with it
um in in its place. multiplying it by
the upstream gradient gives us the
downstream gradient and um this is how
um the calculations are done. As I said,
Jacobian here is mat is is a sparse
because in this case the operation is
element wise and that could actually be
instead of in the in the backward pass
instead of calculating that huge sparse
jacobian matrix what we do is just use
these rule-based calculation of the
gradient for for this max function. So
we don't really store that that matrix
and and do not calculate that because we
know the how the the function uh
operates.
And then this could also be extended to
matrices um and even tensors if the
inputs are not vectors. They are high
higher dimensionalities uh high
dimensionality data. So in those cases
again the gradients with respect to the
variables would be of the same size as
that specific variable and calculating
the upstream and downstream calcul uh
matrices and derivatives is going to be
done same as how we discussed uh and and
showed
earlier for vectors and then when it
comes to the local gradients although um
however it's going to be a huge matrix a
huge jacobian because we have a matrix
as in as the output and the matrix as
the input and then the local gradients
will be the
same size as the multiplication of its
input size and and the output size. So
it's it's going to be a huge matrix by
itself. Let me give you an example. If
this is input X and W as as input for a
node for a gate with matrix
multiplication,
what happens is
uh and and generates this this Y as the
output. Calculating
derivative of L with respect to Y gives
us these Jacobian matrices. And say we
have a batch size mini batch size of 64
and dimensionality of those matrices is
is 4,96
then this means that that Jacobian
matrix that huge Jacobian matrix will be
over 256 GB for just one single multiply
um matrix multiplication.
So in order to
simplify this we often um what we do is
we try to look at the values and how
they impact each other. For example,
what part of parts of Y will be affected
if element one element of X um gets
impacted. So there uh x uh n and d this
this specific one often affects just one
row in the output. And this is um this
basically helps us uh identify for
calculating each of these nodes. We
don't need to create the huge jacobian.
we can actually write the backward pass
functions uh specifically for matrix
multiplication
uh in a more efficient way and uh I'm
almost done so you answer this question
how much does x and d affect the value
of y and m so this is y and m that is um
getting impact from x and d
how much Does it get impact? It means
that what should I place or or put as
its gradient with respect to um
the the specific value x and d.
Just to remind you this is a
multiplication operation.
In multiply gates it should be a swap
right. So whatever
this this uh the answer to this question
is something a value in W right remember
that we had this multiplication gate
which was a swap multiplier so there is
a swap happening here so the value of
X being affected uh affecting Y one of
the elements in Y is going to be
dependent on
a W that is in row D defined by the X
matrix and column M defined by the Y
matrix. So it's swapping the values.
It's the same swap but here now we have
to look at the the giant matrices and
find which which uh specific element uh
it should be and then based on that we
can actually replace the entire thing
with matrix multiplication
matrix operations. The gradient of L
with respect to X will be defined as
this simple matrix operation. And then
the gradient of L with respect to W will
be defined as this very simple
multiplication. Again swap here for X we
include the entire W. For W we include
the entire X and do the uh
multiplications.
These formulas makes it easy to to
implement larger and and harder
operations
and um get them implemented in the
backboard passes. All right, we're done.
Um just to summarize, we talked today
about fully connected neural networks.
We went through all the steps needed for
back propagation, the forward passes,
backward passes and next session we will
be getting into the topic of
convolutional neural networks.
Thank you.