good afternoon everyone and uh thank you
for joining us today my name is
Alexander amini and together with Ava
we're going to be your instructors for
the course this year this is uh MIT
introduction to deep learning or 6cs 191
is our official course title now we're
super excited to welcome you to this
class and I think probably the a good
place to start is always you know asking
ourselves well what is MIT intro to deep
learning this is a onewe boot camp on
everything deep learning right so it's a
both a very fun but also a very intense
one week because we're going to cover a
ton of material in just the next five
days now this is our eth year teaching
this class and the pace of the field
especially in the past couple years is
really remarkable and every that we
teach this class it's getting more and
more I should say interesting to
introduce this this lecture in
particular and how we introduced this
lecture has really start to adapt and
evolve over the many years now many of
you in the audience have probably even
started to become almost a bit I would
say desensitized to a lot of the
progress of deep learning in the past
couple years because of this progress
how rapidly this progress is happening
so I think it's it's also important to
not forget you know where we came from
just a few years ago so I want to show
you know this this image right here just
to start this off and what better way to
show you than for you to actually see
the progress with your own eyes exactly
one decade ago this was the state of a
state-of-the-art deep learning based
facial generation system so this is not
a real face this was the
state-of-the-art model that could
generate faces and this was the best
that we could do fast forward you know
just a few years uh down the pipeline
and progress in image generation had
already started to advance tremendously
and here you can see you know you know a
lot of more realism photo realism in
these types of images being created and
then you know fast forward another few
years after that and and these images
start to come to life right they start
to have temporal information they start
to have video and uh you know movement
as well to those uh to those images
right and in fact this this video that
you see on the right is a video that we
created in this class uh some years ago
and for those of you who haven't seen it
already it's it's uh you know it's
online and people have seen it but in
case you haven't I'll play just the
first 10 seconds I won't play the whole
thing just so you can see it as well hi
everybody and welcome to MIT 6s
one91 the official introductory course
on deep learning taught here at MIT now
I won't play the whole thing right but
you get the gist of this video this this
video was created five years ago we made
it as part of this class and we we used
it to actually introduce this class uh
back then now when we did this in 2020
it got a lot of even back then right
like especially back then maybe you guys
aren't that impressed by it today but
back then this video was a huge deal
right this was a huge jump in photo
realism for uh for for capabilities of
deep learning models and the clip went
you know very uh very rapidly a bit
viral and people commented a lot about
the realism but actually one interesting
thing that people didn't see they saw
the end result but actually at that
point what people didn't see was that
for us to generate that clip which was a
two-minute clip you only saw the first
10 seconds but that clip was 2 minutes
in total and to generate that two-minute
clip it cost around two hours of
professional audio data being recorded
and captured uh of the speaker which was
not us it cost around 50 hours of
professional High def video data to
build you know the face model and it
required around
$155,000 US dollars of compute to
generate that two-minute video and all
of that was just going to generate you
know a predefined script right something
static you couldn't talk to it you
couldn't interact with it it was just a
predefined script static not flexible at
all but uh you know still a tremendous
amount of resources both time data
energy and and Financial Resources as
well and I wanted to start this class by
basically asking this question of you
know what would this look like today
right that video was created in 2020 but
today we're in
2025 and what would cloning you know and
generative AI look like in today's world
right especially understanding all of
those limitations that we had back then
in 2020 and I thought what better way to
to to tell you about this than to just
show you instead of you know all of that
compute and resources that we spent in
2020 let's do it live and unedited right
in front of everybody today so in fact I
have a bit of a secret so I'm going to
share my other screen and move this over
so this is a a terminal window that you
can actually see something's been
recording audio in the background as
I've been talking I've been having this
program that we made you know listening
to my audio recording my voice and what
I'm going to do is just uh you know
pause the recording now and we're going
to see how quickly it can actually
immediately start to uh you know just
take my voice and do an instant clone as
opposed to all of that time intensive
resources that we saw before so I'll
pause it right
now you'll see it instantly
clone and and yeah now now my voice is
cloned and what we're going to do with
this is actually try and not have a
predefined script like we saw before I'm
going to actually have a live and
unedited conversation with this voice
and see how Dynamic and flexible these
types of generative AI models have
become in today's world so let's try
this
out hello can you hear me hi yes loud
and clear how are you doing wait a
second actually you sound a lot like me
don't
you that's interesting you're right
we're even more similar than I thought
what are we up
to well actually I was just kicking off
this year's MIT deep learning class and
you know I'm I'm standing right in front
of the audience right
now uh MIT introduction to deep learning
is such a great class what's the class
like so
far actually we just started uh I you
know what I had an idea so I was just
about to introduce what is deep learning
how about you take that part over for
me deep learning is a type of machine
learning that uses artificial neural
networks to learn from data these
networks are inspired by the structure
of the human brain and are able to learn
complex patterns from large amounts of
data deep learning is used in a wide
range of applications including image
recognition natural language processing
and self-driving
cars it's pretty good actually you know
I think the amazing thing I was telling
everybody in the audience about was that
the the state of deep learning today is
so flexible it's so Dynamic what do you
think you're right deep learning is
incredibly dynamic it's constantly
evolving with new architectures
algorithms and applications being
developed all the time actually wait let
me interrupt you right there just to
show how Dynamic you I'm going to
interrupt you and uh let's try this
enough about deep learning how about you
tell me a story about turtles and make
it
wild oh Turtles you want the wild turtle
story okay picture this there's this
Turtle named shell right he's not your
average Turtle oh no Shell's got dreams
he dreams of flying he spends his days
practicing flapping his little FP trying
to get off the ground one day he meets
this crazy inventor a mad scientist
Turtle named Dr Sheldon who's built a
rocket powered shell Shelly jumps in and
boom they blast off into space they Zoom
past planets meet Aliens who love to eat
I'll interrupt you I'll interrup one
more it's Turtle tastic oh let's end it
here okay thank you so much this was a
this was a cool way to introduce the
class I'm glad I could help okay thanks
byebye
[Applause]
bye
okay awesome okay so that's just a fun
way to just to show you know how far
we've come in this field you know just
from a few years ago generating very
static content and now you know live
unedited extremely Dynamic content as
well
so you actually just heard a very brief
introduction on what deep learning is
and in fact in that demo uh and all of
the progress that all of you have been
seeing over the past many years you've
been seeing what you'll see in this
class over the next one week is the
fundamental techniques that drive all of
that progress so let's just start by
maybe laying some Foundation laying some
groundwork on exactly you know uh what
this field is all about and to do that I
think first I have to introduce to you
what is intelligence first of all right
so to me uh the word intelligence means
the ability to process information in
order to inform some future decision
right some future action this is what
intelligence means so all of us exhibit
this capability every single day you
know some more than others uh but
artificial intelligence is just the
practice of building algorithms
artificial algorithms to do exactly that
same process right use information use
data to inform future decisions
now machine learning what is machine
learning machine learning is a subset of
artificial intelligence that focuses on
not explicitly programming the computer
how to use that data how to process that
information to inform that decision but
just try to learn some patterns within
the data to make those uh decisions and
finally deep learning is just a subset
of machine learning which focuses on
doing that exact process with neural
networks deep neural networks and we'll
learn EX exactly what what deep neural
networks are throughout this class but
really at at a high level right this
entire course is about this core idea
fundamentally right this is what we will
teach and you will all get a very strong
handle on throughout this entire week is
you will learn how to teach computers
how to learn how to do tasks directly
from observation directly from data and
we'll provide you both a solid
foundation you know in the lectures but
also through practice iCal understanding
in software Labs as well so you can get
very handson and that's probably a good
segue to tell you a little bit about the
entire course just high level so this is
going to be a combination like I said
between the technical lectures and the
software Labs we'll have several new
updates this year in particular as we're
you know as the field is advancing so
quickly we're really going to try start
to uh you know you know drive home a lot
of key points especially in more of the
modern side of deep learning and then to
that end we'll conclude with some guest
lectures from industry leaders on
state-of-the-art deep learning methods
and AI methods that are being developed
in industry and this will really start
to advance your your knowledge even more
in
addition yes that's right also tonight
we're going to have a reception uh at
4:30 and you all invited to that
reception as well uh to you know talk to
to everyone and and learn more about
deep learning there's also food provided
as well um this year we also have have a
lot of great updates on the software
Labs uh so we'll be introducing both
tensorflow and pytorch software labs and
these are you know number one these are
a great learning experience for all of
you to get Hands-On with everything that
you learn in the lectures but also
they're a medium for you to enter into
the competition prizes and make
yourselves eligible for a lot of cash
prizes uh at the end of this course so
how exactly does that work each day
we'll have a dedicated lecture uh and
we'll have a dedicated software lab that
mirrors that lecture and the the
software Labb will just basically
reinforce what has been taught during
the day in the lectures uh starting
today you'll have lab one where you're
going to basically focus on building a
form of a a language model actually
it'll be a very small language model but
it's a next token predictor language
model that learns how to generate music
and predict the next token of music so
you can generate novel folk songs uh and
then tomorrow we'll move on to facial
detection systems you'll get Hands-On
with building your own computer vision
system from scratch understanding also
some automated techniques to fix
imbalanced data in those systems and
then finally lab three is going to be a
a brand new lab uh premiering this year
for the first time on large language
models and you're actually going to in
that part of that lab fine-tune a two
billion parameter large language model
uh on uh you know on compute that you'll
control uh in a mystery style and you'll
also build a AI judge to evaluate the
quality of that language model so all
three of these labs are going to be you
know a lot of a lot of fun and then
finally on the last day of the class
we'll have a final project pitch
competition uh each group can groups I
think of uh up to three to five people
and each group is presenting up to uh
three to five minutes kind of in a shark
tank style pitch competition and then
you'll be eligible for even more prizes
as part of that as well
okay uh I won't go through this slide
there's many great resources available
as part of this class uh this slide as
well as the entire lectures are all
posted online you can already check the
website they should be online already
and if you ever need any help please
post a Piaza if you have any questions
we have a team of incredible Tas and
instructors this year that you can reach
out to at any time for any questions or
issues myself and a will be your two
main lectures for most of the course but
then you also be hearing from a lot of
guest lectures uh throughout the rest of
the class uh here are some of the names
this course in general would not have
been possible uh each of these years
without all of our amazing sponsors so I
do want to give a huge thank you for all
of their support over the
years okay so now that we've gone
through all of that I want to start with
a lot of the the fun stuff yeah go
ahead sure
yeah that's right yeah so this course
has been Tau t for eight years we've
taught it to over around now 13 million
people uh so and just at MIT alone
because MIT you know that's the global
audience the MIT audience is around
probably 3,000 at this point and every
year online around 100,000 people take
this class so you're you're in great
company and a lot of really amazing
people have taken this class and we're
really excited for all of you to be here
today so I want to start now as we dive
into the technical part of this class I
want to start by you really asking this
fundamental question why deep learning
and why now and hopefully this is a
question all of you has asked before you
came here today uh you know
understanding exactly what gets at the
basis of deep learning is really
important so that we can understand how
we can move forward and build even
better algorithms that drive this field
so traditional machine learning maybe if
we start there for a second traditional
machine learning typically defines what
are called sets of features I'll tell
you more about that word in a second but
usually what the these features are
these are basically rules of how to do a
task step by step right and the problem
is that if we as humans Define those
features uh we're not usually very good
at building very robust features so for
example let's say I wanted to tell you
or I told you to build a AI model that
could you know detect faces how would
you do this what features would you
build in an image to detect faces well
what you could do is is you could uh you
know start by first detecting lines in
the image just edges right very simple
lines then you could start to compose
those lines together to detect things
like uh you know curves and edges and
and uh you know uh you know curves
basically yeah curves of lines not just
straight lines and then you can combine
those together to start to form more
composite objects right like eyes and
noses and ears and then from you can
actually start to build up structures of
faces why would you do it like this well
it's actually naturally hopefully this
is the way that you would also think of
doing it because it's very hard to
immediately just one shot detect a face
you actually don't process faces like
this first of all you actually start by
processing much more Co features the
low-level features first or excuse me
the high level features first then you
compose these together to really form
your own intuition about a face right
now the key idea of deep learning is no
different than than this process the key
idea is to learn these features instead
of me telling you or you telling me
exactly what those features are the key
idea of deep learning is to say after
observing a lot of faces can I learn
that I should first detect things in
this hierarchical fashion step by step
you know first detect the lines then
detect the curves then detect the you
know the composits like eyes noses and
ears and then build up to facial
structure like this and it turns out
this is exactly what deep learning is
able to do and we'll see how how this is
uh being done underneath the hood
throughout this lecture it's really
important to understand though that you
know even though we are seeing so many
of these amazing things of deep learning
over the past few years everything that
you'll learn especially in today's
lecture this is an intro lecture so
almost everything that you'll see today
has been invented or developed uh
decades ago right this is not new thing
new things that we'll be showing in
today's lecture tomorrow and the day
after and after that you'll start to see
a lot more of the recent Advan
but why are we seeing this all today
right the reason is because number one
we see an explosion of these techniques
even the techniques that are decades old
because of three key components number
one is data right data is becoming more
and more plentiful throughout the world
and this is really driving deep learning
progress the compute is number two right
compute is becoming more and more
powerful and more and more commoditized
GPU architectures especially are driving
the progress in learning and gpus were
you know uh you know only recently
starting to be commoditized and finally
open source toolboxes like you see on
the right hand side tensorflow P torch
caras and so on you know make it very
very streamlined and very easy for all
of you just in a onewe course to get
Hands-On with these architectures and
start to build
directly so let's start by you know just
understanding the fundamental building
blocks of every neural network and
that's just a single neuron or a
perceptor
right so what is a perceptron the idea
of a perceptron or a single neuron is is
really simple right so let's start by
just taking and defining a perceptron
purely by its forward propagation of
information so given some inputs how
does a perceptron compute an output
let's start by defining you know a set
of inputs X1 to
XM and each of these numbers each of
these inputs will be multiplied by a
corresponding weight W1 through WM what
we're going to do is after we do this
multiplication we're going to add up all
of those numbers together we'll take the
single number that comes out and then
we'll pass it through what's called a
nonlinear activation function this is
just a nonlinear one-dimensional
function that you can pass through uh
this single number on the output here
it's denoted as
G okay I left that one Minor Detail so
I'll correct it right now so the one
thing that we have to remember is that
after we multiply all of our weights by
our inputs we're also going to add this
one number called a bias term and the
bias term is effectively if you look at
the equation it's a way for us to shift
left and right along our activation
function G so this is just a shifting
scalar appro like designed within the
equation here now on the right hand side
of this equ of this slide you can
actually see the diagram on the left
mathematically Illustrated or
mathematically written as a single
equation
right now I'm going to now rewrite this
for the sake of cleanliness uh using
linear algebra in terms of vectors and
Dot products so let's do that now so now
instead of you know X1 through XM I'm
going to write just a vector capital x
capital x is going to be a collection of
all of my inputs and capital W will be a
collection or a vector of all of my
weights the output then Y is simply just
going to be obtained by having a do
product between X and W adding our
bias and passing through G passing
through a
nonlinearity now you might be wondering
you know I've mentioned this
nonlinearity a few times what is this
thing uh well I said it's a nonlinear
function right but what exactly is it
one common example here would be What's
called the sigmoid function so the
sigmoid function you can see right here
it's it basically can act over any real
number on the x axis but it outputs only
between Z and one so usually the sigmoid
function is really good for things like
probabilities if you wanted to convert
your output of your perceptron your
neuron to a probability but in fact
actually there's many types of nonlinear
function it's just one function that's
commonly used in neural networks but
throughout this presentation you'll see
basically a few examples of different
nonlinear functions uh and also I'll
point out on the bottom of this slide
you can see some code Snippets both in
tensorflow and P torch that will help
kind of like uh you know align what
you're seeing in the math with also code
that will be relevant for some of your
software Labs later today the sigmoid
function that you saw earlier this
output's very good for probabilities
you'll also see things like on the right
hand side this is called the rectified
linear unit this outputs uh things that
are strictly positive it is piecewise
linear so it is linear before zero and
is linear after zero but it has a single
nonlinearity at x equals
0 now why do we need activation
functions actually that's a question
hopefully everyone here asked it seems
like unnecessary if at its first glance
the point of an activation function is
actually quite simple it's to introduce
nonlinearities into your model right
without a nonlinear activation function
you have a linear model so why do we
want nonlinearities well it's just
because real data in the real world is
heavily nonlinear right now you might be
maybe just a good example to to show
this would be let's say I show you this
picture here and if I asked you to build
a classifier a separation draw a single
line that separates the red points from
the green points can you draw that
line at first glance yes you could draw
the line but what if I told you that it
had to be a straight line right if I
told you it's a straight line then it's
not really possible anymore to do this
task well so that that makes the problem
really hard that's the problem with
having a linear model the benefit of
having nonlinearities is that it allows
us to approximate arbitrarily complex
functions with enough depth in our model
this is exactly what makes neural
networks nonlinear neural networks
extremely powerful let me just help you
all understand this with a simple
example so imagine I gave you now a
trained neural Network that you can see
here it has one perceptron right but it
has two inputs X1 and X2 it also has two
weights W1 and W2 and it also has this
bias term on the top as well now how
would we how would we process this
information it's the same story as
before we're going to compute a DOT
product we're going to add the bias and
pass it through our nonlinearity
G now if we plug in our data we already
know our inputs here our inputs are
going to be uh let's see it's NE it's
positive 3 is the first input X1 and -2
is our second input X2 we can plug these
into our equation along with our weights
as
well and we can see actually uh that we
can obtain this line which is going to
be a two-dimensional line that
parameterizes our entire function space
of this neuron
since it's only in two Dimensions we can
even plot this line so we can say
exactly how this whole Space would look
like and for any new input that this
model sees where with respect to this
line would it fall so let's say for
example that if I had this new Point
here the point is on this x1x2 space
it's going to be at point1 by 2 and we
can see graphically exactly where on
this plot it Falls with respect to the
line now also we can plug it back into
our equation as well and we can see
exactly you know okay if we plug in one
or excuse me negative one as our input
to
X1 positive two to our input of X2 we
can plug it into the equation on the
bottom left we pass it through the
nonlinearity the nonlinearity here is a
sigmoid function it squashes everything
to be Zer and one depending on which
side of the line it falls on and we get
this Final Answer here in this case the
final answer is
0.2 right this is less than 05 .5 is
going to be the divider because all of
our outputs are going to be separated
between zero and one and we can actually
graphically represent this as well so if
you fall directly on the line your
output after nonlinearity is going to be
05 the more to the blue side that you
fall the farther under 0.5 you are and
the more to the green side you fall the
farther above 0.5 you fall so the line
basically represents the point of
separation between these two sides of
the space And depending on which side of
your input you fall on this is the way
for you to classify this point as either
a positive point or a negative
point so now it's also important to
understand you know we just did this for
a single neuron with two inputs you can
imagine that if you had a model with you
know many more inputs than two it would
no longer be possible to draw this plot
and this is something that we'll have to
deal with in terms of uh understanding
and building intuition but hopefully
even at the small uh scale you can build
some level of intuition even with this
plot let's see how we can now start to
tie some of this together to go beyond
just one neuron and start to build
networks right because this is where we
actually build really powerful systems
it's not just from one neuron but from
Full networks so to do that let's just
revisit our diagram one more time if
there's a few things that you take away
from this class this is hopefully the
slide that you take away from right and
I've said it already a few times I'll
say it one more time how do you pass
information through a neuron you take a
DOT product you apply a bias and you
apply a nonlinearity it's these three
steps and these keep getting repeated
over and over again I will simplify the
diagram since I've now told it to you so
many times hopefully it's starting to
stick now I'm going to remove all of the
weights from this diagram and I'm also
going to remove the bias term so now you
can always assume that those two things
are there I'll just remove them from the
illustration moving forward to keep
things cleaner now Z here Z is going to
be the result of that term it's going to
be the result of the dot product plus
the bias it's going to be before the
nonlinearity G okay so we will then pass
Z through G and that will give us Y and
you can see that represented right
here okay now what if we wanted a
multioutput neural network not one
output but two outputs how would we
change this picture okay actually is
pretty simple we now just create a
second perceptron we now have two
neurons instead of one neuron both
neurons have the exact same inputs but
because their weights are different they
will have two different outputs so they
both take as onep put the same
information they process it their own
way with their own weights and they make
two different outputs from
scratch now these types of NK these
types of layers let me call them a layer
are typically called dense layers
because everything in my inputs is
connected to everything in my outputs
and if you exclude the nonlinearity this
is also a linear layer right this is a
linear layer because it takes all of my
inputs X and just linearly operates them
with my weights W and add a bias which
is also a linear operation so we can now
actually implement this entire operation
from scratch in Python so let's try it
out so we're going to start by just
defining those two weights we Define
self. w this is our weight vector and we
also have self. B which is our bias
scaler this is just one number but here
since it's an entire uh n dimensional
output we'll actually have n uh uh n
neurons in the output as
well when we want to do our forward pass
through
this through this layer how do we do
this it's the same story as before we
take a DOT product which here is this
multiply we add the bias and then we
apply our nonlinearity this is the
sigmoid here but you could change this
to any nonlinearity in P torch you can
actually see that there's almost perfect
analog to on the left and the right side
it's the same story here you create your
your two weights your weight and your
bias you apply a matrix multiply add the
bias and apply your nonlinearity exactly
the same as before now luckily
tensorflow and pytorch have already
implemented this type of dense or linear
layer for us so we don't need to do that
that was just a good learning exercise
we just went through but here you can
just call it right you can see the
function calls on the
bottom now let's take a look at a single
layered neural network a single hidden
layered so not where the output is
directly from a single perceptron but
where we have to actually pass through
two layers okay what does that look like
so this is one where we have the single
layer layer single hidden layer is
placed basically between our output
layer and our input layer why do we call
it hidden well it's just because we
don't directly observe the data that
happens in this layer right input layer
is data that we provide to the model the
output layer is typically things that we
would supervise over the hidden layer is
one that is learned over the course of
uh just observ observable uh
data since we now have a transformation
both from inputs to Hidden and from
hidden to outputs we now have two layers
right and that's also going to mean that
we need two weight matrices W so we'll
actually have a W1 on the left hand side
and a W2 on the right hand
side now if we look at a single unit a
single perceptron a single neuron in
that hidden layer let's take Z2 for
example it's just a perceptron that we
saw before it's the same story nothing C
has changed its answer is computed by
taking a DOT product adding a bias and
passing it through this
nonlinearity if we took a different node
a different neuron let's say like Z3 the
one right below it it would also be
computed with a do product bias
nonlinearity it would take the same
inputs as
Z2 but it would have different weights
so the dot product and the bias would be
different this picture again looks a bit
messy so I'm going to simplify it even
more I'm going to replace all of the
Arrows with the single icon here the
simple uh the symbol which is just going
to denote uh you know this dense layer
this this linear connection layer that
is happening between these two
components and again we can see that to
build a network like this in tensorflow
pytorch these convenience functions are
really starting to uh you know help us a
lot because we don't have to implement a
lot from
scratch now if we wanted to create a
deep neural network how would we do that
what is a deep neural network it is
nothing more than just sequentially
stacking more and more these linear
layers followed by nonlinearities
followed by more linear layers followed
by more nonlinearities over and over and
over again in a hierarchical fashion so
this is just a model where the final
output is created as a hierarchical
combination of going deeper and deeper
into these linear followed by nonlinear
uh
operations yes
please here to give us
exactly yes of course a question was
about maybe just for a quick real world
example of why we would have different
layer so different layers on the depth
axis but also different outputs on the
you know up down axis right so different
layers on the xaxis basically this
corresponds to more depth more
complexity in your network right so for
more complex tasks you would want more
depth because you're introducing more
hierarchical nonlinearity
after one layer if you have a single uh
you know dense connection followed by a
nonlinearity you have a limited amount
of complexity that you can extract is
only coming from one nonlinearity so
it's limited to the expressive capacity
of that single nonlinearity so for as
you get more and more complex tasks you
require deeper and deeper expressive
functions so that's this one axis on the
other axis more outputs this is just a
problem definition so if you wanted to
predict more things then you would need
more outputs a good example is that if
you wanted to do generation right let's
say to generate an image you would need
to generate values for every pixel in
that image that's a lot of outputs right
versus if you want to just predict let's
say uh you know the weather tomorrow
that's a temperature value right it's
just one output it's a number right so
depending on your problem definition
those two things can
change excellent okay so now that we
have
an idea of architecturally what makes up
a neural network I think now it's time
that we can actually start to compose
all of this together and actually in
line with that that example that
question that just came up let's try and
go through an example of applying some
of this Theory into practice and
actually understand you know uh how we
can look to apply a neural network to
solve a very real problem let's say
maybe not that real but maybe real for
all of you that you've been thinking
about it so here's a question that maybe
all of you have been asking yourselves
you know will I pass this class uh and
let's try and build a neural network
that can infer or predict this answer
for all of
you so we're going to do this by
building a very simple model it will
take us input two inputs uh one output
the one output is going to be will I
pass this class yes or no so single
number probability of passing the class
and it will be two inputs defined by
number one how many lectures you attend
over the course of this one week and
number two
the number of hours that you spend on
your final project okay so let's let's
plot because we've taught this class for
many years we actually have data from
past students on this operation we can
look at all of the green points are
people that have passed the class all
the the red points are people that have
not and we can also plot where you are
or you can guess how many hours you're
going to spend on this class how many
hours you're going to spend on the the
final project and what we want to do is
build a neural network that will
determine from all of this past data of
all of these
students where will you fall on this
probability chance of passing versus not
passing so let's do it okay we've we've
actually learned all of this so far in
the class so let's take it step by step
we have two inputs this is this new
person right you have spent four day
four lectures you've attended and you
spent five hours on your final project
those two numbers you can feed in as
input on the left hand side to your
model we also have a single layered
neural network a very basic neural
network where we're just going to start
with this for now and we're going to see
that our hidden layer has three hidden
units and our output will just have one
output which is a binary output yes or
no on passing the class or
not and what we're going to see is
actually that this model got the answer
very wrong it predicted that you would
pass the class with probability 0.1 or
10% when in reality actually you did
very well you you definitely passed the
class so can anyone tell me you know why
you think that this network failed so
badly
here yes exactly exactly yes so the
answer was it's not trained and that's
exactly right so the the model here
hasn't seen any of this data that we
showed on the previous slide right it's
it's basically like a baby that has not
seen any knowledge about the the real
world it doesn't know anything about
this problem as well it needs to First
learn about this problem and this is
something that we haven't talked about
so far in order to train our model our
model has to also understand when it
makes bad predictions what does a bad
prediction mean it means that it has to
be able to quantify how bad a prediction
is versus how good a prediction is this
is called the loss of a neural network a
neural Network's loss is just going to
be uh a measure of how far apart its
predictions are from the ground truth
answers or the ground truth observations
of of a piece of data the closer your or
the smaller your losses it means the
closer these two things are so your
predictions are really matching the
ground truth this results in a small
loss now let's assume that our data is
not just from one student but we
actually have past data from many
students right now we want to Care on
how the model is doing not just for this
one student but aggregate empirically
across the entire past class now this is
what we call is training on not just a
single data point but we train on an
entire data set so when we train neural
networks we want to find neural networks
that minimize our loss or maximize our
accuracy not just on one student but on
the aggregate empirical data set this is
called the empirical loss and it's just
simply the average of my loss for every
data point in my data
set now right now we've been focusing on
this problem of binary classification
yes no answers and for those types of
losses we can use the what's called a
softmax cross entropy loss we'll learn
more about this later but this is
measuring the difference or the distance
between two probability distributions
two binary probability
distributions now let's just suppose
that instead of predicting an output of
uh binary output we want to predict a
final output that is a real number like
a continuous value so let's say like a
grade A percentage grade instead of will
I pass the class or will I not but a
percentage grade of how well I'll do for
doing something like that we won't be
able to use a binary loss anymore so
we'll have to actually change our loss
we can change it for example to a mean
squared error loss so we can take our
two grades predicted grade and true
grade subtract them and then Square them
to create a distance
measure and these are roughly the two
types of losses that you'll see both
categorical discreet losses like binary
losses as well as continuous losses like
MSE losses of course there are so many
other losses that you'll get Expos two
over the class but these two are uh
having very wide coverage in the
field okay let's put all of this
information together and now start uh
talking about the problem of actually
finding our weights of the network right
we've talked about defining the network
we've talked about uh basically
penalizing the network when it gets
something wrong we have not talked about
how to actually improve the network or
train the network so let's talk about
that as in this next part the objective
here what are we trying to do ultimately
at the end of the day throughout this
entire class is that we're trying to
find and build networks or models build
models that minimize the loss on a data
set the loss measures this difference
between predicted and true we want to
minimize we want to find a network that
minimizes the loss on a data set this
means mathematically right walking
through this equation it means that we
want to find the W's we want to find the
weights that will result in the minimum
L the loss over the entire data set from
1 to
n now remember that W weights is this is
just going to be a collection of all of
the weights in our entire model so it's
the weights from every single layer in
our Network we're just going to combine
those into all of One Piece and those
are the weights that we're going to try
and optimize over now how do we do this
optimization procedure well remember
that our loss function is just a
function of our weights given a set of
Weights our loss function will return a
single value it is how how far apart our
predicted answers are from our true
answers if we only had two weights in
our Network then we would be able to
plot our lost landscape like a picture
like this we would be able to plot it in
a grid of data over weights one and
weights two and for every configuration
of my weights a be able to see how much
error or how much loss that
configuration of Weights is
obtaining now what we want to do is
basically find the lowest point on this
landscape we want to find which weights
one and weights two correspond and give
us the smallest loss so how can we do
this well we can start at some random
point we pick a random point in our
landscape any point and we start from
this point and what we'll do is we will
compute What's called the gradient the
gradient will tell us which way is up
from this point right it's a local
measure it only tells us locally from
where I stand right here which way is up
and what I'll do is I will take a small
step in the opposite direction right and
I'll take a small step going down that
loss and then I will repeat this process
over and over and over again until I
finally get to the bottom of the Mount
of the hill right and I converge at
what's called a local
minimum we you can summarize this this
algorithm this
procedure as uh as what's known as
gradient descent in pseudo code right so
let's go through it again one more time
very briefly we start by randomly
initializing our weights this means that
we randomly pick a place in our
landscape we compute the
gradient here called DJ DW this is how
much a small change in our weights
changes our loss right so this tells us
the direction that we should change our
weights in order to increase our loss we
take a small step in the opposite
direction so here you can see that
actually we take that gradient we we
multiply by negative one we go in the
opposite direction of that direction and
then we multiply it by a small uh step
let's call it Ada Ada here is going to
be a step size of how much in that
direction we actually move and then we
repeat this in a loop over and over
again in tensor flow right you can see
this exactly represented the same way
but here I want to draw your attention
to this term right this is the direction
term it tells us the gradient the
gradient is going to tell us how or
which direction is going up or which
direction is going down if you take the
negative of it but I never actually told
you how to compute this right I just
told you that we need to compute this
right um the process of computing the
gradient in a neural network is called
back propagation so I think it would be
helpful also we can take a quick you
know
stepbystep example walking us through
how back propagation works and how you
would compute this gradient for a
particular neural network and we'll
start just for demonstration we'll start
with the simplest neural network that
that exists it it consists of one input
one output and one hidden neuron in the
middle right so you cannot get a simpler
Network than this and we want to compute
the gradient of our loss L at the end or
excuse me here is J at the end with
respect to let's start with with respect
to W2 okay so how much does a small
change in W2 affect our
loss so we can write out this derivative
right we can write it out in math and we
can use the chain rule to actually
decompose it now why would we want to
decompose it well first of all we
decompose this this uh gradient DJ dw2
into two terms DJ a Dy and Dy dw2 this
is just a basic extension of the chain
rule nothing magic here but why is this
possible it is possible because Y is
dependent only on the previous layer
okay now let's suppose now that we
wanted to compute the gradients of this
weight before W2 let's say W1 here what
we can do is just replace W2 in this
equation with W1 and then again we have
to apply the chain rule yet again right
because Computing this last term here is
not well defined so we have to actually
expand it one more time this is why we
call it propagation back propagation
because you actually have to start from
the output and keep Computing these
iterative chain rules back and back over
the course of your network step by
step and we repeat this process of you
know propagating those gradients all the
way from output to input across our
weights and at the end of this whole
process what we're left with is for
every single weight in our Network we
have this direction of basically saying
okay if we increase this weight a little
bit will our loss go up or down now if
our loss was to go down that means that
we should increase that weight just a
little bit right or we would go in the
opposite
direction and that's the back
propagation algorithm right in theory
it's it's nothing more than an an
application of the chain rule from
differential calculus but but in
practice you know it can get very messy
and very hairy it's a very computational
me measure to do because you have to do
this you know step by step for every
single we in your in your model uh so in
practice today's deep learning
Frameworks like tensorflow pytorch they
do this automatically so you don't
necessarily need to implement this
yourself but it's important to
understand you know the the the pra the
theoretical side of you know how these
things are operating and and what it's
doing underneath the hood I want to also
like use that as an opportunity to
discuss with you some of the Practical
implications of training neural networks
uh in in reality right and I showed you
this previous picture of like a very
pretty lost landscape that was very
smooth but in practice optimizing neural
networks is extremely difficult and this
is actually a picture of you know neural
networks are extremely high-dimensional
search spaces so we don't actually know
what this picture looks like but this is
a projection of the Lost landscape of a
of deep neural network uh from a paper
that came out several years ago about in
2017 and you can actually visualize now
you know how messy some of these loss
Landscapes look that applying these
types of back propagation and
optimization techniques is very very
challenging and I want you to also
recall you know before we took that dive
into back propagation and the gradient
term in particular we started to talk
about uh you know this this equation
that you see here right so how would we
update the weights we update them by by
taking an opposite step in a
small uh small increment in that
direction that we want to right now this
is the key term I want to focus on now
this small step this is called The
Learning rate of our model this D this
basically dictates how quickly we take
those steps and how quickly we listen to
our to our gradients as we're Computing
back propagation and in practice setting
the learning rate can be very very
difficult if we set the learning rate
too slow then we basically start from
point but we get stuck in some of these
uh local minimum but they may not be the
best minimums that we could get to right
if we set it too large then we get some
unstable Behavior where we basically
overshoot we we start to step in the
right direction but we step too far and
then we explode out of the out of the
stable place of of learning ideally we
want to set learning rates that are you
know not too small so that they can skip
some of the local Minima but also not
too big that they also diverge and they
can so
converge so how do we actually set the
learning rate one option and actually a
very common option is to uh you know
just try a bunch of learning rates see
what works best how can you do better
than this well the idea is uh can you
design adaptive algorithms that
depending on how they are uh optimizing
in the search space can you adapt the
learning rate can you change the
learning rate as a function of your
landscape itself and this basically
means that your learning rate
practically speaking your learning rate
will increase or decrease as a function
of your gradients and a function of your
data uh how fast you're learning right
how how how steep the uh landscape is
how how you all of these different
things can basically dictate all of
these adaptive properties of a learning
rate and in fact these have been very
widely studied and many different types
of adaptive learning rate schedulers
have been created here you can see some
examples adom so all of these start with
like a lot a lot of them start with this
Ada for adaptive right these are
different variations of these adaptive
properties uh atom in particular is one
extremely well used uh type of
optimization procedure that you'll be
using throughout many of your Labs but I
encourage you to really try out and and
experiment with all of these different
types of learning rate schedulers to see
what works best in many times there will
be different types of learning rate
schedulers that work for different types
of problems so you should definitely try
out the different pieces and trying them
out is is as easy as in oftentimes just
a single line change right change to
your uh learning Loop will just
Implement different schedulers so SGD
stochastic gradient descent is just
going to be that that base gradient
descent algorithm that we had seen
before and I actually want to dig into
that a little bit more because what you
saw or what I presented was actually the
gradient descent algorithm not the
stochastic gradient descent algorithm so
I want to tell you a little bit about
you know what's the difference between
those two pieces with those two types of
algorithms to understand that we have to
first revisit one more time the gradient
descent algorithm so the gradient here
this is that that piece that we computed
with back propagation this is very
computational because if you look at it
it's computed as a summation or an
average I should say over all of my data
points in my data set so I compute the
the gradient for not just one data point
but all of my data points in my data set
that's why it's very expensive now in
most real life problems it is not really
feasible to compute your gradient over
your entire data set on every single
iteration of this step because remember
we don't compute the gradient just once
we compute it at every point along this
optimization procedure and you're
optimizing your your network for
millions or even more steps and you
don't want to be looping through your
entire data set on every single one of
those steps so let's define a new type
of gradient descent now we'll call it
stochastic gradient descent like you saw
before instead of computing the gradient
over my entire data set I'm going to
compute a very noisy gradient it's going
to be a gradient computed just over one
data point in my data set so I'm going
to randomly pick a data point and I'm
going to compute the gradient with
respect to that one data point not my
entire data set this is going to be way
noisier here obviously because that one
data point is not going to be
representative of my entire data set but
it'll give me an answer way quicker so I
can get through more
steps now there's also a uh you know
there's a natural trade-off here right
we want to go fast but we also don't
want to be too noisy there obviously is
a middle ground here right instead of
computing the noisy gradient on one
example we can do what's called mini
batched gradient descent right mini
batched gradient descent is where you
set a batch size
and then on every iteration you compute
your gradient with respect to not just
one data point but let's say k data
points where K is pretty small think of
something like 32 or 128 something on
that scale you look at your gradient
with respect to those let's say 32 data
points and then you average that
gradient it helps you get a bit more
reliability and robustness in your
measure but then you also get the speed
right you're not going over your entire
data set 32 is usually way way smaller
than your entire data
set okay so now what does this mean this
means that we now have this increase in
gradient accuracy compared to stochastic
gradient descent so we can we can
converge much more smoothly we're not
super noisy going after one data point
one at a time but it also means that we
can be much more uh quick than compared
to uh full gradient descent where we go
over the entire data set at a whole this
means that you know because we're more
stable on the one side we can also
increase our learning rate these two
things are extremely connected right the
relationship between your gradients and
your learning rates should be one that
you have a very good intuition about
because your gradients are now more
stable you're averaging over a mini
batch not just a single sample you can
now start to uh take bigger steps right
you can trust the gradient a bit more
over over the course of
optimization it also allows you to
really parallelize training because if
you wanted to compute your gradient over
32 data points you can parallelize that
off of 32 processes on your GPU right
you compute them in parallel as opposed
to one at a time this allows you to
really start to utilize GPU speedups
even
further now the last topic I'll touch on
before we uh we take a short break for
lecture two is going to be this topic of
overfitting and regularization of neural
networks and this is a huge problem not
just in deep learning but we want to
cover it because it's one that you're
going to get exposure with in today's
lab especially is basically it's one of
the most fundamental topics of all of
machine learning as a whole ideally in
machine learning we want to build models
that don't just work well on a training
set right we do train our models on
training sets but we don't want them to
work well only on our training set
actually what we really want is we we
actually don't really often times care
about how well it works in practice on
our training side at all we use use that
as a proxy because what we really care
about is how well the model works on
brand new data when we deploy it into
the wild and there it's not our training
data at all it's brand new test data and
the relationship between these two
things is extremely important we use the
training data as a proxy But ultimately
we don't really really care about it all
that much another way to say this is
that when we build models we want to
learn representations from our training
data but we still want them to
generalize to unseen test data as well
now take this picture for example assume
you want to build a line that describes
the relationship between the X and the Y
points on this
picture you know on the left hand side
you can see that you have a very simple
Model A linear model it can describe the
training points and it probably will
also describe the the test points to
some decent faithfulness but it's not
fully capturing the richness and the
complexity of our data set both in the
training set and the test set so we're
not utilizing the full expressive
capacity of the model on the on the left
hand side move over all the way to the
right hand side you can actually see
that we're starting to memorize data
points in the training side so much so
that we're hurting our performance for
brand new test data because we're we're
waiting too much on what we've seen
during training basically what you
always want is to end up in the middle
you want to leverage your training
points but not rely on them too much or
memorize
them
now
yes example for problem of
overfitting oh sorry say any real
example of the problem which we face in
the overfitting yes of course so a real
life example of overfitting would be
let's say if you have a very small data
set but a very large Network you'll
you'll learn a model that just memorizes
uh all of the data in your data set and
it will be it's it's not like it's doing
something bad because uh it has the
power to memorize everything in the
training set remember always that models
don't see test set it's unseen data so
all they can see is your training set
what you give it to them so if you give
them a very small training set and a
very big model the model will do what
it's supposed to do and learn exactly
the training set to the full capacity
right but then when you show it more
test data it's not going to be very
faithful to the training data because
it's not going to be perfectly from the
same
distribution
okay yep
maybe well I think with this s of
example the idea is to
I see I see yeah so the stochasticity is
coming purely from the selection
operator so maybe it's a confusion so
when so what is why do we call it
stochastic gradi say it's because of the
selection process we don't do this over
the entire data set but we
stochastically select a subset of data
and that selection is
stochastic yeah makes sense
no no no so so you take the stochastic
selection and then with that stochastic
selection of data the gradient is is I
mean it can be unbounded right so you
you you grab or you compute the gradient
with respect to those data points
whatever they may be but your
stochasticity is coming from the
selection part not from the gradient
computation yes
way
of what you and then
maybe
com exactly so basically the the
question is about is there a way is
there a more adaptive way almost of
doing selection as opposed to being
truly stochastic and the answer is yes
definitely so truly stochastic uh uh you
know seeing of data is is actually not
very realistic either right even though
this is the way that is is the
convention right we as humans do not
operate right like this right we don't
just randomly see data we see data
sequentially over time and we see data
with with meaning and with purpose
actually in tomorrow's lecture you'll
see an example of how we do this type of
adaptive selection process and and the
benefits of this as well great
question okay so I'll just very briefly
wrap up with regularization so
regularization is just a technique that
allows you to discourage these complex
memorization protocol so if you have a
very small data set big model you want
to discourage the model from just
memorizing that data set so how can you
discourage the model from from those
types of things to to be learned and you
know as we've seen this is really
critical for the the overall performance
of them all because we don't care about
the training results we care about the
test results ultimately the most popular
regularization technique is actually a
very simple idea you'll use this in
almost all of your Labs as part of this
course it's the idea of Dropout so what
is Dropout let's revisit this picture of
a deep neural network in Dropout all we
do is that during training we're going
to randomly set some activations of our
hidden neurons to zero with some
probability so let's say we set drop out
to 50% what we're going to do is say 50%
of our neurons we're going to drop out
the activations or set their activations
to zero which forces the network to not
rely so much on the outputs of any one
neuron right the inputs at the next
layer after a neuron gets dropped it
cannot rely it cannot memorize so much
about the previous inputs because there
are some more stochasticity being
implemented into this forward pass of
the model not just in the data set
curation where this data set selection
but also in just the pure forward pass
even if I pick the same data twice and I
put it through the model twice the exact
same data because of Dropout you also
have another level of stochasticity that
means the model can't even remember the
same exact data twice right this is an
extremely powerful idea because
basically all it's doing is it's
lowering the capacity of the model it's
lowering the ability or it's
discouraging the ability for the model
to learn a singular pathway through the
model it's forcing the model to learn
these multiple Pathways to make a single
decision and basically on every single
iteration we just repeat this process
every time it sees a new piece of data
or every we do a forward pass it always
creates a random pathway for this data
to pass through the model another final
technique that I'll show you is about
this notion of early stopping early
stopping basically just means that we
monitor the deviation between our
training loss and our test loss so we
can have a test we can have a proxy of a
test loss by having a a hell do set
maybe it's not a true test loss but it's
again another proxy that we do not train
on and what we can do is we can
basically monitor how well the model is
doing on both the training set and our
heldout let's call it a validation
set in the beginning both of these lines
as we train they both start to go down
which is excellent it makes sense right
this is because the model is learning
right it's getting stronger over the
course of training and eventually what
you'll see is that the model starts to
Plateau its loss and on the test it
starts to increase so the training
accuracy should if the model has enough
capacity the training accuracy should
always excuse me the training loss
should always go down should always be
getting better and better on the
training set but at some point you will
see that the test loss starts to
memorize data it starts to memorize data
in the training loss which results in
the test loss to go up a little bit now
this pattern continues for the rest of
training and here's the point that you
should really focus on right this is the
point where that if you plotted this
curve you would save your model at each
of these stages but you would only take
the checkpoint you would take the model
that happens at this point because this
is the even though the training loss
even got better after this point you on
if you look at your training set you
actually look like you have a better
model but on the test set you can see
that it's actually started to memorize
pieces of the training set so you do not
take the models on the far right you
actually take these models in the middle
yes
training iterations and every training
iteration not every iteration because
maybe it adds unnecessary compute but
what people typically do is you know
let's say once every so many iterations
you will do a testing run and again you
don't need to do a testing run over your
entire test set you could do it
stochastically as well in a batch right
so let's say you could you could do
let's say every thousand iterations you
do a batch of let's say only 100 data
points in your test set just to get a
approximate
uh no so the drop nodes will not have
gradients because we don't have uh
information that of what's happening
with them but for all of the other nodes
we'll get a we'll get an update y
exactly
yes for this to
work it should be separate yeah so this
is a key assumption is that ideally you
take your training data and what people
can do is basically cut your training
data in a ratio right so let's say you
take 70% of your training data and you
actually use it for training you take
the other 30% of your training data and
use it for testing and inal validation
right okay last question feel a
difference in loss between the testing
and training data
sets great question um I mean I there's
no ideal right ideally actually there
would be no difference right um in
practice though so there are situations
actually where there are very little
difference Let me Give an example is
assume your training set is is also so
massive that it's impossible for your
model to learn the the full cap it's
impossible for the model to memorize
then actually you will see basically
training and testing is very close to
each other a good example of this is
language modeling even massive language
models they still have trouble
memorizing the entire data set just
because language is such a massive data
set right uh so even there basically
you'll see training and testing curves
look very very similar but then that's
why we have to actually do other typs of
validation language models don't really
have the classical overfitting problems
that you know other types of deep
learning models have they have other
problems which we'll talk
about yeah
okay awesome okay I'll conclude now just
by summarizing the three points that we
talked about in this lecture before we
jump into lecture number two uh so first
we talked about you know building neural
networks the architectures of neural
networks we talked about the base
operation the base architecture is
called a perceptron a single neuron we
learned about how we could stack those
single neurons together to form complex
hierarchical networks and how we can
mathematically optimize those networks
using data and finally we addressed a
lot of the Practical implications
everything from you know batch gradient
descent to overfitting and
regularization and optimization of these
models in the next lecture we're going
to hear from Ava on deep sequence
modeling which is the backbone of large
language models uh and this is a really
exciting type of lecture so hopefully
everyone enjoys it and I think probably
what we'll do is just take a five minute
break just so AA and I can switch
laptops and then we will continue with
the lecture and then after the lecture
we have software Labs followed by
reception at link and food okay thanks
everyone