So hello everyone, welcome to lecture 7.
Um I also wanted to go over some
clarifications from last time. So when I
gave lecture last time, there were two
ed posts that I think were good that you
all might want to check out. Uh but in
case you haven't seen it, I'll just go
through it really quickly. I think when
describing dropout, how to scale
probabilities at test time. During
lecture, there was a bit of confusion.
Um and basically the what I said in the
slide had a sort of mismatch. So um in
each forward pass for dropout we have
this hyperparameter P which is either
the amount of neurons you're dropping
out or it's the amount of neurons that
you're keeping depending on which
implementation of dropout you're using.
Generally they do it's the number of
ones you drop out. Um so in most
libraries that's what P means. But the
basic idea is that at test time you want
the expected output to be the same as at
training time. So this means that if you
dropped 25% of your activations during
training time at test time you would
scale by 75 so that the expected output
is the same. Um and so I think there was
a bit of confusion because in this slide
the implementation uses P as the
probability of uh keeping a unit active.
So uh there's a bit of a mismatch there.
Just to clarify, there was also a
question in class from last time about
how normalization can be useful and
maybe resolve the issues that arise when
you have weights that are initialized
incorrectly. But we had this to choice
setting where we have 2D inputs to our
model and a two-layer neural network
with RLU. Um it's outputting basically
this quadrant function. So if the point
lies in the top right, it'll output one
or two or three or four depending on
which quadrant uh the point lies in. And
uh we plot the different training losses
and test losses for uh good
initialization using the kiming
initialization we discussed last time
and bad initialization where the
standard deviation is too high. And the
blue plot here represents bad and the
green represents bad initialization with
layer norm. So you can see it actually
does resolve a lot of the issues but to
get the best performance you still need
good weight initialization which are the
two lines afterwards. So you can go dive
in and also whether or not layerm helped
depends uh depends on the problem. So in
this quadrant one you can imagine that
you don't need to know the exact 2D
position uh of each point. So layerm was
actually helping but for some of the
other functions that are in the code you
can check out um where you need to know
the exact coordinate in order to get the
right output layer actually hurts
performance uh because you lose some
information about the exact spatial
location of your input when you're doing
this subtraction of the mean and
dividing by the standard deviation. So
uh just some notes here um basically at
a high level it does help with the issue
but gap remains. So you can't get by
this weight initialization issue with
just normalization.
Um and as I mentioned it may not always
make sense depending on what you're
trying to model. Um so I think just to
recap also from last time we've been
mainly talking about these sort of
vanilla standard non-recurrent neural
networks so far. So this is a fixed size
input and a fixed size output. Um you
have sort of this onetime setup where
you set your activation functions. You
do data pre-processing according to some
fixed mean and standard deviation for
the images uh the image channels. You
have your weight initialization uh and
normalization functions that you use as
well as um transfer learning. So if you
pre-train on one data set like imageet
or some other large scale internet data
set, you can get better results if you
initialize your weights to those values.
We also talked about training dynamics,
how you can babysit the learning process
and choosing a good learning rate, how
you want to update your different uh
hyperparameters and also how to optimize
those based on the validation
performance as well as uh test time
augmentation to improve performance
further. So, a really good tool for
points two and three here is uh
something I use in basically all my
projects called weights and biases. So,
you might find this useful. It's a
really neat way that you can um
essentially look at different you set
different runs with different
hyperparameters. In this case, uh they
show a dropout column here. So, these
are all the different values of dropout.
Then color coding is really nice. So,
you can see that generally the lower
values of dropout will achieve higher
accuracy. And so you can visualize uh
these different uh validation uh sorry
these different hyperparameters based on
validation step performance and uh you
can sort of uh see you know based on
many runs get an idea of which
hyperparameters work best. So I always
use this I think it's great especially
if you have the compute where you can
just run something over and over again
to improve performance more. This is a
really neat way of visualizing it. I
think they do it well. There are other
tools like tensorboard uh but this is
personally the one that I like.
Okay. Um, so for the rest of lecture
today, we'll be discussing sequence
modeling. So this is in contrast to a
fixed-sized input uh as as input to our
model. What if we have a sequence of
variable length and also we'll be
discussing what are the sort of simple
neural networks that people use before
the era of transformers which mainly
consist of RNN's and some variants of
RNN's. And then I'll also relate in one
slide how RNN's actually are similar to
a lot of and inspire a lot of the modern
uh type of language models that you see
called state space models. So you might
have heard of mamba there's some other
ones too that we'll talk about in the
slide but the basic ideas the key
concepts from RNNs are still being used
today. They're not just used in the past
and they have a lot of nice advantages
over transformers that we'll go into.
Cool. So to specifically formulate this
sequence modeling task, you can imagine
we have a vanilla neural network where
we have one fixed size input to one
fixed size output which is what we've
discussed in the course so far. In
contrast, you could have a one to many
uh sequence modeling task. So here we
still have a fixed size input like say
an image but we want to output a
sequence of variable length. So one
common example is image captioning. So
we input an image and we want to output
a sequence of words or characters or
however you're modeling uh the language
or encoding it but the goal is to have a
variable length caption output for
what's happening in the image. You could
also have a many to one sequence
modeling task. So here we could imagine
our inputs are say a video and we're
trying to classify what is this a video
of. So we give it a sequence of video
frames and the output is one single
class label similar to the image
classification case but now we have
multiple frames as input rather than
just a single image. So this is an
example of many to one. Then you also
have many to many. So um the number of
inputs and outputs in the sequences
don't need to match. So you could have
your input is a variable number of
frames and your output in this case
could be a caption of variable length
and they don't need to necessarily
match. Um but they could match. So you
could have so for every single input you
have one output. And for discussing
RNN's we'll mainly be focusing on this
setting on the far right but there are
basically a lot of small changes you can
make to change and reformulate the
problem to apply to the other settings.
But this is sort of the most
straightforward one. Every time there's
an input there's an output. and we'll be
using it for the beginning of class to
talk about how RNN's work
and a canonical example problem here
would be video classification where
you're classifying every single frame.
Okay, so what is an RNN? Uh the basic
idea is you have an input sequence X and
an output sequence Y. And what makes an
RNN an RNN is this recurrent nature. So
often people will diagram it by this
sort of arrow that's feeding back into
the block. uh this is how you know it's
sort of like a recurrent layer when
you're reading different diagrams. But
what it actually means is that RNN's
have this internal state or a hidden
state as it's often called that is
updated as a sequence is processed. So
every time there's a new input to the
model, we process that and we calculate
a new hidden state or internal state. So
there's a hidden state, it updates and
it depends on the new inputs as well as
the previous internal or hidden state.
Um I think this diagram is sometimes a
bit confusing when you're trying to
think about how the gradients are
actually calculated and what are the
order of operations. So people will
often do this uh diagram of an unrolled
RNN. And so here it's basically the same
as before but we're explicitly showing
that the current hidden state
calculation is dependent on our input at
that time step as well as the previous
uh RNN state. So we're more explicitly
modeling what is exactly needed to
calculate each output and each RNN. You
move backwards uh in the computational
graph.
So I've been speaking with words so far.
So let's formulate this with
mathematical equations. Now so the basic
idea is we're trying to uh process the
sequence of vectors X and we're applying
this recurrence formula at every single
time step. So we have our new hidden
state as a function of the old hidden
state and the input vector at some time
step as well as we have a function with
normally with an activation function
along with some parameters w. So you can
think of this as it's very similar to
the sort of initial neural network
layers we were learning where it's a
weight matrix uh multiply by and then
you follow it up by an activation
function. This is the same thing here.
The only change is that it's now a
recurrence formula. So we're using um
the same set of W's and the same um uh
activation function each time we're
computing the hidden state.
So um basically yeah as I mentioned this
is a recurrence formula. Um and to get
the actual output so how do we calculate
this blue block? we have a separate uh
function that depends on a separate set
of uh parameters that convert our hidden
dimension state into uh the dimension of
our output and it also is a set of
weights to convert the hidden state to
the output. So this does two in one. It
sort of changes the dimension of our
vectors from the dimension size of our
hidden state which can be whatever we
want to the dimension size of our output
and then also it provides a
transformation there. So, why is a
weight matrix that you will multiply by
your hidden state to get the so it does
two things. It converts your hidden
state to the dimension of your output.
So, your hidden state and output could
be different dimensions. And then also
it's uh you know it's a weight matrix
that you learn. So, not only does it do
this dimension change, but also it
applies a transformation to your hidden
state. So, it's how you convert your
hidden states to your outputs. What WHY
is. So the previous slide was how we
calculate the new hidden state. So
there's it's essentially the same idea
where you're doing this uh recursively
with the same set of parameters but we
have one set of parameters and one
function for calculating the hidden
state. We have another set of parameters
and another function for calculating the
output depending on what type of task it
is and how we want to model the RNN.
Yeah. So they still share the same
weights for each time step. Um but
there's two different things here. One
is to calculate basically how do you
maybe it'll be more clear as we go
through more concrete examples but uh
how do you actually calculate the new
hidden state which is this internal
state of the RNN and then how do you
convert that hidden state to the output
which is this slide.
Okay. Um so looking through this
unrolled uh diagram here um we can see
that you sort of need to initialize your
hidden state to some value. So we
usually call we call this H0 and you can
initialize it to whatever you want. In
principle usually this is a learned um
input vector. Um but now we'll
specifically go into each step of this
unrolled uh recurrent RNN and actually
go through a concrete example for what
it looks like when you're doing the
forward pass.
So um one thing to note that already
came up with some of the questions is
that um we're processing the sequence of
vectors x and we're applying this
recurrence formula at each time step. So
uh really do notice how the same
function and the same set of parameters
are used at every time step when
computing the hidden state and a
separate function and a separate set of
parameters are always used at each time
step when predicting the output from the
hidden state. Yes. So can old values of
y affect the new hidden state? uh under
some formulations. Yes. And we'll
actually go through one example of why
that's used. It's most commonly used if
you want to predict the next uh like if
you're doing a language modeling or auto
reggressive modeling task where you're
trying to predict one value given the
previous values. Uh people will just use
the previous values as the input. Uh so
that's generally how people do that
explicit uh formulation of how can y
affect the next hidden state. What is
the difference between h and x at the
first time step? Um so they use
basically different uh weights. So so
the H0 is using uh all of it's using the
weights that are used to update every
hidden state to the next one. Whereas
the we'll go through exactly what the
weights look like but u basically
they're using different weights is the
short answer. Um okay so when people say
vanilla RNN they usually are almost
exactly referring to this type of model
where um we have our hidden state t
which is uh uses tan h or hyperbolic
tangent as an activation function. This
is nice because it's bounded between one
and negative 1. Um so as you do the
operation over and over again your
values will stay within this range. Um
so this is a nice property to have. It's
also zero centered and you can represent
both positive and negative values. This
is why people use 10h. Um uh al also we
um sometimes have an output function fy
here but in the simplest case your
output yt could just be a matrix
multiply by your by your hidden state.
So this is really like the most simple
formulation of of an RNN. And what we'll
specifically go in our concrete example
today and lecture is this idea of just
manly manually creating a recurrent
neural network. So, we're not going to
learn this through gradient descent or
all these different methods. I'm just
going to sort of uh show you how you
could construct one by hand and we'll go
through it and you'll understand the
forward pass, what each of the different
weight matrices are doing as well as how
the output is calculated.
So, in this really toy example, because
it needs to be pretty simple if we're
just going to be like going through all
the different weights, uh you're given a
sequences of zeros and ones. Um, and
your goal is to output a one when
there's two repeated ones in a row. So
you're basically detecting repeated
ones. Uh, and you'll output a zero
otherwise. So you can see this input
sequence coming in 0 1 0 1. Uh, so far
there's been no repeated ones. But now
we have a repeated one. Then we have
another repeated one because there's two
in a row here and so on. So this is the
type of model we're building. It's
trying to do this task. This is
specifically the many to many sequence
modeling task where we have one output
for every input.
And so um we've kind of been talking
high level so far, but if you're trying
to create an RNN to do this, what
information should be captured in the
hidden state? So you have this internal
state of your model, what information
needs to be captured there in order to
do this task?
Yeah. So the input to the previous time
step and if our output is only dependent
on the hidden state, what else do we
need to know? And the current Yeah.
Yeah. Exactly. Um so this is the
information that we need to capture in
our hidden state. So um previous input
and the current value for x. So 0 or
one. And the way I'll do this is I'll
just set the hidden state t to be a
threedimensional vector. The reason why
it's three is this one will come in
handy when we're trying to do the uh
output stage calculation, but you could
probably construct one without a one
here. Um this is just to make the math
easy and simple for the for the purposes
of the lecture today. And the other
information is the current value. So
this will either be zero or one along
with the previous value 0 or one. and
we'll initialize it to be 001. So that
um we're basically assuming it's
basically seen two zeros in a row before
at this point. Um yeah, so this is how
we will do this will be the uh type of
variables we're trying to track in our
hidden state and this is how we'll
initialize h0. So I talked about how you
can initialize it to vary different
strategies or you could learn it. This
is what we'll initialize it to. Okay,
now let's walk by the co let's walk
through the code and I'll do it step by
step. So, I'm just putting it on screen
here right now. But we'll also do ReLU.
Um, I guess sorry, one one other thing I
missed on this slide is that we're
setting our activation functions to be
RLU just to make the math easy. So,
it'll just be max of zero or whatever
the value is. We're only dealing
essentially with zeros and ones in this
case. So, it makes it pretty simple to
think about. Yeah, you probably could
construct it so that it works with tan
h, but this is just something that I
created as an example for how to run it.
And so just to make the math really
easy, we'll just do RLU. Um but yeah,
you could conceivably make a model that
could do this with tanh. Um yeah,
cool. Um so we have RLU. We have two
specific weights here. We have the first
weight which um converts our uh previous
hidden state. Uh it it applies a
transformation to the previous hidden
state onto the sort of to calculate the
next one. And then we have this weight
here which um converts our input x to
the dimension of our hidden state as
well as applies a transformation. So we
are setting this second one. So our our
our current hidden state is a function
of the previous hidden state as long
along with the current time step. And so
when we're trying to calculate this uh
hidden state at time step t, we're
looking to calculate this current value
first. So we'll use the x value here.
We'll set the weight to be a 3x one
column vector um with values 1 0 0 such
that when x is zero and we do the matrix
multiply we get 0 vector and when x is 1
we'll get 1 0 0 and we'll add this to
another term but basically this is going
to be calculating what is the current
value here. So it'll be either uh zero
on top or a one on top and it's
calculated based on this first operation
here.
Okay. Um, so that's how we're
calculating the current value based on
the uh input. Now we'll talk about uh
you know how are we doing this hidden
state transformation. So we want to just
use the current value for this top value
here. So in our weight matrix we'll just
have zeros in the top row. This means
that when we multiply it with the
previous hidden state we'll get a zero
value here for the top. So it'll be 0
plus whatever value the right hand side
contains. So that's how we're going to
maintain this not changing based on the
previous hidden state. And we'll set it
to be 1 0 0 for the next row. Why we do
this is you can imagine we have the
hidden state from the previous time step
here. And we want to set the uh now
previous to be the former current time
step. So we have a 1 0 0. What this will
do is it'll multiply by htus one. We'll
set the current value over to now the
previous value for this time uh step. So
basically this term will be a zero on
top and it will be whatever the previous
time step uh input value was as the
second term and then this final bit here
just maintains the one so that we're
keeping this one across all
calculations. Um so just to recap we
have zeros here because we want the
right hand side term to be tracking this
uh current value. We have a one here to
copy over the current from the former
time step to be the previous uh sorry
the the to to copy the current of the
former time step to be the previous of
the current time step. Uh so we're just
doing you know h uh maybe it's easy in
the code but uh you know ht previous is
equal to ht then we want to also move
the corresponding value down one here
and then this is just a copy of the one.
Um so how do we actually get our output
now? So we tal we basically talked about
how we can track these values given the
weight matrices I talked about. So whhh
and w xh. So if we have a weight matrix
to convert our hidden state into the
output dimension we want it to be uh
1x3. So it's uh single value that's
being output when we have this hidden
dimension as input. And this is sort of
like a dotproduct between the values
here and the values here. So what this
will correspond to is the current plus
the previous minus1 minus one because we
multiply the minus1 here. This is where
the one became useful and uh the current
associated here with a one and then also
the the previous associated here with a
one as well. Um so that's how we
actually do it. And if you if you think
about it um this general formula will
work. So uh if we have say we're looking
here we have the current plus the
previous is 2 minus one is one for this
uh left hand term inside the ru so the
max of one and 0 is one and if these are
both zero you'll have a minus one so
we'll get zero these are a one and a
zero then you'll still get zero so these
are how you can construct these weight
matrices but I actually wanted to pause
briefly um and talk about if there were
any questions about any step among this
calculation
because this is the only example we'll
go through in class where we're
literally doing all the matrix and
vector multiplications and the rest will
be more highle explanations for how
people tend to put these layers
together. So I just want to pause and
see if there's a question about how the
matri matrices and vectors are tracked
and multiplied and updated.
Yeah, so the question is how do you go
about constructing the weight matrices
which is a really great question uh and
I thought to put it in the slide here.
So, how how would you actually do this?
Um, it's the same way we're always
finding the weight matrices in this
class. We're going to be using gradient
descent and we'll talk about how you do
gradient descent descent when you have
multiple time steps and maybe you have
losses computed at each time step as
well. So, that'll be a lot of what we go
into right next. So, it's a great
question and very relevant to the
lecture. So, this is um just an example
so you can see how all of the weight
matrices are multiplied. Um the
basically if you were trying to change
if you're trying to initialize with this
and then train it to do another task um
that would be sort of like transfer
learning where you're initializing the
weights with this. Um but in practice I
don't think it would work very well at
all because your hidden state is really
small and people normally do much larger
hidden states. I just wanted to do
something that I could fit in the slide
here. Yeah. Okay. I'll go over the
second row again. Um so if you imagine
we have ht minus one as a column vector
here when you do the matrix multiply um
to get the value of the left hand side
here what this second row is doing is
you're taking the value and you're sort
of you know rotating it and doing the
dot productduct with the values here. So
for the second row that gets calculated
it will be the entry here will be equal
to the top of the the vector here. So
this is how we move the current down to
the previous is in this step here. So
the the end result of this matrix
multiply will be that such that the
second uh value is the uh is the current
value from t minus one.
So we do the matrix multiply with t
minus one here. And so the second row of
this operation and this operation are
both giving us vectors of the size of
our hidden state. And so we're adding
them together. Yeah, the left is doing
the previous carryover and the right is
doing the current. And that's also sort
of how it works for RNN's when you are
doing it beyond this sort of toy example
where this weight matrix is being
multiplied by the current input and this
other weight matrix is being multiplied
by the the previous hidden state. So um
that's what these weight matrices track
more generally than this specific
problem as well.
Okay. Um so how do you actually compute
the gradients? Uh let's look at the
computational graph. So uh just to draw
it a little bit more explicitly than
before. Um we have these x1 coming in
and then x2 and we have a sequence of
x's. We're calculating a hidden state at
each time step. And we're specifically
using the same w's uh same weight
matrices for each of these calculations
as well. So we need to be thinking about
this when we're thinking about how we're
computing the gradients.
And let's start with the many to many
scenario. So we have an output for each
input. And um in this scenario you can
often also calculate a loss for each
output which is how correct is the
output at that stage. So if we're doing
this uh setting you have a loss at each
uh step and you can sum them all
together to get your total loss and this
would be your loss across the entire
input sequence.
And um when we do back prop basically
the final loss is the loss uh you know
this final loss when we comput our final
loss we can then calculate the loss per
time step as well um or depending on the
formulation. So if we're calculating a
loss per time step you can treat them
independently. Um sometimes you have an
overall loss based on the loss uh per
time step too. Um we can also uh get the
basically the final gradients for each
of these W's. You can calculate the
gradient for each time step separately
and then you're going to sum them all
together. So this is how it works in
practice. You could imagine if it were
different W's at each time step, you
could pretty uh probably easily see how
the computational graph could be
structured such that you're calculating
a different gradient for each of these
different W's. And so we're essentially
treating our single W for computational
purposes as uh a set of um different
W's, but then at the end we merge all
the gradients together because it's just
the same weight matrix that's being
multiplied. So conceptually you can
think of it as you're just calculating
it for each time step almost treating it
in your head like it's a different W
being used, but because it's the same
value of the weights, you just need to
sum all the gradients that you calculate
at each time step together.
Um in the many to one scenario, you'll
just have a a single loss calculated
here. Um so and sometimes you'll only
use the final hidden state uh to
calculate the value depending on the
problem setting. Like say you're trying
to do video classification, it may make
makes sense to use the hidden state from
every step because you might have
information about the video throughout
the entire course of the video during
classification. You can do some pooling
like average pooling or max pooling or
something like that to compute your your
y-value. Um and then sort of uh if you
have this sort of one to many mapping
like in image classification
um or sorry in image captioning um there
was a question about how you could
incorporate the previous Y's. So um you
still need to have an input input to
your FW
uh because it's sort of two different of
these weight matrices. One that's
expecting input vector X and the other
that's expecting um the previous time
steps hidden state. So um you could
imagine that you can put a lot of values
in here. You could just put zeros or you
could put the the previous um the
previous output here.
Okay. Um so I explained at a high level
how you do the back propagation. But
there's actually some specific issues
that you'll run into uh when you're
trying this conceptual when you're sort
of looking through this conceptual
framework that are very practical in
terms of running out of GPU memory which
is always the cause of basically all the
issues when you're trying to train a a
neural network that and I guess nan loss
during training. So um when you're
computing say a loss at each time step
um and you have an extremely long input
sequence you'll actually it's really
easy to understand you need to be
keeping the activations and the
gradients at each uh time step in memory
then summing them all together. This is
going to get extremely large as your
input sequence increases. So what can
you do practically to resolve this
issue? Um this is called back
propagation through time by the way when
you have the same weight matrix that's
being applied in multiple different time
steps and then you're summing the
gradient at each time step together. Um
so um what you can do is it's called
truncated back propagation through time.
So you basically fix a time window and
you can look at basically uh pretending
that this is uh all the model was
trained on so far. We start with our h0.
Um we calculate based on the input at
time step one and our previous h value.
We can calculate what is the current
hidden uh state at h1. And then we can
use that to calculate our output. We'll
have our loss. And we can run this for
each of our examples. And you can
imagine how in this setting it's
relatively easy to see how you just sort
of treat the beginning sequence as if
this is all we were seeing during
training. And moving to the next block,
you can now essentially you're starting
your H0 with now it's the output of your
previous step here. So we're
initializing the hidden state with
whatever the output was in our final
step, but the gradients are no longer
carrying over. So we're basically
batching the computational graph such
that we're only looking at the loss in a
neighborhood of these time steps at a
time. This is a fixed window size that
you set. So this is how you get around
this um relatively I would say um common
issue especially as you have really long
input sequences. Um and so yeah you
basically are batching it out and you
can just keep doing this for the entire
input uh sequence. So um one other thing
is that um you know you might ask how
does this work if we have just a single
output at the very end. Um so you can
still calculate the gradients at each
time step but you will no longer have
this um uh loss that's uh dependent on
the time step uh itself uh the output of
the time step itself rather you'll be
relying on upstream gradients. So you
can imagine we're looking at the far
right of the diagram here and we have
our loss that we calculate based on the
output at the final time step. um we can
calculate what is the gradient uh with
respect to our current uh hidden state
at the end. And then we have our whh
matrix to help us understand how did the
uh how did the previous hidden state
contribute to the uh final hidden state
and we can use that to uh calculate the
gradient and understanding based on the
previous hidden state and the weight
matrix. how can we change this
transformation matrix whh such that um
we would be changing our loss and uh
then you can just you basically just
applying the gradient rule to whh over
and over again here and you're only
looking at how the hidden state changed
the next hidden state and how that
contributed to the loss. So you look at
the final example here. This tells you
how changing the hidden state depends on
loss and then you know how the previous
hidden states how they change how that
affected uh the current hidden state
which is given by this whh matrix. So
using the W's at each time like using
different W's at each time step would
essentially mean that you're um no
longer modeling it as a recurrence
relation. So basically you have uh you
can think of it as one layer for each
different possible time step. Um so you
would probably see um worse performance
because um if you are sort of no longer
modeling it as a sequence recursively.
You're just uh I mean imagine you train
a neural network where you have a series
of inputs. Each one has a separate
weight that it goes to
>> independently.
>> Yeah. Independently. That would make
sense for a problem where it's not a
sequence modeling problem. You just have
a set of things that you want to
classify. U you would need to know like
the the amount of the sequence ahead of
time. So I think it could work if it's
not a sequence but for uh sequences of
variable length um I I think it would
not work very well u because you're sort
of um I mean I'm trying to think of the
simple way to explain it but it's sort
of like you're just training one neural
network for each uh time step. So it's
sort of not the way to formulate it. So
how does this work with chunking? So um
we have our so we we can do you
understand how to this point we can at
the point right here with the red dot we
can calculate um the gradient of the
loss with respect to our final hidden
state. Okay. So um if we can do that
then we can calculate the gradient of
our loss with respect to our second to
final hidden state because we know our
final hidden state is dependent on our
previous hidden state times this weight
matrix W. Okay. So we can do this and we
can go back and forth until here and at
this point uh we can uh sort of all we
need to save is this final step here. So
what is the gradient of this very final
uh or finals I'm maybe overusing the
word final but what is the gradient of
this initial um hidden state within our
truncated batch with respect to the loss
and then when we're calculating
backwards we just use that value to
calculate all the previous time steps.
So that's the overall process. You're
only looking at how the hidden state
transforms to form the new hidden state.
And that's the only value that's getting
updated here.
Um uh yeah. Yeah. Oh, and also the also
how the input uh changes the hidden
state. So you're looking at two values.
Both how the input affects it and how
the input affects the next hidden state
and the the previous uh hidden state.
Sorry, there's two values. Yeah. So the
learning still occurs for all the
batches. Um so um you have your loss
with respect to um each of your
parameters in W here and then when
you're calculating it for the previous
time step um you you you basically keep
this one value. If you change the final
the initial hidden state here, how does
that change loss? you can calculate that
and then you can see how all the
variables feeding into this uh and
namely this original hidden state and
the current time step how will that
affect the variable but then when you're
actually moving to the next chunk over
you only need to look at how does the
this hidden state here affect the hidden
state on in in the next chunk. So you're
looking at this division boundary. The
one variable you need to track over is
what is the gradient um of the hidden
state that occurs after the chunk. Um
and then you can use that to calculate
the gradient of the current hidden state
which is dependent on input x and the
and the previous. So there's different
ways you can formulate it, but you can
imagine we just apply uh the update to
all the the weights here and we zero out
the memory. The only thing we're
tracking is uh yeah the the gradient
right here. So you're you can apply you
can do a gradient apply step where you
apply all the gradients to the weights
depending on the learning rate and your
optimizer and all this stuff and then
you move on to calculating the next
batch. So the reason why this isn't a
perfect calculation is because um you're
calculating these independently rather
than all at once. So you sort of have
three different updates rather than just
one update at a time. But it should be
um you're still calculating the gradient
for each each step here. you keep one
thing in memory which is how does this
hidden state the the first one in the
batch how is that
how can we update the hidden state here
to to determine the loss and we throw
out all the other ones so you have the
weights in memory you can apply the
gradient you do your learning rate
multiply and you apply it to the weights
you'll also see a similar thing if you
do distributed um uh learning so if you
have a gradient calculated on each GPU
separately
they will apply them all to the same set
of weights even though they're
calculated independently. So I think we
have a lecture on distributed learning
coming up. So it's a similar thing where
you're not tracking it all in the same
memory at the same time and you're
applying it to the weights one at a
time.
>> Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. It would be better if
you could fit it all in memory. Yeah.
Yeah. It would be better if you fit it
all in memory. I mean this is mainly for
for this one it's essentially the same
but in this setting u maybe it's more
clear how you're explicitly losing
information.
So, um, here you're only looking at some
of the outputs at a time. Um, so you
it's really clear how we're not looking
at the entire set of the losses when
we're calculating because there's losses
at each time step. So, you lose
information here, but in this case, you
wouldn't lose information. Uh, I think
one more practical example where we
can't fit the whole RNN on the slide is
this idea of a character level language
model. And it's really funny because
these were shown to be quite effective
uh 10 years ago. Um and you can it's
really funny because you can see how the
current wave of language models are sort
of a buildup of this really simple
approach of just predicting characters
with RNN's. Um so usually when you do a
model like this you will input uh your
characters and then people call this a
one hot uh encoding where um you
basically have one uh you have a a one
in your vector and zeros in every other
location. So it's sort of like the index
here. Uh you can encode this as the
index and then uh we can use these as
inputs and we can calculate our hidden
layers based on the previous hidden
layer as well as the current uh input.
And then we have our output layer the
same where now we can look at um you
know what is the the output for the
corresponding correct value here which
is taken as the next time step. So we
want the output for example to be E. We
map it over here. We look at you can
imagine this is something like softmax
and we have the logits. So these are the
scores. Um 2.2 it's lower than 4.1. So
um so yeah we we have a we have a you
know this is maybe not so great of an
output at this time step um and so on
and so forth. So you can really view
this as a time stepwise classification
problem and that's exactly what uh in
general these language model these
language models are doing is timestep
wise classification based on softmax.
Um, so at test time, the basic idea is
we need to also sample characters one at
a time and and just feed it back into
the model. So it sees what it generated
at the previous time step. Um, so so on
and so forth uh repeating until we
generate the words. So you can actually
create RNN's to do this um basic uh
language model language modeling task by
operating at a character level and it
works quite well. Um, one thing to note
is that in terms of this input layer,
um, usually we don't actually input one
hot embeddings into the model and
instead we'll have something called an
embedding layer where, um, this is
essentially just a giant matrix which is
the dimensions um, the it's d byd where
d is the number of different inputs you
have to your model. And um what you do
is you sort of you can imagine this as a
matrix multiply where we grab the first
row or in this case we grab the second
row of our embedding matrix based on
what our input sample is here. And we
just use this as a matrix multiply.
This is incorrect actually. This this
one should be higher probability. Yeah,
it's it's funny. We've had these slides
for quite a few years and I guess no one
noticed it. question. Um anyway, so we
have uh E here as our target character.
Um and so in this case, you're correct
that it's the model's actually getting
it wrong. So we will want to penalize it
heavy for this time. So yeah. Yeah, it
was a good question. Um yeah, so um one
of the nice things about this
implementation is also it's really
simple. So it's like 112 lines of Python
code and you can train these models on a
variety of different tasks. So this is
like the prelim era of what you could
do. You can train it on sonnetss by
William Shakespeare. And as I mentioned,
there's a blog post by former instructor
of this course, Andre Carpathy, back in
2015 which talked about how these RNNs
are sort of unreasonably effective at
what they do in generating text. Yeah.
>> Could you explain why you use the why
you use an embedded layer? Oh.
>> Yeah. So, the basic idea for an
embedding layer is that generally it's
better to have vectors as input to our
models. And you can learn what these
embedding layers are too. So um you know
we tend to favor like spread out weights
in general when we're trying to learn uh
these. So you can initialize your
embedding layer to this sort of very uh
small zero values with something like
the kiming initialization we talked
about and then you're just looking at
one row of it at a time as your input
vector rather than it being like a a
number as input. Uh how you would have
to represent that is basically a one
with a bunch of zeros and
optimizationally the embedding works
better.
Okay. Um, so yeah, you can do it in 112
lines of Python code, which is pretty
neat. Um, you can train it on songs by
William Shakespeare and it'll actually
output reasonable text. We'll go through
some examples. So, one of the cool
things is you can see as you train the
model more, it becomes more and more
coherent. So, um, at the beginning, it's
basically just gibberish because it
hasn't learned proper values for W. And
then as you train it more and more, um,
it becomes more like this stage three
kind of looks like English, at least
some of the words, you know, right
there. And then as you train more it
actually starts working really well. Um
which this is I guess was a a bit of
foreshadowing for what was to come in
the era in the era of AI which is pretty
cool. Um you can see fullon uh it learns
things about the style how you should
you know have someone's name and how uh
you know something that seems fairly
plausible. Uh as you have it generating
more and more it starts making less and
less sense but it it's pretty cool to
see. Um, you can train it on code like I
think this in this example they trained
it on Linux. So the just the source code
for Linux they trained one of these
character level RNN's and you can see it
generating C code which looks pretty
good. Uh I don't know if this would
compile but it looks reasonable just
looking at it. And this idea has really
taken off over the past uh few years. So
um I mean I'm sure you all are know
especially since a lot of you work in
computer science or coding or your
students in this area but um there's all
of these different programming tools now
for these language models that were
essentially trained on a similar task
where they've consumed a bunch of this
uh uh training data that's just existing
code and instead of trying to predict
the next character they're trying to
predict the next token which is a group
of characters and how they define tokens
depends on the model and there's a lot
of details we could get into there But
at a high level, it's a really similar
thing. They're just predicting groups of
characters autogressively, one after the
next. And it's really seen a blow up in
recent years with all these existing
tools. Yeah.
>> What is the input to the model? Is it
like a trigger?
>> Oh, what? Like for this?
>> Yeah.
>> Um, you could have the input be Yeah,
you just maybe you start with a random
character could be one way to do it. Uh,
but you would need some initial input.
Um there could be usually with uh
language models they have a start token
as like a predetermined this is always
what you see at the start of your
sequence. So you could do a similar
things with RNNs. I don't know in this
exact scenario what they did. Maybe they
just did a character but it's hard to
know. So the question is how does
labeling work with language models? And
the neat thing about these pure language
models all they're doing is just
predicting the next token. You don't
need to label it. You just need to give
it a lot of text. That's why these
models are so good is because they
scrape the internet for, you know,
essentially all available text and then
they train a model on all of it. So
that's that's why they're so good. It's
cuz you it's just generating the next
token and you don't need to label it. So
that's why language models are so good.
So the question is uh if we're always
taking the maximum probability output at
each time step, um won't we always just
be generating the same thing over and
over again? And the answer is yes,
actually. So if you just took the
maximum probability uh I guess uh this
example is not so good but imagine the
probabilities are correct here and you
just took the maximum probability at
each time step you would always be
getting the same output given the same
input. In practice what people do is
they don't do this is called greed
decoding. You're always picking the
maximum probability. In practice they
sample based on a distribution the
distribution given by the probabilities
output by your softmax. So you won't
pick the max probability. You would pick
uh say in this case probability
84 for this one or probability.13 for
this other uh output variable and then
you would run that for each uh sequence.
And there's a bunch of different ways
you can do it too. There's like you can
search ahead called beam searching where
you're trying different ones and seeing
which one has the highest overall
probability for the sequence. So there's
there's a lot of this is like a whole
active area of research. How do you
sample from these models? But the simple
answer is you don't always pick the
highest probability. Yes. The question
is in the case where we have many to one
outputs are we outputting something each
time or do we have something to look at
here? So I think in practice to save
compute you wouldn't want to output
something that's never used but you
could feasibly output it at each time
step and it might be interesting
depending on your problem to look at
that and understand is the output
converging over the course of training
or not something like that. So you you
it might be useful to look at but
generally people wouldn't do it just to
save compute but it could be useful
actually. Yeah could help you understand
the way your model works if there's
certain triggers or things that help it
predict uh the correct answer.
Cool. Good questions.
Um okay so we'll keep on chugging along.
Um we talked about these RNNs how good
they are at generating characters. We
related them to some of these modern
coding tools which are really neat. Um,
one of the cool things also about RNN's
is you can look at the activation
uh activation values and they'll
actually sometimes tell you interesting
things about what the model's tracking.
So, we had in our little toy example, we
had we looked at the act output
activations and you would see it's the
current value and the previous value.
That was what the RNN states or cells
were were tracking. Um, what you can
also do is give it basically a sequence
here. Um, in the models I'll show in
these slides, it's using a tanh
activation. So this is from one to minus
one and minus one means it's visualized
as red here and very close to one would
be blue. Um we get the whole spectrum
here. And you can look at for each
character coming in what is the
activation of that cell at that time
step. And so that's how they're color
coding these plots here. This one's not
really showing anything. It's random. A
lot of them won't be interpretable. But
some of them have pretty cool things
that you can track. Like for example,
this one's a quote detector. So it turns
on basically as soon as the quote starts
and it uh ends when the quote ends. So
this is basically something in the RNN
tracking. We need to have an end quote
at some point. Uh and when to put it is
sort of uh something the model is trying
to figure out, but it's tracking it. Um
another cool thing is the line tracking
line length tracking cell. So it starts
uh kind of very uh high value and then
it becomes a very low value as you near
where the model thinks there'll be a new
line character. So this is also kind of
cool as a way to look at uh this other
value. And these are again just single
activations in a layer of this model
that we're looking at and mapping it to
um each character. So it's highly
interpretable.
Um they have this sort of if statement
cell. So anything within an if statement
is being tracked here which is also
pretty cool and uh even uh things like
detecting quotes or comments because it
needs to know to output the end of
comment uh character here. So it's
something it needs to track and so you
have this nice interpretable cell as
well. And then finally this code depth
cell. So as you sort of have nesting in
your code, it activates uh more and more
at each time step at each not time step
at each uh step into the sort of
indentation into the um into your code
hierarchy. So yeah, this is pretty neat.
You can actually look at the activations
and directly map them onto the inputs
without needing to do any fancy tricks.
Um which is which is actually pretty
incredible if you think about how
interpretable some of these hidden
states are in the RNN. It's actually
somewhat similar to what we were doing
where we were manually assigning it, but
the RNN is sort of internally doing a
very similar process.
Cool. Um, so I'll talk about now some of
the trade-offs like why you might want
to use an RNN and when is it helpful.
So, um, the nice thing is they can
process any length of input. So, a lot
of these modern language models that
rely on transformers have something
called a context length or context
window, maximum context window. Um, RNNs
don't have this. they can just take a
sequence of infinite length essentially
as long as you can keep running the
model on it. Um so there's no context
length limit. Um the computation for the
time step t can in theory use
information from many steps back if it's
captured in the hidden state. So if your
model is effectively capturing all of
the dynamics of your input sequence in
the hidden state, in theory it can use
values from an extremely long time ago.
Um but in practice there might be some
issues with this which we'll kind of go
into some details there. Um also the
model size does not increase for a
longer input. So um you know we had an
example where what if you just had a
different layer for or different layer
for each input time step. Uh you don't
have this issue which is nice. And then
uh we're applying the same weights at
each time step. So basically we know the
update rule for how we calculate the
outputs is the same every single time.
So um there's some nice like symmetry
here and also just and when you think
conceptually about the problem you're
always doing the same thing at every
single time step which is is nice
conceptually and also helps with some
imple implementation as well. So what
are the main disadvantages? So you need
to compute the previous hidden state to
compute the next one every single time.
So this can be slow if you need to you
sort of have each hidden state is
determined and uh is conditioned on all
the previous ones then this recurrence
computation can actually tend up taking
end up taking a lot of time. So although
this is not an issue at during inference
time when you're always like for a
transformer also you have this issue
where you need to output the next uh
token or character every single time but
at training time it's actually difficult
to batch uh all of these together and
and during training because in order to
calculate the loss you need to calculate
the previous hidden states. Um so so
this can pose challenges for scaling up
to a lot of data and then in practice um
it's actually difficult to access
information many time steps back because
we have a fixed size hidden state and
we're trying to cram all the information
into it. So you'll eventually lose some
information as your sequence goes longer
and longer.
Cool. I'll talk about some uh uh
applications more specific to computer
vision where RNNs have seen success now.
Um so one of them is image captioning
which we talked about. So um the basic
thing here is we mentioned there's this
sort of start token or start character
which begins the sequence and then you
will terminate when you have this end
character or end token. In this case it
seems like it's word level uh tokens. So
um you could have a model like this. you
have um the most basic way to do it is
you essentially have a CNN or something
that encodes a visual encoder that
encodes the image and we use that as
input to our uh recurrent neural network
as well as the uh previous text that was
generated. So we sort of have two stages
here and and very more concretely how
would you combine the CNN and RNN? You
can imagine you have this test image. It
comes in. So your your model sort of
going downwards here starting at the
first layers at the top and then moving
downwards. Um you can imagine this is
something that was like say trained on
imageet or something. Um and so we're
not going to use the class uh labels but
we're going to use this second to last
layer. This is sort of the common
strategy we saw for transfer learning as
well or this sort of getting good visual
uh representations of images.
So we use the second to last uh layer
and then we can start using this as
input to our hidden state. And now our
hidden state is also a function of um
this w
um value here. So we don't necessarily
have um just a hidden state. We're also
tracking the visual components here. But
I won't spend too much time on this
because um this won't be in any of the
assignments. But just to give you a
flavor of here's how RNN's were used
historically with CNN's where we're
taking a CNN pre-trained on imageet and
now we're including this information
into the hidden state as well. Um so you
know we use the sampling process either
greedy sampling some other version of
sampling to calculate tokens at each
time step. We end it when we have this
end token whenever we sample the end
token. That's how we know when to
finish. And these models actually worked
very well for the time. I think uh they
had a lot of great successes. So you can
see here a lot of nice examples of where
the model's outputting very reasonable
uh captions based on the input image
but also they the models would struggle
in a lot of scenarios too. So um a lot
of these have to do with sort of the
distribution of where these images are
commonly seen in the training data. For
example, um someone holding something
with their hands sort of cupped like
this. Um very much looks like how they
might hold a mouse, but obviously um you
know, we can tell this is a phone
because it's a flat object they're
holding and their their their hand is
facing up, not not downwards. So, this
sort of thing is interesting to see. Um
also, I guess they think the woman's
holding a cat where she's just wearing
some fur uh clothing. um you know they
see a beach so they assume there's a
surfboard. This type of hallucination I
would say is still extremely common with
vision language models today where uh
it'll think there's objects present that
are commonly present in a given scene
but aren't in this particular scene that
you're looking at. Um also you know
things like bird being perched in the
tree or uh throwing a ball but he's
catching a ball. These are all based on
the bias in the data set. Essentially in
the model learning that during training
it is most probably true that a certain
object or a certain action is being
performed when in the actual image it's
not the case. Um so in the data set uh
there's high coccurrence of these
actions or objects with the particular
scene. So the model learns to associate
them but it doesn't learn to
disentangle. Okay, it's happening in
this scene because of the, you know, in
this scene we know they're not throwing
because the glove is here and the ball's
going into the glove, not in the other
hand. But you need to sort of explain it
uh like that. And the way we train these
models, we're we're training them just
to output the caption. So we're not
doing any sort of explanation there. And
that's why u it's part of the reason you
see this co-occurrence issue.
Okay. Um so for visual question
answering, this is another really common
task where RNN's reused. And there are
sort of two formulations for visual
question answering that were commonly
used. One is to basically um you say you
have a model that is a a captioning
model and you want to see how well it
could answer questions. One thing you
could do is to give it this question and
then have it output text and look at the
probabilities of each of the answer
sequences. So you have a probability for
each character or token and you could
multiply them together to get the
probability of the overall answer. This
is like one way you could use one of
these RNN style uh models to do question
answering. Um a more common way people
did it is they would have basically a
question as input to the model. Um
multiple different answers also as in
separate inputs to your model and then
it's outputting essentially a
probability per question. And so in this
case it would be a four-way classifier
where uh you have four different classes
answer one, answer two, answer three,
answer four and you're just outputting
the probabilities and a lot of different
ways you can formulate it but um this is
a very common task in computer vision
where you need to use language and where
sequence modeling helps.
Um also visual dialogue um you know at
the time these were all considered very
separate tasks. these days the tasks you
have sort of one model that can do
almost all of these um but you know how
can can you have a chat about an image
we've really seen an explosion in the
capabilities of these kinds of models in
the last 2 years
um maybe uh one other type of model that
RNNs were commonly used for is for this
visual navigation task so um you know
you you have these images coming in and
you want to output a sequence of
directions to move in some 2D floor plan
how do you get to the target destination
Um this is another application for you
all to be aware of where these sequence
modeling um these sequence models were
used.
Okay. Um one thing I want to note that I
didn't really explicitly mention before
but um just in the same way where we can
have multi-layer CNN's or multilayer uh
uh of these sort of dense or fully
connected layers um you can also have
multi-layer RNNs. And in practice most
of the RNNs I showed were multi-layer
RNNs. Now the main difference is that um
you sort of treat each layer uh
separately. So the hidden state of say
layer 1 depends on the hidden state of
the previous time step of of layer 1. Um
so in this in the sort of depthwise
dimension sorry in the yeah in in the
depth dimension each of these
layers you're only looking at the hidden
states from that layer in the previous
time steps. And then in terms of looking
at windows in the time dimension um
instead of so the first layer will have
the actual input x as the input but then
the second layer will take us input the
output y from the previous uh layer. So
you can sort of stack these up and it
forms this grid where we have each layer
is operating uh with regards to the
previous hidden states only within that
layer. But then in terms of passing
input output that is between layers. And
so you can see to calculate this top
right value we need to calculate all of
the different values uh all of the
different hidden states in this entire
computational graph beforehand. So you
can get a feel for how as you start
training this gets to be a very involved
process and not very efficient.
Okay. Um I'll talk about one of the key
variants for RNN's that was proposed
actually a while ago in the 1990s but
saw a lot of success for quite some time
until the transformer revolution called
LSTMs. You won't need to know about the
details of how LSTMs operate, but what I
hope you learn is that RNN's have some
key um disadvantages that LSTMs seek to
alleviate and a lot of the more modern
statebased models also try to seek to
alleviate some of these same issues that
RNN's face.
So um you know we talked about how by
default tanh is a really commonly used
activation function and we also talked
about how you have this whh matrix that
converts your previous hidden state to
the to the uh sort of the new one and
it's summed with this uh wxh matrix that
converts your input uh vector xt at the
current time step into your uh hidden
state dimension. Then you sum these
together. Um, you can also formulate
this as sort of uh we have our weights
here and weights here and you're sort of
stacking the vectors uh like this. And
so sometimes for shorthand people will
just combine both of these W's together
to form one big W. Um but you should
note that um it's sort of like these are
two blocks that are uh diagonally
positioned together where there's there
would be like if you're formulating like
this there's sort of a lot of zeros in
this w because whh is not interacting
with xt at all but this is a shorthand
way to notate it where it makes thinking
about it and writing down the math
easier. So you will see all three
variants here. Um, this one's maybe the
most explicit about where the actual
values, the non-zero values in the
weight matrices lie. And so one way to
think of it is you stack these vectors
together, which is shown here. Um, we're
multiplying by this w and then we pass
it through tanh. This gives us our
output ht, which we pass to the next uh,
RNN. You can imagine these are stacked.
And then you may also have either the
output directly YT or we have this layer
um where it's a weight matrix time HT
with a with an activation function
around it too. Uh yeah question.
>> Oh sure. Yeah.
>> Okay.
>> So here we have multilayer RN.
>> Yeah.
>> How is the uh the symmetric pretty much?
>> Yeah. So the weights are shared within
the layers for multi-layer RNN. All of
these um all of these hidden state
updates will use the same weights and
then each layer which you stack it
vertically in this diagram each layer
will have a separate set of weights.
Okay.
Um yeah. So so this is sort of the way
that it works. And then when you have
back propagation, we talked about if you
don't have a loss for each time step y,
um you need to only calculate your loss
based on what the loss is of your output
ht. Um and so when you do this back
propagation, you're multiplying by w and
then you're also taking the derivative
of tan h. And both of these can actually
have some issues. So um when
specifically mathematically looking at
what is the gradient of the um how can
you know if we change each component of
our hidden state t um with respect to t
minus one. So so sorry if we change each
component of t minus one how will that
affect ht um this is what this gradient
is calculating. we need the derivative
of tan h um because this is our
activation function and then we have whh
which is the the multiply here for
converting the previous hidden state to
the next one. Um so this is actually how
we calculate the gradient and here we
can run into issues. So um if we're
calculating the loss at each time step
and we have the loss here the total loss
we just sum it for each of the weights.
Um so the total loss is just the sum of
the loss at each time step with respect
to these this reused w matrix.
Um and so you end up getting this
product of these um of these d L uh you
know uh you circuit to calculate sorry
the loss of L at the final step LT with
respect to HT you need to calculate each
of the intermediate hidden states and
how that affects uh W. In order to
calculate this final uh loss here by
using the chain rule u we sort of
mentioned example here and just to point
out why this is an issue. Um if we look
at these individual terms so if we hone
in on this aspect of how does changing
the uh current hidden state change the
next one which is the majority of these
calculations uh contained in this
product term here. we get that it's this
tan it's this uh it's the same thing we
mentioned earlier where you have this
derivative of tanh multiplied by your
whh and so why is this an issue? Well,
first of all the this is sort of the
derivative of tanh plotted here. The
maximum value is one and so almost
always you're getting less than one. So
you can have vanishing gradients from
this term here. Um but even if we assume
there's no nonlinearity uh nonlinearity
or we pick some um activation function
that doesn't have this issue um if we
look at this uh weight matrix here um
that we're multiplying at each um time
step either we're going to have a large
singular value. So um this will be you
know as the as the vectors are coming in
what is the maximum they'll be uh
stretched if it's say a unit vector uh
singular value is telling you what
what's the maximum that a unit vector
could be stretched by the matrix. Uh so
if it's very large you can have these
gradients explode or if it's very small
you can have this vanishing gradients
issue. Um, and if you have exploding
gradients, we have a fix which is this
scaling the gradient. So you can just
divide or like clip it and somehow so
that you don't. So too big of a
gradient, it's not too much of an issue.
But this really small gradient vanishing
gradient issue is actually the main
issue with why people don't just use
really long RNNs in practice because of
tanh and because you under many
scenarios your your weight matrix has
this property where it's either um you
know expanding your activations or or or
reducing them. So um yeah I think these
these are the main reasons why it
motivated a change in RNN architectures
and why a lot of the reasons why people
don't use RNN's. This is one of the main
issues. So how do you resolve this? So
the way that people did it was this
creation of the LSTM and the highle idea
which I won't go into too many details
because it's actually quite complicated
um is that you have four of these
different gates that are tracking
different values that instead of just
having one hidden state, you sort of
have multiple of these values you
premputee to determine how to change
your hidden state and then also what
information to pass through a different
pathway. So you have the regular hidden
state pathway. You have a different
pathway where it's easier to pass
information. And this is the basic idea.
Um you know at a at a high level they
call it a gate gate or like what are you
actually writing to the hidden state of
the cell. The input gate which is
deciding whether or not you write
information to the cell. The forget gate
how much to forget from previous time
steps as well as the output gate which
is like how much are you actually uh
outputting for your hidden state. So you
can see this is like really involved a
lot of design choices here and they put
it all together into this I would say uh
fairly complicated diagram but the basic
idea is uh this part is the same where
we're doing this weight multiply but now
we have four different values we're
computing instead of just the ht um we
have the input gate and the gate gate to
determine how much to write here and we
have our output that's passed to the
next hidden state um this is sort of you
can think of this top section here is
like a highway where the goal is to not
have any activation functions. So no
tanh so we avoid the issues we had where
tanh made the gradients vanish. Um and
all we're applying is this forget gate.
So as long as we're not basically
forgetting uh all the information at
each time step we're able to pass
information more easily. This is the
highle explanation and then more
importantly in practice people seem to
see that this worked very well. Um again
you won't be implementing this for the
course at all. Um but I think this is a
really commonly used baseline still in
some uh deep learning papers. So it's
good to know about but uh I think you
can think of this through the lens of
people are trying to construct these
things to make up for all the issues
that RNN's had which is vanishing
gradients and also the lack of
information being captured. Uh you need
to cram everything into this hidden
state. Right? So you have really
long-term dependencies. Those are lost.
So they created a separate pathway to to
to pass over this uh more long-term
information through the top here.
Um so do LSTM solve the Ganishing
gradient problem completely? Um it
definitely helps. So um it makes the RNN
easier to preserve this information over
many time steps by using this top
pathway diagram. Um so it's in contrast
it's a much harder for vanilla RNNs to
learn our current weight matrix that
preserves info uh info in the hidden
state across every single time step if
we're always doing the same operation
and we're not able to just pass
information directly without an
activation function. Um so it doesn't
guarantee it but it's makes it
significantly easier uh and it helps
improve learning long-term dependencies
and uh works very well empirically. So
people generally don't train RNN so much
and they'll more often train LSTMs if
you were going to go with this recurrent
um modeling route. Um but I think in
general these are also I would saying I
would say significantly fallen out of
fashion. But this gives you a sense of
the way that people have tried to design
RNNs to account for the issues they
face.
So, um, one other thing that would be
kind of cool to tie in to something you
learned earlier in this course is this
idea of directly adding outputs and
skipping some activation functions or
other layers is actually highly related
to the idea that we discussed in ResNets
where you have these skip connections
where uh the value is just copied over
and added uh later in the in the in the
in the layer block. So you have multiple
in resonance you have multiple of these
convolution layers stacked together and
then you add uh skip connection where
the value just gets added here and you
can sort of think of uh this in a
similar light for LSTMs how it's
skipping over some of these uh layers
and it helps improve as you get in this
case instead of very large depth of the
model it's very long sequences of time
steps. So um this is sort of it's a
parallel but it's a little different
because one is the number of layers and
the other is the number of time steps.
Okay. Um I think the final slide for
today's lecture is just a little tie-in
for how um these RNNs have sort of made
a bit of a resurgent in the last uh year
or two which is kind of funny uh because
I think if we taught the course maybe a
year or two ago I would have been much
more willing to want to cut RNNs
entirely. But there are actually a lot
of nice advantages they have. So the
main one is this unlimited context
length. So one of the main issues with
transformers is they have a limited
context length. As people are really
pushing the boundaries for what these
models are capable of, this context
length is becoming more and more of an
issue. So if there have been various
workarounds in the transformer space,
people do things like rope and some
other techniques to try to extend the
context length. But it's a pretty
significant limitation of the model. Um
the other thing is that during um during
inference for RNN's the compute scales
linearly with the sequence length or or
during training too but uh basically as
you add more and more uh steps to your
sequence uh you just need to recomputee
the same operation over and over again.
So there's no operation that looks
across the entire input sequence like
you have for transformers. Um so these
are really big advantages and there have
been a couple of papers. So to shout out
a few um there's this RWKV model um you
can check out archive link here and also
mamba are both uh mainly highlighting
this idea of we're able to achieve
linear time sequence modeling. So as you
scale up your input sequence the compute
also scales linearly as opposed to
quadratically with transformers and so
you get uh it's better for long context
problems sometimes in terms of compute
it works better and has these main
advantages. So we will try to get the
best of both worlds and there's been a
lot of research in this area. How can
you get the performance of transformers
with the scaling of RNNs? Okay. Um so
that's all for today in class. We
basically talked about how uh there's a
lot of different ways you can design
architectures with RNN's. Vanilla RNNs
are simple but they don't work that
well. And there's been more complex
variants that people have proposed that
introduce ways to selectively pass
information. um this backward flow of
gradients in the RNNs can either explode
or vanish depending on the activation
function you use or what is the
properties of your weight matrix. So um
you often need this back propagation
through time to actually compute the
gradient as well. Um and then finally
basically these better architectures are
hot topic of research right now as well
as just generally new paradigms for
reasoning over sequences. So yeah I
think that's it for today. Uh next time
we'll talk about attention and
transformers.