So, we'll get started. Today, we're
going to cover a mixture of experts.
Last year, this was kind of a fun bonus
lecture that I threw together. Um, but
this year, thanks to, you know, lots of
people doing, this has become a much
more critical lecture. So I've added a
lot of um the recent developments and at
the end we'll try to walk through um
DeepSeek V3 and try to understand like
what are all the sort of components that
make up a state-of-the-art open source
system or at least on the architecture
side what that looks
like. So mixture of experts is how a lot
of you know the most modern high
performance systems today are are built
and deployed. Um, so there was the funny
Nvidia leak of uh GPT4 actually being
potentially revealed as
GPTOE1 BT. Um but more you know broadly
others like Grock um and Deepseek and
Llama 4 now um have all adopted a
mixture of experts uh architecture and
it seems like at this point in 2025 that
the advantage of mixtures of experts
over dense architectures is very much
clear right almost um all compute scales
training a mixture of experts model if
you do it well um is going to give you
benefits over a dense model and so
everyone seems seems to be doing it in
both the east and the west. And so this
will be an important um thing to
understand if you're trying to build
sort of the the best model that you can
um for the flops that you
have. So mixture of experts is very
simple. Um it's a very terribly named
concept. I think you hear mixture of
experts and you think oh there must be
experts specialized for different
domains and they're like doing different
things. Like there's a coding expert and
like an English expert and a other
languages expert. um it is very far from
that mental model. A mixture of experts
is a type of fancy architecture that has
several subcomponents called experts
that are activated sparsely. Um and in
particular when you think about mixture
of experts you should be thinking about
the MLPS. This is where all the action
is right. So ae architecture and a nonoe
architecture are going to be similar in
almost all of its components um except
for one and that is you know if you look
at this this slide over here you know
this is the components um of a standard
transformer you got your self attention
you got your FFN if you zoom in you know
in a dense model the the feed forward
component just sort of you know is there
it's one big block in a sparse model
what you would do is that you would take
this FFN and you would split it up or
you would copy it depending on how
you're going to be setting up your
multiple copies, let's say, of your FFN,
your fully connected networks, and
you're going to have a router that picks
some smaller number of those, you know,
in each forward pass or at each
inference, right? So, this is the basic
idea behind, and we're going to replace
this one big feed forward on the left
side with a selector layer and many
smaller ones. Um, and what's the
advantage of this thing? Well, if it's
sparssely activated, that is, let's say
only picks one expert and an expert is
the same size as your dense FFN, then
the flops between the left side and the
right side, the dense model and the
model, they have the same flops, right?
They're doing the same matrix multiplies
as you do your forward pass. Um, so you
have more parameters without affecting
your flops. And if you're a believer
that what matters is having more
parameters to, for example, memorize
facts about the world, well, you know,
this is a great architecture. So you can
kind of see the the intuition behind. Um
hopefully that's all very clear. Um and
you might wonder okay so it makes sense
that you can get you know more
parameters per flops but does that
translate to actually better performance
for the models that you're training. Um,
and there's been, I think at this point,
many, many, many papers showing that at
the same flop count, at the same
training amount of flops, you get better
performance out of a mixture of experts,
um, than out of a dense model. So, um,
this is a nice paper to so today I'm
going to go over a couple of the the
classic Google papers that, you know,
put this field together. Um, and this is
one of them by Fetis at all 2022. um
where they show that you know if you
flops match your your you know training
flops so that's the same amount of
compute used for training and as you
increase the number of experts the
training loss of your language model
just keeps going down and down and down
and down and down right so you know more
experts better of course the experts
aren't free you need to store the memory
for these experts and when you do
parallelism you're going to have to
think about you know routing your data
into 256 separate experts so that's
there's going to be systems complexities
but if you're only thinking about flops.
This is a great chart to see because you
have the same flops, but you've gotten
free, you know, test loss um here. And
you see the same thing reflected on the
right side. You know, as you train for
longer and longer, the model, the switch
base with 128 experts, right? The model
with more experts, you know, gets better
perplexity um faster, right? So
hopefully that that is quite clear. Um
you might say, well, this is a 2022
paper. Um is this true sort of on modern
architectures on modern scales? Um it
you know continues to very much be true.
Um AI2 had a very nice paper um OLO
which did a whole bunch of ablations and
carefully controlled comparisons into
dense versus um and other architectures
and they sort of see exactly the same
thing. So here on the left side this is
still from Fetus at all. You see the 7x
speed up from having many experts. On
the right side this is the OMO
comparison. You see um the the pink one
is thee and the the teal one is dense
and the training loss for the dense
model goes down much more slowly than
thee. Right? So hopefully you know I
have in some sense sold you on the value
of and for for learning this kind of new
slightly new architecture. Right? So
we're going to pay a a price for all of
this but at least at the flops level
this looks very compelling. Right? So
yes question the last lecture you
mentioned uh like yeah the bias turning
part because although the it's a pretty
cheap
computation affects our actual process
pretty badly we're you know loading in
and
out is there
right so the question was in last
lecture you know I was saying um even
small non- flops you know negligible
flops can be really big in wall clock is
anything in thee world going to look
like that and so I think one of the
drawbacks of why you know that's not the
standard thing that's being taught you
know let's say at 224n is because
there's significant systems complexities
to making this thing efficient so I'll
you know get to that it's possible to
make these things very efficient
especially if each expert lives on a
separate device so that you know you're
routing thing data to different places
you can be very efficient when you do
that but it's not easy right so there's
a lot of infrastructural concerns s and
you're going to see a lot of
complexities to get this thing to work.
But when it does work, you know, you're
you're putting all of your flops to
use. Okay. And then uh the last one uh
that I wanted to show is, you know, a
lot of the companies really love because
you get to present plots that look very
compelling like this, right? This was
from the DeepSeek V2 paper. Um you know,
on the X-axis, this is this is a little
bit of slight of hand. This is only
activated parameters, right? So this is
only the parameters that are used you
know for computation. So you ignore all
the deactivated experts and the y- axis
is mmlu performance, right? And we see
deepseek v2. Wow, look, very few
activated parameters, really good mmlu
performance, right? And so if you're
only interested in both training and
inference flops, you know, activated
parameters is the name of the game. You
get really good performance here. And
this is, you know, not just an ablation.
This is a real system that someone, you
know, spent a lot of money to train um
and deployed out in the wild, right? And
we'll see this sort of pattern uh recur
in other uh examples as well. Oh, was
there a question? Oh, no. All right. And
so the systems thing that is also um a
benefit is that allow us to have another
axis of parallelism. So I'm going to get
into parallelism in much much more
detail sort of in the systems lectures
when I'm going to talk about how you're
going to take your model and you're
going to cut it up into many small
pieces and lay them out across many
different devices. But I'm going to talk
at a very high level. But when you have
experts, there's a very natural way to
parallelize at the expert level, right?
So you have multiple different feed
forward blocks. You can take each of
these experts and you can put them on a
different device, right? And because
experts are sparsely activated, all you
have to do is take your token and route
it to the appropriate device and the
computation will happen on that device,
right? So it's a natural sort of cutting
point to be able to shard your model
into different devices. And so this is
called expert parallelism. Um, and this
is another reason why are very popular,
right? If you really want to paralyze
really big models, this is a thing that
you're going to have to do. And kind of
interestingly enough, I think, you know,
developed at Google um and many of the
the frontier labs, the closed labs were
doing it, but I think the open results
actually came from China um very
frequently. um Quen and Deepseek were
doing you know a lot of work um last
year and it's only really recently that
I think western open source groups have
started to do more uh work so Mixstrol
Grock um I guess Grock's not open um and
then now Llama is now ane architecture
right and so here you know Llama 4 just
got released right latest and greatest
um this is also a sparsee and I'll talk
about llama 4 as well um as I go through
the
lecture Um as I said before, so you know
one of the kind of starting points for
this is um some of the Chinese groups
Quen and Deepseek have actually done
some really nice work benchmarking and
understanding and evaluating um some of
these results. So these so Quen 1.5 was
one of the first uh models that I knew
of to have like this largecale well-
tested well doumented. Um, and what they
did was they took a Quen 1.5 dense model
and they had a nice trick to upcycle it
into a mixture of experts. That's a
clever kind of trick to take a dense
model and then turn it into ane. And
they showed sort of significant gains at
least in terms of compute efficiency um
while sort of m decreasing the total
number of parameters relative to their
sort of 7B uh model. Deepseek, which is
now famous, um, but originally when
these papers were coming out were were
not quite as famous, um, did some of
the, I think, really foundational work
in the open-source world. Um, a big part
of this lecture is actually going to be
tracing the trajectory of the mo uh,
Deepseek MOE architecture. But if you
look at their original Deepseek paper,
you'll see very nice papers, sorry, very
nice sort of comparison showing things
like what happens when you train a dense
model with a particular amount of flops.
what happens when you train a a really
naivee that doesn't do very smart
routing what happens and then if you use
a smarter routing called the switch sort
of uh what happens and so you'll see all
of these very carefully controlled
comparisons and you see you know as you
go from dense to sparse right so that's
the leftmost column to the rightmost
column you see all of these sort of
benchmark metrics very consistently
improve for a fixed amount of flops
right so this is um very consistent and
kind of um one thing that I think almost
everyone at this point has probably
heard of, right, is Deepseek V3. And
that's in some sense, you know, a
culmination of all this line of work.
But if you had been following and you
were excited about kind of this branch
of of um neural networks and and
language modeling, you would have
actually known about, you know, Deepseek
long before V3 got popular. Um, and
we'll see at the very end of this
lecture actually Deepseek V3 is not very
different from the very earliest
DeepSeces. architecturally, you know,
they had kind of nailed it way back when
they were training these sort of much
smaller two billion parameter models.
They really just kind of got the
engineering right to get something that
is actually really quite remarkably
good, uh, which is their V3
model.
Okay, so now I think you know I have
spent quite a few minutes trying to
really hype you up ones and they really
are I think worth hyping up. They're
very good. Um, but I think there's a
question of why haven't they been more
popular, right? Why isn't it the
standard thing we teach in, you know,
NLP and and language modeling classes?
Um, it's just that they're very complex
and they're very messy and I'm hoping
that they'll get simplified over the
next few years, but they still remain
pretty nasty. Um so one of the things is
you know the infrastructure is very
complex and the biggest advantages of
really happen when you're doing
multi-node training like when you have
to split up your models anyway then it
starts to make sense to shard experts
across different models that's a very
natural thing to do but until you get to
that point maybe are not quite as good
right so um some of the earlier Google
papers really talk about this trade-off
where they say actually when you get
these really big models that you have to
split up then exports become uniquely
good. Um there's also other things that
are are really tricky. Um if you think
about it carefully, right, this decision
of which expert you route tokens to is a
very difficult thing to learn, right? In
deep learning, we really like
differentiable objectives, right? Very
smooth things that we can take gradients
of. Routing decisions are not
differentiable because we have to pick
and commit to a particular expert. So if
we're doing that, you know, we're going
to have a very tricky optimization
problem. And the training objectives to
make that work is either heristic and or
unstable, right? And so we're going to
have to really carefully engineer those
guys to get them to work, right? So
those are two reasons why you don't
really um want to to maybe do this
normally. Um so what do look like? As I
started this lecture with, you know, the
classices that you should think of is
you take, you know, the densely
connected layers, the the FFNs, and you
split them up or you, you know, copy
them um and you have sparse routing
decisions among them. Of course, you
could do the same kind of idea. You
could have a sparsely routed attention
layer. And some people have done this.
There's been a couple papers and a
couple releases that have taken this
approach. Um but it is actually quite
rare uh to see this in the major model
releases. Um I think I've seen people
talking on the internet saying like this
approach is actually really much even
more unstable and very difficult to
really train consistently. Um it's sort
of I haven't really seen the ablations
to to back that out but certainly there
haven't really been many people training
those kinds of models with uh
attentions. So now you know I've told
you about the basic architecture, right?
It's really simple. It's just you have a
router of some kind and you route and
then you have different MLPS. So what
are the the things that might vary
across different choices? Um you might
ask how do we route right the routing
function is an obviously important
choice. How many experts and how big
should the experts be? That's another
choice. And then the final one is how
would we train this router? Right? this
non-ifferiable objective that seems very
difficult to train. So those are very
important design questions and we're
going to go through each one um
hopefully covering the design space um
of all these things. Okay. Any questions
before I get into to each one of these
different subcomponents
here. Good. Okay.
So if you're interested in in just kind
of understanding a broad overview of at
least circa 2022 um there's a really
nice sort of survey or a review paper by
fetus at all in 2022 that covers a lot
of these and and many of my figures you
know are credited to that paper. If
we're thinking about how we're going to
route or essentially match tokens to
experts, right, this is the core
component of because whate does is, you
know, tokens are going to be coming in,
right? You have your sequence that
you're processing and those sequences
are going to be assigned to experts,
right? Not all experts will process
every token. That's the whole point of a
sparsely routed. And so you can ask how
are these routing decisions made? So you
can sort of have three different kinds
of choices. You can have token choice
where each token is going to have a sort
of routing sort of preference for
different experts and I will choose the
top K experts for each token or I can
have expert choice where each expert is
going to sort of have a rank preference
over tokens and then I'm going to choose
the top K tokens for each expert. This
has a really nice benefit of being
balanced over experts. Um and then the
last one is sort of you could solve some
sort of complicated optimization problem
to make sure that the mapping between
experts and tokens is somehow balanced.
Right? This is global assignment.
Um and just to to you know give you a
bit of a a teaser here almost all the do
token choice top K. Um in the early days
of people tried many many different
things sort of spanning this whole
spectrum of design space of token
routers. Um if you look at the big
releases they have all converged to
basically one class of routing
mechanisms which is token choice top K.
So each token is going to rank order um
experts by affinity and then there's
going to be kind of a top k choice for
each one of this um and mo which I'll
keep referring to uh throughout this
lecture because they have a really nice
series of ablations. So it's really nice
to teach off of um have exactly this
oblation. They compare a token choice
routing versus an expert choice routing
and they show if you look at validation
loss token choice is much much nicer
behaved um much faster um in loss decay.
Yes. Is this function a function of the
token itself for its position? Uh it's a
function of the sort of the hidden
state, right? So the token is going to
get processed with all the position
embeddings and so on and then the hidden
state will come in and then it will be
processed by the MLP. And so for the
other um for the other two like for the
experts choosing the token and also like
the next one when you say it's like more
balanced across the experts are
they like it's still for the current
like token sequence but it's like it's
forcing them to be more distributed like
it's still going to be the same set of
tokens but really it's about kind of the
ranking selector function right in token
choice I'm just going to take the top K
amongst the columns like maybe the fours
are even identical, right? I'm just
going to take the top K amongst the
columns. In expert choice, I'm going to
take top K amongst the rows, right? Um,
and top K amongst the columns is kind of
nice because you might be able to say,
oh, I can define a scoring function such
that the score is how well each token
gets processed by each expert. And token
choice will will route me to the best
expert, right, for that token. So, that
makes sense from processing. But expert
choice has the benefit that each expert
gets exactly the same number of tokens.
And so now you might like if you're
putting different experts on different
devices, you've got balanced
utilization. So there's different
trade-offs at play as you think about
routing. Yes. Um how does a token know
which expert is the best? Good. Yes. So
the question was how how does each token
know which expert is good? That is
exactly the role of the router. And I'll
give you the router equation, but to
give you a bit of a not really a
spoiler, but you know the routers are
much more lightweight than you think. So
you know your token, let's say, is
represented by vector X. That's your
like hidden you know residual stream
coming in. So now X is going to get
multiplied by you know W a matrix and
then you'll just take you know a sigmoid
or something and that's the score. So
it's really just a a vector vector inner
product almost like an attention
operation in a way. Yes.
Right. So the choice of so the question
was is K1 here? Um so K is actually a
hyperparameter and different will choose
different things. Um, I will talk about
this again, but to give you the high
level intuition, the initial argument
that the the earliest MOE papers made
was that K should be greater than two
because that way you get some
exploration, right? If you're doing K
equals 1, maybe you're just always
exploiting the best arm and you'll never
know about the potential other things
you could do. But if K is two, then
maybe that second arm can tell you a
little bit of exploration information.
So, um, you know, K equals 2 was the
canonical choice. Um, and K equals 2
actually continues to be very popular.
That would be like double the flops.
Like that's right. That's right. So So
that would double the flops. And so when
people talk about they usually say
things like x number of activated
parameters and that would account for
the fact that you're you know put
putting in two MLPS. Yes. So when k is
um greater than one like even time do we
combine the outputs of the different
experts into? Yes. The question was when
k is one do the outputs get combined?
That's right. Like if you if you look at
I guess like look at the attention
diagram over there you know um you got
the router it's routed to two MLPS up
top and then they get combined together
right after right so that's exactly
right
so in that case you can just like a
simple average
so the question was how does the the
aggregation happen it's just the
sum right so um I'm going to go over the
variance very common variance that
people do um and really in some ways All
you need to know is top K in order to
actually implement a uh high
performance. But I'll give you the other
variants because they're natural things
you might think of. Um top k routing is
what is used in most token choice top
routing uh topk routing. So how that
works is you know you have your residual
stream inputs x. Um that will go into a
router and as I said a router is really
kind of like the attention operation.
There's like a linear inner product and
then a softmax and then you pick the top
k most highly activated um experts and
then those outputs are um gated.
Depending on the implementation you
might weight the outputs based on um
this router weight or you might not um
and then you will just output the
weighted average or just a straight sum
depending on how your implementation
works. Um and so a lot of thee papers
and and methods use top k switch
transformer gshard grock mixtro clan uh
all the deepseeek um variants use uh
different top k
variants. Um maybe a very surprising
fact and this should really make you
think about what's going on with um
there are a lot of results that show
that actually you don't even need a
smart router at all. you can actually
just use a hashing function at the very
bottom to map these X's onto your
experts. And even if you're doing
hashing, so no semantic information at
all, you will still get gains from a
hashing based, which is pretty
wild. Um, some of the earliest work
ones, I think, had the very smart idea
and in many ways the right idea if
you're thinking about this top down of
using RL to learn the routing behavior,
right? Of course, you know, the choice
of where to route to is a discrete
decision, and RL is great for learning
discrete decisions. Why don't you use RL
to learn routing? It was used in some of
the earliest work on mixture of experts.
Um, as far as I know, basically no one
does this now. The compute cost to do
this is too prohibitive and you already
have stability issues. You might not
want to do that. Um, there have been a
couple of papers that have explored
things like solving linear assignment
problems or optimal transport style
problems. um they're very elegant but
once again the cost of doing this is
much higher than the benefits that it
gives you I think in practice and it
hasn't really uh been adopted but
there's a lot of really interesting
things that people are doing like this
um to try to improve uh the
routing so now I can you know point at
this slide and really talk through how
routing um works in detail um so this is
the kind of top K routing that almost
everyone has converged to um now Um this
is the the router that's used in
Deepseek v1 to2 Quen and Grock do almost
exactly this. Um there's a instead of
having a softmax directly at the bottom
here um they do a soft uh DeepSseek V3
mixrol dBrx um don't have a softmax at
the bottom but they'll softmax the G of
its but it's a very minor difference. So
let's walk through what's going on here
um and try to to reason about you know
the behavior of this. So what's
happening here is at the very bottom um
we've got our inputs. This is our our
UFl uh input and I would like to take
this sort of residual stream input and
process it through you know
my first thing I'm going to do is I have
to figure out which experts are going to
be activated. Now how am I going to do
that? Well how I'm going to do that is
very similar to attention. I'm gonna
take my U, which is my residual stream
input, and I'm gonna take the inner
products with the E of I's. These are
kind of learned vectors that are for
each expert that tells the expert I'm an
expert, you know, that points in this
direction, right? And so I'm computing
in this inner product here expert and
input affinity and I'm computing a
softmax to determine for each, you know,
uh, token what are, you know, the best
experts, right? So I normalize this is S
of T. Now I take the S of I of T and I
go through a top K function. I only
select the K best um weights and then I
use this as my gate. So I zero out
everything else and I take the weighted
average of each of the experts outputs.
Um and then I add that to my original
residual stream and then I return that.
Right? So this is hopefully very
familiar to kind of um what you're all
very familiar with in terms of how you
know uh transformer works with only the
difference of this top k routing piece.
Is that clear kind of to everyone how
this thing
works? Good. Excellent. So in some sense
the the mechanics of the the forward
process of the routing is very simple.
Um what is kind of mystifying is that
fact that you can learn this very well.
Right? This is in some sense a fairly
complicated set of things to have to
learn to do well by a model. Yes.
So we're using soft max here. Uh
previously one of the benefits of soft
max is that it's going to push you
pretty extremely to choosing a singular
max. It's not a hard max, but it was so
I'm having trouble thinking of the
intuition of putting the soft max
basically on top of like combining it
with the top K where you're getting
multiple and then you're using something
that's going to push you towards
choosing just one thing. Yeah. I mean I
think maybe one way of thinking about
the soft max is you know it the whole
purpose of this is just to make it so
that when I average my experts later it
kind of sums to one. Don't think of the
softmax as like a soft max operation
even though that's literally the name.
Um really the softmax operation is a
normalized to one operation and the
normalize to one operation is going to
make that a weighted average up top. Um
the other thing that's very important is
you know you might think why can't I
just get rid of the top K why don't I
just use the softmax here and just you
know gate all the experts well then you
immediately lose the the systems
efficiency aspect of this right you have
to have top k during training otherwise
you pay the training cost of all capital
n of your experts right this is the key
thing about like we have to do all this
gymnastics to make sure that both at
training time and inference time we have
a sparse number of activated ated
experts. That's why we go through the
top K, right? Okay. Yes. From the back.
Yeah. So, because you're doing soft max
first and then the top K get the
weights, you no longer have to
guarantee.
So, the question was, yeah, so the
question was um if you soft max first,
you no longer sum to one. And yes, uh
that's absolutely right. You no longer
sum to one. And in some ways, like
there's no requirement that you have to
sum to one cuz you know the next layer
can magnify it back up. you know there's
layer norms everywhere. It's not as if
it has to sum to one. But I think that
is the reason why some of the other
architectures basically move the
location of the softmax. There's a kind
of aesthetic choice about whether you
really want that, you know, weight to be
normalized to one or not.
Yes. Yeah. So I was wondering like how
does the E vector here relates to the
weight of the feed forward? Okay. So the
question was whether the whether and how
the E vectors relate to the feed
forward. Um they're not really tied in
any way. The E vectors are just learned
vectors for the just think of the E as
parameters for the router, right?
They're just separate objects from the
FFM.
Yeah, I was just
wondering how does compared to sampling
from the soft.
Great. Uh the question was about how
does it compare to sampling from the
softmax? Um you can sample from the
softmax and and some um uh methods
actually do a kind of soft sampling from
the softmax. Specifically, um, one of
the Google papers has a procedure where
they take the top element of the softmax
and then they randomly sample the second
element proportional to the remainder of
the softmax. Um, and that gives you more
exploration, which is good, but the
drawback of that is that if you don't
sample at test time, now you've got a
train test mismatch.
Okay. Yes. Why not just reormalize after
the top K? Uh, why not just reormalize
after K was the question. Is that right?
Um, in some some models do that. Some
models do bring normalize off to the top
K, but that's a kind of a choice like
some architectures don't do that, some
architectures do. It doesn't actually
matter because the scale can be
basically adjusted post hop, right? So
there's no reason why it has to sum to
one after the G
operation. Cool. Oh, sorry. Yes, the
bias term is U there up there. Yeah. So
the first term of the sum if g is
approximating probability vector could
be seen as an expectation of the
function fn right plus you. So so ff
actually uh this is not an expectation
of ffn because each ffn is a different
fn so this is not actually an
expectation and the gates are sparse. So
this is like a weighted selection
operation over k different or actually
capital n different ffns and then the
utl at the very end there you know if
you remember the transformer that's the
residual stream right so I'm adding back
the inputs because I want sort of a
identity connection throughout
okay oh there's another question uh why
does the router have such a basic
parameterization like what happens if
you put more weights into um your router
function right the the question was why
is the router so basic seems like if
you're going to have experts, it seems
important to route to the right experts.
Um, so why don't you do that? Um, I
think, you know, there have been some
oblations in some of the the earlier
Google papers on having like MLP uh
routers and like more sophisticated
things. Um, I think the the sort of
complex answer here is that the systems
concerns sort of weigh heavily. If
you're using a lot of flops to make
routing decisions, you know, you have to
pay for those flops and so you have to
get performance improvements in just the
routing, you know, and I think the one
other thing to appreciate here is that
there are really big limits to how well
you can route because the learning
process for this routing thing is
actually pretty dicey, right? Because
how are you going to get gradients for
which routers are good or bad? Well, the
only thing you have is if you have top
two, then you can compare the two things
that you have and you can push the
gradients into S of T because your your
G is a weight and then the S of T might
inform your your inner products. But
that's a very indirect way to be
learning your affinity. So even if you
make it complex, there's no guarantee
that you're going to really learn the
optimal router,
right? Great. Okay.
So um I think the one of the great
innovations of the
deepseek and uh which was very quickly
adopted by all the other sort of Chinese
uhe releases is this idea of both a
shared expert and a fine grained expert.
Um and so the basic structure that was
sort of originally proposed is to take
your dense architecture and kind of copy
the experts over right. So in this case,
you know, you're going to have, let's
say, if you have two, if you have top
two routing, you know, you're going to
have twice the activated parameters of
your original dense model, right? So you
take your and you copy it over and you
activate K equals 2. So this is kind of
what you might think of as like the
vanilla or like the basic that you might
start with. Um, people realize fairly
quickly um that having lots of experts
is good. And the logical sort of next
step beyond having lots of experts is
good is I want lots of experts but I
don't want to pay the parameter cost for
having lots of experts. And so um
DeepSsee basically argued that the right
thing to do then was to cut the expert
up into smaller pieces, right? So
remember last lecture I was you know
telling you about oh the the kind of
golden rule in some sense is to have you
know your your hidden layer and then you
multiply that by four and that will give
you kind of your projection layer right
so now what you would do is you would
instead of multiplying by let's say four
you might multiply by two right so now
you have smaller matrices you have more
fine grained experts you can have twice
as many of them right um and you can
kind of take that logic much more to the
extreme you can like you know quadruple
or multiply by eight and you can keep
decreasing the size of your sort of
projection uh dimension there that's
fine grained experts and there's you
know drawbacks I'll I'll talk about
later it's not it doesn't come for free
so you have to be very careful about how
you you structure these things um and
then the the other thing that you know
uh has been sort of studied and noted is
maybe it's helpful to have at least some
MLP that can capture shared structure
right like maybe there's just like
processing that always needs to happen
no matter which token you're processing
in that case it seems like kind of a
waste to do all this routing work and to
have all these like, you know,
parameters spread out everywhere when we
can just have one shared or one or a few
shared experts, you know, whose job it
is to handle all of this like shared
processing that's needed. And so they're
shared experts. Um, and so this setup of
using fine grained experts plus shared
experts um originally came out um in
DeepSeek um although I think the
original inspiration came from deep
speed um and Quen and others. Um, so
almost all of the uh open uh releases
since DeepSeek have adopted some sets of
these innovations because it's it's
quite clear that especially fine grained
experts is just really really useful.
That's a kind of no-brainer um at this
point to do. Um, one of the things I
really like about uh reading Deepseek
papers is that they do ablations. You
know, it's not like a whatever sales
tech report. you know, they actually
care about whether or not their methods
work. Um, and so they have this lovely
ablation in the Deepseek paper where
they show, you know, the the blue bar
over here, this is G-Shard. This is a
very basic vanilla implementation of you
know, you can have uh one shared expert,
that's the orange bar, and that gives
you a big boost on some tasks and no
boosts on others. Um, you can have fine
grained experts, that's the green and
orange, you know, bars, and you get
further boosts from that. And if you
compare the blue to the orange, you
know, composing all these differences
give you quite the big boost um over
others. Um and so we can see that, you
know, more experts and shared experts
generally um seem to help. Okay. Yes.
Question.
Like when it says seven out of
something, does that mean it's doing
like top seven? Yes. Sorry, I should
have I should have explained that.
That's right. Um so X out of Y means X
activated out of Y total routed experts.
That's right. Yeah. And so you can kind
of see the pattern here as well of as
you increase the number of experts, you
also often increase the number of
activated experts. Um especially if
you're doing fine grained experts, it
flops wise it's free, right? Because you
know each expert is now
smaller. Good.
Okay. Um so has you know basically
corroborating evidence that shows really
nicely uh that these things work. So,
uh, the bottom one I think I'll start
with because it's more decisive, um,
shows, you know, fine- grained experts
going from 8 to 32 to 64 fine grained
experts mirroring in some sense the
deepseek ablations. Um, and you see very
clear trends and losses and other kinds
of um, uh, metrics that you see
improvements going from 8 to 32 to 64,
right? Fine grain experts is great. Um,
shared experts, which is, uh, purple
versus teal at the very top, um, you
actually don't see really any gains, at
least in the mo setup. Um so they
actually end up going with no shared
experts. Um even though the Deep Seek
paper seemed to show more gain. So that
one actually is maybe more mixed given
this sort of follow-up or this you know
third party uh replication of these
kinds of
ideas. So at this point you might be
wondering you know what are common
configurations? I think I'm going to,
you know, take the page out of, you
know, last lectures playbook of looking
at a lot of the recent releases, you
know, looking at what people do and
trying to talk a little bit about the
patterns that have have arisen. Um, so
some of the early um, uh, Google papers,
so Ghart, Switch Transformer, Stmoe, um,
some of them had really large numbers of
routed experts. Um, and there was a lot
of like really interesting stuff going
on in those papers. I'd encourage you to
read them. Um some of them happened in
LSTMs and other kinds of architectures.
Um regardless you know very quickly I
think there was like kind of a period of
like 8 to 16 experts like mixtrol DBRx
Grock with two active um experts. Those
worked reasonably well but then kind of
deepsee or deepseek you know v1 comes
out. Um that has kind of the the
prototypical configuration I told you
about fine grained experts 64 of them
six actively routed two shared experts.
Um, and each sort of expert is sort of
one/4 the size of a of a normally sized
expert. Um, take that last column with a
grain of salt because I had to sort of
back them out from like config files and
things like that. So, I'm not 100% sure
about the exact ratios here. Um, so
we've then got essentially Quen 1.5,
Deepseek V3, um, Minax. These are, you
know, Chinese. They follow essentially
in the same footsteps as Deepseek v1.
the specific numbers are different but
in the in the sense that they use you
know um fine grained experts and they
often have shared experts they're very
similar to kind of this um original
deepsee configuration um OMO minimax and
llama are very recent they definitely do
all this like fine grained expert stuff
um and llama 4 also uses um a shared
expert and you kind of see um sort of
variations in configuration but you see
what's basically shared which is this
this fine grained experts ID idea and
especially for the big models like llama
4 and deepseeek very very large numbers
of routed experts or sorry not not
routed like total total experts. Yes. So
can you explain what the ratios are the
the ratio is expend uh is representing
roughly like how much each export is
sliced relative to having just the
standard dense configuration. So in
terms of hyperparameters, you know that
if you're following the rule of thumb,
your hidden dimension and sort of your
projection from in your MLP should be
about 1 to four or one to 2.6 if you're
doing a gated network, right? And so by
looking at the hidden layers of these
architectures, you can kind of see how
many times they sliced up that that
original uh uh feed forward size. So if
like
for those experts, does that mean that
like still increasing their group like
the factor. That's right. Yeah. So, so
you know, you can think of this as
roughly, you know, they have, you know,
16 normally sized experts. Oh, okay. And
so they, you know, they're they're of
course having more parameters than the
dens equivalent. They have six routed um
so they have eight total active experts
at any time each that are quarter sized.
And so you should think of them as like
roughly double the flops, right, of a of
a dense equivalent. So some arithmetic,
but hopefully uh the math is clear and
consistent hopefully. Yes.
like the ratios like one are like
so for some of the exotic ratios I'm not
quite sure why they're that way but they
are very precisely whole numbers when
you when you take the ratios between the
the FFNS and the implied hyperparameters
and so I think those are exactly the the
split counts of like how much they were
sliced but I'm not sure why they they
have one over 14 I mean like like does
it do you ever like project to like
smaller dimension because like that
ratio is so small in the MLP. So yeah.
So yeah. Oh, that's why you're asking
like do they do they down project? Yeah,
that's right. In some of them they are
actually smaller. I don't remember which
models in particular, but in some of
them I do remember they were actually
down project.
Yes. What is the intuition for wanting
more than one shared expert? Yeah, I
mean I it does kind of seem like there
was a period where where some of the
Chinese LM companies tried many shared
experts and then you know people have
come back to zero or one. And if you
look at um the OM ablations, it's not
quite clear that even one shared expert
is decisively useful. Um I think the
original motivation was that then you
have equally sized, you know, experts
like these are both one quarter sized
experts and now you have eight active
experts total and so you can keep the
sizes consistent. Otherwise, I don't
really see a particular justification
for why it should be two smaller one
versus one larger
one. Okay, cool.
So then hopefully you know you get a
sense of how the the routing works um
for a lot of these and how it's all set
up. The forward pass hopefully you fully
understand. Um now we need to think
about training and training is pretty
pretty gnarly right um and the major
challenge I foreshadowed earlier right
when we train we cannot turn on all the
experts because if we do that then we
pay the full flops cost of all the
experts right having a model that's like
I don't know 256 times more expensive to
train is a total no-go right so we need
train times sparity but sparse gaining
decisions are are obviously not
differentiable we now have a kind of
annoying RLish problem. And so we could
do any of these things like RL to
optimize gating policies. We could do
you know bandit inspired things of doing
randomization to to do exploration. Um
or you know we can just have some
heruristics that try to balance things
out right like put some loss terms in
there and hope things work out. Um you
know having gone through deep learning
classes of many kinds you can kind of
guess internally which one people use in
practice. Um and I'll talk about each
one of these three in turn.
Okay, so RL I think is one of the the
earliest things that people tried. It's
probably the most principle thing that
you can do in this space, right? You
have a you know non-ifferiable routing
decision. Well, think of that as a
policy, throw RL at it and then solve
the problem. Um unfortunately it's not
better than a lot of the other things
that you can do. Um there is a paper by
Clark at all in 2020 who were exploring
various like scaling related questions
in
uh and they do have an RL baseline that
you know I was able to dig up. Um but
unfortunately it's not really that much
better than say using hashing for
decisions and they were you know they
were really interested in benchmarking
this thing on the left called SBS which
is like a linear assignment kind of a
method and that thing you know handily
beats you know doing RL and I think In
practice, the the gradient variances and
complexity means that it's pretty
finicky to use and no one, you know, at
at scale has really used um an RL based
approach to optimize these gating
decisions as far as I know. Um a thing
that has been done much more at scale um
is stochastic approximations of various
kinds. Um so what they might do is they
might add a bit of you know
perturbations. Um so here is an example
of one um from Shazir in 2017. Um this
is one of the early uh papers where
they're still going to do kind of top k
routing. So they're going to keep the
top k elements of this h of x operation
and they're going to softmax that to get
the gate. But what we're going to do to
get this you know h of x operation is
kind of the following. So what we're
going to do is we're going to have our
original sort of linear you know
affinity. This is identical to what we
were doing before. Um, we were basically
just computing, you know, our inputs X
and, you know, a sort of learned weight
for each gate. And so this part's the
same, but I'm actually now going to
jitter it a little bit. I'm going to add
a normal and then I'm going to pick sort
of a W noise scale um that's learned.
And this thing is going to control how
much noise to inject into this process.
And you can kind of think of this as a
stochcastic exploration policy. And by
manipulating W noise in particular ways
like sort of a kneeling it down or doing
various things I can control the
exploration exploitation trade-offs um
that this is going to have right and so
this is going to give you one solution
to the to the explore exploit dilemma um
and especially if you're noising things
up each expert might randomly get you
know some other tokens that it wasn't
expecting to get. So it'll lead to
experts that are less specialized but
maybe a little bit more robust. Um and
so that that seems generally quite nice.
Um of course the stochasticity also
means that you don't get as much
specialization and that leads to loss of
efficiency. Um and you know there's
another approach that people have done
where they sort of multiply the router
loits um or sorry they they uh add yeah
have a multiplicative perturbation to
the to the router logets um with the
goal of getting less brittle experts. Um
but this sort of jitter process was kind
of removed in some of the later papers
because they found it just didn't work
as well as some of the heristic loss
based approaches. And so this was an
approach that was tried in a couple this
kind of stochastic routing tricks were
were tried in a couple of the the early
Google papers. Um but I think that has
generally been abandoned by a lot of the
the people training these.
Okay. So yes, um for the stochcastic
like what problem does that solve?
Because we're still taking the top K. So
we still can't differentiate backwards,
right? Well, if you think of this, so
the question was um we still can't
differentiate because we're taking the
top K. But if you kind of change the
your interpretation of the problem a
little bit, um if you think about a
bandit problem, right, it has the same
structure as this where you know you
pull a bandit arm and you don't see any
of the other arms. So you can't, you
know, really allocate your resources
efficiently. If you pull some of the
other ones at random, now you've got
enough data to be able to do some
optimization. And so this jittering is
very similar to in spirit to this kind
of like epsilon greedy style exploration
thing where you're randomly pulling some
of the other arms with some probability
where the probability itself depends on
how confident you are about this routing
decision. So that's kind of the
intuition and then of course you know um
that's going to give you some way of of
getting some signal back.
Okay. So, um the thing that in practice
um people have ended up with is you know
we don't do any of that. We don't do you
know RL we don't do stochastic
exploration. Um but we rely on really
another mechanism to sort of keep things
reasonable. So if we're doing top two
routing right technically speaking we do
get some signal in the gradient descent
process because we can compare the top
two you know uh experts that we did
evaluate. Um and so it's possible to do
you know some optimization but when we
do you know ignore if we if we drop all
the other constraints um the big issue
that arises is you just end up sort of
picking one expert all the time and that
expert is good at everything and all the
other experts are terrible right you end
up in this local minimum where you've
routed all of your tokens to one experts
all the time so really the key game
becomes then how do we get out of that
local minimum and loss balancing or like
balancing losses is really the key trick
to get out of this. And this is this is
kind of important to understand because
this is the the loss that mostly
everyone actually uses to train the
right. So if you were zoning out
earlier, you know, you probably should
make sure to pay attention to these this
particular set of equations here. Um so
this is originally from the the switch
transformer um from fetus at all in 2022
and they add this particular loss where
what they're going to do is they're
going to you know loop all over each of
the experts and they're going to take
you know the you could think of this as
an inner product between the vector f
and the the vector p. And so what are
these vectors? Well f is for each of the
experts this is the fraction of the
tokens that were allocated to expert I.
So you can think of this as kind of a
probability vector that's telling me you
know what fraction of my tokens in my
batch or in my you know whatever the
unit is here um did I route to expert
per I. Now P of I is the fraction of the
router probability that was allocated to
expert I. So the router probability is
kind of the um the the original sort of
softmaxed routing decision that I was
sort of intending to send. Right. So
this is kind of measuring P of I is what
was sort of the the intended probability
from the router and then um F of I was
what was the actual sort of like you
know uh what was the actual routing
decision made by the top K method. And
one thing that's kind of interesting to
to look at here is let's say we take the
derivative of that loss with respect to
to P of I. So you know this is a a
linear function with respect to P of I
and you'll see that the strongest
downweing action happens on the sort of
biggest experts with the biggest
allocations. Right? So the it's actually
in fact proportional to the amount of
tokens that you get. So you're going to
be pushed downwards um sort of more
strongly if you got more tokens. And so
this is kind of the basic behavior of
this loss. And you know almost everybody
uses this kind of F.P kind of a of a
trick to try to balance tokens across
different units. So the basic unit that
you might want to balance over um
initially is batches. You might want
each batch to get allocated evenly to
experts but you might actually have
other kinds um of uh balancing that you
might want to do. Um and Deepseek does
uh exactly this kind of thing. I'll talk
about all the variants that they've
thrown in but you know the first thing
is per expert balancing per batch. So
each batch they want to make sure
experts get an even number of tokens and
you know this is from the deepseek paper
and hopefully this looks you know very
familiar to you. This is exactly the
same you know F.P P inner product
structure as you saw before you know P
of I is defined a little bit differently
that's S of I of T you know but that
should be familiar from earlier as well
that's the softmax pre-top K right so
hopefully this looks all pretty good to
you um the other thing you might want
though is you know you might want to
balance across experts that's all well
and good but you might also want to
think about the systems concerns right
because you're going to shard your
experts onto different devices and you
might want to balance per device right
and so you might have another loss
that's essentially the same structure,
but instead of summing, you know, which
tokens go to which experts, you might
measure which tokens go to which
devices, right? And that's going to be a
different f that's measured over the
device groups rather than over each
expert. And so now you can set up a
different loss to balance over devices.
You optimize this. you're naturally
going to try to learn routing functions
that make sure each GPU or each TPU,
what have you, um, have an even number
of tokens leading to even utilization,
right? And that would be great from a
systems
perspective. So, basically, everyone
does, you know, kind of this kind of a
thing. Um, and so, Deep Seek V3, um,
actually kind of innovates a little bit.
This is this is kind of cool, and I
don't think I've seen this before. It's
one of the uh first things in thee world
that doesn't actually come from Google
really. Um which is that they have
gotten rid of this per expert balancing
term. They've gotten rid of this
entirely and instead what they now do is
they basically take their soft max
scores and they add a little fudge
factor B of I where B of I is a little
fudge factor score for each expert.
Right? So expert I you know might get
upweed or downweed. So, if if an expert
isn't getting enough tokens, you know,
it's going to uh be given a higher B of
and then that's going to allow it to
grab more tokens. Um, and the way that
this works is um uh the way that this
works is that they're going to learn
BOFi through a really simple online
gradient scheme, online learning. And so
they're going to measure at each batch,
you know, what are each of the experts
getting, like are they getting an even
number of tokens? And if they're not
getting enough tokens, they add sort of
gamma, some learning rate to B of I,
sort of making it higher. If they're if
they're getting too many tokens, they're
going to subtract gamma, making that
expert slightly less attractive, right?
So they're just learning little, you
know, offsets for each of the S of I.
And notice here, you know, you're only
using the B of I to make the routing
decisions. You're not actually sending
it over as part of your gating weights,
right? That's a that's a sort of
somewhat important thing to do. So they
call this auxiliary loss free balancing.
If you go and read the Deepseek V3
paper, which all of you should because
it's a it's a really nice paper, um
they'll make a big deal about how this
makes training so stable, so great. Um
so wonderful. Um and then of course you
like keep reading the section and
they're like actually but we decided
that you know for each sequence maybe we
still want to be balanced and this
doesn't work well enough so we've added
the the you know the heristic loss back.
So they do have um something called a
complimentary sequence-wise auxiliary
loss that you know is basically exactly
the auxiliary loss um that they decided
they needed because what they wanted to
do was to balance um uh load balance the
experts at a per sequence level rather
than a per batch level. Um I'm not sure
why they do this particular thing rather
than any other sort of you know uh B of
style trick but that's just kind of what
they do um in deepseek v3. So it's not
fully auxiliary lossfree as they'd like
you to believe. Okay. Oh yes. Question.
This is a bit of an unfair question, but
if we did not have to worry about
systems optimizations, do you think the
performance of this model would be a lot
better or would it stay roughly the
same? If we did not think about systems
optimization, would the performance of
this model be better or stay the same?
When you say this model, what do you
mean? Deep Seek V3 or like just in
general like this model never. So are
you saying like if we ignore the systems
concerns um do we think are still good?
Is that kind of one way of asking that
question? Like would the performance on
downstream pass for example be better
than what we have right now? Yeah. So I
think um I didn't have to balance this
like I must set roughly equal number of
tokens for every expert or Yeah. Yeah.
That's right. That's right. Well, I
think actually per expert balancing this
term, right? This is not a systems
concern. So, you still want to do this
because if you don't do this, what
you'll find um and actually there's, you
know, I'm going to keep referring to the
old mode paper because they have so many
ablations. They have a a really nice
ablation where they get rid of exactly
this. Um, and what they find is um
basically early on in training the model
just picks like one or two experts and
all the other experts are dead. Like the
router never sends anything to them. So,
you're just wasting memory at that
point, right? So now you've just lost
performance for free. You've effectively
gotten a smaller model. And so even if
you ignore all the other like device
balancing parallelism concerns, you've
just gotten a worse model because you
didn't properly allocate your your
experts, right? It's the same way as
like you want to use all your
parameters, right? You would like to
effectively use your parameters. You
want to do expert debalancing.
Sorry, say uh device. What does device
refer to? Yeah, actually um so normally
this would refer to like GPU or TPU.
There is a subtlety. I I'll talk about
this maybe in the very last or second to
last slide. Um there are more
sophisticated and cool versions of this
where you try to balance things to
minimize communication costs as well.
And so there's you know broader notions
of device like you know one rack or
whatever else but here it usually refers
to like GPU.
Yes. going back to the fact that like
hashing as a routing algorithm seems to
improve performance like is there
intuition for that because that's
effectively just like randomly choosing
a um like one of the few forward members
to send it through right so like why
does having multiple copies of that I
guess each of which get less data why
does that make performance better yes
the question was um why does hashing do
anything at all um I don't have the you
really precise intuition for this. But
you can make arguments either two ways.
One is, you know, even if you're
hashing, the same tokens are going to go
to the same, you know, or the same kinds
of, you know, sequences are going to go
to the same expert every time, right?
And so each expert will still get some
deterministic subset of the inputs. And
so there's some specialization that can
still occur. It's just non-semantic or,
you know, non-learned. Um, and if you're
a distribution Zipian, like the word
'the', might dominate one expert, you
know, and so you might still get
actually semantic specialization where
like one expert is effectively dominated
by like very frequent things, but like a
random uh routing function probably
wouldn't be a day like a pure random
thing that's not dependent on input.
Yeah, I would bet that that would be
really terrible. Yes, I have never run
or seen that, but yes, I think that
would be that would be horrible. Good.
Yes. Yeah. So for like during LM like
you have many layers right many
transform I think in the lecture you
mentioned that each expert okay so like
you do like ad like 32 layers like 64
experts that's like a lot of GPUs or I
wonder if like experts are bundled
together on like a single GPU is that
the question was like won't you need
lots of GPUs if you have lots of layers
and lots of experts. Yeah if you if you
exclusively give a GPU to a single
expert. Yes, that would be that would be
kind of crazy. Um, but you would kind of
shard things so that each GP would hold,
you know, enough of these units um to,
you know, effectively use memory, right?
The name of the game in parallelism is
you always want to use up all of your
memory because that's one of your
resources, right? You don't want to
paralyze more than you have
to. Cool. Okay. Excellent. Oh, okay. I
did put the ablation in here. Yeah. So,
this is exactly what happens to the
question of what happens if you don't
do, you know, um, uh, expert balancing
loss. I think the the great picture to
see is this bottom left one. If you
don't do load balancing, you know, what
are the tokens assigned to which expert?
You see the pink and the yellow expert.
They just like kind of take over. They
take up, you know, about 50% of the
tokens. All the other experts are dead.
They do nothing, right? And so you've
wasted, you know, the majority of your
experts at this point. You know, uh six
out of eight of your experts. Um and
you've created a two experte
unintentionally. And you know that gives
you uh you know worse losses up seen up
on the top right the teal lines. Um of
course maybe that's still better than
the dense model because at least you've
got two experts going. Um but you could
have done better right counterfactually
speaking. Okay. So um I won't go quite
as deep as I could into the system side
because I haven't really started to
cover you know the core systems concepts
necessary for you to deeply appreciate a
lot of the parallelism concerns like you
know basically the hierarchy of
communication speeds in a data center
and so on. Um but really as I said
before you know one thing to keep in
mind is just how nicely can fit into
devices. you you know the the thing that
people say is expert parallel you know
that involves sending or putting one or
a few um you know uh experts onto each
device and what happens when you you
know are basically processing a token.
Well, you would hit the router and after
the router, you now have picked few
experts. And so now you would have a
collective communication call like all
to all communication dispatch that would
send the tokens to the relevant devices.
You know, the feed fors would compute um
you know their outputs and then you
would return the tokens um to sort of
where they belong or you would you know
combine I guess multiple experts and so
you would need another sort of
collective communication call. And so if
your your feed forward computations are
sort of big and beefy enough, you can
kind of pay for the cost of basically
doing this expert parallelism. Um, and
the one of the the thing that's nice
about this is that it's another form of
uh parallelism in your in your toolkit.
So you've got on the right side, you
know, you know, data parallelism, model
parallelism of, you know, two or three
different kinds and then you've got
expert parallelism and you can combine
all of them to come up with sort of ways
of trading off all the resources you
have. So the communication speed, the
amount of data that you have, your batch
size, um, and your your, um, number of
experts and your memory. So, um, I'm not
going to go into too much detail about
how specifically this is going to help,
but keep in mind that this gives you
another sort of tool in your expert
toolkit.
Another thing um that is also you know
useful is let's say you have multiple
experts um on a single device you know
you might hope that because the
computations are sparse like let's say
you know token one this first token you
know gets multiplied to export zero the
second one is expert one and this third
one's expert two so this is really three
matrix multiplies that are small and
sparse and you might hope that modern
GPUs can sort of take advantage of these
kinds of you know complex uh these kinds
of sparse matrix multiplications. Um and
that's exactly right. So if you you know
lay out your your sort of experts
correctly and the weights are sort of
fused in the right way then modern sort
of sparse matrix multiply sort of
engines can sort of effectively make
sure that you're not wasting any flops
in doing this one big matrix multiply.
So, so modern libraries like meta mega
blocks can basically take advantage of
this you know device level sort of
sparity support to do multiple expert
computations sort of all at once. So
this is yet another advantage that you
get um
with. Um so one fun side thing um which
maybe isn't mysterious to you all
anymore because you've sort of grown up
in the era of GPT4. Um but when the GPT4
API first came out, it was kind of
mysterious to me because when you set
the temperature to zero, you know, you
kind of got different responses even
though it was supposed to be
deterministic. Um, and lots of people
speculated about why would that be. Um,
I'm not saying this is the the answer to
that reason. Um, but there is actually a
interesting source of randomness in
right. So in movies, think about you
know what happens. You're going to route
your tokens to experts, right? And
experts live in different devices. Um,
it could be that you know you have a lot
of examples. You're going to batch of
course batch your queries when you're
processing them. And so if you've
batched your queries, these tokens are
going to get routed into different
experts. So imagine you've got, you
know, this this uh this batch to process
and you've got a bunch of experts, but
for whatever reason, this batch really
loves expert number three. Like all the
tokens go to expert number three. So now
what happens? Well, the device for
expert number three doesn't have enough
memory to load all of those tokens. Um
and then what happens is what people
call token dropping. And this happens at
training time as well. You often have
what's called a load factor where you're
sort of controlling the maximum number
of allowed tokens. And if the router
just allocates too many tokens to an
expert, you just drop those tokens off
either for systems reasons or because
you're just worried that that expert is
going to take over at least in the
training time. And so now this token has
gotten dropped and it's not going to get
anything at all. Like the MLP is just
going to do a zero computation and the
residual connection is just going to
pass things straight forward. Um, and
then you're going to return an output.
And so if your token got dropped, you're
going to get a different result than if
your token didn't get dropped. And so
based on, you know, who else is in your
batch, can induce stochasticity both at
training time and inference time, which
is like kind of an interesting thing
that you don't normally think about
because you almost never think about
like cross batch effects um when uh
doing
inference. Okay, so that's kind of the
the main bits of of you know the the
main basic components of of building the
fun side thing. If you were to actually
go out tomorrow and trying to train ane
um I think the system side will make you
a little bit sad, but the other thing
that would make you sad is probably the
stability side of things. Um so kind of
have this property that sometimes
they'll just kind of blow up on you if
you try to fine-tune them. They're very
difficult to fine-tune and they'll
sometimes blow up on you. Um and so you
know um Barrett Zoff and others um
really studied they had a whole paper on
basically trying to make more stable and
there's a paper which is the one I'm I'm
referencing here um whose entire purpose
is to stabilize training and there's a
couple tricks that I'll I'll mention um
that I think are relevant and that
people do. Um the first one is you know
if if you're doing the router softmax so
this goes back to last lecture about
stability right like what did I say
about stability well the thing to be
afraid of is the soft maxes right the
softmax is always where you want to be
afraid and so um so for the um they do
all the computations in float 32 for the
router computations just to be safe
right um and sometimes they also add the
you know an auxiliary zlos so hopefully
you remember that it was just last
lecture you know you do log of the sum
of the the exponentiated you know values
in the softmax and you square that and
you add that as an extra loss right so
this is going to keep the the normalizer
values near one which is nice for
stability um so this is actually one of
the places where zlos was used earlier
before it got sort of more popular for
training um models you can kind of see
the effects here um if you look at the
losses I think the the center the second
plot here is maybe a great one you know
if you remove the zloss from your router
uh routing function you see these like
giant loss spikes um in your validation
loss where you know the model just kind
of goes a little bit crazy um for a
couple iterations and then gets kind of
pulled back. Of course, it like still
trains okay, but you are better off
having the Z loss than not having a
Z-loss. There is a pretty noticeable gap
in the validation loss by the end here,
right? Um, other things that can happen,
um, people, you know, of course you want
to fine-tune your like also RLHF your if
you're going to, you know, ship and
release it. Um, but this turns out to
be, uh, kind of problematic. some of the
earlier work, you know, when people were
starting to do, this was back in kind of
the BERT and P5 era. So there was a lot
of fine-tuning going on. Um, and you
know, one of the things that people saw
was, you know, actually there's a lot of
overfitting that happens if you were
kind of doing uh sparse models. You see
this big gap between train and val,
right? This blue and orange line. Um
whereas the dense model, this green and
red line, has a smaller train test gap.
Um, and so there was a lot of worries
about overfitting because you have these
like gigantic parameter models that
you're fine-tuning on small data. Um,
one of the solutions that was proposed
at the time, I don't think this is very
popular, um, as far as I understand, is
to architect yours such that not every
layer is layer, but you like let's say
alternate dense layers and layers. Then
you can just fine-tune the dense layers
and then that will that will still be
fine, right? That behaves just like a
dense model. Um, so that was fine.
Another solution um the one that we saw
in the the Deepseek MOE paper is just
kind of use a lot of data like if
overfitting is a problem you know we
have access to lots and lots of SFT data
just shovel all of those guys in so in
the case of uh Deepseek they use 1.4
four million training examples. Um then
maybe you're you're not quite as worried
about these overfitting concerns. Um the
last thing I'll end with which is a is a
trick in the toolkit that I that people
have done and seen um is upycling. And
so this idea is to take a dense model
like the one over here um and then you
take your MLP and you make a bunch of
copies of it. um and then you maybe
perturb it and then you have your router
that's initialized from scratch and then
you just pretend this is and then you
train it from that point on right you
just initialize thee from a dense model
and this is a trick that's kind of
called upycling um and you know people
have shown that if you can get it to
work um it is a very very very
cost-effective way of getting right and
thee is great for inference because not
every MLP is going to be active or uh at
inference time right So, so you're going
to you might effectively get a much
larger parameter model without doing the
training of a much larger parameter
model. Um, and several people have
succeeded at this. Um, mini CPM, which
um, I'll mention again in the scaling
wall lecture, but this is a Chinese open
LLM that basically tried to build really
good small uh, language models and they
succeeded at taking a dense model and
upycling it into that you can see that
their numbers get significantly better
in the last two rows, right? So the
dense models to thee, they get a a
pretty non-trivial bump in performance.
Um Quen, uh I mentioned at the start of
this lecture, one of their earliest
attempts ate was taking one of their
dense models and then building upcycled.
Um and they got, you know, fairly
significant uh performance gains
relative to sort of smaller models at
the time. Like they got models on par
with their 7B models with a 2.7 billion
parameter active model.
Um so uh to wrap up um I want to sort of
walk through the DeepSseek architecture
at the very end here. Um and hopefully
this will give you a sense of you know
the first thing I want to do is I want
you to understand the DeepSeek V3
architecture setup and all the changes
that they did. Um because that's an
example of a modern high performance
open source system. I also want you to
maybe appreciate that architectures
don't change that much. Deepseek v1 or
you know deepseek v1 um is uh you know
it's not that new it's like maybe a year
and a half or something maybe two years
old um and they basically nailed the
architecture at that point right so I
want to see I want you to see what they
changed from that very ear the earliest
attempt um to their big training run so
this is the the very first starting
point this is um deepseek I'm calling it
v1 but actually you know probably the
right way to refer to it is deepseek
it's a 16 billion parameter model with
2.8 of those parameters active. Um, and
you've seen already this diagram over
here. This is the um shared two shared
plus 64 fine grained um experts um of
which uh four of them are active at a
time or maybe about six of them are
active at a time. Sorry. Um and the
routing you know you've already seen
this I presented this in the in the
middle of the lecture here. This is the
very standard top K routing uh where the
softmax is at the bottom before the the
top K selection. Um and for balancing
right at training time all they do is to
add this auxiliary loss balancing term
right both the expert and device level
balancing terms right so hopefully you
know you remember those from earlier so
that's the the v1 um and then um they
saw how sort of effective their model
was so I guess to add some more context
right deepseeek originally had a dense
model and then they had ae model and
thee model was remarkably good and so
when they went to v2 um they went
straight to thee and now this is a 236
billion parameter model of which 21 of
those billion parameters are active
right so you need a lot of memory but
your your flops consumption for for
inferencing this model is not so bad now
um the architecture is identical I
copied literally the the same figure
because the architecture is literally
the same minus changes to the number of
you know experts that are active um and
uh we've got now sort of some new things
happening but not too many new things.
So the top selector is the same. So the
equation from before, this previous
equation, this is identical. This this
is still how they do things. Um but they
have this very clever trick that they
add on. And this is um you know, I was
going to say at the very beginning, you
know, what's the drawback of having fine
grained experts? Why can't I have, I
don't know, uh 1024 fine- grained
experts or 2046 fine grained experts?
Well, the problem is when you shard your
experts very finely and you have a lot
of active experts, right, you're going
to have to route to those experts,
right? So, your communication costs
potentially grow and if you're very
fragmented, you might have to send a lot
of tokens to a lot of devices, right?
And so, the clever thing they come up
with is to say, I'm not just going to,
you know, at for each batch route to the
top K exports naively, which might force
me to send my tokens to lots of devices.
What I'm going to do is I'm going to
first pick top M devices, right? So I'm
going to do my, you know, normal scoring
calculation, but I'm first going to sort
of subset the set of allowed devices to
top M, right? And once I've picked my
devices, then I'm going to pick top K
for each token within each device,
right? So so now I've restricted the
devices. This really controls the
communication cost. And now this gives
you more efficient training when you're
scaling up to these gigantic sizes,
right? you need to start really engaging
with the systems aspect of things when
you're training a 236 billion parameter
model. The other thing which reflects
the systems concerns that are necessary
at this scale is that they add a
communication balancing loss. Um, one
way of thinking about things is, you
know, for an expert, there's kind of
inputs and outputs, right? The inputs
are, you know, the the token comes in
and you route to your expert. And the
outputs are, you know, you have to kind
of bring the tokens back where they
belong, right? So, if a batch belongs on
this device, it has to go back where the
original device was. So, we have to
think about both the input communication
cost and the output communication cost.
And so, they add a balancing loss to try
to balance out the output communication
cost as well, not just the sort of input
side. Um so that's a minor note but you
can kind of see their attention to
detail on trying to make sure all the
different sort of systems aspects are
properly um taken care of. And then
finally we kind of get to to the you
know the big deepseek uh v3 sorry that
should say v3 not v2 up there 671
billion parameters of which uh 37 are
active. You know once again um you know
exactly the same figure because thee
architecture itself doesn't change.
that's stayed the same since Deepseek
MOE, right? Like if it works, don't
change it. Um they do change a couple
things. Um maybe they were, you know,
hearing you all say, why don't you
normalize to one? And so, you know,
they've normalized the gate to one.
They've moved kind of the softmax
normalizer operation up there. Um but
they're not actually exponentiating um
sort of the the sort of gating
decisions. They're actually taking
sigmoids um which is a sort of softer
sort of more nicely behaved operation um
you know, than the soft max. So they
they've got some changes here, but
conceptually this is still the same as
the top K routing decision, right? You
hopefully see very very similar things
happening. And then in terms of the
losses, um they've gone to this
auxiliary loss-free trick of this B of I
being incremented or decremented based
on the expert load. And then they have a
sequence-wise auxiliary loss. Um and
just to, you know, add some context, why
would you want to balance different um
uh experts on a single sequence? Well,
the thing that they're very concerned
about is at training time, you know,
it's fine to to not have a sequence-wise
balancing loss, but at inference time,
it might be the case that someone sends
you very out of distribution sequences,
and that might overwhelm certain
experts, right? So, at inference time,
you can't control which sequences you
get. So, you might want sort of stronger
balancing that operates at a single
sequence level rather than overall batch
level. Okay. And then in the Oh, sorry.
Yes. Um, does 3 still do like the top M
devices like does it keep the B2
improvement? Yeah, they keep the top M
improvement. They do not keep uh for
example the communication loss. So so
they've they've jettisoned some things
but top M is a I mean it seems like a
pretty clever idea they keep it.
Yeah. Yeah. But it's not like they they
always add things. They have removed
some of the things. Um, and so in the
last two or so minutes, uh, of the
class, I'm going to go over the none
parts of Deepseek V3 because I think,
you know, we're already at the point
where I've explained most of DeepSeek
V3. I might as well go through the the
steps of explaining the rest of Deepseek
V3 at this point. So, you all know kind
of how that works. So, um, they have a
clever sort of optimization for the
attention piece called MLA or multi head
latent attention. And um you all
actually already know all the
ingredients that you need to understand
this because at the end of last lecture
you know I talked about like GQA and MHA
right so those are all inference
optimizations that you need in order to
optimize the size of the KV catch. So
the deepse folks take a different tac or
different approach at optimizing this
instead of reducing the number of heads
um they're actually going to sort of
project the heads into a lower
dimensional space. So you have your
inputs H of T and instead of sort of
generating the K's and V's directly from
these H of T's, what I'm going to do is
I'm going to first generate a
lowdimensional C. This you can think of
this as like a, you know, compressed
version of H. And this C is going to be
smaller and easier to cache. And I'm
just going to cach these C's. And
whenever I need, you know, these K's and
V's, well, I can sort of up project from
this KV sort of conceptually speaking.
And then, you know, I can take the inner
products with the Q's, right? So you can
kind of see how this would be a KV cache
savings if I only have to save the C
instead of the higher dimensional H of
T. Um and that's exactly the idea. So
you take your H of T, you project it
into a lower dimensional C and then you
up project this back into the K's and
V's, right? And if the C's are small,
well that's you've compressed the KV
cache. That's good. Um and then you know
in terms of the computation, right? If
you're thinking about flops, well, you
might think, well, this is not good
because I have to multiply an extra
matrix W U K, right? I didn't have this
matrix before. That's an extra matrix
multiply that I have to pay for. But
kind of the clever thing here is
remember that on the other side of K,
right? I'm going to take K. Q, right,
there, that Q.K is going to be an inner
product in the attention operation,
right? And Q itself has a projection
matrix Q. And so the trick here is you
can merge this W U K and this Q matrix
together into one matrix. So I haven't
gotten any extra matrix multiplies. I've
just merged this new matrix multiply
into my other one. Right? This is, you
know, just associivity. Um I can just
merge the two. Um they also compress the
queries for memory savings during
training, but really that one is is not
quite as necessary because it doesn't
interact at all with the KV cache. Um,
I'm only going to mention this last one
in passing. Um, because it is a
subtlety, but it's kind of a clever
subtlety that you realize, which is that
this original trick, this sort of thing
that I just described at the top is not
compatible with rope, right? And the
reason is because, you know, the rope
matrices, you know, basically you have
the Q's and the K's and you rotate each
of those Q's and the K's by multiplying
with a rotation matrix RQ and RK. But if
you do that, then these RQs and RKs are
in between the query projection and this
up uh latent vector up projection
matrix. And since I can't reorder these
matrix multiplies, you know, rope kind
of gets in the way. And they still have
a a solution of basically um doing rope
on non-compressed dimensions. That's
kind of a side point. I think it's not
quite as important. You can kind of look
at the paper if you're super interested.
The other thing that they do, and this
is the last thing I promise, is that
they have a a minor change in their loss
function called MTP where they predict
multiple tokens um in parallel. And so
what they can do is normally, right, you
have your inputs, you shift them to the
to the left by one. So you're predicting
one token in the future and then your
transformer is going to predict all
those tokens, right? That's your normal
transformer loss. But then what you can
do is right before you make those
predictions you can take you know the
hidden state you can pass it to a very
lightweight one layer transformer and
that model can predict you know one
token in the future right so now the
model is not just predicting the next
token it's predicting the two tokens
into the future right so that hopefully
all makes sense um and this is just a
small lightweight model that can do that
um you can sort of see the architecture
right here um the one thing that is is
kind of disappointing that I learned as
I was sort researching for this lecture
is actually they only do MTP with one
token ahead. So even though they have
this very complicated diagram of how
they could do it for many tokens, um
turns out it's only done for for one
token. Okay, so now I'm all done. Um are
kind of now at the core of how you would
build and deploy, you know, a really
high performance large scale system. And
they take advantage of of kind of the
sparsity idea that you don't need all of
the uh parameters all the time. and
discrete routing is the real big
challenge. And this is I think one of
the big reasons why didn't immediately
catch on. It's very scary to have to try
to optimize this top K routing
decisions. Um but heristics somehow seem
to work, right? Like they they just do.
And so there's a lot of empirical
evidence now that at least for for uh
flop constraint settings is just a good
idea. It's cost effective. Um you should
do it. So definitely worth learning. Um
thanks a lot uh for listening.