So this is lecture 10. We're going to
take a brief respit from scaling laws.
Um and we're going to talk about
inference. So the question of inference
is a very simple one. Given a fixed
model that we've trained, generate
responses given prompts. Okay.
Um first we're going to start by
understanding what the implications of
inference are um and the workload um
that it entails. Um and then we're going
to talk about ways of making inference
uh faster. And throughout this lecture
you're going to see that there's a lot
of inference is a very deep topic. It's
actually the uh we didn't do inference
uh last year in lectures. So this is the
first year we're doing it. But there's
actually many many topics that could
span multiple lectures which I'll try to
condense into one. So inference shows up
in multiple different places. The most
obvious place is if you actually want to
use a model, you want to use it to chat.
Um you're using cursor or something to
do code completion. If you're running
batch a data processing job using your
language model, all of these cases
demand inference because you need to
generate tokens from your actual model.
But it also shows up in other contexts.
If you want to even evaluate your model
um let's say on instruction following
you need to do inference. Um there's a
lot of interest in test time compute
which means uh thinking more before um
you actually output some um uh the final
answer and that's also more inference
because thinking is basically generate
tokens. And then finally, even training
itself, if you're using reinforcement
learning, you need to sample responses
and then evaluate them based on some
reward. And that also requires
inference. So inference isn't just I
want to put up a chatbot demo. Inference
actually is going to underly many of the
basic functions of a language model. And
even though it's one lecture, I want to
stress how actually important it is for
uh many things. And we'll probably come
back to this when we talk about um in
alignment um later in the class. So now
inference is important. So the theme of
this class is efficiency and efficiency
clearly matters. Training is a one-time
cost but inference you repeat multiple
times. So here's some you know anecdotal
uh um stats on why inference is a big
deal. So Sam says OpenAI generates a
100red billion words a day which is
quite a quite a lot. Um and even cursor
which is not that new of a a product is
um allegedly generating a billion lines
of accepted code um each day.
So um it's just giving you an idea of
how much inference is accounting for and
you know costs of inference compared to
training um are definitely you know
increasing. So how do you measure what
inference good inference looks like? So
there's time to first token TTFT. So
this is how long a user an individual
user needs to wait before any generation
happens at all. And this matters clearly
for interactive applications. If you
have a big prompt and then you have to
wait there for 10 seconds, that may not
be a good user experience. Latency is
how fast tokens are arriving after maybe
the first first token. Um this also
matters for interactive um
applications. Throughput is is something
a bit different. Throughput is um how
many tokens in general are generated per
not for overall users. So this is it's
particularly useful in batch processing
applications. So you can think about the
throughput is um high throughput doesn't
mean low latency because uh some you
know requests might just take a very
long time and you still have high
throughput. Latency is is kind of like
the you know worst case over any
individual
user. So what do you need to uh think
about when you think about the
efficiency of inference? Um so in
training
um the the key idea is that you get to
see all the tokens at least a supervised
training which means that you can
parallelize over the the sequence. This
is exploited heavily in the transformer,
right? So you've done the transformer
training. You know that you basically
construct these tensors over the entire
sequence and it's just like tensor
tensor tensor uh you know mats and then
you get your output. But the the key
defining feature of inference at least
for transformers is that you have to
generate sequentially. You can't
parallelize because um the generation of
a a token depends on all the past. So
this is going to be the key thing that's
going to make inference a lot harder and
in particular it's going to be harder to
utilize all the compute that's uh
available and it's going to be memory
limited as we'll see uh in detail later.
So a lot of people are doing inference.
Um anyone who's actually has a product
and platform quickly realizes that these
uh cost in doing large models is going
to go up. So they spent a lot of uh time
and you know engineering effort trying
to reduce that time. So both providers
serving closed models and providers
serve open m open weight models uh pay a
lot of attention to um to imprints um
more so than I think the average
academic because we're not actually
serving any models. We're just training
and getting a score and putting in the
paper. But people who are actually
serving models pay a lot of attention to
inference.
Um so there's also a bunch of open
source packages which are um interesting
to to look at uh as
well. Okay. So um I want to understand
the inference workload uh kind of in
detail. So I'm going to review briefly
um the sort of this transformer math
that we uh um you did in assignment one
and we talked a little bit about it
during the the first week of of class.
So this is from the scaling um JXML book
which um is is something you guys should
really take a look at. I think it does
an excellent job of outlining many of
the of the key concepts um here. Um and
they have this really nice diagram that
shows essentially the the computation
graph taking an input and having it go
through attention and the MLP layers. Um
in particular um we're going to use this
notation. So just to kind of review this
this quickly. So B is the number of
sequences in your batch. L is the number
of layers. T is the sequence length. Uh
you can think about as the number of
tokens you're going to generate u or or
query using. S is also the sequence
length but how many you're um kind of
conditioning on in your prompt. V is the
vocabulary. D is the dimensionality of
model. F is the MLP hidden dimension
which is usually four times D. um h is
the attention head dimension. N is the
number of query heads. So generally N
times H equals D. Um and then in
GQA group query attention you have a
different number of key value heads as
query heads. Usually K is smaller than N
and um G is the number of um of groups.
Um so K * G equals N. Okay. Okay. And
this diagram shows that you take your X,
you feed through the the Q KV matrices,
um, and you do a bunch of bunch of
things. Um, okay.
So, so remember that the flops required
for a fever pass is six times the number
of of tokens, which is B * T times the
number of parameters uh, plus for the
tension. there's another order t. So t *
t is t ^2 um
dependence. Okay, so let's also review
arithmetic and intensity which is going
to help us characterize when something
is compute limited versus memory
limited. Um so just to start with the
basic you know u map mall. So let's take
a matrix X which is B by B by D and a
matrix W D by F and you know just to
give some color to this uh computation B
is the batch size D is the hidden
dimension and F is the up projection
matrix in the gated
MLP. Um so next let's do count the
number of flops and memory um read and
writes u for just doing X times W. Okay,
so we're going to start with um
initialize to zero. And what one has to
do for this is we're going to um read X
from HBM. So you that means it incurs a
memory cost of 2 * B * D assuming
everything is in BF 16. Um you also read
W. So that's 2 * D * F. Um then you do
the the mat mole and that encurs 2 * um
b * d * f flops. So remember this is
from the first lecture so hopefully this
is review. Um and then you have to write
it back out which is you uh have to pay
another transfer. Okay. So the total
number of flops is uh just the the
mammal and the number of bytes
transferred is essentially the size of
all the the matrices that are read and
written and arithmetic intensity is
basically the ratio. Um so the ratio is
this expression. Um and in general just
to simplify things a bit um generally
the batch size is much less than D and
F. um B maybe you know hundreds and a
DNF might be you know thousands or tens
of thousands.
Um so I'm using simp here just to keep
myself from making silly mistakes. Um so
basically I'm letting C go to infinity
um and D scales as C * B and F scales as
C * B and that gets you a simplified
equation of B. Okay. So the arithmetic
intensity is B for this particular
matrix
multiplication. Um and um and the
okay so the way to interpret this is how
many flops are done per bite that was
transferred.
So now um the second part is you look at
the accelerator which for H100 flops per
second is um
98989 teraflops memory bandwidth 3.3 ter
bytes per second and you divide and that
gives you what is called the accelerator
intensity and um if you look at the
computational intensity um which is B if
it's greater accelerated intensity that
means you're compute limited that means
you're able to use all the the GPUs or
TPUs and if you're less than that then
you're memory limited which is uh you
know bad and so you're computer limited
in this matrix multiplication case if B
is greater than uh 295 uh for a H100 and
all of this is a bit idealized the
actual details there's it's this is
giving you a kind of a first order
approximation
um so in extreme extreme case. So
generally if you that means if you use
batches of size let's say 300 then
you'll be be able to saturate the GPU.
But what happens if your batch is really
small? So in particular B equals 1 which
essentially corresponds to a matrix
vector product then the arithmetic
intensity is basically one and that is
really really bad. that means you're
going to be um memory limited and which
which kind of makes sense because
basically you're reading and writing
this D times or actually you're just
reading this D* F matrix and you're
performing essentially in the same
number of flops right so the ratio
between the flops and the reads is the
same which is gives you one and one is
bad you want a lot of flops to be done
for any memory read because memory reads
are uh
slow But this is in in essence what
happens with generation right because
you're proceeding token by token. We'll
see that basically um your arithmetic
intensity is going to be like one and
that's why uh generation is going to be
memory limited um and not compute
limited. Okay. So this is a very simple
example that I think gets at the core of
why uh generation is going to be slow.
So maybe I'll pause and take any
questions on this um just to make sure
everyone's clear.
Yeah,
I mean when doing why don't we have a
batch size of say larger than one. So I
think I heard the question why don't we
have a batch size more than one. So I'll
get to why you can uh but there's um
batch size is going to mean batch size
time sequence length um
later. Okay. So in summary
um matrix multiplications are the kind
of the core computation. So we just
studied a matrix multiplication and
counted the number of flops it requires
over the number of read and writes and
we show that that ratio which is
arithmetic intensity depends on one of
the dimensions in case in this case the
batch dimension and that's why big
matrices are are good because that can
saturate your um your compute whereas if
you have even a thin matrix um B equals
one that's really bad because you're
spending a lot of time reading
from memory and not doing that much uh
compute. Okay. So um now let's talk
about the arithmetic intensity of of
inference.
Um okay so let's let's just uh kind of
get more into the weeds of what
inference looks like. So, so the naive
thing you can imagine doing and all
these nice pictures are taken from this
this book um is that you have a
transformer, you give the prompt in, you
gives you logits over the the vocabulary
of the next token and you just sample
from that and then once you get that you
attach it to the prompt and then you
feed it through the transformer and you
look at the logic sample again and you
repeat, right? So that's um the sort of
most naive thing to do. Um and you know
the complexity here is is pretty bad
because each token you generate is like
n squ or t squ um you know computation
through the through the
transformer. Okay. So that that's no
good. But if you look at this closely,
you'll notice that you're doing a lot of
redundant work, right? All these um the
work um in basically encoding the prefix
basically stays the same.
So this is for a uh for a birectional uh
transformer it would be different but at
least for a auto reggressive causal
transformer it is the case that you
should be able to share a lot between
prefixes and so the solution is you
cache and you cache in the IBM HPM
because that's uh where you have enough
space to store stuff. So this is what it
looks like if you have a KV cache in
schematically.
Um
so you take your prompt the prefill step
is you feed it through the transformer
and you compute this KV cache
um and then you generate the logits over
the next token and then you
um put that into um you know take that
generated token and the the cache and
then you can feed it through the
transformer. But you've already computed
these so you don't have to do that
again. you just need to compute this new
um KV uh vector for this token and now
that allows you to more quickly generate
the next um token and and so on. So
basically you're filling up this KV
cache which corresponds to the tokens
that you've either prefilled with or
that you've generated so far. Okay. So
instead of T squ per token, it's going
to be more like
T. Okay. So concretely the KV cache is
for every sequence in your batch for
every token in your sequence for every
layer of the transformer for every head
you're going to store a hdimensional uh
vector. So you might think that this is
going to take a lot of memory and you
wouldn't be
wrong. Okay. So there's two stages of
inference. So prefill is you're given
your prompt encoded a vector. So this is
just like what you do in training. It's
paralyzable. It's fast. Your compute
limited life is good. And then you're
doing generation which is you're
generating response tokens one by one
sequentially. And this is a part that's
going to give us a lot of trouble in
terms of uh
efficiency. So now let's compute the
flops and memory IO for both the for the
transformer. So we're going to break it
down into MLP layers and the attention
layers. Um and um just notationwise,
we're going to do this computation with
s being the number of tokens we're
conditioning on. Think about the length
of the prompt. And T is the number of
tokens we're generating or or quering
using. Um and in prefill t is going to
be s because we're sort of I mean we're
not generating uh t tokens, but we're
sort of like querying um using each of
these tokens. and a generation where t
is just
one. Okay, so hopefully the matrix
multiplication is still fresh in your
head because this is going to be
essentially that but a little bit more
complicated because it's a transformer.
So we're going to count the flops and
bytes generated. Um so first we're going
to um take x which is a um b by t by d u
matrix. I think maybe these T's should
be S's. Um but um anyway, so um so that
involves doing a bunch of uh transfers.
Um uh basically the size of that matrix
times two because BF 16. Um then there's
the the three-way matrices, the up
projection, the gate, and the down
projection. They're all the same um you
know size up to transposition. Um so you
need to transfer those. Um then you do
the
um you know up projection um that's some
number of flops. So B * D * C* F. So
whenever you multiply you know two
tensors basically the contracting
dimension only gets counted once whereas
other dimensions you just you kind of
gather together. Um you need to write it
out. You also have the gate which is the
uh same same thing. You write it out.
You compute uh your um nonlinearity. You
multiply some stuff and you down project
um and that's b * t * d * f which is
basically the same number of flops and
you write um out uh the the result.
Okay. Okay. So if you look at the the
counting um I guess maybe I'll just uh
you know you can check the um you know
results. Actually you don't need to
check it because this is simp and it's
guaranteed to be you know correct. Um so
but again we're going to assume that B *
D is much smaller than DN and F and we
get that the intensity is B * T. Okay.
So this is analogous to the matrix uh
multiplication case where the in
arithmetic intensity which we want to be
high depends on how large your batches
and how many tokens you're you're
essentially generating. Okay. Okay. So
now if you look at the two stages
prefill life is good remember because we
can just make BT large enough you use a
batch size even a batch size of one
actually is is maybe okay if you have
long enough uh sequence um so that's not
a problem. Now generation this is where
it becomes a little bit harder because
you're generating one token at a time.
So T is
one right? So if t is one that means for
bt to be large you need b to be large
and b is essentially the number of
concurrent
requests. Okay. So this is kind of
interesting because your your sort of
efficiency depends on um having large
batch sizes because I mean intuitively
it makes sense if you can take a lot of
requests batch them together then uh you
can get um you know better uh efficiency
at least throughput. Um, but this also
depends on what um B is because if it's
um you're only getting a few requests at
a time, then you're not going to be able
to use your hardware very
efficiently. Um, and this is talks
speaks to the sort of the very dynamic
aspect of inference which we'll come
back to later in the
lecture. Okay, so now what about
attention? Turns out attention is even
worse um for reasons I'll I'll try to
get into. So let's do the counting flops
um bytes transferred. Okay. So I'm going
to read the QKV
um
matrices from
HPM. I'm going to compute the the
tension which is a matrix which is Q *
K. And the number of flops is B * S * T
* D. So remember S and T are the same
during a prefill. So that's your um
sequence length squared times b * d and
then um I'm I'm sort of only looking at
the matrix multiplications because the
flops from the other steps don't really
matter. Um and then you project out to
your uh oh sorry you you take a
combination of this and v. So actually
this is mathematically incorrect because
there's some soft maxes there but the
essence of the map malls are are the are
the same. So that's the same number of
flops and then you write to
HPM. Okay. So and here I'm assuming
there'll be more bytes transferred if
you didn't use fly flash attention.
Flash attention means that you don't
have to keep on writing back to HPM
intermediate steps. So um but the
order is actually not u really affected.
So qualitatively doesn't really uh
matter whether you use flash attention
or not but the the math here depends on
the con the constants matter. Um but
let's look at the flops and the bytes
transferred and if you uh divide and
simplify you get this rather nice
expression. I mean nice in that it's
simple, not nice in that it's uh it's
good efficiency which is S * T / S plus
T. Okay, so let's try to interpret this
a bit. So in
prefill T equals
S. So that means your prefill intensity
is order S. So that's good, right?
Because as long as you have long enough
uh you know sequences then uh you're
you're you know good to go right and
generally the sequences can you assume
are kind of long enough. Um during
generation however um you'll see that
the entity is uh essentially one s over
s+ one but that's basically one um and
remember one is is really bound.
Okay. So, but but notice like what
there's no dependence on V at
all. So, unlike in MLPS, remember in
MLPS
um the the generation the prefill was BT
which is great um and then arithmetic
intensity was B which was not great
because it depends on the whims of your
users and workloads but still could be
larger than one. Whereas um for
attention it's actually just always less
than one. No matter how many how long
your sequences there are, how how how
many users there are um it's always one.
So why why is this intuitively that
there's no dependence on on B the batch
dimension. So the reason is that in the
MLP layers intuitively every sequence
hits the same MLP weights.
So whereas in attention layer each
sequence has its own uh KV cache right
because the KV cache is sequence
specific which means that you you can't
really you know
uh use in ML case you can kind of read
all the weights and then you process a
batch intuitively whereas in attention
case um every sequence kind of requires
additional memory you don't get any kind
of savings if you um if you kind of
batch them up mathematically I guess you
can look at it through here where um the
number of flops there's a b here which
is expected but the number of bytes
transferred is um you know b times um
there's a scaling in in b so when you
divide that b uh
cancels um whereas over here um there is
a b here but um we're assuming the df f
dominates. So when you divide um
basically there's no b essentially left
in the the denominator. So you can look
at it mathematically or you can just
kind of reason about it intuitively as
um during for the attention the kv cache
is sort of every sequence's own unique
uh
snowflake. Okay. So the summary is
prefill is compute limited whereas
generation is memory limited. Um the MLP
arithmetic intensity is B. Um which to
make good enough you need bunch of
concurrent requests but attention
intensity is one which and it's also
impossible to improve
that. Okay. I'll pause bit for any any
questions. Okay. So let's let's move on.
Um so now we know that inference it due
thanks to generation is memory limited.
Let's uh try to study the throughput and
latency um um at least in in theory
um so let's focus on
um let's see actually okay so um we're
going to make some assumptions. So all
of this is sort of napkin math is a
little bit stylized um but it gives you
roughly the right kind of scaling and
the right way to think about things. So
we're going to assume that commu
communication and compute can be
perfectly
um overlapped which is obviously false
but it's it's good enough for for making
these qualitative uh um estimates. Um so
what we're going to do is we're going to
instantiate the latency and throughput
for a llama 2 13B on H100. Okay. So for
a 13B
um here are the values. So the se let's
just put the sequence length to be a
th00and hidden dimension to be model
dimension to be 5,000 four times uh I
don't know if that's that's not four
times but anyway f is um some multiple
of that number of heads number of uh key
value um I guess uh query heads number
of key value heads which for llama 2 is
the same we'll get to that point later
um and and so on and for the memory
bandwidth of H100 that's the
Okay, so that's uh the config and we're
going to compute the the memory latency
and throughput. Okay, so Oh, okay.
Um so first uh let's just quickly get
the number of parameters. You guys did
this in assignment one. So I won't bel
labor this but it's some expression. Um
that depends on all the different knowh
um and uh the to store the parameters
we're going to use f B bf16
um because inference is generally going
to be 16 bit not 32-bit um so we're
going to multiply between two. So that's
the memory that the parameters take.
Okay, we don't need gradients. We don't
need optimizer states because we're not
training. But we do have to store the KV
cache which are the act some of the
activations um not all the activations
but some of them for every sequence of
length s and how much we have to per
store per sequence. It's basically the
sequence lengths times the number of key
value
uh um heads times the dimension of that
head times the number of layers times um
basically two for basically both a key
and a value and two for BF 16. Okay, so
that's how much the cache size uh takes.
Um and so the total memory is batch size
times the cache per sequence plus the
memories uh plus the parameter size. So
now
latency is going to be determined by
memory. Remember it's memory limited. So
we're just going to compute how much
memory needs to be transferred
uh into the GPU to do this computation.
is simply memory over the memory
bandwidth. Um, and throughput is
essentially the inverse of latency but
scaled up by B because we're looking at
generating B tokens in in
parallel. Okay. So now if we substitute
our um llama 2 config um we'll see that
the number of parameters checks out it's
it's um you know 13 billion roughly the
memory latency and throughput have these
expressions
um so memory you know grows obviously
this is the parameter size this is the
key value uh cache size times times B
latency also goes up as a function of B
throughput
um um increases but you'll see that it
increases up to a point. The B shows up
in both the numerator and the
denominator. Um so there's limits to how
much you can stretch throughput even if
you could fit everything in
memory. Okay. So those are um the
expressions uh for latency throughput
and memory for this particular model. So
now let's instantiate with different
batch sizes. So if B equals 1
um then the latency is about 8
milliseconds. So 8 mill every 8
milliseconds you generate a token and
the throughput is 124 uh tokens uh per
second. Okay. So that's 13B on a H100 um
if you're using batch size of one. So
now what happens if you use um batch
size of 16?
So you'll see that the um the memory
usage increases because you need to
store the KV cache for all 64 sequences.
Now the latency goes up. Um because you
kind of have to instead of just
processing one, you have to kind of wait
for everything to finish. Um but the
throughput also goes up actually quite a
lot. Okay. So you're seeing kind of this
uh immediate trade-off between latency
and throughput. If you want low latency,
you just use one um one uh B equals 1.
But if you want high throughput, you
want larger B in general. Um what
happens if you use a batch size of even
larger? So
256. Um you'll see that the latency goes
up, throughput goes up, but you see that
throughput isn't going up that much
because you get diminishing returns
after a while.
But the most kind of uh you can't
actually do this on a 100 because if you
look at the uh the memory it's 240 uh
gigs. So it doesn't even
fit. Okay. So batch size you can only
increase to a certain point um because
of memory. Okay. So just to recap,
there's a trade-off between latency and
throughput. Smaller batch sizes yield
battery latency. larger batch sizes
yield better uh
throughput. And finally, there's uh we
talked last week talked about
parallelism for training and it was, you
know, kind of complicated, annoying. Um
at least one type of parallelism for
inferences is really really nice and
simple. Um you just launch M copies of
the model. Okay, no communication
because the model you don't need to
update the models. the latency is the
same and the throughput increases by m.
So that's that's pretty good. So always
remember that uh you know don't forget
easy things. Um now there are cases
where you if you have a large enough
model then uh maybe it doesn't even fit
on a single uh GPU and you need to shard
the model and in this case you also want
to uh start sharding the KV cache in
some cases um to get you know better you
know efficiency. So um there's for more
details uh check out this uh book
chapter. Okay. So uh the time to first
token um which is a metric I mentioned
earlier is essentially a function of of
the prefill. It's basically how long
does it take to encode the prompt and
usually it's uh you know this is compute
limited so you're basically going as
fast as you can. Um and there's not much
you can do about it given a fixed
architecture.
Um and uh well okay so sorry you you can
improve it if you um if you reduce the
the batch size uh still um but if you
want to improve the throughput you have
to um you know increase the batch
size. Okay so any uh questions about
that? So this was on computing the
throughput and latency and because of
the memory limited uh argument that I
gave in the the previous um part I just
focus on memory and compute how many
bytes need to be sent and that gives me
uh a rough bound on um the latency. In
practice the compute there are some
regimes where compute does matter but
I'm sort of ignoring that just u to keep
things simple.
Okay, a question. Is this assuming a
single GPU? Uh the qu Yes, this is
assuming a single GPU.
Uh while creating a batch from multiple
users, uh each of these will be
completed
different tokens.
Yeah. So the question is if you have
multiple users and you're batching them
together, they might arrive at different
times. They're going to finish at
different times. So, we're going to get
to that. Um, that's going to be a
special issue that we're going to have
to deal
with. Any other
questions? Okay, so now we have a good
handle on what the inference workload
looks like. U, we looked at the
arithmetic intensity. We looked at the
the transformer inference with respect
to in arithmetic intensity. We saw that
it was memory limited thanks to the
tension where the KV cache has to be
special for every sequence and then
using that we can compute throughput and
and latency which are the main inference
metrics that we we care about. Now how
do we make things better? Okay, so there
are some things that you can do on that
are lossless. You can write better
kernels. You can improve your your
systems. But I would say that the the
high kind of there's a lot you can do if
you're willing to take uh you know
shortcuts. Um and these are kind of
really interesting because technically
this lecture is on inference but
secretly it's on model architectures
because what you'll see is that a lot of
the changes in model architecture are
going to have direct impact on inference
and we're actually inspired by needing
to do inference quickly.
Okay, so the big bottleneck here is the
KV cache, right? Because remember memory
limited, which means that the less
memory stuff takes um then the faster
you go. Not just because of flops, even
though that's the part of it, but mostly
due to memory because um it's mostly
about the memory transfers. If that's
one thing you take away from this
lecture, it's like all about the the
kind of the memory uh for
speed. Okay. So the the problem is that
if you just start whacking away at the
KV cache, you're you might lose
accuracy. So how can you make sure you
don't lose too much accuracy but still
uh maintain um your your KV cache uh
small?
So there's a bunch of ideas I'm going to
go through um that all essentially try
to change the architecture to reduce
your KV cache. Some of these ideas I
think you you've seen um but I'll go
through them kind of in this sort of
more systematic way. So there's this
idea called group query attention. So
multi-headed attention which is the
vanilla transformer keeps around uh
basically number of heads and for each
of the that number you have same number
of keys values and queries.
Um there was one time a multi-query
attention which you only have one uh key
and one value basically one key value
head. Uh turned out that that was not
very expressive. So there is a sort of
intermediate point where um you have a
reduced number of keys and values and
then you have more
queries. So why are we doing this? Well
remember we want to reduce the KV cache
size. So the fewer keys and values there
are the better. So the batch size and
the sequence length doesn't uh get
changed but it's and the dimensionality
of the the these vectors don't change
but it's the number of key value heads
that we're reducing.
Okay. So, so that's basically the idea
and this paper shows that you do get
latency and throughput um improvements.
So, times per sle sample and as you
increase the number of groups um then uh
up to eight or so basically there's a
negligible um uh is it's really fast
compared to um the full attention. Um
and as you increase the number of groups
obviously you kind of end up at the the
original. So that's uh latency and
throughput improvements.
Um and just to actually do this kind of
more rigorously. So we have our llama
213 uh B model. And if we compute the
the statistics
um this is using a batch size of 64.
Remember this is what we got.
Um uh I guess I should have printed out
latency here. Oh well. Um and then
um if you run it with GQA you see that
the memory is reduced and the throughput
goes way up. So this is actually great.
Um so this is what happens if I take the
llama to 13b architecture and I just
reduce for every query head I'm going so
for every key value head I have five
query heads that's what 1:5 ratio means
um so which this also means we can use a
larger batch size because remember last
time we tried to do 256 it didn't even
fit in um an H100's memory so now um we
can actually comfortably fit into the
H100 memory and then we can further
improve the throughput by using a larger
batch size. So you can see kind of a lot
of different effects here. By reducing
the number of uh key value pairs, the
memory of the KV cache reduces. Um that
means the the throughput and latency go
up automatically because fewer memory
transfers and furthermore as a secondary
effect I can increase the batch size
within the GPU and that further improves
the throughput.
Okay. So that's that's wonderful. Um we
have to also make sure the accuracies
doesn't drop. So this is um this
original paper that shows that uh this
is full attention. This is GQA. Um the
time is much less but the accuracy is
basically the
same. Okay. Now um you know what
actually happened? So I don't uh so
llama 2 did not use this ratio but llama
3 actually picked up you know GQA and um
you know probably motivated by the kind
of inference costs actually llama 2 I
think the 70 the large model did have
GQA but not the smaller
ones okay so that's GQA there's another
way to reduce
the key value cache and this comes from
deepseek So this is actually from the
deepseek v2 paper and it's called multi
head latent which tatsu lectured about
uh previously but I'll try to um talk
about it in the context of inference and
its
implications. So the basic idea is uh
here's full attention and GQA says I'm
going to use fewer keys and values. MLA
says I'm not going to change the number
of key and values. I'm going to project
these into a lower dimensional space.
So, it's another way of shrinking the KV
size, but just in a I guess in a
different um
dimension. So, instead of using N* H
dimensions for each uh um for the KV
cache of each uh you know uh token, I'm
going to project out to C dimensions. Um
and this is what Deep Seek did. It's
actually quite a aggressive reduction
from 16,000 to 512. Only wrinkle is that
this is not compatible with rope. So
they need to add a few more more
dimensions to put rope back in. But
overall, this is actually quite uh
promising um from a KV reduction
perspective. I'm not going to do the
math. you can but you can just trust me
that you can see kind of how the KV
cache would be reduced a lot and you get
the same kind of latency and throughput
advantages. Um, and in terms of
accuracy, they actually showed um that
compared to GQA um the MH uh sorry, the
um actually maybe I'm showing the wrong
thing here.
Um maybe okay. Um I meant to show that
the um MLA actually improves, but this
table does not show that. So I'll have
to um dig that up later. But but anyway
it MLA does um preserve the the accuracy
as
well. Okay. So there's another idea
which says well um you know GQA
basically shares you can think about it
as a sharing key value uh vectors right
within um a token and within a um
sequence. Um but we can also look at
something called cross layer attention
which uh there's a paper on this but I
think many people have been kind of uh
thinking about this and doing this uh so
I don't know know if this is actually
the first paper but basically if you
look at the transformer I diagram um you
have the key value projection of one
layer and then you have the next layer
and these key value um vectors are
separate um usually um but IDE idea here
with uh CLA is that we're just going to
use the same key value projection across
layers. That's why it's called cross
layer attention.
Um so
um so just as GQA shares across heads,
CLA shares across layers. So here we
they show that they empirically improve
the paralo frontier of accuracy um and
the KV cache uh size. So KV cache size
which relates to throughput and latency
um you want to be small and you want
perplexity also to be um you know small.
So they're able to you know improve uh
that
um okay so so notice that I mean for
example H6 64 heads you know the cache
size goes uh it gets reduced but the
validation perplexity does go up a
little bit but overall the the there's
kind of advantage um in you know making
that trade-off.
Okay, so there's yet another way to do
things. Um, so local attention
um, which has been explored actually
quite a bit since even kind of the
there's a long former there's an open AI
paper and then Mistro and I think many
others use this as well. Um, it's a very
I guess a natural idea instead of if you
look at a full attention diagram it's
dense n squared. Um, and that's where a
lot of your complexity comes from. Um,
and basically the idea is, uh, you're
going to just attend to only the past K
tokens. Um, which means that in the KV
cache, as you're generating the
sequence, you don't have to remember
everything as as soon as the token kind
of falls outside your window that you
have of attention, you can just like
throw it away, right? So local
contention is very uh you you could say
that the KV cache size remains constant
as opposed to growing with the sequence
length. So this is really good right
because that means for even long se
sequences you can have um quite a small
cache. Okay.
Um but you know the problem is that this
still you know hurts accuracy because if
you just think about it like why are we
doing attention instead of RNN's is that
we needed to have long range to MAC
model run long range dependencies and
this is in some sense even to call it
attention is a little bit kind of a um
overselling this this is only looking at
the local context um which is not very
expressive. So what you do here is you
can interle local attention with full
global attention hybrid layers. Um so
for example character AI used um for
every six layers they had one global
attent global layer and five um local
layers. So it looks something in
addition to cross layer attention. So it
looks something like uh this um where
full attention every layer um you have
to store the you know KV cache um and
for um what they did is that for every
six layers you have the full attention
but in between you have this local
attention and on top of that they have
KV cache sharing um locally both at the
for the local attention and the global
attention.
So this is like all the tricks kind of
you know not all the tricks but many of
the tricks kind of combined you know
together. Um so in summary these are a
few ways to reduce the KV cache size
because remember inference is memory
limited. Um so you want to reduce the
cache size but you don't want to hurt
accuracy too much. And there's many ways
to do it. You can lower the
dimensionality of the KV cache. You can
have few KV cache vectors. You can
reduce the dimensionality of a a KV
vector. You can share the KV cache
across layers. Um and also you can use
local attention on some of the
layers. Okay. Any questions about um the
set of tricks for reducing the KV cache?
Uh yeah. Yeah. Question about the
costion. So like how many like I feel
like the weights are all being shared
across the like the same layers like do
you just have like one set of weights
which just like KV that's shared across
the blue ones? Yeah. So the the question
is are the weights shared? So the KV
cache is shared but the weights are
shared. So what happens is the weights
for doing the um you know the projection
need to be shared so there's some
consistency. Yeah.
Yeah, there was another question.
The the context size is is too large
every you know and then it increases the
KV catch as well the contact size when
you pump
the context that is given to the trans.
Yeah long then it increases the size. So
we try reducing those context by
summarizing the context context. Yeah.
So the question is uh if you have really
long context let's say your prompt is
huge that's going to intrinsically take
a lot of KV cache um so all these tricks
can try to reduce uh that um you can do
more aggressive things that like you
know there's ideas like you know just
tokens or ways to summarize the prompt
um which we're not going to talk about
in this class but there's ways of that
address the long prompt situation as
Okay. So now I'm going to talk about
even more radical ways of uh making
inference go faster by changing the
transformer. So the KV cache these are
basically variants of the transformer.
Um but maybe you can actually go um
outside the transformer and and do
better because the transformer wasn't
really designed with you know heavy
inference workloads in mind. They were
just trying to try and train a good
model that um efficiently. It was mostly
about training efficiency and the auto
regression as we sort of pointed out is
really causing this kind of um you know
bottleneck here with the auto regression
plus the kind of the full
attention. So um we're going to talk
about two directions uh state space
models and diffusion models. Um this is
going to be fairly quick.
Um so the idea of state space models is
actually drawing ideas from you know
signal processing and control theory. Um
initially the motivation was trying to
model long context uh sequences without
suffering the n squ blowup. So it wasn't
necessary about inference speed but it
turns out if you solve that problem you
get faster inference too. So there's a
kind of early paper on S S4 U which uses
classical uh state space models which
are basically these kind of linear
dynamical systems u which are you been
used to kind of model along context and
sort of shoehorning them into the kind
of a modern neural um setup. Um this
work is uh allows has is you know nice
in that it has sort of this RNN kind of
interpretation due to the linearity
structure and also has a you know
convolution
um interpretation as well. So they
published this uh this uh this paper and
um you know showed that it I think
worked really well on these long context
you know synthetic tasks. Um but what
they found is that what I guess what was
uh discovered is that they don't really
work well for language modeling. uh and
that's obviously kind of a
disappointment because a lot of the
value of transformers is being able to
do language well. Um so in a series of
papers there was um they sort of
identified a set of kind of synthetic
tasks that captured the essence of why
these models weren't working well and
that's basically these associative
recall tasks. So here's a synthetic task
where you're given a basically a
sequence of key value pairs and
um and the goal is to predict basically
look up the key and output the value. So
in some sense it's kind of a logically a
trivial task but it's long sequence
because I can have a lot of key value
pairs and um I'm going to have to look
far back. It can be arbitrary long
dependence and you can see that local
attention is not going to work very well
because it's just going to remember the
last few sequences and um what the
problem with states space models is that
they're sort of good for these kind of
signal processing tasks but um really
this is like you need to go isolate a
particular key value pair and pull out
the the answer and for those type of
tasks it didn't really work. So there's
a bunch of work um I'm not citing
there's like hyena h3 and then mamba um
which basically tweaked the or changed
the hssm
um to basically handle these associative
recall tasks and eventually it worked
better up to kind of 1b scale was
matching you know transformers
um and uh mamb idea of mamba has been
popular and scaled up um even to a 52b
um um by AI21 folks. Um notice that in
this case they still had to use a
transformer. So a transformer but only
every I guess eight layers they had a
transformer. The rest of them were mamba
layers. Um and so that still get led to
a fairly big you know uh savings and and
speed up.
Um and
uh but more recently there's this kind
of revival of this older idea called
linear attention. Um
where instead of um let's see if I can
make this bigger.
Um is actually a kind of a very simple
idea. So you know what local attention
or sliding window attention is? Um
linear attention is this idea that uh
you
essentially in so in this basically in
the um attention computation there's a
key and a query and you uh dotproduct
them and you take the x of that which is
basically giving you a x kernel. So you
can basically take a tailor expansion of
that and write that computation as
basically dotproducts of some nonlinear
map. So then what you essentially have
is you you can think about for every uh
key value position you are basically
applying some sort of nonlinearity
blowing up into some space and then
doing some linear computation over it.
And because it's linear attention, it
actually kind of behaves like an RNN and
it's linear in the the sequence length
rather than quadratic. I know that was a
little bit uh fast, but um I just want
to give you sort of the the taste of it.
And so this idea has been
actually uh scaled up quite
successfully. So there's this um um
organization called Miniax that's
training um pretty legitimate models um
up to 456 billion
parameteres. Um and they use this
basically linear attention idea. Now
they have to use full attention um still
once in a while. It seems it I don't
think um people have been able to get
around having some full attention but at
least it seems like people have been
able to get rid of most of full
attention in like most of the layers are
not full attention anymore. They're just
either linear layers or local attention
layers which are much much more
efficient.
Okay, so the linear plus local attention
um you know now are actually yielding
serious state-of-the-art models and it's
probably you know safe to say that well
I don't know what's uh exactly the the
closed model providers are doing but I
would suspect that there would be at
least as kind of advance in terms of as
efficient as um this and leveraging
sparsity
So it's it's kind of an interesting
question when people ask like well you
know is trans attention all you need is
transformers it well you know yes and no
I mean I guess in some sense there is
still the sense squared there maybe
we'll be able to get rid of it but most
of the transformer has been like pretty
radically changed by having other much
lighter weight you know components and
you're still able to get much of the
same and kind of accuracy
And all of this is, you know, really
helpful for inference because on these
non-ful attention layers, you're
basically replacing the ordered t KV
cache which grows as a sequence length
with something that's uh
constant. And there's there's papers by
um uh that followup I think they uh on
the based paper where did that go?
there's some f uh either in this paper
or in follow-up work
analyzing basically the trade-off
between the KV size and the ability to
do uh various types of kind of recall
tasks which makes sense because if you
don't store very much you won't be able
to solve certain tasks but there is this
trade-off curve that you can try to play
with okay so that's all I'll say about
um the state space models
So now let's talk about a completely
different style of uh generation models,
diffusion models. So diffusion models
have been very popular image generation
but they turn out to be fairly tricky to
get working in text although there
recently have been some advances here.
So the idea of diffusion is that you
instead of generating all regressively
you just generate every token in
parallel. So obviously if you only do
that you know via some simple layer it's
not going to be very good. You can't
generate all the words in parallel and
expect it to be coherent. But what you
do is you iterate and you keep on
refining um this this generation until
it gets to your final uh generation that
you
output. And
the the idea behind generating in
parallel, you're no longer auto
reggressively, you know, bound and that
generating all tokens in parallel well
can be done in parallel. So you get to
saturate your your G GPUs relatively
easy as long as your context length is
large enough. Um so recently there's
this uh and session labs has um produced
some pretty interesting models. Um
there's not much written about them but
you can see kind of a a demo of the
generation and process. it just kind of
generates um code instantaneously but
it's obviously kind of broken code and
then it uh you know kind of refineses
over
time. So, and this is one of their their
benchmarks that show that at least on
coding, I'm not sure about other uh
tasks that if you look at that at tokens
per second, these models are like way
out here in terms of speed compared to
anything that's transformer. Even Jamba
remember is like a hybrid mamba um um uh
transformer architecture is is quite
slow compared to these diffusion models.
So now whether diffusion models are you
know be will be kind of general purpose
and powerful enough in all these that
remains to be seen but I think it's you
know you have such a lead on the the
kind of the token speed here that um
even if you um I think you can put more
compute and kind of recover some of the
accuracy uh losses if you if you need
to. Okay. So the the summary here is
that I think this whole kind of
architecture novel architecture thing is
actually really exciting for inference
um because um they allow you to sidestep
kind of fundamental obstacles right so
if you're dealing with attention you
just have this fundamental KV cache
obstacle that you can quantize you can
optimize but it's still there and and so
by making a kind of safe space model
you're shrinking that to like a constant
size and as long as you can keep up the
accuracy which is big if um then you win
big time. Same with the diffusion models
auto reggressive generation is a key
bottleneck. Now if you just generalize
generate things in parallel now all of a
sudden you kind of like change the game
you know completely. So there's much
more work to be done here um in proving
inference. So as you can see now
inference is the inference game is is
much broader than it seems at first
sight. It's not really about kind of
necessarily the systems optimizations to
make it fast although you obviously need
those but I think the real gains are
coming from um like real radical changes
in
architecture. Um okay so I have about 10
minutes left. I'll go through these
quickly. Uh quantization and model
pruning. So quantization the key idea is
just reduce the precision of the
numbers. Okay. So easily e very easy to
do and the thought is that less memory
means uh less bytes transferred higher
sorry there should be lower latency
higher throughput. Um and you do have to
worry about accuracy of course that's
the the trade-off. Um if you look at the
different types of uh you know formats
FP32 used for training not used for
inference really um BF-16 is sort of the
default for inference. You can go down
to FP8 or INT8 which now is um is less
accurate but much you know cheaper than
even FP8. Um so people do do a bunch of
inference in int 8 which if you look at
the range I mean it's an integer between
127 minus 128 which is not that uh it's
pretty low precision and people even
going down to in4 which is they're not
oh yeah so int4 is pretty you know low
um there's also other ways you can do
okay so you can so once you kind of
decide that you want to
um quantize. I guess you could
do several things. You can train with a
quantization, but obviously that means
you need to retrain models and more I
guess commonly you do post-training
quantization where you take an existing
model and you try to quantize it and try
not to screw things up too much. Um so
the there's a paper called element int 8
which I'll I'll talk through you know
kind of briefly. So in quantization
um basically what happens is that you
take your you know your your vector
which is let's say FP16
um and then you need to figure out the
dynamic range right if you want to pack
it into int 8 you need to figure out
what the largest value is and once you
figure that out you can kind of um you
know divide uh by that and multiply by
128 and then you get your integers and
then if you need to um dequantize then
you kind of go the other way. So, so
basically quantization means that
remember memory is a bandwidth, right?
So, bottleneck. So, you're all your
transfers are happening in um in in end
date but when you actually do the you
know I guess uh you sometimes have to
upcast to um a floating point to
actually do the arithmetic.
Um okay so the problem with int8 is that
not everything you know fits nicely and
you have these outliers which appear in
larger networks that screw things up. So
what this paper did is that you take a
this matrix you identify the really
large outlier values and then you handle
them separately use in full 16bit
precision and then do the most the vast
majority in
88. Um so this works well but is
actually a bit um you know uh slower. So
the motivation here wasn't inference
speed but more even being able to fit
your model into u memory. There's
another paper called activation aware
quantization and here uh the idea is
that you you're kind of quantizing the
bas kind of the the weights but you're
going to figure out which weights to
quantize based on the the activations um
you know really quickly this you're
going down to actually in three um and
this obviously reduces memory by quite a
bit and leads to a 3x uh you know speed
up And so the general idea here is that
you want to um you get a trained model
and it just happens that some of the
weights or activations are going to be
abnormally large. So for those you
handle separately and then everything
else you can kind of work in low you
know
precision. Okay. Um talk about model
pruning um ideas very like quantization.
It's sort of the basic idea is very
simple. you just rip out parts of an
expensive model to make it cheaper and
then you fix it up. So in this Nvidia
paper what they do is they first
identify
important either layers or heads or
hidden dimensions um using a small
calibration size. say use some you know
uh simple scores to compute that and
then you just remove the unimportant
layers or hidden units or heads and then
now if you just take that model it's
going to be clearly worse right but so
then the last step is you distill the
original model into the prune model so
you kind of repair the model from the
initialization which is your prune so
you're not starting from scratch you're
starting from something that's worse but
hopefully not worse and hopefully
retains a lot of the same structural
properties of the original model. It's
just maybe not kind of like calibrated
in some sense. Um, and the results are
pretty good on that. So they have these
15 billion parameter models that they're
able to reduce to 8B with hardly any
drop in this I guess at least according
to MMLU and then down to 4B with uh some
drop but you also are going down quite a
bit to a 4B model.
Okay. So um so maybe summarize this
taking shortcuts idea. You can uh reduce
inference complexity without hurting
accuracy. You can do it from scratch
where you just define a fresh
architecture that's by construction fast
and just train it. Or you can distill
you define that architecture. You can
take a slow model and you figure out a
some sort of scheme to initialize the
new model with the old model. And then
you basically do
distillation.
Um
so okay so now all of these are a little
bit unsatisfying because they're lossy.
So you get massive speed ups but you
always wonder well maybe this model
isn't as actually good as original. So
speculative decoding or speculative
sampling allows you to um basically have
your cake and eat it too. So recall
there's two stages of inference. You
prefill
um which you're given a sequence, you
encode all the tokens in parallel. This
is compute limited um which is great.
Notice that this also gives you log
probabilities for each of the tokens.
And then there's generation which is one
token at a time. It's memory limit. It's
slow. So in other words, checking is
faster than generation. So intuitively
this makes sense. But hopefully now you
also appreciate the math behind why this
is true. Um and the speculative sampling
idea is actually really really again it
was proposed in parallel by these two
independent teams from Google. Um and uh
the idea is
to use a cheap draft model P to just run
ahead and generate some
tokens and then you're going to evaluate
those tokens with a target model and
because evaluation of given tokens is
just prefilled so you can do that in
parallel which is fast and then you
accept it if it looks
good. So uh this is what it looks like
in uh real life. So if you're using a
big model generating one token at a time
that's slow but in speculative decoding
you have the draft model that's racing
ahead generating um a lot of tokens and
using the big model to essentially
verify and sometimes it will reject and
sometimes it'll accept and the
acceptance rate basically determines how
fast of a speed up you you
have. Okay. So here is the more formal
um algorithm. Um so you're going to have
a look ahead of K. So you're going to
use your draft model and generate K
tokens auto
reggressively. So this is hopefully fast
because your draft model is small and
then you're given these K tokens that
you generated and I'm going to score
them based on I'm going to compute the
probability under the target model Q.
Now I'm going to decide whether I want
to accept this not or not. So I go
through each token and I'm going to
essentially accept it with probability
um Q over P and the one just is uh make
sure this you know probabilities are
between zero and one. Um if this kind of
looks like if people are familiar with
Metropolis Hastings this is kind of
where this uh this kind of comes from.
Um so intuitively you're you're sampling
with P. Um so you need to divide that
out because you don't want P you want Q.
So this is kind of importance weight um
on this. So if you accept it then great
you kind of move on and you look at the
next draft token and so on. Um and if
you don't accept it then you're going to
sample from the the the target model the
slow model but you kind of do this
correction where you've already tried to
sample using P. So you don't need to do
that anymore. You subtract it out and
you sample from Q.
So this is basically kind of a rejection
sampling with a proposal P and a target
uh sorry target Q. Um the only
difference is that um you are sampling
you you injection sampling you if you
reject then you reject and you just try
again and you try again. Um, and here we
don't want to keep on kind of looping
forever. Uh because if you reject, we're
just going to say, "Okay, fine. We'll
bite the bullet and just sample from the
the more expensive
model." So the cool thing here is that
you're guaranteed to get an exact sample
from the target model. Okay, so those of
you familiar with sampling, this is it
shouldn't be too surprising. You're able
to use kind of prior information to
speed up sampling. Um but in a language
modeling context this is kind of nice.
Um I'm going to skip the uh this is not
really a proof. This is just kind of
some derivation to show that for a case
of vocab 2 it why this these formulas
kind of give you the right unbiased
sampling
procedure. Um and it works uh pretty
well. So the accuracy uh is you know it
should be actually the the same since
it's the same model. But maybe there's
some randomness there. But the speed up
is you're getting a factor of two speed
up essentially.
Um
so and so in practice what you do is you
take you have something like a 70B model
and your draft model is much much
smaller. Um and if your target model is
80B 8B then your draft model might be
1B. And you generally want to make the
draft model as closest to your target as
possible. Um and so if you're doing some
distillation that could um make it even
better. There's a bunch of this is a
pretty uh hot area of of research and
inference. There's a lot of ways to
improve this process. Um you can use um
Medusa which is this uh way to have the
draft model instead of generating auto
reggressively sample multiple tokens in
parallel or eagle where you're actually
taking highle features of the target
model and pumping them into the draft
model to generate. So the draft model
doesn't actually have to stand alone. It
can be kind of glom on to the target
model to help it generate.
Um so uh summary exact sampling from the
target model thanks to math. Um and this
exploits the symmetry between checking
and generation right so or um prefill
and generation and there's actually a
lot of room for innovation on a draft
model um which can you know everything
that we talked about before where you
can have different radical architectures
different ways of quantizing all of
those apply right the only thing is that
um you get to basically guarantee that
you're getting exact act uh sample.
Okay. So now I'll go uh I'm out of time
but quickly go through the um the
question that came up earlier which is
that in practice when you're serving
there's live traffic requests come at
different times. Um they finish at
different times they have some of them
have shared prefixes some of them don't.
They have different lengths. So it's
very heterogeneous
um in comparison to training where you
get basically a dense block of tokens
and you're basically going to p push it
through your GPU at at full speed. So
what do you do in this case? So there's
a series of papers that kind of ex
explore this um and the the basic idea
is is this is so the last two parties
are more of a kind of systems level um
contribution. So the idea is that you
don't wait for batches to, you know, the
the train leaves. There's no the train
doesn't um wait for you. Um so when a
new batch comes, you're just going to
put it in, right? Which means that um
the the sort of this uh the the the um
the worker that's generating tokens
needs to kind of hand control back to
theuler every step. So you generate a
token, come back to the scheduleuler and
say if there's new um uh new u requests
then they get stuck in and then it kind
of continues. So you're kind of not
wasting any time waiting around for
requests. Um now there's a kind of a
problem with batching I think which is
behind the question. Um batching works
when everything's the same
dimensionality but every request might
be a different length. So there's this
idea of selective batching where um you
basically break up your computation for
attention. Everything has to be handled
separately. But for your MPs remember
which are the bulk of the computation
you can actually take tensors of
different sizes and you just flatten
them. And because they don't interact um
they can just like be kind of kind of
along for the ride in the batch
dimension. Okay, I know that was fast,
but uh I'll just quickly go over page
detention. Now, um this is the the paper
behind VLM, which some of you probably
have used. Um and this addresses the
memory usage problem. So, if you have a
KV cache and prompts are coming in and
finishing, then your cache is going to
get fragmented. So, you're going to have
um you're going to allocate a bunch of
uh space for a request, but you don't
know how many tokens are getting
generated. So um there's going to be
internal fragmentation and then there's
also going to be external fragmentation
where there's padding between the the
requests and responses. So that's no
good. So the page attention basically
says remember operating systems we have
um and how kind of virtual memory works
we divide the KV cache into a sequence
of contiguous blocks and then we just
put them wherever um we find white
space. So if you have two requests
coming in then um they might just you
know the first request might be here
here and here and the second request
might be here and here. So the blocks
are the things that you're going to keep
contiguous and that's going to give you
your allow you time to coales your
memory.
Um so you can also play these tricks
where if you have uh sharing of
prefixes then there's another idea from
uh operating systems which is copy on
write. So you basically maintain
reference counters for how many
basically uh sequences are using this
particular block and then if you need to
kind of diverge and have blocks go in
different directions then you copy and
you reduce the reference count. Um
there's a bunch of other VLM
optimizations which I won't go through
but basically the summary is remember
your your operating systems classes you
can apply them to inference as well.
Okay, so quick summary, inference is
really really important. It's where um
and the characteristics are distinct
from training. You're memory limited and
it's also dynamic. So which leads a
bunch of uh uh new challenges. We saw a
whole host of different techniques
around new architectures, quantization,
pruning, distillation, um speculative
decoding. uh there's ideas from systems
which can allow you to better use your
memory um overlap communication and
compute and things like that but but I
would say that there's probably even
more um opportunity in sort of the
modeling and architecture because if you
think about it all you you don't
inference narrowly is inference in a
particular model how do I run this
particular model but who cares running
about that particular model you care
about delivering good accuracy given
your resource budget. So a lot of these
ideas that are trying
to change the reduce the KV cache,
changing the transformer are basically
ways to sidestep the problem and say,
well, I have something that's more
efficient and if I can train in a way
that gets me better accuracy, then then
I win. Okay, so that's all I have and I
will see you next time. Then we're back
to scaling lots.