Okay. Uh so let's get started. Um
today's the the second and last of the
scaling laws lectures. Um and today it's
going to be a little bit more of a a
case study and details oriented lecture.
Um I'm going to cover two separate kinds
of things. The first one is I'm going to
go through a couple of papers um where
people have done careful scaling loss
studies as part of their model building.
Um and I'm going to use that as a way to
to convey to you how modern large um
language model builders use scaling laws
as part of their design process. Right?
So um motivation from last time and
today is what's the best practice for
scaling a large model. Um we want to
have um large language models with nice
hyperparameters and good architecture
choices. Um, and you know, I've already
told you about chinchilla and using
scaling laws to validate some of this,
but I think you know, you should have
rightfully skeptical questions about
scaling laws, right? Like it's curve
fitting on a log log plot. Is it really
as good as as you know, um, I said it
was last lecture. So, does Chinchilla's
approach to scaling laws actually work?
Um, you're finding this out in your
assignments. Um, you know, if you fit an
ISO flop, is that really telling you
about the right token trade-offs? um can
you use this stuff to really set optimal
learning rates um and should we be
picking sort of particular architectures
or parameterizations to scale um
nicely. So um the last paper or the
newest paper we talked about with like
lots of detailed scaling studies in last
lecture uh was the deep mind chinchilla
paper right and after that um chat GPT
happened and kind of the competitive
landscape of large language model
building really changed and people just
stopped publishing anything about you
know data and scaling and all these
things right it it was sort of very
secretive um I've talked to you know
people at some of the frontier labs
before and ask them, oh, you know, like
what are you guys doing for scaling? And
they're like, no, we will not tell you
anything about what we do for scaling.
And so, um, we have to sort of rely on
other sources for how scaling happens in
practice. And there have been, um,
several, you know, competently executed
largecale models that have done scaling.
Um, and so, you know, last year, um, in
this lecture, I covered Siri, GPT, u,
Deepseek LLM and mini CPM. Um, and as a
as a nice side note, you know, last year
I had to really strongly justify why I
was covering these like Chinese models,
so to speak. But this year, thankfully,
hopefully you're all already excited to
hear about DeepSeek rather than me
trying to convince you that this is the
right thing to listen to. Um, in the
years since then, um, I've looked at a
lot of the the models that have come
out. Um, actually the the hall in terms
of new scaling law insights and papers
is actually much sparser. Um I'll
briefly mention some results from um
Llama 3 which came out at the later end
of last year. Uh Hunan Large um which is
thee model from China. And then Minimax
01 which is a linear time sort of hybrid
attention model um from or long context
model um that came out this year. And
all three of those have some scaling
studies, but really nothing quite as
extensive as DeepSeek or MiniCPM, which
have really been the gold standard, I
think, for uh modern scaling law
studies. So, that's one part of what I
want to talk about today. I want to make
sure you guys have an understanding of,
you know, what scaling looks like in a
real, you know, semi-production model.
Um and the other thing I want to talk
about which is an important deep dive I
I think is uh the MUP uh method that I
mentioned last time. So, MUP is this
approach. Just as a recap of um last
last lecture is you know when we train
these models as we make them bigger we
need to change certain hyperparameters
right um on the left hand side of this
plot here you see that as you make
models wider um in this case like a MLP
you make them wider the optimum learning
rate sort of shifts downward so you need
smaller learning rates for these bigger
models and that's a really big problem
potentially because then you need to
hyperparameter tune your learning rates
at the very large scale right and that's
going to be very computationally
expensive. It's going to be a huge
problem. Um, if on the other hand, if we
could sort of parameterize our model
differently so that you know the
learning rate that's optimal just stayed
the same forever across all the scales,
you know, that's great. That's really
simplified our search process, right? We
would like all of our hyperparameters
and really choices in general to remain
stable across scales, right? That's the
ideal. And MUP is a is a very
interesting class of approaches. Um, and
you know, it teaches us some pretty
interesting sort of ways of thinking
about the problem. So, I'm going to
actually go through some of the the
details in the in the math. Um, in the
years since last time I taught this,
there were a couple of very nice
tutorials on MUP that came out. So, I'm
going to follow those um because they
have math that's pretty easy to follow.
And then I'll talk about some um uh work
that has come out doing sort of
thirdparty validation and uh evaluation
of MUP style methods. So, okay. Um the
focus of the first part of this lecture
which is the case study is going to be
on three models. Um I talked about three
additional more modern models but
actually the the details in those are
much more sparse and I think the lessons
you learn are primarily from these three
papers here. So that's going to be my
focus u for the first part of this
lecture. So, I'm going to talk about
Cerebrus, GPT, MiniCPM, um, and
DeepSeek. And each one of these will
have actually a pretty different mix of
of scaling strategies. And it'll also
have different things to teach us about
how to get scaling, um, right. So, we'll
get started. Um, Cerebrris GPT is the
first of the uh, models and sort of
scaling things that I want to talk
about. Um, it's a large family of
models. It's trained um, 0.1 to 13
billion parameter models. um trained
with the chinchilla recipe. Um so
roughly the the same number of like
token to parameter counts as is optimal.
Um and you know they have a interesting
core finding. Um the cerebrus folks
actually are are pretty interested in a
lot of these like scaling and
parameterization studies and they have a
really interesting core finding which is
they scale up this MUP thing that I
mentioned before and they find that it
makes scaling a lot more stable and a
lot more pleasant to deal with. And and
just to kind of show you the punch line,
right? You've got um test loss on the
pile. Um and you've got sort of the
scaling curves here of like the cerebrus
GPT in blue. This is with standard
parameterization. You've got MUP in in
orange. This is the model that they you
know also train with using the maximum
update parameterization. And they show
that it scales uh more nicely if not
better than things like Pythia or uh
GPTJ. So that's nice. Um and the thing
that I want to emphasize here is that
this is kind of one of the few if not
first public validations uh of MUP. Um
we know that all of or most of the labs
that are doing uh LM scaling pay close
attention to how they parameterize their
networks. Um their initializations as a
function of the scale of the model as
well as uh things like per layer
learning rates are things that people
pay close attention to to make scaling
much more uh stable. And so things like
new are pretty important in this space.
Um llama 4 for example um the paper for
that isn't out and I don't know if they
it will be out but they talk about um a
technique they call metap uh which is a
variant of this um as well. So um what
they show is that when they train models
using sort of standard parameterization
they find that you know they have sort
of big oscillations kind of around the
predicted scaling point. So that's the
this dash line. You know, they have kind
of oscillations due to the fact that,
for example, they have to adjust the
learning rate as a function of scale. Um
and so it's hard for them to kind of
really get the predicted performance
sort of exactly right, which is this
dash line, um using their scaling
recipe. On the other hand, um what they
find is you know if you have um uh sort
of the three risk GPT uh sorry MUP
scaling then you get this orange line
which is much much closer to the scaling
law fit for um this MUP version. And so
their claim here at least is that using
this alternative parameterization allows
them to get much more predictable
scaling much more nice hyperparameter
tuning. Um we're going to see this in
more detail. I'll return to this slide
again once I've sort of gone through the
mathematical derivation of MUP. Um, but
in case you're you're ever interested in
implementing this thing. Um, some of the
cerebrous GPT folks and in general, um,
the kind of artifacts that the Cerebrous
research folks are putting out is very
very helpful for MUP because they have
this big table in the appendix that
really just tells you exactly the
difference between the standard
initialization and parameterization or
SP and the maximum update version or
MUP. Um, and you'll see that, you know,
I I'll just give you kind of the the
oneliner version. Basically, every
non-mbbedding parameter is initialized
with one over the width. And then the
learning rates per layer are scaled down
by one over kind of the width, right?
So, so the the interesting difference
from standard parameterization, even if
you're already doing sort of one over
width scaling on the initialization, is
actually there's per layer learning
rates that are different. And I'm going
to get to that um later. I'm going to do
a full derivation of this result. Um but
you can kind of see uh here there this
kind of like nice quick reference and
also if you want to implement this thing
this gives you very easy ways of
implementing uh
MUP. Um another interesting thing that
we also see in in some of the other
scaling strategies is that you combine
these strategies like MUP which makes
hyperparameter selection stable with
very very aggressive scaling. Um so what
they do here is uh they scale down um
their experiments all the way down to 40
million parameters. Um they do extensive
extensive hyperparameter search on this
proxy model. Um and then they scale
things back up using sort of MUP to try
to keep hyperparameters as stable as
possible. Um and so this is sort of what
they see um in their small scale
hyperparameter search. Each one of these
dots is a model run and there's sort of
a hyperparameter associated with each
one of these and then they pick the
minimum across these runs giving them
essentially their sort of hyperparameter
grid. Um this is a very like clean
approach to hyperparameter selection.
It's unclear whether you know this kind
of this level of aggressive scaling down
is really what you want to do if you
want to train these like really really
large models. But this is kind of one
strategy that we see also in in mini CPM
and deepseek like training much smaller
surrogate models and then trying to
figure out how to stably scale them back
up. And that's going to be kind of a a
theme that we see uh
throughout. And yeah, if if folks have
questions uh please stop me actually.
Maybe I'll stop here for a moment in
case anyone has questions for the
cerebrus GPT uh piece. Although maybe
it'll be clearer once I talk about uh
the MUP derivation later in this
lecture. Okay. Um there is another paper
I want to talk about mini CPM um or
another you know uh artifact I guess.
Um, for whatever reason, I think mini
CPM hasn't been talked about quite as
much. Um, especially in sort of like
western academic circles. Um, but at
least for me, this was one of the first
sort of releases or papers I saw coming
out of like a Chinese research group
where they had done some like really
cool in-depth, you know, scaling and
other kinds of research. It really felt
like, you know, stuff coming out of the
frontier, right? Um, and to give you a
overview of what they do, their goals
here is they want to train, you know,
relatively small language models, but
use a lot of compute to train really
good small language models. That's their
ostensible goal. Um, and in doing so,
they do a lot of careful scaling
computations. They also once again use
MUP to stabilize and simplify scaling.
Um, when they sort of end up scaling
these models, not in size, but in in
terms of the amount of data.
um and to try to convince you that you
know this is a paper worth following
right um you know at the time that they
were trained uh this was a remarkably
good 1.2 to 2.4B 4B uh models. Um it
beats out, you know, most of the 2B
models that were out there. Um and it
matched many of the modern 7B models. Um
at least modern as of 2024, uh
standards. I mean, now of course you've
got even better 7B models. The arms race
is fierce. Um but this should give you a
sense that at least, you know, given the
the amount of compute and technology
available, you know, back in mid 2024,
this was actually really uh at the
frontier and they did something right to
to get models uh of this quality.
And so much like cerebr um they do
essentially they have to have you know
some strategy to get scaling right right
so so stepping back right you're going
to do a really big model run what do you
have to do you have to pick
hyperparameters you have to make sure
those hyperparameters scale nicely and
then you scale up your model right so uh
we can do the same thing as the
cerebraas GPT folks we can try to pick
hyperparameters at a small scale hope
that they sort of stay stable and then
scale everything up and the way to do
that would to use something like mup and
this has exactly the same kinds of
strategy at play here. You see um so for
embedding you don't really do anything
you just scale it by a constant um
whenever you have some sort of like
residual connection like an MLP you
scale it by the square root of the
number of layers um you initialize it by
sort of fan in one over the the base uh
width and then um the learning rates are
also scaled by the width of the model.
we see basically the same um strategy or
the same kinds of scaling factors appear
as the cerebrus GPT um case, right? And
they they also end up with very similar
parameters um as SUS GPT, the same kinds
of scale embeddings um similar learning
rates um off by a factor of two or so.
Um but generally you end up in similar
places um as these kinds of
hyperparameters.
And then what you do is once you have
this um you're sort of relying on your
optimum learning rates to remain stable.
So you're just going to keep those
roughly fixed. And we know that the
aspect ratio is a pretty important
thing. So we just fix that after
figuring out what the right one is. And
then you scale up the overall model size
going all the way from you know 9 or 30
30mm all the way to half or or one uh
billion parameter models, right? Um, and
so what they have is like a roughly 5x
or maybe a little bit more compute
savings going from the smallest models
that they've got to the the uh largest
sort of pilot run models that they have.
And now you can use this and then you
can sort of figure out um whether you
have sort of optimal batch sizes as a
function of scale. So you know you want
to figure out crit which is the critical
batch size. If you remember correctly
this is um the critical batch size is
roughly the diminishing returns point
right. So as models get bigger, their
losses get lower. As their loss gets
lower, you you can make use of bigger
and bigger batch sizes. So the critical
batch size is roughly telling you for
the given model size and scale that I'm
operating at, what is what is a
appropriate global batch size um for me
to be training these models with. And so
um much like the the Kaplan paper, they
follow a similar kind of recipe. You
know, the plots look different from the
Kaplan paper, but the underlying
strategy is kind of the same. What
they're trying to figure out is what is
the critical batch size for training or
the optimal batch size in this case of
for training different models and
they're trying to find relatively
predictable scaling relationships um
between the batch size and for example
the data size or the loss size
um and vertical columns here sort of
represent a single training curve and
then sort of the the the quadratics are
sort of being fitted um to try to
identify the minimum right so the red
line here is the is the minimum across
all these points as we go um upwards and
this is trying to tell us the optimum
batch size for a particular choice of
model size um and data set
size. Um and then at this point you know
you can follow the same logic as the
Kaplan paper for identifying the batch
sizes. Um basically you you reproduce
the same kind of plot if you remember
the Kaplan uh paper and the critical
batch size discussion from two lectures
ago. um if not you can kind of pull up
the lecture slides. Um you'll remember
that basically the thing that's highly
predictable is the loss that you're
trying to train to the terminal loss and
the batch size of like the critical
batch size point. And so we see that
once again much like in Kaplan um you
see a log log linear relationship here
um between the target loss or the the
terminal loss and the batch size that
you want right and so from this you know
you can kind of figure out what batch
size you're going to get right because
if you have a particular target scale
you can use scaling loss to figure out
what is the loss that I expect to get
once you know the loss that you expect
to get you can use that to to back out
what batch size you can kind of operate
at right so there's a fairly clean trend
polinomially increase the batch size as
loss decreases
Um now batch sizes do sort of shift
around as a function of um of uh target
loss and thus compute. So we have to fit
a scaling law for that guy. But we
already did mu and so in theory right if
the approach works at all um what we
should now get is we should get that the
optimum learning rate here is stable. So
on this plot we're seeing um essentially
different model sizes from sort of small
models in the light colors to their
biggest models in in the dark colors.
And you see them sort of varying
different learning rates. The big models
they're only running for a little bit
for compute reasons. But what you see is
a is a fairly clear trend and you know
once again very consistent with some of
the earlier results that we've seen um
in Kaplan at all where you have a
relatively wide basin and then sort of
sharp increases as your your model
becomes very unstable. Right? But the
important thing here is that the minimum
remains fixed across relatively large
orders of magnitude. Right? From your
small model to the big model, the
minimum or at least tied with the
minimum is at the exact same point at
roughly uh 10^ the -2 um learning rate.
And so this is a nice sort of piece of
evidence or some validation that
properly scaling um your model
initialization and properly scaling your
per layer learning rates allow you to uh
avoid tuning learning rates over and
over or even fitting scaling laws on
learning rates um in order to try to
predict what the optimal um learning
rate
is. Okay. And then the final thing is,
you know, you might want to figure out
um essentially model size to data
trade-offs. If you're training small
models, um you're going to be probably
overtraining your models or at least you
want to justify to yourself um why
you're training on so many tokens. Um
and so you might want to re replicate
something like the chinchilla analysis.
Um so the mini CPM people um had a
really cool or nice innovation. um
others have done similar things but I
think they were the first to really
popularize this in the LM setting
especially um in the context of of uh
chinchilla style scaling is kind of the
following so let's say I want to fit a
chinchilla scaling law um when I do that
what do I need to do well I need to vary
um the number of uh tokens and I need to
vary model sizes right and so when I do
that I'm going to fix a model size and
I'm going to train a model for longer
and longer it would be nice if I could
sort of early stop and take the
checkpoints of this model and have that
be sort of the difference or changes to
the data set size, right? Because
earlier checkpoints see less data. It
would be nice if I could use a single
run to collect um all this sort of data
scaling things. Unfortunately, what I'm
showing here, right, is that kind of the
cosign learning rates for different data
targets are different, right? So, if you
have a very small amount of data, you
have a cosine that goes up very quickly
or sorry, that goes up the the the
warm-up is always the same, but a very
fast cool down, right? You you train for
a little bit and then you come down very
quickly. If you have a lot of data, then
you're going to very slowly come down to
the end. And so your learning rates
between a small data training run and a
big data training run will be different.
Right? This is a very very key point.
Right? Lots of people get tripped up by
this. You cannot use a single run of a
cosign learning rate model and try to
get early checkpoints and reason about
data scaling behavior based on that.
Right? This is this bites people all the
time. And so in order to avoid this,
what you would normally need to do is
you need to train a model from start to
every single end point, right? So you
you have to train it to every single
target. And so this kind of takes you to
n squared runs, right? Like some of the
runs are small, but you have to
basically run lots of runs, each one
with a target termination point rather
than using a single run and collecting
checkpoints. It's it feels kind of
senseless that we have to do this.
So, um, the mini CPM folks, um,
popularized this idea of a of a WSD or
warm-up stable decay learning rate. Um,
and so this plot on the left really
shows you, um, you know, what's going on
here. Normally, what we would train with
is something that looks like this cosine
learning rate shown in yellow here,
right? It goes up, there's a warm-up
period, um, usually very short, um, to
get to your full learning rate, and then
there's a cosine that goes all the way
down to kind of your termination point.
And maybe you stay at your minimum
learning rate. Um this is all of course
optional. You might terminate here as
well. You might go all the way to zero,
right? Um and so cosine learning rate
looks like this. And the issue here of
course is that if I have a different
target, the cosine is going to be
totally different. So everything past
the warm-up can't be reused. Now if you
look at the this this new WSD, which is
basically a trapezoid learning rate,
what it has is three phases. It's got a
a warm-up phase that's the same as a
cosine. It's got a stable phase that's
flat. And then it's got a decay phase
that rapidly cools down the model down
to its minimum learning rate. And of
course, you can have variations of this.
You can go up, down, and then stay
stable at your minimum. You know, you
can do any of these variations. But I
think in general, um, the simplest form
to think about is warm up, stable,
decay, terminate, right? Um, why is this
nice? This is nice because you can reuse
the stable part, right? So the thing
that you do is if you want to do
chinchilla in almost one run, what you
do is you sort of warm up. you have a
stable run all the way to the end and
then you cool down and then if you want
to figure out oh how would my model have
been if I used less data you rewind the
checkpoints and then you do another cool
down right and now you've got a exact
warm-up stable decay learning rate shape
without having done the training from
the beginning right so this is a very
nice thing the fact that the stable part
essentially is flat allows you to uh do
chinchilla style scaling or data scaling
um in a single training run or for for
mostly the cost of a single training run
um and a lot of people now do
Okay. Um, so they work very well. Um,
mini CPM I think popularized this and
you know I think a lot of people have
since then adopted it and and we see a
lot of WSD style schedules in many many
places. Um, they you see curves that
look kind of like this. If you have a
cosign learning rate um schedule, you'll
see essentially
relatively predictable smooth decay
towards your terminal loss like this
yellow line here. Um, if you train with
WSD, uh, you'll see much much funkier
learning curves that look like, you
know, the the curves that I have here
above them, the darker lines, right? So,
you've got your warm-up phase, which
doesn't really show up in this training
curve. It's so short. Then you got your
stable phase where it sort of goes down
normally, and then as soon as you hit
your decay phase, like the cool down
part, your loss really rapidly drops off
until you've hit your sort of either
zero or or minimum learning rate point,
at which point you you've gotten your
terminal loss, right? So um these losses
may look very disturbing to you but they
are actually pretty normal when you're
training with these kinds of sort of
rapid cooldown learning curves. And
maybe the point to make here is at every
single token count you see that the
warm-up stable decay curve you know the
minimum point um beats or matches the
cosine learning rate. That's not always
the case. There can sometimes be cases
where cosine works better WSD works
better. But in general, I think a lot of
the I think things that people say here
is that the two learning rates are
roughly comparable, but WSD has the
additional nice advantage that you don't
have to worry about your termination
point. You can repeatedly cool down to
get checkpoints of different data
counts. Okay.
Um, cool. Okay. And then of course
there's um other things that have
appeared for for trying to estimate
chinchilla. um some folks um a
collaboration of like Udub, formerly
Udub and um Apple folks had this um
paper on estimating sort of the
chinchilla penalty that is when you keep
adding more and more data you know how
much worse is your loss um than if you
had you know scaled according to
chinchilla. So you have your sort of
teal line here which is sort of m equals
20 you know 20 tokens to uh parameters
and you can sort of think about okay
what happens if I train with 320 tokens
to parameters well then you have a
separate parallel scaling line and then
you have another line which is the
circles which is what if I train with
640 um or the darker one is there and so
the thing that they show is actually
instead of doing this WSD style thing
another thing you could do um is you
could try to figure out okay how much
does my model degree grade as a function
of sort of higher tokens to parameter
ratios. Well, that turns out also to
have a fairly predictable shape. Um, and
you can sort of extrapolate that based
on sort of degradation at small training
runs. Um, I don't think I've seen large
scale training runs using this idea, but
it's kind of an additional cool thing to
know that essentially you could do
chinchilla in almost one training run by
sort of extrapolating the the uh excess
token penalty at a small scale as well.
So okay going back to mini CPM um now we
have the tools that we need. We have the
WSD learning rate which allows us to
essentially do one training run and that
one training run allows us to you know
have both variation sorry not that one
training run allows us to vary data as
we go along and then we have multiple
training runs for different model sizes
that gives us all that we need to do
chinchilla analysis. Um and they use
method one and method three if you
remember what those are. Method one is
you overlay all of the learning curves
and you take the lower envelope and the
lower envelope of all the training
curves um is supposed to be um roughly a
power law. And then method three is you
basically jointly fit this equation two
you have here. You you hypothesize this
two variable scaling law and you kind of
fit it to all the data that you have uh
in kind of curve fitting style fashion.
Um and then that you know allows you to
solve for the optimum uh token to to
data ratio uh through that fit. Um so
they do both of that. Um they do see for
chinchilla method one fairly clear
although not perfectly linear trends
that allow them to essentially go from
um uh compute to to token ratios. Um and
their primary approach that they use to
to justify a lot of their design
decisions is the method three. It's the
curve fitting. So the the kind of
contours that you see here is the curve
that they fit. The dots that they have
here is the small scale runs that they
did to fit the chinchilla parameters. Um
and just to you know um sort of uh
justify what they do they find very very
high token to parameter ratios like so
high that I feel like this is an outlier
that doesn't really agree very closely
with most of the other literature. Um
they they argue that llama style
architecture should all have a higher
ratio because of you know improved data
quality and improved model efficiency
but their token to parameter ratio
estimates are really really high 192
tokens per parameter which I don't think
I've seen um anyone else derive I think
other people have done replications of
chinchillaa I don't think anyone's ever
really done uh or or argued for 192
tokens to parameter regardless um you
know we have seen that recent models
like llama 3 have significantly higher
data to model ratios. We also don't
really see diminishing returns. Like
these models aren't way worse than the
equivalent chinchilla scaled like llama
2 models. This kind of suggests that
with careful optimization and careful
tuning, we should be able to go far
beyond like the 20 times model size rule
of thumb, right? So if there's one thing
you take away from this set of sort of,
you know, these last two slides, maybe
not necessarily that you should trust
whatever scaling law fits that mini CPM
vid. um but rather that sort of the
chinchilla analysis isn't really um you
know a strong constraint right like 20
times model size is just a starting
point you should be you know feeling
free to significantly increase that
token to parameter ratio
um finally the the curve fits that they
get are generally pretty good looking um
so this is the scaling lock curves for
essentially um data and model size um
scaling and perplexities on code in
English they do have some really weird
outliers that I don't really understand
um why they get these um but their sort
of fitted scaling laws are generally
pretty good um as they increase the
amount of data on their relatively small
model. So this is one example of a you
know large scale training run scaling
recipe. So I'll stop here. Um things
like WSVR are probably new to you. So um
you know if you have any questions
please feel free to to ask or or any of
the other bits including um like the
chinchilla replication and mu and so on.
Oh okay
sure the main adaptation of mu is in
terms of initializing the weight of
parameters right so the question was the
main change in mup was initialization um
so there's two things that will happen
when you derive and you implement mup um
one of them will be the initialization
will change and the other thing will be
that the learning rate changes um or the
learning rate changes per layer right um
and that is probably a more exotic
object than many of you are used to Um
the initialization actually is not that
different. If you're already using like
um a standard like um like kynang style
initialization, that's already one over
the fan in uh one sorry one over the
square root of the fan in um which is
going to be already the right thing. Um
whereas the learning rate normally like
unless you're doing something really
exotic, you're using like a global
constant learning rate, right,
everywhere. So that's going to be a big
difference um from what you're you're
normally training with. So you can think
of that as like the practical difference
for a lot of the MUP implementations.
Yes,
was kept
constant. Uh we saw that the curve was
very close to the cosine decay.
Yeah. So you're talking about this this
curve and you're saying like oh when
when we're in the stable phase of WSD
like when we're up here the curve
remains pretty close and like why is
that? Well, it's kind of close, but also
not really, right? Like if you look at
this this last curve over here, um, you
know, there's a big gap before we enter
the decay phase between cosine and um,
WSD. And I think this is like one of the
pretty interesting, you know, mysteries
about deep learning optimizers. Um,
clearly you need a stable phase to to
kind of get you far from your
initialization, but also the cool down
phase is what gets you most of your
gains and your losses, right? If you
don't cool down, this is a gigantic loss
in your losses. Um, so the cool down is
actually really critical. And you know,
a lot of the gains from cosine versus
here, like this relative gap, this is
all from cool down, right? Um, and so a
lot of the optimizer learning rate uh
design is about this balance between
like how do I keep learning rates high
to to travel far from my my
initialization but still have, you know,
good decay on my learning rate to be
able to unneal my loss down um to a very
low value.
So um the other paper I want to talk
about is uh DeepSeek. Um this is the
original DeepSseek LLM uh paper from
2024. Um and in many ways if you read
the original DeepS LLM paper, you'll
kind of you can know that these are like
very serious science people, you know,
because they do a lot of very careful
scaling ablations and they're really
trying to get it right when they scale
up. And that's kind of an attitude
that's shared amongst um sort of the the
players that that get scaling right. Um
so you know they have seven and 67b
parameter models. Um you know at the
time very high performance relative to
you know llama um which is really the
primary competitor at the time. Um and
you know there at the time I guess you
know llama 2 and mistrol were kind of
the big players. Deepse comes in and
they they're able to match the
performance. Not quite the the flashy
impact of Deepseek V3 coming in and sort
of matching um OpenAI's uh GBD40, but
you know, for a first time sort of
attempt, this is a pretty remarkable
result. And so, let's kind of dig in and
try to understand, all right, like what
did DeepSeek do that allowed them to go
from essentially zero to um you know, at
least for open source state-of-the-art
um at the time, right?
So, and I think um DeepSeek more than
you know most other players maybe the
only comparable one being mini CPM is
very very open about a lot of the
experiments they did and their the
approach they use to choose a lot of
these hyperparameters. Um so immediately
we see one difference between Deepseek
v1 and uh mini CPM and also Cerebris GPT
which is that they don't use any MUP. um
and they're going to directly try to
estimate both the optimal batch size and
the optimum optimal learning rate. So
it's like a really direct method you
might call it um and requires kind of a
strong belief in scaling laws. Um so
what they do is they you know take um
two relatively small models and they
have uh they run a grid over different
batch sizes, they run a grid over
different learning rates and they get
losses um across this grid. they do the
same thing at a larger scale and you
know you can get kind of the optimum
batch size and learning rate right um
and so they're saying all right well
this is a pretty wide basin so we don't
maybe have to be you know too scared
about messing this up and so then what
they do is they know that all right this
the choice of learning rate and batch
size are both relatively forgiving but
we do want to get the order of magnitude
of these things correct right so how do
we get the order of magnitude of these
things correct Well, you know what we're
going to do is we're going to train a
bunch of models um with different
amounts of you know non-mbedding flops
and we're going to change um essentially
across a grid the the parameters that I
had before both the the batch size and
the learning rate and by varying these
you know we're going to have the optimum
batch size and the optimum uh learning
rate sorry across these different scales
right so you can imagine basically
making these grids across many different
flop scales um and basically marking
down a are for each
one. Um perhaps unsurprisingly because
it's the scaling law lectures, these
things seem to kind of follow um a
scaling law line. Um at least for the
batch size, things seem more clear and
you can kind of fit a line to here and
you can, you know, extrapolate out to
the big models that you're going to
train what your optimum batch sizes
should kind of look like, right? Um they
do the same thing with learning rate. um
and they sort of fit this line and they
say, "Oh, these are the two learning
rates we're going to use." Um it might
be because the points are being plotted
on top of each other, but I find this
line to be particularly not particularly
like somewhat suspicious looking. I
mean, I could have probably fit a
horizontal line and that would have also
looked okay. This one, I don't know,
even as a as a scaling law enthusiast,
uh I'm not quite sure I would, you know,
bet my life on this one to pick the
learning rate, but they did. And you
know, that's how they get the learning
rate.
Um now they also uh kind of follow best
practices at the time. Um they do a
chinchilla style analysis and they use
once again a WSD style learning rate. Um
where you know they're trying to
essentially minimize the amount of
repeated work that they do. Um they do
kind of something a little bit weird or
a little bit uh more non-standard where
what they're doing is you know they do
warm up, they do stable and then they do
two sets of decay steps decaying down to
zero. So it's like two, you know, decay
phases um consisting of um kind of like
10% plus 10%. And they sort of analyze
different choices of that decay phase.
Um and they kind of doesn't seem to
matter very much, but generally speaking
it, you know, it's about 20% of the
total compute budget is going to be
spent on that cool down phase.
Um and so they also show once again that
it matches cosine learning rates. But
once again the advantage here is that we
can do chinchilla style analysis um for
very cheap in contrast to the learning
rate sorry learning rate fits um you
know chinchilla style analysis just fits
really really cleanly. I think this is a
a broad lesson when you look at lots of
people's scaling laws. I think the stuff
on hyperparameters always looks a little
noisy and and tenuous. Um but the
isoflops analysis from all the players
look always like very very nice. And so
this is you know replication of the
chinchilla result. You see you know
different compute scales. We see
different quadratics. We draw a line
through the bottom of the quadratics. We
get um you know exactly the kinds of of
sort of optimum uh sorry optimum flops
per token and optimum token size as a
function of training flops. Right? So
this gives us a very straightforward way
of analyzing uh the token size to model
size trade-offs. Um and this allows them
sort of do everything from scratch,
right? Of course, I think, you know, as
a side commentary, I think it's really
nice that they're kind of redoing a lot
of this. Like they could have certainly
cargo culted um chinchilla and just
picked 20 tokens per parameter but they
said no like let's actually go and do
the the scaling law analysis and like
let's actually make sure that you know
that the token uh sizes are relatively
appropriate for
us. Okay. Um and then they have you know
a fitted scaling law at the very end. Um
this is in some ways not surprising
because this is after they fix their
scaling strategy. They do predictable
scaling. they try to predict what
happens on the 7B and the 67b models.
Um, you know, it's unsurprising in many
ways, but very nice that they're able to
extrapolate out from about uh 10 to the
20 to 10 to the 24 um and actually nail
the prediction on the basis of the
scaling law. Right? So, it's a very nice
thing to be able to see that we can
actually get um uh predictive uh
measures of of model capabilities before
we actually train them. So, that's um
kind of the deepseek part. Anyone have
questions for for kind of the Deep Seek
strategy and kind of what they did and
and any of the other pieces? I think
most of this I think WSD was probably
the newest thing that I've sort of
mentioned today. Um the other thing that
DeepS seek does is directly fitting a
scaling law to the optimum learning rate
and batch sizes rather than using
something like
yes. Uh do they have a global learning
rate? Yeah. So so they're tuning that
global learning
Cool. Okay. Yeah. Once we know the
problem.
Yeah. So, so the question was like do
people redo this kind of analysis for
new frontier models? Um to be honest,
I'm not actually sure and I I'm
beginning to think that a lot of people
maybe don't like exactly replicate some
of this. Um because we see that in the
newer paper is just increasingly less
scaling details. Like even from deepseek
um for example like deepseek v2 and then
v3 we see a lot of emphasis on the new
parts of each paper like so for deepseek
v2 we see a lot of emphasis on like uh
MLA and like the architectural
improvements and then deepseeek v3 we
see a lot of the systems components
being emphasized like the the low bit
training um but we don't see for example
in either of those um any additional new
scaling loss studies um and so I think
my guess is that there's not much new
there like maybe they're replicating it
just to make sure it works but nothing
new to report. Um, and I think that that
will kind of um be captured in the next
couple slides where I'm going to talk
about uh scaling laws and papers and and
models from the last year or so. Um, so
I I did a little brief survey. Um, but
actually there's nothing that is at the
level of detail of either mini CPM or
deepseek like those are really still I
think the most detailed open studies
into scaling that we have uh in
2025. Cool. Okay. So, you know, Llama 3
was probably one of the bigger model
releases in the past year since I last
taught this class. Um, and they do have
some pretty interesting scaling bits.
Um, for one, you know, just the question
right now of like, do people actually
replicate these analyses once they've
run them once? Well, kind of yes. um
Llama 3, you know, redo the isoflop
style scaling um chinchilla scaling laws
and they find you know roughly that the
optimum ratio um if I if I got the
calculation right is about 39 to1 right
um and I do think this is interesting um
because you know chinchilla got the 20
to1 parameter ratio um I think many of
us have trained models at the chinchilla
ratio um in our research and so on um
you know it's quite clear that the 20
isn't really that stable like other
people that have in fitting it have been
getting generally slightly higher ratios
than before. Um, and that might point to
things like improved algorithmic
efficiency in in sort of architectures
that that learn better from data. Um, it
might mean uh something else like
improved data quality. Um, all of those
are kind of moving parts. So, it's hard
to know like what's leading to these
slightly different ratios, but the
results seem fairly clear. The the fits
are relatively good and they do get a 40
to1 ratio.
The other thing which is um close to the
the data scaling stuff that I mentioned
um the early parts of my first scaling
lecture. Um one of the interesting
things that the Llama 3 folks do is they
try to essentially correlate um compute
into uh NLS like log loss and then
correlate those NLS back into downstream
accuracies. Right? And so, um, the
thinking that they're trying to do here
is they would like to not really scale
against log likelihoods. That's not
really a thing they truly care about,
right? They care about improving, I
don't know, benchmark numbers on um,
MMLU or Lombata or whatever other
benchmarks that they've decided to hill
climb on, right? Um, and so if that's
the case, then what they're going to
need is to have a conversion factor
going from these NLS per character,
these these, you know, perplexities or
equivalent to perplexities, and then map
them into accuracies. And so they
they've done some studies in in llama 3
essentially trying to relate these two
fitting sigmoids showing that you know
um if you fit uh essentially these small
models and you fit some llama 2 models
and you fit a sigmoid on the whole thing
you can accurately predict the
performance of llama 3 uh 405b on the
basis of those fits. It's interesting.
Um I think they say that they use these
kinds of ideas for for data selection.
Um, but I think it's a there's not that
much details there and it's unclear
whether this is like a really core
object um when Llama 3 was being trained
or whether this was kind of a sidecaling
thing that was like just of interest to
the
authors. Um, another recent work that
has come out um sort of yet another
Chinese LLM that's nicely executed is
Hunuan 1. Um, hopefully I didn't really
butcher the pronunciation there. um they
are training and so because they're
training they want to kind of redo the
chinchilla style analysis they fit once
again they do isoflops analysis they fit
quadratics they figure out the minimums
and then they're able to get a different
token to parameter ratio so they get a
96 to1 data to active parameter ratio um
these ratios are obviously going to be
quite different because they're training
there's lots of differences about the
architectures we don't really expect the
same thing as chinchilla right um and so
we do actually see in in various papers
Essentially replications of chinchilla
happen again and again because a lot of
these people are are very interested in
understanding like how far can I push
the token to um parameter size ratio. we
would like to stay on the higher end of
that right like have more data than
parameters because then people will
actually use our models or or our models
will be cheap to serve right so for all
those reasons um people have been
replicating um chinchilla I think this
is one of the the best replicated
results in scaling in many ways um the
the actual 20 to1 parameter ratio isn't
the thing that you know consistently
replicates but the fact that you can do
isoflops and fit the minimum and get
these like very predictable um tradeoffs
in flops to uh minim optimal
act optimum parameters is um quite clean
um and consistent in the
replications. Okay. Um the last one
which is honestly a little bit more of
an exotic um uh scaling law over the
last year is minimax one uh which came
out pretty recently. Um so minimax one
is a kind of linear time or long context
language model um released by another
sort of Chinese startup. Um and their
interest is well what we're going to do
is we're going to take softmax attention
which is quadratic and you know they
have this thing called lightning
attention which is a kind of linear um
attention or linear yeah linear
attention uh layer which is linear time.
Um, and then you know they have a hybrid
version of this model and they want to
figure out like all right, how much cost
am I paying in terms of the performance
of the model going from softmax to to
linear to hybrid um attention. And so
they do things like they basically
replicate method one for chinchilla
where they're looking at the lower
envelope of the loss curves as they
train. They look at essentially the
implied optimal model size and the
implied optimal token count as they go.
And roughly the conclusion that they
draw from this is that you know the the
lightning um and the hybrid models you
know roughly perform the same as the
softmax attention um and thus they can
they're you know okay to train long
context models on the basis of these
architectures. Um, we've seen these
kinds of plots um occur very often in
research papers. Like if you look at the
the Mamba paper or the Mamba 2 paper or
any or the Delta paper or any of these
other kinds of linear uh time complexity
R&M papers, you'll see plots that look a
lot like this where they say, "Oh, the
full attention scaling and my linear
attention scaling are basically the same
as a function of compute." But this is,
you know, um I would say like a kind of
a rare case of this same plot being
produced um almost at scale from a uh
major sort of artifact
release. Okay, so putting all that
together, right, I know that was like a
bunch of mini case studies uh that I I
went through fairly quickly. Um but I
want to sort of step back and recap it a
little bit, right? We've seen several
common ingredients being used in these
scaling recipes. Um we've seen cerebrus
deepseeek mini CPM um and then the few
new uh papers since um so Cerebris GPT
and mini CPM both use MUP as a way to
make hyperparameters more stable across
scale. Um and you know they essentially
uh mini CPM especially has um a nice uh
WSD schedule which is a a thing they
popularize to be able to do chinchilla
style scaling. Cerebrus doesn't bother
to to replicate chinchilla. Deepse seek
does a little bit different thing. They
assume that most hyperparameters just
don't change with scale but they do a
full scaling analysis on batch size and
learning rate and then they use the
scaling laws as a way to figure out
optimum scaling. You know I've already
noted that some of the scaling looks a
little bit more suspicious than others
but really this is a way to at least get
the order of magnitude hopefully right.
They use isoflops analysis. you know,
they replicate chinchilla once again to
figure out the model sizing and to make
sure they're kind of in the right order
of
magnes. You know, Llama 3 and Hunan do
uh isoflops analysis only. Um Llama 3
does a little bit more, but that's
basically it. And then Minimax does the
more interesting thing of of basically
justifying architecture choices uh
through the lens of a scaling law. But
we see generally speaking um that
there's a few different things that get
replicated like chinchilla um and
learning rate and batch size are really
the things that people are really deeply
concerned about when they're scaling
models up and they sort of do things
like fixed aspect ratio and just scale
the total model size up and that's
generally the way that people handle a
lot of the the moving pieces uh of
scaling
up. Okay. Um any questions about the the
case studies pieces? Actually, I'm going
to stay here and just make sure um I've
covered any questions that people might
have. Okay,
cool. Okay, so the second and and kind
of last part of this lecture is going to
be understanding up. Um hopefully
through the case studies you've seen
that essentially getting the learning
rate right is one of the core concerns
that people have. um and also the batch
size. But in general, I think we want to
have scale and variant hyperparameters.
And it is the case that you know our
choice of initialization and our choice
of per layer learning rates are
essentially arbitrary, right? Like
there's no reason why we have to
initialize them one way and not the
other. Um and so if we could manipulate
those sort of three variables to get
scale and variance in our learning
rates, that would just be really
wonderful, right? Like that that would
make our lives way easier and it would
make, you know, small scale experiments
much more possible.
So you know I'll also talk you know
first through the the math of this like
how it's derived what's the
justification what are the core
conceptual objects behind trying to make
models scale predictably and then I want
to talk about uh a pretty pretty nice um
preprint by an independent researcher um
on basically just a bunch of ablations
on up like what makes it break what is
it robust to um does it work on a real
you know transformer language model
these kinds of questions um are explored
pretty well in this preprint that I'll
talk about um at the very end
here. So, okay, what is MUP anyway? I
feel like um maybe I've jumped the gun
for the last two lectures because I've
mentioned what this is without really
giving you the core conceptual object
that it's based off of. Um on the other
hand, I think I'm I'm justified in doing
this because I think most of the
literature doesn't explain MUP that
clearly either. They're just like, yeah,
just scale the the initialization by one
over the width and scale the per layer
learning rate by one over the width.
That's MUP. Um, but I think the ideas
behind MUP are pretty interesting and
worth discussing because I think they
speak to to some core objects that that
recur in uh deep learning in general.
So, I'm going to be basing my slides off
this uh preprint or paper. Um, if you're
interested in kind of reading about MUP,
um I would point you to this one. I
think this and another um uh blog post
called a practitioner guides to MUP I
think are the two kind of readable um
descriptions of what the sort of this
paradigm is. Okay. So I'm going to base
myself off this. Um the math is for
whatever reason not exactly the same
across these different presentations. So
I'll I'll you know clarify that I'm
basing the math off this one. So MUP is
based off of this the following
relatively simple ideas, right? So
there's two things that we think should
happen when we're training a neural
network, right? So you know when we
scale a neural network, we're going to
make the in this case, let's just say
only the width, the width of the network
bigger, right? I'm going to fix the
layer size or the sorry the depth and
I'm going to make the width bigger as we
go. Now if I do that, um, as I make the
width bigger, I want the activations at
initialization to remain uh, you know,
big theta of one, right? I want it to
remain roughly constant, you know,
bounded above and below by universal
constant, you know, roughly constant as
I make the width bigger. It shouldn't
blow up. It shouldn't vanish, right?
Seems like a pretty natural thing to
want, right? You don't want your
activations to get too big. This is per
uh coordinate. Now, the second assertion
I want is that, you know, I'm going to
initialize my model and I'm going to
take a single gradient step. And when I
take that single gradient step, I want
to make sure that the change in
activation should also be um big theta
of one, right? Um, so both of these seem
like very natural conditions, right?
Because if you violate these, it's going
to mean that, you know, as I make the
models bigger, either the initial
activations will blow up or or vanish or
after one gradient step, my activations
will either blow up or vanish, right?
Those are both bad bad conditions,
right? Um, and as a note, right, I'm
talking about individual activations
like coordinates. And so if you're
thinking about norms, right, of of an
entire vector of activations, right,
that should look like, you know, big
theta of square root of NL, right?
Because each one of these are going to
be roughly independent. So the norm is
going to look like um the square root of
the width the the number of uh elements
in my in my um width coordinate. So um I
can derive uh you know mu from those two
conditions. So the first condition which
is that I want my activation to remain
stable um imposes sort of constraints on
the uh initialization right so so I'm
going to walk you through a very very
simple example right so I'm going to
consider a deep linear network so this
is h of l so this is the activations at
layer little l and that's going to be a
function of the the weight matrix at
layer l and the uh activations from the
previous layer no nonlinearities no
fancy stuff right like you know it's all
square just forget all this complexities
if you want complexities you can go read
the preprint they'll explain um in
slightly handwavy terms why those things
don't matter um now the initialization
I'm going to pick a gausian
initialization right so it's going to be
zero centered it's going to be a
rectangular size of the of the sizes um
that depend on the the sizes of my
activations and then I'm going to have
one hyperparameter which is the um noise
scale um of this matrix at this layer.
Sorry, there should be a little L on
this sigma. Um, so now what can we say?
Well, I want to understand the size of H
of L, you know, at initialization. So,
how can we do that? Well, one thing we
can do is we can consider sort of the
limiting behavior of this system, right?
I'm going to take the um basically
little n of L and little N of L minus
one to infinity. And if I do that, this
W is going to concentrate. It's a random
Gaussian matrix. If you remember your
your um random matrix theory, actually
that's not a prerequisite for the
course, but um you know if you know some
basic random matrix theory, you know
that the the operator norm of a g
gausian matrix is going to roughly
concentrate to this object, right? It's
going to be sigma which is the noise
scale times, you know, the square root
of both of the coordinates added. And
importantly, you know, you can write
down roughly that this equivalence is
true, right? So the activations at layer
L the norm of that is going to be
approximately equal to the operator norm
of WL times the activation norm of H of
L minus one. Right? And this is roughly
assuming that W of L is independent of H
of L minus one which is true at
initialization. So I think you can
basically make that a right arrow if
you'd like. Um now I'm going to say I'm
going to pick a particular choice of
sigma which is going to be square
nl nl minus one times this object.
You can simply think of it as this right
hand side thing. Um this is the exact
form. This is kind of the more asintoic
form that you can think of this as, but
really it's just one over the square
root of the fan in of your layer times
the minimum of one and sort of the the
aspect ratio um of your your model in
case um your fan in is much larger than
your fan out then then this sort of
kicks in. Okay. So let's say that I pick
this sigma what happens right roughly
one over the square root of my fan in.
So now what happens? I can I can plug
this back in to this formula, the matrix
concentration limit and also this
approximation here and I can sort of
inductively prove that every layer is
going to have the right sort of
activation size. So let's just go
through all the layers and assume that
up until layer L minus one I have this
property right so that's the inductive
assumption at layer L minus one I have
that my activation norm is square root
of N L minus one. Okay, so that's just
an assumption. Now if this is true then
I just plug all of these in right so I
plug in square root of nl minus one into
this component into wl operator norm I
plug in the limit and then for sigma I
plug in this expression over here you
see that this inverse cancels this and
then you're going to get um exactly that
h of l uh the l2 norm of h of l is equal
to um square root of n of l. So this is
the the thing that we wanted because
before remember we said we want to make
sure that the activations remains big
theta of one which means that the norm
should be square root of n of l. So
that's exactly what we get plus some
lower order terms right. Um so you know
this is a fairly clear step-by-step
argument that shows you what the right
thing to do is for initializations. I
want to pick one over the square root of
the fan in plus a small correction
factor um in order to make sure that my
activations do not blow up at
initialization. Right? Um I'll pause
here for a moment in case someone has
questions. I feel like this is actually
maybe the first like real math that
we've done in the class. So maybe it's a
bit of a context switch for people. I
did not warn you that I was going to
talk about a bit of
math. Okay. Um is this all relatively
clear for people? one over square root
of fann. Yes. Okay. I'm gonna assume
that everyone's on board with one over
square root of fann. Okay. So now um
we're gonna derive uh the second part of
muup. Right. So the first part of muup
was about initializations. The second
part of muup is going to be about
learning rates. Right? Um and so how are
we going to think about learning rates?
Well to think about learning rates I'm
going to look at the second condition.
The second condition A2 which says when
I take one gradient step past
initialization what needs to happen is
that my activation sorry my update size
needs to remain constant. It can't blow
up. It can't vanish. Okay. So what does
that mean? So if I have an update of
delta WL on the weights at at layer L um
what where does that come from? Well
that comes from let's say I'm doing SGD.
Um that's going to come from this
expression. It's going to be a learning
rate times um L which is my loss, the
gradient of L which is my loss and then
the activations transposed. Um in the
case that my batch size is one, this is
a rank one object, right? This is a rank
one update to delta of L, right? Um and
because it's rank one, you know, there's
a nice easy expression. the change of WL
times the um activation of the previous
layer is equal to the norm of the change
in WL the operator norm of this thing um
times the L2 norm of H of L minus one
right and now you know combine this with
the fact that the change in activation
at layer L is kind of this expression
you can convince yourself that this is
true you can write this out by by sort
of figuring out what the actual final um
activation is at layer L after the
update and that and canceling out um wlh
of ll which is a a shared term across
left and right then you'll get this
expression um you'll get that you know
what is the update in h of l this is the
object that we want to keep roughly um
square root of n of l right the norm of
this object so so let's look through
each of these terms and look at what the
magnitude of this is the first term here
wl delta h of l minus one this you know
we can assume is going to be controlled
from the inductive assumption because
this is exactly um the uh sort of the
the delta h of l um that we have plus
the condition a1 argument right
condition a1 basically says um sorry
condition a1 is going to say that uh
delta of h of l minus one is going to be
square root nl and then wl is going to
maintain that norm um the more
complicated parts is going to be these
two arguments the second and third terms
that we have here delta wl h of ll minus
one and delta wl delta hl minus one
sorry that's that's quite the mouthful
um they all have the same order of
magnitude actually. And the only thing
that we need to really figure out is
this expression here. What is the
product of the previous layers norm
times the operator norm of delta WL?
Right? Because we don't really know how
big the update is going to be in the
weight matrix W if we knew that. All
very straightforward
stuff. Okay. Um and so the remaining
argument is actually relatively
straightforward. Um even though this is
actually like a you know complicated
jumble of things the intuition is
actually very clear. Um the intuition
for this is says okay what do I really
need to figure out? The one thing I
really need to figure out is this
expression here. How much does the
weight at layer L change right? If I can
figure that out then I can sort of
derive all the relevant quantities and
solve for the learning rate. That's at a
high level that's our strategy here. Um
and so how can we possibly figure out a
after one gradient step how much delta
WL moves right that's really the key
question well um there's an additional
sort of sneaky assumption that then
shows up here um and the assumption is
something like this if our learning is
well behaved then after a single
gradient step then the change in the
loss delta of L this quantity has to
also be big theta of one right and why
is that well because we don't want the
size of our losses, the update, the
decrease in our losses to kind of blow
up or go to zero as the width goes to
infinity, right? We want essentially our
our improvement in losses to remain
roughly the same order of magnitude no
matter how big our models get. That's a
stronger assumption than what we've had
before. But assuming that's true, then
essentially we can say, okay, the change
in the loss is kind of like multiplying
the gradient with the change in the
weights. This left side is O of one. We
know how big um this uh delta of L
should look like. So now or sorry we
know how big this delta wl looks like.
Now we can solve for the gradient size.
And once we have that we can plug that
in here. We know delta wl we know uh the
gradient of l. We know the size of h of
l from condition a1. And now we can
solve for the learning rate. And that's
exactly what you get at the bottom here.
Um and the you know if you work through
the the arithmetic the final result that
you get here is that the learning rate
for SGD is equal to the fan out over the
fan in right so so lots of steps
involved and lots of like substitution
and slightly sketchy bigo notation being
substituted into the equations here. Um
but once we do that we're going to end
up with a very simple formula. Um, note
that this is true for SGD. And those of
you that have kind of been paying
attention and like kind of staring at
this equation are probably, you know,
um, internally complaining. You're like,
you have you have misled us because, you
know, in a transformer, well, what
what's NL over NL minus one for like a
MLP that actually is like a a four,
right? Because you've got a factor of
four between DFF and and D model, right?
And so this thing doesn't really change.
It's just a constant in most models,
right? unless your aspect ratios are
like dramatically changing uh through
your network. Um the reason why MUP is
different from standard parameterization
is because this derivation is for SGD
where um the uh primizations look very
similar between MUP and SP. Um if you do
the exact same derivation for atom,
you're going to find that um actually
you're going to get slightly different
things, which is that it's going to be
one over the fan in rather than the fan
out over the fan
in. Okay, so here's the recap. I have
sort of dragged you through um hopefully
willingly um the derivation of the basic
what people call the spectral conditions
that define MUP. Um but now I will give
you the kind of one slide highle
takeaway of that result. Right? So um
you know when we want to do something
like mup if we following the guidelines
from before directly what we will end up
with is the following blue box. at
initialization, you know, you set
yourself to one over the square root of
fan in times a correction factor.
That's, you know, one if your fan is is
uh smaller than your fan out, but you
know, square root of the ratio
otherwise. And then this is a a simple
initialization uh for the scale of your
gausian. Um for your learning rate, if
you're doing SGD, then you set it to fan
out over fan in. Um but if you're doing
atom, that's going to be slightly
different. It's going to be one over the
fan in. Now um in case you already sort
of know the standard like kiming
initialization and so on off top of your
head you know you can mentally compare
what this looks like um to the standard
parameterization. So in a standard
parameterization if you're doing it
right um you should probably be already
setting your um gausian to initialize to
one over the square root of fann so
that's good that's already perfectly set
um but your learning rates are probably
being set globally to a constant this is
fine for sgv not so fine for atom where
the really big difference between sp um
and mu comes in.
So okay um that brings us right back to
kind of the serious GPT paper. Now we
have all the context we need to
understand all the operations they do.
Um if you look once again at the column
over here of muup um the embedding layer
is special. Um it doesn't really do
essentially like any scaling because
embeddings are one hot so their norms
don't scale linearly with the number of
of uh vocab elements. But ignoring that
basically you see that all the layers
get scaled down by one over the width.
you know that's the initialization rule
and then the learning rate rules are
scaled by one over the width as well
right so this is once again uh the
learning rate rule for atom right so if
you're using atom that's exactly the
right thing to do and that's also
exactly what they do in cerebr cerebrus
GPT so hopefully that's clear and
hopefully this gives you a sense of you
know both the interestingness of
manipulating per layer learning rates to
get more predictable scaling and also
maybe an appreciation of this idea of
trying to control activations and um
updates as a function of model width
right like you know I'll pause for a
moment there and just mention right
that's like a very successful idea from
physics right lots of physicists think
about ideas like reormalization as I
take limits of certain things I want
things to remain stable I want them to
not blow up or go to zero this is an
exact application of that idea that's
that's kind of an interesting um use of
that okay um any questions about I don't
know m up derivation or sus GPT or any
of the other things. Yes, there's no
assumption about any architecture,
right? So any transformer or any model?
Yeah. So so that is part of the
subtlety. The question was you know
what's the architecture assumptions? Um
well I mean technically there's a even
stronger assumption here. Oh why did I
go? There's an even stronger assumption
here which is that I'm assuming things
are a deep linear network, right? I'm
just multiplying matrices repeatedly.
You know this is the kind of silliest
network that you can have. Um, basically
there are arguments for why adding
nonlinearities are fine. There are
arguments for how you would take the
same arguments and apply them to the uh
attention layer. Um, there are arguments
for why much more complex things are
needed for a gated linear unit. So each
one of those architecture pieces needs a
careful analysis in order to have a you
know corresponding object. Um,
yes. How are these like ends determined?
Like it looks like they're indexed by
layer. Right. Right. Right. Right.
Right. So, so N subl is just the output
of a matrix multiply and N l minus one
is the input. So for example, if you
have a MLP, you're going to have a
matrix multiply that takes you from D
model dimension to four times D model
like the DFF dimension, right? So that
would give you a NL over NL minus one of
four for example. So all the different
matrix shapes are giving you the NL and
NL minus one. Oh,
the fan in and the fan out of a matrix.
Yeah.
Exactly. Yeah. Yeah. So, so the input
and output dimensions are determining
all these objects.
Okay. Excellent.
It's also just in and out of the Yeah,
fan in and the fan out are like the
input and output dimensions.
Yeah, I was using those terms
exchangeably, but I should have been a
little bit more uh uh clear. Oh, yes.
Since Deepseek only has a global
learning rate, does it mean that they
don't have order one updates?
So, so the question was like since DeepS
uses a global learning rate, does that
mean they don't have an order one
update? Um so, you know, all this
argument is asic, right? It's basically
saying as I scale my width out to
infinity, things will kind of be big or
small. And I mean if you if you look at
um the MUP plot for example, you do you
do kind of see this, right? You see that
the learning rates have to shift as the
model gets larger in order to compensate
for the fact that the updates are
getting bigger and bigger, right? Um
what's empirically, you know, been seen
is if you do nail the learning rate, you
don't need MUP, right? Like it's not
like MUP is necessary for you to train a
good model. It's really just an attempt
to try to keep this shift as small as
possible so you can use the same
learning rate, you know, throughout
scaling. Um, and if you go back to to
DeepSeek, you know, um, if you remember
the, uh, scaling law that I was, you
know, being a slight hater for, um,
you'll see that, you know, they they too
have learning rates that that go down as
a function of scale in order to try to
compensate for the fact that the bigger
models are going to have bigger updates,
right? And so you know to to respond
more directly to the question um yes in
the case of deepseek right as we scale
the model up you know our our activation
updates will get bigger so we have to
shrink the global learning rate or we
should shrink the global learning rate
to compensate for
that cool.
Okay nice questions.
Um okay so that was kind of the
conceptual somewhat mathematical
components of mu. Um, now I want to talk
about um the uh empirical aspects of
MUP. Um, and so I'm going to talk
through uh a preprint or I think this
one's being published at Colm um a large
scale exploration of of mute transfer.
Um, and I like this because it's got a
bunch of ablations and I think I'm a
sucker for ablations. So I'll present
any paper that has large scale ablations
um in the course. And so they do um
essentially with MUP as we've described
it. Um just look at the right hand side
which is the more relevant piece. you
know, they're scaling down the
variances. They're scaling down the
learning rates by the the width, the
global width of the models M. Um, and
they're primarily keeping the the depth
fixed, which is a little bit of an
unusual scaling regime because usually
you'd see scale depth and width
together, but they really want to do a
controlled experiment where they're only
looking at width variations, and they
want to see if MUP precisely nails um
scaling in this regime.
Um there's also a little bit of a of a
kind of weird subtlety that all of the
MUP papers seem to do which is that um
if you remember your 224N lecture you
know you remember that there's like a
scaling on the attention um activations
you scale you know you do your inner
product and then you scale it down by
one over the square root of D you know
and I told you kind of this was a magic
constant that was like the right thing
to do um you know mu and other papers um
use uh one overd scaling um instead of
one over square root d for various
arguments related to activation and
update size um stability. Um and so
that's another thing that I think was
worth pointing out because you might
sort of not initially think of that as
being something that's related um to
MUP. Okay. Um architecture is is mostly
similar to the standard you know
transformer stuff. Um, and as I already
mentioned before, they only consider
width scaling, right? So they take a
standard transformer trained auto
reggressively on, you know, pre-training
text and they want to basically make the
model wider and wider and wider on the
MLPS um, and sort of the the model
residual stream dimensions. They're
going to make that bigger and bigger and
bigger. And what they want is for the
optimum learning rate to remain the same
as they scale the width up. And if if it
remains stable, then that's the big
victory for MUP, right? So the game is
hopefully clear to everybody. um you
just want to scale with I want my
learning rate that's optimal to stay the
same. So um question number one is you
know does it work? Well um the answer is
yes. So we have different width 128 512
2048 we have different learning rates
across the columns. Um and you know the
sort of idealized strategy here is we
run a sweep of learning rates at the
small scale. I pick the smallest scale
um and I scale that up and hopefully
that base learning rate remains um
optimal um and yeah it seems like you
know learning rates transfer very
reliably um across model sizes if we're
doing this like you know somewhat
precise uh with
scaling and so then I think you start
asking questions of all right um very
similar to the to the previous question
that was just asked of like okay when
does mu break right so you can ask that
question in theory but you can also ask
that question in practice, right? So,
I'm just going to try all sorts of
modern variations to architectures that
people do and then I'm going to ask, you
know, does this hyperparameter transfer
thing continue to hold under these
variations or not? And, you know, the
the paper is quite nice because they
just go through a lot of different
stuff. They'll vary the activations,
they'll vary the batch sizes, the
initializations, the RMS norm gains. Uh
they'll even use like really exotic
optimizers like sort of sign gradient
style stuff. And then they'll also vary
the regularizers. So which one of these
prevents learning rate transfer? Um so
the first one you know which I think is
probably relevant if you were kind of
looking at that deep linear network and
saying oh no one just multiplies
matrices together there's like
nonlinearities in between right so does
m work when we change nonlinearities
around well um swigloo squared relu um
and the baseline um uh sort of mu
approach um of relu all have the same
minimal learning rate. So no changes at
all. Um you know we just see that for
example swigloo and squared relu just do
better uh than baseline muup.
Unsurprising sort of agrees with a lot
of what we've learned in the course
right
um we might vary the batch sizes because
we know that batch sizes are kind of
going to be um sensitive to scale like
we've seen mini CPM and we've seen
deepseek basically fit scaling loss to
batch sizes to try to get what the
optimum batch size was. Um you know once
again we see that uh you know as we
scale up batch sizes by four up or down
you know learning uh optimum learning
rates uh remain
stable. What about initializations right
um you know there are some
initializations that you know people
vary like for example um some people set
the query matrix to zero so that all the
different items get uniform attention
maybe that's more stable. Um some people
uh sort of the unmbedded layer at the
very top they'll scale differently based
on either you use standard
parameterization or mu maybe that
matters a lot um turns out neither of
those do you know the center column the
optimum learning rate remains optimal in
all of these cases
um you know what is it not robust to
well you know it's not going to work for
for every single case um for example uh
if you um add sort of learnable gains um
that turns out to break new Right? So
you need to remove the biases. Um but
you know if you if you remove them the
mu works if you add them back in um
don't necessarily work. Um similarly you
can try um sort of more exotic
optimizers. Lion is an optimizer um that
takes like the sign of the gradient
updates which to me feel a little bit
crazy but I think this was searched this
was found through like evolutionary
search or something like this uh to find
like the fastest optimizer. Um, if you
use this kind of a more crazy optimizer,
it really breaks down. Um, and I think
this is what you expect, right? New is
designed to adapt to a very particular
optimizer like atom W to control the
update sizes. So, you know, if you're
using a totally different optimizer, I
don't know why you'd expect the learning
rates to transfer. So, maybe expected
that this thing
fails. Um, and then sort of finally,
what is it, you know, also not robust?
Turns out if you really have much
stronger weight decay, um, MUP actually
starts to to fail. Um, and so this is
one of the few significant MUP failures
that are in there. A lot of the other
ones are kind of just like, oh, we maybe
expected that or that's not standard to
do. Um, you know, weight decay is
something that you actually do do. Okay,
so um, mu seems generally useful like if
you take standard parameterization like
kind of going back to the baseline,
right? You might ask like all right but
what if I just do you know standard
baseline stuff you know you can't use
the same learning rate your the same
learning rate results in you know
significantly worse losses at 2048 right
like your model just blows up gives you
basically you know degenerate losses you
would have been very sad scaling up at
the same learning rate you know and we
see also that the learning rate needs to
scale down predictably as a function um
of the width on the other hand you know
even if you scale up all the way to a
10b parameter model you know you see
that the base loss remains the same um
so they do one large scale experiment
and they see that the learning rate
remains sort of ideal at the 2 to the
negative6 level which is a kind of cool
validation right so they do the whole
study at a medium to small scale they do
one big sort of hero run and then uh the
learning rate remains um optimal so um
the empirical results on that look
somewhat promising um the fact that uh
meta used it for llama 4 is also quite
nice um but as far as I know it's not a
consensus that people use
mute okay um so putting it all together
um you know how do you scale in the
wild? Um I have never trained a you know
70B model at you know super tinchula
sizes and so we're going to have to rely
a lot on case studies and we saw several
examples of scaling um in the wild. We
saw people setting things like uh model
hyperparameters especially learning rate
and batch sizes um using scaling laws.
We saw you know people using things like
new P or assume stability to try to
avoid search over these spaces. Um, and
then also the use of things like
alternative learning schedules like WSD
can decrease the amount of compute that
you need in order to fit a lot of these
scaling loss. So, um, that's all I got.