Okay. So last time uh we started to
discuss some kind of the slightly kind
of different way in terms like making
the gen models uh inspired by the
longerman dynamics and also the way to
basically calculate this cord functions
and the basic idea here was that like
what if we basically assume that uh we
are basically having some kind of the
large scale the training data and just
like making our generation the process
is not really generation but just like
picking
one of the data point in the given the
training the data set. So that's kind of
really the possible way but the things
that we wanted to have in terms the
feature in our digit model is to make
some kind of the making some kind of no
images not just like picking one of
those kind of images. So here the
question is that how can you basically
uh generate some kind of the new data
points that are basically not identical
uh to the any of the specific the the
data points. So for that the basic idea
that we started to see last time uh is
to add some sort of the blurness into
the training data. So basically what we
can see is that let's say this like qxio
here is kind of the underlying the
distribution for the data points that we
have. So that's the kind of the
information that we don't know right we
only have the samples from the qx0. Uh
so it means that if we really want to
trackly sample the data points from the
qx0 that will be really just like just
picking one of the existing the the
training the data points. So that's not
we want to do because we want to make
some kind of the uh something the new
the data point.
So for that basically we are basically
adding some kind of the gausian noise in
terms like you know making some like
gausian smooth the version of the
distribution like this. So you can see
that the new distribution becomes like
something that is like applying some
sort of the gausian de convolution into
the some underlying the distribution
here the qx0. So we are basically define
some kind of the new data distribution
which becomes the qxt. So by adding some
kind of the gausian the noise into the
underlying uh the distribution we want
to basically sample from this and making
something that is closely one of the the
training the data points uh but still uh
it's kind of new. So that's basically
what we want to do.
So the question for now is that then how
we can sample from this kind of the new
uh the data distribution the QXT right.
So for that the basic idea was to uh
leverage the idea of the the long-term
bundy dynamics. Uh we chose basically uh
very uh the good idea in terms of that
we don't need to directly have the
information of the qxt. We just need to
have some the information of the score
function. So once we can compute the
score which is the gradient of the log
the probability and based on that we can
basically sample from that the
distribution by iterating this kind of
process right starting from the the
sample of the any of the prior
distribution and then basically moving
that point using this kind of the the
step uh using this core function here.
So this is already actually quite close
with like what we are doing in our the
uh in the DDPMD process right. So we are
going to we are basically seeing some
kind of dissimilarity between the DDPM
and this process.
Then this mean is that for the new data
distribution for the QXG
uh this distribution the only thing that
we need to know is basically this core
information right uh this gradient below
the probability. So then the question is
basically how we can compute uh the
score function for the gausian the
blurred the the distributions and for
that the the basic idea was that you
know we are going to train the score
prediction the network like this by
minimizing the L2 loss with the score
function here and it turns out to be
that if you derive all the things into
the new expected value here then we can
actually see that this score function uh
can be seen as kind of the expected
value over those things. Basically
sampling the XU and then then sampling
the XT based on that and then then
basically this expected value becomes
actually matching the uh the score
function for the conditional
distribution.
Uh so that's basically the the basic
idea in terms of that you know we are
going to train the score function in a
way that we can perform the lang
dynamics while this score function uh
score the predictor is trained to
basically match the score function for
the conditional distribution while
basically computing this expected value
then it becomes more feasible because
now for this conditional distribution
this is basically what we defined as the
Gaussian distribution
with the gausian distribution we know
how we can compute the score function
right it's just like simply just taking
the gradient of the log of the
probability so uh then now we can see
that you know training this like score
the predictor becomes visible because of
that know the derivation of the new the
expected value here
and then the only thing is that then how
much kind of the the noise that we need
to add right so as we basically have
some kind of add some sort of the small
the gausian the
into the underlying the the
distribution. The thing is that we're
going to get some basically very high
the the accuracy for these core values
near the in the some highly concentrated
region like this. But for some kind of
the regions which are basically quite
far from the existing uh some kind of
training the data points basically these
quality values in this region will be
very close to zero. Right? So which
means that even when you train our score
predictor the value will be basically
not that much kind of the accurate and
also since the score function will be
very close to zero there will be
basically almost like the zero the
moving force to getting closer into the
highly the concentrated region right so
that's kind of the problem so if you
start from the any of like those regions
here uh with some kind of the particles
here uh would not be really just moving
that much into the the regions basically
staying almost here. So that's basically
will uh you know involve some kind of
the loss of the iterations to getting
closer to the highly uh the concentrated
regions and also even this course that
we are basically predicting in these
regions would be not that kind of
accurate.
So the other option is that basically we
are increasing the the variance in terms
of basically adding some kind of the
bigger the gausian the noise into the
underlying the distribution. Then the uh
the good thing is that now we are not
basically having some kind of the uh
less regions like having almost the zero
discourse which means that we can
basically
making it easier to move the the
particles into some kind of the highly
the concentrated regions. The problem is
that now when you have some kind of the
bigger the gaus and the noise the
modified the distribution will debate
more from some kind of the underlying
distribution. So which means that what
we are using for this core function will
not be that also the accurate this core
function uh with respect to the kind of
the some kind of ground trross uh the
distribution here.
So that basically uh motivates us in
terms of uh basically you know
decreasing the variance over time. But
here the basic idea is that we are
starting from some kind of the high
variance in terms of like adding some
kind of the bigger the gaussian noise in
a way that from like wherever we start
in terms of the particles here we still
have some kind of the moving force in
terms like moving to the some highly the
uh some kind of saturated regions like
this and as we have some kind of the the
the particles that are basically getting
closer into the highly concept regions
like this then we are decreasing the
variance in terms of that now we get
some kind of the more accurate this
course in these regions in a way that uh
now we can get some kind of the more the
accurate samples in the highly the the
concentrate regions. So that's the basic
the motivation of like the the annual uh
the long the dynamics.
So which means that uh in terms of like
training our the uh this quality
predictor here
now we are basically varying the
variance of the the gaus and the noise.
uh so we are also going to basically
learn the score uh for each of the time
step t so the time step t we are going
to basically decrease the the variance
over the time so for each of the time
step we need to learn this core function
right uh so that's basically what we are
going to do and after like doing all the
things now this looks like the same the
thing we have seen uh for the ddpm case
right so this is actually exactly the
same thing with the the noise predictor
that we have seen in the DD DDPM case.
So now we can see that this is kind of
the same thing uh with the DDPM. So
actually this is like one uh possible
way to uh define a the diffusion model
and this can be also kind like one way
to interpret the diffusion processes uh
in the diffusion model. So we can see
that actually the reverse process of the
diffusion the model is basically
simulating this kind of the anal the
lang dynamics basically started from
some kind of the bigger the gausian
noise and then getting it the smaller in
terms of that we can basically make some
better samples with the more accurate uh
these quality values.
So that's the basic idea
and also if we see some kind of the
reverse process of the long dynamics
actually that turns out to be the same
with the B process in the diffusion
model right uh it's basically uh
gradually increasing the variance in
terms of that we are starting from the
uh this kind of the the distribution
which is close to the our underlying the
data distribution and basically
gradually adding some kind of the bigger
the gausian noise in terms of that from
you know wherever start with the
particles we can basically move the the
particles getting close to the highly uh
the constructed regions.
So that's a thing. So you can see that
actually this is kind of the like one
way to basically interpret uh each of
the diffusion models and also showing
many things uh with the DDPM that we
discussed last time but actually it's
not exactly the same with the DDPM
actually one small kind of the
difference with the DDPM case is that
the DDPM we defined uh the fourth the
the uh the distribution in this way
right so there's basically some kind of
scaling term here.
While in this specific case with the
annual the lambda dynamics what we have
seen in terms like adding the noise was
that we defined the for this this was
basically the some kind of gaus and the
uh the convolution kind of distribution
right in this case like we defined the
four process like this. So these two are
not exactly the same. So you can see
that like each of these is kind of like
one specific way that we are defining
the future models. Uh while these are
basically not exactly the same but you
can see that they are basically sharing
lots of the the ideas in terms of like
how we can uh you know design some kind
of the generation the generative process
you know kind of the iterative manner.
Any questions on this
model? How do we sample from the prior?
How do we sample from the prior? I mean
it's the matter of like how we define
the the prior distribution. So we can
actually set any priority distribution.
So typically we going to also start with
the standard gausian distribution but it
does not need to be standard gausian
distribution in this case
it doesn't standard. Oh
well yeah but in this case uh the
difference with the DDPM is that no uh
it does not need to be so when we
increase the variance to be very big it
does not need to be like matching the
qxt to be exactly the same with the
gausian the standard gausian
distribution so actually we going to uh
even you know uh we're going to start
from the any other the prior
distribution and then perform the long
dynamics to getting closer into that the
Gausian blur the distribution the thing
is that this would be something that is
kind of like deviated from the original
distribution right so that's why we
obviously gradually decreasing the
variance uh yeah
any other questions
one
question you might have is that so how
many times steps that we need to have
right so both for the DDPM and also this
case we are basically somehow have the
notion of the the time right starting
from the prior distribution and
gradually performing the reverse process
to getting into the uh one of the the
realistic the data point uh which means
that in all the implementation basically
we will need to have some kind of the
discrete the time steps right starting
from the capital t and all the way to
going to the the zero right uh But as
you can see here actually the time does
not need to be uh discretized. This the
whole idea actually can be defined in
the continuous the time step right
continuous time domain.
So actually so that's not something that
we are going to discuss for today. uh
but what we are going to uh discuss in
the
week after next week uh is more actually
some kind of the deeper idea in terms
like what happens if we define all this
kind of the process in the continuously
time domain but like it turns out to be
that you know if we see this kind of the
anal the long dynamics process with the
continuously time domain you can see
that this is actually the process that
we are basically performing some kind of
degeneration based on this like stoastic
differential equation. So basically this
is the stoast the differential equation
in terms of that we are having this term
while basically injecting some kind of
stoasticity here uh and also so as we
define the fold process in the ddpm and
also in this like score based models in
the continuous time the domain we can
first define the fold the process using
the sd like this and the interest thing
that we're going to also see next time
is basically that once we basically
define the uh the SD for the full
process like this then actually we can
find the corresponding the SD for the
reverse process as well and the uh the
closed form for the uh SD for the
reverse process is defined in this way.
You can see that everything is kind in
terms like the terms and we are
basically having this term which is
still the same the the score function
right. So when you discuss the diffusion
models in the continuous time domains uh
we're going to get back to seeing some
kind of score the functions here and see
how this like score function uh play
some kind of role in the the generation
the process and we can see that like all
those kind of DDPM and also the score
models are some kind of the some
specific cases that we are basically
performing all the process with the time
domain the discretization.
So that's the the high level the idea uh
that something getting deeper uh into
the diffusion models but we are not
going to discuss this for today.
So
before we get into the content time
domain uh this is the today's main topic
uh that we are going to discuss.
So uh if we get back to some kind of the
comparisons uh for the the generate
models. So we have seen this kind of the
three the main some kind of the some
properties that we want to basically
satisfy with our the the generative
model right. Uh so what we have seen is
that for the GAN GA gen is good in terms
of making some high quality samples and
also making the the generation the
process to be fast. Uh the problem is
that it typically have some kind of mode
collapse issue in terms of like losing
some kind of the diversity right. uh for
the BAE the problem was that especially
the fastests and also making some kind
of diversity outputs uh but in terms of
the quality but the quality is not good
right that was the problem. So that is
like why we started discuss the
diffusion model which is good in terms
of like making high quality samples with
some kind of the the diversity. the
problem was in the uh the speed right
uh so if you implement uh the things in
the assignment one uh you're going to
see that actually as you have some kind
of the more the time steps as you
basically increase the number of the
time steps there you're going to get
some kind of the better quality the
outputs uh typically for the DDPM you
might need some like more or less like
1,000 time steps which mean like 1,000
iterations right uh which sounds like
quite the iterations.
So actually the research of the division
on the models uh recent researchers for
the uh know previous like two or the
three years were all about basically how
we are going to basically accelerate
this kind of degeneration the process.
Uh so actually over the the entire this
this semester you're going to see that
we are now basically making some kind of
model that needs to be performed like
the 1,000 steps. uh we are going to see
how this can be reduced into the 50 time
steps and next time you're going to see
how we can also even more like reduce
this into the 10 step the five step
three to one step. So basically this is
like all about like how we going to
accelerate kind of the uh the generation
the process uh while preserving the
quality uh of the the outputs. So that's
kind of the big question.
So as kind of the first step uh in terms
of basically uh making it like the
faster of the diffusion models uh we're
going to basically uh discuss this idea
which is the DDIM
and here the key idea is that last time
we basically defined both the food and
the reverse processes as kind of the
marovian process. uh which means that
when you sample the XT uh conditioned by
the uh the XT minus one and also any of
the some kind of the previous states uh
all these kind of the previous states
can be ignored because we are assuming
that XT is only depends on the the the
one right before basically XT minus one.
Uh so that is basically the our basic
assumption uh in terms of defining the F
and the reverse depresses right. So
that's kind of like basic thing. Good.
Uh
and here the question is that can you
also basically make some kind of
non-marovian the uh the process
uh the for that uh what we are going to
see is that for the fold the transition
the distribution
uh what we did last time for the DDM is
that we first defined this right
uh we first defined the fold the
transition distribution how we can
sample the XT conditioned by the XT
minus one and we defined this as kind of
the Gaussian D distribution and based on
that we could derive the other things
this distribution like I would call this
before the jump distribution sampling
the XT directly from X0 this was another
the Gaussian distribution right and also
this one as well so this was the
distribution that we need to match with
our reversed process sampling the XT
minus one conditioned by the both the XT
and the X0 so this was kind of the basic
thing But basically here the main
question is that
if we get back to the alable function.
So this is like something that we wanted
to maximize here. Uh is that uh what we
need to do is that we need to basically
have the uh the probability distribution
for the all the latent the variables
conditioned by the x0.
Uh so basically this is all about
basically know what would be the
likelihood for each of the latent
variable conditioned by the realistic
the data point here right so once we
basically if you find this if you
decompose this into the multiple the the
terms here then what we need to have was
basically actually these two we could
see that know this was basically all the
de composing into that we just need to
have these two distributions.
So actually this looks like uh the only
information that we needed uh was
actually not the fourth detrion
distribution but actually these two.
So that basically gives some kind of the
motivation in terms of that uh what if
we do not define the for the transition
distribution but actually directly
define these two uh in a way that this
uh all the uh default distribution can
be defined based on these two.
So that's kind of the main idea.
So here basically we defined uh
basically this first and derived these
two based on this. But actually if the
only information that we need is the
only these two uh the distribution then
would there be some kind of the other
way around in terms of that we directly
define these two and do not define this
uh in terms of basically that we are
modeling all this kind of uh the
distribution basically this one
then this would be basically some more
the generality idea in terms of that. So
this is really the idea in terms of how
we are going to generalize the DDPM uh
in terms like define the for process in
a different way. Uh so that's kind of
the main thing.
So what we are going to say is that now
we are not going to define this uh sorry
so we are going to basically define this
like the board the the distribution
sampling any latent variable from the x0
by only defining these two without
defining this like the transition
distribution.
So this would become like this. So for
any of the intermediate the latent
variable so if we want it to XT
previously in the DDPM what we need to
do was basically sampling it right from
the X0 you go to the X1 X2 X3 and all
the way to the XT right so that's
basically what we need to do last time
but instead of like doing this now what
we are going to do is that these two
were basically something that we needed
right and based on that if we want some
sample the XT
What we are going to do is that actually
we are going to jump all the way from
the x0 to the x capital t here and then
going backward. So basically if you have
the x0 and the x capital t based on this
you can sample x capital t minus one
right x capital t minus 2 all the way to
the xt. So that's kind of the another
way. So when we basically define this
and this then if we want to sample the
XT then instead like just going the
forward way actually we can first
directly jump from the X0 to the X
capital T and just going the backward.
So actually that's kind of the another
way that we can actually define the fold
process uh define the full process like
the reverse process right so that's kind
of the idea so this is kind of the idea
in terms of making our default process
as kind of the non-marovian the process
because now sampling of the xt minus one
depends on the both the uh even the xt
and also the x0 which is like the the
the first kind of the uh the the data
So uh so in terms of that we only want
to define these two uh now we are going
to basically switch out the forward
process like this from the x0 we first
sample the x capital t and going the
backward in terms of going to the the xt
uh so that's basically some kind of
changes that we are making
then the question is that how should we
define these two distribution
obvious Obviously there can be like lots
of the ways uh to defining these two uh
but today uh we are going to see some
very specific the idea in terms of like
know still we are directly defining
these two while basically making these
two be the same.
Uh so this was basically some kind of
the the default the jump distribution
right the uh sampling the xt directly
from the x0 right so we have seen how we
can derive this from the previous
default the transition distribution in
the ddpm case
so given the xt condition by xt minus
one we could derive this right but now
we are going to define these two in a
way to basically making these to be the
uh with the DDP case and this was
basically the the BD distribution that
we have seen last time.
So actually you you will see basically
how we can basically define these two
you you will need to do yourself how can
you define these two in a way to
basically match these to be the same.
Then before we get into like how exactly
we need to define these two the question
might be is that so what's the point? So
why do we need to make this to be this
to be the same right? You you can see
that this is like one of the the
specificity cases uh of the latent
variable right uh in the case basically
we are basically define this uh so for
all the t for the all the time t we
wanted to basically model this right and
based on that we are basically define
the elbow function. So this means that
if we basically match uh this uh
distribution
this means that our elible function will
be the same as well.
So that's the actually the most
important part. So when we define these
two distributions uh while basically
preserving this to be the same uh what
we can achieve is that we are making the
elbow function to be the same uh with
the DDPM case up to this killing factor
right
can you see the meaning of like this
what's the meaning of that we are making
the elbow function to be the
Yes. So the meaning of this is that once
you train the DDP model with the same
elbow function you can change the
generation the process
that's actually quite interesting the
point
uh have you seen such kind of the neuron
net that you paint like one like
specific way and use the model in
different ways
is there such kind of a case I think
there is no such kind of case right but
once you train is some kind of classific
ification in network can you use the
network for the other kind of things.
So this is kind of the interesting point
in terms of that while you basically uh
train a specific model using the the the
objective function in the generation the
process uh you can run either the
marovian process or you can also run the
non-marovian process to do the same the
generation
uh and we're going to see what's the
effect of that actually that uh changes
uh the performance of the the uh
the generated the model. So that's
actually very interesting point. Uh we
going to actually know keep seeing this
idea multiple times in terms of that
once you pre-train a model we only
change the inference the process the
generation the process uh in terms of
basically improving the performance.
So that's actually quite interesting the
idea. Have you seen such kind of the
case like you train the classification
network and do something at the
inference time and just improve the
performance? Uh you can do this with the
diffusion models without having using
any other information or any other kind
of neural network or any other kind of
some priority information only by just
changing the generation process.
So that's the kind of the key thing and
this is kind of a start to see that we
are making some kind of the changes uh
in the generation the process in terms
of like accelerating uh the generation
uh and then we going to actually see
many other the cases like reducing the
time step from the 1,000 to the 50 for
now and this to the 10 5 3 2 1 uh so
that's be kind of the case.
Okay, so this is kind of our main task
for today. Uh which means that there
will be some case here. Uh so what we
want to do is that we basically want to
define these two distribution in a way
to basically match this right for all
time step t. So this was basically the
old distribution that we have seen the
DDPM case for the old time step t we
want to basically match this by defining
these two right. So it basically means
that for the capital T here that this is
like what we are defining here right for
the capital T here this should be
obviously the same with this right by
setting the capital T in the time step
right so it's very obvious right so for
this we know how we need to define this
right the problem is like this one right
how should we define this
so um so as we already have some kind of
some past experience in terms define
those things. uh you can now feel like
you know basically
we we don't know exactly but somehow
this should be something like the
gausian distribution right that's that's
what we have seen all the way from the
lectures like all the kind of things
that we are defining in default the the
process was just the gaussian
distribution so we can feel like it
should be something like the gausian
distribution
and for many of the cases that we have
seen actually this like mean function
was also defined as some kind of linear
function of those are kind of the
conditions right uh so while we don't
have the clear idea for now uh let's see
that actually let's assume that this
should be some kind of the gausian
distribution with some kind of the
linear function combinating uh these two
the conditions
uh and then the problem would be
basically finding these two so what
should be basically this like w and the
wt
and this is actually what you will need
to do uh actually this is quite doable
and also very simple So we're going to
basically consider some kind of
induction.
We are starting from the capital t here.
We already defined uh this conditional
distribution with the capital t to be
the same uh with the the the
distribution right starting from the
capital t and we're going to do some
kind of induction by decreasing the the
time step.
So let's assume that the time step t we
already basically defined the other
distributions in a way that this to be
the same with this. So we'd do like to
define the some the other distributions
in a way that basically defining this
like w and the wt in a way that now for
the t minus one also this basically
holds
that's basically what we want to do
right so which means that so let's see
how can he drive this distribution from
the qxt and the x0 of this and also the
other distribution that we are going to
define.
So given these two
this is like what we are going to define
right and let's say like we already uh
have this uh distribution from these two
just simply by just taking uh this the
product like so for this this is quite
obvious right so if you uh ignore the x0
here x ignore the x0 for now uh then you
can see that this multiplication like
these two becomes the the joint
distribution
and taking the integral become just like
simply the marginalization.
So from the simple kind of the uh some
the math we can say that this should
hold. So which means that from these two
the uh the distribution now we can
compute the xt minus one conditioned by
the x0 right this is obvious
and also one more thing that we actually
have seen last time uh was this uh
without proof because there some details
here but when you basically have some
kind of the prior distribution and the
likelihood distribution that are both of
them are defined as kind of the gaussian
distribution like this uh we have seen
that actually the marginal distribution
also becomes like something like this
another region distribution.
So based on these facts now we can
derive the W and the WT there. So once
again when you consider this as kind of
the prior and the likelihood the
distribution when these two are
basically the gausian distribution by
taking the condition the mean as the sub
linear function of the the conditions we
can derive the marginal distribution as
another the gausian distribution right
so so then the question is that we know
uh the prior and the marginal here now
we want to define find the likelihood
especially while assuming that this mean
function is the linear combination like
these two in a way to basically simply
finding those the coefficients
make sense.
So let's try this. Um
so the first thing that you need to do
would be is that so what will be the
mean and the variance of this
conditional distribution with respect to
the w and the wt
and based on that uh can you also derive
the the w and the wt.
So this is the quiz. Um
so
uh so yeah if you solve those things uh
I think you should have this right uh
for the xt minus one condition by the x0
you the mean and the variance should be
computed like this. So based on that you
basically compute der the wg and the wt
uh then you'll see that the wt and the
wg are derived in this form. Is this
something that you got? Yeah.
uh looks quite dirty, right? But uh
basically what this basically shows that
now we can have some kind of the uh the
some kind of closed form into also the
the gausian and the distribution uh
defining this distribution xt minus one
conditioned by the both the xt and the
x0 in a way that we can basically match
the fold distribution to be the same uh
with the ddpm
Why do we need to consider?
>> So, what was the question?
>> Why?
>> Why we didn't consider some
>> We have to serve.
>> Oh, you you mean some some kind of be
some bias term here, right? Yeah,
actually my original version of this
slides is basically having the bias term
there. Uh after all theation you can
you're going to see that the bio term
become zero. Uh but yeah
so I just basically simplify this
question you can uh easily see like what
we get. But typically when we have this
kind of the linear function without the
kind of some the some bias term uh we
can see this kind of some kind of
composition of the gausian that becomes
another gausian.
So yeah so I just like make this kind of
the question simple in a way that I just
already gave you this form uh the this
distriution should be in this form. So
let's finding these coefficients but
that actually involves some kind of
intuition like in terms like you know
what this would look like when you
define the have the default the
distribution that way.
So based on this, so this is basically
the uh the distribution that we are
defining and also this was the uh the
distribution that we need to match uh
with the our learned uh the reverse the
transition the distribution right here.
The thing is that now we don't need to
specify this uh so for any arbitrary
barriers here. So actually this is
really the key point. Whatever the
variance that you have here uh for any
of the the varian here whatever you have
uh this definition like the distribution
uh will match the uh the distribution of
the DDPM.
So which means that there is like not
just like only one way to make the
another the non-microbial the the
process uh depending on like what we
choose here even we can basically make
some kind of some variations of the
non-marovian the process.
So we are basically seeing that uh some
kind of like very different ways to
define the for process and also that
will change the reverse process right
the thing is that even when you make
some like all the changes for the
forward and reverse the processes these
are all the cases where the elbow
function becomes the same which means
that even when you change our default
and reverse the processes all the
objective function become the same. So
for the same model that we trained with
the same objective function we just need
to we can just change the reverse the
process. Uh so that's the really the key
idea in the diffusion models.
So again in the DDP case we defined this
B transition distribution into the
specific the Gaussian form in a way that
we can derive like these two the
distributions right now in the DDIM we
are directly defining these two
distributions.
Then what will be the fourth the
transition distribution in this case?
I mean depending on so what would be
exactly this uh so depending on how we
define these two actually even it not
would not be possible to derive some
closed form of like this.
So in terms of that we are seeing some
kind of more easy generalization right.
uh so we are now defying these two uh
even these two may not give some kind of
any closed form for the for the
transition the the distribution but it
doesn't matter right because like based
on these two we can still define the
full default process and based on that
we can also define the reverse process
so that's kind of the key idea
but since the the elbow function will uh
remain unchanged up to the the scaling
def factor uh while basically uh Uh
yeah, which means that the our reverse
uh the transition the distribution will
be basically still be defined in a way
to basically match this distribution
and we already defined this right uh
with some kind of arbitrary variance.
Uh so yeah so that's the thing we don't
need to retrain the noise predictor
based on the pre-trained the noise
predictor. Now we can think about how we
going to really perform the reverse
process uh in the DDIM uh the the wave.
Uh so since this is still the same like
basically the reverse transition should
still the match the uh this one with
some kind of the estimate of the x0 from
the xt whatever we have the mean
predictor or the clean sample the
predictor or the the epsilon the noise
predictor what we just need to do is
that with the any of the predictor given
the xt we just get the compute the
estimate of the x0 and based on that we
basically sample based on the
distribution that we have seen for is
the conditional the case. So that
becomes the reverse process of the DDI
MD case.
So again in the DD case uh so this is
actually what we have seen as kind of
the quiz in the previous lecture. So
given the noise predictor here
prediction we get some kind of the
prediction of the X0 given the XT right.
So based on the prediction of the x0
what we can do is that now we can
compute this whole the mean function
here looks complicated but we can still
compute right and based on this that
means that we have some kind of the uh
we know the reverse the transition the
distribution that should be the same
with this we sample from this and then
getting the xt and repeat this
uh so we are making some some small
changes in this part right uh slightly
changing the reverse the transition the
distribution in the DDID case. So like
in terms of the formulation this might
look complicated but in terms of the
implementation actually you're going to
see that this is literally like just
like couple of the lines of the changes
in the PyTorch in the from the DDPM to
the DDIM and the very magical thing is
that when you just like change a couple
of the lines in the PyTorch with the new
the reverse the process you're going to
see some kind of a difference in the
performance actually very big
difference. So that's actually very
magical thing
and here the question is that we now
have the option to choose the variance
here right whatever the variance that we
can choose
uh let me ask this question first so
what be kind of the maximum value uh
here
can you really choose any variance
obviously this car the the term here
this should be the zero or greater than
zero right uh but can you Choose any
value here. Would there be some kind of
the upper bound maximum value?
>> Sorry.
>> This Yeah. Oh, that's the right answer
actually. Yeah. Thank you for the
answer. Uh so this is the hint, right?
Uh what you can see is that we have the
like square root term here, right? We
the variance which means that this is
giving the the sense of the the upper
bound. Uh so basically the variance the
t this should be uh great same or
smaller than this right. Uh we are
saying the upper mount was the lower
bound we can set zero right.
What happens if we set zero in this
case?
So then actually as we have seen in the
previous slide we are basically sampling
the xt minus one iteratively from this
distribution.
But if the variance becomes zero then we
always take this mean as the xt minus
one.
Actually this this is like very
interesting case because like what we
have discussed uh over the entire the
the previous lectures where all these
stoastic process we are basically doing
some sampling right uh we are sampling
the xt minus one from the some specific
distribution which means that every time
we are injecting some kind of the noise.
So the sampling was basically like this
right we are having some gausian the
noise here and then basically adding
like this right. So actually all the
process that we have seen was basically
injecting some kind of the some noise
having some kind of stop
which means that even when you start
from the X capital T from the same X
capital T at the end of the all the way
to the generation the process you might
get into the very different kind of the
points because every time you're adding
some kind of the random noise
but when you make these like variance to
be zero then the whole process becomes
deterministic.
So starting from some kind of some
stoastic process now actually we are
discussing deterministic process which
means that if you start from the same x
capital t every time you're going to get
into the same x0 because like it's just
iteration like this computation
make sense. So this is actually very
interesting point in terms of that uh we
can find uh some kind of the reverse
process uh which is basically giving
some kind of same uh the marginal
distribution basically that the output
will be still the the point from the
same distribution but the reverse the
process become the generation the
process becomes deterministic by setting
this to be zero.
So they can have some kind of lots of
advantages, right? If you want to
reproduce some kind of outputs you make
some kind of images using some kind of
stable diffusion whatever and someone
ask you to basically reproduce this
images can you just make this image
again? Uh no actually because like we
already have like lots of some kind of
random noise. So I don't know even how I
can bally make this image again right
with the DDIM you can do that if you
just like remember the X capital T that
you started from based on that if you
start always from the same point you're
going to always get this kind of the
same the outputs uh making the
generation process to be deterministic
and also you can uh the thing is that
DDPM is actually the special case of the
DDIM so I'm going to make this as kind
of the homework uh but what you can see
is that if you set the various system to
be like this into quite a not
complicated by this form then what you
can see is that actually when you set
the variance to be like this then this
becomes exactly the same with the DDPMD
case. So one of the some very specific
case of the DDIM actually become some
kind of the marco process. So you can
see that really this like DDIM is kind
of like doing some kind of a
generalization of the DDPM in a way that
we can either increase the variance or
basically decrease the variance in a way
that we can even make it like
deterministic
some kind of degenerate ideas. So check
out like whether you know or this varian
will really make the DDM to be the same
with the DDP. So this is kind of
homework
and so yeah so typically we parameterize
the various like this in a way that uh
zero means the determinist the process
and the one means the DDPM and you can
increase this more up to that the upper
bound right uh depending on which varity
you're going to set you're going to get
some kind of different results right
so why do we care about basically this
like DDI in the case so what's the
meaning of that kind of the having that
diver there uh So it's not possible to
explain the meaning of the difference
like everything in this like single
lecture. So we're going to continue this
discussion in the actually week after
next week especially when we go into the
continuous time case uh it'll be clearer
like the meaning of like having that the
zero dearian but for now we're going to
just see some more the empirical the
results like what do you get so we are
talking about the kind of the slow speed
of the deep models right so how we going
to basically reduce the the time step
while basically maintaining kind of
quality of the outputs
so we can consider basically somehow
like skipping some of the time steps. So
the the main thing here is that even
when you basically somehow train the uh
the DDPMD model by setting some kind of
the discrete time step from the one to
the capital T. uh we can consider
basically in the reverse the process we
can consider skipping some of the time
steps making having some uniform
interval not sampling from the capital t
to the uh t minus one uh but sampling
like some kind of the bunch of kind of
steps right so even for this kind of the
some uh skipping kind of the process
actually the objective function is not
being changed so that's alo kind of
thing but typically uh when you
basically reduce the number of the time
steps then the quality of the output
also gets basically worse but uh without
any kind of theoretical things for now
we're going to get into that later. The
thing is that when you make our
degeneration to the process to be more
the deterministic the thing is that even
when you decrease the number of the time
steps the quality degradation is not
that uh big much as kind of the some
stoastic process.
So let me show some kind of the
experimental the results.
So this like the image generation the
case is something that we'll need to do
for the image generation the challenge.
Uh here basically we use some kind of
the evaluation metric which is called
the app ID here. Uh so maybe we're going
to have some chance to discuss like what
this means is the fret insertion
distance. Basically you can see that
this is kind of some sort of the
distance between the distribution of the
output the samples and the distribution
of the some uh the ground trust the
training the data. So lower is basically
to be better and what this table
basically shows is that uh what sort of
the output that we get when you vary the
stocket in the DDI in the case and also
when you vary the number of the time
steps. So when this number is basically
the one that's the case that we are
making the DDPM right the same the DDPM
when you make this to be zero that's the
the deterministic DDI in the case and we
can also make this to be the much
greater right and typically for the DDPM
as I said like we use the 1,000 of the
time steps and for the case like for the
DDPM here uh here this is the last one
right so this is the DDPM the case so
when the time step is like 1,000 the FID
is like a 4.07 quite a very quite low
number as you decrease this like number
of the time steps all the way to the 10
here and you can see that the FID
increases like 10 times more like 41.07
07.
But if you see the determin the
deterministic case here for all the
cases basically the quality is much
better uh basically the better than the
DP DPMD case and especially if when you
decrease the time step all the way to
the 10 here uh the quality degradation
is not very big compared to this case.
So this was basically the 10 times more
kind of the increase of the FID while
this is like three times kind of the
increase in uh the the FID right which
basically shows that even when you
basically reduce the time step in the
determin case now we can achieve some
kind of the good results you can compare
this and this here in the DDPM you
needed to basically run the 1,00 time
step to achieve the PI of the 4.7 7.
Now for the DDI in the deterministic
case only with the 50 time step you
cannot already get the 4.6.
Okay. So this mean is that uh what we
need to do in terms of like accelerating
the generation the process is not to
train your model again uh with some kind
of new idea just use the pre-trained
model but just change your reverse
process into the DDI the deterministic
process and just like reduce the time
step
and then you can get some kind of the
almost the same quality uh and also the
diversity uh while basically reducing
you know speeding up uh the computation.
So that's quite magical things right uh
to accelerate the generation the process
actually you didn't need to even retrain
your the model you just need to
basically change the generation the
process
so that's kind of the idea uh so this is
actually the key things that we're going
to keep seeing uh in this class so from
the 1,000 to the time step of the 10 uh
without doing any kind of finetuning
whatever kind of things by simply
changing the generation the process uh
we can still match the same quality
while speeding up into the all the way
to the time step 10. uh if you want to
reduce further the time steps then now
you need to have some kind of the
finetuning so that's also the idea that
we are also going to discuss uh so if
you see some kind of this open source
model for the image generation
especially uh then you're going to see
that there are some kind of the options
so I guess in the first class we also
have seen the flux the case right for
the flux there's also kind of the model
with some kind of the more the time step
and also the single the time step which
is like way faster for the single time
step the case is the case that they
somehow fine-tuned in terms like doing
some kind of exploration.
So basically this means that uh if you
uh develop some kind of the new method
that you don't even need to do some kind
of like second stage the training with
the single stage training if you can
make the whatever diffusion flow models
in a way that they can run with the
single step while achieving the same
quality
that will be really big thing that's
kind of the unsolved problem. uh if you
can really make some such kind of the
model that is like running with the one
step with the same the performance uh I
guess you're gonna make some really big
money
that's really unsolved the problem but
now the state-of-the-art is that like
reducing from the 1,00 to the 10 and
furthermore if you go all the way to the
single step then you need to do some
kind of fine tuning uh so that's kind of
the idea that we're going to discuss
question
same for the
other
generation.
>> Yeah,
>> for the other data domain you can use
DDM. Actually using the DDIM is quite
standard for now for all the cases not
only for the images for all the other
DDR domains. uh you can really use the
VDID ideas for the all the diffusion
models not only for the image generation
and now it's not very intuitive like why
we are basically having some kind of the
better quality uh with some kind of
deterministic process to better
understand that actually we you'll need
to you get into this point in terms like
uh how we can interpret like all these
process in the continuous time D domain
uh so after we start to discuss like all
the things in the contest time domain
actually what we are going to see is
that ddim is kind of the case like we
are finding some corresponding ordinary
differential equation from the stoastic
differential equation so it's really
just like removing some stoastistic
parts in the differential equation in
order to solving the od not the SD so
we're going to basically get into this
point so what's the difference between
these two any question on this
so yeah this was kind of the basic idea
for the DDM. Uh so we discussed some
kind of the some basic theories for the
diffusion models until this point. Next
week uh we're going to get into slightly
more the practical the ideas. So what we
really need to have in terms of the
implementation to make some like
immediate like models and how we can
also use some kind of the some
pre-trained uh immediate degenerate
models for some more some practical
applications. So we're going to have
those kind of the ideas uh the next
week. Okay, I will see you next Monday.