So uh until last week basically what we
have discussed is basically some kind of
the some actually some basic ideas in
terms of like how we can basically train
a either diffusion model or the flow
model and also how we can perform the
generation the process and from this
week for the until the next week what we
are going to do is that uh what we can
do more uh with some kind of the
pre-trained models. So as you would
already know actually there are some
kind of the many some pre-trained uh the
diffusion models especially for the
image video generation also the video
generation and we are also seeing some
kind of the many other diffusion the
flow models not only for the images and
the videos for the many other things
like for the molecules versus I don't
know for the motions or some kind of the
robotic the robotics the applications
for the many other things and these
models are typically uh trained with
some tones of the data
So we don't have some kind of the
computing resources that we can really
train those kind of models with the
tones of the images for the videos for
example right uh but here the question
is that with this kind of the
pre-trained models uh what can you do
more can you just like get some kind of
like typical images or can you some like
many other things uh so that's basically
the topics that we are going to discuss
for this week and the next week
and this is basically the slide we have
seen multiple times
Uh so basically the advantage for the
diffusion model were that it's basically
achieve some kind of the better quality
without basically losing the the the
diversity right
uh but the kind of the things uh some
kind of a downside with diffusion model
was basically the slow speed because of
that kind of iterating the process and
what we have discussed so far was
basically how we can accelerate this
kind of the degenerative process uh
through some kind of the inference time
the techniques which is basically
changing the some formulations uh in the
uh generation the process in a way that
we can achieve some kind of the good
results even with some kind of build the
iterations right and we also briefly
discuss some kind of the techniques that
we can also accelerate the generation
the process through some kind of the
fine tuning right so those are some kind
of the all the attempts in terms of like
how we can basically uh run the the
generation the process the faster uh
with the few number of the steps apps
but actually what we are going to
discuss for today is that uh this kind
of the iterative process actually can be
useful in terms of like injecting some
kind of the guidance. So what we have
seen in the previous lecture is that the
generation the process of the diffusion
the flow model is all about making some
kind of the trajectory right starting
from the if we go back to the diffusion
context uh starting from the capital T
and all the way going down to the zero
right in the diffusion context right uh
then it's basically really making some
kind of a trajectory starting from the
standard Gaus and the sample X capital D
and then just like uh making the path in
the space in a way that we are reaching
to the x0 right
uh so it's all about basically making
this kind of a pass but here basically
what we are going to do is that we are
every time when you basically make this
kind of the some pass we are basically
pushing those kind of points in a way
that the trajectory becomes something
that is reaching to the the final point
which is something that we really want
to see
actually we already have seen such kind
of the uh the case as an example. Do you
remember what this was some kind of the
case is that we are injecting some kind
of the guidance in the generation
process?
No idea.
Yeah, the classifier guidance and the
classifier pre guidance uh actually was
the case that we are basically injecting
some kind of the the guidance. Basically
what we are doing is that it's all about
basically computing the predict the
score and basically performing the
reverse process based on the score
information
and what we have seen last time for the
classify the guidance is that uh given
the condition now we want to compute the
uh score for the joint probability here
right and the score for the joint
probability it could be decomposed into
the margin of the score here and also
the likelihood score here. So it just
the matter like basically how we can
compute the likelihood score here in
some of that we are basically injecting
some kind of the some offset uh to some
kind of the uh each of these core
function here and the idea for the
classifier the guidance was to basically
uh was to train a kind of the classifier
in terms of that we can compute uh this
uh more explicitly by just training
another kind of the additional the uh
the neural network
and the idea for the question of
priority pre guidance was to basically
train a single network that can learn
both the unconditional noise and also
the conditional noise as well which are
corresponding to the uh the marginal
discore here and also the likelihood the
score here. Uh so and we could also even
control the strength of the conditional
noise in terms like how much we are
going to push the kind of the u the
intermediate the data point over the the
the trajectory in a way that we can
control those kind of the the passes. So
that is kind of the basic idea that we
discussed last time.
But the thing is that these are all the
cases that we need to basically train
the kind of the additional neuron net or
basically we are training the the noise
predictor with the pairs of the output
that we want to see and also the noise
here. So we need to basically have some
kind of the training data uh in terms of
the training the logic the predictor
and what we are going to discuss for
today is that uh how we can do this kind
of the uh some the injection of the
guidance uh with some kind of the
pre-trained the models uh without
basically the training uh those kind of
models from scratch with some kind of
the condition the information. So how we
can do some kind of the test time kind
of things uh in terms of basically
adding some kind of the guidance.
So more formally uh we are going to try
this which is guiding our regenerative
process at the inference time uh to make
some kind of the realistic data point uh
which is basically something that we
want to see uh which is aligned with
some kind of the some uh specific the
usual preference. So how we are going to
do that at the test time is kind of the
the basic idea.
And actually diffusion and the flow
model is really kind of the framework
for doing those kind of thing. So as I
said uh for the GAN and the BAE these
are basically all the onestep the model
right for those kind of one step models
it's really hard to basically as some
kind of the guidance at the test time
but for those kind of the iterative
process as I said we can basically
control the kind of the either the
velocity or the noise in a way that the
the trajectory that we are making is
going to some kind of the target data
point that we want to see. So there are
some pawns of actually the techniques
for that. So I typically classify those
kind of techniques into these 3D
classes. Actually there are more there
are many other kind of the things. So we
are going to briefly talk about some
kind of the very recent techniques in
terms like achieving uh this goal uh
into these three the categories. So
actually the first two are kind of the
same. So you can see that actually the
second one is kind of the some special
case of this quality manipulation. So
for today we are going to discuss like
first these two things and the next week
uh we're going to have some time to also
discuss this one as well.
Uh so for the first these two things the
basic idea is that as we have seen for
the classifier the guidance and also CFD
case uh we are doing some kind of the
manipulation of the score. So every time
when you perform the reverse process we
give it a model uh we are basically uh
modifying this quarter here in a way
that that becomes some kind of like you
know the trajectory making some kind of
the the output that we want to see. So
there are actually quite many practical
ideas in terms of this cool
manipulation. So I'd like to just like
show like one specific example here but
I also uh would like to emphasize that
there are literally literally like tons
of some kind of examples for that and
also there are many uh some practical
the ideas and some of those techniques
are basically not explained with any
kind of theory. So quite some practical
the ideas but basically it works well uh
in practice. uh and also many of those
kind of the techniques are basically
developed uh especially for the image
and the video generation and you can
also consider applying those techniques
for the other the data modalities as
well. So if I showed like this specific
example which is called the repaint uh
this is the problem which is basically
filling some kind of the missing regions
in the images. So let's think about the
case and now we want to generate the
images uh which is basically having this
background region. So we basically want
to fix these parts and we only want to
fill in the this kind of some the mask
region. Then how we can make some kind
of the image which basically preserves
this kind of the background region
and this is obviously kind of the some
uh problem of the generation because
there can be multi multiple the the
possible some kind of the ways to fill
in this kind of foreground region right.
So if I show some examples here uh for
instance if I erase this part and fill
in some kind of the images here uh there
can be some multiple different kind of
the some expressions the facial
expressions like this right so this is
really the generation the process uh the
the problem uh another very extremely
example that we only have this part and
we want to fill in the the the outer the
part then there can be even some cases
that we are not even like making the
what's that some kind of some apple?
It's not the apple some kind of fruit
images but something else while still
basically fixing this kind of the some
uh the the this kind of the the center
region here.
So you can see that this is basically
some kind of a conditional problem right
and we can consider basically training a
diffusion model with this kind of the
condition. If we already have some kind
of the tones of some kind of the pairs
of the input condition and divide on the
outputs then you can obviously use some
kind of the classify the classifier the
guidance or classify free guidance
whatever kind of things. So there are
actually lots of the approaches uh to
solve the same problem.
But here basically the idea is that uh
without basically training another
diffusion model what we are going to do
is that we are going to use the
pre-trained model uh to do this kind of
the the the uh the task.
So the basic idea for this is that uh we
are basically performing the den nosing
the process for the uh foreground
region. So let's say this foreground
region is basically the region that we
are going to fill and this background is
the region that we want to basically
preserve uh from the input. So here the
basic idea is that how we can basically
perform the den noising the process uh
for the foreground reason uh while
basically also preserving this kind of
background
and here the kind of the idea is that so
as I said basically there is no
theoretical explanation uh why this
works no theory here just practical the
idea and you can try this yourself and
see how much it works uh so the basic
idea is So each of the denoing step
let's say we have the XT
right so this is the intermediate the uh
the noisy the data point and we perform
the dning uh one step in a way that we
get the xt minus one right so this is
the xt and we perform the one den noing
step and getting the xt minus one and
now what we want to do is that for the
background reason here uh we also
perform not the reverse process but the
fold process
So which basically means that uh we are
performing the reverse process for the
foreground region and the B process for
the background region with the same
amount of the uh the the time step t
minus one here in a way that we are
getting some kind of the two dod data
points but one is coming from the
reverse process and the other one is
coming from the fourth process. So this
one is basically uh having some kind of
the information about the input the
background region here because we
perform the B the B process and this is
kind of the the output from the purely
reversed process the generated the
process and what we do is that we
combine these two uh for the foreground
region uh obviously we take the uh
information here and for the background
region we take the information here. So
we have basically the here the the the
idea is that we are achieving having
some kind of a two xt minus one here the
intermediate the uh the data points
while basically the background region
the xt minus one is basically achieved
by the performing the full process from
the background uh for the for the
foreground region we are basically
achieving the xtus one by performing
reverse process.
So 2 xt minus one with the same amount
of the noise, same level of the noise
but one is coming from the pool and one
is coming from the reverse. Uh and then
uh combine this and then repeat this
process.
Then somehow this basically leads to
basically getting some kind of the
outputs which is preserving the
background region and also making the uh
images in the foreground region which is
basically aligned with the uh the
background.
So can you guess why this works?
So here basically one the thing is that
it's pretty sure like why we are
basically preserving the background
region right because every time we just
like run the full process from this like
given the image which means that if it
goes to the end the last step of the
reverse process what we are going to do
is that we are just performing the the
full uh the diffusion like just like one
step probably out of the like 1,000 step
and also running the uh reverse process
again based on that. So basically which
means that for the background return uh
the information that we are basically
making here would be quite the same
almost the same from the input image
because we just like perform the
forground like one step and just like
learning the noising again with just
like one step out of the last of the
steps typically like 1,000 steps. So
it's quite clear in terms of like why we
are going to achieve some kind of the
like know preserve the the background
region from the input images. Obviously
it is not very clear in terms of how we
can make this kind of like seamlessly
like the connected images for the
foreground basically. But this kind of
the combination of the uh the xt minus
one coming from the uh the forward
process is giving some kind of the
guidance in terms of that the xt should
be uh going into the direction in a way
that this like background should be
should match the the given the image. So
for those kind of the techniques the
thing is that there's no uh uh
theoretical guarantee and if you try
yourself actually there will be some
failure cases as well. uh there are
actually some cases that the foreground
and the background basically do not
match uh each other. So there are some
kind of some engineering the techniques
in terms of basically how we can achieve
some kind of the better the outputs. uh
but this is kind of like one sort of
like uh example uh in terms of that how
we can do some kind of the uh some score
manipulation very practically uh in
terms of that we can use some kind of
the pre model not only to make some kind
of the full images but just to build in
some kind of the missing regions. So
there are many this kind of some
interesting the examples
and also especially for the uh uh the
image generation what also people do is
that typically when you design the uh
the noise partition the network uh we're
going to have some kind of the attention
the modules right the the cross
attention and also the s attention the
modules inside the the the noise
position the network for those kind of
the cases we can also do this coding
manipulation by manipulating making the
attention maps in the self attention and
the cross attention the the modules
inside the no the noise position the
network in a way that this core also
become something uh that we want to get
there are also tons of examples for that
but this is basically not the main topic
for today so I'm going to skip some
details here uh if you are more
interesting some kind of those kind of
practical the techniques I recommend you
to check out the survey paper and also
check out lots of the work here these
are all the the kind of the techniques
things that are doing this kind of some
quality manipulation.
So if I show some kind of more examples
for that uh what you can do by doing
this kind of this quality manipulation
is that you can do something like this.
So given this kind of the tool images
like we are taking the some structural
information from the this image from
this building and some some style def
factor the appearance information from
the this image in a way that we are
making another image like this. So these
all can be done basically doing some
kind of like doing some like the cross
attention and also basically
manipulating this core function based on
the cross attention.
Uh this is also another example there
actually work that we have done uh which
is basically not only making the image
which is not aligned with the given the
text but also basically aligning some
kind of the the objects in the image
with the given the layout here. So what
we can see here is that uh now we have
some kind of the some correspondence
between the some words here and also the
2D bounding boxes here. So which means
that the car yellow here should be
located on the this yellow box and also
the green the castle should be also
located on the left the green box here
and also the balloon as well. You can
say that those objects are placed in the
right region given this kind of the
additional some kind of the the guidance
information. And these are some kind of
the other examples as well. And this
kind of the some kind of the uh the
arrangement of the objects in the the
images can be also achieved without like
the training another diffusion models
but doing some kind of the manipulation
the score uh in the with the kind of pre
model.
So this is actually quite interesting
thing uh or the the diff flow models uh
through some kind of the iterative
degeneration the process by just like
somehow uh you know guiding some kind of
the the score function actually we can
do some kind of the many those kind of
the manipulations and also the editing
as well
and this is also the examples for the 3D
uh for the video as well. So this is the
the case that we have some kind of the
uh given the video like this and by
performing the inversion here what we
can do is that now we can regenerate the
video while basically moving the object
into the new uh the locations here. So
those are some examples uh doing some
kind of the video editing using the
pre-traint the video models as well.
So there are lots of the examples for
this. Oh, more examples. Moving the base
here at the low new locations and also
moving the chairs as well.
So this is basically uh the basic idea
in terms like how we can do some kind of
the uh you know giving some kind of
inference time the guidance uh with the
pre-trained models and especially for
the first category here uh it's kind of
good in terms of that we can uh give
some kind of the very direct uh some
kind of a guidance by just like you know
manipulating this course but obviously
the downside for these like the first
class of the technique is that uh first
of all there is no theoretical
explanation. That's kind of the biggest
problem. And also the second these are
all the techniques that are only
applicable to some kind of some
specialty cases for especially for some
specialy guidance especially for the
images. So you can also consider
applying those kind of things for the
other data modalities as well. But be
careful in terms of that uh it does not
guarantee uh to work. there can be some
failure of the cases and there's also no
some kind of the explanation the the
theoretical uh the explanation.
So that's kind of the downside. So
that's why we are going to discuss the
second one uh which is kind of some
special case for the the quality
manipulation uh but with some kind of
the more uh slightly more the specific
cases but for actually more the the
broader the applications and also with
some kind of the some theoretical the
the explanations.
So based on the second type of the the
technique uh the typical the types of
the problem that we are going to solve
is this like inverse problems. Is there
anyone who has heard about inverse
problems before
inverse problem I mean this very uh the
common problems right so this is really
the problem that we can see for many
applications.
So here the the basic idea is that uh we
want to basically find the causal factor
x here. So this is basically what we
want to find. The thing is that the only
information that we have is basically
the y here. So let's say y is kind of
this some partial observation the
partial information and given the
partial information the thing is that we
know how each of the the data point x is
basically mapped to the one of the
partial observation y here. So this
function a is given
and the thing is that this function a uh
may not be immutable which means that
given the partial observation there can
be some multiple some possible deculture
factors that would basically result in
getting the y here and even there might
be some kind of the some noise which is
basically injected into the observation
here. So what we know is that we know
the function a here and also the
observation y here and given the
observation the y here how can it get
some kind of some plausible the output x
here one of the plausible kind of the
outputs. So as I said typically this a
function is basically not imbutable
which means that there can be multiple
possible x given the y. So you can see
that this is actually the conditional
deg right. uh basically if you have some
kind of the loss of the pairs of the x
and the y then you can consider
basically training a another diffusion
model using whatever like the classify
fragance guidance or whatever kind of
things in terms of the just like we only
make the neuron net that takes the y as
the input and making predicting this
core that can produce the x right but
here obviously what we are going to do
is that how we can solve this inverse
problems uh without collecting the
training data set for those pairs
But only when you have the uh pre model
that can produce the x without the
condition of the y. So that's basically
what we are going to do. Uh clip
make sense. So again this is the setup
that we only have the observation y here
and based on this uh based on this uh
and also we when we have the information
for the the function a here we want to
make one of the possible dx that would
result in the observation d y here and
there can be some cases that we are
having some kind of the noise small
noise into the partial observation where
there's no noise uh and there are lots
of the applications uh of the inverse
problems
uh yeah I just brought up some kind of
the examples especially for the image
and the the image domain and but also
for the other data modalities you can
also find many of the inverse problems
as well. So for example let's see uh the
gausian and debing the case. So this is
the case that we are basically only
having the the blurred image here and
based on the blurred image we want to
find this kind of the clean image. uh
that's basically what your the
smartphone does right for your the
images right so here this is the case
that this kind of the mapping function
from the clean image into the blurry
image is basically defined is so we
assume that this kind of the mapping is
defined as kind of the convolution of
the gaus and corner so in a way that the
function a here is basically
approximated is kind of the convolution
of the gaus and the corner and we only
have some kind of the blurred the image
and given this kind because it's some
blurry image. How we can make some kind
of the clean the image the this one is
basically the problem of the gaus and
the dor. Uh so this is basically one
specific case.
The other example might be super
resolution. So let's say like we only
have the low resolution image. So from
the low resolution image how we can make
some kind of the higher resolution
image. So this is also one of the
inverse problem. Obviously we know how
we can do the down sampling from the
higher resolution to the low resolution.
Right? This function is given. Uh so
this kind down simply the function is
given but we want to do the uh the the
immersion in terms of that when you only
have the r resolution the image how we
can generate some kind of the high
resolution image. This is also one of
the the problems of the inverse
problems. Right?
How about the inpainting? So this is
exactly the same the problem that we
have seen for the repaint case. So
repaint was the example that which is
actually solving the inverse problem uh
with some kind of some practical the
ideas like score the manipulation but
this is actually really one of the the
case we only have the background image
and the a function here is basically
some masking function right which is
only taking some the some kind of region
of the given the the full image. So when
we have some kind of this masking
function the a here and we given the
background image how we can make some
kind of the full image uh that will
basically result in this background with
some kind of the the masking the
function
makes sense
and also this is another example of the
tomography uh like some kind of CT scan
or MRI scan kind of things. uh what we
do is that we only basically have some
kind of the observations of the
projection of some kind of 3D things
here into the multiple views right so
this basically what we acquire through
the some kind of the MRI scan or some
kind of CT scan kind of things right so
when you have some kind of the multiple
the projections of the 3D things into
the multiple reviews from those kind of
the 2D projections how we can
reconstruct the 3D is kind of the the
tomography the problem and this is also
the case that we know the projection
function from the some kind of real
things that we want to get here into the
multiple the 2D views and we want to
basically reconstruct 3D from the
multiple the projections also one of the
examples of the um inverse problems. Can
you come up with some kind of the other
the inverse problems uh for not only for
the images for the other the modalities?
So actually it can be kind of
interesting some research problem if you
can find some sort of the some inverse
problems for the other the uh domain as
well. I don't know for the some molecule
for some other kind of things there
might be some cases that you have some
kind of the some partial observation and
you want to make some kind of the full
output that is kind of the align with
this kind of the partial the information
uh and those kind of the mapping
function is already known for those kind
of the cases you can see that this is
like one of the immerse problems and
then you can solve that problem using
the technique that we are going to
discuss here. uh so actually there are
lots of the applications
uh and as I said obviously the solution
of the inverse problem would not be
unique for many of the cases for many
kind of the typical the the cases uh
when you solve the inverse problem
that's basically the typically the case
that the solution is basically the not
unique so that's why basically we need
to uh make some kind of either some
conditioner deserate model or we need to
somehow leverage the pre-traint
unconditional designed models while
doing some kind of the conditional
degeneration.
So if we go into some more details in
terms of like how we can solve the
inverse problems with the pre-trained uh
diffusion model.
So what we are basically predicting
using the pre-trained diffusion model is
that we are predicting this score right
we now know that the noise that we are
predicting using the diffusion model is
kind of like corresponding to this
information this core function but now
what we want to do is that we basically
want to do some kind of a conditional
degeneration
which means that now we want to compute
uh the conditional score here the score
of the xt conditioned by dy.
So given that we only have this
information how we can compute this uh
this is basically the problem that we
are doing
and using the base rule basically what
we can see is that uh we can see that
this part is basically the constant. So
after basically computing the gradient
of the log of the probability I say what
we can say is that actually this
posterior uh the square conditioned by y
is the same of the summation like these
two the score of the uh the marginal
distribution here and also the score of
this kind likelihood distribution the
the score of the y conditioned by the x
t. uh is clear.
So basically what we are going to see is
that what we want to compute is
basically this this conditional the
score the condition uh the score of the
xt conditioned by the y but actually
computing this uh this condition score
is the same with this one from the base
row in terms of like bically this is
already the uh the information that we
already know right so instead of like
computing this conditional discore
actually we can just compute this and
like add this to the marginal discore
score. So it's the matter like whether
we just directly compute this posterior
score or the likelihood score here
adding this to the the margin score
here. And the reason basically why we
are seeing obviously this is that we
we're going to see that actually
computing this is like much easier than
this. Uh this is basically what we going
to do right and also for the uh previous
slide we have seen some examples like
computing this right
you should be familiar with like this
core function this is already we have
seen the previous slide
uh for the classifier the guidance or
the classifier the free guidance we
already have seen like how we compute
this right
so in the case of the classifier the
guidance
this likelihood score was computed from
the pre-trained uh the classifier.
Right? So that was kind of the the idea
for the classifier guidance for the
class three guidance. Uh we also uh
jointly learned uh both the conditional
and the uncondition scores using the
same neural network and this the likely
score was computed based on the the the
noise that we are predicting. Right?
So these two were basically the examples
that in terms that we are computing this
likelihood square uh using another
neuron network by training another the
classification network or jointly
learning this the noise with the
unconditional d noise. So these are
already some kind of examples and
obviously here what we are going to do
is that we are going to somehow uh so
the thing is that without some kind of
the additional some kind of training
there is no way to basically compute the
accurate value like this. uh what we are
going to do is that we are going to do
some kind of the approximation uh for
this without any kind of the training uh
in a way that we can do some kind of the
uh inference timely guidance in the
generation.
So this is like basically all about how
we are going to model this kind of the
condition score the likelihood score
without any kind of the training.
uh for this actually I'm going to give
some kind of the very basic ideas in
terms of how we are basically
approximating how we are modeling this
core there are tons of the ideas for
that uh we are going to get into the
some uh easiest the ones first
so before we get into some more details
for that let's think about some kind of
the easy case first in terms of like
know we are assuming that this mapping
function da is kind of a simple linear
function function.
So basically linear function basically
means that the observation y here can be
achieved by multiplying some kind of the
the either some kind of matrix or
something here uh into the our clean
data point x0 here
actually for many of the examples that
we have seen the previous slide for the
convolution or some kind of the super
resolution for the masking for the
protection for those cases. So all the
applications uh you can see that
actually this a function becomes linear
function. So actually for many of the
applications actually the inverse
problems that we are seeing is the
inverse problems with the linear default
model linear functions here.
So obviously there are some other cases
that which is not linear. But if we
basically assume that uh this function
is the linear function then now we can
make it easier. Basically what we can
see is that uh given that this uh a is
kind of linear function. Now what we can
see is that we can treat this condition
y here uh the partial observation y as
kind of the sample from the gaussian
distribution.
Make sense? Since now this is kind of
the linear function. What you can see is
that uh this is the mean and this is
kind of the the variance uh the standard
deviation for the uh this uh the gausian
distribution
and now we know that when everything is
basically the gaussian distribution then
it becomes much easier right so that's
kind of the purpose that we are making
this as kind of linear function so now
we are basically modeling this as kind
of the uh the the the gausian
distribution
then what you can do is that since this
is the gausian distribution
Then we can now directly compute this
conditional score.
Basically the meaning of like this score
is that how likely we going to have the
partial observation dy given the clean
data point x0
make sense.
Okay. Like the meaning of like this
function would be is that uh how much we
going to have this partial observation
dy uh given this clean data point x0.
But as you can see the thing is that
when you only have like this core
function there is no way that we can add
some kind of a guidance in the
intermediate steps of the generating the
process. What we want to do is that we
are basically using this information to
basically add some kind of the offset to
this core in the intermediate steps in a
way that we can basically bend the
trajectory uh into the some kind of
output that we want to see. But based on
this information only thing that we can
do is that we can only compute this
core function for the conditioned by the
clean data point x0 here. But this is
actually the the score that we want to
get the clean data uh the the uh score
for the y conditioned by the interal
data point xt
make sense.
Okay. So basically the thing is how we
going to basically approximate this and
do you remember the first test that we
had last time?
Actually the problem four was basically
about this right? Uh if you remember
still remember the problem for the the
first test actually the problem for the
first test was like all about that how
we are going to do this kind of like
solve this like inverse problems and at
that time uh actually we did some very
crude approximation. we assume that this
is the same uh we did this uh this is
really bad approximation uh so this is
the simplest case obviously the thing is
that as I said uh there is no way that
we can uh have some kind of the precise
computation for this we need to involve
some kind of the approximation but the
worst approximation would be that we
just treat this is the same as we did
this you know that we can directly
compute this from the formulation like
this
But let's do slightly the better the
approximation. Uh but also before that
uh you might already have some kind of
feeling that you know this is now all
about basically uh having this core
function of the xt while we can compute
this right. So seems like we need to see
some kind of the connection between the
xt and the x0
which means that this is alo the place
that the tweet formula need to comes in
right so we also going to use the twis
formula here. So again uh we have seen
this like multiple times. Uh given the
XT uh we can compute the mean of the X0
conditioned by the XT right the expected
value of the X0 given the XT. So this is
like we have seen multiple times using
the TW.
But actually the thing is that if we
want to approximate uh this based on
this information what we want to have is
that we need to actually know the exact
distribution of the x0 conditioned by
the xt. So we're going to get into that
point how we can basically use the
information in terms of like the
conditional distribution of the x0
conditioned by dxt to compute this
conditional score from this one. We're
going to see the connection between
these two. But the thing is that
basically we want to know how we can get
some kind of the uh the probability
distribution of the x0 given the x t
here we only know the mean uh we can
compute the mean using the d3 formuler
but we don't know the full distribution
so we are going to do some kind of the
uh really bad approximation in terms of
that approximating this distribution
again as kind of the gaussian
distribution. Again, this is really also
the bad approximation, but this would be
still better than this. Just making
these two be the same. Uh this is the
kind of the worst case. Uh slightly the
better result might be that we basically
uh treat that this conditional
distribution the X0 condition by the XT
to be another the Gausian distribution
with some kind of the arbitrary some
kind of the variance here. So we set uh
some numbers here because we don't know
uh this distribution. So it's kind of
like really bad approximation but we can
uh only compute the mean value here
using the T formula right make sense.
Then based on this what can you do?
Actually we already discussed like what
we can do. Uh so do you remember this
slide?
This is uh almost the same the slide
that we have seen the lecture five. Uh
if you go back to the slides of the
lecture five then you're going to see
that actually uh there was a slide that
looks like this. Uh so this is basically
all about how we can compute the
marginal distribution here when the both
the prior and also the likelihood are
basically the gaussian distributions.
So given that when the prior is the
gaussian and also the likelihood is like
another degian defined in this way then
we could see that the marginal
distribution dpy here could be derived
into the another gausian distribution.
So that's basically why we approximating
everything as the gaussian for the
convenience to computing all those those
kind of things. So the thing is that now
we know how we can compute the marginal
distribution here even these two when
these two are basically gausian
distribution
and obviously this is the time that we
need to solve the quiz right.
So this is basically what we know uh
from all the the inverse problem we have
when the a function here is defined as
kind of the uh the the linear function.
So the our basically the assumption that
this like the a function is linear is
making us to have this kind of the
gausian here and this is basically the
our approximation. We simply just
approximated this condition distribution
the X0 condition XT as kind of the
Gaussian distribution for simplicity.
Obviously as I said this is really bad
approximation and but the thing is that
based on these two now we can compute
this. This is what we want to compute
right basically this core function for
this specific uh the the conditional
distribution right. So based on the
facts that we have seen in the previous
slide uh based on this uh you can also
download the slides in the course web
page or this slide uh download this and
you can check out this and based on this
information now let's consider computing
this.
So while you basically calculate this uh
so here basically is that the more
important thing than just like calculate
all those kind of thing is that we need
to understand the mean like computing
this core like this
this score of like this conditionality
distribution is basically some kind of
the the guidance that we are adding uh
in the generic process. So we can
basically imagine this kind of situation
that we are seeing some kind of the some
journey of the xt like starting from the
x capital t uh the time is basically
decreasing from the capital t all the
way to the zero right uh starting from
there going to some like one of the
points. So if we basically follow the
given this score function then whatever
starting point that you have this will
basically go into the one of the some
data point the realistic the data point
right having some kind of the journey
from the x capital t like going to the
x0 right uh so when making this kind of
be some the pass uh in the space what we
do is that we want to have some kind of
a final output uh which partial
observation becomes exactly this Right?
We know basically how we can map the
final the output into the poly
observation through the given function
the a function here right what we want
to get is that we want to get not just
kind of the any realist data point but
it should be realistic and also each
partial observation should be this
exactly y here.
So in this way uh while we make some
kind of the pass from the x capital t to
the x0 what we do is that we add this
amount of the score the condition of the
score which is basically pushing the
intermediate point to go into the some
specific way so that the output gets
closer in a way that the final the
output is aligned with the post
observation dy here.
So how we are going to add this kind of
the some additional some kind of the
noise or the score to push the
trajectory uh to get closer to the one
of the data point which is partial
pubation becomes the y here.
The thing is that uh if we make assume
that the our the inverse problem is the
linear the function then we can compute
this the conditional score condition by
the x0 has some the closed form the
analysis form but this is not that
helpful because actually we wanted to
compute the score for the intermediate
data point xt here. So that's the point
that we need to make some kind of a
connection between the XT and the X0
here and this is the formulation how we
are basically bridging these two in a
way that we can compute this cor like
this uh from the condition of the this
condition by X0.
Uh so we had that very crude
approximation like this conditional dist
distribution the x0ero condition by the
xt obviously this is really bad
approximation if this is really the
gausian distribution then why do we need
to perform the reverse process we can
directly sample the x0 from the xt right
there's no need to run the reverse
process so which doesn't make sense at
all right uh so if this was could be
really approximated well with the
gausian distribution then we didn't need
to run the reverse process we can
directly sample the x0 from the xt. Uh
so typically this uh conditional
distribution would be way more the
complex distribution than the gausian
distribution. But for now without any
kind of the some further the 3D training
or the fine training there is no way to
really compute this. So that's why we do
this kind of some growth approximation.
So which means that uh when you apply
those kind of techniques uh it does not
guarantee to work for all the cases but
you can try this for the many
applications and see how much it works.
So basically this with the this
formulation uh we going to get this kind
of the the final the gausian
distribution for this likelihood
distribution the y condition by the xt
you get this formulation.
So this is basically what we can compute
uh with the the formulation the previous
slide and since this is the gausian
distribution uh now we can compute the
gradient of the log of the probability
uh with respect to the xt right the
gradient with respect to xt which means
that if we take the the chain rule here
then we all the way to the other things
then now we can compute uh the
likelihood score into the this form
Looks quite complicated but actually
this is not very complicated kind of
things. We can compute this
and then so we get this and here so one
more thing is that uh for many of the
cases especially for the super
resolution or some kind of the gausian
the develing for many of the cases uh
there may not be some kind of the noise
in the measurement for example like the
down sampling is not involve any kind of
some kind of noise right for many of the
cases we can assume that this sigma
would be zero then the final the
likelihood of the score would be this
one
make sense. So this is called pseudo
inverse guidance uh because of the fact
that we need to basically compute the
pseudo inverse of the a here. And as I
said uh this formulation holds only when
the uh inverse problem is defined as
kind of linear function otherwise we
cannot compute the square right. Okay.
So you can really try this yourself for
the cases like when you have the known
the a function you can compute some kind
of the the additional the offset of the
the the score function here and then see
how much this will be basically affect
uh in the reversive process.
So this is basically like one idea. uh
the other kind of the idea is that uh we
we are really going back to that the
even cruer the approximation. So what if
we assume that uh this distribution is
not simply the go distribution but it's
the direct delta the distribution like
this. So this is basically the case that
we have seen the uh the the first test.
So in this kind of the very uh with some
kind of very cruel approximation really
bad approximation the thing is that we
can directly define uh this uh
approximate uh this conditional
distribution the likelihood the y
condition xt as kind of the gausian
distribution like this as I said this is
really even worse the approximation
then what the reason for this uh the
reason why we are saying this is that
this is obviously making the even the
competition even much simpler. uh so
that's kind of the so we this kind of be
some much simpler the uh the
approximation
now even we don't need to assume that
this like the the inverse function is
linear function which means that with
this kind of the even crudder the
approximation now we can cover the
broader range of the applications even
when this kind of the a function is not
linear function
then what you can see is that uh the
conditional score for this term this
distribution can be directly computed in
this way.
So this was actually the answer of the
the the
first problem in the first test. So this
is kind of good. Uh now we can compute
the likelihood score as kind of the
gradient of the L2 loss L2 difference
between the observation that we have and
then the basically the the things that
we are computing from the tweed model.
So you can also see the meaning like
this right the meaning of like this the
likelihood score is that we simply
compute compare the given the
observation and also the output that we
compute from the tweed formula here uh
through the mapping here. So see how
much these two is different compute the
L to loss and that take the gradient
with respect to XT. So that becomes some
kind of the additional the guidance that
we are adding to the noise uh in the uh
the generation the process.
Okay.
So yeah this is kind of thing simply
what we can do is that based on the
really bad approximation we simply take
the gradient of the L2 difference
between the this is our reconstruction
based on the twist formula and this is
the given the input and this becomes the
additional score.
One more the additional thing is that
if we go back to the DDPM uh
deformulation. So this is basically the
things we have seen like how we compute
the XT minus one given the XT. Uh so if
we go back to this slide uh we can
actually see that this XT minus one
deformation is actually some kind of the
aine function. Basically having some
linear term here multiplying something
into the our noise here the predict
noise pull out some kind of the some
other terms here right you can simplify
in this way
then what you can see is that uh let's
say that this xt minus one d prime here
let's say this xt minus one prime is
kind of the next sample which is
computed with the original d noise here
so without the any kind of this some
conditioning. This was something that we
wanted to have right the xt minus sample
with the original discourse. But now the
thing is that now we want to uh adjust
the noise by adding this term right.
So here the thing is that when you have
the next sample of the xt minus one
let's say this is xt prime here which is
computed only with the this noise.
uh what's the kind of the next sample
that can be sampled by with the this
summation of the the noise here
and what you can see is that if you
already computed the XT minus one prime
here with the original the noise so
instead of like know adding some kind of
the uh the noise in the noise prediction
here basically what you can see is that
we can basically add this term uh into
the next sample computed with the
original D noise to sample the new Xtus
one which is now computed with the some
the addition of the the noise
make sense. So the point is that instead
of like updating your the noise we can
do basically the update of the Xt minus
one
is basically the same thing.
So in the DDPM deformation basically
what you can see is that uh either you
can basically update the node here and
compute all those kind of things and
this is this is exactly the same thing
that we are basically computing the xt
minus one first and then updating the
xtus one uh with basically this amount
I mean this is not any kind of some
complex kind of things you can just like
write down all the things and you're
going to say that uh whether you
basically add some kind of the
additional den noise into the noise here
where basically adding this term into
the xt minus one these two becomes the
same you can basically just derive
yourself uh nothing complicated but from
this basically what you can see is that
these two basically the same thing and
this is exactly the same the generation
the process of the dpm uh for the
guidance what we need to do is that we
are literally just like adding one line
of the code in your the PyTorch code by
just adding just a single line by
literally just adding a single line uh
in your the PyTorch code uh you can add
some kind of a guidance in the
generation process.
So this is kind of the really
interesting the point uh adding the
guidance in the at the test time even
without any kind of fine tuning using
the pre-tusion model is such easy thing
you just need to add like one single
line into the code uh to give some kind
of the guidance in the outputs and based
on that you can solve many inverse
problems you can solve the uh super
resolution in painting whatever debing
many other kind of
interesting.
But obviously this does not guarantee to
make some kind of the some the some
desired outputs uh because as we have
discussed in the previous slide actually
we introduced many kind of the some bad
approximations like this.
Obviously this is really the bad
approximation. So because of the fact
that there are many kind of the best
approximations that we are removing here
actually the finality outputs may not be
something that we want to see they may
not be really aligned with the partial
observations but actually actually some
applications actually this approach
really works quite well. So we also have
seen the two techniques for the
impainting right the first one was
really basically doing some kind of the
combination of this core the terms using
the repaint technique and the other
thing is basically just like using this
technique adding this line in the code
in terms of the injecting the noise uh
which one would work better
I'm just like showcasing there are uh
explaining that there are multiple ways
to achieve the the test time this the
the guidance using the premium models uh
you can try yourself and see which one
is working better. Uh basically there
are multiple ways to do this kind of
this adding the guidance and the test
time and the idea that I introduced here
was basically two very basic the ideas
and there are 30 more the ideas you can
see in the many other places.
So and if I go back to the slide uh
actually the title that I had for this
second class technique was basically the
graded sense from the future worked uh
but I didn't say anything about the
reward here right uh and also here the
question might be that I explained this
all the things based on the uh DDPM
deformation that we uh discussed from
the beginning of like this class uh but
what if we explain the same thing with
the the continuous deformation with the
OD and the SD deformation.
Uh actually we can also try to explain
the same thing uh based on the OD and SD
deformulation. So we're going to get
into the point how the same thing how
this kind of the deformation can be
explained with the OD and the SD
formulation. Next time uh we're going to
also get into the uh the point of the
the third one the particle filtering the
next week. So as I said uh there will be
no lecture this Wednesday and we're
going to continue the discussion for
this second and the third one uh the
next Monday. Okay.