Welcome back to CS231N lecture 13. Today
we're going to talk about generative
models. Last time we were talking about
self-supervised learning um which is
this really interesting paradigm where
we want to somehow learn structure
directly from data with no with no
supervision with no labels. the and and
the typical present like the typical
formulation of self-supervised learning
that we talked about a bunch of examples
last time is you have your big data set
with no labels. Ideally, it's just
images. This is great. You can get a lot
of images. Um you're going to feed these
through some kind of encoder that's
going to extract a feature
representation from your images. Then go
through some decoder that will predict
something from that feature
representation. And in the whole trick
in self-supervised learning is coming up
with some kind of pretext task that you
can train this whole system on without
requiring any kind of human annotation
or human labels. Um and then and then so
we talked about things like rotation uh
different kinds of tasks that we can use
as pretexts for these self-supervised to
to formulate these self-supervised
learning objectives. And then typically
um this is usually a two-stage procedure
where first you're going to go and learn
this self-supervised encoder decoder on
your self-supervised task on all the
data that you can find. And then after
that you're going to throw away the
decoder and then slot in some new maybe
tiny possibly tiny fully connected
network um and actually train this thing
maybe end to end or maybe just learn the
fully connected network at the end um on
some small labelled task. And the idea
here is that via self-supervised
learning this pretext task you can train
on lots and lots of data millions
hundreds of millions billions of samples
where we don't have access to to high
quality human labels. And in the process
of self-supervised learning it's going
to learn something about the general
structure of images or of data. Um, and
then you can transfer that knowledge to
downstream tasks where you have small
amounts of human labels. So then the
typical setup you should keep in your
mind that we want to work towards in
self-supervised learning is that you're
going to train on like a billion
unlabeled images that we're getting from
the internet somewhere. Um, and then
we're going to transfer those features
to tasks where we're going to we're
willing to sit down and label maybe
tens, hundreds, maybe thousands of
examples for particular tasks that we
really care about. But we want those
tasks to be um improved by this generic
knowledge that from that we've learned
through this self-supervised pretext
task. And we talked about a couple
different kinds of pretext tasks last
time including rotation, rearrangement,
reconstruction. Um all of these are
basically having this this sense of that
you're making some geometric
perturbation, geometric disturbance to
the input pixels and then you're asking
the model to somehow recover from that
dis from that perturbation. So in the
case of rotation, maybe you rotate the
image and you ask the model to predict
how much it was rotated. In the sense of
rearrangement or solving jig jigsaw
puzzles, you're going to cut the image
up into patches and ask the model to try
to predict what was the relative
arrangement of those patches in the
original image. Um or in reconstruction,
maybe you're going to delete some parts
of the input image and then ask the
model to fill them in as some kind of
inpainting or reconstruction task. Um
and these are fairly successful. Um, we
also talked last time about a different
formulation of self-supervised learning
called contrastive learning, which has
been very successful. Um, and here I I
was told that you ran out of time a
little bit to cover a couple of these
later methods. So, I wanted to just go
over go over those really quickly at the
beginning of today's lecture instead.
Um, so the really the idea of
contrastive learning is you're going to
get pairs that are similar and pairs
that are dissimilar and you want to pull
the similar pairs together and push the
dissimilar pairs apart. And the way that
you usually do this in the context of
self-supervised learning is you're going
to start with your input images. And
again, these are unlabeled images. You
don't have labels. You don't have labels
for them. And now for each input image,
you're going to apply two random
transformations. So in the case of the
cat, we sort of took one crop around the
cat's face, another crop around the
backside of the cat, um, and and around
the monkey, we sort of took one around
the monkeykey's face and also dropped it
to black and white and, etc., etc. So
basically for each one of your input
images you're going to apply two or
possibly more possibly more than two but
two is a is a nice minimal subset two
random perturbations to your input
image. Now you're going to feed all of
those randomly perturbed um versions of
your input data to some kind of feature
extractor um which is which could be a
vit could be a CNN um any kind of neural
network that can input an image and
output a feature representation. Then
you want to apply this notion of
contrastive. So um for each of the two
augmentations that came from the cat, we
want those two feature vectors to be the
same. So we color them green. So
basically you you basically comput this
big n square similarity matrix where if
well I guess it's 2 n open pern 2 n
closed pern squ. So it's 4n^ squ if you
have n if you have n images you put two
perturbations on each. So we have a
giant um 2nx by 2n matrix for all the
all these perturbed images all these
perturbed uh augmented samples that we
that we got. Um, and now basically we
want to pull together the two augmented
samples that the two augmentations that
came from the original image. Um, and
for every pair of augmented for of every
pair of augmentations that came from
different original images, we want to
push them apart. So you basically run um
run through this feature run all of
these things through your feature
extractor, compute this giant um 4n
squared matrix of all of your scalar
similarities between those feature
vectors and then pull together the ones
that are similar, push apart the ones
that ought to be different. Um, and
that's the basic idea of contrastive
learning. Um, and one paper that really
pulled all this together, um, a couple
years ago was called Simincar that, um,
applied this very successfully to
self-supervised representation learning
on images. Um, and that's the one I
think he walked through last time. Um,
but one kind of problem with the SIM
clear setup is that it requires a fairly
large batch size um, to actually good to
get good convergence. Um, because it
gets too it's sort of too easy of a
problem for the network. If there aren't
that many samples, it's sort of too easy
to pick out the two cat ones that looked
similar. So to make the problem hard
enough for the network to give it good
enough learning signal, you tend to need
quite a large batch size in order to get
this model to converge to good features.
And then once you do that, you need to
rope in all the ideas around large scale
distributed training that we talked
about a couple of lectures ago, which is
totally feasible. It totally works. Um,
but you might ask, is there some way you
can get away with with without that? Um,
and that that leads to a couple of
approaches that I don't want to go into
too much detail. I actually don't want
to walk through through these and tell
you exactly how they how they work. I
just want to make you aware of their
existence and give you the the general
flavor of what they're trying to
achieve. Um so in this MOCO or momentum
contrast approach to self-supervised
learning, the setup is very similar to
what we just saw in Simcle. You're
taking data, you're getting augmented
pairs. You want you run them through
with feature encoder. You want to pull
together the ones that are similar, push
apart the ones that are dissimilar. But
the thing that with the thing that
differs is that we want to get away with
not having to have a gigantic batch size
at every iteration. So to do that they
keep a queue of um negatives. They keep
a queue of samples from previous
iterations of training. Um and then at
every training iteration I've got my my
X query is my current new batch of data.
And I have this this Q um X0 X1 X2 key
which are previous batches of data that
I've seen on previous iterations of
training. Now, my current batch of data
I'm going to run through my encoder
network the same as I always did um and
compute these sort of compute the
contrast of loss the same way that we
did with SIM clear the and then these uh
these this larger Q these like previous
history of batches we're going to run
through something different the momentum
encoder um and then still get feature
representations and compute the same
kind of similarity that we did through
the through through the SIM clear uh
thing but the problem is that we don't
want to back propagate into the momentum
encoder because it has too much data it
too big of a batch. We can't afford to
fit that in GPU memory. Um, so we want
to not have to back propagate through
that part. So instead, so that means
that we're not we cannot upgrade update
this momentum encoding encoder, this
second encoder via gradient descent
descent. Instead, we're going to do
something kind of wacky. What we're
going to do is have this momentum
encoder have its own set of weights.
We're going to learn them not via
gradient descent. Instead, what we're
going to do is have the momentum encoder
be a exponential moving average of the
weights of the normal encoder. So the
normal encoder, we're going to learn via
gradient descent. everything is normal.
Um, we'll forward prop, we'll back prop,
we'll get gradients, we'll make a
gradient update step on the in on the on
the typical encoder. That's the normal
thing. But then after we do that, the
momentum encoder, we're going to take
we're going to decay the encoder
weights. We're going to decay the
current momentum encoder weights by
like.99 um, and then add in 1% of the
encoder weights. So then the momentum
encoder, we have this other update rule
where it's this lagging trailing
exponential moving average of the
encoder weights. Um, and I don't have a
great intuition or explanation for why
this exactly makes sense, but there's
very strong empirical evidence that this
works. Um, so I unfort so that's uh
that's kind of the state of things, but
it's nice because it means that you can
now get away with learning these
self-supervised representations without
having to have this gigantic massive
batch of negatives at every iteration.
Um, and this was fairly successful.
There were a bunch of follow-up papers
that uh that push this direction. Um,
another one that you should be aware of
is called Dino. Um, again the idea is
very similar. It uses this similar sort
of momentum encoder, this like dual um
normal encoder that's learned via
gradient descent and a momentum encoder
just as in Moco. Um but the loss is a
little bit different. Instead of using
softmax, they use some kind of kale
divergence loss. Um and the reason I'm
mentioning this one is because you
should be aware of the existence of
Dinov2 even if we don't talk about
exactly what it does because Dinov2 is a
really strong um feature a really strong
model for self-supervised features
that's used quite a lot in practice
these days. So what they basically did
is took this recipe from Dinov1 which
was kind of similar to MoCo has a lot of
ideas from Simcle clear as well but a
lot of unique details in their approach
as well. Um but the big the big
difference in Dinov2 is that they scaled
up the training data quite a lot. So a
lot of these previous self-supervised
approaches had been trained on the
imageet data set which was 1 million
images. Um and Dinov2 was able to
successfully scale up this approach to a
much larger training set of about 142
million images. So, you know, in deep
learning, we like bigger networks, we
like bigger data, we like more GPUs, we
like more flops, we like all of those
things. Um, and Dinov2 was able to find
a recipe for self-supervised learning
that successfully scaled up to this much
larger data set gives very strong
self-supervised features. And this tends
to be used quite a lot in practice
today. Um, if you want to pick up
features and then super fine-tune them
or supervise them for some for some of
your own downstream tasks. Um, so again,
I don't expect you I don't want to walk
through all the details of how this
works. I don't expect you to know, but I
want you to know that it exists in case
you want to pick it up and use it for
some of your own projects um in the
future.
Um so that that's basically all I had to
say about self-supervised learning. Um
any any questions about that before we
move on to the the meat of today's
lecture?
Okay, guess not. So today the main topic
is generative models. Um this is really
cool. Uh this is an area of deep
learning that basically went from not
working at all 10 years ago to like
really really working in the last couple
of years. Um and this has given rise to
things like language models. These could
be these can be viewed as generative
models as we'll see. Um all kind of
image generation models, all kinds of
video generation models. These really
went from just absolutely not working at
all when I was in grad school. Like that
you would look at these samples and peer
into them and they just look like low
resolution, complete blurry garbage, but
somehow you could view some promise in
them. And I'm glad that people kept
pushing on that and pushed through the
blurry garbage and scaled it up over the
past decade because now a lot of these
techniques really do work and that's
very exciting. So this is a this is a
this is an area of deep learning that
basically didn't work at all with the
first time we taught this class and
that's really cool that it now does. Um
but that said like a lot of the
fundamental ideas around generative
modeling actually remain the same. um
the ideas about how you think about data
um what are what are approaches for
modeling them a lot of those
mathematical fundamentals actually have
not changed that much um in the past
decade um and so but what changed is
better is more compute more stable
training recipes uh bigger data sets uh
distributed training and the ability to
scale all this up into more useful tasks
I think was really what drove the
progress over the past decade um there
were some algorithmic tweaks and
especially we'll see that next lecture
as we talk when we talk about diffusion
models
But um first before we talk about
generative modeling, I wanted to step
back a little bit and talk about
supervised versus unsupervised learning,
right? Because there's a couple of
different there's a there's a couple of
different tasks that we try to approach
in deep learning. Um and they can
sometimes be sliced along a couple of
different orthogonal axes. So I wanted
to talk about those a little bit just so
we get our terminology and our
nomenclature clear. Um so supervised
learning is what we've mostly been doing
all semester um except for last lecture.
Um, in supervised learning, we have a
data set of pairs X and Y. Um, and the
goal is to learn some function that maps
from the input data X to the target or
label Y. Um, and we've seen a lot of
examples of this kind of approach so
far. Um, something like image
classification. Our input X is an image.
The output Y is going to be a label or
image captioning. The input X is going
to be an image. The output Y is going to
be some piece of text describing what we
see in that image. Object detection.
Input is an image. output is a set of
boxes and category labels describing the
objects that appear in the image or
segmentation. Maybe you assign a pixel
label, assign a label to every pixel in
the input image. And these are
supervised learning problems because the
task you're trying to solve, the thing
you want to predict is exactly what you
have in your data set. And you sort of
all you need to do in some sense is
learn a function that mimics that XY
mapping on your training data set and
then generalizes that mapping to new
samples um beyond your training data
set. Now, unsupervised learning is
something a bit more fishy and
mysterious and hard to describe. Um, but
the idea of unsupervised learning or
sometimes self-supervised learning is
that you don't have any labels. You just
have data. You just have samples X. Um,
you just have images and you want to
learn some kind of structure from that
data. Um, there's no particular task
you're necessarily targeting. You're
just trying to uncover good
representations, good structure in all
of that data. Um, why? so that you can
you know as we talked about in
self-supervised learning often so you
can apply it to downstream tasks later
on um but there's but the the task
itself in unsupervised learning is often
somewhat unspecified
some examples of this are K means
clustering where maybe we're trying to
identify um clusters in the data which
is which is some kind of structure that
we can examine from the raw pixels that
you know was even though we didn't have
labels for um or dimensionality
reduction PCA where we're trying to
uncover some lower dimensional subspace
or lower dimensional manifold that
explains the structure of our data. Um,
and again, this is something we're
trying to discover from the data itself.
We don't have annotations of what this
what this ought to be. Um, or density
estimation. Maybe we're trying to fit a
probability distribution to the data.
We're trying to understand what is the
probabilistic function that gave rise to
the data samples that we're seeing. And
again, we don't have explicit labels for
this or an explicit training set for
this. So, this is some kind of hidden or
latent structure that we're trying to
uncover through the process of training.
So, this um supervised unsupervised
dichotomy is something that you always
should keep in mind. Um and you can do
unsupervised learning which is not
probabilistic or not generative
necessarily. Something like clustering,
something like PCA, you know, often they
have probabilistic interpretations. Um
but these are examples of unsupervised
learning that don't necessarily have a
generative or probabilistic
interpretation or or don't have to be
thought of as such. Um so I often like
to think about the supervised
unsupervised dichotomy as kind of one
spectrum along which methods or or or um
systems can lie. A separate spectrum
along which we can classify systems or
tasks is that of generative versus
discriminative models. Um and these are
inherently probabilistic. And when when
we talk about generative or
discriminative models, we're always
imagining some kind of probabilistic
structure in our data that we're trying
to uncover or learn from. Um and the
difference is exactly what is the
probabilistic relationship between the
variables that we're trying to model. Um
so in discriminative model, so so
typically we have some some y and some
x. Um, and usually we think of the X as
something large, highdimensional,
usually an image in our case, and the Y
is some kind of label or description or
auxiliary information. Um, and so that
would be like your text, like your
caption, like a category label,
something like that. Um, and when you do
when you talk about a discriminative
model, we're trying to learn a
probability distribution of Y given X.
So, we're trying to learn a distribution
over labels um conditioned on our input
image X. Um and to understand to really
appreciate you know what's going on
probabilistically you need to remember
one very important feature of
probability distributions and that's
that they are normalized right when you
talk about a probability distribution or
more generally a density function p of x
um p of x is basically a function that
applies that that um that that uh that
assigns a nonzero number um to every
every possible input x with the very
important normalization constraint um
that if you integrate over the entire
space of all possible x's It integrates
for it integrates to one, right? And
this normalization constraint really
gives rise to the the power of
probabistic models in some sense because
the normalization constraint means that
all of your x's need to compete for
probability mass. There's a fixed unit
amount of probability mass. Um, and the
and a prob and and choosing a
probability distribution or density
function basically amounts to aortioning
out that fixed amount of probability
mass and smearing it across all possible
values of x that could exist. Um, and
all of those X's are in competition
because there's only a fixed unit amount
of mass to go around. So if you want to
push up the probability of one X
necessarily, the probabilities of or or
densities of other X's have to go down.
And this this and so then in these
different formulations of probabilistic
models, basically what's changing is
what are the variables that are
competing for probability mass. Um and
that means that even though the symbols
that we write on the page look very
similar um they they the different the
different competitions among what is
competing for probability mass um
induces very different structure that
the model is trying to learn or uncover.
So in the case of a discriminative model
we're learning a probabilistic model of
y conditioned on x which means that for
every x we our model is predicting a
probability distribution over all
possible labels. So if our labels are
discrete and categorical um like cat dog
then that means we have a fixed amount
of probability 0 to one um and cat and
dog must must sum to one um and we have
a separate probability distribution over
the labels for every input x um and
crucially notice here that there is no
competition among images for probability
mass because every image is inducing its
own distribution over the label space
there's no kind of competition for mass
across the different images the the only
things that are competing for mass are
the different labels for each image and
that's very important when you think
about discriminative modeling. Um and
one interesting other thing so you know
and one interesting other facet of
discriminative modeling is that they
have no real way to reject unreasonable
inputs. So once we've fixed our label
space of say cat and dog in this example
if we feed in something that's not a cat
or a dog at all like a monkey or a piece
of abstract art the system has no
flexibility. It has no freedom to say
this is unreasonable. it's forced to
output a a distribution over the fixed
vocabulary that we assigned at the
beginning. Um so that's that's maybe
could be seen as a shortcoming but it's
just important to understand what
exactly is happening under the hood when
you think about modeling different kinds
of data probabilistically.
Now a generative model is something very
different. Now instead what we're doing
in a generative model is learning a
distribution P of X. Um we want to learn
a distribution over all possible images
X. Um and now this is very interesting.
This means that all possible images that
could ever exist in the universe are all
now competing with each other for
probability mass. Um, and this is now
really really a hard question that
requires, you know, it sounds kind of
simple in in on its face, but this
requires you to confront some very deep
and philosophical problems about the
world, right? Because now all images are
competing for probability mass. And it
you're forced in order to model that,
you're forced to answer questions.
You're like, you know, should an image
of a three-legged dog, how should that
get probability mass in relationship to
an image of a three-ear armed monkey?
Probably the three-legged dog should get
pro more probability mass because
that's, you know, you can have that
happen by a dog losing a leg. But how
are you going to get a three- armed
monkey? I don't know. That seems much
more rare. Um, unless you're modeling
sci-fi images or something like this. So
once you're in this regime of im all
possible images competing for
probability mass now your model really
needs to think very carefully about the
kinds of structure that can can exist in
the data and it becomes a much much
harder problem to solve.
And another interesting thing here is
that now with a generative model the
model now does have the capacity to
basically say no this is not a
reasonable image this is not a
reasonable input and the way that it can
do that is by assigning you know low or
even zero probability mass to any one
image that it gets. So maybe in our
generative model um maybe we only want
it to recognize you know be a generative
model of zoo animals and if we want to
have a generative model of zoo animals
then you know if we feed in an image of
abstract art it should have zero
probability mass. So now we have a
mechanism for rejecting or or saying
that this type of image is not within
the scope of what we care about.
And now a conditional generative model
is um even more interesting. So this is
where we're learning a conditional
distribution over images x conditioned
on some um some some label sigma y. And
now this means that for every possible
label um maybe we're now inducing a
distri a competition among all possible
images. So in this case if y is say a
categorical label of cat and dog now um
for every for each possible categorical
label cat and dog the model is
separately inducing a competition among
all possible images. So now you know in
in the top distribution maybe this is
the probability of all these images um
conditioned on the cat label. So then
obviously the cat image should be high.
Maybe the monkey and the dog images
image should be somewhat higher because
they're still mammals at least, but the
abstract art should be very low, maybe
even zero. Um, and then you know a
different distribution among images if
we're conditioning on the dog label. Um,
and this gets even more interesting if
you imagine that your conditioning
signal Y is something much richer than a
single categorical label. That that
conditioning single signal Y might have
been a text description. It might have
been a whole paragraph of written text.
It might have been another image plus a
piece of text. So now once you talk
about modeling these very rich output
spaces X um conditioned on very rich
input spaces Y now you're actually
asking the model to solve a very
complicated and and quite illdefined
problem that requires very deep
reasoning about the about the objects
involved. Um so that's why I think that
generative modeling is such an
interesting topic because it looks kind
of simil it looks kind of simple. All we
did was flop the X and the Y. How hard
could it be? Um but all of a sudden it
required us to think really hard about
what's going on in the visual world. Um,
and what's also interesting is that we
wrote down discriminative generative
models and conditional generative models
as three separate categories of things.
Um, but actually they're all related.
Um, and they're related through Baze
rule, which is um, you know, your kind
of your one of the most one of the most
amazing relationships in probability.
And in particular it says that you know
if we have we can write we can if we
have access to a discriminative model P
Y of X um and an unconditional
generative model P of X um as well as
some prior distribution over our labels
Y we can compose those to build a
conditional generative model P of Y
given X um or in general you can always
rearrange B rule in some way so that if
you have any two of these you can always
get a third one which is pretty cool. Um
so I mean so in practice like in in
theory you can in principle build a
conditional generative model out of the
other two components. Although in
practice this is not really how you do
it. You tend to sort of learn
conditional generative models um from
all from scratch on their own. Although
as we'll talk about in diffusion you do
end up sometimes learning conditional
and unconditional models jointly um for
some reasons. Um but this is nice to
keep in mind that there's a very deep
relationship across these different
flavors of probabilistic models. So then
you might be wondering, okay, what can
we do with these different flavors of
probabilistic models? Um, with with
discriminative models, this one
shouldn't require a lot of creativity.
We've seen a lot of these examples so
far this this this uh this quarter. So
with discriminative models, after you
train them, you can assign labels to
data. You can also do feature learning,
right? In the case of say um supervised
learning on imageet, we've seen that by
in the process of trying to predict um
categorical labels of images, those
models tend to learn useful feature
representations in the middle that can
be transferred to downstream things. So
this is an So you tend to use
descriptive models for just directly
predicting the y's that you care about
or for learning feature representations
that are induced in the process of
trying to predict those y's.
Generative models um actually these
unconditional generative models I I
think are actually kind of useless um in
general but what they kind of let you do
is maybe detect outliers. Um they look
at images and say are they are they
really do they really have low
probability mass? Are they unreasonable
images? um you can view that you can
sort of use them for feature learning
without data without labels. Um so hope
that in the process of trying to fit an
unconditional distribution P of X the
model maybe learned some useful feature
representations. Um although in general
these have not been super successful for
self-supervised learning. Um and
typically the contrasted methods that
we've talked about in the previous
lecture have in practice been much more
successful for self-supervised learning
as compared to an unconditional density
estimation.
Or um in principle you could use this
unconditional generative model to sample
and produce new samples X. Um but I
think this is actually kind of useless
um because it gives you no control over
what what is being sampled right if you
have an unconditional generative model
of images then you can sample from it to
get a new image but you have no control
over what what's in that image. Um so I
think that's that's actually you know
it's mathematically interesting to think
about how to build such models but it's
I don't think they have as much
practical significance.
Um and conditional generative models are
where are where I think actually things
are the most useful and the most
interesting. Um and these are the kinds
of generative models that get trained
and used in practice by far the most. Um
so you can in principle use them to
assign labels while rejecting outliers.
Right? You could say you know if I have
a piece of data X then look at the P of
X given Y over all over all of my
possible Y's and then you know I could
reject if if the if that's too low among
all the possible Y's. So in principle,
you could use conditional generative
models to do some kind of classification
while also maintaining the ability to
reject outliers. Um although I don't
think that's really used too much in
practice. Um what's really useful for
conditional generative models and what
is used in practice all the time
everywhere is sampling to generate new
data from labels where you actually get
to control what is generated, right?
Because if your Y is now maybe a piece
of text, you can write down I want to
see a cat wearing a hot dog flavored
t-shirt on the moon or whatever and then
your favorite generative model of images
will generate you a brand new image X
conditioned on that label Y. So this is
where I think all the juice is, where
all the magic is, where all the
excitement is. Um although somewhat
confusingly in the literature whenever
you see the term generative model you'll
they kind of mush up between um
unconditional and conditional generative
modeling. Um, and a lot of the papers
that you read will even sometimes drop
the conditioning signal. Why? Because it
makes the math look cleaner. It makes
the equations look cleaner. Um, but I
don't think unconditional generative
modeling is super useful. Um, it's
almost always conditional generative
modeling that you really want to do in
most cases. Um, so just keep aware just
be aware that if you read papers, see
equations, hear people talk, when they
talk about generative modeling, they're
probably the one they care about
training more are these conditional
generative models. Even if the math
doesn't even if the equations or
notation doesn't reflect that.
>> So uh for unconditional generative model
what does this
>> ah so I I didn't really tell you that um
and and I I was sneaky there because how
you parameterize that actually depends a
lot. There's a lot of different
formulations for all of these things and
what exactly are the going to be the
inputs and the outputs of the network
are going to vary quite a lot depending
on the formulation. Um so we're going to
talk about a whole tonomy of those in a
couple slides.
Okay. So you know why generative models?
Um the main reason you want to build
generative models is whenever there's
some ambiguity in the task you're trying
to model, right? So the the the beauty
of a probabilistic model P of X given Y
is that it's probabilistic. Um there
might be a whole space of possible
outputs X conditioned on that input
label Y. So whenever there's not a like
in some case sometimes there's just a
deterministic mapping, right? I look at
an image, I want to ask how many cats
are in the image. There's just three
cats. There's just one answer. Um, but
in a lot of cases it's more subtle. If I
ask for a picture of a dog wearing a hot
dog hat, like there's a lot of different
images that could exist based on that
query. Um, there's uncertainty in the
output. Um, and that's exactly what
generative models are trying to model.
They model a whole distribution of
outputs conditioned on their input
signal. So, anytime that there's
ambiguity in the kind of output that you
want the model to produce conditioned on
the input, that's where you want to turn
to a generative model. Um, and this is
why, and this is we've seen, we'll see a
couple examples of why where this has
gotten used a lot in the last couple of
years. So, one example is language
modeling. Um, someone asked about chatbt
a moment ago. So, in language modeling,
what you're often trying to do is
predict output text X from input text Y.
Um, sorry, the X's and Y's ended up
flipped in an awkward way on this
example. Um, but you know, so so here's
a here's an example from Chad GBT, but
the input is write me a short rhyming
poem about generative models. And wow,
it actually works. This is crazy. This
didn't work at all when we first taught
this class. Um, I'm not going to read
it. That would be embarrassing. You can
read it yourself. Um, but you know, now
this is a conditional generative model.
You could imagine there's a lot of
different possible rhyming poems about
generative models that one might write.
Um, and we had to pick one of them. And
the beauty of a generative model is that
it in principle models that whole
distribution over over possible outputs
conditioned on that input. Um, or text
to image. You know, make me an image
showing a person teaching a class on
generative models in front of a
whiteboard. um you're kind of looking at
one example through your eyes. Chat GPT
gave you a different example, right?
There's a whole different space of
possible images that might match this uh
this input text and a generative model
allows you to model that whole space and
sample from that space depending on what
you want. Um or image to video, you
know, input an image. What happens next?
Um you know, this was me holding my
AirPods over a cardboard box. Maybe I'm
going to drop it. Maybe I'm going to
move my hand. Maybe, you know, maybe I'm
going to move my hand and the AirPods
will morph into a different kinds of
AirPods. Um there's all kinds of things
that could happen. A generative model in
principle lets you kind of model and
sample from these possible futures.
Um so those are so I I so this is sort
of why we want to care about generative
modeling. Anytime there's ambiguity in
the output that's when you want to try
to turn to a generative model to solve
it.
Um and someone asked about what are the
inputs and outputs. It turns out this is
a huge field. Um and this is
surprisingly one field of deep learning
that is quite mathematical. um because
it requires you know thinking about what
are different ways to model probability
dist distributions, how can we write
down loss functions that cause the right
things to happen. So this is one area
where when you read papers there may be
a lot of math there may be a lot of
equations um and you actually might need
to think through those equations pretty
carefully to understand what's going on.
So this is one sub field that tends to
have more more math and more equations
um which I think is kind of fun kind of
interesting. Um so there's this whole
taxonomy of different kinds of
generative models that people build. So
on the one hand you can imagine one part
of the family tree are what we call
explicit density um methods. These are
ones where the model actually does you
know the whole thing is we're trying to
model P of X or P of X given Y. Um and
with these explicit density methods you
can actually compute you can get that
value out P of X for any sample X. Um
and the counter the counterpoint are
implicit density methods. These are ones
where you can't actually get that
probability mass value. you can't
actually get that density value P of X
out from the model, but you can somehow
sample from that probability probability
distribution. So the difference here um
is that in an implicit model, right, you
can't actually access the the the value
of the density function, but you can
sample from the underlying density
function somehow. So the model has
implicitly learned to model the density
even if you can't get the value out. Um
and on the explicit density side, um
it's almost the almost the opposite
where in many cases even when you like
you can get that explic that explicit
density value out but then sampling
tends to be more complicated sometimes
with these explicit density methods. Not
always but sometimes, right? And the
reason why you might turn to implicit
models is because in many cases you may
not actually care about knowing what
exactly was the density value for any
input. you maybe all you care about is
generating samples and get generating
good samples get generate generating a
good diversity of samples. So if the
thing you really care about is sampling
then maybe you don't actually need to
explicitly be able to see the value of
the density for any for any for any
input. Um and then things break down and
cascade and get more fractal-like from
here. So inside explicit density methods
um there's ones where like actually yeah
you can really compute the real P of X
that's being modeled. Um and auto
reggressive models are one example of
that. um or another version of explicit
density methods are ones where you can
get a density value out but it's not the
real one. It's some kind of
approximation to the true density um of
the data. Um and variational
autoenccoders are one example of an
explicit but approximate um generative
method that we'll see. Now on the other
branch of the family tree um we can
think about direct methods for implicit
density. These are ones where maybe it
requires a single network evaluation to
just draw a sample from the underlying
from the underlying distribution that's
being modeled. Um, and a generative
adversarial network is an example of a
generative model in this part of the
family tree. Um, and the other part is
um, I don't know if it has a good name.
Um, I I called it indirect, but this is
a name I made up yesterday. So, please
feel free to correct me if there's a
better term for this. Um but these in
indirect ones are ones where you can
sample from the underlying um from the
underlying density P of X that's being
modeled. But it requires some kind of
iterative procedure. There's no feed
forward function that where you can
input and get the sample directly out.
There's some kind of iterative method
that you need to run in order to draw a
sample from the underlying density
that's being modeled. Um and diffusion
models are an example of this that we'll
see next time. I told you a couple
slides ago that people are sloppy with
notation and drop the Y. And I did that
explicitly on purpose on this slide so
that someone would ask me that question
and you would always be attentive to
that fact. Um so yes exactly every time
I've written P of X on this slide and
actually all the rest of the slides this
lecture I also have been lazy and
dropped the Y but you should always
imagine an additional condition on Y um
in all of these P of X's that you see
for the rest of the lecture. So thank
you for asking that. So the question was
like is the is the indirect method is it
still you know can you just treat that
indirect iterative procedure as a
blackbox and then treat that as as a
direct sampling method. Um in principle
yes but in practice no because your
samples kind of end up end up
approximate um you know depending on
exactly the method but like with with
diffusion models you kind of would need
to take an infinite number of steps in
order to draw a true sample so instead
we approximate that with a finite number
of steps and that's you know true of
other methods as well diffusion models
are the most common for this today um
but you know some kind of marov chain
method or MCMC method in years past
might have also had this property where
there is an iterative procedure but if
you want to draw an exact sample from
the distribution that's being modeled,
you need an infinite number of steps to
converge. Um, so we always approximate
that and by taking a finite number of
steps.
Okay. And I was I was pretty I was
pretty proud of this tonomy because it's
very symmetric. There's, you know, it's
a it's a there's there's four leaves,
there's two branches, and we're going to
cover half the tree today and half the
tree next time. Um, so I thought that
was a pretty nice uh pretty nice
breakdown. question is what's the
difference between the approximate
density and directly sampling from an
implicit p of x? The difference is that
even in an in an indirect but implicit
method there's no density value anywhere
to be found. You can't compute one at
all. Um but you can still iteratively
sample in some way. Um with an
approximate density method um you can
still get a value out like you can
actually get a density value out that's
going to be some approximate or bound to
the true p of x.
Okay. So then the first such auto the
first such generative model that we'll
actually talk about in a little bit more
concrete specificity are auto
reggressive models. Um so autogressive
models we're actually going to take a
slight detour and talk about an a really
general idea behind all of generative
modeling and that's the idea of maximum
likelihood estimation. Um and maximum
likelihood estimation is actually a
quite general procedure that we can use
to fit probabilistic models given a
finite set of samples. Um so the idea is
we're going to write down some explicit
function for the density. um we said
that in that that um some methods are
going to explicitly model the density.
Well, let's do it with a neural network.
Let's write a neural network that's
going to input the data x um input the
weights w of the neural network and it's
going to spit out a number that's going
to tell us what is the density. Um so
then you know we're going to train the
data we're going to given a data set of
samples x1 x2 xn we're going to train
the model via this this objective
function. We want to find the weights
that give rise that make the data set
most likely right where we want to set
because as we vary the weights it's
going to vary the kind of densities that
are being modeled by the network. So we
want the network to select the density
that maximizes the likelihood of the
data. Um note that we said likelihood
rather than probability. Um that's a
deep philosophical rabbit hole you can
fall into. Um the difference is what
we're varying. Right? If you think about
probability, you kind of imagine you
that the density is fixed and we're sort
of sliding X around and changing what is
the probability of X under a fixed
distribution. When you talk about
likelihood, instead you're often fixing
the samples X and you're varying the
distribution itself. Um and saying, you
know, what is the how does the prob how
does the probability density of those
samples change as we vary different
distributions. So you have to think
about very carefully in these equations
what's being fixed and what's varying.
So in this process of maximum likelihood
estimation, what we're doing is varying
the distribution that the model that the
that the neural network is modeling to
try to maximize the probability of the
fixed set of samples we have of from
that distribution in our training set.
Right? And I guess the the unsaid thing
behind all of this is that we assume
that there is some underlying true
probability distribution P data which
was used by the universe to generate the
data that we are seeing. Um and in some
sense always what we want to do is try
to model that true underlying unknown
distribution P data and we can never
access P data because we don't know we
don't have this omnisient view of like
exactly how the universe works. um but
instead we get some samples from P data
that the universe has given to us and
what we're trying to do through our
learning procedure is uncover that
unknown distribution P data um given a
finite number of samples from that
unknown distribution right so one
procedure that you can go about this is
like well let's select the distribution
that makes the data that I saw actually
most likely um and that's the objective
that's that's the maximum likelihood
objective function
right and then a standard trick that we
do here right we assume that the data
was iid um independent and identically
distributed. So we assume that each one
of those X's was drawn from that true P
data distribution. And now we want to
maximize the joint distribution of all
the data that we saw. But because it's
independent, we can factor it down um
into independent probab like independent
likelihood of each of the independent
samples. Um and then the common trick
that we always use is the log trick. So
we know that log is a monotonic
function. So if you maximize something,
it's equivalent to maximizing the log of
that something because log is a
monotonic function. Um, and then log is
also very convenient because it swaps
sums and products. So it's common to
just instead of maximizing the the the
pro the the the likelihood of the data,
instead we're going to maximize the log
likelihood of the data. And that's the
same as maximizing the likelihood. And
once we apply the log, then that that um
that product splits into a sum and sums
are easier to handle. Um and now you
know we slot in our neural network um
because our neural network is now maybe
directly outputting the density. So this
gives a direct objective function that
we could use to train a neural network.
Um give it to you know this gives it a
very concrete loss function that we can
use to train a neural network to solve
this kind of generative modeling
problem. Um but we need a little bit
more structure here to actually make
progress. Um so this this is where so
this this idea of maximum likelihood
estimation is very general. It doesn't
really assume anything about the kind of
data. Um it doesn't really assume any
structure in the data. Um and we in in
general need to put a little bit more
structure on this to make some progress.
Um, so auto reggressive models basically
make the assumption that there is some
canonical way that we can take our data
X and split each ind each data sample X
into some sequence of subp parts. Um,
X1, X2, XT. Um, you got to be careful
with indices here. Here I said the subp
parts these are subp parts of a single
sample. Um, so I use a subscript and the
previous slide we had superscript to
indicate different samples um, x1 to xn.
So be careful with that. you know, sub
superscript on this slide is different
samples X. Subscript on this slide means
different parts of the same sample. Um,
so we assume that there's some canonical
way to break up our our data sample X
into some sequence of subp parts. Um,
and now we can apply the chain rule of
probability. So um, probability of X is
just the joint probability probability
of all of those subp parts X1 to XT. Um,
and then given any probability
distribution, you can always break it
apart into this chain rule. Um that
probability of the joint distribution of
all these variables is equal to
probability of the first one um times
probability of the first given
conditioned on the first probability of
the second condition on the first times
probability of the third conditioned on
the first and the second etc etc etc
right and this is this is the chain rule
of probability this requires no
assumptions this is always true of any
kind of um joint distribution of of
random variables
um and then this this sort of gives us
our our objective function or then then
like then you could basically train a
neural network that's going to input,
you know, the po the the the previous
part of the sequence and then try to
give us a probability distribution over
the next part of the sequence. Does that
sound familiar? Does that sound like
something we've done before? RNN's. Yes.
So that's exactly what an RNN is doing,
right? And RNN has this very natural
structure that you know by passing
hidden states along forward through
time, um the hidden state always depends
on the beginning of the sequence up to
the current point. Um so then with
there's a very natural way to use RNN's
to for auto reggressive modeling. Um so
you're you have your sequence of hidden
states that are basically summarizing
your your sequence and then from each
hidden state you predict probability of
the next piece of the sequence. Um
condition on the rest condition on all
earlier parts of the sequence um and
that basically is an RNN language model
that we saw some lectures ago. Have we
seen anything else that can do this?
Yes, transformers. Um and particularly
mask transformers, right? So we talked
in the transformers lecture um
transformers can also be used to have
this this structure where by masking out
the attention matrix in the right way we
can make each output of the transformer
depend on only the prefix of the
sequence. So we can also use
transformers for autogressive um
autogressive modeling and this and
they're very commonly used for this.
Okay, so this is um but the problem with
autogressive modeling is that you need
to break your data up into a sequence
and this is very very natural with um
with text data, right? Because text data
is naturally a 1D sequence. Um and it's
even a 1D sequence of discrete things
which is great because it's very easy to
model probabilities of discrete things.
Um we've been doing that all semester um
with our favorite cross entropy softmax
loss, right? The cross entropy softmax
loss is always, you know, distribution
over discrete like fixed discrete number
of categories. um the network predicts a
score for each one of those. Normalize
it with a softmax, train with a cross
entropy loss. We know how to do that. Um
so that's that's why these things fit
very naturally for language models. Um
because language is already discrete. Um
language is already a 1D sequence. Um so
there's a little bit of fuzziness and
how you know there's a tokenizer in
there. We're not going to get into that.
Um but these are very naturally well
suited to language problems because
language is already 1D. It's already
discreet. Um images are more tricky
because images are not naturally 1D. Um,
images are also not naturally discreet.
We often think of images as continuous
real valued things. Um, so this is they
don't these don't naturally fit quite as
nicely onto images. Um, but you know,
you got a hammer, you're going to whack
some nails. So, um, people definitely
apply autogressive models to images in
kind of a naive way. Um, at least at
least some years ago. So one thing you
can do one one one thing you can do to
um model images with autogressive models
is to treat the images it treat an image
as a sequence of pixels right and in
particular each pixel is actually just
three numbers um and you know in most
displays and in most representations
most representations of images those
numbers are actually discreet right so
most JPEGs or PGs most of the file
formats we use to store images um are
typically 8 bit per channel so there's
actually you know only a fixed number of
values that each pixel can take. So a
pixel is just three um three single bite
values. A single bite is just like an
integer from 0 to 255. So a pixel is
just three integers each of each integer
can be 0 to 255. So what we can do is um
take our image and then rasterize it out
into a long um into a long sequence
where each element of the sequence is
one of the sub pixels values of our
image. Um, and now we've turned our
image into a discrete into a into a
one-dimensional sequence where each
entry in that sequence is a discrete
value. So you can apply autogressive
modeling directly to that sequence um in
exactly the way that you might have for
a language model um using an RNN or a
transformer.
Um can anyone spot a problem with this
approach? Too long. Very expensive. Very
very expensive. Um so you know a kind of
reasonable image that you might want to
model is maybe 1024 by 1020 1024. Um,
that's not even that high resolution
really, but that's a pretty good
resolution. But if you have 1020 1024 x
1024 image, that's going to be a
sequence of 3 million sub pixels. Um,
you know, people actually can model
these days sequences in the millions,
but it gets very very expensive. Um,
there's got to be a more efficient way
to do this. Um, so there were some
papers a couple years ago where people
applied these sort of autogressive
models directly to pixels of images. Um,
but they were not super successful, I
think, because they they're very
difficult to scale to high resolution.
So a spoiler alert that we'll talk a
little bit more in next lecture is that
this actually has made a resurgence in
the last couple of years. Um but the
trick is to not model the individual
pixels in the sequence um as individual
pixel values but instead to use some
other kind of process or procedure or
model neural network maybe to break that
image into a sequence of one-dimensional
tokens. Um so that's something we'll
talk about a bit more next lecture. Um
but this at least gives you the sense of
what is an auto reagive model. Um what's
the probabilistic formulation of them?
How do you apply them to language? how
do you apply them to images? So then
from auto reggressive models we next
turn to variational autoenccoders um and
variational autoenccoders are pretty
fun.
So we talked about you know we in in um
in these autogressive models we talked
about you know we're trying to do
maximum likelihood. We broke up our data
into a sequence of parts. We're trying
to maximize the likelihood of the data.
Um and variational autoenccoders are
going to do something a little bit
different. um instead we're there's
still going to be an explicit method.
There's still going to be some kind of
density that we can compute. Um but
there it's going to be intractable.
We're going to be able to approximate
it. Um why are we going to do that? We
had a perfectly good method that
computed densities exactly. Um and what
we're going to give up for that is we're
going to gain something. Um we're going
to gain the ability to compute
reasonable latent vectors over our data.
We're going to have you know vectors
that represent our data that come out
that pop out naturally from the learning
process. And those vectors are going to
be useful in their own right. And the
ability to get access to those latent
vectors is going to be useful enough to
us that we're willing to give up
computing exact densities and instead
settle for these approximate densities
that are actual actually lower bounds on
the true density. Oh, the the motivation
for breaking stuff up in a sequence in
autogressive models um because it
factors the problem. It makes each part
each part easier to model, right? So
imagine, you know, imagine you're doing
language modeling, right? Um and you
have a vocabulary of Vword um and I want
to model the probability of two words
jointly, right? How many possible
two-word sequences are there? There's V^
squ. Um how many possible three-word
sequences are there? There's V cubed. Um
then in general, if you have like how
many T word sequences with a vocabulary
of V are there? It's um V to the T,
right? So that's bad. It grows
exponentially. If you wanted to directly
model the joint distribution of a
sequence of T things, the number of
entries in that discrete probability
distribution you need to model is going
to grow exponentially with the sequence
length. um and that's quickly going to
become completely intractable if we if
we want to go to long sequences. So then
the reason we break that up is so that
we don't have to model it all at once.
We factor it in this way and predict
only one part condition on the previous
parts. Good question. Can we apply the
log trick to mitigate that? Yeah,
exactly. So in practice like you'll
never actually see these these real
these like probability density values
modeled. Um almost always you're going
to work in log probabilities instead. Um
so the model that outputs um the model
is going to output log probabilities.
You're going to compute your loss in log
space. like for numeric stability you're
almost going to compute everything in
log space in practice. So then the p of
x is being generated because at the
output at the at the top of the
transformer it's outputting a
probability distribution over the next
token condition on all the previous
tokens and it does that for every point
in the sequence. So you could actually
recover this exact probability density
value um by multiplying out the the
values at all points in the sequence. So
if I have an input sequence, I pass it
to the transformer. The transformer will
have predicted at every point in the
sequence what is the probability, what
is the distribution over all the tokens
conditioned on the on the earlier part
of the sequence. Um and I can compute
what was the actual next token, what was
the predicted probability of the next
token, and then multiply all of those
across the entire sequence. So that's
how we can recover the exact density
value out of one of these autogressive
models. And that actually would apply
either to an RNN or a transformer.
Okay. Um good questions. So then in a
variational autoenccoder um things get
hairy. So we're actually going to drop
the V and talk about autoenccoders for
just a couple slides because I don't
think we've done that yet this this uh
this course. So in a non-variational
autoenccoder this is basically going to
be an unsupervised method for learning
to extract features Z from inputs X
without labels. Um and this actually you
know is kind of a ver kind of you know
in this vein of self-supervised learning
that we just talked about. Um, and our
notion is that the features ought to
extract useful information about the
data, right? Maybe they somehow
implicitly encode what is the what what
is the identity of objects in the image,
how many of them there are, what are the
colors of them. We want this feature
vector Z to contain useful information
about about the input X. Um, and this
encoder itself could be a neural network
of any architecture. It could be an MLP,
transformer, CNN, whatever you want. Um,
but it inputs our data X and then it's
going to output some vector Z. And then
the question is how do we learn this
without without labels. Um we actually
saw a lot of examples of this in the
previous lecture. Um but there's a very
simple one which is just try to
reconstruct the input. Um so we're going
to now have a second part of the model
called the decoder which is going to
input the Z and then output back an X.
Um and we want Oh, and I dropped the X.
Um and and we're going to train this
thing to so that the output from the
model should actually match the input.
Um this is the in some sense the
stupidest loss function ever. We're just
training the model to mimic the identity
function. Um why do we do that? we
already know the identity function. Why
are we expending a lot of flops and
training a neural network on a big data
set to just learn the identity function
that we already know? Um it's because
we're going to bottleneck it in some
way. Um if this model had infinite
capacity, for example, if that Z vector
was very wide, if there were no
constraints on the learning, um I would
expect a neural network to just nail
this problem. Um but we don't want to do
that because we explicitly don't care
about learning this objective. We
already know the identity function. We
don't need an expensive neural network
to compute it. What we want to do is
force the network to try to learn the
identity function under some constraint.
And the constraint that you often use in
a in a traditional autoenccoder is by
bottlenecking that representation Z. In
particular, that means that that vector
Z in the middle is going to be much much
smaller than the input X. So your input
X might be a high resolution image,
maybe like a 1024x 1024 image that we
said is composed of 3 million floats,
but then that Z might be like 128
dimensional latent code. So the model is
now asked to solve this problem where I
want to reconstruct the output,
reconstruct the data X, but squash it
through this layer, this like
bottlenecking representation in the
middle. And we hope that this is going
to force the model to learn some
non-trivial structure about the about
the data by squashing it through this
this representation in the middle of the
network. Um, and then after we do this,
we can apply our normal self-supervised
learning trick where, you know, you
could throw away the decoder um, and
then use this Z to initialize some
supervised model for some downstream
task. the same story as in the supervis
the the self-supervised story that we
just saw. Um, but what about what if we
want actually want to use this to
generate data? Um, then what we'd really
like to do is somehow the opposite of
the self-supervised story. What we'd
really like to do is throw away the
encoder and instead be able to somehow
sample Z's that match the kinds of Z's
that the model learned to represent data
as. And if we had some procedure for
sampling Z's that matched the data
distribution in some way, then we could
sample a Z, pass it through our learned
decoder, and now generate a new sample,
right? And now this is an implicit
method, right? You said that there's no
there's no densities floating around
anywhere. But if we had a way to do
this, it would be a way to draw samples
from the model um without explicitly
modeling the density in any way.
But the problem is that, you know, we've
just kind of kicked the can down the
road here a little bit because we said
we wanted we want if we want to generate
images, we want to generate X's, we have
a data set of X's. How do we do that? We
said we're going to solve that by
training this autoenccoder and now we
have a data set of Z's and we need to
sample in Zpace. It's it's not any
easier. So it kind of kind of we're kind
of stuck. Um and the idea of variational
autoenccoders is you know what if we
could force some structure on the Z's.
Um if you have this traditional
auto-enccoder structure all you're
you're not forcing the model to impose
any known structure on the Z's. You're
just asking it to reconstruct the data
um given its latent representation. But
what if we had some mechanism to force
the Z's to come from a gausian
distribution or some other known
distribution. If that were the case then
we could just draw a sample at inference
time after this model is trained. Draw a
sample from that known distribution pass
it through the pass it through the
decoder and now we would have our have
our sample. So forcing these
auto-enccoders to be probabilistic and
to enforce a probabilistic structure on
that latent space exactly is what a
variational autoenccoder tries to do.
Why variational? Um it's a long story.
Um it says has a long history in a long
term lot of history around that
terminology in the literature. Um but
basically variational autoenccoders are
a probabilistic spin on our traditional
autoenccoder. Um, so it's going to learn
latent features Z from raw data and then
we'll be able to enforce a structure on
that learned latent space Z such that we
can sample from it at inference time
after the model is trained and generate
new samples.
So in more more more concretely we'll
assume that our training data X I again
note here the superscript I means these
are different independent samples of of
X. um we assume that um each x i was
generated from some underlying latent
val latent vector uh z that there's some
zi that's lurking under the surface
associated with every x i and in the
universe's procedure for generating data
first it generated the zi then it
generated the xi from the zi um and all
everything that the universe needed to
know in order to generate the image that
we seed that we saw was contained in
that latent vector z but we can't see
those latent vectors z we can never
observe them. We don't have a data set
of them, right? So the intuition is that
X is an image. Z is some kind of latent
feature representation that tells you
everything you would ever need to know
about that image, but you can never
observe that latent vector. Um, and then
after training, we could generate a
sample by uh, oh, and the other
constraint is that we're going to force
those Z's to come from a known
distribution. So then after the model is
trained, then we can do exactly what we
just said. Draw a Z from that known
distribution, pass through the decoder.
That's going to give us a sample. Um,
and then we'll typically assume a simple
prior. Um, almost always a unit gausian
distribution is the most is by far the
most common. So then how do we possibly
train this? Like this feels like an
impossible problem. Um, we want to
basically train this network that's
going to, you know, get these Z's, find
a Z for every X. We can never observe
the Z's. This seems impossible. What are
we going to do? Um, we're going to go
back to maximum likelihood, right? If we
indeed had a data set of X's and Z's,
then we could use maximum likelihood to
directly use the same kind of log trick
um maximize the log probability. We
could use the exact same thing that we
previously saw. Um and then train a
conditional generative model P of X
conditioned on Z, but we don't know Z.
But let's pretend we do for a moment. Um
so but if but because we don't know Z,
we could try to marginalize, right? we
know that p of x is equal to like maybe
there's some joint distribution of x and
z um that must exist even though we
can't observe it. Um and then in
principle you could integrate out the z
to marginalize over it to get a p of x.
Um and then maybe we could do like
pretend there's a joint distribution x
and z marginalize out the z somehow and
still do maximum likelihood. Um you know
maybe let's see how this works. So this
term in and and then here we've also
used the chain rule to break up that P
of X given Z into that that joint
probability P of X and Z into P of X
given Z and just P of Z. So um this P of
X given Z that's okay. Um we could
compute that with our with our decoder
here on the left. That's a neural
network that we're hoping to train. Um
this P of Z term is okay. We're going to
assume that that's a unit gausian or
some other simple distribution that we
can compute or reason about. Um but this
integral kills us, right? In in general,
we have no feasible way to integrate
over the full space of a neural
network's input. Right? This um this p
of x given z is going to be some very
complicated function that's modeled by a
neural network. There's no going to be
no way that we can analytically or or
exactly integrate this. You can train
neural networks for individual parts
here. Right? So the whole underlying
notion here whenever you're doing this
probabistic modeling is like we're going
to write down some probabilistic terms.
Um hopefully some of them are going to
be simple distributions that we can
write down analytically and reason
about. um some of them are going to be
learned neural network components. So
we're kind of assuming that probability
of X given Z is going to be some neural
network that we could that we could in
principle learn via maximum likelihood.
Um but we don't we but we're trying to
write down what objective could we use
to learn that neural network via maximum
likelihood. Um and we're out of luck
here because you can't you have no way
to integrate over Z. Um you could try to
approximate that integral via some like
finite sampling. Um, but in general
that's probably not going to work very
well because this Z is a super high
dimensional space and trying to like do
a do an approx do doing a an approximate
numerical integral in the inner loop of
your training is not going to be very a
very good idea. Um, so we could try
something else. Uh, baze rule. That's
the other thing we always do in
probability. So let's try basu. Um, if
we have basu we have another formula
that we can use to write down p of x,
right? So p of x we can write down in
baze rule. Um, using using baze rule in
this equation on the screen. Um let's
see what we can do with these terms. So
this one okay P of X given Z again we
can compute that with our decoder. P of
Z again okay this one's um we assume
this is Gausian so we can compute
something with it. Um there's no
integrals here that's good. So we're
we're in good shape. Uh but now we're
out of luck. This P of Z given X term um
this posterior of Z given X. Uh we have
no good way to compute this. Um in order
to compute this term you would also need
some kind of integral. Out of luck we
can't compute it. What are we going to
do? Okay, let's use another neural
network. So the variational autoenccoder
trick is like let's there's that
trolistic term on the bottom here, a b
rule that we can't compute. Um let's
just slot in another neural network to
try to comput it for us. Um so we're
going to have another neural network Q
with different weights um phi that's
going to learn a different conditional
distribution prob probability of z given
x. And the whole thing is we want this
other neural network to try to
approximate the the true P of X given Z
of the first neural network. And you
can't really enforce this in general,
but you know, let's put a neural network
there and see what we can do.
So then if we could somehow have this
other neural network that was
approximating this term on the bottom
that we can't compute. Um then we could
go and compute our our likelihood and
max and do maximum likelihood and we
would all be all be set. Um so that's
kind of what we do when training a
variational autoenccoder. We're
basically going to jointly learn two
different neural networks. One is the
decoder which inputs the latent code Z
and outputs a distribution over the data
X. Um the other is an encoder which is
going to input the data X and output a
distribution over the latent codes Z.
And each of these are going to be
separate neural networks that are
separately trained with their own
independent weights. There's a question
you might have which is um how can you
possibly output a probability
distribution from a neural network? That
seems confusing and hard and unclear.
Um, so the trick here is we're going to
actually force everything to be a normal
distribution. Um, and we're going to
have the neural network output the
parameters of the normal distribution.
So typically for the decoder network,
we're going to assume that we're going
to the output distribution from the
decoder is going to be um diagonal
gausian where the where the entries in
the diagonal are the pixels of the
neural network. Um, and the model is
going to output the mean of that
diagonal gausian distribution. And
typically for the decoder we'd assume a
fixed um a fixed uh variance or or
standard deviation sigma squared. Um now
for the encoder network um similar same
idea the model's going to input the data
sample x and then it's going to output
the parameters of a gausian distribution
that model the distribution uh q of z
given x. Um so in this case the de the
encoder network will output one vector
which is the the mean of that gausian
distribution and another vector which is
the diagonal of the coariance of that ve
of that of that gausian distribution. Um
and here it's very important that we
assume the diagonal structure because
otherwise we would have to model you
know h squ kind of entries in that full
coariance matrix right. So here right
you have a you imagine an image that's h
by w p p p p p p p p p p p p p p p p p p
p pixels. Um so that means that the
entries in your diagonal matrix are like
the right the full you could in
principle model the co the full
coariance across every pair of pixels in
the image but that would require h squ
w^ squ entries that would be too big um
so instead we'll just ignore any kind of
correlation structure among the the the
different values um and now that means
that the diagonal coariance is now a
vector that's the same size as the data
itself right so that means this mu of z
given x and this sigma of z given x are
both vectors of the same shape as z um
so we basically treat the neural have
the neural network output two vectors of
the same shape and then treat them as
the parameters of this gausian
distribution. So that's how we can
output a distribution from a neural
network. If you do maximum likelihood on
this uh thing with a fixed standard
deviation, it actually becomes
equivalent to L2. Um and that's a nice
trick. Um, and the reason you want to do
that is because trying to model the
diagonal, like if you want, like you
could in principle try to model the same
thing on the decoder and try to model
the individual like a separate variance
of every pixel, but that would be kind
of useless. Um, because that would be
like if you're not modeling any coarian
structure among the pixels, that would
basically be saying that each pixel is
allowed to like vary a little bit. Um,
and the amount that each pixel is
allowed to vary kind of depends on the
pixel. and then sampling from that
distribution would basically amount to
um fixing the mean and then adding per
pixel independent noise that's scaled by
the per pixel variances and that would
not be a sensible thing to do. Um so in
general like for the decoder you kind of
you kind of cheat a little bit um and in
you kind of pretend it's outputting a
probability distribution but in general
we're never going to sample from that
distribution. Instead we're always going
to output the mean. Does that make
sense? Yeah. And then it turns out like
if you write this down like the that
that that constant sigma square just
comes off as a constant in the front. Um
and in practice all like maximizing the
log likelihood of a gausian distribution
with a fixed with a fixed variance along
the diagonal um is equivalent to
minimizing L2 distance between the mean
and the X which is kind of nice. Yeah,
good question. Is there some kind of
like weird invariance or non-invarian
structure here with the pixel shifting?
Um that would be that would be more a
property of the architecture that you
would choose to build the neural
network. Um, so you could try to build
into your network architecture that's
predicting these, you could try to build
some invariance or um or equariance
properties into the architecture. Um,
but yeah, you're right that in general
that's not accounted for at the at the
loss level here.
Okay, so now we've got this idea. We've
got an encoder, a decoder, they're both
one is inputting X, outputting a
distribution over Z. Other is inputting
Z, inputting a distribution over X.
What's our training objective? Um, and
here's the one slide where we're going
to do some math. Um but we'll see. So
here we're gonna we basically the idea
is we want to do um maximum likelihood.
That's usually the the single thing that
we want. That's like the the guiding
principle behind a lot of objectives in
generative modeling. Um so we want to
maximize log P of log P of X and then we
can use B rule to write that as log P of
this B rule expression. All right, this
is this is an exact equivalence. Um now
we're going to do something silly. We're
going to multiply the top and bottom of
this by our Q of Z given X. Remember, we
just introduced another neural network Q
out of nowhere that was in that was
modeling this other distribution Q of Z
given X. And now we're going to multiply
that density term on the top and bottom
of this uh of this base rule expression.
Now we're going to do some logarithm. Um
and if you're, you know, have some
foresight actually, you know, you'll
you'll you'll for some reason decide to
rearrange these terms in this particular
order. Um and I've colorcoded them so
you can later go and track which term
went where. Um but we do some logarithms
and ar and like break this up into three
separate terms. Um now you need to make
another magical observation which is
that this p of x um actually does not
depend on z right like so far this this
sequence of three terms this is all an
exact equivalence. Um these are all
exact equalities. So even though there's
a z in this expression um it actually
doesn't depend on z because all the z's
would cancel out. Um and if you have
something that doesn't depend on Z, you
can always wrap an expectation um over Z
of that thing. So in this case, we know
that this is a P of X, we can we can
always feel free to wrap an expectation
of Z sampled according to any
distribution that we want um of P of X.
Um and because that internal thing does
not depend on Z, this is always true for
any for any uh for any distribution that
we might choose to to take this
expectation over. Okay. So then because
because expectation is a linear thing um
we can apply that expectation to each of
these three terms upstairs. Um and now
we have these three terms um each of
which looks very mysterious. Um but if
you if you kind of you had a lot of
intuition about probability you memorize
all these formulas that you may have
seen in an earlier statistics or probab
probability course um maybe you could
learn to recognize some of these. So
this first one um we're going to carry
down as it was before and these second
two are actually kale divergence um are
actually kale divergence terms. So the
kale divergence is a kind of measure of
dissimilarity between probability
distributions and it just so happens to
have this exact definition of these
these latter two terms. So we can
rewrite this exactly as this first term
which is this expectation blah blah blah
we'll talk about it. Um and then plus
then plus these two other KL terms. Um,
so these two KL terms are basically
measuring dissimilarity but or or
measuring discrepancy or dissimilarity
between these different kinds of
probability distributions that we have
floating around on this slide. Um, and
now these all look kind of crazy. Um,
but if we stare at each of these terms,
we can actually recover a like
interpretable structure like an
interpretable meaning for each of these
three terms. Um, this first one is
actually a data reconstruction term. If
we walk through what this is saying,
this is saying that we're going to
sample a Z. And the way we're going to
sample the Z is by Q of Z given Q of Z
given X which is our encoder. So we're
going to take our X pass it to the
encoder. The encoder is going to predict
a distribution Q of Z given X. Then from
that predicted distribution we're going
to sample a Z. Then we're going to take
an expectation over all such Z and
maximize the log probability of X given
Z. So this is basically a data
reconstruction term. It's saying that if
we take an X, a data point X, run it
through the encoder to get a
distribution over Z, and then pass any
sample of that distrib of that predicted
distribution over Z into the decoder,
we're going to recover X. So this is a
kind of data reconstruction term. The
middle one is a prior term. This is
saying we want to um this is the
measuring the KL divergence between Q of
Z given X and P of Z. So remember Q of Z
given X this is the encoder is inputting
the data X and outputting a distribution
over the latent space Z. Um so this is
the predicted distribution over the
latent space of the encoder and this
other term P of Z this is the prior this
is the prior that we assumed for the
latent space usually diagonal gausian.
So this term is basically saying um the
model is separately predicting is sort
of predicting distributions of Z given X
and we want those predicted
distributions to match the simple
Gausian prior that we had previously set
um that we' previously chosen. So this
is just measuring how much does that
latent space that's learned by our model
match the prior and this third term gets
us in trouble. So this third term is um
Q of Z given X. So that's the predicted
distribution over Z given the input data
X to the encoder. Um, and how much does
that match P of Z given X. So that's
this uh this flipped around distribution
of what the decoder is modeling. And
this one we're out of luck. We cannot
compute this term cuz remember what got
us into trouble in the first place was
this P of Z given X. The whole reason we
introduced Q was to was because we
couldn't intro we could not compute this
P this P of Z given X. Um, so now what
do we do? We're going to throw it away
because we know that kale divergences
are always greater than equal to zero.
So we know that this last term because
it's a kale divergence of two
distributions even though we cannot
compute those distributions in general,
we know that it must be greater than
zero because that's a that's a
well-known property of kale divergences.
So we can throw it away um and get a
lower bound to the true probability. So
if we throw away that last term then we
know that log p of x um is greater than
or equal to those two terms our
reconstruction term and our prior term.
So this will be the loss that we use to
train our our variational autoenccoder.
Um and the idea is that this is an
approximation to the true log
likelihood. This is this is a lower
bound to the log likelihood. So if we
maximize the lower bound hopefully that
will also maximize the true log
likelihood even though we're not doing
it exactly. So that's our training
objective for variational autoenccoders.
So that's kind of the summary. Um, you
know, you're going to jointly and trade,
you're going to jointly train an encoder
Q and a decoder P to maximize this
variational lower what's what's called a
variational lower bound on the true data
log likelihood. Um, and this is also
sometimes called the evidence lower
bound or elbow. So it's just the elbow
when we're going to maximize the elbow.
Um, and it has this particular term. We
have these encoder network, this decoder
network. Um, that's what we do. So then,
you know, to kind of walk through what
the training procedure looks like more
explicitly, we're going to have this
neural network in we're going to have
this neural network encoder inputs the X
outputs the distribution over Z. Um then
we're then we're going to apply this KL
term to the predicted distribution. Um
and in particular because this this is
going to force the predicted
distribution to be unit gausian. So it's
basically going to force it's going to
encourage the predicted mean to be zero
and the predicted sigma to be diagonal
ones to be all ones. Then once we get to
those predicted distribution from the
encoder, we're going to sample from that
predicted distribution using this
so-called reparameterization trick that
allows allows you to back prop through
this. Then we draw a sample Z from the
predicted distribution. Once you get the
predicted distrib this sample Z, you run
it through your decoder to get your um
to get your normal distribution
predicted by the decoder and then you
apply your reconstruction your
reconstruction term of the loss to the
output of the decoder. So even though
this looked like a large scary slides of
math, it actually led to like not too
crazy of a training objective for this
uh for this thing. Um and I think this
variational autoenccoder is actually
very interesting because these two
losses fight against each other in a
very interesting way. So the reconstruct
because we're basically forcing the
model to bottleneck through this um
through this latent space Z and these
two terms kind of want different things
from the latent space. So the
reconstruction loss um kind of wants the
sigma to be zero and the mux to be a
different and unique vector for each uh
for each data x. Um because if that were
the case then we could perfectly satisfy
the reconstruction objective. We would
have a separate a separate separate
unique vector for every data point. Um
and there would be no probability in
there. We could perfectly reconstruct
everything. So that's kind of what the
reconstruction loss wants. But the prior
loss actually wants the sigas to be all
one because it wants it wants it to be
unit gausian and it wants all the mues
to be zero. Um which is very different
what the two losses want. So in the
process of training a VAE, you're asking
these two losses to fight against each
other to try to find some equilibrium
between um reconstructing your data well
and forcing your latent space to be
close to your prior. And then once
you've trained it, then you can sample Z
from your prior, run through the decoder
and get a sample. Um, another nice thing
is that because your latent space was
diagonal gausian, there's also a notion
of of um uh uh statistical independence
across the different the different
entries in your latent space Z. So you
can vary them separately. Um and maybe
those separate dimensions often encode
something useful or interpretable or
orthogonal about your data. So in this
case we took a VAE trained it on a data
set of handwritten digits and you kind
of see that as we vary two dimensions of
the latent space the the digits kind of
smoothly morph from one kind of category
into another and this is a pretty common
property of VAEs. So that's basically it
for today. Um to kind of recap what we
talked about we talked about supervised
versus unsupervised learning. We t
talked about these three different
flavors of generative modeling. Um and
then we talked about one branch of this
family tree of generative models. Um so
then next time we're going to uh come
back and talk about the other half of
the family tree of generative models in
particular talking about generative
adversarial networks and diffusion
models.