You're in the right room. This is the
right title slide. A tale of two
kittens.
I want to share a story that gave me a
lot of inspiration during my own PhD
time. In 1963,
two scientists held and hine they did an
ingenious experiment. So what they did
is they put two newborn kittens in this
uh device that looks like a merrygo
round. And these two kittens have not
yet seen the visual world and it's just
kind of their first moments in the
world. So what happens is the active
kitten on the right hand side it can
move freely while the passive kitten is
constrained to this basket while the
motion is transmitted over this little
hinge between the active and the passive
kitten.
And the difference is the active kitten
can move around freely and observe the
world while the passive kitten can also
see the world but it does not control
the body. It cannot control its own
motion. And then after a few days, the
scientists test the kitten's visual
system and they found that only the
active kitten developed a healthy visual
motor loop and the passive kitten was
not able to respond to things like
visual cliff or um you know avoiding
obstacles.
And note that both kittens experience
the exact same visual sequences, right?
The data is same and mirrored but the
only difference is the agency that the
kittens too
and these days we have a very powerful
passive kitten and his name is ChBT
but for us humans when human babies were
born we don't go to Wikipedia and read
terabytes of text from the internet we
play with objects we touch them taste
them break them we experiment we fail we
try something new again. So people call
babies scientists in the crib
and embodiment and active agency are
what make us human. So I believe the
future belongs to embodied AI here.
And today let's talk about Nvidia's big
plan on building embodied AGI
project group. And my name is Jim Fan. I
am leading the gear group which stands
for journalist embodied agent research.
So in March this year this is uh a scene
from GTC and video's biggest annual
conference and here on stage we have 10
humanoids. Nine of them are electric or
mechanical and there's one biological
humanoid in the middle and his name is
Jensen.
So this is the announcement of project
group which is Nvidia's goal to build
the AI brain for humanoid robots.
So you have a very natural question
right like why are we doing humanoid?
Well because we know it works right the
human form factor that you and I all
embody right now is what produces all
the economically valuable physical
labor.
And the second reason is we're entering
an age where humans and robots they need
to work hand in hand. And for humanoid
robot form factor, it's much more
socially acceptable. It's much easier
for humans who work alongside robots to
predict what the humanoid would do
compared to some spider robot that is
super unpredictable.
And the third reason is a bit more
pragmatic, right? Because the world that
we live in are designed for the human
form factor. All the public facilities
like hospitals, restaurants,
supermarkets,
all the tools and equipments that we
have are designed for two hands, two
legs, and five fingers for each hand. So
it's just easier for the humanoid to use
all the tools and blending the world
that we already built.
And the second question is why are we
doing this? Now
actually towards the end of 2023
beginning of this year we have seen a
surge in state-of-the-art hardware for
humanoid robots. And just to name a few
and this is by no means exhaustive.
There's Tesla Optimus, Boston Dynamics
Eat Atlas where this robot kind of does
some crazy you know um moves like 360
degree joints. uh that's kind of
breaking breaking our brain and then
figure F-02
and also we see this trend of the price
of the humanoid and the cost trending
towards a very low value actually
humanoids have been around for a while
right in 2001 NASA has built something
called the Robonaut that cost north of
$1.5 million to build and just a couple
months ago unit announced G1 that costs
about 30K, which is the price of a
regular car that most of the households
will be able to afford.
And it just so happens that there's a
general pattern where the manufacturing
cost of a mature product will tend to
the cost of its raw materials.
And a humanoid robot only takes 4% of
the raw material that's needed for a
car. So, it's possible that this
exponential decrease in cars will go
even further. And that makes now a good
time right to enter this space.
So project good that is Nvidia's
moonshot at building the AI brain for
humanoid robots.
And um I cannot take all of you to our
lab which is about 50 minutes drive away
in Santa Clara headquarters. But let me
take you on a virtual tour.
This is in our lab in Endeavor building
headquarters uh during March GTC where
we had four different types of humanoid
robots from partner companies. So know
that Nvidia doesn't build our own
robots. We rely on the hardware from our
partners um to develop our AI on. So
during GTC time we had four different
types of humanoid in this lab and at
that time it was the most number of
diverse humanoid species per square feet
anywhere on earth.
And if you wonder where does the name
project Groot come from it actually
stands for generalist robot 000
technology.
So um we're putting zeros here because
it looks like Star Wars right? is a
serial code for the robot and the
keyword here is generalist
and that is the strategy that we're
taking right so there is one successful
field of AI and that is the field of NLP
before 2019
NLP has been around for a long time and
there are a lot of specialist systems
like sentiment analysis recommendation
system summarization, information
retrieval and all of these will require
different training pipelines, data
pipelines, evaluation and so on. It's a
very complicated field and then in 2021
Chad GBD came and just blew everything
out of the waters. It is one generalist
robot uh generalist model that you can
prompt and tell it the task that you
need to do. And then once you have this
generalist moment, you can specialize it
back by prompting it, fine-tuning it,
distilling it down to smaller models
that once again are domain experts. And
we call that the specialist, the
specialized journalist.
And it's almost always the case in the
historical trend that the specialized
journalists are way stronger and much
easier to maintain than the original
specialists. And that is the success
story from NLP.
And for robotics, we're kind of still
stuck here as we speak.
All the most of the robot systems these
days are specialists. They require
special hardware and special algorithms
that may or may not even be learning
algorithms. May or may not involve
machine learning, specialized data
pipeline for every use case. So what we
do, we copy homework, right? We copy
homework from the field of NLP
and we hope that project root will be
the journalist moment the foundation
model moment for robotics and then after
that moment we'll specialize it back by
prompting it distilling it fine-tuning
it back to the special use cases and we
hope that the specialized generalist
robot will be much stronger than all the
robot systems that we have today.
So this is a guiding principle that we
operate on. But how do we really make
this a reality?
So today I'm going to talk about some
blueprints,
three principles. If you take home
anything from today's talk, just three
things. The data pyramid principle, the
matrix principle, and the foundation
agent principle. and all of my daily
work, our team's research adhere to
these principles that I'm sharing today.
The first is data pyramid.
Have you wondered why robotics is so
hard? Why is NLP soft first, but we
still don't have generous robot? Well,
there's one thing called the Moravics
paradox, which says that things that are
easy for humans are actually really hard
for machines and vice versa. But have
you thought about why? And I would say
the culprit is on the data side because
you can download terabytes of high
quality text from the internet. You
cannot download motor control signals
from the internet. I wish but it does
not exist. So for robotics we need to
build our own data set. And what does a
data pipeline look like? It's much more
complicated than just training text
foundation models.
So let's work our way downwards from the
top. And the top is obvious real robot
data, right? You just collect some human
demonstrations on the real robot
hardware. And unfortunately, you are
limited by a fundamental physical limit
of 24 hours per robot per day. But
still, this data is super useful. It's a
gold mine because it's directly aligned
to the real robot hardware. So, how are
we collecting that? How do we make data
collection as intuitive and easy as
possible?
Earlier this year, um, Apple announced
Apple Vision Pro and then we have these
really kind of cyber punk moments. You
know, this is on New York subway and
someone just kind of typing randomly in
the air. Super weird. Um, but but these
days this is a norm. So we see Apple
Vision Pro using this way and we thought
how about we apply this to robotics.
So we built a system where a user wears
Apple Vision Pro and you can tell
operate both a robot in simulation and
also in the physical world. Simulation
here and this is a physical robot hand
from a humanoid.
And the idea is very simple.
Vision Pro is tracking your pose, your
hand pose and then retargeting it in
real time to the real robot
and additionally you can also operate a
robot in simulation and in this way you
can teleoperate anywhere. So this is uh
what Nvida built the Omniverse cloud and
on this cloud you can connect any XR
device and then teleoperate a virtual
robot there and the result is that we
have a very intuitive interface to
collect data and this is where on the
right hand side is the user sees through
the firsterson camera
of the Apple Vision Pro. So you can
think of it as kind of like the movie
Avatar where by wearing this you're
actually now transported to a different
embodiment. You are now in the body of
the humanoid robot. And that's also
another advantage of using humanoid
because you have five fingers. The robot
has five fingers. You don't need much
training. Right? Anybody come here in 10
minutes you'll be able to collect data
for us.
So here are some more videos from our
lab where uh a user uh is teleoperating
and the motions are transmitted in real
time to the humanoid
and we can also do things that are a bit
more complicated like you know uh
washing dishes and really the limit is
the humanoid hardware whatever the
hardware is capable of.
So that's how we are collecting the real
robot data. But you're limited by 24
hours per day. That is not enough
because we know that foundation models
are extremely data hungry. We're talking
about we need trillions of tokens to
train any reasonable transformer these
days.
So how do we scale this up? How do we
get more data? And the second part is
what I believe to be the most
interesting which will also carry to the
second principle I'm going to talk about
and that is simulation.
And why are we doing it here at Nvidia?
You know, before Nvidia was an AI
company, we were a graphics company. GPU
stands for graphics processing unit. And
what does a graphics company do? Game
engines and simulation. And just so
happens that simulation is also going to
be super useful for robotics.
So
Nvidia has built a set of tools and this
is called ISAC lab.
What it does is it runs physics
simulation in parallel on GPUs.
Basically, one GPU card can let you run
simulation at 10,000 times faster than
real time. And in this way, you break
the physical limit of 24 hours per day.
You are now just limited by compute.
And just as one example to put this
number in perspective,
this character learns the impressive all
of these impressive martial skills by
going through 10 years worth of intense
training in only two hours of compute
time on a single GPU. So it's very much
like the sparring dojo, right, in the
movie Matrix where you learned kung fu
in maybe 5 seconds of real world time,
but you feel like you trained for many
years.
And this is the Omniverse platform.
And here this race car scene is where
simulation has crossed the uncanny
valley. You know, thanks to hardware
accelerated rate tracing.
So in this video, not a single pixel is
real. All of these are rendered in real
time
using ray tracing. And because we can
render very complex worlds with this
breathtaking levels of details, that
means we can also use simulation to
train computer vision models that can be
much more accurate because you can also
query the ground truth states of every
objects, every segmentation mask in a
simulation. And we can use that to be
the perception module for robots.
And um once we have the simulation and
the real robot uh data we still need all
the data from the internet and that is
just the regular foundation model you
know training GP40 multimodal foundation
models you will have you will collect a
lot of text and videos from the internet
and the robots will still need to learn
like physical common sense from lots and
lots of videos online. So this line is
the most amount of data. I'm talking
about xabytes and probably more than
that per day. But this is also the most
noisy. And then for simulation, we're
talking about perhaps terabytes per GPU
per day. And it comes with not just the
pixels, but also the actions.
And that goes to principle number two.
How we think about building robotics.
And I'm calling this the matrix
principle.
And two questions. First, do we live in
a simulation? Right? There's this very
interesting argument that all of us
right now are living in the matrix, a
simulation.
And all the human intelligence is
actually some emerging behavior that an
alien civilization runs on their
supercomput, right? Their Nvidia is now
simulating all of us here, right?
Well, I don't know if this is true or
not, but there's one thing I know is the
future of robotics will live in
simulation.
The robots will spend most of their
lives in simulation. And that's the only
way that we can collect trillions and
trillions of highquality tokens by
breaking the barrier of 24 hours per
day.
And why does simulation work for
training robots? And again, just one
sentence takeaway.
That's because it's easier to simulate a
problem than to solve it. Let me repeat.
It's easier to simulate a problem than
to solve it. And this here are some very
compelling examples from the past
literature of AI. Right? This is Argo in
2016. The moment when Argo beat Lisa Do
at a game of do at the game of Go. And
the first time ever an AI beats a human
champion. The entire game of Go can be
simulated in perhaps 500 lines of
Python. That's a rule of goal. Extremely
simple to simulate, extremely hard to
solve.
And another favorite example of mine is
Minecraft, right? A very simple game.
Minecraft is like what a few hundred
megabytes
of an executable, but there are all the
emerging behavior, all the interesting
things that you can do. And you know,
going online and look at those Minecraft
channels, just absolutely insane things
like people built the entire Hogwarts
castle block by block in Minecraft. And
someone even built a functioning CPU
circuit in Minecraft because apparently
the game is touring complete. So you can
build a simulation within a simulation
within micron.
So if any of you are interested before
you know I started project root um I had
this work called mind dojo and that is a
framework for training generally capable
agents in a game of Minecraft where
[clears throat] we provide a simulator
as an API for AI and we also provide
lots and lots of data from the internet.
So if you're interested check it out
it's mind dojo.org. But basically
simulation always fascinates me. It's
easier to simulate a world than to do
anything interesting in it.
So given a simulation what can we do
right as AI scientists we we need to ask
right how do we generate the data and I
would say two ways the self-generating
data and then multiply data and these
two corresponds to two learning
paradigms reinforcement learning and
imitation learning and let's look at how
to leverage simulation for these two and
we'll start from reinforcement learning
you know reinforcement learning What
does it do? You give an AI a reward
function. Basically, the reward function
tells you what behavior is desired, what
behavior isn't, and then the agent will
do a lot of trial and error to maximize
that reward. And a prime example is
puff's dog, right? Like you kind of give
it some conditioning and it will respond
to that reward after a while.
So reinforcement is very good at
training things that we don't even know
how we do. So here's a question.
How many par parameters in a neuronet
network do we need to build a
cerebellum?
You know it takes a lot of subconscious
processing for us humans to exist right
like you sitting in the chair or
maintaining balance standing walking. It
actually takes a lot of neuroprocessing
power that you don't think about.
And for humanoid robots, this problem is
called whole body control. And if you're
using reinforcement, it's called neuro
whole body control.
And what are whole body control useful
for
um quite a few things like this is Tesla
Optimus walking. So navigation requires
whole body control. And this is shot in
our lab using Apple Vision Pro
doing tabletop manipulation using our
two hands require whole body control.
And this is a latest video from Boston
Dynamics where the whole robot is
manipulating objects while standing
balance at the same time. And we call
this whole body local manipulation. And
again that requires whole body control.
So the answer to the previous question
is actually to build a cerebellum we
need 1.5 million parameters not billion
1.5 million parameters. So we train this
network called hover to control the body
of a human robot.
Basically what this model captures is
this subconscious processing that we
humans do. So we have a single model
that learns how to coordinate you know
the motors of a human robot like arms
and legs to support locomotion and
manipulation.
And here is uh roughly how this neuronet
network works. I will uh send the links
to the papers. So if you're interested
there are a lot more details in the
papers but today we focus on intuition.
So what the neuronet network takes is
that it's able to support different com
command [clears throat] format like
kinematic position tracking right like
all the position of your joints uh local
joint angle right the angle between your
arms for example and then root tracking
where there's a velocity that you need
to move forward to these are different
ways that we can use to to control the
robot and you can think of them as
prompts and what hover can do is you can
prompt in arbitrary combination of these
things
and that enables us to use different
devices to capture these commands and to
tellyoperate the robot and just as a few
examples uh for the VR device you just
saw right Apple Vision Pro this is
basically head and hand post tracking.
So if you want the robot to stay
balanced while standing, you use Apple
Vision Pro. You track three points and
the rest hover will figure out how to
make the robot stand balanced.
And for RGB camera, if you have an RGB
looking at you and you using some
computer vision models to um recognize
the pose of the human, that would be
whole body pose tracking. And if you're
wearing an exoskeleton, that's a more
advanced way to do tracking, super
precise, that would be the whole body
joint tracking. And if you just um right
if if you only have some joystick some
PS5 right game controller then you can
still control the robot but you can only
specify the root command. So hover
enables very versatile control interface
to tally operate the robot to collect
data and also just to control it in
general.
So here's how we train this model. Very
simple. All the ideas I talk about all
the papers today are super simple. You
don't need to be a roboticist to
understand it. So basically I talk about
these control modes, right? So in
simulation you pass all of these
information and then what we call priv
privilege information which are the
information that you can query in
simulators but you cannot query in the
real world like you can know the exact
location and velocity of every joint
every atom of the robot but you don't
have that information in the real robot.
So that's what we call privilege
information.
And given all of these, it's relatively
easy to train reinforcement learning to
get an Oracle policy that controls
robot. But this policy cheats because it
queries things not available in the real
world. So we simply mask out different
control modes. We also remove these
privilege propriception privilege
information and then we distill it into
a student policy using supervised
learning. And this two-stage process is
very simple and very effective because
if you train this directly using
reinforcement learning, RO tends to be
unstable. So you want to train RO in an
easy way and then you do supervised
learning on harder problem. And this is
a two-stage dissolation. And once you do
that by masking out different
information, then hover becomes
promptable because it can take any
arbitrary combination of the inputs.
And here are some examples like you have
can have the head tracking or like you
know these whole body tracking or simply
tracking the three points for the robot
or you can also do like you know
tracking with root velocity. So it's
both tracking the pose and also moving
forward like zombies. I I hope you know
in the next version we'll train it in a
in a better more natural pose but right
now this is what we get.
And you can also vary the terrains,
right? It doesn't have to be flat. You
can vary all the terrains and obstacles
in Isac lab, the GPU accelerated
parallel simulator. So you can run tens
of thousands of humanoids in this
environment. And it's also not limited
to just one type of robot. Anything that
can be simulated in ISAC, you can plug
it into training.
And then what comes out is whole body
control policies where you can have the
robot kind of follow certain pose and
walking while you know maintaining
balance
and in the future we plan to deploy it
to many more robots. Um so in this video
this is from GTC. Not every robot is
running on your network here. Some are
just classical control. Um but hover is
embodiment agnostic.
All right. So that's reinforcement
learning.
And the second type and the second use
case of simulation is to do imitation
learning.
So once again, this is the Apple Vision
Pro I was set up to collect human
demonstration.
While it's quite intuitive, it's still
really slow to collect these
demonstrations, right? You can see it's
not that easy. It's it's a lot of
effort.
And let's say given one human demo which
is very expensive to do like you you
perhaps you can take you need to take a
few minutes to collect one and over an
hour you can only collect 20
demonstrations that's very very little
data.
How do you multiply that into more data?
And that's the second use of simulation.
And to understand how we do this first
we need to look at what is in a robot
simulation. I would say three main main
things right there. There are handmade
objects that typically created by
artist, handcrafted scenes and
handdesigned tasks. And if you do that,
this is what you get, right? It's it's a
really simple scene. If you want
anything more complicated, you need
artists to create those assets.
But how about we ask AI models to help
us automate some of these process like
for the handmade objects there are text
to 3D models these days that are really
good. So can we ask AI to generate lots
of assets for us and we instantiate it
in the simulation
and for handcrafted scenes ultimately it
is the USD format the universal scene
description language the USD format
which has two parts right the texture
and some code that specify the scene
layout for the texture let's just use
stable diffusion we call an AI and it
can swap out all the textures that we
want in a reasonable
No art is needed.
And then because USD is just some code,
there's a tool video called chat USD.
That's basically fine-tuning LM to
generate USD. And you can generate all
different layouts for the simulation.
And for the task, it's a bunch of code
in Python. So just prompt GBD4, clause
3.5, whatever your favorite LM to
generate the code. And we get a diverse
set of tasks specified in the
simulation,
right? There's like making coffee and
some kind of you know daily task around.
And putting all of these together,
we present Roboccasta,
which is a generative simulation
framework where every part of it or at
least as much as possible are generated
by different AI models, you know, from
the objects to the task to all the
textures and layouts of the kitchens.
And in the matrix, we can have 100,000
different kitchens, right? the
simulation doesn't care as long as
there's enough compute that goes into
it.
So this is Robocasa generative
simulation framework and given Robocassa
we take one human demonstration from the
real world and we can replay it and
multiply it into n different
demonstrations.
So here are some results from the paper
where we we train a policy using
[clears throat] the real world data
only. And this is the important part the
the takeaway.
If you mixing the simulation data
augmented by Roboccasta with all these
variations right the vision model all
the variations you will get a lot better
performance out of it just out of box.
And this is just a preliminary results
and we hope to scale this up massively.
So we really take advantage of the
100,000 different kitchens that you can
afford to have in the real world. And if
we apply this to humanoid, this is what
it looks in omniverse rendered, right?
Humanoid is doing one motion, but it can
do it in 100,000 different places. And
that helps us train really, really
strong perception models.
So that's step one, right? Roboccasta
what it does is some kind of visual
augmentation.
Well, you see that the motion itself,
right, it is still really hard to
collect. And how do you augment not just
the visuals but also also the motion
trajectory
and here is a system that we built to
address this problem. So on the left
hand side is what a human collected in a
simulation.
So basically the task is just to kind of
put these two pieces together. That's
it. Right? This is one human
demonstration.
And we can edit this human demonstration
by varying the position of these objects
and also varying the gripper
with respect to these objects. So once
you replay this demonstration, it will
still be successful but it will be a
machine generated demo, right? Why do
you have a human teleoperate that and
demonstrate a thousand different
configurations when you can use machines
to generate that? Right? Let machines
teach the machines. And this system we
built an a set of algorithm is called
mimicch.
And mimic is a very general purpose
framework. So it can be applied to many
different tasks. And here there are like
making coffee, you know, insert square,
three cube stacking. So maybe gen varies
all the object configurations um and
generate new motion trajectories that
are successful. So you get these data
for free without demonstrating over and
over again.
And if the gripper and the robot
hardware are close enough, you can also
generalize even across the robots that
you don't have. Right? We've all been
poor PhD students before, right? We only
have one panda arm. What to do? You call
mimic gen and you also get data on other
robot arms that you can't afford.
And it also works on long horizon tasks
where it's multi-step like preparing a
coffee. You need to take you know some
pot out of a drawer and then place it in
a in a in a coffee machine and kitchen
chs and you know sorting the bins. There
are tons of variations if you want a
human just to keep telly operating that
you need thousands of trajectories to
learn any good model. But you can use
mimigen to generate the data for it.
It can even do very precise task like
this one which requires a bit of kind of
wiggling to make sure that you know all
the nails and uh these holes all line up
very well and you know these very
precise factory tasks that you need to
put a gear on it
and using mim you can generate lots and
lots of data for it also works in the
real world
we want we want it we want all the data
to be useful in the real world as
And this is a figure that shows um the
scaling of the mimic genen generated
data and the trained the performance of
the train policy.
And um we it's obvious that the trend is
moving up. But there is also some kind
of diminishing return where if you use a
thousand mimi genen generated demos and
then you scale to 5,000 it doesn't buy
you too much because one the task is
relatively simple and second there's
also some limit in in the system that um
was maximal for its diversity.
So this was the original mim work that
we applied to a single robot arm. Well,
the next obvious thing is to apply it to
two hands, right? And for for this task
again, it is run by me gen. Uh it is a
bmanual task and we call this parallel
subtask because these two arms
can execute the pickups in parallel
while at the end they need to do it a
bit more sequentially. So this is one
type called parallel subtask.
And then S is called coordination
subtask where you have the two hands
that need to coordinate precisely to
pick up to lift up the tray at the same
time, right? To to lift out the lid and
put it on a box at the same time. And
that requires the transformations to be
applied to the hand correctly. So you
know everything um once you play the
trajectory is still correct.
And then there are also sequential task
where there's a pre-task and a post task
and the next task cannot happen until
the pre-task conditions are met. So here
the humanoid robot is pouring a ball
into pouring a ball into the bowl and
then place it onto the green block. And
again, if you want to use Apple Vision
Pro to tell upgrade this, it's going to
take forever to do all these variations,
but you shouldn't have to do.
You can also mix and match. You can do
the parallel generation and then do a
two arm coordination.
And we can apply this um two hand by
manual system to a set of different
embodiment like a two gripper setting.
Um two hand setting. Uh there's tray
lifting, you know, drawer clean up and
of course humanoid setting as well where
the humanoid is able to make coffee,
sorting cans, doing the pouring and we
can generate lots and lots of data from
it.
And just zooming out
this is dex mim our followup to the mimi
genen work that focuses on dextrous
manipulation.
And once we have this data we can train
policies. We can also study the
differences between different neuronet
network architectures. Now that we have
a much bigger data set and we see that
diffusion policy a specific type um is
the best across all of these. And
because the tasks are much harder, we
also show a much better scaling as you
run the imaging pipeline. If you start
with let's say a 100 demonstrations that
the human collected
um the the the success rate is not great
but you can use AI right you can use
mimigen to generate 50 times more data
and then magically the task starts to
work
and we can also transfer dex mim to real
world that's what we want to do so we
have a human tidy up operate and then we
have this real to sim pipeline where the
real trajectory tree is replayed in
simulation. We capture it in a digital
twing of the real world and then we run
dex mimigen to generate a huge data set
and then we apply that back to real. So
this is a real to sim to real pipeline.
You collect something in real, you
replay in sim, you multiply, you do
everything you want in sim and then it
transfers back to real and improves the
real performance. And this is one way to
use simulation in the loop.
So to put it together, you have
Roboccasta that takes one demonstration
and multiply to n and then you have
mimage that gives you n * n more
trajectories. And I promise you this is
the most complex math we're going to do
today
and run it in omniverse on humanoid.
This is this is what we see. We have
really good rendering and also very high
quality motion trajectories generated.
I want to show that uh this is a a clip
that Elon showed on uh at Tesla Optimus
where there's a big farm of humans
serving their robot overlords, right? By
kind of teleoperating robot. It's kind
of dystopian.
Um and and and the humans do the same
task over and over again. Actually for
for one of those like battery packing
tasks, it may take thousands of
demonstrations for a human to collect
enough data to train a model that works.
So if we can run simulation to multiply
the data, we can save all of these
humans from from this destiny.
And next and the final principle I want
to talk about is the foundation agent
principle.
That's also how we think about building
the group foundation model.
So most of the research on robotics can
be mapped on these three axes.
the number of embodiment it can master,
the number of skills it can do, and the
number of realities that it can work
with.
And um this is what I mean by
embodiment. You know, in Star Wars,
there are so many different types of
robots and my question is, can we have a
single neuronet network that can control
all of them so we don't need to develop
a separate pipeline for each robot?
And um like two years ago, we had a
proof of concept work called Metamorph
where we train a single neuronet network
that can control thousands of different
robots. And here uh all of these robots
are procedurally generated. They're
quite simple. So this is a proof of
concept, but you can use one set of
neuronet network ways to control them.
And here the idea is also quite simple,
right? You take each robots and they're
basically a graph of joints and we call
that kinematic tree and you do a depth
first search
that first traversal through this body
of the robot and you will be able to
flatten it into a sequence of tokens
where each token um has some physical
properties attached to it. So what does
this look like? Right? It looks like a
sentence written in a new grammar where
the grammar describes the morphology of
the robot.
And if you have lots of robots, you can
convert them to lots of sentences. And
each may be of different lets and you
tokenize them. And this is just
screaming transformers, right? Sequence
models, screaming transformers. And
that's what we do. We train the
metamorph transformer that maps the
sequence to the actions directly
and you have variable length sequences
but they are just like English sentences
and you apply you you map them to
variable length of actions
and we train these robots on a few
different task like uh flat terrain,
walking complex terrains or avoiding
obstacles
and we show that using a single set of
neuronet network weights uh plus
reinforcement learning and accelerated
simulation, we can train one neural
network that rules them all.
And at GTC, um Jensen showed all the
different humanoid robot bodies. So
that's where we're going for Metamorph
2.0. We want a single model that can
control all the humanoid robot bodies
even though they are slightly different
from each other.
And the second access is the number of
skills that the robot agent can do. And
we show that mimi genen is one way to
kind of you know have the robot master
more skills. But can we automate some of
this process
and that is uh the ureka work.
So we train an agent that can achieve
robot dexterity at superhuman level.
Well, maybe not all humans. Um, but
definitely with resp respect to myself
because I' I'm never able to do pen
spinning like that. I have given up long
since childhood. So now my AI can avenge
my poor skills. But I am a support human
here. And how are we doing this? Right?
It's actually a very complex skill to
learn here. And it's not clear how to
even specify the reward function for it.
And what we found is basically the
reward function is just a bunch of
Python code, right? Like in in the in
the Isak uh lab simulator, all of the
robot simulation is written in these
Python APIs.
So what we can do is we just ask CHBT to
do the hard work for us, right? We we
give the OM a prompt saying that please
find a reward function that can um make
the shadow hand do pen spinning and you
pass in some context which is basically
the ISAC lab simulator API as code and
to our surprise GD4 or really any of the
frontier models is able to implement the
reward function correctly for most of
the time and it's actually really
surprising because these reward
functions actually take um trained
roboticists to do. You need to be very
familiar with these physics simulators
to even be able to write that. But
models like GPTs, they learned all the
text in the world and they probably read
all the papers that I wrote before as
well. So they're able to do this. And we
take the generated reward function and
we pass it to 10,000 copies running
parallel on a single GPU.
And we're able to quickly get results by
running a reinforcement learning loop on
this reward function in let's say 15
minutes. And that completes a loop,
right? We sample reward functions. We
call a massively parallel accelerated
training. And then um we can report the
results back to GBD. And these frontier
models are actually very good at
self-reflection. So they can debug and
they can kind of find their own
problems. And sometimes they'll they'll
apologize to you and then write a better
function for you and you just repeat
this loop. So it writes better and
better reward functions.
And here are some examples of what types
of reward function edits that GP does.
And it's quite non-trivial. Sometimes
it's as simple as just changing the
hyperparameter, but sometimes LM decides
to change the functional form of the
rule function completely. And
occasionally it adds completely new
components to let's say track the
angular velocity make some penalty on
the on the um you know different joint
angles. It's doing something very
complicated here. But all of these code
is edited iteratively by an LM.
And if you do this iteration a couple of
times, we see that Eureka gradually
becomes superhuman with respect to
expert written reward functions.
And this is a very general framework.
Any skill you can prompt to do it. In
fact, for these pen spinning along
different axes, you actually need
different reward functions to do it.
And LM has no problem figureing this
out. And for some of the the the task
like this is actually spinning pen
against gravity and it's able to write
reward function to solve it.
So that's urea
and when we were doing ureka it was a
work purely in simulation. So the next
question is how can we transfer from the
sim to the real world and that goes to
the third axis the reality access where
here reality means simulation plus the
real world
and we see the hover work here because
for hover we need to transfer the policy
to the real humanoid but hover is
handtuned
but can we automate it so we introduce
Dr. Eureka
and to understand Dr. Eureka first you
need to understand DR domain
randomization
it's actually a very simple technique in
simulation you will vary the physical
parameters like gravity friction you
know weights size um and all of these
parameters
because in simulation the physics is not
going to be as realistic as the real
world right like no matter how good a
simulation is it will never be there
completely there will always be some
imperfections in the simulation. So what
you do is instead of creating the
absolute most accurate simulation, you
trade compute for it, you just run many
many different types of reality where
the gravity is not the same, friction is
not the same.
And here comes the catch, right? If you
have an AI model that can master 10,000
different physical parameters,
then it may very well generalize to the
10,000 and first reality, which is the
physical world that we live in. And that
is the principle of sim to real of
domain randomization. A super simple
idea that works super well.
So again, this is the Eureka loop,
right? We ask GBT to do the reward
function.
Well, how to do the domain
randomization? Typically, what people do
is you rely on your expertise, right?
Domain randomization, all the
parameters. You need a lot of
experience, you know, from your past
papers or whatever to implement. But
we're very lazy, so we just ask GBT to
do it for us, right? Because domain
randomization parameters are ultimately
still just Python code. And to our
surprise, LMS know how to do it. They
know how to do it. They can also
iteratively improve it. And once you
have this loop, let's transfer that to
the real world.
So here on the left hand side is a
simulation. On the right hand side is a
is a real deployment. So we train a
robot dog to walk here. Um have Dr.
Eureka write some parameters and then it
transfers zero shot without fine-tuning
in the real world.
And this is the allegro hand
manipulating a cube. And again, it
transfer zero shot to the real hand. And
finally, we decided to do something
crazy, right? We want to have a robot
dog to walk on a yoga ball. But the
issue is the yoga ball is bouncy and
it's extremely hard to simulate. In
fact, very very few simulators can do
this correctly. Um, and here we just
have a rigid ball. Like this ball isn't
even bouncy. is rigid in simulation. So
the physics is completely off and then
we run Dr. Eureka
and then we just ask for it to transfer
to real world and that's what we get.
Well, we have u the our students just
walk their dog robot dog casually on the
street on a yoga ball. So uh when I when
I shared this with the public um I I got
a comment. So someone actually after
seeing this work they tried it on their
real dog and their dog is not able to
walk a yoga ball. I wouldn't call this
superhuman but I think this is perhaps
some super dog level intelligence
and that's Dr. Eureka.
So to kind of take a step back right
like what do ureka does is you have an
LM and then you have it code in Isaac
API to generate reward function right
this is one loop and this loop involves
a huge foundation model and given this
reward function you have a second loop
that does reinforcement learning to
produce a small neuronet network that
basically simulates you know the dogs
and and the hands and all of those. So
Eureka is a dual loop system. You have
an outer loop that does reasoning and an
inner loop that does motor control.
And Dr. Eureka just take this one step
further. Right? In addition to reward
function writing, it also writes a sim
to real configuration for it.
And my question is in the future for
Eureka plus why can't we just write more
things? Why why can't we just ask LMS to
do more work? Can we have it write new
task, new simulation completely or
perhaps even new training algorithms
that I don't know how to invent and just
have the loop running? So my dream is
someday if we implement Eureka++
correctly, all of my team will take a
oneweek vacation and then we come back
and Jensen wouldn't even notice because
we're still reporting updates to him.
And that's the goal.
And once you have all of these access
and you push to the top right corner,
this is where we want to be where we
have a single foundation agent that can
master all kinds of different bodies and
do lots of different skills automated
and also generalize across different
simulations and ultimately to the real
world.
This is how people train chbt right it's
a sequence model that you take text in
and then you output text be it Python
writing or you know poetry summarization
reasoning it does not matter and chbd
trains this by scaling it up across lots
and lots of internet text data
and I believe this is what the group
model would look like in terms of the
form factor where it takes as input an
embodiment ment specification telling
you what you're controlling and
instruction in natural language and it
outputs actions and you train Groot by
scaling this up over lots and lots of
realities
and how are we doing this we need a
computing platform to do this so this is
um what Jensen proposed to be the three
computer problem for Nvidia the first
computer is called OVX and that's
basically the graphics computer and what
it does is generate tokens right if
you're using the transformer terminology
it generates tokens and robocasa maybe
jan ureka all of these works in
simulation I talk about falls on the
first computer
and the second computer is the DGX
system and those are the Hundreds A00s
of the world and they learn tokens right
they take the generated tokens they
compress them learn them in a
transformer and these are the foundation
Asian models
And finally we deploy tokens and that is
the AGX system the JSON sore series of
chips that will run on board the
humanoid robots. So those are the
computers that deploy tokens from all of
these intelligence and then you can
validate the performance of this again
in a digital twing inside the matrix and
that completes the three computer
problem and there is this software
orchestration framework called Osmo that
we use to schedule all the heterogeneous
compute workload.
So um if you fell asleep, don't worry.
This is the one slide that you need to
take home today. We talk about three
principles, the data pyramid and the
matrix that supply the data to train the
foundation agent. And then we talk about
the three computers as a computing
platform that enable all of these
research to happen. Three principles and
the three computers.
I think it's going to take a while for
us to solve robotics, right? This is
perhaps the last AI problem, the hardest
AI problem.
And on our way to solve the Groot
Foundation agent, we hope that we'll
build all the tools and research that
will inspire the community, lift up the
community, lower the barrier of entry,
right, to access all of these um
advancements that we have built.
And I believe humanoid robots will be a
trillion dollar business. I don't think
this is very controversial because we're
talking about the entire labor market to
be automated once we have these
generalist robot foundation models.
But using Jensen's word, right now it is
a zero trillion dollar business because
things don't work. But precisely because
it is zero trillion, it's zero today and
trillion tomorrow. So we need to start
working on this right now.
And I believe AGI cannot be achieved
without embodiment.
You know, one day, hopefully soon, we'll
build our active kitten in silicon.
And embodied AI is our northstar. And I
believe Groot holds the key to this
future.
And please join us on our journey to the
moon. Thanks.