Today I'm um very honored to welcome Sak
Paul from Hugging Face um who works a
lot on um that fusion models um image
generation and so forth. Um so his
day-to-day includes contributing to the
diff users Dusers um library training
and babysitting dusion models um and
working on applied ideas. He's
interested in subject driven generation,
preference alignment, and the evaluation
of dusion models. And when he's not
working, he he can be found um playing
the guitar and binge watching ICML
tutorials and suits. So without further
ado, um I'll hand it off to um Sak. I
guess I'm here to depart and deviate
from the usual theme that's followed uh
at CS 25. I guess not a lot about visual
modality, especially the generative
aspects of them. So I guess I'm happy in
a way that I'm here to depart and
deviate from that theme. Uh so yeah
uh I wanted to start with a couple of
disclaimers. Uh and this talk is
definitely not going to be uh an
exhaustive overview of all the possible
methods. So it might have it might be
the case that I didn't cover your work
which you thought to be very seinal. So
I'm I apologize in advance. And then I'm
not going to cover what is diffusion or
flow mashing in details but I'll give a
very uh quick overview just to set the
context and tone. And then the
architectures I'll discuss today will be
fairly agnostic uh to diffusion or flow
matching. And since I work on image and
videos primarily, I will take my
examples with images. But just know that
these architectures are fairly well
known to generalize to other continuous
modalities such as audios.
And then of course I'll share my slide
after the talk.
And here's how I want to approach this
talk. This is the rough overview of of
all the things that I want to cover. As
I mentioned, I'll give you a brief
introduction uh to diffusion models or
flow matching as well. And then I'll
I'll I'll try to set the context by
discussing the early architectures uh
for diffusion, the early architectures
for image generation in this field. And
then we'll uh hit straight to uh dits
and as I like to call uh their friends
and I'll conclude with some thoughts uh
in and in those thoughts I'll discuss
some of the promising directions that
I've become lately interested in and
then I'm sure there will be time for
Q&A. So yeah,
I really wanted to kind of fascinate you
with all the cool uh examples in the
text to image arena. But I guess at this
point in time we all know uh these
examples because I think like these days
we are becoming more and more interested
in native multimodel generation not just
uh images but nonetheless I just wanted
to start off by giving you a couple of
examples from the text to image arena.
My favorite is the last one. Tiny
astronaut hatching from an egg on the
moon. I think uh I think human
imagination really took off there. But
yeah, you can see apart from Dali 3, all
these are open models and the photo
realism aspects of these models are uh
quite impressive. So yeah
and then uh I I want to also give you an
infographic of how I like to think about
uh diffusion models in general. So I
like to think about diffusion models as
the following. So when you take a random
noise vector and what happens as you den
noiseise it over a period of time so
that it becomes a photorealistic image.
And if you if you take a look closely,
you will notice that it's a it's a it's
an iterative process unlike GANs. GANs
are oneshot in nature, but diffusion
models are iterative. It's sequential in
nature. So in a in a way we are
essentially denoising uh the random
noise that we had started off with until
unless we are we are uh we are done with
the kind of image that we are looking
for. So just know that it's iterative in
nature. That's the main takeaway uh from
this slide. And you when you condition
when you start conditioning the
denoising process with text for example
you can condition in lots of ways but
let's say I think text is one of the
more liberating conditions as you start
conditioning the deninoising process
with text uh you get you know abstract
creatures like this uh but but yeah you
you you you will start feeling very
liberated with texture image as I like
to believe
and then let's let's take a step back
and start developing a mental model of
what it takes to have a fairly
state-of-the-art text to image model
like let's say I want to get from this
text prompt a cat looking like a tiger
and from all the way up to the image uh
on the top what does it take what are
the what are the components that we are
looking for how should they be connected
so I want to kind of give you uh a
connected graph of how how the different
components should be connected so that
we can backtrack them and start
developing more information.
So of course when you have text you need
to have some sort of embedding so that
you can sort of work with those
embeddings and we have text encoders for
them and like state-of-the-art diffusion
models they usually rely on more than
one text encoders. For example, stable
diffusion 3, it relies on three text
encoders, not one, not two, but three.
So you have your text prompt you pass it
off uh to text encoders and you then
have the embeddings and as we saw in the
earlier slide we are starting off with
some random noise drawn from a gausian
distribution. So we are starting with
some noisy latence and then you have
your text embeddings
and then you have some time step uh uh
which you which you draw which you do
the math with the scheduleuler. I'm I'm
going to come to the scheduleuler
component in a minute. But you have your
conditions at this point in time. You
have your text embeddings, you have your
noisy latence, and you have some time
step, right?
And then uh you have your core diffusion
network uh which uh and you pass all all
these inputs to your core diffusion
network. And it's a sequential uh
process. You run the uh diffusion
network over a period of time as we saw
in the earlier slide. and then it's
going to give you some refined latent
and then you give it to some decoder
model and you have your image out. Now,
now I would like to call out two broad
classes of diffusion models. This
overview resembles the pixel uh the
latent space diffusion models but
there's another class of diffusion
models which is called the pixel space
diffusion model. But the recent or the
state of the diffusion models they are
all latent space based because pixel
space is quite prohibitive and
computationally intensive in nature. uh
that's why it's more common to see
latent space uh diffusion models. So
that's why uh that's why you see noisy
latence there and not raw pixels. And if
you were to sort of generalize this to
other continuous modalities, uh the
basic idea here is how do you represent
the raw modality data points and how do
you compute intermediate representations
of them. So you if you were to do this
on the audio space, you can think of uh
some similar analogies. But long story
cut short for a fairly well performing
text to image system these are roughly
the components that you need. So yeah
and then let's let's now start
developing some notations uh so that we
can start discussing about how these
models are trained and finally how how
you should perform inference with these
models. So again I'm start I'm giving
this examples with images but you these
are these are fairly agnostic modality
agnostic apart a apart from text of
course these won't work on discrete
tokens uh so let's say I have some
original image and I'm drawing some
noise uh from a standard gshian
distribution and then let's say I am
also drawing some time step uh from a
uniform distribution and then I have a
particular noise schedule and also some
terms that are controlling the noise
module and then let's say I have some
conditioning vector and by conditioning
vector I essentially mean some text
embeddings or some other form of
structural uh controls like let's say
depth map segmentation maps and so on
and then uh you have your diffusion
model that you will learn and during
training what we basically do is uh we
we compute some intermediate
representations of the images or let's
say if if you are working on the pixel
space you add add small amount of noise
to your clean images and you make the
model predict what was the amount of
noise that was added. This is one very
popular and widely adopted
parameterization of diffusion network
training. It's called the epsylon
objective if you will and that's
basically it. So we basically make the
model learn what was the amount of noise
that was added. So that's that's
training and during sampling
uh we repeat repeat the noise prediction
part in a sequential manner until and
unless we arrive at an image that we
feel uh good about. So we start uh from
a from from a from a random noise and we
den noiseise it over a period of time
with some condition which can be text
embeddings for example and then we sort
of repeat the denoising process over a
period of time until and unless we
arrive at a data point that we feel good
about.
So yeah and for flow matching which are
which is becoming more and more common
these days for example flux if you have
heard of the model flux or stable
diffusion 3 these are all flow matching
based in flow matching the paths the
paths become like more straight we try
to connect noise and clean data through
a straight path. That's why you see the
linear interpolation equation in the
first point and we try to uh predict the
target velocity field with a neural
network. Uh and we so the broad the key
takeaway here is we try to connect noise
and clean data through a straight line
but in diffusion models the path is not
assumed to be a straight line. So that's
why a lot of simplification you will see
uh in flow matching.
But long story cut short in this talk we
are more interested in the network
component of things. We are not
interested in how you should add the
noise what particular noise schedules uh
you should follow uh and so on. We are
more focused on the parameterization
side of uh things in this talk. Uh so
yeah
and and and and let's now start
discussing the components uh we might
need uh the the components that that are
kind of expected uh in a diffusion model
uh what are the core requirements uh
that we want to see in a diffusion model
to have uh so that it performs uh within
some bound of expectations.
So we we have to figure a way out to
deal with the noisy inputs. As we saw
noise, we we can't really get get rid of
the noise because that kind of gives us
the foundation.
And usually in pixel space your shapes
will look something like this if you are
channels first. And and and if you're if
you're working on the latent space, it
will of course be compressed uh a bit.
And we usually always deal with the
latent space uh diffusion model. So it
helps to have the kind of shapes that
you would expect to see uh in your
models that will flow through
and then you'll have to deal with the
conditions right because all the text
image models that you see text is your
condition. So you'll have to deal with
your conditions and of course time step.
So the amount of noise that gets added
to your latence it should depend on the
time step like like let's say if your
time step is 10 the amount of noise that
will get added to your data points it
will be different from the time step I
if the time step were to be somewhere
like 1 th00and or 100. So that's why
time step is also a very crucial
condition because it it it basically
tells the model that which
which point in the trajectory it's in.
Should it den noiseise less? Should it
den noiseise more aggressively and so
on. And then you have got other forms of
conditions such as class maybe tiger
bird or just like natural language.
And then we have to also model the
dependencies quite a bit. How should the
noisy inputs interact with your uh
conditions? Of course, you you you might
want to think about these things through
the lens of cross attention and so on,
but we'll get to that uh in a moment.
And then how should the final outputs be
produced? Should we just flat out decode
everything if we were to deal with
transformer based architectures? Should
we be upsampling if we were to deal with
pure convolutional architectures? Uh and
so on. And usually for the diffusion
network the input shape exactly equals
the output shape until and unless you
are dealing with a separate
parameterization of uh diffusion. There
are other parameterizations but it's way
more common to see the inputs that are
flowing through the diffusion model will
equal uh the outputs uh that the
diffusion model is supposed to uh
produce.
And then yes here's a bit of a history.
So DDPM all the all the early work in
this area DDPM uh latent diffusion
models they they all used a unit based
architectures and I think historically
speaking uh units have kind of dominated
this area for quite a bit like style GAN
they all had a unit-based architecture
right and then until SDXL which is a
fairly recent I I would like to say
recent because it's like from 2023 and
if you are trying to develop a chron
technology of all the architectures that
have come around I would like to argue
that SDXL is fairly decent and also
based on its usage it's I I think it's
decent so until SDXL all the works
relied on uh unit so I think it makes
sense to sort of discuss the unit based
architecture uh in uh in this paradigm
and then uh start seeing why we really
need uh to transition to uh
transformers. So yeah,
and of course the unit for for diffusion
it's it's it's giant. Uh it's also one
of the reasons why you would want to
probably get rid of it. But that's not
the end of the story. But let's let's
try to see what what are the different
components that are involved uh in our
giant unit. So you of course need to
have an input convolutional stem that
directly operates uh at the inputs that
are coming at it. And then you have a
bunch of uh down blocks which is
basically comprised of uh custom
residual blocks made of you know uh
normalization layers uh and
convolutional layers and then you have
got custom transformer blocks again
normalization projections uh and regular
like transformer blocks
and then you have got convolutional
layers for upsampling. So basically uh
you are so when you are operating on the
latent space you would want to upsample
to a higher resolution and then you
would have some middle block like like
you would have in a standard unit
architecture where where you would would
not where you would not have any
resolution changes and then you would
have a series of uplocks which will
basically down sample the upsampled you
know outputs that you had in your down
blocks and finally you will produce the
output that will have the same shape as
your input and it's it basically
resemble the same kind of blocks that
you h that you would have in your down
block counterpart uh but instead of
doing upsampling it will have down
sampling layers. So yeah and there are
some miscellaneous things that you
should worry about for example time step
embeddings how you should embed your
time steps and additional embeddings for
example if it's a class conditional
model the way to embed them would be
different if it's a tech like text image
model the way to embed the text
embeddings would be different basically
the way you modulate all your
conditional embeddings that will change
depending on the kind of conditions that
you are dealing with
and here's basically really how a down
block of the unit architecture looks
like. I mean it's so so giant that I had
to transpose it. So it's kind of very
painful to even think in the head. So if
you are someone that works with
architectures quite a bit, I think we'll
have to solemnly agree that this is bad.
This is bad news already. I mean I can't
even imagine it in my head. So, and
here's a bit of a zoomed in look of what
goes into that down block component of
the unit. You have got a bunch of custom
resonant blocks as I was discussing.
I've got a bunch of custom transformer
blocks as I was discussing, but nothing
too brutal, nothing that you haven't
seen already. So, it's just a bunch of
composition of those uh blocks. And I
have also tried mentioning the
resolution changes in each of the uh
stages. So yeah
and putting it all together it looks
something like this. I mean I have tried
shortening it quite a bit but I mean if
I were to imagine it in my head it's
going to be extremely painful and the
blocks are just damn it's very
prohibitive in nature just for the task
of image generation.
So yeah that's like the complete
perspective. uh I know it does it it's
not as complete as you might expect but
it's also hard to kind of fit all the
unit in a single screen. So yeah and
then of course the natural next thing
that one would have tried would be to
would be to try to replace the
convolutional layers with MLP blocks to
try to simplify quite a bit and yeah
folks from Google tried it in the UIT
architecture. So that's there like that
was like the pre precursor to the pure
transformer based architectures but not
quite it still had its fair share of
complicies and the architectural you
know painfulness as you saw in the unit
based design. So yeah
now I'm going to now try to motivate why
we really need a pure transformer based
architecture. Now the first point is
probably very obvious. We would want to
benefit from the advancements that are
happening in the transformer based
architectures like all the divine
benevolence as no shazir like likes to
call it. Uh you would want to have
swigloo you would want to have QK
normalization you would want to have
parallel MLP layers and so on. So that's
one of course good scaling properties uh
and so on. And then let's say you would
you want to connect uh the core the pure
transformer based diffusion architecture
or the backbone with some other
backbones let's say a pure LLM based
backbone the integration becomes very
easy and then it allows you to get rid
of the giant unit which I guess is my
main motivation but I hope I was able to
convince you fairly strongly that why we
need uh a change a par like a paradigm
shift in the architectures uh that are
primarily inspired from the unit design
uh and also this is sight to the sore
eyes already. I mean this is not
uncommon you we all know that this is
the standard forward pass in a vision
transformer network. This should feel
very familiar at this point in time. Now
the point I am trying to make here is
this doesn't have to change a whole lot
if we were to sort of extrapolate this
to uh image generation and I think you
will agree with me that this is not
changing a lot like all the core
components are there the patchification
is there the positional embeddings are
there of course the way to class embed
things that's different the y embedder
bit you would still need to have a
component and to embed your time steps
that's different but rest of the
components it's still there like you are
still iterating through the through the
blocks you have your final layer to
finally decode your outputs and so on
and then nonpatchification layer so like
this is still very similar to how you
would do it in a standard vit but of
course you you have to you know account
for the generation uh head also at the
same time so my point is you are not
changing a whole But uh in the standard
v uh forward bus. Now taking a closer
look I think this should also kind of
feel very familiar apart from a few uh
mods here and there like we have got
some scale and shift parameters which
I'm going to discuss uh in a bit. But
rest of the other blocks like you have
got the same layer norm you have got the
patchification layer you have got some
embeddings and so on and then you have
got a linear and reshape operation. So
most of it should feel familiar but the
ones that are apparently a little
foreign I'm going to discuss them now.
So yeah
let's start with the time step bit like
how do we actually embed time steps. I
am I've been talking about time steps
for quite a bit now. Uh but let's now
see how do we actually embed the time
steps and time steps are are really
important. And I'm also going to show
you the expected shapes, the output
shapes. And in this case, this is bat
size, comma, the hidden dimension of the
transformer blocks that you are
expecting.
So how do we embed time steps? And time
steps can range in between 0 to,000
where zero meaning like no noise and
thousand should mean it's fully noised.
So each T is embedded into cyanosidial
frequency uh to make them phase aware
like at any point in time the network is
seeing extremely low frequencies and
extremely higher frequencies and it must
be aware of the kind of phase uh it
should be it should be modulating into.
So that's why cyanocidal frequencies are
really helpful and then after that how
how how the network should weigh these
different frequencies and in order to
model those weights we basically pass it
through a very shallow MLP
and then how do you embed class labels
you just take an NN embedding layer as
simple as that and is the standard
patchification you do it with a
convolutional stem and for positional
encodings they they use the standard s
cosine uh scheme.
A and the final conditioning is you
first embed the time steps and then you
embed the class labels and you basically
sum them up and then you have your final
condition that goes into the transformer
blocks and this is very important to
note that C remains fixed across all the
blocks. So that's very important to note
and you would probably think uh the
conditioning uh in order to model the
conditioning with the actual inputs the
noisy latency you would probably want to
use cross attention but that's not
that's not the case as we will see uh in
a few in a few slides later. So let's
take a step back and try to think of how
how we can how we can inject uh the
conditioning bit into uh the transformer
blocks. So we have something called
adaptive uh layer norm which is very
important in order to be able to sort of
model the stylistic aspects that you are
getting out of your images and it's
basically this. So you have your
standard layer norm and then then you
have an additional set of parameters
which we call modulation parameters
which we which basically operate on the
condition space and remember the
condition is basically a summation of
the time step embeddings as well as the
class embeddings. So that's your
condition right there.
And and skipping the regular transformer
bits like the QKV, the the multi head
self attention and the MLP layers, we we
know the equations that govern the
computations that take place within a
standard transformer encoder block.
Right? So this is fairly wellnown. Now
the part that's not known at this point
in time hopefully is how do we how do we
modulate the conditioning bit? How do we
actually inject the conditioning in the
transformer blocks? So this is this is
how we do it. Instead of doing any cross
attention which would have been a fairly
natural choice I guess we actually do
not do cross attention. We are still
doing self attention and then we are
basically modulating the conditioning
along with self attention as you can see
in the bottom half of your equations.
And these modulation parameters are
learned from the modality uh that you
are training these things on. So yeah
and then and then in order to get your
final outputs you basically have a
single layer decoder uh and then you
basically unpatchify it uh to get the
same uh uh shape as your inputs.
Now uh a note on init because the
initialization uh is fairly important.
It's it's all standard vision
transformer in it but with two key
modifications. Each transformer block is
is initialized as identity block taking
inspiration from the early works in
imagenet training wherein uh if you have
a bunch of reset blocks you usually
initialize the beta parameter in the
batch normalization layer as zero. it
helps with training stability and
stabilization and turns out that's the
case here as well.
Now coming to the the adaptive layer
normalization thing, it's very important
and it's also more compute efficient and
I was and as I was mentioning cross
attention would have been the natural
choice in order to kind of model the
dependency between the conditions and
the noise inputs. But that's not at all
the case if you take a look at the
graph. In fact, adaptive layer norm
performs the best and it beats cross
attention big time. And it's also not
not because the conditions are fairly
simple to model, but it's because when
you are operating with continuous
modalities like images, it's not it's
not that trivial uh to model
dependencies with cross attention. And
when you are conditions are simple like
class embeddings, it doesn't make sense
to model them with cross attention. It's
also because like it's a waste of
compute and the graph kind of confirms
it
and later works have also explored like
a more compute efficient variant of uh
adaptive layer num which we are going to
get to in a couple slides later
and how you are modulating these
conditions like in in this case we are
basically operating on a summation of
the time step embeddings and the class
embeddings. Now how you are modulating
it across and throughout your different
transformer blocks that becomes very
important as we will see in a couple
blocks later.
And as expected it scales fairly
graciously uh with more compute and
turns out that you can basically apply
all the all the unit based uh training
techniques to uh to a diffusion
transformer. So that's pretty cool. It
scales pretty graciously
performs also well when compared to
other equized unit counterparts. Uh so
yeah
and of course at this point in time you
must be thinking no one really does
class conditional in the space of image
generation. So yeah that's where we are
headed next.
Uh now I want to I want to I want to I
want to try to motivate what it would
take to enable text to image generation
in the standard uh diffusion transformer
architecture because I think it makes
sense to approach the problem in that
sense. Uh like what are the components
that are missing in a standard uh
diffusion transformer so that it becomes
a tool for text to image generation as
well. And I think Pixart alpha is one of
the early works uh that explored it. Uh
so yeah we are going to definitely see
it in details.
Now one question one natural question
would be how to embed the input uh
natural language text prompts and the
answer would be simple. You would need
uh a text encoder and that's exactly
what uh the Pixart alpha work does.
And then how to learn your contextual uh
dependencies. Uh now we have instead of
class uh instead of classes we have got
natural language text on top of uh time
steps.
We could do self attention on noisy
latence and then we could do cross
attention in between your noisy latence
and text. And mind you this text is not
just class. This text is some natural
language description may like a baby
astronaut hatching out of an egg on the
moon. So this is natural language
description we are talking about. This
is not simply class labels.
So that could make sense. Uh it could
make sense to have self attention on
noisy latence to model the local
dependencies within the patches and then
also do cross attention in between the
noisy uh patches and the text embeds.
And then we'll have to figure a way out
to modulate the time steps as well. And
as we saw in the dit work that it's
important to modulate the time step
embeddings throughout your uh
transformer blocks
and then if you have got access to a
class conditional diffusion transformer
and if it's compatible it might also
make sense to kind of initialize some
some blocks uh from it because why why
why waste compute right? It might help
with uh training stabilization uh and so
on.
Now that's exactly what Pixard Alpha
does. So if if you were paying attention
at this point in time, you would have
realized there's imple that implementing
these things is not extremely
challenging. But that's exact but but it
it helps to know that that's exactly
what Pixat Alpha does. So it uses a text
encoder to embed the prompts. It uses
self attention on noisy latence. It uses
cross attention to model the dependency
between the noisy latence and the text
uh embarrings and it also initializes
from a class conditional d model in
order to accelerate training. So kind of
helps uh to know that you can still
think about these things and see it
getting implemented in practice. So yeah
and here here's some discussion uh
around the use of text encoder. So,
Pixard Alpha used Flan T5XXL in order to
in order to really get that text
rendering ability. Uh, and some of the
concurrent works like imagine they they
showed that if you scale the text
encoder and if you ever wanted to render
text in your images, having a better
text encoder actually helps. And also
then there there's this problem of long
prompt following ability because models
like XD SDXL they rely on clip for
embedding text and clip has a very short
context length I think it's 77 but with
a T5XXL you get a way longer context
length so you basically get to have
longer prompts you get to describe your
prompt in a bit more detail uh so that's
there and also exploring the space of
text encoder It's still a kind of good
research problem to take a look at. And
if you were wondering why not just use a
standard language model in place of uh
T5, well, it's it's not that difficult
to actually use it. And many works like
Lumina, they explore it uh quite a bit.
And if you were wondering, diffusion
models are already computebound. So why
why add the baggage of adding another
heavy model? Well, I think it's it's
okay to use that because computing
prompt embedding it's a one-step
process. So, it's okay to have a memory
bound model like a large language model
in the in the mix.
Cool. And and here here we will again
see the return of adaptive layer norm.
Uh and remember if if you if you forgot
remember that for each for each
diffusion transformer block we were
operating on a summation of time step
embeddings and class uh class embeddings
right
and and for for pixard alpha we
basically we basically h we already have
a way to compute our text embeddings
which we do not want to touch because
those embeddings are already computed
with a dedicated rich text encoder. So
we maybe do not want to touch those
embeddings and modulate them unlike
unlike diffusion transformers where we
modulated the class embedded as well.
And instead of instead of having
adaptive layer normalization blocks for
in every diffusion transformer encoder
block, we basically maintain tables. We
basically maintain embedding tables and
we sum them up. So instead of doing
another math mull for for for each and
every transformer encoder block we
basically get away with addition
addition with uh another embedding table
and it helps us reduce the compute quite
a bit. It helps us reduce 27% of the
original diffusion transformer
computation and I think the idea is
fairly elegant. uh it also gives another
perspective to think about how you can
reduce parameters and still uh sort of
maintain performance. So this was good.
Cool. And I I must say this is
impressive performance for a fairly
compact model. Like it's only 6 billion
parameter model and it's already like
breaking all the charts. Like when it
came around in 2023, it was fairly
fairly good. Fairly good. Uh I think I
have the Genevwell scores. No. Uh we
don't. But but the last chart here, it
basically shows you the human preference
rating. Uh quality wise, it's overall
image quality and alignment wise, it's
the alignment between the text and the
generated images. And in both of those
aspects, Pixart alpha performed fairly
well.
Now before before I before I jump to the
time and memory complexity
of of these models because we are still
using the quadratic vanilla attention
thing. I want to see if there are any
questions at this point in time. Uh so
I'm going to open the floor for
questions if that's okay Stephen. That's
okay.
Yeah.
You mentioned um that the
state-of-the-art diffusion models rely
on more than one text encoder. Why is
that? Like what's the benefit of having
multiple uh different types of encodings
for the same text? Oh yeah, for sure. So
the question is why would you want to
have multiple text encoders? Uh and why
does it help improve the image
generation performance? So you saw in
class conditional deaths you modulate
not just the time step embeddings but
also the class embeddings.
Uh so the conditional embeddings that we
were modulating along with self
attention were a summation of class
embeddings and time step embeddings. Now
for for for text to image models that is
not as trivial. So apart from your text
embeddings, you also kind of have your
time step embeddings, but what about
what about what about modulating the
other condition that you computed from
your uh text input? So turns out that
the richer the representations are, the
diverse the representations are, the
better it is for the uh generation
backbone. Now when I said many many
models do use more than one text
encoders they usually have a combination
of clip and T5. Now clip is an entirely
different model and T5 is an entirely
different model. With clip you embed
some kind of contrastive nature in the
text embeddings and with T5 you have a
completely different uh nature in your
text embeddings. So more the the more
the divers are these embeddings the
better it is uh for the generative
performance but there's no like
systematic study of this that's what uh
that's what the general belief is. Yeah
but there are works that get away just
by using a single language model. So
maybe the language model maybe the
language models inherit both as a virtue
of their good pre-training.
Yeah.
Any more questions?
Yeah. Most current cutting edge
companies use diffusion diffusion
transformers now or some still using the
original net with convolutions or is it
just like dependent on the use case? I
think most of them are uh using
diffusion transformers because of their
efficiencies and also they are easy to
adapt like if you wanted to embed
another form of control like let's say
you you wanted to additionally prompt
the model with some stylistic reference
from images. It's easier to do that on a
diffusion transformer as you would as we
will see in a couple slides later.
How you exactly the matrix
multiplication?
Oh yeah, sure. Can you expand? Yeah.
Yeah. Yeah, sure. So,
so far in the in the in the original
diffusion transformer block, you
initialize all your modulation
parameters as basically an aine layer.
So, you can do that, right? I mean, you
can chunk it and then you have your
different modulation parameters.
And this is this is where this is where
your m matrix multiplication lies. And
and and notice how I am computing the
modulation parameters, right?
But here I am only computing it through
an embedding table. There's no there's
no fine transformation happening
and I end up adding it to my time step
embeddings. That's it.
So that's how I avoid the matal.
And that's that's that's largely why I
am able to sort of reduce the
computation by 27%.
Yeah, I'll take one last question before
I jump to the next section if there's
any. Got some um over zoom as well as
online. Um I'll ask some um let me see
someone's wondering is there still any
point of GANs for image and video
generation or have they been fully
replaced basically with diffusion
models? I won't say they have been fully
replaced because you as we saw diffusion
models are still sequential in nature.
So if you're looking for really ultra
realtime generation I think GANs are
still the way to go and many companies
are in fact using them. So if you're
looking for really cool oneshot
generation, I think GANs is the way. And
even if so there's this literature
around time step distillation that
basically looks at reducing the number
of time steps uh or inference steps that
you need in order to produce a good
quality image. There you need a GAN loss
actually. So GANs are not going to be
completely ripples yet. Okay. Cuz I
thought I thought GANs had a lot of
issues like mode collapse that are
fixed. They have. But if you have got
specific use cases and if you have got a
fairly good data set, you can still
train a good game.
I can ask one more if you time from
online. Um,
image generation generally requires a
lot of data to train especially for that
fusion models. Are there techniques or
architectural choices for low data
regimes?
That's a good one. Short answer is no.
You need you
I mean it I think it's kind of
correlated
with your use case a bit like for
medical imaging probably you do not need
a whole lot of diversity but if you need
a fairly well well and generic gen
generative model I think you need to
train it on a lot of data to inherit all
the biases that you are looking for like
if you if you want to train on the
distribution of natural images and you
you want the model to always produce
realistic images I think you need to
have a lot of data at least diverse
data.
Yeah. Okay. Because nowadays for like
LLMs, you know, there's like zero shot
few shot learning after you pre-train.
Talk a bit about in context learning for
diffusion models. Okay. Uh but but you
still you are assuming you have access
to a pre-trained model, right? Right.
Right.
So there you go. All right.
I'm going to
I'm going to start this leg of uh the
talk by discussing the quadratic time
and memory complexity argument a bit
because now we are in the image
generation territory and when you are
trying to generate like really high
resolution images like 4K images vanilla
attention becomes extremely prohibitive
even if you were to operate on the
latent space like take a look at the
dimensions of the latence. Uh let's say
your uh number of latent channels is 16
and your latent dimensions are 512,
512. Like it's it's still way too large,
way larger than what we are used to
seeing in the VLM space, right? And I
have some dummy computations here. This
is of course not using flash attention.
If I were to give you some dummy
estimates, it would be like 190 GBs
in floating point 16. And this is all
like reasonable defaults. I mean, I have
24 attention heads. I've got bat size
one. The sequence length is flattened
out. I would need 190 GB. And this is of
course not using flash attention, but
you kind of get an idea of the
prohibitive computation space of the
quadratic attention that we usually use
in diffusion models if we were to deal
with really uh high quality and high
resolution uh images. So what could we
do like two simple things that we could
do is operate on an even more compressed
space like this this 1A 16A 512A 512.
this space is already compressed enough
but could we even increase the
compression ratio further right and then
the second second obvious thing could be
to use some form of linear attention
that doesn't do the n cross n uh
multiplication
so that brings me to my next
architecture which is the sana
architecture and it uses both it uses an
an even more compressed latent space and
it also uses a linear variant
uh of the of the of the attention
mechanism. So let's see.
So our linear attention is on the other
hand and of course you might expect some
performance loss with with the linear
comp complexity of the attention
mechanism and to compensate for the
performance lost we use mix FF. And I'm
going to I'm going to get into the
details in a bit but just wanted to give
you a quick overview. So sana does self
self attention selflinear attention as
you will but it still does cross
attention to model the dependencies
between the noisy latence as well as uh
the text prompts that you are providing
it to and then there's no n square
computation happening in the self
attention and the equation makes that
clear so we have got shared terms shared
terms computed from the kv projections
and these are reused for all the queries
and this way we are basically ally and
effectively
not doing the n cross n multiplications
and all of the multiplications are upper
bound to n that's why we are able to
reduce from order of n² to order of n
and then as I was mentioning there has
to be some form of accountability as we
are not using the quadratic attention
mechanism right so we use mix ffn blocks
it's basically a bunch of inverted
residual blocks and point force
convolutions in order to model the local
dependencies because it turns out that
when you take the softmax out of out of
the picture you lose all the notion of
locality let's not say all majority of
the locality notions are taken out also
so that's why you you need some some
components to also model the locality
aspect and mix fn blocks are used for
that
and for the first time sana got rid of
the positional embedding bit So I mean
it's very it's very funny to say it.
Nope. So no positional embeddings and
mix flocks actually helps because you
have a bunch of convolutional blocks in
there. So we are still returning uh to
the convolutional argument but not so
much like it's it's not fully
convolutional. You just have a few
convolutional layers thrown in there. So
it's largely did based but instead of
using like a linear MLP you have uh uh
two convolutional layers uh to to to
account for the local interactions
and it performs fairly well for its
compact size. It performs fairly well. I
I must say that we shouldn't take take
into account the kernel fusion and the
fancy fancy DPM solver that they're
using. But up until the fourth row, I
think it's still performing fairly well.
Like it's giving very decent G&L
performance. It's giving very decent DPG
uh performance. And these are all
metrics that assess uh that assess a
given image in terms of
compositionality, in terms of their
fidelity, uh in terms of their overall
quality uh and so on. And these metrics
are fairly well grounded uh in terms of
reality. Uh so yeah
and and this is this is probably going
to be the final flavor of attention that
I'm going to discuss before I move on to
uh other topics and this is I think a
bit new uh and also new in the sense
that no one in the VLM space uh really
does it. So what happens if we were to
kind of you know model dependencies of
the different modalities in separate
spaces. Uh so let's see.
So and the and and one motivation behind
this could be text embedded. Let's say
you are computing text embeddings with a
large language model. You will end up
inheriting a lot of bias from it. Right?
like the unidirectionality
uh bias will be there. If you're using a
standard auto reggressive large language
model, you will end up inheriting the
uni directionality bias. So, so you will
have bias and they might you know creep
into uh your your generative model in
all sorts of different ways.
So, so one idea could be to do QKV
projections but but separately like you
do QV projections on the text embeddings
and you also you also maintain another
set of QV uh projection parameters for
your uh noise relations and then you
concatenate them before you compute the
attention. So you operate on a
concatenate concatenated representation
before you actually do the attention and
conceptually this becomes basically
this. So you you project your QKV stuff
on your image latins separately from the
text embeddings. You concatenate them
before you actually compute attention.
So this is basically it. So this is mmd
that was introduced in the stable
diffusion 3 paper. uh and their
motivation was to get rid of the
different biases that might be there in
the text embeddings and they also showed
how qualitatively different text
embeddings can be uh from the image
embeddings. So I guess that kind of
gives you uh an hint about why we might
need different text embeddings to not
end up inherit each other's biases and
have more diversity in the mix. So yeah,
so it basically looks like this. So it
might feel a little complicated but the
reason why it's so big is because we
have separate projection matrices for
the different modalities that we are
modeling. So on the
left hand side we have got the captions
and on the right hand side we have got
the noisy latence and we have got
separate QV projections and adapt
adaptive layer nom matrices for the
separate modality. So that's why it it
feels big but conceptually it's it's
basically this. So uh yeah
so you have got separate adaptive layer
non matrices for the separate modalities
you have got separate QV projection
matrices you have got separate output
projection matrices and then you have
got separate everything separate
everything is separate from from the two
modalities that we are interested in. So
yeah,
so in a way it kind kind of gives a way
to co-evolve the two embeddings uh from
the two different modalities that we are
working with for the given task which is
image generation in this case. And also
if we are very used to cross attention
you might want to ask if we were to
compute attention in this way how do we
do masking in the first place and that's
actually an active area of research. We
do not know how to do masks holistically
if we were to do uh mmd variant of
attention
and then modu modulation happens with
both time steps and the conditional
embedding that you are operating with.
Uh so stable diffusion 3 uses a
different set of pulled text embeddings
that are usually computed from cliff and
not the not the T5 based text encoder.
So you again you need some form of
diversity to not end up inheriting the
bias from the other text encoder that
you have
and stable division 3 uses three. Uh so
but they can be mixed and matched during
inference. They showed that you need the
T5 if you if you need to have really
good text rendering capabilities, but
other than that, you can still get uh
you can you can still do a lot with the
two clips that they use. And you can
drop the T5 if you are not solely
focused on uh text rendering tasks. So
yeah,
and of course it matters quite a bit.
You might want to ask does MMD matter at
all? And it turns out that it it does
matter like they tried all forms of
different uh attention variants. They
tried crossd. They tried u and mmd seems
to be the variant that gives you the
lowest validation loss. And they also
show that validation loss is fairly well
correlated with the kind of image
generation matrix that we care about
such as geneal uh and so on. So yeah and
it sca scales fairly well but it needs
QK normalization and thanks to the
concurrent set of works they didn't have
to reinvent QK nom from the scratch. So
thanks to the you know uh developments
in the regular transformer literature
they were able to just use Qenom to
solve the training instability issues
and I think stability fusion 3 is
basically incomplete without this
picture and and and I'm not showing this
picture just for fun but also because it
shows how complex is this prompt and how
well stable diffusion 3 was able to
interpret this prompt and get us a
creature like this. So I must give
credits to the authors of stability
fusion 3 who came up with these kinds of
prompts but it does fairly well. So it
was among among the first kinds of
models that shows impressive prompt
following ability and also while also
preserving uh the details that we care
about. So that was cool.
and and mmdit didn't stop here. There
are different flavors of mmds that I
wanted to uh discuss like in in in
stable diffusion 3 all the transformer
blocks followed the mmdit uh flavor of
attention and it's computationally
demanding I mean if you have if you have
worked with transformer encoders you
would appreciate the computation the
computational intensity of mmds because
you are having to kind of maintain
separate projection ction matrices for
the different modalities that you are
working with. So it's computationally
extremely demanding.
So maybe we could com combine mmd blocks
and regular did blocks to be able to you
know better utilize the flops.
So conceptually this becomes this. So
you have some number of mmd blocks you
concatenate the final representation and
then you operate on the concatenate
concatenate space and basically do
vanilla did you do not do mmd and you
end up utilizing the flops a little bit
and that's exactly what recent models
like flux from black forest labs they do
so
so another another twisty one could be
you have modality A, you compute output
A by passing it through a bunch of
transformer blocks and then you have got
modality B, let's say text embeddings,
you pass it through another set of
transformer blocks. You concatenate
these outputs and then you pass them
through another set of trans transformer
blocks and then you basically have your
final output.
And in this way you can configure all
the different all the different blocks
in their own manner like the the the
transformer blocks for modality A could
be different from the transformer blocks
that you would use for modality B. So
this way you have a greater level of
flexibility and control. And that's what
the Lumina 2 work did. And as we can see
for for conditions they pass it through
a separate set of transformer blocks for
for noisy latent they pass it through a
separate set of transformer blocks and
they they end up concatenating them and
then again they have another set of
transformer blocks. So transformer
blocks on the on the left hand side uh
in the in the RHS big block can be
different from the transformer blocks
used to model uh the noisy latence. So
you have got like bit greater
flexibility and control
and and I want to give you a sense of
how we can think of simplifying all of
this design because it might feel
complicated at this point in time but uh
I don't know maybe we can simplify it
quite a bit but I I want to quickly see
if there are any questions at this
point. Do we have any questions over
zoom? Yeah, we got some online
questions. Um,
let me see. Somebody just asked, "Is
GPT40 a completely different
architecture? How does that compare with
um the diffusion transformer?"
That's a good one. I think it it uses a
hybrid uh architecture. It definitely
has an LLM component to it which was
evolved to uh generate images. I'm going
to come to this sort of hybrid
architectures in a moment. Okay. And
then someone's wondering for evaluation,
are there good automatic metrics for
image and video generation or is it
mainly human based subjective evaluation
similar to creative writing? I think
it's an ensemble of different matrix
like you can't evaluate an image on a
single uh matrix like and also it
depends on what you are exactly looking
for like if you are more interested in
compositionality
the matrix will change you are more if
you are more interested in aesthetics
the matrix will change so that depends
um let me see what are your thoughts on
the vision
um someone noted yeah there's a common
perspective about like image generation
models failing to generate things like
fingers. Um I also see that you know on
Reddit posts and stuff. Um do they still
suffer from things like counting and
like spatial consistency or are those
basic things pretty much like solved? I
think models like flags definitely uh
they do a whole lot better, right? Yeah.
Um
and there's a question like what are the
major additional challenges of video
generation compared to image generation
and ways to overcome them? Well, the
first problem is the time because image
generation uh diffusion based image
generation models are already compute
intensive and then with video generation
models you have got another dimension of
temporality.
So they just become more compute
inensive and then you have got more curs
of dimensionality uh to to basically
address and then if you are generating
more and more frames they just become
more and more computensive. So how do
you how do you kind of make them more
efficient is definitely the need of the
R. It also adds things like temporal
dependencies. Yeah. Yeah. Exactly.
Right. Yeah. Another access of
dependency to model. Right. And you are
basically doing full 3D attention which
is extremely prohibitive to even think
about. So right
you have the video like you wouldn't
have to sorry I didn't in the video you
don't have to generate frame by frame
from scratch. You already have something
more like figure out and then just do a
small change.
Well, I mean if you if you take uh if
you take a 2D image generation model and
if you try to conflate it such that it
can also do spatial temporal generation
well it doesn't turn out uh it will work
well at least in the realistic setting
like if you wanted to generate cinematic
frames it won't work because the spatial
temporal consistency it just gets lost.
Oh, but but but but there has to be a
limit, right? Like if you are operating
with that many frames as your previous
input, your your like the Q also becomes
extremely prohibitive. So you have to
figure out how how how you can compress
the temporal dimension effectively. Like
let's say you have a variable number of
frames. Now how do you map it on the
latent temporal level so that it still
has some meaning? uh to it while being
efficient at the same time. So when you
are doing videos, you no longer just
have the special temp compression but
also you have temporal compression. And
how how do you model the two as you as
you as you make progress? So are there
any other questions?
I'll just take one maybe.
Come on. Zoom asks, can you give some
intuition about adaptive layer
normalization and why it works so well?
Oh yeah. So, so for for layer norm, so
you you basically using layer num for
stabilizing training, I would say like
you have more stable representations
across the across the across the blocks.
But for images, there are certain kind
of characteristics that you would want
to model beyond the standard
representations that you are computing.
and in and you will have to let those
kind of let those features flow freely
into your transform blocks and that's
why you need the modulation parameters
otherwise the interaction in between the
normalization parameters and your
regular attention features or whatever
MLP features that you are computing they
don't get to interact uh in a way that
will benefit the generation performance
if you were to deal with just
understanding or maybe just
discriminative performance it wouldn't
have mattered that much much. But if you
care about stylistic aspects and
fidelity, you need to kind of modulate
uh the additional features that you are
getting from the uh visual uh cues.
Yeah.
Any any other questions? Yeah.
Masking for for mmd. Yeah. Yeah.
Flavors. What's the next best thing? Is
there an alternative to masking? Maybe
that's a hunch you. Yeah. So may why
would you need masking? That's a good
question to ask for because if you if
you are so mmd mmd was done in order to
benefit like in order to get away with
the un directionctionality bias that you
may have in your text embedding
representations. So that was one.
Second, if you have really long prompts,
you do not need to compute masks in the
first place. Right. Yes. And it also
turns out that it's always better to
have long prompts like descriptive
prompts rather than having to have short
prompts. So that is kind of a handwavy
way to answer this question. But long
story cut short it's really non-trivial
to add masks when you are doing mmd
attention. So uh there you go. So that
was about doing separately 2kb text and
an image. How about on the image side?
Yeah, you you so when you are doing the
image image interaction, you could in
theory do masks, but again, how would
you frame the problem? Where would you
end up adding the masks? If you are just
doing text to image, maybe maybe if you
have another form of conditional
control, maybe you would want to mask
some of the interactions there. But if
you are just restricted to text to
image, where would you add the masks in
the first place?
What I'm asking to avoid masking, you
know. Oh, yeah. Yeah. Yeah. I mean,
probably that's why they didn't do
masking in the first place. Maybe their
motivations. Yeah. Yeah. Exactly.
Exactly.
Uh I'll maybe take one final question if
there's any.
Okay. Cool. Uh so I I I also want to
leave you with some ideas for
simplification simplifying the design a
bit if these things felt a little
complicated because they do do not have
to be complicated at all. we can
simplify it quite a bit. Uh and let's
see how
so how much is parameter sharing uh uh
is useful like things like adden that we
saw and the and the and the work on
pixard alpha that reduce the computation
by 27%. How much is that kind of
parameter sharing is useful and we saw
at Alan already. Can we also share QKVO
and the MLP like Albert? Like this is
from back in the days Albert where we
shared all the projection matrices for
for a couple of layers. We also shared
the MLP matrices and so on. And do we
really need like self attention and then
cross attention or do we really need
MMA? I think this will probably answer
your question. So look for I look
forward to that. So do do we really need
these things because this kinds this in
a sense complicates the design space
quite a bit. Can we simplify it?
So can we basically do self attention on
this concatenated space? So we do not
have to do self attention on noisy noisy
latence. We do not have to do cross
attention on noisy latence and text. We
do not have to do mmd. Can we basically
concatenate all all the image tokens and
the text tokens and compute self
attention on it? Can we do it?
And text encoders like what's the secret
source? We are using three, we are using
two. What helps uh what helps the cause
of text to image generation at the end
of the day? It turns out you can
simplify things a lot. So one thing that
you can do is you can parameter share
quite a bit. You can parameter share
QVO. If you are looking for efficiency,
you can definitely parameter share the
uh adaptive layer norm uh parameters and
you can basically do self attention on a
concatenated uh representation space of
image tokens and text tokens. So this is
I think good news but not so much
because Apple didn't open source this
work. So we'll have to do our own but
this is good to know that you can
simplify uh the design quite a bit. So
the extreme right hand side is the
simplified design that I was talking
about. So you you are basically
operating on a concatenated space. Uh
you are you are reducing the adaptive
layer num parameters quite a bit and
then you are parameter sharing the QKV
projections as well as uh the MLP
layers. So yeah and it turns out turns
out to be working well fairly well I
must say in practice. Uh so the green
one uh is the is the simplified design
and it always gets the lowest amount of
loss. So yeah
and as as I was mentioning other than
sharing the adaptive layer num
parameters you can also uh share the QKV
parameters as well as the MLP if you if
you can compromise some of the quality a
bit and if you are only targeting
efficiency
and for text encoders uh the Apple folks
found out that birectional clip and
texton LLM is better. So instead of
using a combination of clip and T5, if
you use clip and a regular large
language model, it's better for text
representations.
So the performance is pretty good. The
final the final row is Apple's work.
It's called date year. So turns out
fairly well all the bold uh numbers from
date. So it turns out pretty well. You
so long story cut short, you can
simplify the design quite a bit. So you
do not need mm data as it turns out but
we will see I guess.
Now one burning question you must be
having at this point in time is text to
image is liberating but how do I how do
I inject more control more sources of
control like if I were to do more
structural inputs to my text to image
model. How do I do that? Maybe I want
the model to follow a particular pose.
Maybe I want the model to follow a
particular segmentation map and so on
and how do I do that and can I combine
multiple structural signals uh at the
same time. So
one could be to learn maybe an auxiliary
network that that gives you a way to
compute salient representations from
your structural image signals and maybe
you then figure a way out to inject uh
those structural signals into your base
uh diffusion model. So that could be one
and control net these lines of work uh
they basically follow uh follow uh they
basically follow this philosophy
and then maybe you could change also
change the base diffusion transformer
model. you basically increase your input
channels to accept, you know, more more
controls. Uh, and that's what the flux
control framework does.
And maybe you could also learn a small
adapter network to model the
dependencies between all your conditions
and your uh uh and your noisy latent
tokens.
And also one important call out here is
structural control will always have
spatial correspondence but other tasks
like subjectdriven generation or image
edits they may not have direct spatial
correspondence. So what do we do in
those cases and and this is again an
active active area of research.
And for videos, well, rope works fairly
well uh for positional encoding. And I,
as I was mentioning, the attention
computation space becomes way more
prohibitive because it's full 3D. And if
you were thinking about some form of
factorized attention, it doesn't work. I
have been very explicit about it. Uh and
and for efficiency, if you are
particularly interested in efficiency
related literature around video models,
I highly suggest checking out the LTX
video work. And for performance, like
for fidelity, photo realism, and so on,
I think one has to be has to be my
favorite. It's pretty good. Uh I have a
little demo here. It's not that bad. So
it's it's still short short form video
but the realism aspect and the fidelity
aspect of these videos I think they have
improved quite a bit
and some next generation architectures.
Now I'm coming towards the end of my
talk. Uh I wanted to also give you a
flavor and a sense of next generation
architectures like you probably have
this question how do we enable in
context learning in diffusion models
like in language model it's very common
zero short learning and so on. How do we
enable in context learning in diffusion
models? Current architectures are
clearly not sufficient to enable it in a
reasonable time. So the basic idea is
you take an LLM model, you add some
components so that it also becomes adept
at generating images like recent works
like bagel then there are works like
Lada Mada they they they basically
follow this area of work. They are not
necessarily diffusion based but they
they have they share a similar
philosophy.
So you basically start from a
pre-trained LLM, you add components to
it so that it also becomes adept at
generating images like you could do auto
reggression on discrete tokens for
example and you could also do at the
same time diffusion on the continuous
tokens. So that's one line of work
that's called transfusion.
So as I was mentioning there this
playground v3 this fused it this
transfusion fused it is from our group.
It's the only open-source work that you
will probably find uh that tackles uh
this problem of in context learning and
how do you sort of explore these
architectures uh in a holistic manner.
Uh and if you are already feeling
inspired, I hope you are feeling
inspired to explore these architectures.
I high I highly welcome you to check out
the library that I work on at hugging
face. It's called diffuses. uh we have
got reasonably clean implementations of
all the models that I discussed today uh
which should probably uh inspire you to
hack into these things and tweak them.
And there's a bunch of things I didn't
get to cover. Of course uh I am a little
bit over time. I think 1 minute over
time uh I'm probably going to finish it
in the next 1 minute. So I apologize I
didn't cover MOS hot topic again but are
making their ways uh in the diffusion
community it's called hydream I didn't
cover training at all there are all
kinds of shenanigans there uh how do you
do data how do you do alignment how do
you do post training how do you do
safety mitigation how do you do
memorization mitigation and so on and of
course these architectures go well
beyond image and video generation they
find their application in all sorts of
stuff like like robotics, gene
synthesis, uh and so on. And if you are
into mechanistic interpretability,
interpretation of these beasts are are
not trivial at all. So they interest me
quite well. And yeah, that's about it.
Thank you.