welcome to uh week five of
cs153 uh we have
today with us the CTO and co-founder of
cursor so we switch things up a little
bit yeah we're keeping it
spicy we heard folks wanted some gnarly
details on on the infra under the hood
and so Michael very kindly offered to
let swall take us behind the scenes the
usual drill um we're going to spend the
first half uh talking a little bit about
some of the questions that swali and I
have ched about before and then the
second half we're going to go through
the questions from the Discord so get
your questions in I think um you'll see
SW tag in there in our Forum Channel go
crazy um he's offered to be fully
unfiltered uh and so you're welcome to
ask anything thanks for coming so of
course all right first question just
give us a sense of the scale that cursor
is at today um okay so scaled by like a
factor of 100 um 100 or more in the last
s year um some of the things even more
and so like on custom models we maybe do
something like 100 million mools a day
uh if that does not sound scary to you
that is scary uh and you know we're
pretty substantial portion of like the
Frontier Model traffic uh we're starting
to sort of host you know some of the
large models so uh and then on the
indexing systems there's like they sort
of go
through
uh a billion or so documents uh a day
and probably hundreds of billions over
the lifetime of like of the company so
you know some some of these things have
gotten like some of our data stores have
gotten quite big um uh yeah it's now
kind of a service at
scale it's been fun
many many lessons along the way yeah so
la last week we we uh we had benman one
of the co-founders of
anthropic here and we got into the
subject of of coding AI assisted coding
and so we did a quick poll on how many
people here have used cursor basically
every hand R up um and
then I I you know we it became clear
that everybody you can take for granted
here that everybody kind of understands
the product experience but why don't you
just take us a little bit under the hood
um and walk people through what's the
infrastructure that actually delivers
that product experience you were talking
about so at this point I think there's
like three Three core things so there's
the indexing systems there's two or
three of them uh the most famous one is
sort of just the retrieval systems uh
but we also spend a substantial amount
of effort sort of indexing G and uh you
know some of the other things to really
understand your posit stories uh that
are like get quite large so like you
know maybe the size of like instaart or
some of the bigger companies you've
heard of and then there's sort of the
model model section so there's uh the
autocomplete model that sort of runs on
every single keystroke and that means
you know we're at any point in time
doing on every second 20,000 is model
calls do this Fleet of something like
2000 h100 or like a th h100 something
like that
um that's that's just the and so and so
that that infrastructure is now split up
over you know much of it is is on the
east coast and some of it is on the west
coast like Phoenix and Virginia uh but
then some of it is in London some of it
is in Japan uh and
Tokyo uh so it's it's got like at some
point we tried to have a Frankfurt
deployment that was a little bit
unstable um so now now that that the
gpus are pretty spread across the world
so like in in general if you're in Japan
you you you still get a relatively fast
experience of the auto complete uh and
then on the indexing side you know sort
of starting to scale up pretty large
retrieval systems that um like if you
ask a question to the to the agent you
know and it goes in searches the
repository uh you know that's that's
certainly being scaled at like you know
pretty high pretty high throughput now
so so you said there's the indexing side
the models and then there's a third
pillor um so so the the three things
about cursor right now so there's the
indexing uh there's the models and then
there's like uh the the the rough thing
that is the product which involves like
lots of clever tips and tricks to make
make you feel like you really enjoy you
using it so there's for example this
like apply model that is served uh and
part of the apply model is like pretty
gnarly sort of uh apply tricks um some
some of which on the sort of inference
side uh so you you have this idea of
sort you want the apply to feel
relatively fast uh to the point where it
feels like you're not even using a model
at all right it feels like all your data
is sort of copy paste uh but obviously
it's not actually copy paste it's this
model that's run over like you know
100,000 to a good or 200,000 tokens or
you know stuff like that and and
architecturally what happens when
somebody decides that they want curs and
then okay so so the third pill that I
forgot about is it's like the entire
streaming infrastructure for like you
know how we how we store the data that
comes in and how we use that for
creening and all sorts of things that
are like uh running in the background
once you've sort of that it's not a sort
of real time it's not the thing that
like you're querying it's not the thing
that like uh you're directly interacting
with but it's the thing we use to make
cursor better for for everyone every day
and and um what happens from the moment
architecturally on when when somebody
says okay here's the my code base but I
want to now interact with the editor to
the point where you run inference and
you get it
back
um kind of I feel like it's like kind of
traditionally everything under you know
so there's um so usually you know they
they hit our service in the east coast
uh we're we're pretty monolitic
architecture so everything is one big
monol that we deploy uh we try to deploy
the so so one of the interesting Parts
about doing this like service scale here
you're you're trying to make sure that
like usually blast radius of like the
things that are um things that are
really critical it's like kept in in
like a much more secure section than
like the blast radius of some like
experimental code that someone wrote uh
a common thing that used to happen is
you know okay so this like September
maybe maybe June of 23 or something like
that or July like everything is one big
server and like someone would I only
write infinite Loop uh you know infinite
Loops obviously happen uh and this was a
pretty gnarly infinite loop it's sort of
like if you do one of our ifue problem
SS like we ask you dbug said infinite
Loop um and that would take down like
chat for someone and and you don't you
don't want some of like the core
services to go down like you don't want
login to go down if if someone like
accidentally writes an infinite loop on
the server and so one of the things that
like has become really important is sort
of this compartmentalization of the
servers so you get to one of like
hopefully your asking like composer to
go write code over your code base uh
while you're typing uh there's like many
requests that are being sent to figure
out the relevant things that will be
selected from your code base to go into
into the final prompt um and then then
we have some bidirectional stream of
like the model taking actions on the
server on the infer side and that
getting translated to any many any of
like you know clients in I don't know
India or Pakistan like you know you do
your thing and then the servers results
are being communicated back and forth
and uh one of the things we've tried to
design
for so so usually you know when we
started off it was like oh you know
things things are mentally complicated
so you would write these complicated
things but nowadays you know there's
like a strict ruos on the on the server
because if it too complicated you don't
understand it you can't run it um that's
been sort of become quite an important
part and as you guys have um scaled
inference there you said there was
roughly about 100 million mool a mool a
DAT yeah okay so that's independent of
the Frontier Model traffic so there's
like yeah out so that inference is just
selfhosted um curser models yes right
then you've got the whole other inflence
you rely on the model providers for yes
roughly what does that split look
like I don't I don't know the numbers I
can I can tell you independently but
like I don't know how to compare them or
and and these model providers are like
like in terms of like number of input
tokens I think like obviously the number
of input tokens on autocomplete like
very much dominates the frontier models
because the autocomplete thing is like
hitting tens of thousands tokens like
every single keystroke that you click
and and um what are you finding is it is
your our biggest
challenges working with third party
inference whether that's anthropic or
open AI gcp versus having full control
over your own microservices um oh my God
yeah
um well so there's a lot of fun
inference stories I think the tldr
inferences I don't think people have it
quite figured out I mean obviously we
run these services at like global scale
and you know everyone else was run them
but like still everyone is like
relatively
mature
um you know like it's like the the the
thing you have to be really careful is
like you TR which provider for what
thing uh but uh in said unnamed provider
uh that that you usually interact with
you know they're um
you know their inference for example was
like getting stood up when we were sort
of scaling up and we would like sort of
go to them every day and be like oh like
you know we want like you know 10
million tokens per minute more like 100
million tokens per minute uh you know
scaled up at Peak traffic and you know
they would crash at 30 or 40 millions of
tokens per minute uh you know you know
they had they hadn't had their caching
figured out I think a lot of the things
so one underappreciated fact about these
things uh especially model calls is how
uh there's a traditional sort of this
cold stru problem when you're running
the server so the the co start problem
says something
like um imagine so this we've s of shot
ourselves in the foot many times imagine
you're running something that is you
know something like 100k requests per
second and like all your nodes die and
so all of a sudden like nothing is
working uh you might have something
where like you know notes usually can go
up one by one by one if you if you go up
slowly and you don't sort of prohibit
people from making requests like the 10
nodes that you brought up out of like a
fleet of a thousand will get smashed by
every single person's request and so
before the 10 nodes can can even become
healthy you'll just you'll just kill
them and so you know before the 10 can
become 50 you know you you just kill
their 10 notes so there's like a coold
start problem on all these services and
uh I know we'll go into one of the
incidents later but one of the the
tricky Parts about going from a really
bad incident recovery is this like
problem you have to do these coal starts
uh or like you have to try to at least
kill some of the traffic or uh
and many of the favorite providers you
have have like various tricks of being
able to kill traffic you know on our
side we have some priorities of users
and we try to
like don't like you know or or we just
try to kill everyone at the same time
like it will works uh WhatApp for
example you know tries to use a prefix
they will find uh certain prefixes that
are really important to them and those
one if if WhatsApp goes down completely
then WhatsApp will just could try to
bring up one of those fixes first before
they bring up every single person
because you can't serve every single
person everything is done like you can't
you can't do it I mean model providers
have like go look up their status Pages
they all have historically terrible
reliability no one has good reliability
right and we're going to we're going to
get to that um but you know a
a a a core concept of infrastructure
which we've talked about previously in
the class is a big part of owning
infrastructure is and scaling it is
entrop high stakes entropy management
right the world flows entirely new
attack vectors it two as you scale um
and and systems break which is the only
constant in the in the entropic system
is something will break um and then the
question is how do you respond to an
incident like that so let's talk about
an incident what what what recently in
the last 12 months of the insane scaling
is one of the most challenging incidents
you've had to deal so what are I I'll
talk about two um so let's start with
indexing so when when indexing started
so September 23 okay so so I'll try to
give a two-minute world tour of indexing
so it starts off as this thing on on
GitHub that we later are like uh if you
add a lot of buttons that people have to
click to index their codebase no one
will index their codebase so you have to
make it totally automatic and the only
way you can make it totally automatic is
it happens when you open up the editor
and if we can't index you know your sort
of default allowed us to index or Cate
we will justess index we will not ask
any questions no matter how big it is
unless it's like not at the size of
install cart we'll just index the C
Straight Up
and we eat the cost okay so so we're
starting to write a new thing and um the
way it works is it computes what is
called a Merkle Tree on the client and
then a Merc Tree on a server and what
that means is sort of every single file
gets hash and every folder's hash is the
hash of its children up to a root hash
and then the way we figured out if like
something has changed so you know you
quit your computer you uh opened up your
computer again you did get check out
from a year ago you boot up cursor
cursor figure out everything that has
changed from the server to the client
and the way you figure it out is you uh
you sort of defend you know desend this
tree so you find that the root hash the
hash at the at the root node is very
different from the hash of the root node
on the server if these two like hashes
are different then at least one of the
folders has changed underneath it has to
have because otherwise the hash would be
the same so okay so you you descend down
and you find which which of the folders
has changed and maybe you find out that
like the server folder at the top level
changed so you descend down in the
server folder and then you find the
hashes of all of their children and you
find which of the sections have changed
maybe the section that has changed is
like inference and then you design down
into inference and like down to the
point which you find the files that have
changed uh so this is this back and
forth communication where the server
knows something about the state of the
files the client knows something about
the state of the files and you're trying
to reconcile this
state uh
um so when this inference system uh
sorry this indexing system was going up
uh we
had well we have a few problems so first
um we're living on this uh database
called yugabyte uh so uh when I was at
MIT at later when I was studying I was
like a big databases fan and in database
world uh there's maybe two or three sort
of amazing databases that like you think
of as these like the solution to all
your problem problems so one of them is
is this Google database called spanner
um it's like really famous for being
global scale then there's
um a database called Foundation Tob uh
which is really famous
and and then there's sort of these KV
stores like redish redish Etc these are
sort of like really really famous dates
there there's others but like those
those feel like you know usually if you
have the three of them you could make
everything worth like maybe maybe you
need some Analytics
and uh one of the descendants of spanner
is the state of Bas called yugabyte so
we're we're on yugabyte and uh I was
thinking man you know we have to scale
this thing let's choose like a a thing
that like scales infinitely and ubite
has this property where like it scaled
really well and we cannot get yle to run
just you're not we're paying a lot of
money or sort of try to scale down as
many nodes as we can and it just it just
wouldn't run and a lesson in life you
should
uh we move that workload to RDS and it
works like a charm uh so don't don't
choose a complicated database go go with
a hyperscalers you
know they know what they're doing their
full is really good use use pois don't
don't do anything complicated oh so so
we we we moved this workload to post and
and so the the STS of the time look
something
like as soon as you would turn on
traffic the database would get too hot
and basically me you die and so we do a
lot of complicated tricks and so the
reason this was happening was because we
were doing a very large number of long
transactions and uh civiliz of
transactions especially when you do
these like globally globally distributed
databases they have to do a consensus
protocol and the consensus protocol can
to take up a lot of time uh so so while
full Scrat you know a single node would
have no problem whatsoever you try to do
globally distributed version of it you
get like a complete show uh this is
try to you a bite like if you run it
well presumably it runs really well but
you should start off with post uh so we
we moveed to this this postr world
and uh almost immediately uh we hit a
massive spike in traffic and the first
thing that happens when this massive uh
Spike and traffic is we have this uh
enormous cach in the middle uh that runs
on one of these AWS Serv is called
Dynamo and there's a slightly gnarly bug
in the code where if you have a large
enough file
uh it it is not cached on Dynamo and we
don't know that so we're not exactly
monitoring the error rates on this
database and
so uh we missed this fact and so what
happens is the people who have really
large files uh they try to embedded
Dynamo has a m so uh you go to the
embedding model uh okay now because your
fire is really big the embedding model
actually gets a high enough load on this
uh on on this thing and then um we have
another narly r condition on our Q uh so
one of the things that happens is sort
of you know once you've done a lot of
the chunking and embedding and stuff you
sort of save before you could commit the
transaction you have to go update the
hashes of all the things above the tree
and this hashing happens on a que the
que is a waste condition especially when
it has to do with large files so large
files are not getting committed and so
your client discovers the ha large files
not committed they said it again well
now you get a Miss on the cache again so
you go to the embedding mod
and you don't commit it so well you try
again and so we noticed at this time
that like load just keeps going and
going and going you have no explanation
of what the hell is going on um because
the global erates look they look totally
normal like there's everything is the
problem is the only thing you're missing
is like these loadbearing
files uh and so that that was a pretty
gnarly week because the entire merkl Tre
reconciliation was happening just as a
the merry would only miss these enormous
like 60 line files and those those would
C all the dramaa so so walk us through
the so so um presumably a bunch of angry
customer support calls start coming in
people's I I think I think we like
stopped we ignored all of them you know
uh and and I think like we just dug it
dug into the code until uh until one of
us noticed well we first noticed the
cash hit rate being a little bit weird
and and once you start do do to this
cash hit rate uh you're like well you
know let's let's monitor her very very
carefully once we noticed the once we
brought the cash back on you then
immediately notice uh that why where you
start F not getting committed and then
you had to hunt down and you could find
these race conditions uh but the but the
race conditions on Qing are uh I mean
the race conditions if distributed
systems are are if you go to distributed
systems that's everyone will tell you
they're really gnarly and hard to find
and that does not make it any easier in
real life to find them uh like even if
you know that you probably have a race
condition finding it is is enormously
difficult and it comes down to just
um I guess I guess a lot of car thought
but yeah so so you're in the War Room
what what now that you've the fun War
Room the fun War Room uh is so so once
we fix
everything this machine this runs
beautifully for like eight months no
incidents nothing yeah I probably I
forgot about the dashboards we have like
two data do dashboards completely forgot
about it life is great and
and
um one day uh I wake up to a lot of PES
and and you start look diving into the
pages and everything in the system is
going haywired uh so the cach is is is
in trouble like the embedding models are
are causing a lot of trouble and we pin
it down to fact that like our RDS uh now
has something like 22 terabytes of data
and RDS if you know has a limit of 64
terabytes uh so actually that moment can
you just walk through what it took to
diagnose the root cause how did you
pinpoint we had some database alerts we
had had some database alerts that like
okay you're probably running up against
like storage limits I thought like 22
terabytes meant like oh we had a couple
months so we'll like you like casually
deal with it later usually if you hear
like 20 out of 60 probably not that bad
right um uh but the answer is no not not
not in postr land and the reason it's
not in postr land is because uh the way
our work our workload works is uh every
time you update a file we delete the
entry or we call an update of the entry
um uh now one of the core differences
between post and MySQL is that MySQL if
you call an update it just like goes to
that record on the dis and just updates
the record that is not how postc Works a
post and update is actually a delete and
an ad um so if you call update on a
record it actually deletes the record
and adds a new
record uh and if you have a a workload
where the only thing people are doing is
typing
uh well the only thing you see is
updates which means the only thing you
see is there's enormous numbers of
deletes and enormous number of ads and
uh in postgress a delete is just like a
tombstone it just like marches a dead
rail helps the index don't don't go to
that rail in again but it doesn't
like I mean you you know you could just
think about it on dis you know there
record record record record record uh if
you delete thing you know the memory is
not being reclaimed uh so you're you're
just constantly at deleting and reing
these records but like uh there's a
background process called a vacuum that
is meant to in the background like clean
up all the things rewrite it to another
block and like reclaim that space and
give it back and
um the the reverse of this happen for
something called transaction idas which
is called the anti- transaction thing
now okay going into all these details
because what am I watch to tell you if
the vacuum and the antiv vacuum both are
going he wire um so we we notice okay d
is not happy right now uh and what a not
happy database looks like is like all of
a sudden like I mean the transactions
are kind of going through but then it
start and then like it's like a car that
just you know you start it and then it
just grinds to a halt and just goes
everything goes down again then you look
do all this effort to like kill the
traffic
um uh you know slowly clean up all the
back transactions you start traffic
slowly again and then boom it grinds to
Halt so you're just having this like
it's like just imagine a car that just
like you know shuttering it's just like
not moving and so so for a couple hours
you know okay we do this and
and yeah I can't remember what exactly
happened but at some point realized the
database even stops booting up back in
uh so now you know emails are pouring in
so you know everyone's really mad that
indexing isn't exactly working uh and
because the data is now completely
grinded to Hal we can't even do your
queries um
so at this point there's um a friend of
ours called Martin right I I call
Martine I'm like Martin we are in big
trouble uh do you know any RDS SCS so
you know we call up AWS support has no
clue what's going on uh so uh we
like like at least there's a few people
in the team that are extremely talented
I mean one of them was the you know VP
of infrared GitHub so he knows his
databases uh up you know up down
Center
and uh so now we're on the call with
these like uh RDS Architects the people
who sort of written the database and
they're like well gosh uh I can't can't
tell you anything uh you guys are in big
trouble and they like well very helpful
very helpful um so now there are two
kinds of people in STS in my personal
opinion there's like the people who sort
of are like get shuty uh and then
there's the people that really come
alive so we have uh one of the
co-founders he just really he does not
like day-to-day infra but he loves Zs he
just gets like really happy you the
happiest you ever see him is you know in
the middle of a SV everything is grind
do know what a SV is a SV means
uh like like an incident like a
something going wrong okay so this is
like this is stressful like because
everyone is like can we you know
Michael's yelling like can we can we put
the service back on like you you really
want the service to go back and healthy
uh and at whatever
cost uh so we are faced with a few
options we
could so the first thing we
do right so so we had we had this all
this extremely nice schema structure uh
where like some of the tables had like
four end keys and other tables and so
like that means like once you delete a
record in the in the I don't know how
many of you have been to database crash
but like you delete a record in one
thing and it's sort of like automat you
you have all these nice foreign Keys uh
foreign Keys add a lot of load to the
database because it has to sort of do a
lot of pointer chasing to figure out uh
so you sign one guy you know go delete
all the foreign Keys you know that your
job is to make sure you alleviate the
load in the database delete all the
foreign Keys um we assign another person
to go uh you
know rewrite the load uh have like so
one of the TBS out of the 22 terabytes
one of them is a 20 terabytes or like
your job is to try to delete this t as
fast as possible you know completely
change the workload uh we assign another
person to like go so one of the things
that like kind of special about the S is
because we have quite a few really
talented folks you can like really try
very crazy crazy ideas and like let them
uh do it and the SE team was staffed
mostly by inter the internal INF or did
you have did you have the the vus uh you
know live op
support this is the
uh then there's a few people who are
sort of like manually sitting in the
postris console and deleting
transactions and trying to bring the
post to be healthy uh and uh one of them
is trying to do like a migration of that
database onto uh like trying to like
spin up an old replica of it um and like
this point we had maxed all the
parameters this is like the biggest RDS
you can find on AWS you can get a bigger
RDS than this um
yeah long long story
short um so at this point you're in
full-on process yeah it was fullon and
long story short in one of the craziest
things I've ever seen the guy who is
supposed to rewrite the entire workload
succeeds faster than the rest of us at
and bring it back on and so uh you know
he relo it to run on like
uh uh so pause for a second Side Story
Side Story is one of the trends in datas
in the last uh few years so there's like
this database world runs on these like
really interesting Trends so uh you know
obviously post is really old but say
they kind of the early 2010s was these
large analytical
engines um uh and so the most famous of
which is snowflake but then there's data
rcks um and then there's like lots of
various op Source versions of these
analytical engin and what's famous about
these analytical engin is they do
vectoral operations and so Theory really
fast and uh you know a recent a recent
Trend that uh I really like is this idea
of writing databases on top of uh object
storage so object storage is something
like S3 R2 uh your blob Etc and object
storage has been optimized to death and
is extremely
scalable and uh relatively fast and very
very very high reliability there's
nothing in the world that is more higher
reliability than object storage and the
one of the hardest parts about writing a
database is the storage layer the
storage layers
relatively can get really messy uh
there's all these weird things you
really have to carefully worry about to
not have corrupt data and so uh our a
recent Trad so variations of this is um
is a company called warp stream that was
acquired by confluent and what warp
stream does is a rro kfka which is a
famous sort of streaming system uh to
run on on blob storage so that's the the
main idea of the handed company was to
move kfka to blob stor which me kofka is
like
um if you're ever starting an infer team
the thing that people will tell you is
never run Kafka like it's it's like
cancer it goes and you know never can
never can really get it um and so
another uh provider we really like and
rely on is this company called tribo
puffer uh that does a Vector database
also on object
storage and so now back to St so I tell
this person let's try to move this to
object storage so this is in the middle
of it app I'm like your job rewrite this
on object storage uh the biggest table
that's storing the chunks and uh he he
actually manages to move it to object
storage before any of the rest of us uh
because you know this is one of the
longer running stabs that we've ever
ever had it you don't know if you'll
ever get your database back online um
and so then we sort of remove a lot of
the workload off the database and we um
um a full essentially at this point
you're like well we just need a full
refactor we're doing a full new
migration yeah you're doing a full
imigration in the meanwhile you know
your customers you're like scaling up
your inference capacity because if to do
this new migration you have to like move
re-embed every single person's gold base
that you've ever embedded I mean this is
Charn of Charn of data and and what
point did you make the call that look we
just debug we we can't save the current
instance anymore we've got to do a full
new instance uh what like 10 hours in
something like that all right and and
what's the hero stick going we can't we
can't resuscitate the patient anymore
the the corpse is dead we we' just got
to I don't I don't remember when I made
made the call but
it I mean it wasn't like that risky it
felt like the kind of thing where it's
like I mean the thing isn't running
anyways right like it's not running like
you nothing is happening so you might as
well just let traffic onto this new
slightly refracted system that like you
know someone just tells you ah it's like
my code is you know no bugge in this
code you know no no test needed no
nothing I just wrote it two hours ago
and you're going to run like the highest
T service that we run on this uh this
code is like relatively complicated like
any any small change to the code uh
because it's like a super highr pipeline
any small dent can just like blow up in
her pipeline so it's it's a very uh
messy thing to run and yeah I mean uh
this was one of the co-founders Arvid
and I trust my life in or he sort of you
know he does he does his thing uh we
Rite it on the
Fly um and so it goes on it goes on Bob
storage and uh now we still we still
want it on blob so there's there's
actually a new new project to actually
moved the entire thing to bobge kill
kill all the all the databas in the
middle uh because
uh uh the best way to scale a database
is to just not have a database you
know I love this story um mostly because
completely unprompted you've probably
seen this almost like a beat the similar
parts of the story that we had in in
lecture one if you remember with son his
co-founder Arvid was basically uh you
know our son uh when we were dealing
with the Sev outage if you guys remember
with M Journey so I just want to make sa
for the record that was not
coordinated but you'll see over and over
again you know the physics of of
incident response end up looking dram
it's extraordinary how often there's one
person on the infro team who ends up
being pivotal to refractor that then
ends up being a pretty steady state
solution for much longer than you expect
anyway so that was fantastic thank you
we've got a bunch of questions piling up
so we're going to switch to student
questions the first one's from we're
g one funny one funny for uh part part
about this is um
this is not like the worst that we had
the wor the the second worst one
obviously we had like like a week and a
half ago so C was down for like 230
minutes or something this uh and usually
it's like it's like these really small
things like you can't really blame the
person like one one of the you know the
the this really bad set where we sort of
lose all of our noes happens uh because
someone makes like a single line change
that is if you look at that change like
you wouldn't have got it um um but like
you know sometimes in in in in our in in
this new in the new sub where uh this
like single line change C is like
sometimes models can catch it actually
kind of funny and uh see like it's kind
of it's kind of cool to have these
like sometimes like you can be protected
by have have models review your code uh
you know they'll find they'll find
things you don't predict and probably
probably save you a lot of time and pain
how far are we from just having a full
automated set response team if it's AI
agents all the way down um
I I you know I I don't think we're like
that far from Models like being
revealing your code and cashing really
really gnarly bugs uh in this again in
this particular case the model would
have caught the bug if we had run the
bugbot uh like Chris is going to release
a bug b we had run the bugbot we would
have caught the S and uh in this
particular it like felt like not
important change
and terrible this was on on the scale of
you know classic Sev seev is um severity
levels in is s is short form for
severity um on a scale of s one to five
where would you put this the most recent
one is like you know I guess one's the
highest one so like one um wow okay it a
be zero yeah all
right uh should we questions do
questions okay cool first one from son
at this time I'm just going to read them
aloud so that we don't have to waste
time rep repeating were nervous about
building a cluttered space we GI up
copilot codium Etc and how did you think
about differentiating I I keep these
questions are always always overplayed
um so the reason we started this company
is
because
well so so all of us had been had been
uh watching scaling laws in college and
and had you know been really interested
in Ai and like our first thing was we
should we should build some sort of uh
coding product and we had sort of talked
to away in passing but at the time I
mean copal had felt like a true Nemesis
because at you know copad and Microsoft
and openi just like like the Dream Team
it's like why would you ever why would
you ever go there that feels like a
horrible idea so you go through other
complicated ideas that are like uh
really messy but the copar didn't change
at all for like a year and a half I mean
you saw the auto complete
was the AI the first AI product was uh
you know kPa auto complete and and then
they make no changes and and one could
clearly see that the ceiling was really
really really high I mean I I truly
believe the ceiling you know goes up to
automating a lot of engineering and you
couldn't see like anything past
autocomplete and that that so like I I
think it was like it's like a n
phenomena that there's a lot of uh
people but like where the longest time
there was basically no way um cool it it
only feels cluttered in
retrospect um the second question is a
quick one are you gonna offer Stanford
students a discout on cursor
um uh fun fun step story um
I I'll come back to the answer in a
second so the fun St story is uh people
have been uh trying to get free tokens
because we're uh one of the largest
uh on the Frontier Model inference like
uh one of the largest group but uh you
know inference users like in in terms of
tokens were're like one of the biggest
on the planet uh uh people have found
various ways of
exploiting uh exploiting cursers uh you
know team structures and stripe and all
sorts of to like try to get free
tokens uh I.E this is a invitation if
you can find a way to get free tokens
and uh report it to us we will uh we
will give you a free subscription but
only if you find uh you know a bug
responsible disclosure guys remember uh
find find a bug find a way to get free
tokens and uh and then and then we'll
give you a free
subscription uh a lot a lot of a lot of
time has been spent uh blocking spammers
who really find most creative ways um uh
the one from two nights ago was there's
some some guy I I don't know where he is
he's he's managed to find a way to
create like uh tens of thousands
hundreds of thousands of Hotmail
accounts uh just like a relatively a
stable domain it's not even the shitty
domain uh and uh he sends graphic from
like I don't know 10,000 IP addresses
and you know 100,000 uh users sort of
sharded and
you you have to spend a lot of time sort
of like analyzing the traffic to like
block the spammers so uh you know if
Michael wasn't a fan of the free trial I
I wouldn't do anything is is he just
trying to Dos you what what what's
Vector here um oh just try to get free
tokens from the free trium so he's
actually G workloads yeah assumably he's
trying to run his own service on he's
trying to get some code done okay cool
um working around rate limits this from
sure of how do you work around rate
limits for foundation model apis do you
have an Enterprise contract that has
high enough rate limits that you don't
have to worry about throttling or was
there any interesting infra engineering
work that had to be
done um there is indeed a bunch of infra
in fact one of the messiest parts of the
system is the hand the system that
handles uh weight limits and um
tokens uh Andre I don't know how much
time we have I I don't know so it's it's
like we about seven
minutes the one minute version is yes
it's really messy uh we run over
multiple providers they go down all the
time we try to be reliable on top of
them yes we run into rate limits I um
there's a lot of a lot of so
like for for some of the model providers
feel like they're one of their biggest
customers or their biggest customer
which means a lot of the time is Go is
is spent into like please give us more
tokens uh and they're like we can't give
you more tokens and you're like well we
would like we would we would like more
tokens and yeah then you go your we're
basically in the middle of like live
negotiations uh you know that that
mirror a lot the early days of of
provisioning negotiations in the cloud
era but I don't think anybody was
prepared for the the relative amount of
inference workload jumps that are
happening right now but just to pain a
picture of of what I think is happening
is you know I I got a uh email from Aman
one of your co-founders I think it was
the night before 3.5 Sonet had come out
saying an like who had anthropic and you
know get us the whatever tier four um
and so and and and they're they're
calling so so you guys are calling
anthropic and Tropic is calling Google
because they run on tpus saying when the
hell can we get three times more tpus
and then the TPU team is calling their
Borg team you know who are the folks
racking and stacking the the infras
going how soon can you bring online more
tpus so I think what you're trying to
say is it depends on the day um and and
who in that stack is the well well both
both you're there are two things
happening one is where any any of the
particular inference providers you're
like calling them up all the time saying
we need more inference uh and uh one of
the other things that happening is
you're sort of calling a multiple
different providers uh so like uh either
you're trying to like for your own gpus
you're trying to call a bu room provider
so you can be like multic cloud of the
different uh your own models or if
you're runting son it you're calling up
like I don't know AWS and uh Google
cloud and and ovic at the same time and
you're like which of you can you know
give us more tokens back and and then
you try to balance users on on these
things and uh and then their sales teams
are on a race condition basically to try
to get to you yeah yeah uh fun times we
we're going to ask you again next year
the same question um or see how the rate
limits are going that uh the next one is
on security of code from Ashley which is
how does cursor AI consider that it
reads the code of programmers
considering that some code maybe
proprietary private is this info on a
specific programmer's code at that point
technically
public uh sorry I I couldn't make C Jil
as a question but it's the question do
we care about security uh the answer is
yes um a lot a lot of time and effort
and pain and sweat and tears have been
ped to making uh the security really
good
um we not going into to too many details
uh even when we're sort of embedding
code we do various encryption encryption
te techniques to make sure that like all
your vectors uh that are stored in the
database are actually encrypted uh with
a key that lives on on your device uh so
even if someone gets like a hold of the
vector database which is like quite hard
I mean you'd have to make sure like the
Google Cloud security or something like
that but in in the worst case the still
can't make heads of it because the
encryption Keys is on your device um and
so uh
and uh I'm not sure anyone else does
this but because it's uh we're runting
code that you know for opening eye and
all these other things uh I feel a
little bit safer at night knowing that
there's a key even though I'm I'm like
99.99% sure there's no way to go from a
vector to code uh but because it's it's
not some provable fact about the world
it's it's better to just have this
encryption key
and
uh I don't know it's like it's like
difficult obviously it's like it's like
a responsibility
and uh you know we we try relatively
difficult uh you know tricks and things
to like make sure that we don't
up uh the next question is on the end of
non- theoretical CS at
Stanford is it time to pursue
math
um sorry is is it like you don't need to
study any of it or does does curse does
the power of cursor mean that basically
the the all the investment and actually
I'm understanding computer science is
largely a
waste wa come on
I I I have a job to do you know like
um there's like the unreal version of
this and there's the real version of it
the unreal version of it it's like uh
you know will will none of us have jobs
and
um obviously like more and more of our
work will get automated right like they
they is like um a
boring unimportant work that goes into
maintaining some of these systems that
are is unnecessary but is there no
reason to spend time architecting and
Greening up new systems I I think that
is just like kind of untrue in fact uh
probably the thing that actually happens
is that like you can actually be more
creative because for a lot of these
systems you actually need a lot of
people to build uh as these things get
more and more complicated uh you need
you need a lot of people and in fact
having
um being able to collaborate with models
on this will actually be like a I I
expect a lot more system from the future
than than not
um I another word of saying is I I don't
think cursor would be uh you know doing
as as much sort of uh we cover a lot of
surface area on our infosystems uh with
uh a very talented team but also because
of AI assistance and I I I expect that
you know ratio you get bigger and bigger
and you know I expect us to do actually
like really really difficult complicated
things
because uh because the models are there
to help you with like the boring uh un
meaningless aspects like I don't know
like adding a adding a variable to a
function call is not something that like
it's it's like asking like you know is
is is like a football player the only
thing they're doing is like moving their
legs I mean they are but is that the
most meaningful part of it um I we've
got time for a couple more since we did
attendance at the start so I'm going to
keep going
um the next question is from Akira on
will Ides become obsolete in the future
do you think IDs will continue to play a
significant role in software development
given the rapid what's happening in I
mean it's it's a question of what what
do you define as an ID I mean would
there be a tool that programmers use to
write code
yes great moving
on uh the next one's from
sorry there's there's several questions
about student discounts uh so we already
cover that one uh dropping out year and
a what's your take on whether models are
expensive but like they're so useful
like they're worth more than a burger of
you know just you know pay the $20 I
promise you it's it's worth the $20 I uh
like I I don't think you'll regret it
over like you know the the Marshal
Burger
you guys don't appreciate the amount of
time and energy that goes into well this
is not like a mean statement I actually
think we spend a lot of energy to try to
keep it to $20 uh the the the the much
easier thing we would be doing was would
be sort of like you know raising the
price because uh anyone in the industry
uh $20 is kind of meaningless uh to them
and and in fact like the reason we try
it like a lot of hard workare optimizing
the systems is just so like people
people can use it pretty easily
uh these are still not free I mean at
any point in time like if every
keystroke is doing like you know a
billion floating Point operations like
they are doing still a you know probably
actually 100 billion floating Point
operations it's just like a lot of flops
I don't know to tell
you um so you actually end up graduating
yeah you didn't drop out but the
question is would you recommend people
drop out or is it worth staying in
school on graduating before trying to
build
something I mean the thoughtful answer
is like it it C can you
actually it's really hard to tell uh on
the one hand the obvious question of
like did you learn anything uh from your
classes is like a yes or no I mean uh
much of the operational skill you have
to learn
after
um I still really enjoyed my distributor
systems classes I I made a lot of
friends along the way so uh I don't know
like I maybe the correct answer is
something like if the the choice should
be obvious to you right like just like
think about it for yourself and if the
choice is OB you do it it's not don't do
it I don't
know on that note we're going to end
thank you so much for coming SW this was
awesome