[music]
Hi everyone. Thank you so much for the
introduction. It's great to be here. Uh
it's great to have this opportunity to
share with you guys uh some of our
latest progress and efforts.
So uh one of our major pursues uh is to
build better open models and we believe
in democratizing intelligence. With open
models you can deploy anywhere. You can
be on your local servers, you can be on
the cloud and you can access every
single bit of the weights in the
modeling instead of just uh using a
black box. And this is one of the slides
that I took from Jensen's uh talk
earlier this year at CES. So as you can
see, open models are quickly uh closing
the gap with uh proprietary models and
it's reaching the frontier. And we
believe that with better and better open
models, we're going to u make
intelligence more accessible to anybody
in the world in every corner of the
world. But open models cannot be just
open. they have have also to be great.
So uh in this talk we're going to
discuss how we make open models great.
Uh so as we know uh scaling is a primary
driver uh for a lot of progress maybe
all of the you know major AI
developments that we have witnessed in
in the last few years and here we're
going to discuss how we scale our model
in different dimensions. So on the left
hand side the first figure you see here
is kind of the the standard scaling law.
So on the x-axxis you have the uh log of
the number of training tokens and on the
y-axis you have the log loss and as you
scale the number of training tokens you
get a lower loss. But here the point is
we're not going to just scale the number
of training tokens but we also want to
want to improve uh the token efficiency.
uh meaning that we want to move this
curve to the left hand side so that we
can achieve a lower loss a much lower
loss using the same number of training
tokens and this can be achieved by
having better architectures and
optimizers as we'll discuss in in our
later slides and the second scaling
dimensions that we're very interested in
is to scale the context lens so as you
can see in the second second figure uh
if we increase the context length then
we can uh have a much higher accuracy in
terms of predicting uh the token loss at
a given position. Uh and this means that
we can increase the capability of the
model to achieve more complex task by
increasing uh the context. So this is
the second scaling dimensions that we're
going to talk about. And the third
scaling dimension is the number of
agents. So we introduced this new
learning paradigm of agent swams where
we can we don't just rely on a single
agent but we also uh orchestrate a swarm
of agents that can accomplish the
subtask in parallel so that we can
increase the task capacity and we can
translate all of this in into the
language of agents. So if you look at
token efficiency, it's mostly about
having a stronger prior so that you can
uh have more efficiency when you do
agent RL to search for a uh better
solution. And you think about long
context is it's mostly about increasing
the context length so that you can have
a longer running agent. It can probably
run for days or even weeks or months to
accomplish more uh more more tasks more
uh complex tasks and about and for agent
swarms is is another dimensions that
that add to it and at the end of the day
we're going to have a swarm of agents
that each of them have a super long
context and each of them have a very
strong prior for us to uh search uh in
this entire agent RL system.
All right. So we're going to start uh
from token efficiency. So this is one of
the most you know classical figures in
the history of machine learning. Right.
So it's taken from cap Kaplan Adel and
it basically says that if we scale
proportionally the number of training
tokens the model parameters and also the
amount of compute we can get lower and
lower loss. And this is you know one of
the major breakthroughs that that the
entire community uh has achieved in the
last few years to to get uh better
intelligence. But here what what we're
interested in is is to have better and
better uh token efficiency. And uh
here's the thing. So one thing that I
would like to emphasize is that token
efficiency is not just about efficiency.
is actually also about improving the
upper bound of intelligence. So here
here's why. So uh suppose you have uh
say 50 trillion tokens, 50 trillion high
quality tokens and then you apply this
new optimizer maybe the m optimizer and
then all of a sudden you have a two
times token efficiency. So it means that
it's almost like magic that you get uh
equivalently 100 trillion tokens. Uh and
nowadays we are scaling towards the data
war and we're hitting you know the data
war and the amount of high quality data
is quite limited and if we suppose that
is a constant amount then we increase
the token efficiency it means that uh
we're going to get better intelligence
out of it. It's not just about
infrastructure efficiency. It's about
you know better uh intelligence. So so
this is why we spend you know a lot of
efforts in this aspect because it's
going to push uh the frontier of of
intelligence and m optimizer is one of
the things that we have heavily invested
in uh since last year. So it's a second
order optimizer and basically every
single gradient update is transformed in
a way that each entry is orthogonal to
each other and this is very different
from the traditional atom optimizer and
if if you implement this optimizer
properly you can get a two times token
efficient efficiency improvement. Uh so
we we are one uh we are the first uh
work we published the first work to
demonstrate that SM optimizer is
actually scalable for LLM training and
these are two key techniques that it we
employ to make it effective for large
scale training. So one of them is decay
it it is critical for scaling to larger
models and the second is uh we want to
ensure a consistent RMS updates compared
to Adam. So we have this uh adjustable
coefficient that is applied uh to each
update so that uh the uh resulting RMS
is going to be comparable to Adam and uh
to make MIUI memory efficient across all
this uh Nvidia GPU clusters. We also
develop a distributed mumm optimizer
implementation that partitions the
states across uh the data parallel group
so that we can have a very efficient
imple implementation for the mum
optimizer and these are some of the
results uh that we presented in the
paper. So as you can see with with the
same number of parameters and the same
number of training tokens we just
replace the original AdamW optimizer
with the new MU optimizer is going to to
improve the performance across the board
uh sign uh significantly.
But there was uh this new challenge that
we encounter when we try to scale it up
further. when we try to scale muon for a
one trillion parameter model we
encounter a new issue uh about training
instability. So as you can see on the
left figure we uh we observe that the
max logits quickly explodes and quickly
exceeds 1,000 and the typical values for
uh for uh training for this max logics
is about say 50 or maybe less than uh
100 but for uh for m it quickly exists
1,000 and at the same time we observe
training uh divergence on the left hand
side. If you look at the trading loss,
uh it goes down a bit but then at the
end of the day it explodes and it cannot
converges uh as expected. So this is one
of the technical challenges that we have
to to address. Uh and the solution to
this is to introduce this new technique
called uh QK clip. So basically what it
says is that for each attention hat in
this entire neuronet network we're going
to in the forward pass we're going to
compute the max logit and then we're
going to calculate a dividing factor
that can be applied to each uh key
projection as well as the query
projection so that we can uh sort of
clip the maximum uh value of the query
and the key to to sort of constrain it
into a a given range so so that uh we're
not going to have exposion anymore. Uh
so these are some of the empirical
results. On the left hand side there are
two curves but there are strictly
overlapped with each other. So these are
the training curves before and after
applying the clipping technique. So you
can see uh the clipping technique does
not affect uh the training loss uh uh uh
decrease at all. But on the right hand
side if we inspect uh the intermediate
metric if we inspect the max logit it's
going to be effectively uh constraint.
So it first expose as before but at the
value of 100 it's going to be clip at a
constant value for a long time and then
after a certain number of steps will
just naturally go down. uh so the neural
network sort of uh find a way to uh
constrain the maximum value of the uh
max logic to ensure a stable uh training
process and at the same time it doesn't
affect you know the training convergence
as shown in in the in the left figure.
So we employed this technique in our uh
K2 model training and successfully
scaled it to one trillion parameters.
And this is uh the first example of a
large scale mong training in the history
of machine learning.
And the second dimension that we're very
interested in is isl context. So this is
another figure. It's probably less
known. uh is is one of the hidden gems
in these papers. Uh so instead of just
you know pushing down the training loss
by training on more tokens, it has some
uh uh insights from another perspective.
So as we can see this is a comparison
between transformers and LSTMs. So on
the left hand side we can see that
transformers achieve a lower training
loss given the same number of parameters
and the same number of training tokens
as expected. And this is why
transformers become you know the you
know the sort of the de facto
architecture that people are using right
now. But on the right hand side it's
really interesting to see that
transformers are actually better because
it can improve through the whole
context. So the x-axis is the token
index in context. And if you increase
the token index, you can see that the
training loss of transformers actually
drop by a lot. If you just continue
continually increase context lens, the
loss just continuously drops down. But
if you look at you know the curve of
RSDM, it just is saturated after a
certain uh number of tokens. It means
that transformers have this better
capability of capturing longer context
and this is this is what makes it uh
better uh because if it if you go back
to like 10 years ago uh people use LSTN
for tasks like machine translation but
it is not good for for example
understanding entire codebase or running
a super long agent trajectories to solve
uh a a uh for example writing Linux
kernels uh from scratch. is not going to
be accomplishable by STMs. So this is a
very uh much neededed capability in the
era of agents because tasks are becoming
harder and harder uh and we need longer
and longer context. Uh so the research
idea here is to develop a better
architecture so that we can uh
efficiently scale to a longer context
length and at the same time achieve a
lower per token loss at uh larger token
indices. And this is the motivation uh
for which we introduce this new
architecture called uh Kim linear. And
it's uh contains this new uh linear
attention variants called uh Kimmy delta
attention which improves the original
uh delta rule GDR uh by improved
recurrent memory. I will show the
details later. And at the same time,
we're going to mix linear attention
layers with full attention layers using
a one to three ratio so that you can
balance between uh this long context
capabilities and at the same time having
a more efficient uh implementation.
So this is uh some of the formulation.
Uh the basic idea is simple. If you look
at linear attention uh in the original
formulation uh the memory is going to be
global. So there is a global single
decay factor that is applied along the
way. So it means that uh basically if uh
there are only two cases in one case is
in one case you're going to forget
basically everything and you're not
going to retain any information and in
the second case you can choose to retain
you know almost everything but at the
same time you don't have the capability
to leave out some of the unnecessary
information in this long context. So we
introduce this key idea of having a fine
grain uh decay factor as shown in this
highlighted alpha term. So it's going to
uh instead of being a scalar, it's going
to be a a diagonal matrix which controls
uh the decay rate for each channel. So
that we can have two possibilities. For
some of the channels, we can uh decay
really really slow, meaning that we can
retain this long context information
across a very long uh range. And at the
same time, for the other channels, we
can sort of quickly forget uh the
information from the past indices to
refresh it and observe new information.
And this is uh to increase the
expressivity uh of this model.
And of course to leverage modern GPUs we
have to use this chunkwise uh
formulations so that we can uh paralyze
the computation on modern GPUs. So the
first equation here is the chunk uh
chunkwise um formulation of uh Kimaria.
But as you can see this is going to
bring massive infrastructure uh
challenges because of this newly
introduced alpha term. Uh because now it
is a matrix instead of a scalar it
cannot easily be factored out. So to
achieve a efficient implementation uh we
rewrite the entire equation into the the
bottom three equations. Uh so it we
introduced this matrix inversion
operation as well as introducing uh the
uh cumulative decay factor so that we
can implement this entire thing in
parallel without sacrif sacrificing uh
any efficiency and more importantly this
is not an approximation. is an exact uh
mathematically equivalent formulation so
that we can achieve much efficient
implementation without sacrificing uh
any loss in terms of uh performance. So
it's going to be as efficient as uh you
know previous linear attention variance
but at the same time much more
expressive. So these are some of the
results that we obtain uh using a fair
comparison. So on the left hand side we
see the performance on two different
types of task. So MMAU is a short
context task. So for short context task
uh Kim achieved a better performance
compared to MLA and GDN. And at the same
time for longer context task such as
ruler uh Kim linear is uh also better
than the varants uh the other variants
while being much more efficient compared
to MLA.
And when we scale the contact lens
further to for example 1 million tokens
or even longer uh it's going to be much
more efficient uh compared to uh the
baselines. And this is also uh the first
architecture that can outperforms full
attention across across the board uh
including short context task uh long
input task and long output task.
So these are two uh key dimensions that
uh we are interested in and the third
dimension uh is the agent swarms. So
here's a diagram to showcase how we
design this agent swarm paradigm to
solve some of the more complex task
compared to single agent paradigms. So
here we have an orchestrator or you can
call it a main agent. It's responsible
for orchestrating task. It has different
options. For example, we can spawn uh a
group of sub aents and assign new task
to these sub aents or you can collect
the results uh from the return of these
sub aents and you can sort of uh
performing this process in an iterative
way and at the end of the day you can ac
accomplish a more uh complex task
compared to using one single agent and
it's analogous to to human society. For
example, if we build a a company, uh we
need different roles and we need for
example uh orchestrator or maybe we need
a CEO to to decompose and assign the
task to different rows and then at the
end of the day uh the entire
organization is going to have uh to move
towards this same goal. And here for
example in this case we have maybe you
have the AI researchers uh you have the
web developers you have physic
researchers and they can study different
topics and at the end of the day you
just collect the results and spawn uh a
group of fact checkers and web
developers and file downloaders to um to
assemble the results to into a a a
single report.
And this is another pers perspective to
to look at uh this new paradigm. So the
x-axis is the complexity of the task uh
and the y-axis is is the execution time
and the complexity of the task is
measured by the accuracy of uh a group
of models uh on on such task. So we can
see with agent swamps it's going to uh
substantially uh uh in uh reduce uh the
execution time uh compared to uh uh
compared to single agents. Uh it's going
to be more effective. Uh and this means
that we can scale uh this agent swarm
paradigm to uh for example if you run
this uh agents roams with 100 or maybe
even 1,000 sub agents you can accomplish
a complex task within a certain period
of of time that is tolerable for um for
to producing real economical value
and we can we can certainly scale it in
different dimensions. We can scale the
inputs. For example, we can download and
read hundreds of sources or even maybe
thousands of doses in parallel or you
can output uh write a 100page literature
review uh in uh in parallel or you can
take actions at scale. You can perform
data analysis uh for 10 different tasks
and also it is orchestration at scale.
You have to learn to design subtask and
aggregate the the results.
And technically uh we define some new
objective functions to guide the
learning process of our agents realm
system. So there are three rule
functions uh reward objectives that are
uh considered here compared to uh the
conventional single agent IO learning.
So the first term is what we call the
instantiation reward. It incentivizes
sub Asian instantiation to prevent uh uh
this uh serial uh collapse uh phenomenon
from happening. So basically we don't
want it to default to single agent
execution. We want to encourage uh the
parallel executions especially uh when
we when when it's early stage in
training. uh and of course we can decay
the weight for uh this instantiation
reward time over training course because
uh when it learns to uh learns uh par
execution we can reduce uh the weight
and the second term here is is finish
reward uh and it is used because we
observe one of the things in training uh
that uh some of this uh subtask are just
created but never finished. So it's
almost like it's going to hack the first
term by just spawning a bunch of sub
agents and the task might be too complex
or maybe the task just doesn't make
sense. And here we use this finish
reward to basically encourage that each
of the subtask should have a relatively
high ratio of uh completion instead of
just spawning a bunch of uh pseudo
tasks. We need it to be uh meaningful.
Uh so this is the second term that we
use and of course we use the same you
know decay strategy. We use a relative
highway at the beginning of training and
we decay it to a relatively low weight
at the end of training. And of course
the third term is the standard term uh
is is the outcome reward. Uh it's going
to measure whether the entire task uh is
completed. Uh and then we're going to
add these three terms in our uh
reinforcement learning uh system. And of
course we have to build you know the
entire infrastructure because uh right
now you need to support the parallel
execution and then you need to support
different reward functions uh and and to
you know maximize the efficiency of the
entire agent swarm IO system.
So here are three uh different things
that that we have uh tried scaling. Uh
the m clip optimizer uh improves token
efficiency and Kimmy delta attention uh
in the Kimmy linear architecture
improves long context and we also have
the agent swarms paradigm to further uh
create a new dimension of scaling and
all of this put together uh we created
uh Kimik K2.5 a new model that we just
released uh over one month ago. Here's a
short video to demonstrate some of its
capabilities.
[music]
>> [music]
>> Heat. Heat.
[music]
>> [music]
[applause]
>> So
yeah, there are a lot of interesting
things capabilities that we discover
from the model. For example, uh it
merges the visual capabilities with
coding capabilities. So a lot of new
things just emerge out of it. It can
read a video and then produce a website
that uh sort of replicates or style
transfer the original video and all of
this are due to successful uh and stable
training uh at the pre-training stage.
So this is also one of the most
beautiful curves that uh I observed in
my life. Uh so this is the training
curve of the K2.5 based model. Uh so as
you can see it went through over 15
trillion tokens and of course in K2.5 we
additionally train another 15 trillion
tokens and the entire uh train uh the
training process is just so stable.
There's no loss spike especially when we
introduce this new m optimizer. We
didn't observe any spike and this smooth
stable training process produces a very
stable outcome that uh a very strong
base model that we can fine-tune on top
of it uh to achieve you know new
capabilities as as we introduced and saw
in the video uh the video and this is
also of course uh trend on Nvidia H800
GPUs and each node in this H800 cluster
contains two uh TB RAM and AGPU use uh
they are conducted by MV link and uh one
of the another you know key innovation
of K MK2.5 is that it is the first open
model with native joint vision uh text
capabilities. So if you look at previous
open models, usually there are visual
capabilities added on top of a text
space. Meaning that for example, if you
train the text models for 20 trillion
tokens and then on top of it, you do
another two trillion sort of a post
training process to add additional
visual capabilities on top of it. Uh but
for K2.5, it's different in the sense
that we feel the training process of
vision and text from day one. So it's
called early fusion here. We start from
you know 0% of the progress. So from day
one we're going to merge uh the vision
and text tokens and as shown in our pre
preliminary experiments it outperforms
uh late fusion and some of the new
capabilities that we observe also come
from this training recipe. Uh for
example, if you want to do vision to
code, you really have to merge vision
and text into a single brand to achieve
that. If you separate these two brands,
it's not going to happen. You have to
align these two modalities into a share
embedding space uh entire uh a share
representation space so as to uh achieve
this. And another interesting thing that
we observe is that these two modalities
can actually enhance each other. So
that's uh that's been long been a
challenge that if you add vision
capabilities into a text model, it's
going to somewhat uh uh hurt the text
performance. But here we found that if
you train it properly, these two
modalities can actually enhance each
other. So this is one of the key
findings that uh we observe in in in our
training. Uh so first vision improves
tax. So this is so interesting. So
before vision RL the performance uh in
the first column and then we have the
performance after vision RL. So here
vision RL refers to a process that we
only use vision task. So there is no
text task involved here. We only have
vision task. For example, we teach the
model how to how to count uh how to
answer some of this visual QA uh
problems uh without any for example math
any coding problems in in in this space.
But we observe that it's going to
improve the performance for even you
know reasoning heavy text task and on
the other hand text also improves
vision. If you have a very strong text
base, you you actually don't need any
vision SFT data in the training process.
And this is the approach that we adopt.
So it's called zero vision SFT. Uh
basically we don't have we have
basically zero vision SFD data. And the
only SFT data that we have is the text
SFT data. And then we do a joint IR over
text and vision. And you can see that we
can achieve uh almost state-of-the-art
performance across the board on on
vision task without any vision data. So
it it's clear that uh if you have a
strong text base is also going to
improve uh the vision if if you uh align
these two modalities into a shared space
in your in your pro training.
And also uh these are some of the
examples of uh
uh yeah as I was showing the video. So
it's it demonstrates strong capabilities
of uh uh visual design and front end
coding and this also emerges from our uh
vision text for training.
So uh after all this so this all about
Kim K2.5 and as probably uh you probably
know we released our new architecture uh
yesterday uh in our tech report it's
called attention residue. So here I'm
also going to briefly talk about our new
work uh which serves as a a sneak peek
into our next generation architecture
that we're probably going to adopt in in
our later models. Uh so here the
motivation is is quite simple. Can we
apply some of our techniques that we use
in in the in the temporal dimension and
we we just take some of the inspirations
and we apply to the death uh dimension.
So uh and it starts from this residual
connection. So I still remember uh
listening to to uh Kami's talk uh at a
tutorial in in ICML 2016 10 years ago.
Uh so it was a brilliant idea. So
basically before RestNet uh nobody was
able to train deep networks. If you
increase the depth, if you increase the
number of layers for neural networks,
nobody was able to train it because you
observe this gradient exposure, gradient
vanishing, all this, you know, stability
issues. But then after the introduction
of of RestNet, we can train, you know,
an arbitrarily large number of layers.
You can stack as many layers as as you
want and you you you don't have to worry
about the training stability issue uh
and stuff. And as discussed in Ilia's
talk uh two years ago, it basically says
that residue connection is a variant of
RSTM but just rotated 90 degrees. So how
do you understand this? If you look at
LTM is is a variant of recurrent net,
right? And it's a recurrent u model
process. So we're going to take the
hidden states from the last step and
then we're going to have some gating
mechanism some function to produce the
current state right and if you look at
the uh the depth dimension residue
connection is basically the same we're
going to take the output from the last
layer and then we're going to apply some
sort of function on top of it to produce
uh the current uh uh the current output
of the current layer.
It's just the formulation is different.
For example, for residual connection,
we're going to use a fixed addition.
We're going to have this uh we're going
to add uh the previous hidden states uh
with the current output. It's just the
formulation that's different, but the
basic idea is the same. It's a recurrent
net applied uh in the dimension of
death. And but on the other hand we can
think about uh reformulating uh this uh
this function instead of having an STDM
can we have an attention in the
dimension of that and it's going to
create new possibilities because
attention have has been demonstrated to
be so successful uh in the transformer
era. So what we're going to do is not
just to take the last hidden state, but
we're going to consider all the previous
hidden states and use the attention
operation, the attention mechanism to
assemble and aggregate all of these
previous hidden states to compute the
current state. So this is exactly
attention rotated by 90°. uh is sort of
we view it as a natural generalization
of residue connections uh in the ASM
analogy. Okay. And here is the detail
formulation. So on on the left hand side
is a standard residue as I said it's
basically
rotated by 90° and the second figure is
attention rotated by 90°. So what we do
is to collect all the previous hidden
states and have a simple attention
operation on top of it to produce the
current layers outcome. Uh and of course
to increase the efficiency to reduce the
infrastructure for example communication
and memory overhead. We also design a
new variant called uh block attention
residue on the right hand side. So
basically the ideas is also simple.
We're going to divide uh all the layers
in the neural networks into multiple
blocks. For example, each block can
contain say 16 layers or it can contain
maybe four layers. And then for each
block, we're going to uh apply uh this
attention residue only on the output of
each block. But within each block, we
also we still adopt uh this standard
residue. So this is going to reduce a
lot of overhead while having minimal uh
loss in terms of training accuracy.
And these are some of the impressive
results that we achieve uh uh on this
new architecture. Uh so on the scaling
law we can uh improve the token
efficiency by uh 24%.
uh meaning that if you have 50 trillion
highquality tokens now you just
magically have uh uh over 60 trillion uh
tokens and then for the validation loss
you you can also observe that uh it's uh
consistently lower than uh the original
curve u demonstrating uh this stability
across optimization and also achieves
the best improvement uh on some of this
coding math and reasoning heavy task as
shown in the benchmark results of GPQA
uh math and human val
so the entire community uh keeps moving
forward uh and we're happy that we can
we're able to contribute to to the
community with uh you know new
technologies and some of this are h you
know some of these technologies have
been sort of standard and de facto for a
long time but as you can see we still
see a lot of opportunity unities to
improve it to uh to have revolutionary
new design to achieve better
performance. If we multiply all these
scans together, you can actually have a
much better model. So, Adam was invented
in 2014 uh and now we scale an open
source mirror and click a a dropping
replacement for uh for Adam. And I'm
sure that uh if you train a transformer
LLM uh it's going to be much better if
you use Mong clip instead of atom. And
attention was invented uh over eight
years ago. And then now we have Kim
linear which is a linear version. We
don't have to use full attention across
all layers. Uh we can have linear
tension that performs better on short
long context at the same time. and also
residue connections are now uh also
challenged uh we scaled in open source
attention residue. So I think one of the
uh interesting things about our error is
that we sort of adopt a different
mindset for for doing research. So if we
go back to 10 years ago it's mostly
about publishing a new idea. uh but then
I think the lack of the rigor of the
experiments is very hard to produce uh
solid experimental results. But now we
have this scaling ladder. We have uh
enough resources to you know trend the
model and run it on different at
different scales. We can have you know a
whole set of benchmarks to measure the
progress. So it is it becomes easier to
make confident and solid conclusion out
of it. And this is one of the reason why
we are observing you know new progress
uh on this ancient techniques and I'm
sure that we'll see more and more
especially in the open-source community.
I think we're going to have more and
more even better architectural and you
know optimization uh improvement in in
the next few years.
All right. So to summarize, we're going
to uh keep scaling our models. And so
these are three dimensions. Uh for
example, we we see uh we we see uh
different architectures and optimizers
that optimize all three, you know,
dimensions and we'll keep you know see
new dimensions for scaling. Uh agents
ROMs is is not the end. And we are glad
that we can uh move forward with the
entire open source community to achieve
better and better uh you know
intelligence. Thank you so much.
[applause]