the founder and CEO of Reddit uh with us
today. Welcome. It's great to have you.
Thanks. Steve is uh this is the third
year Steve has participated the class
and it's great to have you again. My
pleasure. Um so let's start at the
beginning. So you what
2005 you and Alexis are looking about
starting a company like how like how did
it get? Uh it's a long story. Um so 2005
it's almost 20 years ago uh which is
crazy to think about. So
um we had just graduated from uh
University of Virginia uh Y cominator
uh common
uh we had just graduated from UVA. Um we
had applied to Y cominator in the spring
with a different idea. Uh that idea
would probably be most closest to like
Door Dash today, but this was in 2005.
The iPhone didn't exist yet. Um many
restaurants weren't on the internet. And
so that idea was early to say the least.
Uh and we actually got rejected from Y
Cominator uh with that idea, but uh the
YC team liked us and so basically
invited us to come back like two days
later and talk about a different idea.
And so that idea ended up being Reddit,
but the the idea then was to build a
place where people could find new and
interesting content online. So we we
weren't talking about communities yet.
Um really was the kind of mashup of of
two websites at the time. One slash dot,
which I was a big user of. Slash is
still technically online.
Um uh it was like a it was it it was
headlines, news headlines around tech
news, but really what slashet was was a
community around tech news and the
community lived in the comment section
on on each of the posts. Uh so was a
mash of slash and delicious and
delicious was a bookmarking website. Uh
I had I don't even know if you guys
bookmark anything these days, but
bookmarking was a thing back then. Um,
and then Delicious was a website for
bookmarking and social, like sharing
public bookmarks. And among other
things, Delicious invented tagging, like
the hashtag. Um, but you could kind of
see this living list of what was being
bookmarked most often on Delicious. And
so, it's kind of that that dynamic
userpowered nature of Delicious with the
kind of community
uh newsy aspect of Slash. That was the
original idea of Red. Hm. And so uh but
you were providing you were basically
curating all the content sort of or was
it still was it community from the
beginning or when when did that switch?
So all of the content on Reddit was user
submitted and then user ranked which is
still how it works today, right? Users
submit the links or submit the the the
posts or whatever vote on them. And so
that was from day one of Reddit. It's
just we didn't have any users in the
beginning. And so we had a bunch of
tooling for for Alexis and I to
basically kind of seed the seed Reddit
with content. And so every morning I'd
wake up, I'd run a script that scraped a
bunch of other websites on the internet,
spit out all the new links, I'd read
them all, and then I'd submit them to
Reddit and I add extra little tooling so
I could make a new account and submit a
link at the same time so it look like
there's a bunch of users of Reddit. And
so we had to do this for the first like
two months of Reddit. And then I
remember it was in
August. I did a duo one day. It was like
a weekend. I forgot. I slept in. I don't
remember what it was.
Uh and then I I was worried when because
if it usually if I don't do that, I'd
open up Reddit and it'd be blank because
we'd only show links submitted within
the last 24 hours. And so if there
wasn't enough links submitted in the
last 24 hours or zero, the front page
would literally just be blank. And so I
opened up Reddit that day expecting it
to be blank. I hadn't done my job and it
was full of links. I was like, "Oh,
okay." And I was like, and I remember
looking at the usernames. I was like,
"Who are these people?" Um, it's not me,
it's not Alexis. And so that kind of
from that moment on, we actually had So,
it's purely organic. I mean, did you do
any kind of SEO or or No. So, SEO didn't
like SEO was irrelevant to us because uh
you know, SEO is relevant to us now. You
know, we get a lot of traffic from
Google, but we didn't have any content
in Google's index. Mhm. Um and so yeah,
it was purely organic. The the main
source of users was Paul Graham, one of
the founders of Y Cominator, so our
first investor, he uh linked to Reddit
from his blog. So somewhere around in
June, he had linked to Reddit. And so
Paul had a uh I I don't know, a few
thousand, maybe more than a few thousand
readers of his blog. I was a big fan of
his. That's how we learned about YC in
the first place.
Um, uh, actually it kind of comes full
circle. So Paul had a big readership on
slashdoc and so he posted to his blog. I
presume it was popular on slash dot.
Bunch of people clicked the link to
Reddit and that was the seed. So I don't
know we got maybe a thousand 2,000 users
from that. Got it. And that that from
there was just organic and and still now
which is amazing. I mean to do to do
something like that from the beginning
is just I think pretty pretty
remarkable. So, it's compounding in
growth. You've raised a little bit of
money. $12,000. $12,000. So, very little
bit money. Um, and then you as you grew
you then you sold it to Yeah. So, what's
that? Like tell us the history because I
don't think a lot of people know the
history. So, the brief history, we
started Reddit summer
2005. We sold to a company called
Advance.
um more commonly known as Kai Nast. Uh
we sold uh to them in 2006. So that deal
closed October 31st, 2006. So about 18
months
later. Uh and then I and the team uh
worked at Reddit under contract
basically as employees of Advance for
another three years. Uh and then we more
or less all left. Uh and so so started
2005, sold 2006, we all left uh towards
the end of 2009, few years later.
Um and then while I was gone, Reddit, uh
spun out from Advance and this was in
2012. Um they brought in an external
CEO. They spin out was the series A.
Uh they raised a series B at the end of
2014. I was I was gone. I was working on
a different company at the time. Um a
series B at the end of 2014. The CEO
then quit two weeks later. It was like
high drama. Um company kind of lurched
from one crisis to another. So the kind
of beginning first half of 2015 and then
I came back in the summer of 2015. And
were you the CEO from day zero or what
was um I mean I was the deacto leader of
the company though and we never used
that title um for the first yeah call it
four and a half five years and then I
was gone like I was in the team was only
six people when I left and three of us
more or less left together. Um the
Reddit actually was down to a single
employee
uh in the middle there. Wow. Truly kind
of amazing it didn't die. I mean,
especially like a continent like public.
Yeah, it was down to a single employee,
this guy named Eric Martin.
Um, and
uh and
so and then yeah, I came back in 2015.
The company when I came the company I
came back to was about 70 people. Um,
and it
was serious crisis moment uh at the
company.
Uh and now so it would be 10 years.
It'll be my 10 year anniversary this
July of coming back and now we're like
2,000 people. We're a real company. When
when you came back I mean as you said it
was kind of I remember it was going the
company was going through a lot of
turmoil. How did you assess the
situation and like what were the things
you started to change because like
obviously over these last 10 years which
we'll get into you've had to deal with a
lot of challenges content moderation and
scaling but hold off on that for a And
so the main thing was we do so our
content policy on Reddit for the first
10 years was very short. It was
basically we don't remove things. And
that was kind of the premise of Reddit
was
uh you know our our original thinking
was like we're not the gatekeepers.
We're building this platform
specifically to be powered by users and
to not have gatekeepers like us or to
not have gatekeepers the way traditional
media has editors uh the way slash do
had editors. We wanted to be entirely
powered by users. And so we said we are
not going to remove content. It's
entirely powered by users and the
voting. And this honestly worked pretty
well. We didn't have a lot of content to
remove. Mhm. Um there was a ton of
content critical of us. So in terms of
like bad content that we would later
face, like racist content for example,
it just we didn't really have it. There
was some there was some spam. There was
the occasional bad thing that we would
we would take down. It wasn't really
controversial. It was mildly
controversial, but there was so little
of It didn't really And then what
happened while I was
gone is Reddit both grew and then there
was a handful of communities that
basically popped up
to troll would be the most generous
description, but they had all sorts of
heinous content. It was really bad
stuff.
Uh, and the challenge was the team at
Reddit at the time, and I learned this
when I came back and I was at because I
came back, I was like, we need to fix
the content policy. We need to define a
policy, what's allowed, what's not, and
we needed to enforce it. That was the
main thing I had in mind when I came
back to the company in 2015.
Um, and when I was talking to the
employees at Reddit at the time about
like how they were thinking about this
and why they didn't hadn't done
anything, their explanation was, well,
we don't know how Reddit works or rather
we think it's fragile and if we make any
changes, we're afraid we're going to
break it. Meanwhile, we're just letting
this be on like our front page and
we're in the press for all of the wrong
reasons. Now, it was a small percentage
of the content that was really bad, but
it was getting all of the attention.
network. Uh, and so that
was bad. So I was like, look, we have to
we have to fix this. And so I remember
the first conversation I had with
employees was they were telling me,
we're afraid if we change it, we'll die.
And what I told them is, we are dying
and if we don't change it, we will die.
Um, and that was one of the the the big
changes. Um, and some of the folks were
on board with that and some of the folks
were not. Uh and so there's a lot of
turnover in that first year uh among
among those employees. I want to say of
those 70 a year later maybe 10 or 15.
Yeah. Wow. 10 and 15. Yeah. 70. It was
quite a lot. And honestly, if I couldn't
do it again, I would have done that much
much faster. Some of some people I let
go right away, but other people I let
quit. Like they just didn't like me.
They kind of hung on things and they
kind of, you know, eventually self-
selected out. But we kind of knew in
hindsight it was like very clearly not
going to work between between us and and
and those folks and I probably should
have just pulled the trigger. Yeah, it
it's hard in those situations though.
And it's easy to look back and say I
should have done it. But yeah, but I've
seen that same thing too where you've
got the people kind of ankle biters
that'll hang on that you think are going
to maybe turn it around and then just
cut people like there's like the ankle
biters or like maybe they'll turn
around, but there some people actually
are just bad. Yeah. Like either weren't
skilled or they were um corrupt in some
other way. Yeah, but the problem was I
uh I was still finding my own voice and
confidence in this because it was very
public. It was bright spotlight on us.
Um yes, I was a founder uh and and had
you know designed and built most of
Reddit at that point, but I also been
gone 5 years uh and wanted to be
respectful of the team that was there.
Um, and and so I didn't have the
confidence to like to to do it as fast
as I think we would have benefited,
which makes sense. So you you come in,
you say we've got to start putting some
guard rails around this. Like tell us
about like how you initially thought
you'd solve the problem and then how
that solutions kind of evolved over time
because, you know, today it seems like
you know you guys do a very effective
job uh at moderating, but I'm curious.
something. I'm sure it was not a smooth
road. It was not a smooth road because
so I learned this lesson. I didn't know
it coming in. So I came in thinking we
just need to write the rules and enforce
the rules. Well, turns out both writing
the rules and articulating the rules and
enforcing the rules are three separate
things and they're all very difficult.
Um because wherever the line is,
there'll be other ways of interpreting
that line of just kind of sticking your
nose over the line of pushing our
boundaries. And remember the context was
we had these users who were on the
platform to do exactly that like they
were there to um to be a pain in the ass
like that is what they were doing. Um
and so whatever rule we made they would
you know find some literal
interpretation of it that was
technically acceptable or you know just
made our lives full. And so one of the
lessons we learned in that is is in the
rules uh two things. one, we have to be
specifically vague. And so, you know, we
try to be as specific as possible to let
people kind of know what we mean, but
vague enough that there's some room for
interpretation. So, we can say things
like, well, you know what we meant. Bam.
Um, and so it it took us a little while
to find that. And if you look at our
content policy, so our content policy
today, it it's 10 rules, I think. Um uh
no hate, harassment or bullying, no
inciting or glorifying violence. Um no
doxing, no spam, nothing illegal. Um no
involuntary sexualization, nothing
involving kids. All
right? Uh no regulated
marketplaces. Every word in our content
policy is is is a decision. Is a lesson
learned the hard way probably. you know,
we we we've changed the policy, you
know, dozens of times over the last 10
years because, you know, we we'll put in
a rule, it's either too specific or
wasn't specific enough and this and
that. And so it really was a a work in
progress. It still is. Uh it it it still
is. And and then of course enforcing it,
we didn't have a safety. There was no
safety team at Reddit when I got back.
Um and so we had to create the safety
team and we had to create all of these
enforcement mechanisms because they
didn't exist at all. Uh the previous
management had had actually stopped that
for some reason. Um so you know we had
to get that going. And then Reddit is
different than a lot of other places
online. Uh yes we have our centralized
safety team now. Uh but we also have the
the user moderators and and the user
voters and and so kind of navigating
that whole ecosystem. her. Uh, you know,
it was a challenge. Uh, and it's it's
funny now I look
back, you know, there's a lot of hard
decisions and and the hard decisions all
seem so easy in hindsight because
they've worked out, but at the time they
were really hard decisions. And now I'm
just kind of sitting here and I
sometimes wonder like, why was that so
hard? Uh but you know that's I think
that's the way it goes sometimes when it
makes sense that you leave that kind of
kind of vague you know uh description so
you can provide interpretation. How does
that do you have a forum where you
review then and then how does that work?
Yeah. And so there there's a group of us
that meet um we meet every week uh
sometimes more frequently right like
right now more frequently
um that is you know me our legal team
our policy team our community team our
safety team and we go through these edge
cases you know this community is doing
that this this post is you know getting
some attention like this users are
behaving this way and it's like do we
need to make a policy change do we need
to do some enforcement do we need to
make a a structural change. Uh uh we've
done kind of all of those things in the
last few months. And so it really is uh
kind of a a work in progress. Yes. In
that work in progress, are there
examples where you look back and go we
we made the wrong decision to either
keep or remove? So the the like sort of
uh a tool that we didn't have in our
toolbox like the really the only
enforcement mechanisms that we had for a
long time is ban a user, ban a piece of
content or ban a
subreddit. Now we could get pretty far
with that but sometimes a ban is not the
most appropriate thing. user makes a
mistake um uh or a subreddit can be
salvaged uh you know maybe they've gone
off the rails but they can be recovered.
Banning up post is usually fine. It's
pretty low pretty low stakes. Uh and so
then we over the years we built you know
the the whole warning system for users.
So if you if you make a mistake if if
you post something that you know is is
uh is is violating the content policy
you get a warning then you get a
temporary ban you get a longer ban. like
you kind of got to be consistently uh
troublemaker to to get a permanent
sitewide ban, but we didn't have that in
the beginning. It was just like ban or
not. So, we needed that flexibility. And
then on subreddits,
um yeah, all we could do is ban for a
while. Mhm. And so, there are subreddits
where it's like, okay, they're kind of
going off the rails or uh they just need
to cool down. And it was tough. We let
some subreddits live longer than they
should have because we thought a ban was
too heavy. And there's some subreddits
that got banned that I wish we had a
little more flexibility. And so, you
know, now we have and actually we
recently just used, we could put a
subreddit in timeout so we can shut them
down for a week or two. Um, let things
cool off, talk to the moderator, see if
we need to make any changes there, look
at the rules, see if we need to make any
changes there. Um, so I wish we had had
the subreddit temporary ban over the
years. That would have been really
helpful.
Now, you guys went public about a year
ago, almost exactly a year. March last
year. Yeah. Cuz I think we you kid the
class like just a couple weeks after,
which was like amazing that you did
that. Um, after going public, have you
felt more pressure to moderate one way
or the
other? No, I think
um I think there has always one been
plenty of pressure to moderate one way
and the other. That that has kind of
always been the case.
Um, uh, I think all of these decisions
or often these decisions are in the gray
area. Because if there weren't if if
they're not in the gray area, we're
probably not talking about it. Yep. Um,
so if if if I'm talking about it, it's
gray area. If it has attention, it's in
the gray area. And if it's in the gray
area, people are going to disagree
because it's kind of, you know, it's
just kind of a fact of life.
Um, but I think Reddit, even without
being public, had a brighter spotlight
on it than than many private companies
just because it's so public. Like not
not public in the corporate sense, but
just we have a lot of users. Our users
care, the press cares, people, everybody
cares. So, I think it's always been um a
a little more in the spotlight than
typical. Um what I tell the company is
we shouldn't do anything because of
external pressure. We should listen to
the external pressure. Right? There's a
message there. It's important
information and we may not agree with it
and we may not agree with their motives
and we may think it's fair or unfair.
uh but we should always try to find the
truth in what people are saying or why
they're saying it and and then we should
make our own decision from our own
principles and values. So uh and I
always tell the company giving somebody
we don't like a moral victory
uh or not giving somebody we don't like
a moral victory is not a reason to not
enforce our rules or to uh live
according to our values. Mhm. So, for
example, right, somebody some some
journalist or blogger or whatever just
writes a real nasty hit piece. Uh, you
know, they're really loosey goosey with
the truth. Uh, you know, just as cynical
and uncharitable as possible,
doesn't matter. If they point out a
piece of content that shouldn't be on
Reddit, it better not be on Reddit and
we take it down. And if they find a
loophole in our thinking, um, then we
need to address it. Mhm. Uh, and I think
that that um I'm proud that we do things
that way. I think it's meant we've been
overall, I think, consistent, more
consistent than I think other folks in
the space um in in how we operate. So,
we're not kind of wildly swinging, you
know, this direction than that. Very
consistent. We we don't change because
the political winds are blowing this way
or that. We can uh we can look we can
point out all of our decisions and see
our thinking. Yeah. which is fantastic.
So, one of the things I I was thinking
about before this discussion is that in
that last year since we last spoke um
you at least in the press it's been kind
of reported that you've done various
deals with different companies working
on frontier models with uh to use some
of the Reddit's data because there was
speculation before that that folks were
and you weren't getting any kind of uh
compensation for that. Um can you share
a little bit like how how you think
about content ownership and that
monetization?
So, Reddit is an open platform. Uh,
always has been, right? You don't have
to have an account to see what's on
Reddit. It's pretty low barrier to
create an account. You can just post on
Reddit. Um, and we like that about
Reddit. It's important. I think it's the
only platform it size where you can
actually genuinely see just about
everything that's on Reddit. Um, I think
it's good for the internet. I think it's
good for consumers. I think it's good
for safety. Uh, on the latter point,
it's because there's no surprises on
Reddit. uh like if there's no skeletons
in our closet. If there's a skeleton on
Reddit, people are telling me about it.
Um so I think that's important. It keeps
us honest.
Um but in we've also been we had been
historically permissive about so access
and scraping. Um and our terms have
always said look you can you can um
scrape Reddit's content um as long as
it's for non-commercial use
uh and for search engines, right? we
really benefited from the kind of search
ecosystem. Uh what what kind of happened
over the last couple years is Reddit's
data is really valuable. It's really
useful. It's particularly valuable if
you're training a a large uh AI model.
And Reddit's data was used to create all
of the large AI models that exist uh
whether folks admit it or not. Um and so
our hand was kind of forced.
Um, and so we got in a position where we
went to the the partners that we're
friendly with. So, Google, OpenAI, and
said, "Let's let's do um let's make this
a formal
uh agreement." Uh, so that you know, you
know what you're getting. We know what
we're giving. Uh, it's it's a fair
exchange of value, and we can explain to
our user base, you know, what's going on
and what what the content on Reddit is
being is being used for. And so we told
this to the user base. So we created a
public content policy. I think we're the
first platform to create a public
content policy. Every platform has a
privacy policy which says you know what
what platforms do with your private
information. Uh and Reddit's privacy
policy pretty simple. It's like we use
your kind of behavioral information on
Reddit to run Reddit and it doesn't
leave Reddit. of a content policy for us
is well if you put something on Reddit
you're putting something on the public
internet and we will do our best to
block unauthorized scraping of it but it
will it's an arms race it will never be
perfect so don't put something on Reddit
you don't want it to be on the public
internet if you don't want it to show up
in search engines uh if you don't want
to show up in AI training because we
can't prevent it 100%. Then we said
we'll also uh license public content on
Reddit for these things for commercial
and non-commercial purposes. But it
comes with some stipulations, right? You
can't reverse engineer the identity of
our users. You can't use it to target
ads. If users delete content on Reddit,
we ask that it gets deleted out of, you
know, wherever it's going. Uh and so
we've done some commercial deals like
Google OpenI. We've done some smaller
ones for like social listening services.
We've done a ton of free agreements with
universities and researchers and things
like that. And so the the principle is
like look, it's it's uh it's open. You
put it on Reddit, it's out theirs. Um
and then if somebody wants to use it for
commercial purposes, you know, we're
open and open for business, but we'll
want to have like commercial terms. And
um I should have found this data, but
like give us a sense today of what the
scale of of Reddit is.
Um I don't remember posting comments off
the top of my head. I can tell you we
generate if you take English Wikipedia
uh the number of of words or tokens in
in English Wikipedia that's about how
many um tokens we generate in two weeks.
Um, so it's it's a absolutely massive
uh data source because it's interesting
that the community and conversation
product that's the core of Reddit. Uh
you're really only interacting with
posts from the last day or two. Uh so
you know if you go to you open the app
or you go to reddit.com everything
you're going to see is within the last
day or two.
Uh but it used to have been talking
about all sorts of stuff for almost 20
years. they've left behind this
absolutely massive corpus of information
that covers pretty much, you know,
everything that people are thinking
about going through. Um, and so, you
know, some of that is revealed by
Google. Um, but even they don't crawl
the our entire corpus. Oh, really? Uh,
and and so now we're revealing that with
our own with our own search efforts as
well. Uh, so even we we are learning
kind of how how deep it goes. Mhm. Yeah.
I've personally found that like Reddit
is by far the best place for news or for
any of these services to get more
accurate information. Yeah. I think
especially things that are subjective.
Yeah. Right. Um news advice kind of
things that people want to talk about
where there isn't, you know, maybe uh um
a a a easy objective fact base, right?
What's the best backpack? Well, I don't
know. Depends what you're into. Yeah.
How do I how do I get my toddler to
stick to the night? Well, depends on the
toddler. Um, so th those sorts of
things. Uh, or even like is this good or
bad? Uh, those sorts of things you kind
of you need the conversation. Yeah. And
that's what Red provides. Yeah. No,
those are phenomenal. Let's switch to
some questions from students because I'm
sure there's a bunch. Okay. Yeah. So,
the question is about paid subreddits.
uh what's our thinking there and how do
we do this so it doesn't alienate the
existing Reddit. So the idea here is
there's a class of content I think
that's just not on Reddit right now and
a class of creator that's not on Reddit
right now. Um, and and so what we're not
talking about, I think these headlines
sometimes get uh misconstrued
intentionally, I think, for what it's
worth, that we're going to take existing
subreddits or content on Reddit and put
it behind a payw wall. We're that we're
not doing that. Uh what we're going to
do is allow
um allow users
um to create um basically exclusive
areas of subreddits. So the first
version will be basically uh you want
like a lounge. So we used to have if you
if you bought Reddit premium used to be
called Reddit gold. If you bought Reddit
gold, you got access to the gold lounge
which was a subreddit that only um
paying members had access to and it was
actually the most popular reason people
bought Reddit premium. So the first
thing we want to do is do a um basically
community powered version of that. So if
any community wants like a private area,
uh they can charge their users for
access to that. That'll be the first
thing. Um but then longer term, uh we
look at I I want creators, the people
who create original content on Reddit to
be able to use Reddit. Right now they
can't. If you're if you're like a an if
if you're an internet creator uh that
monetizes their content, uh even if your
community lives on Reddit, you have to
go to another platform to host and
monetize your content. And so I think
that's a missed opportunity. And so for
those creators who want to have their
home be on Reddit, but they can't afford
to do so, we'd like to give them the
ability to create um you know, paid
content on Reddit. And so this these
features will only exist if users decide
to create them and use them. Uh what
we're not doing again is putting up pay
walls on Reddit. Uh it'll be entirely
user powered. So users decide what they
want to build, what's uh public or not,
um and whether to charge for it. So I
don't know if these things will work. I
think they will because the model works
on pretty much every other platform. Um,
but it really just about everything we
do on Reddit is about giving more tools
to communities to do to cover more use
cases. And so this is the kind of paid
exclusive higher quality content. I
don't love the last term because I think
the content are great. Um, but give the
users who want that uh the ability to
have it on. Great. Next question. Next
question. Yeah. Uh, it's a good
question.
Um, it's I'm I'm going to assume the
premise is
true. Uh, but I'm going spend 10 seconds
on suggesting that maybe that's not
true. Uh, I'm going to assume it's true.
I mean, I see what you see. Right.
Right. If if my name's mentioned on
Reddit, it's never kind. Uh,
and but it's also um there's like a
pretty strong selection bias there of
the only reason people would mention my
name is because we just made a change
that they don't like. Um, so that is
what it is. I would say just a
counterfactual to that is I've met many,
many, many users in person and they're
all really nice.
Um though I've met a few that that
started off uh uh really disliking me
and then we off had a nice pleasant
conversation. So it is what it is. But
let's take your prompts. Everybody hates
me. Uh let's take that as true. Um
look, I wish that weren't the case, but
it also, as you kind of point out, I
don't know how much it matters.
Um, I and we who work at Reddit want the
best for Reddit. Uh, we spend every day
I've spent literally my entire adult
life thinking about how to make Reddit
awesome, how to make it better for
communities, how to make it better for
our users. Our our love and desire to
improve Reddit is genuine. And you know,
whether that kind of comes through or
not is kind of beside the point. I wish
it did. I wish I was better at comms. I
wish I was um kind of better at
interacting with people on the platform.
Um but at the end of the day, our work
is our work. We do it for the reasons we
say we do.
Uh and you know, we managed to grow the
platform. I think we managed to make it
better. We managed to grow the business.
And those are the things I really care
about is is is Reddit growing and
evolving.
Um, and you know, if if whether people
hate me or hate the uniform or hate the
feature change or whatever it is, we'll
continue to do the best that we can.
Um, okay. So, the change was we had a
free API. We still have a free API. Um,
API has been used for all sorts of
things. It's still being used for all
sorts of things to uh enhance Reddit,
build modules, this and that. We had a
handful of folks who were
uh using that API to build clones of the
Reddit app uh and monetize uh within
those apps. Uh so the biggest were
Apollo and Reddit as fun uh and so
basically making competitive versions of
the Reddit apps that had no ads uh and
then monetizing it for themselves. So
they were making I think Apollo's making
like six million a year on um and
actually costing us uh more than that in
API usage. And so we went to the
heaviest users um of the API and said
you've got to pay for your usage. Uh and
actually those conversations were going
fine until we told them the price and
then they went not fine. Um and then uh
kind of all hell broke loose because
both I think there's a lot of
um uh basically lying from the creators
of those apps among other things uh
about their usage about the cost about
how much they were making. Um it's kind
of beside the point. Uh at the end of
the
day we were just not going to pay to
support people who was you know
effectively taking advantage of us.
Um,
and so then what happened is there's a
big protest on the on the site. Um, and
so a lot of mods, I think a lot of mods
use those apps, so they were getting
Reddit for free, right? No ads. Um,
basically took their subreddits offline.
And so, look, I think protests are a
natural part of democracy. Reddit is a
democratic platform. So, these protests
happen from time to time. As I was
saying before, even if you don't agree
with it, uh there's information there.
Um, but one of the things that happened
that I thought was not right is the mods
and in many cases against the wishes of
their communities took the communities
offline
um, and took years of content that users
had created the mod create that the
users had created took it offline um,
leaves Google search takes people's like
all these stories that people had told
all of these things just took it
wholesale offline. Um, and in some cases
we're actually laughing about it behind
the scenes.
Um, and so we basically said, look, you
can have your protest, you can be really
mad, but you don't get to decide whether
these communities that you didn't
create, you didn't create the content,
whether that content does not get to
exist on the internet anymore. That's
not your decision to make. Um, and so,
you know, eventually the protest went
down. Most of the communities came back
online. And there's a few who basically
said like we're not we're not going to
bring these communities back online. So
they said okay well then if you don't
want to moderate on Reddit you don't get
to moderate on soup.
Um now the goal of the the price change
was to cover our cost was literally to
cover our costs. We didn't say you can't
build um third party apps on Reddit. We
just said you have to pay your for your
usage. Like we pay for our hosting so
you've got to pay for yours. Um, the two
big ones, Apollo and Reddit is fun,
basically preemptively shut down. Uh,
some of the others are still online. Uh,
they they they pay for their usage. Uh,
and they still have users and it's, you
know, still fine. So, it was messy, but,
uh, I I think we could have handled
things better. I think we could have
done the coms. Uh, up until the moment
it all exploded, the comps had been
private between us and the heavy users
because there's only like six really
heavy users of the API. Um, everybody
else was well within the what would be
the free
tier. Uh, we should have had those those
coms should have been public. What we
were doing, why we were doing it, the
scale that we were talking about. The
Apollo app used 100x more resources than
our own app. Uh, in terms of API calls,
it was just like relentless. It was
extremely waste which is people can be
extremely wasteful if they don't cover
their so they don't pay for resources.
Um so we should have made all of that
information public. We should have had
the conversation in public. I think that
would have helped a lot. Um and as for
the the the the protest and unwinding of
that
protest, like I said, I think protests
are important, but I think there's also
a line in there. Like just imagine a
protest in the real world. Um yeah, you
can have a protest. You have a right to
protest in the United States as
protected speech, but you don't get to
shut down a city's transportation system
indefinitely. Uh, you know, nobody would
expect to do that or for that to be
allowed. And so, you know, I think we
have we have some amount of tolerance
for protest, certainly a lot more than
anybody else online. Um, but you can't
shut down Reddit indefinitely and take
it away from users, especially if you
don't have the support of the users,
which in this case the mods do not. So,
that was our thinking. Mhm. Uh, and I
think,
look, I regret that it was such a big
fight, but I think we, you know, we the
the critical decisions about whether or
not to charge and how to unwind that, I
think, were ultimately the correct
point. The first $12,000. So, that was Y
Combinator's investment. Um, that paid
for our rent uh in the Boston area and
that paid for our server
uh and it paid for some food. Um, so we
raised $12,000 and then at the end of
the summer we raised an additional
$70,000. I think that was the last money
we
raised. Did we raise
more? Can't we raised 70? I seem to
remember we raised a little more, but my
mind is fuzzy. Uh, before we got
acquired
uh so I I think we may have ra Oh, we
did a commercial deal with Advance. I
forgot. Uh, so before Advance bought us,
we did a commercial deal with them where
we would run uh lipstick.com, which was
a pink version of Reddit for celebrity
gossip. Um, so I did uh so we ran Reddit
and then all the things that I did in
the early days to get Reddit off the
ground with like the the user submission
and accounts, I did that all over again
with a a team of uh
contractors um for celebrity gossip. And
so, uh, yeah, I ran lipstick.com for
like, I don't know, a year or so as
well. But that paid us, I I can't
remember what that paid us, like 15
grand a month or something like that.
And so that helped us cover rent and
basic necessities until we actually sold
the company. Did you sell the company
because you needed more money or were
you No. Uh, we did not sell the company
because we needed more money. Um,
although it did seem like a lot of money
at the time. Um, we sold the company
because it seemed like a lot of money.
It was like we're working on this thing
and and we didn't know where it was
going. We didn't really know what we
were doing and all of a sudden
somebody's offering us millions of
dollars for this thing. We we were just
like college kids. And so we were like,
"Wow, somebody is offering us millions
of dollars for this things that we've
been working on for a year. Like we'd be
silly not to take it." Um, you know,
I've gone back and forth, certainly
flip-flopped over the years on whether
or not that was uh the right decision.
Um, uh, I think I'm pretty happy with
where things are today, so it must have
been the right decision. Yeah. What's
there you go? Yeah. So, how do we handle
traffic spikes? Look, there's a lot of
infrastructure, uh, many layers of
infrastructure. So,
um, you've got, you know, we've got our
CDNs, we've got our various data
centers, we've got, you know, some
surplus capacity, you know, so we we we
build for, you know, these days our C
capacity is pretty flexible. And so, you
know, on most days we can more or less
predict our traffic and so we kind of
flex up and flex down and that's really
a cost savings thing, you know, the
flexing down part. Um, but then our CDNs
can absorb a lot of traffic. So, if
there's like a um a DOS, our CDNs, our
load balancers can uh absorb a lot of
that. Um, it's relatively rare that
we'll have
uh a huge amount of traffic that affects
the site, but we did have a few
instances last year where we had
um single comment threads. And so the
comment threads around the presidential
debates, those got overwhelmed. I think
we had that happen two or three times.
Um, so actually this like frontline
traffic were pretty good at handling and
shedding and adapting, but there'll
still be areas of the site where you get
like a ton of activity, you know, on
one, you know, one database basically,
you know, one comment thread. It all
lives on like a single machine or
something like that. Um, so we had some
downtime related to that. Um, and then,
uh, we've since addressed that issue. So
it's pretty rare that today that we'll
get a traffic spike that meaningfully
affects the site. There's always ways of
degrading. So we had uh you know we we
use um uh both AWS so Amazon and GCP
Google are two cloud providers. We had
an instance last year where um it was
our fault. we lost a big chunk of our a
AWS um uh
servers and we were able to in like 20
minutes divert all of that traffic to
Google and so we can now kind of at at
world scale shift around traffic to kind
of stay up through those moments um like
back when I I was an active engineer and
and doing um you know it for Reddit we
would degrade into like readon mode so
things are getting hairy a databases get
too hot we didn't know what going on. We
could just flip the site into readonly
mode. So you could still read Reddit but
you couldn't write. Um I remember at
least one instance our databases just
got overwhelmed. So I just clicked it
into read only mode just to like get all
the rights in um and then click it back
on. U you know not that was kind of uh
some cowboy sis admitting. We don't
really do it that way anymore but you
know honestly you know we may actually
do it that way from time to time. I'd
say, you know, when you're in an
emergency and your platform's down or
struggling, uh, there's a lot of stuff
that you'll do
to keep it online. Yeah. It'll do
anything it takes. That's right.
Um, okay. So, it's a great question. Um,
how does AI change, let's call it the
usage of there's another question, uh,
which is how does AI make Reddit better?
Uh, long story short, in a million
different ways. But how does AI existing
change the usage of Reddit? So there's
kind of two ways of using Reddit today.
Uh the first we call them the scrollers.
These are the users who scroll on
Reddit. They're coming to Reddit for the
community and conversation platform.
They're coming specifically to talk to
other human beings to
I don't see that use case on Reddit
going away with AI because they're
specifically there to talk to other
humans. if they wanted just information,
they would do something else. Today, the
information seekers, we call them
seekers, um they largely interact with
Reddit via Google. They go to Google
with a question and then uh they end up
on Reddit to get their answer. Um so
Google's, you know, evolving their
products, doing AI summaries and this
and that. Um still linking to Reddit.
We're still growing on Reddit. um you
know that
that the it's a you know their product
is evolving as you would expect it to
but you know we we've been we've had a
close relationship and symbiotic
relationship with Google for a long time
and they're still very very close
partner with us. Um, so I see that
changing but not I see it changing
somehow but I don't see it changing in a
way that really meaningfully hurts
Reddit because again uh internet
consumers broadly want what Reddit has
which is connection to other humans and
up-to-date relevant recent information
about all sorts of things. We're also
investing in the seeker use case on
Reddit so that you can run a search on
Reddit or ask a question on Reddit and
get an answer from the corpus. Um, and
that's been really interesting. So, we
built um a quick and dirty product
called Reddit Answers. We built it in 90
days. We launched it in
December. And this is basically
traditional Reddit search with an LLM
summarizer on top of it. Uh that's
actually really cool. So, you can if
you're logged in on Reddit, you can go
to reddit.com/ansers or you can go into
the app and it's on the bottom n bar. Go
to answers and just ask it a question
like a subjective question. And
effectively what it'll do is it'll run a
search on Reddit, you know, get a 100
posts back and then basically summarize
everything that's in those posts, but
everything it says uh every like factual
thing it says is it links to the
specific Reddit comment where it came
from. And that's been really really
interesting um to see how that evolves.
And so I think that use case, the seeker
use case is evolving on Reddit. I think
there'll always be Google and Reddit and
our relationship there. And I think we
can also um build a better product for
the seekers on Reddit. But that's using
AI to summarize what's on Reddit. And
those users aren't looking to talk to a
human. They're looking to see what
Redditor said about topic X, you know,
whatever. Did you have a followup? Yeah,
actually I give credit. That's a great
question. Um, I'm not sure I have a
fully formed answer. So, so the question
is about agents. We're going to have
more agents on the internet. Agents are
going to be interacting with all
platforms, including Reddit. Like, how
do we how do we think about that? Uh, I
think you're exactly right. Right. We're
see we're watching it happen right in
front of our eyes. got these agents.
They can use the internet. They can
browse the internet. They can summarize
what they see. They can help you make
decisions. Um,
so let me put aside Reddit for a second.
I think there will be an evolution where
platforms build APIs for agents because
right now the way agents interact with
your platform is through the web and so
they reduce your content or knowledge
the information to a website and they
try to interpret that. No, they're very
good at it. But I think um APIs designed
for agents will probably become a thing.
It's probably something we should build
on Reddit. Um we're not opposed we're
not opposed to that. I think it will
kind of going back to maybe the API
conversation. It's like if we have a lot
of
agents using right right now if you're a
human using Reddit, you see the ads. So,
if you have a lot of agents using Reddit
and not seeing the ads, well, we'll just
have to consider like what's the what's
the fair way to have that relationship?
Um, like is there like a agent API cost?
Um, do do agents see ads? I don't I mean
they agents may see the ads. I I don't
know. That stuff is a kind of
interesting question. So, I I think
there will need to be some evolution
there, but um I could never say we're
anti- agent because we don't get to make
that choice. they're coming. Um, and so
we just need to figure out how to adapt.
Um, but I think we we've been able to
adapt before and we'll figure it out in
this case, too. But in in general, I
will say my preference, as I was saying
before, is for Reddit to be open and
accessible even to AI bots or agents.
Um, it's possible that we're not able to
do that because it costs us too much
money or it breaks Reddit in some other
way, but we won't admit defeat until
we're defeated. I'd like it to be open
and
exec. Thank you. Thank you, Steve, for
coming. Well, that was fast. All right.
And uh