We're here with our final guest lecture
for the course. Um, and today we have uh
Dr. Yunju Lee. He is an assistant
professor of computer science at
Columbia University where he leads the
robotic perception interaction and
learning lab. He is also a former
instructor of CS231N like all of our
guest lecturers. and he taught the
course in 2023 while he completed his
posttock here at Stanford with
professors fee Lee and Jaun Wu. His
research lies at the intersection of
robotics, computer vision and machine
learning and specifically his work
focuses on robot learning uh and aims to
significantly expand robots perception
and physical interaction capabilities.
In today's lecture, he'll be discussing
exactly that topic, robot learning. And
I'll now hand it off to Yunju for
today's lecture.
Yeah, thank you Z for the very kind
introduction. I'm super excited to be
here like last time I was here giving
lectures was two years ago 2023 and uh
similar lately like I was going through
many of the lectures and today I'm going
to talking about like some of things
that I have been working on and also
it's also a very coherent piece of this
overall pictures on deep learning for
computer visions and this is
specifically on robot learning. So I'll
be discussing like what are some of the
interesting considerations especially in
enabling the robots to better perceive
and interact with the physical world and
how some of the considerations might be
different from some typical computer
vision task and computer vision like
methods. So first of all like you guys
have already learned like a lot about
supervised learning. The thing and the
setup for supervised learning is that
you have data X and Y. X is the input
and Y is a label and you are trying to
learn a mapping that maps from the input
X to the output Y. There are examples
you have already learned like
classification, regression, object
detections etc. And you have also
learned about selfsupervised learning
where instead of having labels in this
case you are just having the data
without any labels. when you are trying
to do is you come up with learning
algorithms that is able to extract or
identify the underlying hidden
structures of the data just by like uh
working or designing some auxiliary
loss. Some typical example including
like autoenccoders. There's many other
like examples in trying to do
unsupervised learning or self-supervised
learnings like on top of this mass
amount of unlabelled data.
And the special thing and the unique
things about robot learning is that
robots has to make physical interactions
and make interactions with the world. So
it's not just you have the input and
outputs and mapping from the input X to
Y or some kind of latent
representations. It's really about you
are influenced evolutions of the
environments. So no matter what action
you decide to take in the real world,
the world will change as a result of
that actions and the world will give you
some kind of new observations or reward
telling you like how the thing how the
environment has been changing and how
good you are in executing certain tasks.
So the goal is trying to actually come
up with a sequence of actions with
feedback from the environments that is
to maximize some reward or minimize some
cost and robot learning like especially
in the recent like years has attract
significant attentions both within
academia and also within industries. So
we have seen like a many like startup
companies and including for example
physical intelligence like a Tesla bots
or figure they are producing those like
a very seemingly very nice and fancy
videos of robots doing a wide range of
very complicated tasks like folding
shirts like manipulating coffee beans or
trying to have this humanoid like doing
interesting tasks in the real physical
world. So this field like I mentioned
has attract a lot of attentions and also
a lot of investments. Here are just some
examples of some recent startups in the
field of robot learnings that is able to
attract a huge amount of investments
trying to build this general purpose
robots that can make physical
interactions with the environments. So
obviously not only those startups many
like a big established companies are
also having their own uh robotics in
investigations and initiatives trying to
develop their own like general purpose
robots that is able to make uh general
purpose and high performance physical
interactions with the environment.
So for today's lectures I'm going to
give you some kind of overviews on some
of the key techniques enabling factors
of the current success and boom of robot
learnings. We will start with like a
problem formulination. So how can we
more concretely define the problems we
have been building and how can we
formally thinking about the robots
interactions with the environments. So I
will then discuss on the more perception
sides. I will talk about the difference
considerations between how robots
perceive the environments and how people
typically consider in the computer
vision community and what's special
about robots perception. Now talking
about reinforcement learning, model
learning, model based planning,
imitation learning like also some of the
recent trends on robotic foundation
models and also like using the remaining
time to discuss some of the challenges
we still see like a lies ahead of us. So
starts with problem formulation.
So this is in general like how the
problem should look like at least in a
graphical u illustration. So in the
middle we have this agent. The agent is
given some task objective. This task
objective could be for example language
instructions from human or some kind of
objective functions measuring how good
this agent is in doing some specific
task. This agent is taking states from
the physical worlds or some kind of
environments and the agent decides what
action to take like this at here that
needs to be executed in the physical
worlds and this physical worlds will be
updated and given this agents this
states S+ one as well as the rewards
telling the agents how good it is doing
its task. So this is how the framework
in general look like. So you have to be
very clear on this type of formulations
that consists of goal, states, actions
and also rewards that specifically
defines the problems of the robot
learning like type of scenarios is very
different from the computer visions. I
would like to say like computer vision
is mostly about trying to learn some
kind of representations of the
environments based on the inputs like
highdimensional data. But for robotics,
it's basically trying to solve some kind
of optimization problems where you have
the constraints which is a physical
world of the environments. You have your
objective functions defined over your
goal and you are essentially trying to
solve this optimization problems by
coming up with a sequence of actions
that can maximize or minimize your
objective functions. So that's a key
difference between like robot learning
and what people typically consider in
computer vision.
So some specific instantiations of this
problem like for example carpole the
goal is can be balance the pole on the
top of a movable carts and the states of
these environments essentially describe
the physical states status of the
systems which can include the angle the
angular speeds positions horizontal
velocities etc. And the action could be
the horizontal force that is applied to
the carts. And you could have the
rewards or one indicating at each time
step if the pole is being kept as an
upright position.
Some other example could including like
robots locomotion where the goal is to
make this robots moving forwards and the
states could include the angle,
position, velocities of all joints
within this robots and the action could
be the torque applies to each one of the
joints and the reward can be like one at
each time. the robots like make a step
forwards and also being kept in an
upright positions
and also like some like interesting
example including the Atari games. The
goal can be complete the gaming with the
highest score as high as possible like
you can get. And the states will be the
raw pixel inputs of the gaming screen
and action could be the gaming control
like up, down, left and right. And the
reward could be the score increase and
decrease at each time step. And uh some
of the like a more famous examples you
probably have noticed like earlier
especially with the developments of
alpha go. And the definition and the
problem of go can also be defined in
similar ways where the goal is to win
the game. In the states will be all the
pieces that are currently already on the
go brought and action could be where to
put the next piece down on this board
and the reward could be uh on the last
turn. If you win, you get a reward of
one and if you lose, you get a reward of
zero. And this not only applies to for
example gaming domains like even with
the recent like developments of large
language models, you can also like
thinking about those problems especially
for sequ sequential like generation
problems in a similar manner. Or the
goal could be to predict the next words
and the state could be the current words
in the sentence. And the action will be
what the specific next words you want to
put there. And if it is correct, you get
a reward. If it is incorrect, you get a
rewards of zero. And uh similarly now
you probably have already played with
many of the chat bots quite a lot. And
we can also define a problem like
similarly where the goal is to be a good
companions to the human user. The states
could be the current confi conversation
and action that should be generated by
the chatbots will be the next sentence
you are given to the human user and
according to the human evaluations we
could define the reward. If the person
is happy like if it if they are
satisfied you get a rewards of one and
if uh you are not happy or neutral you
get some other rewards and more
specifically for example in the robotics
domain and the task could be to fold the
clothes and one clothes be folded nicely
in the states is the current
observations the robot is getting from
this environment which could including
the multiv- view RGB or RGBD
observations of the environment And the
robots needs to decide its actions like
how to move it in factors. Should it
close or open its scrapers in order to
manipulate this close and according to
human evaluations if the close is
properly folded? You give the robot a
reward of one. And if the close is not
folded, you give the rewards of zero. So
here is actually how you want to like a
more concretely thinking about the robot
learning problem. This really is a way
that allowing the agents to interact
with the world that considers the effect
of an actions and also this sequential
decision- making problems that is
different from what people typically
consider in computer vision. We just
needs to predict the outputs and the
goal states actions and the rewards and
objective functions are the things you
need to keep in mind whenever you are
thinking about problems along this
direction.
So this is about problem formulation. So
question is like how specific the reward
needs to be designed like in many of the
task the reward can have many different
type of specifications. For example in
the self-driving the reward could be
like as fast as possible or reward could
be like we want the the the the
passengers to feel comfortable as you
are driving along the roads. So even for
clothes folding depending on the user's
preference a clothes can be folded in
many different ways. Some want the total
area to be as small as possible. Some
want it to be as like a smooth as
possible. There could be a difference
like types of rewards. Here I'm just
talking a generic terms like if a person
look at the clothes like do they think
this is folded or not but more
specifically in terms of the reward
design. There's actually a lot of
nuances in like a satisfying specific
needs of a specific application.
Okay. So I'll continue. So this is how
we are thinking about those robot
learning problem that allows the agents
to interact with the physical world. Now
I'm moving on to robot perception
especially in discussing how the
perception problem within this robot
learning domain is different from what
typically people typically consider
incom.
So this image again you you're actually
going to see this image again and again
like through today's lecture. So this is
essentially in the question of how we
are handling the whatever information
you are getting from the physical world.
The physical world can give you for
highdimensional RGB observation or RGBD
observations. It could also include some
other sensory data like tactile
sensings. And this robot perception
problem is essentially trying to distill
or harnessing some structured knowledge
from those highdimensional data that is
useful for the robot to do the
downstream decision-m
and essentially the question we are
trying to tackle is trying to making
sense of this unstructured real world
and the real world can be very messy. So
essentially the observations the robots
are getting from the environments can
only contains like incomplete knowledge
of the objects and the environments.
There could be occlusions. There could
also be like errors from the sensory
like data and the imperfect action may
also leads to failure. For example like
the robots can trying to grasp some
objects but that grasping behavior may
not always be successful. Sometimes
you'll accidentally drop that objects
which will also cause like evolutions
and unexpected changes of this
environment. They will also need to have
this perception system that is able to
handle those scenarios and also this
environments can change. It is dynamic
consists of not just rigid object but
deformable object clothes
medias. There could be other agents like
dogs or other kids or other humans that
are also in the same environments
messing up with the world and your
perception system needs to be able to
cope with all those kind of changes.
So that is why like in the robotics
domain people typically not just working
with like a camera data they try to add
as much sensor as possible to the robots
as long as they can provide some useful
informations. It really considers like
for example like a tactile sensing the
audio information the depth informations
next and typically we will have to like
a design a systems that is able to put
all the sensors togethers that allows
them to uh complement each other whereas
audio information might tell you things
about the physical contacts and the
tactile information might tells you
about whether a grasp is stable or not
and the camera information tells you
about something that is more on the
higher level on the grand scheme of
things about the overall states of this
environment. So how these sensors can be
composed together and work together is
very very important to design a capable
robotic system that are working in the
real physical world. And besides the the
numbers of sensory modalities very
important difference between like a
robot vision and computer visions is
trying to really understand the effect
of an actions and also the affordance of
this environments. On the left is a very
typical examples you have already seen
in computer vision which is trying to do
instant segmentation. What you are given
is this 2D image. You are segments
different instances from this 2D image
like a by drawing like a contours over
this 2D pixels. But what's difference in
the robotics domain? For example, on the
right, the robot can for example given
one object and this object seems to be
maybe just one object or maybe some a
lot of pieces that are for example
stacked into each other. The robot has
to know like what type of actions will
allow us to have better understand
better perceptions about this
environments. Is this one piece of
object or multiple pieces composed
togethers? The robot should come up with
actions like perturb and actively
interact with the environments for the
robot to get a better perceptions about
the states of this environment. So that
is why a robot vision is embodied active
and also environmentally situated. By
embodies what we mean is robots have
this kind of physical body that is
directly experiencing the physical world
directly. Their actions are part of a
dynamic uh with the worlds that have
immediate feedback on their own
sensations
and active meaning the robots are active
perceivers. It knows why it wishes you
to sense and chooses what to perceive
and it determines how and when and where
to achieve that perception. You can move
your head around you to know like what's
behind this table. You can just move
around to see what's behind the tables.
So this is the active parts which is
different from what people typically
consider in computer vision. that are
mostly like work with a passively
collected data sets. The third point is
about situated. The robots are situated
in the world. They do not deal with
abstract descriptions but with the here
and now of the world directly
influencing the behavior of the systems.
Bots really have to understand
especially in closing perception and
action loop. It sees the world and
understanding its goals and be able to
act in the environments upon its
perceptions. Sometimes the robot don't
have to know the full state of
environments. For example, if I'm
buttoning my shirt, I only have to know
the local regions near that button for
me to button that shirts. So some of the
perception has to be tightly coupled and
co-designed with the task and the
downstream decision-m systems for the
robot to focusing on the relevant region
or task relevant regions of the
environments to be properly like a close
this perception and action loop.
So this is about some very specific
considerations and how robots perception
might be different from what people
typically consider in computer vision. I
will starting to discuss some of the
algorithms that not only allow the robot
to see but allow the robot to act in the
world and we will starts with
reinforcement learning. Remember earlier
we have like seen this image the robots
has to act upon this environment and get
rewards from this environments. So one
very typical ways of trying to solve
this optimization problem is allow the
robots to interact with the worlds as
extensively and as massively as
possible. You just collect all the
experience data and do this type of like
a trials and errors allow the robots to
understand this action leads to higher
reward and that action leads to lower
rewards and we can pivot the agents
behaviors towards the actions that give
the agents some higher rewards. This is
like the general ideas of reinforcement
learning. is really a way to allow the
agents to constantly interact with the
environments and do this trials and
error to maximize the reward or minimize
the cost. And here I also want to be a
bit more specific in discussing the
difference between reinforcement
learning and supervised learning. So
this is a typical framework of how
reinforcement learning look like. You
have the environments. Environment give
the agent some states. Agents generate
actions. And the environments like give
the agent the feedback which is the
rewards and the environments will change
where the environment give the agent the
new states S t plus one and it
essentially a sequence like a temporal
sequence on the temporal domain where
the robots has to the agent has to make
the sequential decisions and here is a
typical like image u typically look like
for supervised learning. So you have the
data sets. The data sets will input to
the model this X and this model will
generate the prediction Y and you will
be able to calculate the loss according
to the model's predictions versus the
ground truth from this data sets. So
this is a typical setup of supervised
learning and the key difference some of
the key difference between reinforcement
learning and supervised learning is that
the environments might be stochastic or
the same actions the environment might
change in a different manner. Let's say
if you are pushing a box forward,
depending on the distribution of the
supporting force, the same exact actions
will lead to can potentially lead to the
box rotating into different angles.
Meaning there can be uncertainties and
stochasticities in the environments that
will like lead to like a stochastic
behaviors of these environments which
will also give this agents stochastic
like rewards where the same action may
not always leads to the same rewards. So
this is very different from supervised
learning. We are dealing with an
uncertain dynamical system.
The second is about the question of
credit assignments. So for supervised
learning you give the inputs, you
predict the outputs and directly
calculate the loss like you directly
know like what are the mistakes and what
are the error you are making by making a
specific predictions. But in the
reinforcement learning or sequential
decision- making domain, the rewards can
be delayed. Meaning if you like play the
game of gold like only until the very
ends of this episodes do you realize you
are winnings or you were losing and
that's rewards 01 mice is because of
some very very early like steps maybe
even the first like steps or some steps
during the middle of the games. So how
to properly assign the credits you are
getting along this sequential decision
makings towards all the actions is also
another very like a tricky and important
questions people hope to answers within
reinforcement learning. The third thing
is the non-defision diffusion abilities
of this dynamical systems for example
for supervised learning like you have
the inputs you feed the inputs through
the model you get outputs you calculate
the loss. So everything along this
process is differentiable. So you can
directly g gradients of the loss
functions with respected to the
parameters within the model. But that's
typically not the case for reinforcement
learning where the environments can
often times not differentiable. So how
to properly gather gradients of the
rewards with respect to the actions can
be tricky. Sometime people have to
relies on a massive sampling to do like
those type of zeros order estimations of
the gradients for you to do proper
learnings. That's also is another
difference
like the last difference is about this
non-station of this scenarios where the
evolutions and the states of the
environments is really a result of your
actions. For supervised learning, no
matter whatever you predict, it doesn't
influence other data points you are
getting from this data set. But your
actions will influence the next states
you are getting in this sequential
decision- making problems. It is also
what makes this kind of reinforcement
learning problems a little bit more like
a nuanced than supervised learning.
So here are some more specific examples.
Like for example playing these Atari
games like I mentioned earlier the goal
could be to complete the games with the
highest score and the states will be the
raw pixel inputs from the gaming screen
and the action could be up down left and
right from the keyboards and we're
trying to like the reward are the score
increase and decrease at each time step
and some typical algorithms within this
domain either lies in the field of for
example like a pure learnings or for
example policy iterations Here's a one
examples of like trying to learn this Q
function. Q function essentially
measures the discounted expected future
accumulated rewards like when you apply
a specific action A at a specific state
S and you'll be able to get this Q
functions through like interactions with
this gaming environments and after you
have learned this Q functions you can
evaluate for example like what are the Q
values you are getting by applying
different actions in this case there's
left and rights ups and downs months. So
there could potentially be four actions
and given this four actions you can look
at their Q values and just execute the
action that give you the highest Q
values. So that is what allows you to do
this type of like decision makings in
this domain. So uh because today we're
going to cover a lot of materials so we
won't go into the details of the
reinforcement learnings but some of the
current state-of-the-arts reinforcement
learning algorithms including SACE like
soft actor critics and also PO like
proximal policy optimizations. So if you
are interested you are like very welcome
to look at those algorithms in details.
There's a lot of like open source like
implementations and tutorials online.
But here I want to highlight to you some
of the results you could potentially get
by going through this reinforced
learning specifically like Q-learning
process. This is developed by Google
deep mind that is trying to develop this
agents that is trying to play the game
breakouts in this kind of Atari world.
So just after like a 10 minutes of
training the robot the agent can already
like touch the ball but often the times
like can still missing the ball like
quite often and after some more times of
learning for example like a two hours of
training and the the the agents can
control this kind of paths in a much
more reliable and consistent fashions
that can nearly like all the time can
catch the ball and be able to like
constantly getting more and more rewards
by like a uh by by by by bouncing it
back. And after like a four hours of
trainings, something that's interesting
happens where the agents come up with
actually a novel strategy which possibly
is not known to many of you that is
trying to like a push bounce the ball
back to create a tunnel on the left
sides of this wall and then it will push
this ball like on the upper side of the
wall to do this very efficient like uh
reductions of those uh bricks. This is a
type of strategy that can be discovered
by reinforcement learnings. So this is
like what's nice about reinforcement
learning meaning you allow the agents to
do very extensive and comprehensive
exploration and interactions with the
world. And it is totally possible for
this reinforced learning agents to
discover some strategies that are better
than even the best human players. Like a
very typical examples will be the game
of go. So when Alpha Go came out in the
January 2016, it was also like about the
time when I was trying to decides like
what type of like research directions
I'm going to go. Before that time, I was
just working on deep learning for
computer visions. But when Alpha Go came
out, I'm like I have to work on this
kind of decision- making problems. So
that's why I started to touch upon
reinforcement learning, imitation
learning and all the way until now to do
robot learning that allows the robots do
physical interactions with the
environments. So um I wasn't satisfied
with just working with a passively
collected data sets but we really wanted
an agent that can do active interactions
with the environment. So questions was
how does specifically this Q functions
like works. So you can see this Q take
as input the state S and also the action
and this setup would essentially be the
parameters of this Q functions where the
Q is instantiated as a neuronet network.
In this specific case like I mentioned
earlier the states is the raw pixel
inputs that directly getting from the
gaming screen. So the inputs could be
this kind of four steps four frames that
directly inputed to this Q function. And
if you're dealing with images, a very
like a straightforward way of in
instantiating this Q function is to use
convolutional neuronet networks. So you
have convolutional layers like show in
this kind of orange blocks and then
you'll be able to go through this fully
connected layers to directly derive this
like a Q value and in this case because
there are like a four discrete actions
like in this case probably just left and
right but let's say there's like a four
discrete actions up and down left and
right. So you'll be able to have like
different Q value estimations that is
the results of this specific action A
and that's how you can use this Q values
to make decisions on what action to take
that is the most effective at maximizing
this Q value. Does that answer your
question?
Yes. Like uh this is when Alpha Go came
out and obviously since then there has
been a lot of developments and
evolutions in making this type of gaming
agents better and better. So then later
there's like alpha go zero that is
essentially a simplified versions of
alpha go they're no longer using any
imitation learning to do any initial in
initialization and is able to beat like
at that time the number one like a
player like co. So this is actually one
thing one lessons like people learned
inside u this AI communities which you
can call it like the bitter lesson from
the rich suten where sometimes you want
to find the simplest recipes that is the
most and best compatibles with the
scaling. You want to leverage the scale
like the the power of scalings and
sometimes like making this method
simpler will actually give you better
performance by like making it more
compatible with whatever infrastructure
you can use for scalings and stuff. And
then later uh um they develop alpha zero
that is able to generalize the same set
of algorithms into not just chess uh not
not just go but other games like chess
and shoji and then they they designed
like a mzeros that's like not just like
do this kind of model free reinforcement
learning but it's able to learn a latent
space dynamics models to plan over that
give you like even better performance.
So for this specific domain like I would
say especially in the gaming
developments that really empowers a lot
of like design and developments in how
people can do better and more sample
efficient and more scalable design of
those reinforcement learning like agents
and uh in November 2019 like Liso like
who was beaten by alpha go announced his
retirements and he realized there just
no it's just not possible like at that
times for any human players to beat the
best like a go like AI agents out there.
And obviously since then there has
something been other like more complex
games like Starcraft and Dota that shows
that as long as you put enough compute
as long as you have like a good like a
very welld designigned like algorithms
and infrastructure for you to do the
reinforcement learning you can get very
very good performance in games that are
actually noticeably and orders small
magnitudes more complicated than the
game of go. So I would say like if you
have a game like a reasonably designed
games like uh there's like a very legit
chance like if you put as the the
sufficient resource you can have very
very powerful gaming agents. So not just
in games people have also been
developing this reinforcement learning
algorithms and agents that can work
directly in the real physical world. So
this on the left is a work from ETH that
was published in science robotics 2020
that essentially changed my minds about
how useful reinforcement learning can be
for real physical robots because before
it was just mostly games like could
argue in games like there's a lot of you
can just like spawn as many games as
possible but for the real worlds there's
always like sim to real gap where you
are training on the same game you are
also testing on the same game but for
robots was if you train on a simulation
like how much does the sim to real gap
matters for the agents you generalize to
the real environments and this paper
really convinced me that sometimes the
sim to real gap just may not matter that
much so we are not simulating the bushes
we are not simulating the snows but the
agents that's using reinforcement learn
training simulation can give you some
very very robust performance in the real
physical worlds like snows and slipper
very very slippery like a surface
On the right is a very recent video
released by Unitry that shows just
another levels of like dexterities for
locomotions that can do this kind of sim
to real transfer allow this robots to do
like a very very crazy and dynamic
behaviors that can navigate into some
very rough and challenging terrains. I
would say in the domain of robot
locomotion is close to be a solved
problems and the solution to this
problems is exactly reinforcement
learning. So this is about local motion.
The other domain is about manipulations
where the robots has to manipulate the
objects in the real physical world. So
in 2019 when open AI was still like a
touch upon like a robotics they designed
the systems they are trying to do
dextrous manipulations of rubric cube
they are able to do the reinforcement
learning in simulation and do sim real
transfer they allow this kind of robots
to like solve this rubric cube but one
caveat is that their success rate is
very very low like although this video
seem to be very beautifully done but
their success rate was very low and if
you really look at the papers
uh they only tested a very limited
amount of trials and uh given that
number possibly the reliability is not
very like satisfying but still like
since then people have been able to like
extends upon this texturous manipulation
problems allow the robots to do enhanced
texturous manipulation and
reorientations of different types of
objects and into different like target
configurations um is all thanks to the
developments of reinforcement learning.
But we can see until now our examples in
locomotions and in hand manipulation, it
doesn't really solve the problem. For
example, if the robot can just fold the
clothes for you or doing the laundry for
you in your home like for manipulation
is still in this kind of very like
isolated domains like working with this
kind of isolated like environments.
So this is actually some of the key
challenges and bottlenecks of existing
like a model free reinforcement
learning. This mostly learns from the
trials and error with the environments
and it requires extensive like
interactions with the worlds. For
example, for the Alpha Go Zero, like it
actually learns from 3,000 years of
human knowledge in 40 days, which is
amazing, but like it still requires like
many many like years of computation like
years of like equivalent computations
for the agents to learn. If in domains
where there's like a huge simal gap and
you want to do the reinforcement
learning in the real physical worlds
that will be a huge bottleneck for
learning this reinforced learning agents
very effectively and also of course if
there seem to gap if you only can learn
the model in the real environments
there's a lot of like safety concerns
for example here is an example of
showing this kind of learning
progressions of agents that is
controlling this humanoid robots to move
forwards you can see like during this
learning process Although at the very
end the robot is able to like move
forwards but there's a lot of like a
very weird behaviors that you can
totally imagine if you apply this agents
on the real physical robots it will like
fail catastrophically
and uh uh it also have like a very
limited interpretabilities and sometimes
very hard to correct things when things
go wrong. And like one interesting thing
if you really think about how human
learn to interact with the environment
versus like pure reinforcement learning
you realize that we humans have a very
intuitive understanding of this
environments. We can imagine how the
environment is going to change if we
apply a specific actions. So it's
exactly this predictive capabilities
that allows we humans to plan our
behavior in achieving some specific
targets. And this predictive
capabilities is also actually learned
from with humans physical interaction
and everyday experiences with the real
physical world. So going beyond the
reinforcement learning the next like
topics I want to discuss will be how we
can indulge the robots like with similar
capabilities in imagining the effect of
their actions and to do model based
planning. For this specific examples we
have a simulation. Typically the
simulation people use would be for examp
essentially a bunch of like rigid body
simulations where the robots like just
touching this kind of like a polygon
type of represented like a pl like a
representations of the floor. It is not
simulating for them the bushes. It is
not simulating those snows. But what
people do is to randomize the simulated
environments a lot. They randomize the
friction, the geometry and many other
physical parameter inside this
environment such that people will assume
whatever you encounter in the real
physical world is just one data points
within the distributions you randomize
within your simulation. So if your
policies can be robust like robust in
controlling this robots within that
distribution and if the real just one
data point within that distribution the
policy can generalize and so far at
least from this empirical evidence this
type of assumption actually holds and
the policy actually works very reliably
and robustly in the real physical world.
So the question is about like what is
actual command. So actually in many of
the existing demos there can be a person
providing high level commands to the
robot. For example, which direction
should the robots like walk? Should the
robots like rotates in place or just
still like keep walking forwards
condition on that high level actions
provided by human? The robot has to
decide this kind of low-level actions.
The low level actions are typically for
example the um the the the joint torque
that are applies to each and every one
of joints on top of this robots. So that
is how like this typically like looks
like meaning humans give high level
commands condition high level commands
robot has to use this policy to decide
this kind of low-level like actions
which is in instantiated using like
joint torque. So like I mentioned one
biggest lesson I learned from this lines
of work on locom motion is that the
simulation doesn't have to be perfect as
long as you randomize enough you can
generalize very robustly in the real
environments. But such lesson hasn't
really been generalized like very well
in the manipulation domain. So in the
manipulation domain like how accurate
the simulation needs to be and how much
does the symmetry real gap matters is
still a research question people hope to
answer. So I can give you one specific
example. If in the simulation you are
pushing a box forwards. If in simulation
the box rotates for 10° but in reality
rotates for 12° it may not matter that
much. But if in the real world your
grasping was successful but in
simulation the object shoot just flies
away because of some kind of numerical
issues or if the object like sleep like
away between your fingers that's
problematic. So there are regions where
sim to real gap matter. There are other
regions simil gap may not matter that
much in the manipulation domain and
people still are trying to trying to
answer and trying to understand like how
simil gap can happen and what are some
of the most important like recipes and
characteristics that this simulation
needs to have for the most reliable like
seem to real transfer. So if I
understand your questions correctly
you're asking like there are still a
person like providing high level
commands to the robots. Your question is
can robot come up with better plans than
a human. So I can actually give you a
more nuanced perspective. Although many
of these videos seems very nice. There
is a human operators operating the
robots to choose which route to go. For
example, like what people typically do
is for example, let's say there's kind
some kind of rough terrains or some pile
of rocks. And the humans can actually
try to command the robot to going
forward trying to climb those kind of
rocks. If that fails, humans can
actually provide some other high level
conveyance to get around this pile of
rocks. So there can be some kind of
learning also on the human side in
understanding the capabilities of those
robots. So this is also why some of this
video can actually looks very nice
because human select the routes that
human knows can show the limits and also
the capabilities of this kind of
low-level controllers and how to do that
autonomously. That's actually an very
interesting like questions people are
also doing research upon. Mhm.
So then I'm going to continue. So I have
discussed like some of the successful
examples and power of reinforcement
learnings and I also discussed the
limitations of reinforcement learning
and we still haven't really seen very
very successful and wide scale
deployments of reinforcement learning in
manipulation yet. And we human not just
learn from trials and error. We actually
build this type of internal model. So
we're asking the question can we
actually learn the models from the
robot's interactions with the
environments and using that model for
the robot to do better physical
interactions. So specifically what we
are touching upon again back to this
figure is how we can learn and
approximations of the real physical
world and how can this approximated
physical world that runs on the virtual
domain can help guides the robots
actions and decide what action to take
in the real physical world. So let's say
if you already have the model for
example let's say you have already
learned the models like we humans have
in our like mental like environments we
can predict given the current state s
and also the action t how the state of
the environment will change in new
states t + one and then we can use this
essentially is a forward model like
given the current state and action
predicted next states. So what actually
is the problem for us to do the planning
which is essentially an inverse of this
forward model where the plan is to give
the current state and the target states
and to come up with the action they can
allow the robot to achieve the target
states from a given current state
showing the blue dots. We have a targets
here in the red. We can have maybe some
initial guesses of how the actions might
look like. And our model, our
approximated learned models will be able
to predict the sequence of the
evolutions of the states which is show
in this green like a trajectory. And
then we can measure the distance between
this green dots and the red dots and
back propagates or doing optimizations
using the gradients of those their their
distance uh with respected to all the
actions along that trajectories to do
this type of optimizations in order to
know like what actions can guide us to
getting us closer to the targets show in
the red. And obviously the model may not
be accurate enough. So we typically only
execute the first actions and we obtain
the new states from the environment and
we can reoptimize the action sequence
using gradient descent or any other
optimization technique you use to do
this trajectory optimizations. And one
of the key benefits especially recently
with the developments of GPUs and also
neurodynamics model is that you can use
a GPU for parallel and simultaneously
sampling to allow you to do like a large
scale sampling and optimizations of
those action sequences which is actually
quite efficient.
So like given this like a general
framework you have the model which is
this kind of forward process and you can
always use a kind of forward model to do
this inverse optimizations to come up
with the actions that can like get you
closer to your target configuration. And
one of the key questions has always been
what should be the right representation
of the what should be the right and most
effective state representation is and
how we can learn this model based on
this state representation. And over the
years there has been many different
investigations on choosing or
investigating different type of state
representations. Some earlier work
including how can using for them just 2D
images as a representation of the states
and trying to learn pixel dynamics
meaning how the image might change if
you apply a specific actions. This is a
work called deep visual foresight which
set up some of the initial works in the
whole domains of like a world models.
And by learning this kind of pixelbased
dynamics models, people can come up with
strategies that is able to for example
minimize the distance between the
current observations and some can rotate
objects and pushing the objects around
in order to achieve the targets show in
green and the current states is show in
red. So this is about like a pixel
dynamics and what people can also do is
to use a key points as a representation
of the environments to learn like a key
points dynamics models. And here like
what we can do is to track the movement
of the key points on top of this box
over the 3D space and also neural
dynamics model of those key points as a
result of some pushing actions. And then
we can allow the robots to use this
forward predictive models to plan the
robots behaviors you to track some
specific trajectories in order to push
this box to achieve a target
configurations.
So besides using key points, so what if
you are encountered some objects with
even higher degrees of freedoms. So if
you go like one level finer, you can
also represent those objects using a
sets of particles essentially a set of
points here like which is actually a
work uh uh that was done while I was
here like as a postto where we're
representing this pile of granular
pieces using a bunch of particles and
trying to predict how those particles
will move around if you apply a specific
actions and this forward model can allow
the robots to do this inverse decision
makings. They handle a wide range of
granular objects of different like
granular sizes and we come up with
strategies that can gather those pieces
into the target region show in the
bottom right like a corner of each like
a segment and the same model with like a
good feedback from the environments
allow the robots to correct from the
model's error and come up with
strategies that can be very reliably
aggregates all the object pieces into
the target region and obviously See this
model not just can generalize to like a
different like a granular pieces of
different granular sizes. You can also
change to different target
configurations. Here you will very
quickly realize what the target
configurations are. The robot has to
come up with a strategy that to do
non-trivial redistributions of the
granular pieces. And after the
redistribution you had to align the fine
grain details with the targets like
shape in order to accomplish this like a
pile rearrangement tasks. The task here
is actually to rearrange this granular
pieces into different letter shapes all
the way from letter A to letter Z. And
with this kind of forward models will be
very successful in coming up with a
sequence of strategies. Of course with
feedback from the environments to allow
the robot to rearrange this kind of
object pieces into the target regions.
And this is actually a highly
non-trivial task. And going beyond that,
we are also uh have this like a
subsequent work which I was also
involved and done when I was here at
Stanford. And we designed this kind of
dumping making robots that is actually
equipped the robots with 15 different 3D
printed tools. We have four RGBD cameras
looking at the environments to do a
reconstructions of the geometry of this
doll. And the robots will have to decide
what tool to use and what action to take
in order to guess this dumpling into
getting this dough into a dumpling. And
the key enabling factor is also this
like a forward predicting models
represented like using particles. Right
here the red dots are representing the
shape of the tool and the blue dots are
representing the shape of the object.
The first row is our model's open loop
prediction and second row is like what's
actually happens in the real
environments. So this learn model that
directly learns from this real world
interactions can very actually predicts
the change of the shape of the dough
when using different tools applying
different actions and ins allows us to
have this integrated integrated system
that can make a dumpling out of a dough.
What's interesting about this video is
there's a person constantly perturbing
the robots from doing its job. The
robots will take the real time visual
feedback from this environment to real
time understanding the shape of the
dough and then using the current
observations and also the learn dynamics
model that predicts how the environment
is going to change how the do shape will
change. You use a tool to apply a
specific actions and based on this
forward model is making this inverse
decision. This decision is happening at
two levels. Both at a high level which
is to decide what tool to use which is a
task level decision-m and given this
tools the robot is also have to make
like a lower level like a motion level
decisions in deciding what specific
action to take you to progress into the
next task stage. Human are just so
annoying adding pieces folding the
dough. The robot is very robust to this
external disturbance in continuing its
progress in doing the task. Here's
what's interesting. After robot cuts a
circle, the humans shows no mercy,
destroy everything. The robot knows you
actually have to start from the very
beginning like redo the task from the
beginning in order to progress with this
kind of task objective. So this really
shows the patience and also the
robustness of our systems with this type
of external disturbance. And all of
these capabilities is enabled by this
kind of neuron dynamics model that
predicts how the shape of the dough will
change if you apply a specific actions.
In the end, the robots will place the
skin on top of this dumpling clip and
move this kind of feelings on top of
this dumpling skin and using a hook to
close the dumpling clip. You to use this
general purpose robots equipped with 15
general purpose tools to make a dumpling
out of a dough. So this is about like
how we can learn the model and and how
that model can be useful for for
downstream like model based planning. So
for this specific case like u if we want
to describe it more rigorously we are
not using reinforcement learning like we
just learn the model and using that
model to do planning although the plan
can be distilled into a policy that can
be executed in the real environment in a
more efficient manner but some people
also call it model based reinforcement
learning. decide which background you
are coming from. You can either call it
like model learning and model based
planning. You can also call it model
based reinforcement learning. But the
key idea you want to learn the model
from the robot's physical interactions
with the real physical world and using
that learn model that is very effective
in helping the robot to decide its
behaviors to like a progress with a task
objective.
So in this specific case it is the high
level plane and low-level decision
making is done by two different models.
So over the high level we are given the
current states like current observation
of the environments and the targets the
robot help to achieve is essentially a
classifier and classify which tool to
use and condition on this classify like
tool label there a lowle like a policies
that decides what specific action to
take in order to like progress into the
next task stage. Very good question. So
back then this work was done in 2023. At
that time vision language model wasn't
like very powerful. So at that time like
what we did was to allow a human
operator to do the data collection
demonstration of the task for 10 times.
We use that data to train this kind of
classifier to classify what tool to use.
That allows us to actually jump back and
forth over this chain. Like I mentioned
earlier after the robots cut a circle
the human destroy everything. the ROS
should jump back to some earlier stages
like that fits to its current
observation in order to like do the
proper like um recovery from the
external disturbances. So in this
specific case like what we have been
doing is a combination of sampling based
trajectory optimizations versus like a
policy learning. So what we have been
doing is to give the current states of
this dough. We have our like forward
predicting models. We'll be able to
sample a bunch of actions and sample a
bunch of tools to like a predict like
what is the evolutions of the shape of
that dough. And then we'll compare the
model's prediction with the targets like
we hope to achieve which is similar to
what I showed earlier. For example, our
model predicts the shape of the dough
will go into this green dots but the
targets is this red dots. We are
comparing their distance and then that
allows us to select the most effective
actions that can gets us to the target
at to be as close as possible and we can
do a lot of samples like this but
sampling during the test time is very
time consuming. So we do this type of
sampling in an offline fashions which
give us a data sets and we can use that
data sets to train a policies that can
be uh inferred at a very very like using
a very short period of time to do the
inference during the test time. There is
still a neural network as a policies.
Yeah, although that policy is nerds by
distilling from our models like uh
predictions over a huge amount of
samples. For this specific work, there's
no physics based simulation at all. We
actually have a baseline that use a
state-of-the-art deformable object
simulator which is called MPM, material
point methods. What we realize is that
even if we do very extensive system
identification like estimating the
parameters of those physics based
deformable object simulator, the
identified model is noticeably less
accurate than the model that directly
learned from the real world
interactions. Like I showed earlier, for
example, the first row is our model's
open loop prediction. The second row is
a ground truth. Our model's prediction
aligns very well with the ground truth,
which is just much more accurate than
whatever physics based simulators out
there.
Okay. So if there are no more questions
I will continue. So what we have
discussed is this kind of model learning
and how this learned model can be
effective for the downstream like a
model based planning and next category
of algorithms is imitation learning. So
like just to like recap a little bit
like we discussed reinforcement learning
that is learn direct learning the
policies by doing trials and error with
the environments which has a lot of
troubles for example the sample
efficiency the safety concerns and for
the model learning what we have been
doing is actually forced back to the
category of supervised learning where we
have the evolutions of the environments.
You use that data to do supervised
learning to train this model and using
this model to do model based planning
and instead of just using supervised
learning to do to train the model people
are also asking can we do supervised
learning also for the policies. This is
the general idea of imitation learning
meaning can we have a big data set that
shows how a task needs to be done and
using this data sets like to train this
kind of policies. I'm showing this
figure again. This is trying to learn
this kind of policy taking the states as
inputs that predict the actions and all
of this kind of learning signals and
learning procedures are done through a
large scale collected datas from human
demoing to the robots how a task needs
to be done. So learning from
demonstration is of course not new. that
has been investigated for decades is
also constantly how we human is actually
learning to perform a lot of like a
physical interactions or social
activities in the real world like since
we are very very young. So one of the
most like earlier classic like imitation
learning algorithms is called behavior
cloning and essentially trying to learn
this kind of mapping. The map currently
like from this observation O into the
action A and this policy is represented
using this function pi parameterized by
the SATA. So one of the key issues for
behavior coloning is called cascading
error because like I mentioned the key
difference between the robot learning or
agents interaction with environments is
it is a sequential decision making
problem. It differs from like a typical
like a supervised learning in the
typical computer vision domain in that
your error can accumulate and being
amplified over time. Let's say at the
very beginning you made a very small
error. That small error can list your
states that is slightly deviates from
the distribution of data you use to
train your model. That will lead a
policy to make a even larger error and
this error will be amplified over the
temporal horizons that leads to a
trajectory that can decrease quite a lot
from the demonstration trajectories. So
that's a typical issues of behavior
chronic. So that's why uh often times
when people are trying to make imitation
learning work people follow this type of
pipeline where on the top we have the
demonstration collected by the experts.
Then we'll use that as a training data
to do supervised learning to train this
policy and we'll rule out the policy in
the real environment and observe those
failure cases and we either collect
additional data or provide corrective
behaviors that allows this data sets to
not only contains the initial
demonstrations but also those corrective
behaviors that gets the errors from the
policies back to the cononical
trajectory or get back to the
trajectory. they can still successfully
accomplish the task. So this is actually
a typical like life cycles we are trying
to develop any imitation learning agents
or imitation learning algorithms in the
real physical world
and uh uh along this lines because like
if people do this kind of imitation
learning there's not uh very explicit
definitions of what the task actually is
the task is implicitly hidden within
those demonstrations. So there's a class
of algorithm called inverse
reinforcement learning where on the left
is what people typically like thinking
about for reinforcement learning whereas
on the right where people are trying to
use this inverse reinforcement learning
to like summarize the rewards from your
demonstrations and be able to use that
rewards to do typical reinforcement
learning to learn this kind of
algorithms. Some of the earlier like
susex examples were actually also
developed at Stanford's by uh Peter Bio
and also Andrew in it that allows them
to control uh helicopters to do some
very very crazy behaviors and this is
actually a very old work and uh be able
to achieve this type of like agile and
uh and effective behaviors on this real
physical helicopters is very impressive
uh at that times. So this is the power
of learning from demonstrations and
using that demonstration to summarize
the rewards and in connections with
reinforcement learning this is what we
are able to achieve. So obviously over
the years like people have been making
the imitation learning algorithms more
and more effective especially in
connecting with for example energy based
models. So instead of learning this kind
of explicit policy shown on the left
they directly do the mapping from
observation all to the actions. If you
are coming up with kind of implicit
policies that's takes idea from energy
based models that direct taking the
observation actions to predict the score
and using this kind of like a energy
based model to do inference to get this
kind of predicted actions ahead allows
the robots to handle demonstrations that
are very multimodels or handle scenarios
where the optimization landscapes may
not be very very smooth and the robot is
able to come up with this kind of
strategies like distill these policies
from the demonstrations in doing this
kind of contentrich manipulation tasks.
Another to say like uh some of the
recent very recent success of robot
learning as a whole is a results of this
work called diffusion policy which again
is also taking some of advances in the
community of gener models. For this one
like for the implicit behavior people
are drawing inspiration from development
of energy based model. Energy based
model is a type of generated models
developed in the deep learning
community. And there's another class of
like a more powerful models in the deep
learning community is called diffusion
models. And people are also trying to
use the diffusion models to use it as a
policy function class to allow the
agents to also like inherence the
benefits and the properties from those
diffusion models. So this work uh was
originally done at Colombia. That's is
where I uh am right now and the leads
like a PI of this work now come to
Stanfords. You can see like many of the
work I selected are has a lot of like
roots like here at Stanford's like she's
currently like at the WE departments at
Stanfords and this policy really shows
some like a very diverse set of
capabilities allow the robots to do not
just like a planner pushings but many
like a fine grains like manipulation
task not only pick and place but for
example here spread butter on top of the
spreads and also like like a like a
scramble eggs like like also or peeling
the potatoes and sliding the books. It
really shows that this type of recipe
where you collect a bunch of
demonstrations and using the best like
policies like learning mechanisms, you
can get a policy that work in the real
physical worlds in a very very efficient
manners. Meaning you collect the data in
the morning, you train a policy in the
moment, in the afternoon, you can have a
working policies working in the real
physical world. So obviously there's a
lot of caveats in how reliable your
policy is and how generalizable your
policy is, how diversified the initial
configuration can be for the policy to
still work very robustly. But still
imitation learning is the most efficient
way for you to get a policy that can do
something interesting in the real
physical world. And for the policies to
be very effective and robust to the real
world variations, this type of iterative
like data collections will needs will
needs to be in place for the policy to
cover those kind of like uh unexpected
behaviors or some kind of dev eating
behaviors.
So this is about imitation learning. So
any questions?
Okay. So if there's no more questions, I
will use the remaining time to discuss
some of the uh recent developments that
drive all the craziness about robot
learnings which is like a robotic
foundation models and uh of course like
this is a very involved domain actually
for each one of these items you can
actually have a course around them. So
like for today's lecture I'm just like
skimming through them very very quickly.
I only tell you the gist like the high
level like knowledge you need to get by
looking at those terms. And for robotic
foundation models, it is a type of
models that is very similar to like a
reinforcement learning or imitation
learnings in their function class.
There's no explicit representation for
example of the states or this kind of
model. For example, this robotic
foundation model doesn't learn the model
of the environments. It is still a
policy that map from the observation and
goal into the actions that still like a
representative can be very nicely
represented using these figures. So you
have this agents which is a policy that
taking the current state and also the
goal as inputs that trying to generate
this actions that can be executed in the
real physical world. But you might say
like this is very similar to imitation
learning and reinforcement learning. So
what's special about this robotic
foundation models? So this is actually
all rooted back to the all the
developments within the foundation model
domain especially those language related
foundation model and also those vision
language related foundation models
meaning it is a policy but it needs to
generalize much better than a policy
that just work for one specific task
like here is actually my definitions I'm
joining analogies from the current
developments of vision language models
meaning their outputs may not always be
the perfect one but to always generate
something reasonable as you promise this
kind of foundation model. So what we
hope to achieve with this robotic
foundation model is the synthesized
action may not always be the optimal
actions as conditioned by the
observation and the task. But the
generary trajectory or will always be
beautiful and reasonable to execute in
the real physical world. Like beautiful
meaning it shouldn't just any like
jiggling motions. It should be smooth
and continuous. Reasonable meaning you
should listen to the language
instructions you are given to the
robots. So obviously there are also many
different names describing exactly the
same things. Some people call it vision
language action models like VAS. Some
people call it like a large behavior
models. But in the eence they're all
describing the same thing meaning this
policy taking the observation and
language instructions or whatever like a
task specification is trying to generate
the actions that generalize widely
across a wide range of scenarios.
So this area is actually quite noisy.
Noisy meaning it's very very like hard
to quantify the progress of different
kind of robotic foundation models
because you're coding a foundation
model. What does that mean? That means
you expect this model to generalize like
very broadly over a wide range of
scenarios. If that's your expectation,
you actually need significant evidence
to show it actually generalize broadly.
So that's why evaluation and
quantitative measurements of their
progress is very challenging. But still
by looking at the empirical videos you
can still see a lot of very interesting
and concrete progress over the past few
years. So a lot of the earlier
investigation starts like with like RT1
which was released in the December 2022
and since then I would say maybe roughly
every half a year there's a new model
for RT2 RTX open VA and some of the
recent ones like uh PI zero that's is
making concrete progress along this
lines of developing more and more
generalizable robotic foundation models
and actually this year that's a boost
there's a huge like first of a lot of
like foundation model like a helix high
robot gemini robotics pispin 5 etc. So
there's a lot of investigations and also
investments in this domain in not not
only like a capital investment but
talent investments in developing better
better and better and more generalizable
robotic foundation models. So due to the
time I I I clearly cannot go into
details of all these models. So if you
are interested, I actually gave a
tutorial two months ago at tripleAI
specifically describing and discussing
some of the models along this axis. If
you are interested, please go and uh
watch it. And for today, I'll be mostly
give you a high level overview of what
actually uh is essentials for this kind
of foundation models and what it
actually looks like with an examples
from PI zero. So PI0 was first released
in October 2024.
I think this is a word that convinced me
that this type of robotic foundation
model can do some very reliable like a
texturous manipulations in the real
world environments. It can handle like
cloth folding and box folding and many
other different types of manipulation
tasks at a very reliable manner. And
here's how the framework actually looks
like on the high level. On the left is
data sets. So for any model to be called
foundation model it needs a fuel for
that foundation model and that fuel is
data. So they aggregate a lot of data
both within academia and also data
collected by themselves across course
many different embodiment where the
robots are doing like some kind of
interesting and useful task in the real
world environments and they use this
data to do pre-training and one
important caveat of this pre-training
this starts with a pre-trained like
vision language models the vision
language model that's already trained on
vast amount of like a vision language
related data that can naturally adapt
those kind of semantically and knowledge
from those models and together by doing
co-fineting what they call co-fine
tuning using both objective for action
predictions and also the objective
adapted from those vision question
answering those type of tasks you will
be able to first preserve the semantic
knowledge within those model but at the
same time you can predict the robot
actions and this is a pre-tuning stage a
very important like design for many of
the existing robotic foundation models
is called post training which is also
inspired by many of the developments in
the large language model communities
where you have this base model. Base
model can give you some reasonable
baseline performance but you really want
the performance to be very very good on
a specific task. You actually have to
collect task specific data to fine-tune
the models do post training on the data
for that specific task for the
performance to be satisfied.
So they are evaluating their whole
systems over three different categories.
The first one you should directly use
their base model and their base model
can already be good enough for some very
simple indistri in distribution data.
The the task like is actually the task
that might have already been encountered
during the pre-training stage. If for
indistribution task but slightly more
complicated you can do post training to
allow the base model to further improve
on those indistribution task. And for
unseen task typically you have to do
post trainings by collecting those task
specific data and fine-tune your
pre-trained model on this tasks for it
to be performance
and this pi zero model is actually open
sourced and you can just download the
checkpoints my lab the students in my
lab have already been starting to
playing with this like uh their models
and trying to do post training and we
are starting to see some very promising
like results. So if you are interested
highly encouraged to try it. That is a
very good question. So you are
essentially asking about the efficiency
of the existing robotic foundation
models. So there's a lot of reasons why
the policy is actually slower than
humans. One of the major reason is
actually adapted from how the data was
collected, how the demonstration data
was collected. Typically for many of
these scenarios the demonstration data
was collected by human tele operating
the robots on that exact same robots to
do the data collections in for example
folding this box and human tele
operations is actually slower than human
just using their hands to do this tasks
even if you have gou for them hours of
training. This is because you are just
using a different embodiment than a
environment that you person is the most
familiar with. And also at the same time
because the robot arms are still like
certain distance away from you. There
will be occlusion. Sometime you have to
look very closely carefully like
changing your heads changing the the the
viewing angles in order to really
understand is it a time to progress into
next task stage or not. there's a lot of
like caveats and inefficiencies
of the current data collection regimes.
That is why the policy directly trained
on those data turn out to be slower than
like human speeds. So that's why there's
a lot of like investigations in how we
can do those kind of data collections to
be even more efficient to be at human
speeds that is actually a very active
research direction. So this is a very
good question. So for this like a box
folding house I would argue this is
already a very long hor task. So I was
very impressed by how good this one
single policy is able to handle this
long harden task. But you could argue if
you really want this policy to be useful
in some like a more larger scale like in
a wide scenarios in your home you not
only want the robot to fold a box if I
wanted to fold the shirts and clean the
beds and clean all the messes on the
floor. If in those type of scenarios
like uh currently me personally I don't
believe one gigantic policy is able to
be able to adapt to those scenarios some
higher level obstructions or some kind
of singraft some symbolic
representations needs to be in place as
a condition for this vision language
action models for those like policy to
be the most effective and useful to
steer into different type of tasks and
scale to larger scale environments and
more complicated tasks.
So they started with a pre-trained
vision language models. So that's why
like there's already a lot of semantic
knowledge that are learned through this
large scale pre-training using this
vision language data. So that is why
like some of the generalization are
coming for free. Meaning the base model
can actually have surprisingly good
levels of generalizations at a semantic
level. And it's just that you have to
fine-tune this model with those robot
data to making sure it can also
generalize not as a semantic level but
also as action level.
So we can have the question maybe at
unknown because we're already about time
I still have maybe one the last maybe
two three minutes I'll discuss the some
of the remaining challenges especially
along the developments of robot learning
models so one of the major challenges
the whole community recognize is
evaluation evaluation currency is
primarily done in the real world for
example this is a picture of uh Google
robotics they have a grid of this kind
of teleoperating like Aloha systems that
they are doing data collection and also
evaluation and real world evaluation is
both costly and noisy. Their exact words
to me was for evaluation they have large
enough budget such that they can still
make progress. This was their exact
words. Meaning if you were to do the
evaluation or I were to do the
evaluation the results can be very
different from each other depending on
how we specify the initial configuration
and how the lighting condition might
change. Even the friction parameters of
the manufacturer can make a huge
difference in how robust your downstream
policy is. So this is very costly and
they have to wait for two days for the
results to come back and currently like
uh there's very weak correlation between
the training loss and real world success
rates. This is another very important
caveat and difference between supervised
learning and also this kind of
sequential decision-m this kind of
policy learning is for supervised
learning like your training loss
directly measures how good your model
is. But for this kind of poly learning
your training loss measures how good
this onestep prediction is which
sometimes may not be and actually often
the times is not indicative of the
performance of policy over like a long
task horizons. Even if your loss is low
but for long horizon task execution your
policy can actually be worse. And uh the
training objective versus the task
specific metrics like training versus
test horizons are some of the reasons
explaining like why it is very hard to
come up with even approximate or proxy
metrics to measure the performance of
the policy and people have to rely on
real world evaluations.
So then the question is what about doing
the evaluation in the simulated
environments there has been a lot of
like investigation for the behavior
which is done in fif lab here also at
Stanford's and also the habitat 3.0 zero
from meta. People are trying to come up
with this expensive simulated
environments trying to do evaluation and
measurements of the robot policies and
obviously there has their own issues
especially with regard to sim to real
gap like how can you do very accurate
simulation of rigid body deformable
object close they have good correlations
with the real world performance and
assets is also another major issues
where large scale generalizations and
generations of those assets is a huge
pain um I can elaborate but like maybe
after the lectures and also how to
digitize the real world is an issue and
how to do procedural generations of
realistic and diverse things are all
issues of using simulation to do
evaluations for robot learning policies
and really we want to find a correlation
between s and real and it's calling upon
the imagets in embodied AI like the
reason why imaget was successful is
because at least for few years any
progress in imaget meaning progress in
deep learning and computeration we want
the same thing we want have this
platform meaning any progress on that
benchmark or platform meaning progress
in robot learnings so that's something
that we really want and uh um I can
maybe skip through like uh we talk about
how to build this foundational policies
there can also be investigations on how
to build like a foundational word models
especially now people are collecting
large scale action condition robot
interaction data to train this
foundation policies but there's a lot of
dynamics knowledge embedded in those
data if we just use those data to do
policy learning that would be such a
waste. So we are also thinking about how
we can use this large scale action
condition robot interaction data that
was already collected to train those
foundational policy to train this
foundational word models and how they
can do interplay between each others and
there are some existing works that are
thinking about along the direction of
building this kind of foundational word
models and there are some like very like
interesting like characteristics you
might thinking about like do you want it
to be 3D do you want structural prior
how much learning versus how much
physics and how you can correlate with
the real physical world. And maybe
actually I think uh we are about time so
I will end it here. And uh this is the
future we hope to achieve to really
build this foundational robotic model
that can work very widely and generalize
very well in the unstructured data
environments around us. And next
lectures will be human- centered AI. And
that will be uh the end of today's
lecture. Thank you so much.