okay hi
everyone back from all
cs224n um okay
so for today the plan is essentially a
continuation of what we started on
Tuesday so I'm going to say um more
about language models and more about
rnns in particular introd using a more
advanced form of recurrent new network
which was for a while very dominant um
lstms will talk about those and then in
the latter part as something to be done
with um current neural networks we'll
start looking at neural machine
translation
um okay so on Tuesday what we did was we
introduced language models A system that
predicts the next word and then I
introduced recurrent new Networks that's
was this new neural architecture that
can take sequential input of any length
and it applied the same weight to each
step and can optionally produce output
on each step um so these are two
distinct Notions though they tend to go
together so uh recurrent new network can
be used for other purposes on any kinds
of sequence and I'll mention a few of
those later today um and language
modeling is a traditional component of
many NLP tasks anything to do with
generating text or estimating
likelihoods of pieces of text and indeed
in the modern instantiation of large
language models essentially everything
we do in um NLP is being done by
language models so a language model one
way to do it is with the recurrent
neural network it's certainly not the
only way we also talked last time about
engram language models which were
language models and then starting next
week we'll start to talk about
Transformers which are now the most
widespread way that's used for building
language
models um so just finish off a teeny bit
that I didn't get to last time on
evaluating language models well one way
to evaluate language models is what I
did in class last time generate some
text and say hey doesn't this text look
good um but you know often we want
something more rigorous than that and
the standard way to evaluate language
models is to say well you know a
language model scores a piece of text
and says How likely it is and our
standard for text in the language is
stuff produced by human beings so if we
find a new piece of text which wasn't
text that the model was trained on right
we want some fresh um fresh evaluation
data and we show it um to a language
model model we can then ask the language
model to predict the success of words of
this text and the better it is at doing
that the better a language model it is
because it's more accurately able to
predict um a human written piece of text
and so the standard way that that is
measured is with this measure that's
called perplexity and so for perplexity
we are taking um the probability of a
prediction from the language model we're
in inverting it so instead of it being
you know .002 or something we're turning
into 500 or something like that um and
then we're taking those numbers we're
taking the product of them at each
position in the text and then we're
finding the geometric average of them um
so that's the measure that's normally
used but if we in this class we've been
tending um to look um at um negative log
likelihoods and um the idea of cross
entropy um and so what perplexity is is
it's just the exponential of the Cross
entropy um so if you've already familiar
with negative log like per word negative
log likelihoods if you just exponentiate
that um you then get the perplexity now
there's one other little trick as to
what base you use for your logarithms
and exponentials I mean traditionally
thinking of sort of binary and stuff a
lot of the time people use Bas two for
measuring perplexity um that's kind of
gone out now a lot of the time now
people are using natural logs but if
you're comparing perplexity numbers
they're going to be different depending
on um what base you're using for things
so you needs to be aware of this um so
from a sort of a modern perspective it
kind of makes no sense um why um
perplexity is used um the story of why
perplexity was used was you know in the
bad old days of symbolic artificial
intelligence when all of those famous
people like John McCarthy and Ed Fen bam
were around doing logical based systems
um some people then essentially at IBM
including Fred gelan started exploring
probabilistic methods for speech
recognition and other similar methods um
and um the story Fred gelene used to
tell was well at that time this was in
the late 70s or early 80s that none of
the AI people um that he was trying to
talk to understood how to do any real
math and didn't understand um any
information Theory Notions of um of do
doing things like cross entropy or cross
entropy rate so he had to come up with
something simpler they could understand
um and so what he came up with is by
sort of doing this
exponentiated um perplexity you can
think of per a perplexity number as
being equivalent to how many uniform
choices you're choosing between so if
the perplexity of something is
64 that's like having a 64 sided dice
that you're rolling each time and that's
your chance of your chance of getting a
one on that is your chance of guessing
the right word um so that was why
perplexity got introduced but it's kind
of stuck and so when you see scores for
language models you generally still see
perplexities so a lower perplexity is
better um so here are the kind of
numbers and where progress was made with
neural language models so before that um
people used engram language models and
people used clever ways to smooth them
using methods I vaguely alluded to last
time of this ad case smoothing and doing
back off actually people use clever
methods um around um the 2000th decade
the cleverest method known of smoothing
engram language models was this thing
called interpolated kessi smoothing um
and so for a big language model using
that the perplexity was about
67 um which in some sense means that you
weren't very good at predicting the next
word um but you know that had actually
been enormous progress you know when I
was a young person doing um NLP you know
perplexities were three figure numbers
right you were commonly seeing you know
perplexities of 150 or something like
that so progress was made um so when
rnn's were first introduced people
weren't really actually able to do
better with a sort of a pure RNN but
they could do better by combining an RNN
with something else such as a symbolic
maximum entropy model which I'm not
going to explain but those are numbers
like that 51 but where progress um
really started to be made was when lstm
started to be used as an improved RNN
which is what I'm going to come to next
so here are some lstm models and now
you're getting numbers like 43 and 30
and so for 30 you've sort of halfed the
perplexity which in um cross entropy
terms means you reduce the cross entropy
by about one bit um and so you've made
real progress um in your language
modeling Now by modern standards um
these numbers are still really high
right for the best language models that
we have now you're getting perplexities
in the single digits you're getting
models that are very often able to guess
exactly the right word though of course
not always cuz no one can predict what
words going to be said by someone next
in a lot of
circumstances okay um so um to motivate
lstms then wanted to sort of say a bit
about how there are problems with rnns
and why that motivated fixing things and
these are the problems of Vanishing and
exploding gradients so what we wanted to
do was say okay we've tried to predict a
word at position four and often we're
going to get it we're not going to
predict it with 100% probability so we
we have a loss that's a negative log
likelihood we give to that word and
we're going to want to back propagate
that loss um through the
sequence um and work out our gradients
as we always do now just one note about
something someone asked after class um
last time you know I sort of showed it
back propagating the whole sequence but
we're doing this at every time step
right so we're going to back propagate a
loss from time step two back propagate a
loss from time step 3 4 5 6 7 we're
doing it for each one and in one of the
slides last time we then discussed how
we're going to sum all of those losses
or work out the average loss um but for
doing this one when we back propagate
this loss what happens
well what happens is we're going to do
the same kind of chain roll where we're
multiplying these partial derivatives at
every time step and well here we've only
got a few of them but you know maybe
we're going to have a sequence 30 long
and so we're going to be multiplying
each time the partial of HK time with
respect to the partial of HK minus1 and
so what kind of effect is that going to
have
um in particular you know we might ask
what happens if these are small or what
happens if these are large well if
they're small the gradient will
gradually get smaller and smaller and
disappear as we back propagate it along
the sequence
yeah so why we're taking partial J over
partial should we take partial J
sure I mean we're doing that as well um
but you know in general we have to walk
the partials along and then you know we
then have a w at the next
step I mean if we're thinking of the
sort of computation graph that we're
sort of doing the chain rule backwards
along we're going to be going through a
w at each step and then arriving at
another AG
right
um yeah so I mean at this point you can
you can do some math and thinking about
things um and there's a couple of papers
that are mentioned at the bottom here
which I'm actually uh rushing ahead not
going to do very carefully um but the
point is that if you're taking the
partial of HT with respect to HT
minus1 um and if you make a simplifying
assumption and say Suppose there isn't a
nonlinearity suppose Sigma is just the
identity then what the partial will be
is the Matrix
wh and so if you keep on back
propagating along the recurrent neural
network what you're going to be doing
is what ending up with powers of the
Matrix wh and then there's the question
of what happens when you raise that
Matrix to higher and higher Powers well
at that point you can represent the
Matrix in terms of its igen vectors and
IG values and then there are two
possibilities either all the igen values
are less than one and that means that
that number will be getting smaller and
smaller smaller as you raise it to
higher power or it can have IG ve IG
values that are larger than one and then
things will get bigger and bigger as you
go further back so essentially as you
back propagate the gradients backwards
unless things are sort of just
precisely of um corresponding to a
largest Aon Vector
of large ion value of approximately one
you're either going to get a Vanishing
or an explosion and both of those will
be kind of
bad so why is Vanishing gradient a
problem I mean in a sense you could
think it's it's not a problem it's what
should be happening because all else
being equal you know the closest words
are the most relevant ones and so that's
where you should be updating your
parameters the most and to some extent
that that's true but nevertheless this
vanish gradient in this model happens
much too severely so that if you're
looking at the loss from a later
position and comparing it to the loss um
from an earlier position and then you're
seeing how things are updating it's sort
of primarily the update is being
determined by the very nearby loss and
not by the far away loss um that the
gradient signal from far away is much
much smaller ER and well that's bad
because you know overall for language
modeling there are lots of cases where
we want to be able to transmit signals a
long distance so here's my piece of text
um when she tried to print her ticket
she found that the printer was out of
toner she went to the stationary store
to buy more toner it was very overpriced
after installing the toner into the
printer she finally printed
her yeah so you know human being you
know it's obvious we can predict this
with pretty much probability one you
know so um really low perplexity for
making this decision um but you know if
you're that's depends on getting back to
the tickets which are sort of about 20
odd words back right if you're just
seeing installing the toner into the
printer she finally printed her could be
anything it could be her paper her
invitation her novel um lots of things
could be you're certainly not going to
guess tickets
so we sort of want to have these really
long distance dependencies but we're
only going to be able to learn these
long distance dependencies if we're
actually getting sufficient signal
between that position and when the word
tickets appears near the beginning that
we can learn the fact that having that
tickets 20 words back is the good
predictive thing for predicting tickets
here and what we find is um that you
know when the gradient becomes very
small the RNN doesn't learn these kind
of longdistance dependencies and so it's
unable to sort of make these predictions
well at test time I mean this is a very
sort of just
rough uh back of the envelope estimate
but you know what people actually found
is that you know with this the kind of
simple r&n that we've introduced up
until now that the amount of effective
conditioning you could get was about
seven tokens back um that if things were
further back than that it just never
learned to condition on them and so you
know compared to when we were talking
about NS and I said are usually the
maximum people did was 5 G occasionally
a bit bigger because of the fact that
there was this exponential blowout
although in theory we've now got a much
better solution in practice because of
Vanishing gradients well we're only kind
of getting the equivalent of 8 G so we
haven't made that much progress it feels
like um so there's a reverse problem
which can also happen of exploding
gradients so if the gradient becomes
very large because the IG values of that
Matrix are large well what we're doing
for the parameter update is you know
we've got a learning rate but
essentially if the gradient is very
large we're going to make a very very
large parameter update and that can
cause very bad updates because you know
we're sort of assuming that we're taking
a step in the direction of the gradient
and well we might overshoot a little but
we'll be in a roughly in the right Zone
but you know if we had an enormously
exploded gradi and well we could kind of
be sort of walking off anywhere and you
know we think we're heading to the
sieras and we end up in Iowa or
something like that right you know that
we could just go arbitrarily far and
where we're ending up it might not be
making any progress whatsoever um so
exploding gradients are a problem um
they can also cause Infinities and nans
and they're always a problem when you're
training models um now for
for dealing with exploding gradients um
this is the accepted wisdom um this
unfortunately doesn't this isn't High
futing math really um what people use
for exploding gradients is a crude hack
they clip gradients um but you know it
works really well and you really want to
know about this um because clipping
gradients is often essential um to
having newal networks not having
problems so what we do for gradient
clipping is we work out the norm of the
gradient and if it seems too large and
that varies but you know that's normally
5 10 20 something like that for a norm
of a gradient is seen as the limit of
what's okay if the norm of your gradient
is too large you just scale it down in
every direction and you apply a smaller
gradient
update um it works um yeah so that
problem is solvable um but fixing the
vanishing gradient seemed a more
difficult problem right that this was
the problem that our rnns effectively
couldn't preserve information over many
time steps um and well what seemed to be
the problem there the problem seems to
be really that we've got sort of an
architecture that makes it very hard to
preserve information so if we look at
sort of the Hidden state from one time
step to the next time step um it's
completely being Rewritten right so
we're taking the previous time steps
hidden um hidden Vector we're
multiplying it by a matrix which
completely changes it in general adding
in other stuff from the input so if we
just like to say we'd like to say we'd
like you to carry forward information
there's useful stuff in htus y can you
just kind of keep it around for a while
it's not actually very easy to do in
this formulation cuz you know trying to
learn
uh W vectors that all mostly preserve
what was there before isn't at all and
obvious thing to do um so the question
was could we design an
RNN which had a sort of a memory where
is easy to preserve information yes so
in in one of the earlier slides you
mentioned the
exponentiation happened during their
analysis they remove the
larity
so sort
ofation prevent Vanishing oring no it
actually doesn't I mean you can make an
argument that it should help because
you've got effectively if you got
something like tan H you've got a
flattening function um so it should help
somewhat but it doesn't solve it even if
you're using a t nonlinearity well so I
guess it should sorry it should help
with exploding though actually that even
that still happens but it definitely
doesn't help with the vanishing if you
have Sig think that is one value so
you're always pushing the value between
one so it's not going up or going down
it's staying between Z and
one but so
yeah Z
well I guess would it go up and so you
have a really small value that becomes
oneus a really small value Sig *
1us oh Sig
*
okay um yeah so can we have a
different architecture so we have a
memory that you can add to um and so
that led into this new kind of newal
network the lstm so this is going back a
few years but any rate um this was
trying to improve Siri suggestions and
the big breakthrough that they were
described was being described was oh
we're now using an lstm in the keyboard
prediction and the whole advantage of
that um was was going to be able to
predict context further back so you
could differentiate between the children
are playing in the park versus the
Orioles are playing in the
playoff okay um so so the sort of big
thing that was seen as very successful
was these um lstms long short-term
memory um just to say a little bit of
the history here right um just on the
how to PA this name right that I think
people often don't even understand it
right so what you wanting to do was
model shortterm memory right because so
for humans people this normally
distinguish between the short-term
memory of stuff that you heard recently
versus things that you permanently
stored away um and the suggestion was
well in short-term memory humans can
remember stuff for quite a while right
you know if you're having a conversation
you can still remember um the thing that
the person said a few turns ago the
conversation said bring back up of oh
didn't you say they um took last weekend
off or something right and well the
problem was that the simple rnns their
short-term memory was only about seven
tokens and so we'd like to make it
better than that and so we wanted long
short-term memory and that's where this
um name came about and so this was a
type of recurrent new network um that
was um um proposed by HW and schmidhuber
in 1997 as a solution to the problem I
mean there's actually a second relevant
piece of work that came a few years
later that you know that first paper is
the one that everybody cites um but
there's then a second paper by gz and
smid Huber in 2000 which actually
introduces a crucial part of the lstm as
we've used in the 21st century that
wasn't in the original paper
um and you know so it's sort of an
interesting story of all of this so you
know that um joggen schmidhuber and his
students did a lot of really crucial
foundational work in newal networks and
the sort of these years and the lat
years of the '90s um when just about
everybody else had given up on newal
networks um so unlike these days where
you know doing um pioneering work in new
networks is a really good way to get
yourself hugely compensated jobs at
Google meta or open AI it really wasn't
actually in these days so you know if
you um ask G what happened to these
students um of hot crater and um G um
that both of them are still in Academia
but um G seem to give up on AI and new
networks all together and does stuff in
the area of
multimedia um and SE Haw riter um is
still in machine learning but you know
for quite a long time he sort of
basically gave up on doing more General
neural network stuff and went into
bioinformatics so if you look at his
Publications from about 2
2015 um they were all in bioinformatics
and most of them weren't using neural
networks at all um though um kind of
nicely I mean he's actually gone back
into new networks more recently and is
publishing a new networks again um yeah
so um really not much attention was paid
to this work at the time and so it only
sort of really kind of gradually seeped
out further um so um Schmid hu had a
later student in the mid 2000s decade
Alex Graves um and Alex Graves um did
more stuff with lstms and for people
who've seen um speech recognition where
people commonly do CTC loss and decoding
Alex Graves invented that but um most
crucially um Alex Graves then um went to
um Toronto to be postto for Jeff Hinton
and that sort of brought more attention
to the fact that lstms were a good model
um and then Jeff Hinton went to Google
in
2013 and That Was Then sort of the use
of um lstms at Google um in the sort of
2014 to 16 period was when they really
sort of um hit the world and became for
a while the completely dominant
framework people use for neural
networks um in the world of uh I guess
startups this is what you call being too
early for the first people um yeah um
okay long short-term memories back to
the science um so um let's see um
there's a slide here that talks about um
long short-term memories but maybe I'll
just sort of skip straight ahead and
start to show the pictures so we've
still got a sequence of inputs XT and
the difference now is um inside our
newal Network we're going to have two
hidden things one that's still called
The Hidden State and the other one
that's referred to as the cell State and
so what we're going to do is we're going
to modulate how these things get updated
by introducing the idea of gates and so
gates are calculated things vectors
whose values are probabilities between
zero and one and they're things that
we're going to use to sort of turn
things on or shut them off in a
probabilistic way so we're going to
control the movement of information by
having
gating and so we're going to calculate
three gating vectors so these vectors
are the same length as our hidden States
um and so the way we calculate these
gating vectors is with an equation that
looks basically exactly the same as what
we were using for current newal networks
um apart from the Sigma there is
definitely going to be the logistic that
goes between Zer and one so we get
probabilities and the three gates we're
going to calculate is a forget gate
which is going to say how much do we
remember of the previous times hidden
State I think the forget gate was
actually wrongly named I think it makes
more sense to think of it as a remember
gate because it's actually calculating
how much you're remembering um okay then
we've got an input gate and the input
gate is going to say how much are you
going to pay attention to the next input
the next XI and put it into your hidden
State and then you have an output gate
and the output gate is going to control
how much of of what's in the cell which
is your primary memory are you going to
transfer over to the hidden state of the
network okay so once we have
um once we have those Gates
um what we're then going to do has have
these equations which are how we're
going to um sort of update things so the
first thing we're going to do is work
out uh work out a potential new cell
content so the new cell content is going
to be calculated exactly using the
exactly the same kind of equation we saw
last time for a current networks we're
going to have um these two matrices um
the cell W and the cell U and we're
going to multiply one by the last time's
hidden State and the other by the new
input add on a bias and that's a
potential update to the cell but then
how we're actually going to update the
cell is by making use of our gates so
we're going to say the new cells content
is going to be the old cells content um
hadamar producted with the forget gate
so that's how much to remember of the
previous cells content plus this
calculated update had aad producted with
the input gate how much to pay attention
to this new potential update that we've
um invented and then for calculating the
new hidden State that's going to be
um the had mod product between the
output gate and
um our CT having been put through a tan
H um and you know one idea here is you
know we're thinking about how much to
keep on remembering what we've had in
the past but you know for thinking about
sort of only sending some information to
the hidden State as sort of a way to
start thinking about that is you know
the hidden state of a recurrent newal
network is sort of doing multiple Duty
right like on one part of it is we were
going to feed it into the output to
predict the next token but in another
thing it's going to do is we just want
it to store information about the past
that might come in useful later and that
we'd like to kind of have carried
through the sequence and so really only
some of what
in the hidden State we want to be using
to predict the current word some of it
isn't relevant to predicting the current
word but would be good stuff to know for
the future right so you know if the
previous words were set in um for
predicting the next word we basically
just need to know we're in a satin
context where the or a will come next
but you know if earlier on the sentence
that been saying the King of Prussia we
somewhere in the hidden State we want to
be keeping the information that there's
a King of Prussia because that might be
relevant for predicting future words and
so it makes sense that we only want to
have some of what's in our memory being
used to predict the the next word in the
current context so the cell is our long
short-term memory and then we're moving
over to the hidden state things are
going to be relevant for
Generation um yeah I've sort of said
that okay
uh all these are vectors of the same
length n yeah so all of all of these
things both the gates and the new values
for the cell and hidden state they're
all vectors of length n and part of how
things actually get convenient when
you're actually running of these is up
until here all of these things have
exactly the same shape so you can
actually put them all together into a
big Matrix and do the computations of
all four of these in terms of um one big
Matrix if you want question if you did
not have the Dage activation in the
hidden State update then the output dat
should have been expressed by both the
input dates
and you're if this if this bit wasn't
here then then you would not need an
output dat well because ft and it would
have been able to express it account for
it in some sense my question is how much
does having right well no to the extent
that you want to mask out part of what's
in the
cell so it's not visible when you're
generating the next token isn't it still
useful to have an output
gate you can essentially have XT
C you don't want HT equal to CT you want
H you want some of the contents of CT to
be masked out so you you're not seeing
it when generating the output masking
would have being accounted for by fdn ID
is my no because you want to keep it in
CT you want there's information you want
to keep in CT for the future um but you
don't want visible when generating the
current next
word
yeah um in some sense a bit I have the
hardest part explaining is
why is it necessarily better to have a
tan H here I mean you can sort of argue
that it's a way of this can just stay
unbounded real numbers and then this is
getting it back in the shape of stays
between zero and one which is good for
the um hidden state but it's a little
bit I guess they did it that way it seem
to work well okay um here's another way
of looking at it which may or may not be
more helpful um as a picture so you know
at each time step we've got you know as
before um an input a hidden State and
then we're going to calculate an output
from that hidden state but we've sort of
got this more complex computational unit
and these pictures of this more complex
computational unit um were diagrams were
made by Chris oler who's someone who now
um
right now works at anthropic
um and so if you blow up in that this is
sort of showing the computation so
you're sort of feeding along
recurrently um the
C cell as the primary recurrent unit but
you've also got carried along H because
H is being used to calculate stuff for
the next time step and then a new H is
being generated um and so you're
Computing the forget gate you're
forgetting some of the cell content
you're Computing an input gate you're
using that to compute um a potential new
cell content um you write some of that
into the cell um depending on the input
gate um then you compute an output gate
and then some of the cell will go into
um the computation of H depending on the
output gate and then just like for the
previous recurrent new network for
working out what the predicted next word
is you're working out an output layer by
taking the H and doing another Matrix uh
plus B2 and then using a soft Max on
that to actually predict the next
word okay so you know this all seems
very
complex um
and you know back in do you have a
question yeah I a so how are we deciding
theold I I imagine just some sort of
threshold around the probability of like
what we're remembering and what we're
forgetting um so you know so we we're
getting more than a threshold right
because we're actually we're calculating
a whole Vector of forgetting and
remembering so therefore it can choose
to say Okay Dimensions 1 to 177 keep all
of that and throw away Dimensions 18 to
22 or really probabilistically to
different extents um and so it's sort of
unspecified it's up to it what it learns
but we we're hoping that it will learn
that certain kinds of information is
useful to keep carrying forward for at
least a while um but then we can use
both the contents of the Hidden State
and the cell sorry of the next input to
decide to throw away certain information
so we might think that there are certain
cues for example you know if it sees the
word next it might think okay change of
topic now it be a good time to forget
more stuff and reset but it's sort of
learning which dimensions of this Vector
to hold around in an unconstrained way
whatever's useful to do a better job at
language
modeling okay um yeah so this all looks
like a very complex and
contous um design and you know quite
honestly um you know when teaching this
around 201 you know 16 17 and this was
the best kind of newal network we had
for language modeling you know we
literally you know spent hours of class
time um going through lstms and variant
of lstms with different properties CU
you know there are different ways you
can do the gating you can have less
Gates or more gates and do different
things um and it seemed the most
important thing to know um in
2024 you know it's probably not the most
important thing to know um but um on
lstms are um a thing to be aware of we
are going to use them um for um the
assignment three but you know you can
just ask pytorch for an lstm and I'll
give you one that does all of this stuff
but you know there is one thing that I
really want to sort of focus on as to
you know why what is the good thing that
an lstm achieves and you know really the
secret for why you get this
fundamentally different behavior in an
lstm is you have that plus sign right
there right that for the simple
recurrent neural network at each time
the next hidden state was a result of
multiplicative stuff and therefore it
was very hard just to preserve
information um whereas the essence of
the lstm is to say well look you've got
this past memory of stuff you've already
seen and what we want to do is add some
new information to it which
fundamentally seems like kind of right
for human memories um that they're sort
of basically additive um and when I said
actually it was the second G paper that
introduced a crucial part of the lstm
the first version of the lstm didn't
have the forget gate so it was a purely
additive mechanism that you were
deciding what to add to your memory as
you went along um but you know that
proved to be not quite perfect because
if you keep on adding more and more
stuff over a long sequence that tends to
be dysfunctional after a certain point
and so the big Improvement was then to
add this forget gate so some of it went
away but nevertheless having things
basically additive fixes the problem of
gradient flow you no longer have um
Vanishing gradients and it makes it
something that seems much more memory
like you're adding to the things that
you
know okay um so the lstm architecture
allows you to preserve information over
many time sets in the cell right so if
you set the forget gate to one um and
the input gate to zero you're just
linearly passing along in the cell
indefinitely the same
information okay um it's not the only
way that you can do longdistance
information flow and we're going to look
increasingly in other in future lectures
at other ways you can do um longdistance
information flow um and just to sort of
give a bit of a peek about those now and
to think about other architectures but
there's a question no no question yes um
so so since you're mentioning that those
plus like hand grent uh does it help
with exploding grent at all does it make
it worse is there like no difference or
no it also helps with exploding
gradients because the fact that you're
not doing this sequence of multiplies
all the time that you sort of have this
addition
operator um
so one thing you could wonder is that is
Vanishing and exploding gradients just
uh Rec current neural network problem
and it's not I mean it it it occurs
earlier and worse when you've got long
sequences but if you start building a
very deep neural network surely the same
thing is happening you know the
parameters aren't the same so it's not
quite just raising one Matrix to a power
but surely depending on your matrices
you tend to have the same problem that
either your gradients are disappearing
or else they're exploding um and that's
what people found and that was part of
the reason why in the early days people
weren't very successful building deep
neural networks was because they
suffered from problems of this sort that
if you had basically Vanishing gradients
um in a deep new network you got very
little gradient signal in the lower
layers therefore parameters didn't
really update Therefore your model
didn't learn anything in the lower
layers therefore the network didn't work
well and you know that was part of why
things were stuck in the days around the
early 2000s of deep networks didn't work
um and so there are other ways you can
think about fixing that so one common
way of fixing that is to add more direct
connection so you know the problem when
we went through our um current step was
we were sort of had this in between
stuff of doing a matrix multiply and bl
blah blah blah um and that kind of
caused indirectness and the possibility
for things to either explode or vanish
um so this network is written sort of
upside down when I stole the picture
from the paper so we'll just have to
deal with that like um right so the in
we're going downwards from here to the
next layer so
you know rather than going through sort
of weight layers and weight layers which
will start to produce the same kind of
problems what you can do is sort of
apply the same trick in a vertical
Network and say well look I can also
just carry the input around with an
identity function and add it on here and
so then I've got this sort of direct
carrying of information and so that um
led to the residual Network which was
what completely transformed computer
vision models um and made them much more
learnable um than pure networks that
lack these residual
connections um if you sort of start
heading down that path you can think
well why only provide these residual
Loops that take you one step maybe I
could directly connect each layer to all
the successive layers and so people
played with that idea and that led to
the so-called dens net where you have
these kind of skip connections linking
to every other layer um a variant of the
residual Network the res net um which
was actually again introduced by
schmidhuber and students was to say well
rather than just directly adding in the
input
um summed with the output of the new
network layer maybe again we'd be better
better off having gating so that you are
deciding by Gates how much of the input
to have skip around and so that led to a
variant um the the highway net um where
you've got sort of GED residual networks
so various ideas of doing that um not
going to say more about that right now I
want to skip ahead and sort of do the
rest of new or Nets and get on to um
machine translation
okay um so once you have rnns where RNN
is including lstms normally in practice
lstms you can use them for anything else
where you're doing sequences and so
there are lots of places they're used in
N so if you want to assign words parts
of speech like nouns and verbs that
would be commonly done with a part of
speech tagging lstm if you want to be
assigning named entity labels like
location right I I did this toy version
where we were signing a label to the
middle of a window but you want to
assign a label at each position you can
use an lstm for named entity recognition
you can use an RNN as a encoder model
for a whole sentence so if we want to do
sentiment classifications see whether a
piece of text is positive or negative um
we can say run an lstm over it and then
use this as a representation of the
sentence to in work out whether it's
positive or negative piece of text and
well the simplest way of doing that is
to use the final hidden State because
after all that final hidden state is the
hidden State you've gotten from having
seen the entire sentence and use that
and then have a sort of a classification
layer um logistic regression on top of
that to give you positive or negative in
practice though people have found it's
often better to use every hidden State
and take some kind of mean or
elementwise Max and feed that in as the
sentence
encoding you can also use rnns for lots
of other purposes where you're using it
to generate text based on other
information so if you want to do speech
recognition or summarization machine
translation um that we'll come to later
you can have an an input source which
you'll use to condition your network and
then you'll generate the speech
recognition or the um machine
translation as we'll see later and so we
refer to those as conditional language
models because rather than just
generating text starting from nothing
from a start token we're generating it
conditioned on some source of
information
um one other idea on what normally
happens when people use these um you
know I
suggested
um that you know we could sort of do
this averaging at each position if you
think of these about these hidden State
representations these hidden State
representations that representation
isn't only about the word terribly it
has some information about what came
before it the movie was terribly but it
has no information about what comes
after it and well you might think you'd
like to have a representation of
terribly that knows what came before it
but also what came after it and so
people sort of came up with the next
obvious idea to deal with that which was
to build a
bidirectional lstm so you ran a Ford
lstm and then you start another lsdm
that's shown in that sort of greenish
teal and you ran it backwards and so
then you had a forwards and backwards
Vector at each position and you just
concatenated them both and then you had
a two-sided context for a representation
of word
meaning and so these networks um were
pretty widely used so um we were sort of
running a forward RNN a backward RNN and
concatenating the states
together and those were then sort of
commonly sort of written like this to
suggest that in a compact way you're
running a bidirectional RNN um that and
you know these were very popular for
language analysis they're not they
weren't working able if you wanting to
generate text um but you using them in a
lot of places as a representation but
more recently Transformer models have
normally taken over from that um one
more idea which we'll see for machine
translation is
um you know rnns are sort of deep in the
sense that they unroll over many time
steps but up until now they've only been
shallow rnns in the sense that we just
had one hidden state but you can also
make them Deep by having multiple layers
of hidden States what was also commonly
called stacked rnns so you'd have
several layers of
rnns um built above each other and you
might wonder H does this really do
anything is it are they just big vectors
above the words but precisely because
you have sort of this extra newal
Network layer between here and here here
you get exactly the same power Advantage
you get otherwise with newal networks
that you can do successive layers of
feature extraction and so you get more
power out of your neural network um to
some extent um what
people yeah I okay to some extent what
people um
found with new rnns in those days um is
the having multiple layers definitely
helps but unlike what was happening in
those days with other kinds of newal
networks for vision Etc people still use
relatively shallow shallow RNN so you
know you always got a lot of gains by
having two layers rather than one but
you know commonly it started to be more
iffy whether you got extra value from
three or four layers so commonly people
were running two or thre layer lstms and
that's what people were using
but that's completely changed around in
the world of
Transformers um where nowadays people
are building very deep um Transformer
networks for doing language
understanding okay but I Should Skip
ahead and say a few words before time
runs out about machine
translation um so machine translation is
one of the key natural language
processing tasks where We're translating
um words from sentences in one language
to sentences in another language so
we're starting off um with a sentence in
some language here French and what we
want to do is output it in a different
language here
English um
so that machine translation was actually
where NLP started right so in the early
50s there wasn't artificial intelligence
yet there wasn't a field of NLP yet um
but people started to work on machine
translation um and the story of why
people started to work on machine
translation was essentially you know
computers were first developed um during
the second world war and during the
second world war computers were used for
two things one of them was calculating
artillery table targets artillery tables
to sort of work out what angle to put
your gun on to get it to land in the
right place I'm not very relevant to
what we're doing but the other thing the
other thing that computers were used for
was code breaking um so um after the
second world war it moved very quickly
into the cold war and there were you
know concerns on both sides um you know
of keeping up with the science that was
being developed on both sides and people
had the idea of gee maybe we could think
of translation between languages as like
code breaking and that thought um
occurred to um important relevant people
and science funding agencies and
actually lots and lots of funding was
poured into this idea of can we use
computers to do machine translation
between languages and you know at the
time in the 50s you know after some
initial very impressive looking cook
demos it was sort of basically a
complete flop and the reason you know
there are lots of reasons why it's was a
complete flop you know one was people
knew almost nothing about the structure
of human languages I mean in particular
when I was mentioning the other day the
Chomsky hierarchy right and knowing
about sort of context free languages
right the chompsky hierarchy even hadn't
been invented yet right sort of formal
properties of languages hadn't being
explored but also you know the computers
um that people had in the 1950s right
the amount of P computing power or
memory or anything like this that those
computers had in those days was
laughable right these days you know the
little power brick for your laptop has
more computing power inside it than the
big mainframe computers that they used
to be using in those days so um
basically um people were only able to
build very simple lexicons and
rule-based substitution rules and
nothing like the complexity of human
languages which only gradually people
began to understand um but machine
translation started to become more alive
in the 1990s and 2000s decades once
people started to build empirical models
over lots of data and the approach then
was called statistical machine
translation and so when Google translate
was first introduced to the world um it
was sort of the big unveiling to the
world of statistical phrase-based
machine translation systems where what
you were doing was you were collecting a
large amount of parallel
data words that have been translated
from one word to another and you know
not for all languages but for quite a
few languages quite a few sources of
parallel data so the European Union
generates a huge amount of parallel data
among European languages there are
places like Hong Kong where you get
English Chinese if a certain dialect of
Chinese um parallel data um the UN
generates a lot of parallel data so
getting sources of parallel data and
trying to build models and so the way it
was done was based on that model we're
going to try and learn uh probability
model for translation so this um the
probability of a translation given a
source sentence and the way it was done
at that time was breaking it down using
Bas rule into two um sub problems so the
probability of the translation given the
source is going to be the inverted
probability of the source given the
translation times the probability of the
translation and and you know you could
think that this makes it no simpler
because you've just you know reversed
the order of X and Y but the reason why
it made it simpler and people were able
to make progress was the translation
model was treated as a very simple model
as to how words tended to get translated
to words in the other language and it
didn't need to know anything about you
know word order grammar structure of the
other Lang anguage and then all of that
was being handled by just this
probability of why which was a pure
language model as we've talked about
before so you could have a simple
translation model which just sort of
said you know if you see the word om in
French you might want to translate it as
man or person or and put some
probabilities on that and then most of
the cleverness was in the language model
which was telling you what would be a
good sentence in the target
language okay um and so that was
important because you know translations
get pretty complicated right so um you
not only have to know how to translate
words and those translations of words
VAR in context um but you get a lot of
reordering of words in
sentences
um I'm not going to be able to spend a
lot of time on this
but you know here here for a while um
was my favorite example machine
translation sentence um so um this is
actually a translated sentence so it
comes the original comes from the book
Guns Germs and Steel if you're familiar
with that um but it was that book by
Jared Diamond um but this book was um
translated into Chinese so here's a
sentence um from
um the book in Chinese and you know uh I
guess in the 2000th decade I was
involved in building statistical machine
translation systems and I guess there
was a Mt
evaluation um that um we did where our
system did terribly on this sentence and
I tried it out on Google translate and
it also did terribly in this sentence so
what the sentence should say is in 1519
600 Spaniards landed in Mexico to
conquer the Aztec empire with a
population of a few million they lost
2/3 of their soldiers in the initial
Clash um so here's what Google translate
said in
2019 2009 1519 600 Spaniards landed in
Mexico millions of people to conquer the
Aztec empire the first 2third of
soldiers against their loss um now it's
partly bad because the word choices in
the translations
very good um but you know it's
especially bad because it's just um not
actually able to capture and use the
modification relationships um of the
sentence so you know here's the part of
the Chinese that's saying the Aztec
Empire and over there in Orange is the
few million people and in Chinese
there's this explicit little character
here dur which is saying that stuff in
Orange modifies this stuff in green
which is what it's meant to be in the
correct translation of Aztec empire with
a population of a few million um but
Google translate completely fails on
that and it's Suddenly It's the millions
of people who are going to be conquering
um the Aztec empire um and you know
that's sort of in this way um the worst
thing that's happening here though you
know the 151 19600 isn't exactly a very
good translation um and the first 2third
of soldiers against their loss isn't
very good either um but you know so for
a while I used to sort of update this
and see what happened you know um in
2013 it almost seemed like progress had
been made but by
2015 it had gone downhill back to how it
was before so it just seemed like they
got lucky in
2013 rather than the systems were
working any better um and indeed this
sort of seemed to be the problem
although some kind of progress had been
made in machine translation um these
systems um just you know sort of never
really worked all that great um and so
that led to this amazing breakthrough in
2014 um where we then moved to neural
machine translation and new machine
translation was much better so what did
we do in neural machine translation so
we built a neural machine translation
system as a single endtoend neural
network and that's been a powerful idea
in newal network systems in general
including in NLP if we can just have a
single big system and put a loss
function at the end of it and then we
can back propagate errors right back
down through the system um it means
we're sort of aligning all of our
learning for the final task we want to
do and that's been very effective
whereas earlier models couldn't do that
um so we built it with a sequence to
sequence model so that sounds like our
lstms but it's meaning that we're going
to have two of them one of them to
encode the sentence um The Source
sentence and one to produce the target
sentence so that's what we're building
so for the Source sentence we're taking
here it says RNN but let's just think
lstm because that's what we're going to
use in practice it's much better and so
we're going to chunk through it
encoding um what we've read using an RNN
so this RNN isn't going to Output
anything right we're just building up a
hidden state that knows what's in the
source sentence um so again encoding of
the source sentence and we're going to
use that final hidden state to condition
the decoder RNN which is going to then
generate the translation so for the
decoder RNN it's also an lstm but it's
going to be an lstm with different
parameters so we're going to be learning
one set one lstm with Source en coding
parameters and then for the different
language we're learning a different lstm
that all know about the target language
and so we give it start and say well
feed in for feed in your past what
you've encoded from the encoder RNN as
your starting point um and then we're
going to be I that'll be count as the
previous hidden State you're feeding
into your um lstm and then we're going
to generate the first word of the
translation and we'll then copy that
translated word down using this as a
generative model as I did last time and
we um start translating through he hit
me with a
pie okay um
so does that sort of make sense the
model yeah okay um
so okay there's some note
sorry um yeah sorry what I was going to
say yeah so the the little pink note
here so what I was showing you is the
picture of using it at sort of runtime
at run time we're going to encode the
source and then generate the words of
the translation at training time we're
going to have parallel text we're going
to have sentences in their translations
we're going to run with the same
architecture but as before then for the
decoder Network we're going to try and
predict each word and then say what
probability did you assign the actual
next word and that will give us a loss
and we'll be calculating the losses at
each position working out the average
loss working out the gradients back
propagating them through the entire
network both the decoder RNN and the
encoder RNN networks and updating all
the parameters of our model and that's
the sense in which it's being trained
end to
end okay um so sequence so this is sort
of a general notion of an encoder
decoder model which is a very general
thing that we use in all kinds of places
right that we have one network that
encod something which produces a
representation which will then feed into
another Network that we'll use to decode
something and even when we go on to do
other things like use Transformers
rather than lstms we're still commonly
going to use these kind of encoded ecoda
models because if we want to do not only
machine translation but other tasks um
like um
summarization or um text to speech or
other things like that we're going to be
in this space of using encoder decoder
networks yeah what is the difference
between this encod de model and just
using a deeper neural network with more
layers
um well a lot is sequenced um right so
it has never been very Su you're meaning
like why don't you just build on top of
the source right um people have tried
that occasionally it's never been very
successful and I think part of the
reason is all of what I was trying to
show before about all all of the word
order changes around a lot between
languages and if you're sort of um just
trying to build stuff on top of the
source sentence it's very hard to cope
with that in particular it's not even
the case that the length stays the same
right one of the big ways um in which
languages vary is what little words that
they have right so that in English
you're putting in a lot of these
auxiliary verbs and articles whereas
it's in Chinese you don't have any of
those and so you're neither needing to
depending on Direction add a lot of
words or subtract a lot of words which
is very hard to do if you're sort of
building on top of the source of
it ah is it quick uh yeah so left side
is that b directional or just like a
like the encoder um yeah so you you
totally think and it could be that the
encoder is bidirectional and that might
be better um for the for the famous
original instantiation of this that was
done at Google they actually didn't make
it bir directional so it was simply
taking the final hidden state but that's
absolutely an alternative that you could
do okay okay
um yeah so I sort of said it was um okay
usable for lots of things okay um yeah
so this is our um conditional language
model um this so we're now kind of
directly calculating the probability of
Y given X right that the decoder model
is generating um uh language expression
as a language model directly conditioned
on X um and so we train it with a big
parallel Corpus um and that's the only
case I'm going to talk about today
recently there's been sort of some
interesting work on unsupervised machine
translation meaning that you're got only
a little bit of information about how
the languages relate you don't really
have a lot of parallel text but I'm not
going to cover that today um yeah so for
training it we have um paired sentences
um we work out our losses in the
predictions at each position and then
we're working out our average loss and
back propagating it through in a single
system end to end as
described
um yeah so in practice um when people
built Big Machine translation systems
this was one of the places where
absolutely it gave value to have multi-
layer stacked um lstms and so typically
people are building a model there and
you'll be building a model something
like this that's a multi-layer lstm
that's being used to encode and
decode
um in my two minutes um remaining um I
just want to sort of um quickly say so
um building these new machine
translation systems was really the first
big success
of natural language processing deep
learning now in this in this sense you
know it depends on how you define what
parts of language if you look at the
sort of the history of the Renaissance
of deep learning the first place where
deep learning was highly successful was
in speech recognition systems um the
second place in which it was highly
successful was then object recognition
and vision and then the third place that
was highly successful was then building
machine translation systems um so you
know Google had a big um statistical
machine translation system and it was uh
it was only in
2014 that people first built this sort
of
lstm um deep learning machine
translation system but it was just sort
of obviously super good and it was so
super good that in only two 2 years it
was then deployed as the live system um
that was being used at Google but it
wasn't only used in Google um that new
machine translation was just so much
better than what had come before that by
a couple of years after that you know
absolutely everybody um both us
companies and Chinese companies
Microsoft Facebook 10cent bu um
everybody was using new machine
translation system because they are just
much better systems and so this was an
amazing success right CU um statistical
machine translation systems like the
Google system that this is something
that had been worked on for about a
decade hundreds of people had worked on
it there were millions of lines of code
lots of hacks built in um for particular
languages and language pairs um but
really a simple small um newal machine
translation system was able to um work
much better um there was an article
published about it when it sort went
live in the New York Times that you can
find in that um link it's a um a little
bit of a a praising piece um where you
could be a little bit critical um but
you know basically it's sort of talking
about how just the difference in quality
was so obvious that everyone immediately
noticed even before Google had announced
it of w some Machine translation's gone
so much
better okay um so that's basically today
so um for today you know we've leared
that lstms are powerful if you're doing
something with a current new network you
probably want to use an lstm um you
should know about the idea of clipping
your gradients um bidirectional lstms
are good when you've got an encoder but
you can't use them to generate new text
um and encoder decoder rual machine
translation systems were great new
technology um that advanced the field
thank you