Hey, hi everybody. So, yeah, I'm Non
Brown. Uh, excited to talk about this
today. Uh, so I'll be talking about
multi-gent AI. I'll be taking a pretty
broad uh, view of it because there's a
lot there's a lot to cover. Um, and I
guess I'll start by motivating it. I
think we have seen that um, okay. So,
yeah, first I want to talk about
self-play. So, self-play has been behind
a lot of the breakthroughs that we've
seen in AI, especially for games. things
like Alph Go, um things like Dota and
Starcraft and also Poker. Um and we
haven't really seen that in LMS. And
it's a little surprising, right? Because
if you look at the trajectory of LLMs,
it actually looks a lot like the
trajectory of something like AlphaGo,
right? Uh you start with pre-training on
high quality human data. This was done
for AlphaGo, was also done for LLMs. Uh
then you enable large scale inference
compute. And then you have recursive
self-improvement.
And step one pre-training on high
quality human data. In Alph Go, this
means training on a bunch of human go
games. In language models, it means
training on large chunks of the internet
and doing X token prediction.
And then step two is enabling large
scale inference compute. So in uh Alph
Go, this was Monte Carlo research and in
all the different games there were
different ways of doing this large scale
inference compute, but in AlphaGo is
multiolor research. And then in LMS you
have chain of thought.
And then step three you have recursive
self-improvement. And then in AlphaGo
this is self-play where the AI plays
against itself over millions billions of
different uh games and it gets better
and better uh over the course of those
games. And in LMS we don't we don't have
that piece. So so why is that? What's so
difficult about doing something like
selfplay, recursive self-improvement in
LMS compared to all these games where
it's been so successful?
And I'll give you the the takeaway,
which is that a lot of people's
intuitions about
um self-play is basically overfit to go
and chess and these kinds of two-player
zero sum perfect information games. And
it turns out that when you go outside of
these games, a lot of the like very nice
properties go away and self-play becomes
much more difficult.
So to give one example of this, I want
to start with just like a very basic
question, which is who do you think is
the better poker player? Option one is
someone who over a very large sample
size wins head-to-head against any other
player. So if this person were to play a
million hands of poker against any other
person alive, they would win in
expectation. They they would just like
they would end up winning. They would
end up up money. Option two is someone
who makes more money playing poker than
anyone else over like let's say a year.
So who thinks option one?
And then who thinks option two? Okay, it
seems like pretty split, but I think
most people actually lean towards option
two. Now, it's very interesting that in
poker, this is not necessarily the same
person, right? You could have someone
who is really good at squeaking out wins
against other players, um, but if
they're playing against a really weak
player, doesn't really exploit them to
the max. And you could have somebody
who's really, really good at finding the
weaknesses of weak players and taking
advantage of that to the fullest extent
possible, but when they're up against
another top pro who doesn't have many
weaknesses, they end up doing a little
bit worse. So in poker, these could be
two different people. In a game like
chess or a game like Go, we don't really
consider the possibility that this could
be two different people, right? Like if
you think about who is the best person
at option one and who is the best person
at option two in a game like like chess,
you would just say Magnus Carlson. It
would it would be the same person.
Okay. So option one is what we call a
miniax equilibrium and option two is
what we'll call a population best
response. Now, typically when we think
about AI for games, when we talk about
solving a game, what does it mean to
solve a game? Typically, what people are
talking about is computing a minimax
equilibrium. And that's going to be
important because that's an assumption
that we are making uh about what it
means to solve a game. And it's a strong
assumption. It's not necessarily what we
want. And in games like chess and go,
this is fine because it ends up being
the same thing. But in other games like
poker and a lot of other settings and
we'll see that as we go beyond two
player zero some games this actually
becomes a very significant problem. This
is not necessarily the same thing and we
might actually it's possible that what
we really want is a population best
response.
But for now let's just take it as an
assumption that what we really want is a
bmax equilibrium and and we'll go down
the rabbit hole of what this involves.
So for starters what what is a miniax
equilibrium? A miniax equilibrium is a
set of strategies in which no player can
improve by deviating to a different
strategy. Uh and in two-player zero sum
games in particular, playing a minax
equilibrium guarantees that you will not
lose an expectation. And we're going to
measure something called exploitability,
which is how much we lose to a best
response. So exploitability is basically
how far away are we from from a miniax
equilibrium. If we're in an equilibrium,
then exploitability is zero.
Okay. So, um, to give you some intuition
for this, like let's say you're playing
rock, paper, scissors. One strategy that
you could take, not a very good one, is
to just throw rock every single time.
And in this case, the best response
against that strategy is to throw paper
every single time. And our
exploitability is one because we're
losing every single every single round.
Okay? So, you might have a more
sophisticated strategy. We might say
like, well, let's throw rock the first
two rounds and then on the third round,
um, if our opponent threw paper, then
we're going to throw scissors.
Well, in this case, the exploitability
is still one because the best response
would be to throw paper on the first two
rounds and then rock on the third round.
Now, you might say this is unfair. We're
assuming that the opponent knows our
strategy and they know that we're going
to throw scissors on the on the third
round and and that is correct. And this
is this is an assumption that we're
making when we talk about um equilibria.
And again this is a very strong
assumption and I think it's fair to
question this assumption um which is
that our strategy is common knowledge
but the outcome outcomes of random
processes like the random seed is not
common knowledge. So why why are we
making this assumption? The reason is
because if you are creating an a an AI
that is going online and being used by
billions of users then if there are
weaknesses in that system eventually
people will find it and they will
exploit it. And so the idea behind
Miniax like when we're measuring
exploitability is to say okay well let's
just assume that the opponent has that
that people have you know full access to
our weights. um they know exactly what
the probability distribution is over
actions and can we be robust despite
that
now again this is a very strong
assumption that we're making and I think
it is very fair to question this
assumption um but for now we're going to
go with this and uh and see what happens
when we make this assumption and what
can we what can we do to make our agents
robust despite this assumption
so in rock paper scissors the answer is
to randomize Remember that the strategy
is common knowledge but the outcomes of
random proc processes is not common
knowledge. So in rock paper scissors if
we just randomize equally between
throwing rock paper and scissors with
equal probability each round then our
opponent will not know what we're going
to throw. And the best response you know
the best they can do is is just tie us
and so the exploitability is zero.
Okay. And this is the miniax equilibrium
for rock paper scissors to randomly
choose between rock paper and scissors
with equal probability each round.
Now, it's reasonable to look at this and
say, "Okay, well, great. We're able to
compute a minax equilibrium that
guarantees we don't lose in expectation,
but we're not going to win in
expectation by playing equal probability
each round. So, how do we actually win
in a game like poker?"
And the answer is that in a game like
poker, uh, the strategy is much more
complicated. Like rock, paper, scissors
is a very simple example where
you can just play any action as long as
you balance them correctly and you know
the best you can do is tie. Uh but in a
more complicated game like poker, if you
are playing the Nash equilibrium, if you
are playing the miniax equilibrium, it's
actually very difficult for the opponent
to know what to do to counter you
because there are some actions that
should just not be played at all. You
know, in rock, paper, scissors, that
doesn't happen. In rock, paper,
scissors, the opponent could do anything
in response and they'll still tie you.
in poker that's not true. There are some
there are many actions that they can
make which actually are just what we
call negative expected value um that
actually just cost them even when you're
playing the against the miniax
equilibrium.
So the idea behind minax equilibrium in
something like poker is that your
opponent is going to make mistakes and
that's going to cost them value and
because it's a two-player zero sum game
that means that it's going to increase
your value. And in fact, this is kind of
the strategy that's been adopted by
poker professionals. Now, um they this
guide to poker, for example, that uh
says, "Poker is simple. As your
opponents make mistakes, you profit."
So, the conventional wisdom is play the
miniax equilibrium. And then maybe and
your opponent will make mistakes and
you'll you'll profit off of that. And
then also over the course of the long
run, if you observe weaknesses in your
opponent, then you could adapt from the
miniax equilibrium, deviate, and then
try to take advantage of them.
Okay,
so
we want to we were aiming for minax
equilibrium because that guarantees that
we're not going to lose an expectation
and in practice it means that we're
going to win. Um, self-play
is this algorithm that converges to a
minax equilibrium. So self-play is when
an agent gradually improves by playing
against copies of itself and the initial
strategy could even be completely
random. um as long as you um have a
sound self-play algorithm, and I'll talk
about what sound means because it's
actually non-trivial. Um in a two-player
zero sum game, any sound self-play
algorithm provably converges to a media
max equilibrium.
And so this is actually really
incredible because this means you don't
need any data. You don't need any human
data. uh as long as you have sufficient
memory and compute any finite two-player
zerosome game can be solved via selfplay
and I want to say this again because I
think this is like really profound and
kind of amazing that in any two-player
zerosome game you don't need any human
data if you just do uh any any balanced
two-player zerosome game you don't need
any human data if you just have
sufficient memory and compute you can
just do selfplay and converge to a minax
equilibrium and that guarantees that you
will not lose an expectation to any
human or any other player.
We kind of take this for granted, but
it's actually kind of lucky that that we
can get this.
And so this is behind a lot of the uh
victories that we've seen in games like
Go and chess and poker and and uh
realtime strategy games.
Okay. So what do I mean by sound
self-play? And and what does selfplay
look like in in different kinds of
games? So there's um different kinds of
two-player zero games and we'll start by
talking about perfect information games.
Essentially what this is is just
independent single agent RL. You just
take something like PO and as long as uh
you do sufficient exploration uh it's
actually pretty easy for this to
converge in theory to a minimax
equilibrium.
Now that said that that convergence to
minax equilibrium is is a theoretical
property. In practice you don't usually
get all the way to minax equilibrium. uh
and in particular you might still be
vulnerable to adversarial attacks. Uh
neural nets are limited in in their
ability to approximate a minimax
equilibrium especially in complex games
like Go. So
this could mean that like yes if you had
infinite capacity and infinite compute
then you would eventually arrive at a
minax equilibrium. In practice, you
don't have that. And so, you could still
be vulnerable to exploits. And this is
especially a problem because finding
exploits is generally easier than
defending against exploits. And
especially in imperfect information
games, which we'll talk about later. Uh
and so this there's actually a paper
that came out in 2023 which kind of
showed that in go in many of the leading
Gobots uh there were adversarial
strategies that could be deployed um by
humans even that would allow them to
defeat very very strong gobots.
Okay, so that is perfect information
games and in perfect information games
it's actually relatively simple. When
you go to imperfect information games
things become a lot more complicated. Um
and one thing that I think is surprising
to people is that if we take this
modified version of rock paper scissors
where the payoffs for um scissors and
paper are altered to be plus two and
minus2 instead of plus one minus one
just to break the symmetry of the game.
Um PO does not converge to a minimax
equilibrium.
This is uh a lot of people even people
that are very experienced in RL don't
know this but I think it's pretty
important that there's actually nothing
in PO that guarantees convergence to a
minimax equilibrium in a game like rock
paper scissors and the reason is because
rock paper scissors you have to balance
between multiple actions with a certain
probability
and there's nothing forcing uh that
balance that convergence to a particular
probability distribution in the PO
algorithm
So this points to the fact that
imperfect information games, there's
something special about them that's much
more difficult than perfect information
games. And why is that? Okay. So to
explain what is particularly difficult
about imperfect information games, I
want to talk about uh we we'll
illustrate this game called Rock Paper
Scissors Plus. And this is uh a
visualization of the game where player
one acts first and then player two uh
acts after player one without observing
what player one did. So that's just so
we can observe it as a we can view it as
like a something like a perfect
information game where the players act
sequentially. So here the players are
acting sequentially but player two
doesn't observe what player one did. And
so it's kind of like no different from
them acting simultaneously.
And we're going to modify the payoffs a
little bit so that it the symmetry there
there's no symmetry and like the
equilibrium is to play rock and paper
with 40% probability and scissors with
20% probability. So the way this works
is player one acts first. They choose
either rock paper or scissors and then
player two acts. They choose rock paper
scissors and then the payoff is shown
for player one. And there's dotted lines
between the player two nodes to signify
that player two doesn't know which of
those nodes they're actually in.
So for example, if player one chooses
rock and then player two chooses
scissors, then player one wins two
points and player two loes two points.
And like I said, the equilibrium for
this modified version of the game is to
throw rock paper with 40% probability,
scissors with 20% probability.
Okay, so let's say we do depth limited
look ahead search. So just like we would
do in a game like chess.
So, what does this look like? Well, you
start at player one. We're going to do a
depth of one search. Player one is going
to look at all the different actions
they could take and then look and then
ask what is the expected value after
taking this action. And in an
equilibrium, it's going to look like
this. It's going to show, well, if you
throw rock, you'll get a payoff of zero.
Paper, you get a payoff of zero.
Scissors, you get a payoff of zero. So,
it actually doesn't matter
from player one's perspective. It
doesn't matter what they do. In all
cases, they get the equilibrium payoff.
And so there's not enough information
for them to arrive at the equilibrium of
choosing rock and paper with 40%
probability, scissors with 20%
probability.
Um, but the problem is that this isn't
realistic because this is assuming that
player two is playing the equilibrium.
And that is an assumption you can make
in a game like chess or go, but you
can't make in an imperative information
game. Because if player one were to for
example choose rock with 80% probability
uh then player two would no longer play
the equilibrium. Player two would pick
up on this and they would deviate and
they would start playing rock. They
would start playing paper. And so the
value of player one throwing rock would
decrease from zero to minus one.
And so this is actually fundamentally
why imperfect information games I mean
one of the reasons but I think the main
reason why imperfect information games
are so difficult because the value of an
action depends on the probability that
it is played and that is not true for a
game like chess or go a perfect
information game in perfect information
games the value of an action does not
depend on the probability that you play
it if you're playing chess and you want
to open with the Sicilian defense it
doesn't matter if you do that 10% of
time or 90% of the time, it's not really
going to expect going to change the
expected value. Whereas in a game like
poker, if you want to bluff, well,
whether you're bluffing 10% of the time
or 90% of the time matters a ton because
if you're always bluffing, then the
opponent is going to pick up on that and
they're going to start calling you more
often and the value of bluffing is going
to go down.
So, what this means is that you need an
algorithm that finds the right
probability of choosing an action, not
just what action to play.
Now I I should caveat that a little bit.
I I use chess as an example. The truth
is that chess these days is kind of like
an imperfect information game because
players, you know, kind of like prepare
different strategies and think about
what strategies the opponent has
prepared for. Um but that's modeling
chess as like a repeated game that could
be viewed as imperfect information.
That's not really uh viewing chess as
like a standalone game.
Okay. So, how do we get around the fact
that
we can't use something like PO? We need
an algorithm that doesn't just figure
out what actions to play, but the
probability to play them.
Well, there's a few different approaches
that can be taken. The simplest is this
algorithm called fictitious play.
And the idea is that we'll initialize
the strategies for all players
arbitrarily and then on each iteration,
each player simply plays the best
response to the opponent's average
strategy over all previous iterations.
And if all the players play fictitious
play, then the average strategy over all
iterations converges to a minax
equilibrium.
So to give you an idea of what this
looks like for rock, paper, scissors,
you initialize the strategies
arbitrarily. So let's say we initialize
it to all the players throwing rock.
Okay, so player one throws rock, player
two throws rock. Their strate their
average strategy so far is 100% rock.
And then on iteration two, you compute
the best response to the average
strategy so far. So the average strategy
so far is to always throw rock. So the
best response to that is to throw paper.
And now you update the average strategy
to be 50% rock, 50% paper.
Okay. On iteration three, you again
compute the best response to the average
strategy so far. So the best response to
50% rock, 50% paper is to always throw
paper. And so now the average strategy
is updated to be 33% rock, 1/3 rock, 2/3
paper.
On iteration four, you do the same
thing. the best response to 1/3 rock,
2/3 paper is to throw scissors. And so
then your average strategy is updated to
25% rock, 50% paper, 25% scissors. And
you can kind of see that like as you're
going, as you do this more and more, the
average strategy is going to slowly
converge to a minax equilibrium of 1/3,
1/3, 1/3.
So this is one algorithm that's been
around for a long time. The truth is
that it converges very very slowly to a
minax equilibrium.
Um
there are more uh there are modern
algorithms that converge a lot faster
and basically what they're doing is is
computing a a regularized best response.
So regret matching and hedge are the two
most popular versions of these
algorithms and the idea is that whereas
fictitious play would always compute the
exact best response regret matching and
hedge pick a regularized best response.
So in this case, you're going to have
some kind of like value and then you
look at the expected value of each of
the actions and take the like uh just
the um you just choose proportional to
the amount of mass that's over that
line. So in this case you look at the
expected value of uh paper and expected
value of rock and you see like how how
much are they over that dotted line. Uh
scissors is below the dotted line. So
you just put zero probability on that.
And then for p rock and paper, you just
choose them with a probability that's
proportional to the amount of mass
that's over the line.
I should point out there's a lot of
similarities between these kinds of
algorithms and gradient descent. And
there's there's a lot of deep literature
into this that I won't go into. Uh but
there are strong connections there.
Okay. So this is what uh it would look
like if you ran regret matching which is
like this improved version of fictitious
play. So on the x axis here we have the
number of iterations that you've done
and the y- axis is the average
probability for each action in rock
paper scissors. And you can see over
time it it slowly converges to uh
playing 1/3 1/3. Now there's a whole
body of literature that I won't go into
in this talk that uh shows you can
converge much much faster with better
algorithms. So one for example is linear
regret matching and that's this is this
is what it looks like. Um it converges
orders of magnitude faster compared to
uh just regular regret matching.
So these algorithms the regret matching
algorithms they're iterative algorithms.
They slowly converge to the optimal
probability of playing each action
correctly. And these are the algorithms
that were ultimately used to defeat top
humans in poker which was what my PhD
work was on.
So we were able to use use these
algorithms to defeat four of the world's
best heads of no limit Texas holding
poker pros. Um
and this was actually done without
neural nets. was done. Uh the the main
challenge for poker was how do you do s
one how do you do search in imperfect
information game and two how do you
converge to an equilibrium in a game
with hidden information
and regret matching was a key part of
that.
Okay, so there are limitations to
fictitious play, regret matching, and
hedge. Uh, in particular, they tend to
have poor performance in single agent
RL. And this has always been a really
annoying uh quirk of these algorithms
because there's a lot of great
algorithms for single agent RL that
don't work when for uh for imperative
information games.
And there's a lot of algorithms that can
converge to an equilibrium in imperative
information games but don't have very
good performance in single agent RL
settings.
So it would be really nice if we just
had a single algorithm that we could
deploy in all cases but that really
wasn't the case for a long time. There
has been very recent work from a few
different folks on uh developing
algorithms that actually do have really
good performance both in single agent RL
settings and multi-agent RL settings. um
that converge to an equilibrium quite
quickly and um so I think that this
probably is the future but we're this is
still an area of undergoing rapid
development.
Okay, so I've talked a lot about two
players some games so far. I'm going to
shift away from that. I I want to take
one quick aside which is and and talk
about why haven't I mentioned LLM yet?
And there's actually a very good reason
for this. is that because we've been
talking about two-player zeros some
games this whole time and in two-player
zero sum games if you're what you're
computing is a minax equilibrium then
communication is never useful and this
is actually you can prove this it's
never useful to talk to the opponent if
you're computing if you're playing a
minax equilibrium in a two players some
gaming
so I I get asked this sometimes like is
it ever useful to talk to the opponent
the answer is simply no um and there's a
very simple proof
um which I'll give the intuition for,
which is that in a two-player zero sum
game, there could be multiple miniax
equilibria, but they're all going to
have the same unique value for players
one and two. So there will be some
unique value for player one and then
player two's value is simply the
opposite of that value. That's the
definition. Like the fact that it's the
opposite is what makes it zero sum.
And so if there was some cheap talk
action for player one, then there's
three possibilities. either taking that
action would increase V1, decrease V1,
or it would have no effect.
If it were to increase V1, then player
two would simply ignore it because it's
going to hurt their value. So just
they're just not going to listen to
whatever player one was saying.
If it decreases V1, then player two
should simply not say it. And so the
only remaining possibility is that it
has no effect. And so we can see that in
a minimax equilibrium there is no reason
for the players to talk to each other.
It's either well one player or the other
is going to realize that it's not worth
it.
Okay. So that was two players some
games. Now let's move to the I think
more interesting part which is what
about non two-player zero some games?
We've seen that there's like a lot of
these nice properties for two players
some games. Minax equilibrium unique
values all this stuff. Uh what about
non- two players some games?
And we're going to see that a lot of the
properties that the the uh nice
properties that we saw in two players
games actually don't carry over. And so
that creates a real dilemma for us about
like what do we do?
And the central claim that I'm going to
make in this section of the talk and I
think this is a really important point
is that if you if your goal is to learn
to cooperate with humans then
using avoiding using human data is a
dead end.
The only way in my opinion to learn the
only scalable way in my opinion to learn
to cooperate with humans without is to
use human data.
Um, and this is first of all relatively
controversial because there's a lot of
research on multi-agent RL that's
focused on learning to cooperate with
humans without using human data. And I I
mean I will make my spicy claim which is
that I think that is that is a dead end.
Um, and this is also in truth kind of
unfortunate because I mentioned earlier
that in two-player zero games we have
this beautiful property that you
actually don't need any human data. If
you just do selfplay with sufficient
memory and compute, then you will
converge to this miniax equilibrium
which is this unbeatable perfect optimal
strategy in the in the two-player zeros
game. And what I'm saying here is that
actually that's not true in in when it
comes to non two-player zerosome games.
There's simply no way around the fact
that you need human data if you want to
do well when playing with humans.
And okay, so why is this? I think I can
actually convince you. My hope is that I
can convince you pretty easily um with
this demonstration in the ultimatum
game.
And by the way, I think this is really
like one of the most important slides in
this whole presentation.
So the ultimatum game is this uh popular
game theory game. Uh, and the way it
works is Alice is given $100
and first Alice has to offer Bob between
0 and $100 and then Bob must decide
whether to accept or reject that offer.
If Bob accepts then Alice and Bob keep
their money and if according to the
split that that Alice offered and if Bob
rejects then Alice and Bob get nothing.
So,
for example, if Alice were to offer Bob
$30 and Bob accepts, then Bob gets 30,
Alice gets 70. If Bob rejects, then
Alice and Bob both get zero.
So, I want you to think for a second.
Okay, I want you to think about two
things. First of all, what is the
minimum amount that you would accept as
player two in this game?
And then the second thing I want you to
think about is if you were to do
selfplay RL from scratch without any
human data, what do you think it would
converge to?
Okay, so I'm curious like how many
people would accept
let's say less than $40 in this game?
$40. Okay, some people. Surprisingly
few. How about please raise your hand if
you're if you're if you're going to
accept. So how about less than $30? $30
or less.
Okay, that's a pretty good amount. Okay,
what about $20 or less? Still some $10
or less?
What? Who would accept $1? Really? Oh,
okay. Um,
I'll tell you that in general, people
tend to accept uh tend to be willing to
accept between 20 and 30%. And then if
you offer too low, they they will reject
simply because that's human nature.
Does anybody want to guess what the
miniax Well, not the minax equilib, but
a Nash equilibrium is in this game.
Yep.
50/50.
Well, could Alice do better? Could if
Alice's objective is to get as much
money for themselves as possible, then
could they do better than offering
50/50?
Okay. So what what would the what would
the like optimal strategy be for Alice?
Yeah. Do you want to say?
>> Yeah. So the optimal strategy well a a
optimal strategy and there's like
actually like a lot of details to this
that I won't go into but like the the
intuitive optimal strategy is that Alice
offers the minimum amount possible $1 or
one penny or one fraction of a penny and
then Bob is faced with the decision. Do
they accept this small but positive
amount of money or do they go with zero?
And from a purely game theoretic
perspective, the op if if Bob is simply
trying to maximize their utility, which
RL agents are ultimately about
maximizing reward, then it makes sense
for Bob to take that trivial amount of
money and Alice to get the vast majority
of the spoils.
But of course, if you were to deploy
this in the real world, this would be a
terrible strategy. You know, I don't
think there there aren't that many
people. There are some, I guess, but
there aren't that many people that would
accept a dollar in this kind of game.
Now, there's two approaches. There's two
there's two responses to this that um
you could take like one is to say the
humans aren't doing what the math is
saying. It's the humans that are broken.
the algorithm is fine, you know, and we
should just ignore this whole problem.
Uh, but I don't think that's the right
approach. I think the right approach is
to say, well, okay, there's something
wrong with our optimization algorithm.
If it's not going to if ultimately what
we care about, and there's a question of
what do we ultimately care about, but if
what you ultimately care about is doing
well in this kind of game with humans,
then um there's something wrong with
just doing pure selfplay in this kind of
game.
Now, it's tempting to say, well, we're
not giving it, you know, the the right
priors or something like that. You know,
we're not we're not doing it as a
repeated game. If it was a repeated
game, uh then there would be reputation
dynamics and they would learn to uh
offer a smaller uh offer some larger
amounts of money so that, you know, Bob
would would be more willing to accept or
something like that. Um, and that that's
ultimately where this whole like
literature comes from of like trying to
modify this kind of game to get the
behavior that you would get by playing
with humans. And ultimately, this is a
rabbit hole that I've seen a lot of
researchers go down. And and
unfortunately, yes, maybe you could do
something that like kind of works in the
ultimatum game, but as you go to more
more complicated settings, this is
ultimately not going to lead to success.
And there's one one example of why this
is the case is that it turns out the
ultimatum game is actually very
culturally dependent. There are some
cultures where people will accept 20%
very easily. And there are some cultures
where if you offer anything less than
50/50, they will reject.
Now, how are you going to learn about
this cultural difference without any
human data?
The simplest and most effective way to
address this problem is to collect a lot
of human data. understand how humans
play this game and then figure out the
optimal strategy in response to that.
Okay. So I think what really in my
opinion uh proved this point is uh the
work of my of I and my colleagues on
diplomacy. So diplomacy is a
seven-player game. It's a natural
language negotiation game and the
objective is to control a majority of
the map of Europe.
So this is a popular strategy game. It
was introduced in the 1950s and it's
still widely played today and it's a
seven-player game
and it was actually JFK and Kissinger's
favorite board game apparently.
Now, each turn involves private natural
language negotiation
where um you know this is I think what's
really fascinating about this game is
that the actual tactics are not that
complicated. It's really all the
complexity comes from negotiating with
the other players. And so every turn you
will spend about 15 minutes negotiating
with the other players in private and
then everybody writes down their moves
simultaneously and then all the moves
are executed at the same time.
And um this because the the moves are
done simultaneously.
There's a lot of trust building that is
necessary in this game and a lot of uh
yeah a lot of trust and betrayal. Like
you will negotiate with somebody and say
hey look can you do this with me this
turn? and they might say yes and then
they might not follow through on that
with their actual moves. They might
backstab you instead.
So there's a lot of complexity in the
negotiations
and it's long been considered a
challenge problem for AI. Uh there's
research going back to the 80s. Uh but
research really started picking up in
2019 with the rise of large language
models.
Okay. So one thing that's really
important in diplomacy is that support
is really key. So you can see on on the
left here, if two different powers try
to go in try to send units into the same
territory, they're both going to bounce
back. Neither player is going to go in.
So what the red player can do is they
can support one of their units to go in
there. And then it's a two versus one.
And so then the red player will go into
the territory and the purple player will
go back.
But the key thing in diplomacy is that
supports can actually come from other
players. So the green player could also
support the red player into that
territory. So red could go to green and
say, "Hey, look, can you please support
me into this territory? I will help you
out next turn or something or I'll help
you out somewhere else on this turn."
And the green player can say, "Sure."
And they could write down the support
order and then red player gets in.
Okay, so
like I [clears throat] said, this is a
seven player very complicated natural
language negotiation game. Uh, for now,
let's talk about the non language
version of this game where there's just
moves being written and all the
communication is implicit through the
moves. This is still a very complicated
game, but it kind of just like
simplifies a lot of the experiments for
us so we can really focus in on the non-
two-player zero sum aspect of this game
rather than the natural language part.
Um now my colleagues and I developed
this algorithm called Dora uh which
learned to play no press diplomacy. So
that's non- language diplomacy purely
through selfplay in in a way that's very
similar to Alpha Zero.
So pure selfplay from scratch in the
game of Diplomacy. And sure enough, the
win rate in a two-player version of
Diplomacy was massive. It was clearly
superhuman.
And then we put it into games with uh in
seven player games,
sometimes with other DORA agents and
sometimes with other agents that were
trained on human data. And what we found
is really interesting. So
the um so if you played
one copy of searchbot, if you played a
game with one copy of searchbot and six
copies of Dora, Searchbot is this AI is
this other diplomacy AI that was trained
on a lot of human data. Searchbot would
do terribly. Searchbot would only win
about 1% of the games. And because this
is a sevenplayer game, if you're winning
14% that means that you're tied. So if
you're winning 17th of the games, that
means that you're you're tying the other
players.
Searchbot only went only won 1%.
But if you played one copy of Dora
versus six copies of Searchbot, then
Dora only won 11% of the games.
So that means that Searchbot was losing.
Searchbot, which was trained on human
data, was losing in games with six other
Dora bots that were not trained on any
human data. But one copy of Dora was
also losing to six copies of Searchbot.
And what this points to is that there
are different equilibria in this game.
Dora stumbled upon one equilibrium that
makes a lot of sense when it's playing
with other copies of itself.
But if you stick that same agent into a
game with a bunch of other bots that
were trained differently, trained on a
human equilibrium or something close to
a human equilibrium, for example, then
Dora wouldn't know what to do and it
would do terrible.
Okay, so this is kind of points to the
fundamental problem with non two-player
zeros games. In two in two players some
games, this this doesn't really happen.
Um, you can train a bot whatever method
you want and as long as it converges to
a minax equilibrium, as long as it
converges to an equilibrium, it's going
to do great against some other bot that
was trained in a totally different way.
It doesn't matter. In non two-player
zero games, that property isn't there.
And so this this actually does become a
problem.
So this kind of
gets to the the remember I mentioned
earlier that there was this question of
like what do we actually want? Do we
want a miniax equilibrium or do we want
a population best response and I said
that I mean people were pretty split on
which one was actually better.
Conveniently in two-player a lot of
two-player games there's not a big
difference between these two. In in
chess, for example, it's like typically
the same agent or the same human. Um,
when you go to non- two-player zero
games, miniax equilibrium is just not
useful anymore.
And so, we can't really
use that algorithm. We can't really use
that equilibrium. And the only thing
really that's left that's meaningful is
the population best response.
And then the question is, well, who's
the population?
Is the population other copies of
yourself? Is the population humans?
But depending on what the population is,
you're going to need data on that
population. So this is why you need
human data if ultimately what you care
about is performance with humans.
Okay. So the solution that we ended up
taking in diplomacy and that I I
recommend as the probably the best
solution for uh general sum games or non
two players some games is collect a lot
of human data and train an imitation
model
of those humans.
Scale inference time compute to better
model the human players. not necessarily
to do better, not necessarily to make
the the imitation models achieve better
performance, but to better better model
what the humans would actually do. And
then third, scale RL with these human
imitation models essentially as part of
the environment.
This is the approach that we ultimately
ended up taking in diplomacy and it
ultimately ended up working quite well.
in no press diplomacy. Uh we entered a
bot that was trained in this way in a
200 game real human tournament
uh with 50 games for each bot. So we
entered four different bots and um our
bot which was trained in this way
ultimately ended up doing the best. It
ended up getting first place.
Uh we trained two other bots. One was um
Dora, which ended up doing actually
quite poorly uh below the average human
performance. And then a couple other
bots that ended up doing relatively
well, but not not as well as the
approach that I re I just suggested.
We also use this to train a uh natural
language a bot for the full natural
language version of the game. And here
we did extremely well though not first
place. Uh so we entered this agent
Cicero which again negotiates fully
natural language with actual humans. Uh
and we entered it anonymously in a
natural language diplomacy league and it
placed in the top 10% of players and
second of 19 players that played five or
more games. The average score was more
than double the average human score.
Now,
I think the main reason why
we uh only got second place and didn't
get first is that we were bottlenecked
by the quality of our LLMs. Uh this was
back in late 2022. Language models were
good, but not as good as they are today.
And so, I think if we really make a beta
focused effort taking a similar approach
today, I think we'd be able to do
extremely well.
We also use this in Hannon. And I think
this is really interesting because
there's been a lot of papers on how to
achieve cooperation with humans in the
game of Hannabi. And we actually had a
paper in 2022 that managed to do better
than expert humans when cooperating uh
across a a wide spectrum of human
players. And again it used this approach
of imitate humans scale inference
compute to better model the human the
the human behavior and then basically do
RL with those human with those human
imitation models as part of the
environment.
Okay. I now want to talk a little bit
about agent agent LM cooperation. So so
far I've been talking about competing
with humans, cooperating with humans.
Um, but one aspect where you don't
really need human data is if you just
want the AIS to cooperate with each
other.
Okay.
So, why would we want to do this? Um, I
guess to motivate agent agent LM
cooperation, I want to talk about 01.
Uh, I'm guessing that you've all
discussed this already in your course,
but basically 01 is this reasoning model
that
is very effective at scaling test time
compute. So the longer the model thinks,
the better the performance
and not only and so we've been able to
get these models to think for longer and
longer. And even on top of that, even
better is that um as we developed more
sophisticated versions of these models,
the whole plot of like inference versus
performance curve has shifted to the
left. So you're able to get the same
performance at a much lower inference
today.
And this is getting better and better.
And this is behind a lot of the like
recent successes and like crazy
benchmark performance. And I want to
take a moment in case you haven't seen
this plot to to really just like drive
home that this this is like progressing
very rapidly today. Um this is a plot of
code forc's performance. In January in
early 2022, GP3.5 came out and it could
barely code. I mean it's like still
impressive that it could code at all but
it was below the fifth percentile for
competition coders in code forces.
GPD4 came out in early 2023. Again,
still maybe close to fifth percentile
among competition coders. Not a very
good coder. GPD40 came out. Now you're
looking at 10th percentile. This is um
mid 2024. Okay, so that's starting to
get on the radar, but still not very
good. And then you have the reasoning
paradigm and then things really start to
take off. So you have 01 preview which
came out in September of 2024 and it's
already above the median competition
coder in code forces. 01 comes out
that's just uh that's in December so
about 3 months later and it's above the
90th percentile. 03 came out that was in
April of this year and it's above the
99th percentile. And we recently
announced that we place first among all
humans in the ICPC, one of the leading
competition coding uh uh co competitions
in the world. And um so you can see that
this is very steep trajectory that where
things are progressing very rapidly
today. It's a very exciting very
interesting time in AI.
Okay. So I mentioned that we can uh have
these models think for longer and longer
and just keep getting better
performance. Now there's obviously a lot
of challenges with getting them to think
for longer and longer. Uh 01 uh GBD5
thinking can think for I think pro can
probably think for like 15 or 20 minutes
depending on uh the problem. Uh well can
we push that much longer? Can we get it
to think for hours, days, weeks? Well at
a certain point latency becomes a
problem. people don't want to sit around
and wait for three weeks to get a
response from GPD5 Pro.
Um, and the problem here is that chain
of thought is inherently serial. So, one
of the motivations for multi-agent AI is
is latency. Uh, latency eventually
becomes a bottleneck. And there are
other testime scaling techniques other
than just serial chain of thought that
are parallel.
So, for example, best of n and
consensus. The idea behind best of n is
that you sample um well let's start with
consensus. So consensus you just sample
from the agent you know a dozen or
hundred different times and then you
just look at the most you look for the
most common response. So if you're
taking a math exam you just ask the
model a dozen times see which answer
ends up being the most common and submit
that answer. And you can actually get a
pretty substantial boost in performance
just by doing this. Uh in fact, here is
the U plot from the 01 announcement
where the shaded area is when you do
consensus with 64 agents. And so you can
see that you're getting a pretty
substantial boost on this uh uh
competition math benchmark by doing
consensus over 64 samples.
But there are issues with consensus. So
one, for example, is that this only
really works if you have a very very
short answer. If you're writing essays,
you can't really do consensus over the
essays because you're never going to
write the same essay twice.
So something else you could do is for
example best of n. And the idea of best
of n is you sample multiple times and
then you have some way of judging um
which answer is best. And this works
really well if you if the answer is very
easily verifiable. So, for example, if
you're solving a Sudoku puzzle, you
could try to solve that Sudoku puzzle
10,000 times and very easily check
whether any of the answers are correct.
And if one of the answers is correct,
you just go with that answer.
So, best of end in many ways actually
works better than consensus, but it
again also has its limitations um
because you're you kind of like need uh
a problem that's like really easy to
verify whether you have the correct
solution.
So there's all these different
techniques um that you can use and
there's there are trade-offs but the
general trade-off is that they are lower
latency but less compute efficient.
Another motivation is diversity.
So
when 03 came out uh there was like a lot
of complaints that it couldn't multiply
really large you know 20digit numbers or
something. Um, and I always thought this
was like really interesting because I
don't think there are many humans that
could multiply 20-digit numbers
reliably. Um, and we don't really expect
humans to do that, right? We we don't
expect them because they can use a
calculator and just plug it in. Uh, and
similarly, language models also can use
tools. a language model can instead of
you know today probably actually I
haven't tried but like my guess is that
if you ask QVD5 thinking and ask it to
multiply like two two 15-digit numbers
it'll probably do it'll take a very long
time but I think it'll probably get it
right um but it doesn't really make
sense for it to do that right in the
same way it doesn't really make sense
for a human to multiply two 15-digit
numbers by hand
um
okay so in the same way that you would
want a language model to use a
calculator because it is more efficient.
It's like more reliable. It's more
efficient. It just just makes sense. Um
there are a lot of different models out
there and some models are better suited
for some problems than others. And it
might be the case that your most capable
uh largest model could do the task that
you want, but it doesn't really make
sense for them to do it. it's just not
it's just not as efficient as cost-
effective or they might just not might
just not be as good at it as some other
model. And so in the same way that you
would want a model to be able to call a
calculator when it's asked to multiply
two 15-digit numbers, there are times
when it makes sense for an agent to go
to another agent and hand off a task to
them. So the the another motivation for
multi-agent AI is that diversity is a
strength.
you can use the best model uh for the
particular query that's at hand. And I
would argue that routing is already a
form of multi- aent AI. The idea behind
routing is that um you send a query to
some model. The model looks at that
query and decides which which model is
actually best to answer that question or
to give that response and then it will
route the question to that model and
then return the response back up.
Okay. So, the state of multi- aent AI
today um as of today, I would say it's
actually if if you when it comes to LLM
uh cooperation, I would actually say
it's it's not as uh as impressive as it
could be. Um we're seeing a lot of
scaffolds and these tend to be like very
heavily engineered and very brittle and
um you know, they do work in some cases.
I think that there has been some some
clear successes, but there's clearly
something still missing from from these
systems.
I think it's actually a very exciting
time to be working on multi- aent uh AI
actually because
we've seen a lot of success from AI
models in a lot of different domains and
we haven't really seen a a clear success
when it comes to multi- aent AI in in
the way that we have seen for a lot of
other um
you know measures of intelligence.
But it seems like the models are are are
nearing the point where they can be
effective for this sort of thing.
It's also a really exciting time for
multi-agent AI because the fact is the
field of multi-agent AI has been around
for a very very long time. Uh it's
people have been working on this problem
for like dozens of years and there's
always been this like question of how do
you get the AIS to communicate with each
other? How do you get them to even
coordinate in the first place? And with
LMS we have a very clear answer to that.
Now the answer is you just get them to
talk in natural language to each other
and it just it just works. And again
like if you've only been in the field
for a couple years you kind of take that
for granted. Of course you know you can
use LMS to just talk to other agents in
natural language and they understand
that is that is that there have been
whole uh lines of research whole PhDs
that have been spent just trying to
figure out how to get these agents to
develop a language so that they can talk
to each other and now that's just a
solved problem. So, it's a very exciting
time to be working on multi-agent AI and
I think that there's a lot of uh
potential uh to do exciting things. Now,
there was this blog post that came out a
few months ago from Cognition that
basically said don't build multi- aents.
Um, and I actually think it's a great
blog post. So, I think there were two
blog posts that came out in the past few
months about multi-agent AI. One from
Cognition, another one from Anthropic. I
think they're both really worth reading.
I think that they're they're both really
interesting. They talk about their
experiences building scaffolds for
multi-agent AI and they talk about where
it works and where it doesn't work and
and what's still missing. Um, and in the
cognition blog post, one of the things
they say is
basically they went through this whole
rabbit hole of building multi-agent
systems. It kind of worked, but it was
also very brittle. And their main
takeaway was that it's not the
technology isn't there yet. Um, and they
say, however, agents today are not quite
able to engage in this style of long
Okay, so I I'll I'll say the the longer
part. If we really want to get
parallelism out of our system, you might
think to let the decision makers talk to
each other and work things out. This is
what us humans do when we disagree. If
if engineer A's code causes a merge
conflict with engineer B, the correct
protocol is to talk out the differences
and reach a consensus.
However, agents today are not quite able
to engage in this style of long context
proactive discourse with much more
reliability than you would get with a
single agent.
And so basically he goes on to say
at this moment it doesn't feel like
these agents are able to do it
but the technology is progressing very
rapidly and it feels like we are on the
cusp of being able to do these things.
And so, uh, I think it's a really
exciting time for multi- agent AI and I
think that, um, now is the right time to
be working on it.