early on you decided that you were going
to build an infro layer on top of other
info providers like AWS and a lot of you
know a lot of folks in the in the infer
Community were like well what's the
point of that right why why do you need
versel when you've got AWS so could you
go take us back in history a second and
and talk us through how you got to your
current stack and where you guys sit in
it yeah for sure so my my first
experience with the cloud was actually a
pretty tedious one so I wanted to just
deploy a website and I wanted to by the
way like the thing about versel that's
interesting is the ambition was not to
just help people build websites and web
applications there were a million ways
of doing that I wanted to help people
build the kinds of websites and
applications that the Giants of the web
were building so a little bit was like
that Meme of like copying the homework
like I actually wanted to like help you
build like Google and Amazon and meta
but I wanted to make it as easy as it is
to build with freaking like square space
or Wicks and that was novel it didn't
exist in fact a lot of investors told me
it was
impossible but there were new
innovations that were coming into the
cloud were starting to make it possible
so for example our first version of
versell used kubernetes as the place
where the the the workloads actually run
and then we realized you couldn't
actually create a system that had the
ambition of resell with that system it
was too heavy it was too rigid
it was too static it scaled up and down
quite slowly and so we had to learn how
to design infrastructure that met that
ambition of like hey it should be one
click or one command to
deploy so going back to your question or
prompt about how is it possible well it
turns out that the hyperscalers have
created hundreds of services that
customers need to choose from and they
actually come to the market with a point
of view of you start with the
infrastructure
right log AWS console blah blah blah
configure infra and then you put an
application in it versel actually took
the opposite they we inverted that
process we said you start with the
application here's a framework nextjs
and there's others that give you guard
rails that give it get give shape to
that
application and then when you deploy it
we automated creation the infrastructure
today we call that framework defined
infrastructure it was actually inspired
by softwar defined Network
and it was a similar Revolution but in
the sort of like networking space we
virtualized the cloud so it actually
makes perfect sense that we build on dou
AWS because Enterprises trust AWS
they're leaving behind the data center
but they cannot figure out how to get to
the Cloud and that was not I think I
kind of stumbled upon that and like it
was a lot of work and you know it was
uncertain whether Enterprises would want
this but now Enterprise is actually I
would argue even wanted more than
developers but I started with if I'm a
developer and I have a new idea the
infrastructure has to be invisible and
what matters the most is the idea and
the app
code um there's a you know Meme now that
uh that versel has started has has has
accelerated right which is that um if
you need anything in in the application
layer you essentially just wait around
long enough and versel was for you
um why is that what what how did you go
from going okay we've got an nextjs
framework here that's largely a web full
stack framework then now suddenly you're
shipping multi-agent Frameworks for you
know we had Ben man from anthropic um an
hour ago here you've got all the
anthropic models that you're serving
you've also got all the latest reasoning
stuff what why uh is it just a natural
progression of computing systems for you
to go from nextjs they're also
supporting uh everything at the uh uh AI
layer yeah for us always about what do
developers want to build what do I want
to build actually it even starts with
like what do I think is the future of
software right and we believe and we're
highly opinionated about this but I
think we're right because we started
this journey about two years ago that
all of software will be AI native
software whether it's that you know you
used to write a form for something and
you used to design a lot of UI and now
an agent can automate that or things
like vzer where all of the processes of
writing the application code and
building it and deploying can all be
abstracted out by an AI conversational
interface so we always work work
backwards at verell from what is the
software what what is this software
doing what does it look like backwards
to what is the technology should enable
that and that actually works out really
well for an infrastructure business
because we're not opinionated about well
we have q at vercel we have cues and
storage and functions over here we
actually don't care that much about The
Primitives we inverted the whole thing
of um when when AWS came to Market they
were like Primitives over Frameworks and
that made sense in the beginning of the
cloud because you had to invent
everything from scratch now all of that
is commoditized right S3 has the same
API across all Cloud providers all
models have now largely standardized on
the open open AI HTP calling interface
so when all of the backends become
commoditized most of the value will
acrude towards the application layer and
to towards the front and experience and
that's why we started there and and the
infra is sort of an output sometimes the
mental model that I use that's like
quite technical but I think it makes
sense
is think of your application code as the
input and think of verel as a cloud
compiler vercel maintains an
intermediate representation of that code
being transformed into infra so things
like consider the following right most
of my customer cers in e-commerce do not
have back ends that can withstand the
traffic of Black Friday so versel
invented a technology called ISR that
allows them to massively reduce the
backend burden by versel invoking the
backend for example over a period of
time and then we materialize a page at
the edge of the network and so versel
absorbs all of the traffic we distilled
the application down into Primitives
like S3 objects so behind brel a lot of
what we do is we run computation that
then places the output of that
computation in highly scalable systems
with several tiers of caching one of the
painful lessons of the cloud is that yes
it's elastic but nothing scales
perfectly in the cloud either so some of
our systems involve basically automating
the multiple tiers of caching that the
customer in another world would have to
be writing themselves when I learned how
to do web programming I would have to
like do all of this stuff manually
myself I would have to spin up M cached
I would have to spin up PHP fpm process
pools I would have to spin up worker
threads and then scale my computer
horizontally and then always be thinking
about how does the gash communicate with
the computer and so on and so forth and
versel has basically large it automated
all the way now how do we do this we
kind of learned all of the patterns of
how do scale this systems and we brought
them with a programming model that is
very very friendly it's almost like we
turn the front engineer into a highly
you know Advanced and experienced infra
engineer they just don't know that that
work is being done on their
behalf so the question is would vercel
ever uh build out its own infra instead
of AWS and what would it look
like I think right now for the
foreseeable future there's just so much
Alpha in democratizing access to the
cloud and I think some of the
infrastructure AWS has created has
become some so unfathomably large
for example when I talk about the number
of requests that we deal with during
Black Friday and the amount of compute
that can be sitting there idle ready for
us to harness it on behalf of the
customers it's just that number is so
astronomically large and the
commoditization of that infrastructure
is happening at an accelerating rate
that I think it would be a net loss for
versel to try and compete in that space
rather than help the hyperscalers do
what their best at which is creating
these raw materials and versel being
sort of the bridge for the rest of the
world that wants to utilize it another
metaphor that they used over time is
think how long it took Apple to actually
create their own silicon they' taken
over the world already with the iPhone
by the time they said there's actually
an opportunity for us to do this we've
earned the ride and we can actually go
into this highly specialized
Space by and large customers never cared
it was the Assembly of the components
and its presentation into the best
possible consumer device that helped
them win and I think right now that
opportunity for us exists with AI and
being that bridge to the AI for the
world whether it's in the form of
helping customers create their own vzero
style experiences or helping more people
create software like where would I
rather put my attention towards right
like you have to always ask yourself
because every investment you make with
your own companies even this is true for
infrastructure right like build versus
buy when of the biggest considerations
the one that I have the worst scars with
is build versus buy I'll give you a
quick example we went through four
different databases at versel for the
metadata storage of any time you deploy
it's really interesting one metaphor for
how versel works is that it's almost
like react for
infrastructure because everything spins
down to zero and when you access
something on
demand that access makes the
infrastructure exist
so one of our goals I actually joked the
other day on Twitter is versel is
actually a globally distributed highly
available fast propagating metadata
store that then gets repurposed as a
control plane and as a way of invoking
compute for example and so selecting the
underlying data stores that would enable
this kind of scale where people create
millions of applications per
day was a very difficult thing we had to
iterate and iterate and iterate and
iterate and my worst mistakes were were
when I believed that running and
managing the database myself was going
to provide an alpha for my business when
in reality Pro procuring the best
database for this highly a specific job
making it scale adding all of the layers
of redundancy and having the right
architecture and iterate iterating
towards that architecture was my main
priority so I think in the build versus
buy
consideration I'm very happy to buy from
AWS in in my build priorities is how do
I capture the next wave of software
development with AI rather than how do I
build a data center that no one cares
about I heard it you got the question
the question is how does gamer think
about
competition yeah number one I try very
hard not to think about
competition every time I obsessed about
competition in my career I probably
distracted myself from what customers
were asking me for so number one is we
bring an opinionated point of view to
the cloud and that's that's paid
dividends for us so whereas netlify and
AWS and and ploud flare we're saying
well go and find a framework that works
for you and will'll give you some
infrastructure it works for you over
here versus I'll verticalized that
integration and actually this came from
my obset session of like simplifying
software development to the point where
like imagine that you go to Google Docs
or Google slides and you select a
template like it just has to just work
like you never would think twice that
like you would have to bring the UI for
how to build the thing for them to host
it this is how I see the world of infra
I don't whereas others see a division or
a Divergence I actually see
integration it's very much what happened
with uh uh Linux and distributions or
what happened with the mac and and you
know the Apple Hardware is the operating
system needs to be co-developed in
tandem with the hardware and what our
customers love about versel is that we
actually procure the best components on
their behalf so it's actually better
that we started from the experience and
what the customer needs to do and out
goes the infrastructure whereas the
players that you're mentioning they all
start with like how can I get more users
from my infra like what do I need to do
do I need to drop prices do I need to
create a very
a generous fre tier and pricing is
actually a huge consideration right like
what you might attribute to the fact
that someone owns their infrastructure
might not have to do anything with
whether they own it or not like what is
their marketing abil marketing posture
or ability to say how do I get users
right and you say well there is free and
unlimited this or that when in reality
nothing in nothing in the world is free
and unlimited and on on the competition
around pricing what what we've always
ear on to the degree that is the most
possible is transparency and Clarity
with pricing I believe that everything
has a cost right like nothing is nothing
can possibly be free and unlimited and
you're you're going to face this economy
when designing infrastructure systems
because you're going to find that when
you receive traffic there's all always
some computation something you need to
do to serve that traffic with a high
degree of quality and great quality of
service and so versus has opted for the
posture of here's here's what everything
costs we you pay for what you use and
you pay as you grow and and so far it's
worked out really well for
us cool all right I I will
say the was being very humble but uh
when he was getting started I remember I
I was this was when I was still a
Founder um I remember a number of people
uh being super confident that vercel
would never get to this level of scale
right and that like oh it would
basically be one feature launch away for
AWS to just take you guys out um and
many years here you know later verel is
still thriving and creating growth yeah
and I recently met with Andy jasse and
you know he was very delighted that we
exist because 90% of it workloads are
not in the cloud yet and the best way to
get them to the cloud is to make the
life of developers and companies as easy
as possible and so AWS is very
incentivized to tell go and tell people
use nextjs use for sale in fact in many
ways we delivered on the dream of what
systems like kubernetes and Docker were
going to do which is that you want to go
fast to the cloud but you also want to
like keep the cloud at a healthy
distance in case this one cloud provider
screws you over right so next sh solves
for that you're basically designing an
appli that you can run or host
anywhere and we almost quote unquote
Trojan cores a cloud native architecture
design into it right because when you
deploy it as I mentioned earlier with
the S3 example we can convert and
specialize a lot of those capabilities
into a globally distributed system
sometimes the mental model that I use is
or or I'll give you a provocative
statement versel does not run next s
meaning we never take the nextjs server
throw it into a virtual machine and say
npm start we could do that it would be
less
multi-tenant the reservation of time and
space within that box would be much
higher it' be less optimized because
what happens with front workl that
people want them to be globally
distributed right like versel is more
like a CDN than ec2 actually so over
time we built a lot of of very
specialized infrastructure so that you
can be as fast and optimal as possible
and that is the best thing that could
happen to those 90% of workl that are
not in the cloud they're not going to
have to take that detour of imagine
you're AWS right and you have to
convince that customer hey move to the
cloud start by writing down all of this
cloud formation code all of this
terraform code set up all this and by
the way they've been doing that to date
and I would argue that's why the number
of work that are not in the cloud is so
high it you would think the cloud would
be way way way more successful and
obviously whoos to AWS for building a
100 billion a year at Revenue business
fantastic but there's just um uh so much
more to go
after um you I'll again repeat the
question which is basically apparently
you by for levels F FYI verel PES
Engineers less than Market what's what's
the strategy there I'm not familiar with
levels FYI and I think we're quite
competitive with market and for many
positions we exceed market so I I can't
comment on I can't comment on
speculation I can't comment on those
numbers I would love to double click and
I would wonder my my first hot take
would be like is that really
representative the real data of of
infrastructure I I'm highly I highly
doubt it um I think one of the reasons
that we are here is because we've been
able to hire the absolute best people
for that role and I personally reached
out to the people that are the best in
the world doing this role and we've
hired many of them so um yeah I uh I
will I will get back to you on that
one yeah just as a heads up levels sucks
there's way better sources of data if
you guys want happy to put out resource
links for you guys but a good one is
um there's a compensation survey that
the a16z team does of like 10,000
startups in the United States I think
it's a sing longitudinal survey and you
know is not a portfolio company a6s but
I when I was a CEO I would I I remember
seeing some of those levels FY um
reports about my own company and there's
just gross statistical under sampling
you basically only get self-reported of
folks who are uh Angry and
left uh but I'm sure we could uh which
is by the way I'm not I don't even check
uh those like fake websites um fake news
websites but I'll tell you that typ when
people leave uh and they were fired and
they were like disgruntled or whatever
that you get an over representation of
that in whatever whether it's company
reviews I mean I do this for restaurants
I go to restaurant visit me off and like
it's like the worst in the world at that
very moment uh but I think um you know
in the infra team at bracel has actually
been with us for a very very long time
we we we give them the some of the most
fascinating challenges of the internet
and we give them a scale you know people
actually tell me like when they join
like it's hard to hire for this role
because no one has seen the scale that
we're in and uh so we we do we go
outbound a lot and I don't think those
people are spending time on on levels uh
levels IO or whatever I I won't name
with portfolio company but we just lost
an engineer to levels uh to uh verel
last week because you guys awesome just
kidding I mean whatever all all fair in
uh in love and infro I have the same
advice for anybody that uses anything
that gets mired on consumption and brael
uses many many many systems that are
muted on consumption like snowflake like
data dog like um I mean just everything
AWS Etc and the world is going more and
more and more towards consumption right
like how do you procure AI tokens
consumption the world is consumption
which is why I was telling the gentleman
earlier I believe that the best feedback
loop that you can give an engineer is
what however many tokens of consumption
their infrastructure use usage incurred
in in fact the my least favorite systems
from an infrastructure perspective are
the ones that overpromise because they
systematically under deliver so not to
throw a postris under the bus but a
system like Dynamo or Cosmos DB for
example they give you an A A an accurate
measurement of the infrastructure impact
that each operation makes so when when a
developer uses that system they
understand the cost that they're
incurring in for the application logic
that they they created so it allows a
software engineer to have the same level
of connection to reality that a real
world Civil Engineer would have when
they're making a building oh how many
materials did I use for this H I have a
loadbearing structure how much concrete
did I pour in so I love system that have
this feedback built in whereas people
get in trouble with systems that
overpromise and I think not all
databases but databases sometimes are a
class of this where you get into this
situation with like really noisy
workloads inside the database that you
can't tease apart that make the overall
health of the system degrade meaning I
make a really expensive join and I
Collapse the health of the entire system
and I don't know the system didn't give
me back hey that query cost you 1 two
three four five
cents be be aware and then ideally that
system would then scale horizontally and
then in exchange for my payment I get
scale in
return and then I maintain a consistent
quality of service for all of my
workloads I create the fitness function
and feedback loop with the developer
that hey 1.2 3456 is very expensive for
what I'm doing I can decide to go in and
optimize my query
or cash it or compute less often and so
number one I think it's very important
that when you're dealing with a cloud
and Cloud native engineering you have
that mindset you're trading off your own
personal time that could go into
optimization for infinite ability to
draw compute from this
systems so what bracel is doing is it
gives it's giving you very very good
observability and Telemetry so that that
feedback loop is is very well understood
by you and so with we are making massive
improvements to the usage page for
example we actually have one of the most
realtime systems in the world today as
far as our usage Pace goes in fact a lot
of what you pay for when you pay for a
seat or you pay for a for a platform fee
on the on the Enterprise tier is you're
paying for the foundational
infrastructure that enables you to have
this service right so for example we
spend a lot on the realtime Telemetry
systems that give you accurate it's like
by minute replay of how much your
infrastructure bill is growing whereas
actually other services give you daily
dumps hourly dumps maybe every six hours
they tell you how much you consumed so
we're very much in the cycle of like
real-time consumption we have soft and
hard caps we learned this I think this
is a good lesson if you decide to build
a system like this people still have a
cap on how much money they're willing to
pay for any given service right you
would be surprised about how difficult
it is to arrive to that number when we
introduced soft and hard caps I had uh
sort of
forecasted that it was going to cause
issues in both directions open AI had
hard caps and now they've added a
warning saying hey it's like it's
probably a bad idea to set a hard cap
because he could actually make put your
business in a bad place so I had an
escalation from a customer saying that
they lost $20,000 worth of Revenue
because of the hard cap because in that
moment they actually wanted to keep the
infrastructure let it rip because
customers are buying stuff of course for
sell keep going so soft caps are the
ones that give you learning hard caps
are the ones say this is the absolute
Max I want to pay but you always have to
think about that in terms of as a
function of Revenue or as a function of
growth of a viral marketing campaign and
so on and so forth the other thing that
we're doing is and we're announcing this
on February 4th I'm going to give you
like a sneak peek preview we're coming
to Market with a compute product that is
highly optimized for the new kinds of
work workloads that AI is bringing to
the world so there workloads that the
web as a whole had not seen that much
before which is that you make a request
and the response could take minutes that
didn't exist when I invented verel
because people wanted the opposite right
instantaneous e-commerce
transaction uh oltp database P99 10
milliseconds boom let's go now oh open a
decides to think for a minute and so I'm
reserving a computer for that one
specific request for a
minute so that it can wait on the back
end and respond so we're rolling out and
we've already rolled out some
optimizations for this but you're going
to see that as traffic comes to verell
we can increase compute density
intelligently based on the profile of
the
workload and I think this is probably a
first of its kind in the cloud ecosystem
where if you're CPU bound versel will
scale horizontally aggressively so that
you get reserved CPU cycles for each
request if you're IO bound because
you're wait waiting on deep seek R1 to
think and think and think and think we
will intelligently saturate that
allocated compute so I can of went into
the WIS but this is an infrastructure
class the idea is that some customers
have gotten themselves into some um
usage patterns that as they scale are
punitive to costs now versel actually
came from a good place in those use
cases because we always prioritize I
mentioned it earlier as an
infrastructure guy I'm obsessed with
noisy
neighbors bps's are cool they're $4 doll
whatever bro you know what the problem
is graphic piles up and your customers
are being degraded by the impact that
other customers are having on that
individual process so versell has to
allocate CPU and memory very
intelligently my number one PRI is
always performance I cannot degrade the
quality of the system because you're
being popular and so with optimizations
like compute density I'm going to be
able to retain that quality bar but
being able to load balance more
intelligently I think a lot of those
sort of Twitter horror stories that you
hear are basically um by definition
systematically and categorically
eliminated with zero configurations from
the customer because the other the other
really bad thing that can happen in the
cloud is that you put the burden of
scalability in the customer how many
vpss how many instances how many pods I
got from the world where people hand
tuned how many pods in kubernetes they
needed for a given service right or the
other really bad bit of failure is
tuning CPU thresholds all day every day
right oh what is the right CPU threshold
for this super hit genius workload and
so verell is bringing is removing the
total cost of ownership of that
infrastructure management and is also
delivering on the efficiency profile of
a server so servers meet serverless
coming to you
soon by the way let me know if any of
this makes sense or I just went to the
Ws too
hard the question was um given that you
got a full-time job as a front end
engineer when you were 18 you regret
breaking into Tech too early as opposed
to doing research or taking
classes well I actually got a full-time
job earlier even uh I've been working
online for for a very very long time I
think I've had the pleasure of joining
companies where I was able to do
research at the company and I think even
for my own startup for example I was a
co-author of our first two or three
schedulers and placement systems and
load balancers I wrote my own uh clone
of react I wrote my own clone of
kubernetes I've been involved in writing
the metadata stores so I had the I guess
the blessing and the curse sometimes of
I mentioned sometimes too much build
versus buy too much DIY can kill you but
I was able to use the different startups
that I was in as part of that
foundational education and I actually
have no regrets whatsoever because the
speed at which you can move by learning
how to create the systems I think is
phenomenal and I was able to set
unrealistic expectations for what the
systems were going to be able to do like
I me mentioned in in the very first
version of aell every single get commit
I said is going to become a
deployment and when we Tred the
kubernetes flavor of that it was just
completely unsustainable we're bleeding
money left and right and but I liked the
pain because I set the bar so high I was
like okay there has to be a deployment
per commit I was obsessed with immutable
functional data structures I was like
deployments should be
immutable very PR much like get commits
are immutable right and so we set the
bar so high that that became the
research project in in and out of its
own right like how do we meet the
unreasonable bar that we set for
ourselves and and deliver this beautiful
experience and we continue to do that I
think VZ is a really good example of
that the very first version of VZ I
think was written on gbt 3.5 turbo and
it could not do what we needed to do
there was not even function calling we
had to create our own bespoke function
calling system on top of the models so I
guess the alternative to you know
setting out on on a research path on its
own right is like can you can you push
the Innovation bar so high that that you
end up with this novel problems and
novel research
projects quick show of hands how many
folks know what vzer
is okay so about half maybe you could
just take take a couple minutes to just
talk about V what V is yeah VZ is web
web development AI assistant if you go
to v.d you type in a prompt and it
converts it into a working frontend
application increasingly false stack
application and we've basically made it
an expert in all of the tools that you
know from the versel ecosystem react
nextjs tailwind
seten and it's our fastest growing
product by by a huge margin uh it
basically doubled Revenue three times in
a period of like 14 days 20 days it's
it's uh and it's opening up the top of
the fal so if you have any idea actually
I I
recreated or one of my colleagues I
posted it on Twitter one of my
colleagues recreated the entire versell
dashboard with vzero in the future
version of that we would want it to be
in which has a vertical sidebar
navigation and so for moving really fast
on UI and ideas that you have for future
products v0 is like the best way to do
it and it took a lot of iterations to
actually get it to the point where it is
now and of course there's more to do um
but we had idea Market fit to get to
product Market fit we had to push a lot
of this Innovations forward and we
really had to push what the
state-ofthe-art was was capable of at
the time and uh and and yeah uh
researching in public with your
customers is more painful but can be
quite uh
satisfying how did you acquire your
first customers and how' you get them to
believe in your
product so very first uh idea was built
in three months it was called Global
real-time
deployments one of The Inspirations was
actually uh the idea of really silly but
I was very into Bitcoin at the time and
I had fallen in love with the idea
of um essentially like decentralized
systems those was a system called
ipfs that was a global global content
addressable store so everything was a
checkum and you could acquire anything
by knowing it's checkm from a
semi-structured network where you don't
even know the total size of membership
it's powered by a gossip
protocol Believe It or Not we've
actually under the hood of verell a lot
of the infrastructure works that way for
example our security systems that need
to understand and analyze traffic
profiles in real time and block
attackers are based on a very efficient
gossip
protocol uh one thing that makes versel
hyper fast I mentioned is the fast
propagating global data store so when
you when you say when you deploy and you
say stanford.edu should point to this
immutable deployment we have to
propagate that fact
worldwide to millions of computers and
we do that through an efficient gossip
protocol as well and so I was inspired
by a lot of these decentralized
systems react had also peeled me with
functional programming at the time
immutablejs was the
thing and I actually wanted to literally
ship the most minimum viable product
that I could because I I had begun Angel
Investing and had developed this
hypothesis that some of the best
companies to start out as just apis
one API call or two and so I invested in
three companies one was off
zero U it was the API to off and they
literally just launched with an API
there was nothing more there wasn't even
a website or there was a website with
two
pages CER bet which was an API to
information about people and scale AI
which was an API to data human label
data Etc and it realized there's an
opportunity to create only take this
dribe of deployment it's just an API to
get back that URL that is immutable in
time of your working application and so
I just launched that and it was all this
like super like big sitting on brain
meme wojack of it's going be this super
cool system I didn't have the infra to
make that work realistically it was over
provisioned under the hood it was heavy
so it was it was
about no whether would be product Market
fit and the fundamental idea
first honestly it was also some huus to
be honest it was like oh maybe the
version of this system it's GNA be great
um and I started getting customers right
away people really wanted this people
were really burned out on the complexity
of the cloud and the fact that it could
be one API called one command line
execution resonated right
away the journey for the next year was
how can I optimize and refine the system
so that it's not just just a cute demo
it's not just easy but it leaks I I I'll
give you a framework that has actually
been super helpful for me I think I
think it's somewhat popular but is day
one day 100 day 1,000 you can get a lot
of early customers because the day one
experience is phenomenal but in
infrastructure no one gives a about
the day one experience they care about a
day 100 meaning that the project was as
you keep kept writing code or adding
features the platform doesn't leak
meaning it's possible to absorb that
complexity and day 1000 they think of it
as like the
operations did it stay online does does
it have perfect uptime we had nine
nights of up time during Black Friday
that is the level
of like Perfection that customers expect
so for the next year or more it was
about chasing how could we nail day 100
and day 1000 and that was not working
from the
outset all right I think that's all the
time we have for questions so we have a
couple minutes for any spillover
attendance at the end thank you guo
really appreciate it and we'll be
sharing links thank you share feedback
get in touch thank you so much